<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Discontinuous Petrov Galerkin (DPG) Method with Optimal Test Functions. Space-Time Formulations and Elements of Irregular Shapes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>235014.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>235014</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>matthias gobbert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project focuses on the development of a new technique for simulating complicated physical and engineering processes with computers - the Discontinuous Petrov Galerkin (DPG) method.  The DPG methodology has the potential to transform existing Finite Element software at US National Labs and industry.  Without undermining the logic of existing codes, the method asks for a complete overhaul of local operations (on the element level) utilizing emerging multicore architectures. The method will have a lasting impact on software development for difficult problems arising in applications which require high accuracy simulations. Application areas targeted in this work include aerospace engineering (transonic and supersonic flows), geomechanics and bioengineering (implants, imaging of soft tissues). On the application side, the project builds on collaboration with Sandia and Argonne National Laboratories, Ben Gurion University and Boeing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project focuses on two research directions: (a) DPG space time elements, and (b) use of elements with irregular shapes. The DPG method minimizes residuals in the dual norm corresponding to a prespecified test norm. Computation of the residual requires inversion of the Riesz operator in the test space. With the use of broken test spaces and localizable test norms, the inversion can be done element-wise using standard Galerkin and "enriched" spaces. With the error of inverting the Riesz operator controlled locally, i.e. on the element level, the method automatically guarantees discrete stability for any well-posed problem in the sense of classic theory of closed operators. The methodology leads to uniform stability for singular perturbation problems and, being a minimization method, does not suffer from any preasymptotic instabilities. The residual is computed rather than estimated and provides a basis for automatic adaptivity. The first focus area deals with space-time elements for convection-dominated problems with applications to compressible and incompressible Navier-Stokes (NS) equations in two space dimensions. The second line of research investigates the sensitivity of the method to element shapes with a view to using elements of arbitrary polyhedral shapes. This part of the project will be done in the context of linear elasticity and hyperelasticity in three space dimensions with applications to geomechanics and bioengineering. The proposed work includes both analysis and semi-professional software development. The project builds on existing codes and joint computational effort with Argonne and Sandia National Laboratories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1418822</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leszek</FirstName>
<LastName>Demkowicz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leszek F Demkowicz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leszek@oden.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124714199</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~235014</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall aim of this project was a further development of the Discontinuous Petrov Galerkin (DPG) Finite Element (FE) method with optimal test functions introduced by Jay Gopalakrishnan and Leszek Demkowicz in 2009. The DPG method is a&nbsp;<em>Minimum Residual Method&nbsp;</em>that minimizes residuals in the dual norm corresponding to a prespecified test norm. Computation of the residual requires inversion of the Riesz operator in the test space. With the use of broken test spaces and localizable test norms, the inversion can be done element-wise using standard Galerkin and &ldquo;enriched&rdquo; spaces. With the error of inverting the Riesz operator controlled locally, i.e. on the element level, the method automatically guarantees discrete stability for any well-posed problem in the sense of classic theory of closed operators. The methodology leads to uniform stability for singular perturbation problems and, being a minimization method, does not suffer from any preasymptotic instabilities. The residual is computed rather than estimated and provides a basis for automatic adaptivity. The Project outcomes are summarized in the following.</p> <p><strong>Space-Time DPG for Compressible Navier-Stokes</strong></p> <p>The work focused on space-time discretization of both incompressible and compressible Navier-Stokes equations [3,4]. The analysis has led to the construction of the so-called&nbsp;<em>robust test norm&nbsp;</em>and, eventually, a construction of a&nbsp;<em>robust ultraweak DPG method&nbsp;</em>that delivers&nbsp;<em>L</em><sup>2</sup>-convergence for the primal unknown uniformly in diffusion coefficient. Numerical experiments indicate also robustness for the flux. The methodology was then formally extended to both compressible and incompressible Navier-Stokes equations. We have managed to solve a number of non-trivial examples with Reynolds number up to&nbsp;<em>Re&nbsp;</em>= 10<sup>5&nbsp;</sup>(Fig. 1).</p> <p><strong>Space-Time DPG for Schr&ouml;dinger Equation in Optics</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>The work on space-time DPG methods was then continued in context of linear Schr&ouml;dinger equation (Fig. 2). We encountered there a few fundamental challenges. First of all, the second order problem does not admit an&nbsp;<em>L</em><sup>2</sup>-stable first order system formulation. This limited possible variational formulations to only two: the strong (trivial) formulation leading to least-squares, and the ultraweak formulation. Both formulations lead to graph energy spaces for which no trace theory exists. We have managed to circumvent the difficulty by using classical Banach theory of closed operators that in turns requires non-trivial density results [2].</p> <p><strong>Applications to linear and non-linear elasticity&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The DPG methodology can be applied to any well-posed variational problem. We have studied different versions of the DPG method for linear elasticity [1] and the possibility of coupling different formulations [5]. Such couplings turned out to be very useful for problems with large material contrast and incompressible or nearly incompressible components (Fig. 3).</p> <p><strong>Polygonal DPG (PolyDPG) method</strong></p> <p>The ultraweak DPG methodology calls for the discretization of broken test spaces,&nbsp;<em>L</em><sup>2</sup>-space and traces of energy spaces to mesh skeleton. This makes it a good candidate for 2D meshes consisting of general polygonal elements [10]. The work supports the original claims, to mention a few: the methodology is insensitive to shape regularity (like virtual elements, it works for non-convex elements), supports adaptivity without resorting to hanging nodes technology, and delivers optimal convergence rates for polynomial spaces of arbitrary order (Fig. 4).</p> <p><strong>Related work</strong></p> <p>Applications of DPG methodologies include non-Newtonian fluids [7], thermoviscoelasticty [6] and wave propagation [9], see Figs. 5-6. An exciting reformulation of the DPG method as discrete least squares method, reducing the condition number to&nbsp;<em>O</em>(<em>h</em><sup>&minus;1</sup>), and allowing for solving quasi resonant problems, was presented in [8].</p> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <p>[1]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; B. Brendan, et. al.&nbsp;<em>Comput. Methods Appl. Mech. Engrg.</em>, 2016.</p> <p>[2]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; L. Demkowicz, et. al.&nbsp;<em>SIAM J. Num. Anal.</em>, 2017.</p> <p>[3]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; T. Ellis, et. al. vol. 114 of&nbsp;<em>Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering</em>.</p> <p>[4]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Truman Ellis. PhD thesis, University of Texas at Austin, 2016.</p> <p>[5]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; F. Fuentes, et. al.&nbsp;<em>Comput. Methods Appl. Mech. Engrg</em>.&nbsp;<em>In Press</em>.</p> <p>[6]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; F. Fuentes, et. al. Technical Report 21, ICES, 2016.&nbsp;<em>Submitted</em>.</p> <p>[7]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; B. Keith, et. al<em>. J. Nonnewton. Fluid. Mech</em>.&nbsp;<em>In Press</em>.</p> <p>[8]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; B. Keith, et. al. Technical Report 9, ICES, 2017.&nbsp;<em>Submitted</em>.</p> <p>[9]&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; S. Petrides et. al.&nbsp;<em>Comput. Math. Appl. In Press.</em></p> <p>[10]&nbsp; A. Vaziri Astaneh, et. al.&nbsp;<em>arXiv preprint:</em>1706.06754<em>,&nbsp;</em>2017.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504126487576_01--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504126487576_01--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504126487576_01--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Sod solution with robust norm after 0, 6, 12 refinements; and (b) convergence of density.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Vaziri</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504798876984_02--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504798876984_02--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504798876984_02--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Gaussian solution; (b) convergence plot; and (c) p = 3 operator-specific element.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Vaziri</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799286534_03--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799286534_03--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799286534_03--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sheathed hose problem: (a) geometry; (b) stress in deformed coordinates;  (c) convergence plots.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Vaziri</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799435849_04--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799435849_04--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799435849_04--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Quadrilateral mesh; (b) polygonal mesh; (c) solution; (d) convergence curves.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Vaziri</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799512153_05--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799512153_05--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799512153_05--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Confined cylinder with Oldroyd-B fluid: (a) flow domain; (b) refined meshes; (c) error estimate.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Vaziri</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799598338_06--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799598338_06--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1418822/1418822_10314275_1504799598338_06--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">DMAV validation: (a) experimental setup; (b) displacement and stress; (c) convergence of force.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Vaziri</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leszek&nbsp;F&nbsp;Demkowicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall aim of this project was a further development of the Discontinuous Petrov Galerkin (DPG) Finite Element (FE) method with optimal test functions introduced by Jay Gopalakrishnan and Leszek Demkowicz in 2009. The DPG method is a Minimum Residual Method that minimizes residuals in the dual norm corresponding to a prespecified test norm. Computation of the residual requires inversion of the Riesz operator in the test space. With the use of broken test spaces and localizable test norms, the inversion can be done element-wise using standard Galerkin and "enriched" spaces. With the error of inverting the Riesz operator controlled locally, i.e. on the element level, the method automatically guarantees discrete stability for any well-posed problem in the sense of classic theory of closed operators. The methodology leads to uniform stability for singular perturbation problems and, being a minimization method, does not suffer from any preasymptotic instabilities. The residual is computed rather than estimated and provides a basis for automatic adaptivity. The Project outcomes are summarized in the following.  Space-Time DPG for Compressible Navier-Stokes  The work focused on space-time discretization of both incompressible and compressible Navier-Stokes equations [3,4]. The analysis has led to the construction of the so-called robust test norm and, eventually, a construction of a robust ultraweak DPG method that delivers L2-convergence for the primal unknown uniformly in diffusion coefficient. Numerical experiments indicate also robustness for the flux. The methodology was then formally extended to both compressible and incompressible Navier-Stokes equations. We have managed to solve a number of non-trivial examples with Reynolds number up to Re = 105 (Fig. 1).  Space-Time DPG for Schr&ouml;dinger Equation in Optics   The work on space-time DPG methods was then continued in context of linear Schr&ouml;dinger equation (Fig. 2). We encountered there a few fundamental challenges. First of all, the second order problem does not admit an L2-stable first order system formulation. This limited possible variational formulations to only two: the strong (trivial) formulation leading to least-squares, and the ultraweak formulation. Both formulations lead to graph energy spaces for which no trace theory exists. We have managed to circumvent the difficulty by using classical Banach theory of closed operators that in turns requires non-trivial density results [2].  Applications to linear and non-linear elasticity   The DPG methodology can be applied to any well-posed variational problem. We have studied different versions of the DPG method for linear elasticity [1] and the possibility of coupling different formulations [5]. Such couplings turned out to be very useful for problems with large material contrast and incompressible or nearly incompressible components (Fig. 3).  Polygonal DPG (PolyDPG) method  The ultraweak DPG methodology calls for the discretization of broken test spaces, L2-space and traces of energy spaces to mesh skeleton. This makes it a good candidate for 2D meshes consisting of general polygonal elements [10]. The work supports the original claims, to mention a few: the methodology is insensitive to shape regularity (like virtual elements, it works for non-convex elements), supports adaptivity without resorting to hanging nodes technology, and delivers optimal convergence rates for polynomial spaces of arbitrary order (Fig. 4).  Related work  Applications of DPG methodologies include non-Newtonian fluids [7], thermoviscoelasticty [6] and wave propagation [9], see Figs. 5-6. An exciting reformulation of the DPG method as discrete least squares method, reducing the condition number to O(h&minus;1), and allowing for solving quasi resonant problems, was presented in [8].  References  [1]     B. Brendan, et. al. Comput. Methods Appl. Mech. Engrg., 2016.  [2]     L. Demkowicz, et. al. SIAM J. Num. Anal., 2017.  [3]     T. Ellis, et. al. vol. 114 of Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering.  [4]     Truman Ellis. PhD thesis, University of Texas at Austin, 2016.  [5]     F. Fuentes, et. al. Comput. Methods Appl. Mech. Engrg. In Press.  [6]     F. Fuentes, et. al. Technical Report 21, ICES, 2016. Submitted.  [7]     B. Keith, et. al. J. Nonnewton. Fluid. Mech. In Press.  [8]     B. Keith, et. al. Technical Report 9, ICES, 2017. Submitted.  [9]     S. Petrides et. al. Comput. Math. Appl. In Press.  [10]  A. Vaziri Astaneh, et. al. arXiv preprint:1706.06754, 2017.       Last Modified: 09/26/2017       Submitted by: Leszek F Demkowicz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
