<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Ea SM-3:  Collaborative Res: Surface-induced Forcing and Decadal Variability and Change of the East Asian Climate, Surface Hydrology &amp; Agriculture-A Modeling and Data Approach</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>125255.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>125255</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will contribute to identifying the attribution of East Asian (EA) precipitation changes to anthropogenic and natural drivers and the effects of climate variability on the ecosystem and water resources. The Tibetan Plateau is the source of major Asian river systems that support more than a billion people downstream. The results from this study will provide useful information for surface hydrology and agriculture, critical for a populous and economically vibrant part of the world. The tools for this EA study can be used for global and other regional studies and the state-of-the-art models developed in this project will be released to the research community. This project will also contribute to a number of educational outreach activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A fully-coupled Atmospheric/Ocean GCM/biophysical and biogeochemical models/dynamic vegetation model to: examine the improvements in predictions of EA climate variability and change due to surface-induced forcings, including land use and land cover change (LULCC) and dust and black carbon effects and their two-way interactions in reference to predictions in which one or more of those processes and interactions are neglected; to evaluate and attribute the role played in the EA climate variability by these factors and mechanisms; to examine the effects of those processes on future projections of that regional climate; and to estimate uncertainty through a set of experiments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data from different sources, especially from observations in the Tibetan Plateau (TP), will be applied to evaluate model predictions. In addition, a regional climate model  with high resolution will be applied to assess the regional details of effects of surface-atmosphere interactions on the climate and ecosystem of EA, the TP in particular. Through the representation of key non-linear feedback processes in the EaSM, this project has the potential to substantially improve predictive capabilities and to further explain how different Earth processes and human activities have contributed to EA climate variability and changes over much of the last century.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1419520</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Shen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel S Shen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sam.shen@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6195946280</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000340396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073371346</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921827720</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5500 Campanile Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~125255</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This collaborative EaSM3 project entitled &ldquo;Surface-induced Forcing and Decadal Variability and Change of the East Asian Climate, Surface Hydrology &amp; Agriculture-A Modeling and Data Approach&rdquo; was led by Dr. Yongkang Xue at UCLA in collaboration with Drs. William Parton of Colorado State University and Samuel Shen of San Diego State University (SDSU). The SDSU site focused on data analysis and visualization. A complex system of 4-dimensional visual delivery (4DVD) of big climate data was developed to visualize and deliver some datasets related to the project. The 4DVD system has an interface website <a href="http://www.4dvd.org">www.4dvd.org</a> which can deliver climate data to classrooms and the general public with a very fast speed and make the climate data access only a click away. We also developed a dynamical snow cover monitoring system that can visualize the daily snow cover over the Tibetan Plateau region. Its interface website is <a href="http://www.itsonlyamodel.us/daily-snow.html">http://www.itsonlyamodel.us/daily-snow.html</a> . Our research reconstructed the history of the Tibetan Plateau monthly precipitation since January 1901. The product allows the climate modelers to examine the spatiotemporal patterns over Tibetan Plateau. We also developed computer codes to make statistical prediction of the June precipitation in East Asia using the Tibetan Plateau surface temperature. The research has resulted in many publications, one of which was featured on the cover of the Bulletin of American Meteorological Society. Through these research activities, we have trained 1 PhD student, 5 Masters students, and 2 undergraduate students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;S&nbsp;Shen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This collaborative EaSM3 project entitled "Surface-induced Forcing and Decadal Variability and Change of the East Asian Climate, Surface Hydrology &amp; Agriculture-A Modeling and Data Approach" was led by Dr. Yongkang Xue at UCLA in collaboration with Drs. William Parton of Colorado State University and Samuel Shen of San Diego State University (SDSU). The SDSU site focused on data analysis and visualization. A complex system of 4-dimensional visual delivery (4DVD) of big climate data was developed to visualize and deliver some datasets related to the project. The 4DVD system has an interface website www.4dvd.org which can deliver climate data to classrooms and the general public with a very fast speed and make the climate data access only a click away. We also developed a dynamical snow cover monitoring system that can visualize the daily snow cover over the Tibetan Plateau region. Its interface website is http://www.itsonlyamodel.us/daily-snow.html . Our research reconstructed the history of the Tibetan Plateau monthly precipitation since January 1901. The product allows the climate modelers to examine the spatiotemporal patterns over Tibetan Plateau. We also developed computer codes to make statistical prediction of the June precipitation in East Asia using the Tibetan Plateau surface temperature. The research has resulted in many publications, one of which was featured on the cover of the Bulletin of American Meteorological Society. Through these research activities, we have trained 1 PhD student, 5 Masters students, and 2 undergraduate students.          Last Modified: 10/30/2020       Submitted by: Samuel S Shen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
