<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Communicating appraisals and social motives (CASM): Interpersonal effects of regulated and unregulated emotion expression</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>All people have first-hand knowledge of the importance of emotional expressions in our face-to-face encounters with each other. We trust others partly on the basis of their expressed emotions and in turn, those expressions can help to us to coordinate with different people's actions and intentions. Yet we also know that expressions can be manipulated--people can mask or shape their emotion presentations in order to conceal or disguise their motives, or to protect the feelings of their social partners. Just as we are aware of the importance of emotional expressions we also know they can be manipulated. This awareness means we often refuse to take expressions at face value. This refusal is a double-edged sword--it can protect us from exploitation but can also undermine the effectiveness of communication, especially when misjudge authentic expressions as inauthentic. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project extends prior research on emotional signaling by examining social situations with the potential for emotion regulation. Specifically, the investigators believe that: a) emotion expressions communicate information about the sender's motives; b) senders are sensitive to these communicative effects and regulate their emotion expressions in order to shape their impact on receivers (e.g., to communicate empathy or exert social influence); and c) receivers are aware that these signals may be regulated or inauthentic, and may factor this in when responding to perceived expressions. Thus, the central aim of this project is to investigate how the expression of emotion affects other people's perceptions of the motives guiding behavior, and how the actual and perceived regulation of emotion expression moderates these effects. These questions will be explored through a mixture of naturalistic situations (e.g., doctor-patient interviews) and experimental games (e.g., prisoner's dilemma) in which the respective roles of different interacting individuals or groups can be manipulated, incentives for emotion-regulation can be shaped, and modes of communication may be selectively controlled. These questions will be approached from an interdisciplinary perspective, combining traditional experimental methods in social psychology with modelling and simulation approaches in computer science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1419621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gratch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Gratch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gratch@ict.usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137406478</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314543</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Playa Vista</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900942536</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12015 Waterfront Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>43</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA43</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8093</Code>
<Text>European Open Research Area</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project had three major aims. First, we developed novel computational methods to study how people express emotion in social situations and analyze the authenticity of these displays. To this end, we created a web-based tool where participants could see each other through a Skype-like interface and perform various social tasks like negotiation. This tool allowed us to create tasks where people have an incentive to strategically manipulate their emotions (like negotiation), to measure the emotions they show, and to check if these displays actually reflect their true feelings.</p> <p>Second, we developed theories to explain how people strategically regulate their emotions. We built on a theory, known as social appraisal theory, that claims people attend to how someone emotionally-reacts to an event, and use these reactions to infer their hidden beliefs and intentions. For example, if my brother steps on my foot and smiles, I have a very different impression of his goals than if he steps on my foot and looks embarrassed. Our research shows that people use this theory to guide their strategic emotionally behavior. For example, if my brother is feeling particularly nasty today, he might feign embarrassment so that I drop my guard and he can step on my foot again.&nbsp; Our research provides strong evidence for this theory. For example, we show that people with a Machiavellian personality are more likely to strategically fake their expressions and they fake them in the same way our theory predicts.</p> <p>Finally, we show that this theory has practical application. We build a computer model based on this theory and incorporated it into an autonomous agent that can negotiate with people. The agent would use fake emotions to its bargaining position. We showed that this agent was able negotiate much better deals against human participants than an agent that was honest. Further, people failed to detect this deception and felt the deceptive agent was fair and honest.&nbsp; Facebook recently used machine learning techniques to created a deception negotiation agent which behaves exactly according to our theoretical predictions&nbsp; (see https://www.theregister.co.uk/2017/06/15/facebook_to_teach_chatbots_negotiation/ ) &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>As emotional decption is ubiguious across all aspects of human activity (negotiation, customer service, politics, relationshps), these findings will have broad realvance across several scientific and applied domains.&nbsp;</p> <p>The research also advanced the training of three PhD students and gave them experience in research techniques at the intersection of computer and social science.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Gratch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project had three major aims. First, we developed novel computational methods to study how people express emotion in social situations and analyze the authenticity of these displays. To this end, we created a web-based tool where participants could see each other through a Skype-like interface and perform various social tasks like negotiation. This tool allowed us to create tasks where people have an incentive to strategically manipulate their emotions (like negotiation), to measure the emotions they show, and to check if these displays actually reflect their true feelings.  Second, we developed theories to explain how people strategically regulate their emotions. We built on a theory, known as social appraisal theory, that claims people attend to how someone emotionally-reacts to an event, and use these reactions to infer their hidden beliefs and intentions. For example, if my brother steps on my foot and smiles, I have a very different impression of his goals than if he steps on my foot and looks embarrassed. Our research shows that people use this theory to guide their strategic emotionally behavior. For example, if my brother is feeling particularly nasty today, he might feign embarrassment so that I drop my guard and he can step on my foot again.  Our research provides strong evidence for this theory. For example, we show that people with a Machiavellian personality are more likely to strategically fake their expressions and they fake them in the same way our theory predicts.  Finally, we show that this theory has practical application. We build a computer model based on this theory and incorporated it into an autonomous agent that can negotiate with people. The agent would use fake emotions to its bargaining position. We showed that this agent was able negotiate much better deals against human participants than an agent that was honest. Further, people failed to detect this deception and felt the deceptive agent was fair and honest.  Facebook recently used machine learning techniques to created a deception negotiation agent which behaves exactly according to our theoretical predictions  (see https://www.theregister.co.uk/2017/06/15/facebook_to_teach_chatbots_negotiation/ )      As emotional decption is ubiguious across all aspects of human activity (negotiation, customer service, politics, relationshps), these findings will have broad realvance across several scientific and applied domains.   The research also advanced the training of three PhD students and gave them experience in research techniques at the intersection of computer and social science.          Last Modified: 06/30/2017       Submitted by: Jonathan Gratch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
