<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EDU: Development and Analysis of a Cybersecurity Education Game</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>280492.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>280492</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpiotrow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project involves the design and development of pedagogical games to introduce cybersecurity and cyber safety concepts to students in grades K-6. It will engage students with activities demonstrating the relevance of cybersecurity to the world around them; challenge students with creative puzzle-solving exercises; and will analyze the effectiveness of age-appropriate cybersecurity games to introduce cybersecurity knowledge. A major aspect of this project is the dissemination of cybersecurity principles to elementary school students. If successful in test cases, the games will be provided to school districts for their use nationwide to help establish a national culture of cybersecurity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address the vast difference in capabilities of students in these grades, the project will develop a series of short interactive fun games designed to convey age-appropriate lessons. After delivery to participating school districts in Texas and California, an analysis of their effectiveness will be conducted and the results will be made available to other researchers. The proposed research will be conducted in three phases. In Phase 1, the project will create at least six prototype games accessible to a wide audience, that foster curiosity in security topics. The games will use established and familiar game engines. In Phase 2, the project will develop and deploy at least two of the prototypes in San Antonio, TX and Los Angelos, CA school districts. In Phase 3, the project will evaluate acceptance and impact of the games; disseminate curricular materials, evaluation materials and lessons learned; and will make all software tools available to other educators.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1419367</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory B White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>greg.white@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104586307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000231455</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Grants, Contracts & Ind. Agr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800189185</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at San Antonio]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782493209</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~280492</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project was&nbsp;to study and develop age-appropriate games to help introduce cyber security and/or cyber safety knowledge to students in grades K-6. The first step was to examine currently available games with a cybersecurity theme.&nbsp; After evaluation of these games an attempt to develop games that addressed common issues found in other games was conducted.&nbsp; The final phase was to then evaluate the effectiveness of these games in teaching cybersecurity and online safety topics.</p> <p>In the first phase, we examine 8 different games that were available for free on the Internet.&nbsp; What we were most focused on in the evaluation was whether the game would teach cybersecurity principles to the user.&nbsp; We found that the effectiveness of the game depended on two factors: 1) the playability of the game and more importantly the replayability of the game; and 2) whether the game could be played successfully without ever learning cybersecurity concepts (i.e. did success in the game depend on the user acquiring some knowledge about cybersecurity).&nbsp; Of the games evaluated, most were tremendous failures in regards to our major grading criteria.&nbsp; The two best games evaluated, which still did not get glowing reviews but acceptable reviews from the testers, were Anti-Phishing Phil available from CMU and RPG Puzzle from the University of Memphis.</p> <p>As a result of our examination of the other games that were available, we embarked on developing some games that would address the issues we had identified.&nbsp; Another area we wished to explore was the use of Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR) in gaming to see if that environment might be of even more interest to the students and thus would encourage them to participate in the games more.</p> <p>From our efforts we decided that AR/VR was not a good environment for the target audience.&nbsp; While it is interesting to them and provides some excitement, it requires additional hardware which limits who may elect to use it and the games we explored were just not enhanced by the addition of AR/VR.&nbsp; In particular, we tried to produce a "hidden object" game using AR/VR and it did not add anything at this point to do it.&nbsp; We admit that part of it might have very well been that our game was not sophisticated enough and that with a more elaborate program we might have produced a game that would have sufficiently hidden objects in a manner to make it more interesting for students.&nbsp; This can be left for further research.&nbsp; At this point, the potential benefits are outweighed by the cost and time for producing the game when there are easier and faster ways to produce an acceptable PC-based game.</p> <p>&nbsp;The first game produced and tested was &ldquo;RowdySafe&rdquo; which was designed to promote cybersecurity and safety for young children.&nbsp; It was tested with some students ages 9-12.&nbsp; Pre- and post-tests were conducted to gauge their acquisition of knowledge on the subjects.&nbsp; Pre-test scores ranged from 5 to 155.&nbsp; Post-test scores ranged from 135 to 170 providing an indication that the students did learn from playing the game.&nbsp; In terms of the other gaming factors we were interested in, the student survey showed that students generally liked the game (4.3 on a 5.0 scale), felt they learned something (4.1/5.0), and were interested in the game and continuing to play it (4.4/5.0).</p> <p>Two other games (&ldquo;Pyramid of Knowledge&rdquo; and &ldquo;Project Cipher&rdquo;) were developed and tests run with them.&nbsp; Additionally, a separate game (&ldquo;Cyber Threat Defender &ndash; PC&rdquo;) developed for another effort was also evaluated.&nbsp; All of them with similar results to our first game.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit :</strong></p> <p>Intellectual Merit: This research project hoped to advance knowledge of cyber security principles to K-6 students who normally pay little attention to them. The goal was to introduce security practices to this generation and help in establishing a national culture of security. &nbsp;The project also examined the benefit of using games to convey important lessons to students in these grades.&nbsp; The games developed and tested showed the viability of using games to teach cybersecurity principles and also showed that the students enjoyed them when the criteria of replayability was enforced.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts :</strong></p> <p>Broader Impacts: A major aspect of this project is the dissemination of cyber security and cyber safety principles to students in K-6. In the test cases, the games were provided to school districts for their use. As the games are more broadly used, the potential is to help with establishing a national culture of security.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;B&nbsp;White</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project was to study and develop age-appropriate games to help introduce cyber security and/or cyber safety knowledge to students in grades K-6. The first step was to examine currently available games with a cybersecurity theme.  After evaluation of these games an attempt to develop games that addressed common issues found in other games was conducted.  The final phase was to then evaluate the effectiveness of these games in teaching cybersecurity and online safety topics.  In the first phase, we examine 8 different games that were available for free on the Internet.  What we were most focused on in the evaluation was whether the game would teach cybersecurity principles to the user.  We found that the effectiveness of the game depended on two factors: 1) the playability of the game and more importantly the replayability of the game; and 2) whether the game could be played successfully without ever learning cybersecurity concepts (i.e. did success in the game depend on the user acquiring some knowledge about cybersecurity).  Of the games evaluated, most were tremendous failures in regards to our major grading criteria.  The two best games evaluated, which still did not get glowing reviews but acceptable reviews from the testers, were Anti-Phishing Phil available from CMU and RPG Puzzle from the University of Memphis.  As a result of our examination of the other games that were available, we embarked on developing some games that would address the issues we had identified.  Another area we wished to explore was the use of Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR) in gaming to see if that environment might be of even more interest to the students and thus would encourage them to participate in the games more.  From our efforts we decided that AR/VR was not a good environment for the target audience.  While it is interesting to them and provides some excitement, it requires additional hardware which limits who may elect to use it and the games we explored were just not enhanced by the addition of AR/VR.  In particular, we tried to produce a "hidden object" game using AR/VR and it did not add anything at this point to do it.  We admit that part of it might have very well been that our game was not sophisticated enough and that with a more elaborate program we might have produced a game that would have sufficiently hidden objects in a manner to make it more interesting for students.  This can be left for further research.  At this point, the potential benefits are outweighed by the cost and time for producing the game when there are easier and faster ways to produce an acceptable PC-based game.   The first game produced and tested was "RowdySafe" which was designed to promote cybersecurity and safety for young children.  It was tested with some students ages 9-12.  Pre- and post-tests were conducted to gauge their acquisition of knowledge on the subjects.  Pre-test scores ranged from 5 to 155.  Post-test scores ranged from 135 to 170 providing an indication that the students did learn from playing the game.  In terms of the other gaming factors we were interested in, the student survey showed that students generally liked the game (4.3 on a 5.0 scale), felt they learned something (4.1/5.0), and were interested in the game and continuing to play it (4.4/5.0).  Two other games ("Pyramid of Knowledge" and "Project Cipher") were developed and tests run with them.  Additionally, a separate game ("Cyber Threat Defender &ndash; PC") developed for another effort was also evaluated.  All of them with similar results to our first game.  Intellectual Merit :  Intellectual Merit: This research project hoped to advance knowledge of cyber security principles to K-6 students who normally pay little attention to them. The goal was to introduce security practices to this generation and help in establishing a national culture of security.  The project also examined the benefit of using games to convey important lessons to students in these grades.  The games developed and tested showed the viability of using games to teach cybersecurity principles and also showed that the students enjoyed them when the criteria of replayability was enforced.     Broader Impacts :  Broader Impacts: A major aspect of this project is the dissemination of cyber security and cyber safety principles to students in K-6. In the test cases, the games were provided to school districts for their use. As the games are more broadly used, the potential is to help with establishing a national culture of security.          Last Modified: 11/16/2018       Submitted by: Gregory B White]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
