<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for the 4th School on Spectrum Management for Radio Astronomy, April 7-11, 2014.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41825.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide partial support for a one-week school on spectrum management to be held at the Joint ALMA Observatory offices in Santiago, Chile, during April 7-11, 2014. The emphasis is on protection of radio astronomy frequencies against encroachment by industry and governments throughout the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The school will provide a comprehensive overview of both technical and regulatory issues related to radio astronomers' use of the spectrum. In the past few decades demands on the spectrum have increased substantially due to increases in the demand and availability of wireless applications.  Spectrum management is an importance task for radio astronomy as well as for other radio services, but it is not part of any academic curriculum. The IUCAF Spectrum Management School provides an introduction to a unique combination of technology, science and international diplomacy by experts in this field.  Radio astronomers interested in pursuing this area will get valuable training via this school; the broader impact of this proposal lies in this training.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1419985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>DeBoer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Robert DeBoer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ddeboer@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5105209077</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>4650</Code>
<Text>RADIO SPECTRUM MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~41825</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Analogous to natural reserves that allow researchers and the public to study and enjoy processes of the natural world consistent with our desires for human development and construction, retaining access to the electromagnetic spectrum in certain frequencies or locations allows this same access for study of both the Universe as a whole via astronomy as well as the earth and its processes via remote sensing of the environment. &nbsp;In order to achieve a balance, it is important that scientists understand how public access to the spectrum is managed and be able to engage in this process. &nbsp;</p> <p>This international School on Spectrum Management (see http://www.iucaf.org/sms2014) is an important educational opportunity for scientists (who are naturally generally very focussed on their scientific pursuits) to glimpse the process to be able to meaningfully incorporate these important concepts as they pursue their scientific work and also to train up a new generation to these concepts so that they can participate in this important debate going forward. &nbsp;This NSF support allowed US researchers to participate both as presenters and students in this opportunity. &nbsp;Without this grant, there would have been minimal US participation and an important multi-directional educational opportunity would have been lost.</p> <p>This School is conducted under the auspices of the Scientific Committee on Frequency Allocations for Radio Astronomy and Space Science, which is the key participant for scientific input into frequency management at the international level, primarily by actively participating in the World Radio Conference, which is the treaty-level global mechanism for spectrum management. &nbsp;It was co-sponsored by a number of national and regional organizations and this year was held in Santiago Chile, being hosted by the Atacama Large Millimetre Array (ALMA).</p> <p>ALMA is a new premiere radio telescope that operates primarily in the millimeter-wave band. &nbsp;Holding the School there was particularly timely as there are many new industry initiatives for access to this band of frequencies, whereas in the even recent past this has not been the case. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2014<br>      Modified by: David Robert&nbsp;Deboer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1419985/1419985_10292459_1412180618922_School_photo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1419985/1419985_10292459_1412180618922_School_photo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="School Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1419985/1419985_10292459_1412180618922_School_photo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="School Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image shows many of the participants of the Spectrum School.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ALMA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David Robert&nbsp;Deboer</div> <div class="imageTitle">School Participants</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Analogous to natural reserves that allow researchers and the public to study and enjoy processes of the natural world consistent with our desires for human development and construction, retaining access to the electromagnetic spectrum in certain frequencies or locations allows this same access for study of both the Universe as a whole via astronomy as well as the earth and its processes via remote sensing of the environment.  In order to achieve a balance, it is important that scientists understand how public access to the spectrum is managed and be able to engage in this process.    This international School on Spectrum Management (see http://www.iucaf.org/sms2014) is an important educational opportunity for scientists (who are naturally generally very focussed on their scientific pursuits) to glimpse the process to be able to meaningfully incorporate these important concepts as they pursue their scientific work and also to train up a new generation to these concepts so that they can participate in this important debate going forward.  This NSF support allowed US researchers to participate both as presenters and students in this opportunity.  Without this grant, there would have been minimal US participation and an important multi-directional educational opportunity would have been lost.  This School is conducted under the auspices of the Scientific Committee on Frequency Allocations for Radio Astronomy and Space Science, which is the key participant for scientific input into frequency management at the international level, primarily by actively participating in the World Radio Conference, which is the treaty-level global mechanism for spectrum management.  It was co-sponsored by a number of national and regional organizations and this year was held in Santiago Chile, being hosted by the Atacama Large Millimetre Array (ALMA).  ALMA is a new premiere radio telescope that operates primarily in the millimeter-wave band.  Holding the School there was particularly timely as there are many new industry initiatives for access to this band of frequencies, whereas in the even recent past this has not been the case.            Last Modified: 10/01/2014       Submitted by: David Robert Deboer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
