<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research on the Role of Domain-General Executive Functions in Language Production: Resolving conflict in lexical selection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9193.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9193</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Badecker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbadecke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding how speakers succeed in producing fluent speech with little conscious effort is critical not only to our understanding of the human capacity for language, it also provides insight into how injury to the brain can result in different patterns of loss to that capacity.  Producing speech is an impressive mental feat. For example, even cognitively intact individuals sometimes slip up and say the wrong word (e.g., monotony instead of monogamy). How is it that most of the time speakers manage to avoid such difficulties? Building on previous work, this project proposes that speakers efficiently manage the complexity of speaking by drawing on general mental processes called executive functions. These allow speakers to "focus" mental processing, allowing them to efficiently retrieve the words they wish to speak. This project tests this hypothesis by examining how the efficiency of producing speech is related to (i) individual differences in executive functions and (ii) recent experience using executive functions in other cognitive tasks. Gaining a better understanding of the links between general and language specific mental processes may help professionals capitalize on those links in therapeutic and educational settings. For instance, recent research on bilingualism suggests that regular experience with difficult language processing--e.g., when a bilingual alternates between multiple languages may improve general cognitive control and delay the onset of dementia. Identifying which general processes are involved in speech production may therefore allow the development of cognitive control training that targets those processes--which may be used to help individuals with deficits to language production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will specifically examine how particular parts of general cognitive control contribute to word retrieval during speech production. Previous work has shown that there is competition among multiple representations during word retrieval (e.g., upon seeing a picture of a CAT, the words CAT, RAT, and DOG all come to mind). This project will examine whether general control processes known as executive functions help resolve such competition. Specifically, it will investigate two executive functions that support conflict resolution: response inhibition (suppression of an automatic response to a stimulus) and interference resolution (prevention of an incorrect response when multiple options are available). The first of two studies will test whether speakers? individual differences in response inhibition and interference resolution abilities influence their picture naming performance in the context of strong competition. If the target executive functions help speakers resolve conflict among competing word-level representations, then speakers with higher control abilities should show have less trouble naming pictures in the presence of competition. Importantly, several behavioral tasks will be used to evaluate each executive function, ensuring that the executive function measures do not reflect task-specific effects. The second, parallel study will examine the causality of the relationship between the target executive functions and word retrieval using a procedure known as negative transfer. Each of three groups will receive intensive practice in non-linguistic tasks intended to 'exhaust' a specific executive function. If the target control process (e.g., response inhibition) is involved in conflict resolution during word retrieval, then negative transfer should occur, such that speakers who practiced that process have more trouble naming pictures after practice than before it.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1420820</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew A Goldrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matt-goldrick@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474677092</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Fink</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela A Fink</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>AngelaFink2015@u.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913003</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660731</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Linguistics]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080854</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2016 Sheridan Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~9193</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During conversation, speakers are faced with a series of choices about what to say. They must pick concepts, words, and sounds to convey their ideas to listeners, and they must do so efficiently in order to converse fluently. How do speakers avoid mistakes during this complex process? This project extended previous work, which suggested that speakers might recruit general mental processes called executive functions to guide production. Executive functions help individuals &ldquo;focus&rdquo; mental processes, and such focusing might streamline the process of selecting words to speak.</p> <p>The behavioral results of this project provide some support and some challenges for this hypothesis. They confirmed that specific executive functions can influence word selection, helping the speaker to ignore non-target words (e.g., upon seeing a picture of a CAT, focusing on the word CAT rather than RAT or DOG). Engaging the executive function of interference resolution (suppression of previously relevant information) allowed speakers to produce the right word more quickly, but engaging response inhibition (suppression of an automatic response) did not. However, the results also suggested that interference resolution is not automatically recruited to assist speech production. Instead, speakers seem to engage this general mental process only after encountering a major mental conflict (e.g., a task that requires participants to ignore information that was relevant on previous trial, but is now no longer relevant).</p> <p>The primary intellectual merit of this project is its advancement of our understanding of the mental processes involved in word selection, as well as the link between general and language specific processes. It has extended previous correlational work to demonstrate a causal link between executive function engagement and fluent of spoken production. These findings have implications for the broader community. With an improved understanding of the link between general and language specific processes, practitioners are more likely to succeed at capitalizing on that link in therapeutic and educational settings. Speakers who have developmental or acquired difficulties choosing words may benefit from cognitive training that targets specific executive functions like interference resolution.</p> <p>This project also addressed a secondary question: does the difficulty of word selection influence the articulation of the words produced? In other words, the project explored whether and how the planning processes involved in production affect the actual execution of speech. The results suggest that the relationship between planning and articulation is flexible, depending on task conditions and individual variation in cognitive processing. Word selection difficulties can change the sound of an utterance (e.g., increasing word durations), but those changes may only be detectable when selection is seriously disrupted or the speaker hurries through planning. The presence of such flexibility in the production system helps explain why previous studies in this field generated inconsistent evidence. This project therefore clarifies the empirical landscape within the field of spoken production, suggesting that areas in cognitive psychology might benefit from consideration of such flexibility and individual variation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2016<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goldrick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During conversation, speakers are faced with a series of choices about what to say. They must pick concepts, words, and sounds to convey their ideas to listeners, and they must do so efficiently in order to converse fluently. How do speakers avoid mistakes during this complex process? This project extended previous work, which suggested that speakers might recruit general mental processes called executive functions to guide production. Executive functions help individuals "focus" mental processes, and such focusing might streamline the process of selecting words to speak.  The behavioral results of this project provide some support and some challenges for this hypothesis. They confirmed that specific executive functions can influence word selection, helping the speaker to ignore non-target words (e.g., upon seeing a picture of a CAT, focusing on the word CAT rather than RAT or DOG). Engaging the executive function of interference resolution (suppression of previously relevant information) allowed speakers to produce the right word more quickly, but engaging response inhibition (suppression of an automatic response) did not. However, the results also suggested that interference resolution is not automatically recruited to assist speech production. Instead, speakers seem to engage this general mental process only after encountering a major mental conflict (e.g., a task that requires participants to ignore information that was relevant on previous trial, but is now no longer relevant).  The primary intellectual merit of this project is its advancement of our understanding of the mental processes involved in word selection, as well as the link between general and language specific processes. It has extended previous correlational work to demonstrate a causal link between executive function engagement and fluent of spoken production. These findings have implications for the broader community. With an improved understanding of the link between general and language specific processes, practitioners are more likely to succeed at capitalizing on that link in therapeutic and educational settings. Speakers who have developmental or acquired difficulties choosing words may benefit from cognitive training that targets specific executive functions like interference resolution.  This project also addressed a secondary question: does the difficulty of word selection influence the articulation of the words produced? In other words, the project explored whether and how the planning processes involved in production affect the actual execution of speech. The results suggest that the relationship between planning and articulation is flexible, depending on task conditions and individual variation in cognitive processing. Word selection difficulties can change the sound of an utterance (e.g., increasing word durations), but those changes may only be detectable when selection is seriously disrupted or the speaker hurries through planning. The presence of such flexibility in the production system helps explain why previous studies in this field generated inconsistent evidence. This project therefore clarifies the empirical landscape within the field of spoken production, suggesting that areas in cognitive psychology might benefit from consideration of such flexibility and individual variation.            Last Modified: 07/18/2016       Submitted by: Matthew A Goldrick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
