<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EPSCoR Workshop: A 2014 Workshop on Engineered Crops</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Uma Venkateswaran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Iowa State University (ISU) is organizing a workshop focused on the knowledge, technology, and education needed to engineer agricultural products that are robust under changing climate.  The ultimate goal is to develop a research and educational roadmap for engineered crops, of interest to the EPSCoR community because many jurisdictions are rural and have a strong agricultural heritage. The workshop is bringing together plant scientists, with expertise in improving crop performance, and engineers with knowledge of transport phenomena, thermodynamics, and modeling, to unlock the underlying structural and physiological properties of superior plant varieties.  Engineering- and physics-based modeling of transport phenomena in plants is still in its infancy, but approximate models have been made and verified experimentally to describe the transport of water and sugar in plants.  This workshop provides opportunities for plant scientists and engineers to develop a common language for engineered crops, share ongoing research, form new partnerships, and design the discipline of "plant engineering" - a cyber-enabled framework that will support accelerated crop design with desired optimal performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Food security is among the top challenges facing humanity. Environmental stresses due to climate change are accelerating the need for plant modifications, either naturally or through genetic engineering. As a step towards addressing these challenges, ISU's workshop focuses on the emergence of engineering design methods rooted in plant physiology and transport phenomena, to develop improved crops with increased yield and/or better tolerance to abiotic stresses caused by climate change. These technologies have reached a stage where fundamental questions about optimal crop phenotypes can be answered, and the answers efficiently translated into crop improvement. The goal of tailoring crops using engineering know-how coupled with genetic engineering is novel, promising, and challenging. Workshop products include a written roadmap summarizing the necessary education, research and development to advance engineered crops, as well as publications, and a website for displaying outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a constant need to improve the efficiency and yield of global agricultural crop production in order to increase food supply. This workshop at ISU will offer opportunities to scientists and engineers from EPSCoR jurisdictions to develop an interdisciplinary approach towards the design and study of engineered crops. Activities in the workshop will highlight the contributions of agricultural businesses and researchers in EPSCoR jurisdictions to the development of engineered plants, and the education of future researchers able to work in this field. Workshop recruitment efforts focus on junior faculty and students from EPSCoR jurisdictions, including from community colleges and schools in the nearby locale that have high underrepresented minority science, technology, engineering, and mathematics enrollments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1420704</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
<LastName>Heindel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theodore J Heindel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>theindel@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152940057</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336839</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Attinger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Attinger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>attinger@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152941423</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000154653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112161</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2025 Black Engineering Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Outreach and Workshops</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCOR OUTREACH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~99996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of this project were to: (1) organize and host a workshop bringing together engineers and plant scientists that focused on the knowledge, technology, and education needed to breed improved agricultural products, (2) develop a research and educational roadmap for engineered crops, and (3) facilitate collaborations between plant scientists and engineers.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Organize and Host a Workshop</strong></span></p> <p>A workshop entitled &ldquo;1<sup>st</sup> International Workshop on Engineered Crops&rdquo; was organized and presented on April 28-29, 2014, at Hotel Fort Des Moines, in Des Moines, Iowa. The final workshop format was composed of three plenary talks and five panel sessions that spanned over two days. A poster session for students (with cash prizes provided by DuPont Pioneer) was also organized. The plenary talks focused on (1) genomics overview and why we need engineered crops, (2) engineering and physical challenges to engineered crops, and (3) biophysical drivers to increase crop yield. Topics covered by the panel presentations and discussions included: (1) genotype and environmental interactions and stresses (2) plant physiology and flow and nutrient transport, (3) numerical modeling and optimization, (4) phenomics and imaging, and (5) education and training needs.</p> <p>Workshop participants were surveyed at three different times: (1) during the workshop online registration process, (2) at the conclusion of the workshop, and (3) six months after the workshop was completed.</p> <p>Of the 95 participants at the workshop, 52 identified themselves as &ldquo;plant scientists&rdquo;, 30 as &ldquo;engineer&rdquo;, 9 as &ldquo;biologist&rdquo;, and 4 as &ldquo;other&rdquo;. Hence, we were able to bring together plant scientists and engineers. There were also many verbal comments made to the organizers during the workshop that this was a unique environment to bring together plant scientists and engineers, and there had not been any other venue to-date that did this; the comments were universal that the workshop was a good idea.</p> <p>Based on participant survey data, 80-90% of the participants either agreed or strongly agreed with the following statements at the conclusion of the workshop:</p> <ul> <li>More aware of opportunities for cross-disciplinary research in engineered crops.</li> <li>Better prepared to collaborate with researchers in other disciplines/organizations.</li> <li>Made contacts with researchers to develop future collaborations for research in engineered crops.</li> </ul> <p>Based on these data, we conclude the workshop was successful.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Develop a Research and Educational Roadmap for Engineered Crops</strong></span></p> <p>Roadmap development was the most challenging part of the workshop and is still on-going.</p> <p>In the area of research (and a result of our workshop), the Plant Science Institute (PSI) at Iowa State University has initiated a PSI Faculty Scholars program. This program builds on traditional ISU strengths in plant breeding and crop improvement, crop genetics and genomics, bioinformatics and statistics, and fosters new collaborations with engineers and computational scientists. Two of the workshop organizing committee members and several of the ISU workshop attendees became PSI Faculty Scholars.</p> <p>In the area of education, a new education collaboration was formed as a result of our workshop and it resulted in a funded National Science Foundation Research Traineeship (NRT) grant (DGE-1545453: NRT-DESE: P3 -- Predictive Phenomics of Plants), which started September 1, 2015. The goal of this NRT is to develop a graduate specialization in predictive plant phenomics that includes engineering, plant science, and data science graduate students.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Facilitate Collaborations between Plant Scientists and Engineers</strong></span></p> <p>The goal of enhancing collaborations between engineers and plant sciences was a complete success. A significant number of survey respondents answered favorably to the following collaboration statements 6 months after the workshop:</p> <ul> <li>Made contacts with researchers to develop future collaborations (82%).</li> <li>Initiated efforts to collaborate outside your discipline or institution (64%).</li> <li>Continued or expanded efforts to collaborate outside your discipline or institution (73%).</li> <li>Part of an ongoing collaboration outside your discipline or institution (70%).</li> </ul> <p>Many participants indicated they were involved in engineered crops related research activities 6 months after the workshop, where 87% of the participants planned to initiate or continue/expand collaborations with colleagues outside their discipline or institution/organization in the area of engineered crops.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Theodore&nbsp;J&nbsp;Heindel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1420704/1420704_10292288_1493307655868_WorkshopParticipants_smallerimage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1420704/1420704_10292288_1493307655868_WorkshopParticipants_smallerimage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Workshop Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1420704/1420704_10292288_1493307655868_WorkshopParticipants_smallerimage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Workshop Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participants at the 1st International Workshop on Engineered Crops</div> <div class="imageCredit">Robert Elbert, ISU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Theodore&nbsp;J&nbsp;Heindel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Workshop Participants</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of this project were to: (1) organize and host a workshop bringing together engineers and plant scientists that focused on the knowledge, technology, and education needed to breed improved agricultural products, (2) develop a research and educational roadmap for engineered crops, and (3) facilitate collaborations between plant scientists and engineers.  Organize and Host a Workshop  A workshop entitled "1st International Workshop on Engineered Crops" was organized and presented on April 28-29, 2014, at Hotel Fort Des Moines, in Des Moines, Iowa. The final workshop format was composed of three plenary talks and five panel sessions that spanned over two days. A poster session for students (with cash prizes provided by DuPont Pioneer) was also organized. The plenary talks focused on (1) genomics overview and why we need engineered crops, (2) engineering and physical challenges to engineered crops, and (3) biophysical drivers to increase crop yield. Topics covered by the panel presentations and discussions included: (1) genotype and environmental interactions and stresses (2) plant physiology and flow and nutrient transport, (3) numerical modeling and optimization, (4) phenomics and imaging, and (5) education and training needs.  Workshop participants were surveyed at three different times: (1) during the workshop online registration process, (2) at the conclusion of the workshop, and (3) six months after the workshop was completed.  Of the 95 participants at the workshop, 52 identified themselves as "plant scientists", 30 as "engineer", 9 as "biologist", and 4 as "other". Hence, we were able to bring together plant scientists and engineers. There were also many verbal comments made to the organizers during the workshop that this was a unique environment to bring together plant scientists and engineers, and there had not been any other venue to-date that did this; the comments were universal that the workshop was a good idea.  Based on participant survey data, 80-90% of the participants either agreed or strongly agreed with the following statements at the conclusion of the workshop:  More aware of opportunities for cross-disciplinary research in engineered crops. Better prepared to collaborate with researchers in other disciplines/organizations. Made contacts with researchers to develop future collaborations for research in engineered crops.   Based on these data, we conclude the workshop was successful.  Develop a Research and Educational Roadmap for Engineered Crops  Roadmap development was the most challenging part of the workshop and is still on-going.  In the area of research (and a result of our workshop), the Plant Science Institute (PSI) at Iowa State University has initiated a PSI Faculty Scholars program. This program builds on traditional ISU strengths in plant breeding and crop improvement, crop genetics and genomics, bioinformatics and statistics, and fosters new collaborations with engineers and computational scientists. Two of the workshop organizing committee members and several of the ISU workshop attendees became PSI Faculty Scholars.  In the area of education, a new education collaboration was formed as a result of our workshop and it resulted in a funded National Science Foundation Research Traineeship (NRT) grant (DGE-1545453: NRT-DESE: P3 -- Predictive Phenomics of Plants), which started September 1, 2015. The goal of this NRT is to develop a graduate specialization in predictive plant phenomics that includes engineering, plant science, and data science graduate students.  Facilitate Collaborations between Plant Scientists and Engineers  The goal of enhancing collaborations between engineers and plant sciences was a complete success. A significant number of survey respondents answered favorably to the following collaboration statements 6 months after the workshop:  Made contacts with researchers to develop future collaborations (82%). Initiated efforts to collaborate outside your discipline or institution (64%). Continued or expanded efforts to collaborate outside your discipline or institution (73%). Part of an ongoing collaboration outside your discipline or institution (70%).   Many participants indicated they were involved in engineered crops related research activities 6 months after the workshop, where 87% of the participants planned to initiate or continue/expand collaborations with colleagues outside their discipline or institution/organization in the area of engineered crops.        Last Modified: 04/27/2017       Submitted by: Theodore J Heindel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
