<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Double Isolation: Social Pressure and Gender Disparities in Computer Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>596747.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>631747</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jolene Jesse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjesse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In 2010, women earned about half of all science undergraduate degrees; yet in the same year, women earned less than 20% of computer science degrees. Computer science remains one of the least gender diverse of the STEM fields and one of the most impervious to change. Current theories that explain this disparity typically focus on women's attitudes and backgrounds (e.g., lower confidence, lack of prerequisites) or the unwelcoming climate of the field (e.g., negative stereotypes about women's abilities). This work will focus on an overlooked component of women's experience in the selection of an academic field: social pressure from peers to conceal an interest in the field. Specifically, the research will investigate whether women express less interest in computer science because they anticipate negative judgment for entering a stereotypically masculine field. Current interventions to draw girls into male-dominated fields typically focus on changing women (e.g., providing computing experience). The research proposed here suggests that women may be forsaking important learning opportunities in STEM before trying them because of the social pressure they perceive. However, relatively simple changes to educational environments may be able to "turn off" this social pressure and increase women's interest in computer science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current work develops and tests a theoretical model that identifies the sources of social pressure on women and the consequences of this social pressure on women's interest and performance in computer science. To test the theory, researchers will conduct two surveys in Year 1 and seven behavioral experiments in Years 1 to 3. In Year 1, the focus will be on whether women perceive more social pressure than men in computer science but not in other fields (e.g., English), and the effects of perceived social pressure on interest and performance in computer science. In Year 2, the research will examine how to reduce social pressure by using private learning mechanisms and broadening stereotypes. In Year 3, the researchers will partner with the Computer Science Teachers Association to conduct a large-scale field experiment across multiple high schools that tests whether exposure to female computer science role models who are portrayed with their friends reduces perceived social pressure on women and increases their interest in computer science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1420351</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sapna</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheryan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sapna Cheryan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scheryan@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065435688</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311609</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951525</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box 351525]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1544</Code>
<Text>RES ON GENDER IN SCI &amp; ENGINE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>018Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~596747</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~35000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our findings demonstrated that the perceived masculine culture of computer science, engineering, and physics is a powerful reason explaining why these fields continue to have gender disparities in participation in high school and college. Our work further investigates how to change these masculine cultures in order to encourage women&rsquo;s participation. We have produced seven publications in high-impact journals (e.g., <em>Psychological Bulletin,</em> <em>Developmental Psychology</em>, <em>Journal of Educational Psychology</em>) addressing the four main program objectives: to investigate women&rsquo;s anticipation of social pressure surrounding computer science, physics, and engineering; to investigate how the cultures of computer science, physics, and engineering contribute to gender disparities in these fields; to examine effects of cultural factors across development; and to implement and investigate interventions to reduce gender disparities in computer science.</p> <p>In one line of work, we demonstrated that when undergraduate women consider majoring in computer science, they report identity expression threat, or a concern about conveying a social identity that may be inconsistent with their gender role. This threat results in women&rsquo;s greater reported likelihood &ndash; relative to men&rsquo;s &ndash; of downplaying their interest in CS to peers. Women majoring in computer science perceive an unfortunate &ldquo;double isolation&rdquo;: they anticipate isolation not only from those inside computer science but also from peers outside the field for choosing it.</p> <p>In a second line of work, we demonstrated effects of the perceived masculine culture on younger students. By age 6, students already have gendered stereotypes about computer science and engineering, believing that boys are better than girls at these subjects. Among high school students, classroom environments that are depicted in a way that counter prevalent male-oriented stereotypes about computer scientists successfully increase high school girls&rsquo; interest in introductory computer science courses. Intervening to address stereotypes at young ages is crucial to ensuring that girls have opportunities in these fields equal to those of boys.</p> <p>In a third line of work, we have been synthesizing current literature to answer novel questions about gender disparities in STEM fields. In a paper published in 2017 and cited more than 175 times to date, we answer the question of why some STEM fields (e.g., biology, chemistry, math) are more gender-balanced at the undergraduate level than other STEM fields (e.g., computer science, physics, engineering). We found that masculine cultures and little pre-college coursework intersect to explain why computer science, physics, and engineering have gender disparities. In another paper, currently under review, we propose broadening the definition of gender bias to include masculine defaults, or aspects of cultures that reward or see as standard characteristics and behaviors that are associated with the male gender role.</p> <p>One goal of the grant is to disseminate the research, especially to those who can help change STEM cultures. We continue to reach a wide and varied audience with multiple dissemination efforts, including talks, conference presentations, and through our website and blog. Notable media outlets have disseminated our work during this time period, including <em>Time</em>, <em>BBC</em>, <em>The Washington Post, The Atlantic</em>, and <em>The New York Times</em>. The PI has had a number of speaking engagements at a variety of institutions (University of California, Berkeley, Harvard University, Stanford University, University of Chicago), professional conferences (NCWIT; Society for Personality and Social Psychology; Learning &amp; The Brain), and companies (Apple; Google; Microsoft; Zillow). Notably, the PI was also invited to The White House in July 2016 to speak to the President&rsquo;s Council of Advisors on Science and Technology on the role of masculine cultures in deterring women and girls from computer science and how we can change these cultures to encourage women&rsquo;s participation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Sapna&nbsp;Cheryan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our findings demonstrated that the perceived masculine culture of computer science, engineering, and physics is a powerful reason explaining why these fields continue to have gender disparities in participation in high school and college. Our work further investigates how to change these masculine cultures in order to encourage women?s participation. We have produced seven publications in high-impact journals (e.g., Psychological Bulletin, Developmental Psychology, Journal of Educational Psychology) addressing the four main program objectives: to investigate women?s anticipation of social pressure surrounding computer science, physics, and engineering; to investigate how the cultures of computer science, physics, and engineering contribute to gender disparities in these fields; to examine effects of cultural factors across development; and to implement and investigate interventions to reduce gender disparities in computer science.  In one line of work, we demonstrated that when undergraduate women consider majoring in computer science, they report identity expression threat, or a concern about conveying a social identity that may be inconsistent with their gender role. This threat results in women?s greater reported likelihood &ndash; relative to men?s &ndash; of downplaying their interest in CS to peers. Women majoring in computer science perceive an unfortunate "double isolation": they anticipate isolation not only from those inside computer science but also from peers outside the field for choosing it.  In a second line of work, we demonstrated effects of the perceived masculine culture on younger students. By age 6, students already have gendered stereotypes about computer science and engineering, believing that boys are better than girls at these subjects. Among high school students, classroom environments that are depicted in a way that counter prevalent male-oriented stereotypes about computer scientists successfully increase high school girls? interest in introductory computer science courses. Intervening to address stereotypes at young ages is crucial to ensuring that girls have opportunities in these fields equal to those of boys.  In a third line of work, we have been synthesizing current literature to answer novel questions about gender disparities in STEM fields. In a paper published in 2017 and cited more than 175 times to date, we answer the question of why some STEM fields (e.g., biology, chemistry, math) are more gender-balanced at the undergraduate level than other STEM fields (e.g., computer science, physics, engineering). We found that masculine cultures and little pre-college coursework intersect to explain why computer science, physics, and engineering have gender disparities. In another paper, currently under review, we propose broadening the definition of gender bias to include masculine defaults, or aspects of cultures that reward or see as standard characteristics and behaviors that are associated with the male gender role.  One goal of the grant is to disseminate the research, especially to those who can help change STEM cultures. We continue to reach a wide and varied audience with multiple dissemination efforts, including talks, conference presentations, and through our website and blog. Notable media outlets have disseminated our work during this time period, including Time, BBC, The Washington Post, The Atlantic, and The New York Times. The PI has had a number of speaking engagements at a variety of institutions (University of California, Berkeley, Harvard University, Stanford University, University of Chicago), professional conferences (NCWIT; Society for Personality and Social Psychology; Learning &amp; The Brain), and companies (Apple; Google; Microsoft; Zillow). Notably, the PI was also invited to The White House in July 2016 to speak to the President?s Council of Advisors on Science and Technology on the role of masculine cultures in deterring women and girls from computer science and how we can change these cultures to encourage women?s participation.          Last Modified: 05/14/2019       Submitted by: Sapna Cheryan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
