<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>OCE-PRF Track 1 (Broadening Participation): Near-Inertial Oscillations on the West Florida Shelf in the Eastern Gulf of Mexico</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Pugh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gpugh@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Near-Inertial Oscillations (NIO) in the coastal ocean may play a significant role in vertical mixing and horizontal dispersion&lt;br/&gt;of nutrients and particles in the eastern Gulf of Mexico, particularly on the West Florida Shelf (WFS).  There is evidence that on the WFS the depth of the thermocline appears to migrate vertically over the course of a day, suggestive that a NIO mode structure may be modulating the thermocline depth and possibly affecting the distribution of biota across the thermocline, making the NIO potentially important to the coastal ocean ecology on the WFS. This award will support a Postdoctoral Fellow to investigate the dynamics of NIO on the WFS. The Fellow will work at the College of Marine Science at the University of South Florida (USF-CMS) with the sponsorship of Dr. Robert H. Weisberg, and in the Center for Ocean-Atmospheric Prediction Studies at the Florida State University (FSU-COAPS) with the co-sponsorship of Dr. Dmitry Dukhovskoy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;She will also mentor a summer undergraduate student through the Florida-Georgia Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (LS-AMP) at FSU, develop a physical oceanography lab to add to a set of bio-geochemical labs for the Oceanography Camp for Girls and contribute physical oceanography questions for the Spoonbill Ocean Sciences Bowl.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will investigate the kinematics of NIO on the West Florida Shelf (WFS) with a full documentation of their spatial and temporal variations. This will be followed by a thorough investigation of the dynamics of the processes, particularly, how turbulence and bottom stress enter into the force balances and affect the conditions and mechanisms of generation of NIO in the region. Finally, the role of near-inertial motions in mixing on the WFS will be assessed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1421180</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ekaterina</FirstName>
<LastName>Maksimova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ekaterina V Maksimova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8503396287</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662914</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Maksimova               Ekaterina      V</Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<ZipCode>323092878</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Florida College of Marine Science]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Petersburg</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>337015016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8205</Code>
<Text>OCE Postdoctoral Fellowships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~174000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The physical oceanographic study considered inertial currents on the west Florida shelf in the Gulf of Mexico. Inertial current oscillations refer to near-circular motions of water (&ldquo;swirly whirlies&rdquo;) in which a special balance of physical forces holds true: namely, the inertial acceleration and the Coriolis acceleration due to rotation of the Earth balance each other.&nbsp; Inertial currents were first observed in the Baltic Sea just a little over 80 years ago. To this date, there is no clear understanding of all factors responsible for their generation and dissipation in the real Ocean. It is, however, recognized that mixing in the ocean driven by inertial motions may significantly control the climate! Taking advantage of the unique current, temperature, and salinity data collected off the west Florida coast in waters as shallow as 16 ft and as deep as 525 ft, this study aimed at better understanding of the &ldquo;swirly whirlies&rdquo; and of their role, potentially leading to further improvements in ocean and climate model predictions. The major result of the study was a better explanation of some of the observed patterns in the near-inertial current variability using mathematical theory.</p> <p>The broader impacts of the work were the following. We developed and provided a hands-on, inquiry-based physical oceanography research lab for the Oceanography Camp for Girls at the University of South Florida. We contributed physical oceanography questions for the National Ocean Science Bowl and judged at the regional Spoonbill Bowl in St. Petersburg, Florida. Finally, we mentored an undergraduate student in the field of physical oceanography. These activities aimed to achieve a specific societal outcome - broadening participation of the underrepresented groups in the important field of physical oceanography.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2016<br>      Modified by: Ekaterina&nbsp;V&nbsp;Maksimova</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The physical oceanographic study considered inertial currents on the west Florida shelf in the Gulf of Mexico. Inertial current oscillations refer to near-circular motions of water ("swirly whirlies") in which a special balance of physical forces holds true: namely, the inertial acceleration and the Coriolis acceleration due to rotation of the Earth balance each other.  Inertial currents were first observed in the Baltic Sea just a little over 80 years ago. To this date, there is no clear understanding of all factors responsible for their generation and dissipation in the real Ocean. It is, however, recognized that mixing in the ocean driven by inertial motions may significantly control the climate! Taking advantage of the unique current, temperature, and salinity data collected off the west Florida coast in waters as shallow as 16 ft and as deep as 525 ft, this study aimed at better understanding of the "swirly whirlies" and of their role, potentially leading to further improvements in ocean and climate model predictions. The major result of the study was a better explanation of some of the observed patterns in the near-inertial current variability using mathematical theory.  The broader impacts of the work were the following. We developed and provided a hands-on, inquiry-based physical oceanography research lab for the Oceanography Camp for Girls at the University of South Florida. We contributed physical oceanography questions for the National Ocean Science Bowl and judged at the regional Spoonbill Bowl in St. Petersburg, Florida. Finally, we mentored an undergraduate student in the field of physical oceanography. These activities aimed to achieve a specific societal outcome - broadening participation of the underrepresented groups in the important field of physical oceanography.          Last Modified: 12/09/2016       Submitted by: Ekaterina V Maksimova]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
