<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Project TRUE (Teens Researching Urban Ecology)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1413826.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1413826</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen McCallie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emccalli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925115</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The nation's job market is creating more STEM jobs than jobs in other fields - a trend predicted to continue for the next 10 years. Although there has been a slight increase in the number of STEM graduates in the US, the percentage of graduates from underrepresented populations remains low. This project will study how a hands-on urban ecology research program can positively impact underrepresented teens and lead them to pursue STEM-related courses and majors in college. Through a partnership between an informal science institution (the Wildlife Conservation Society) and a university (Fordham University), 200 teens from underrepresented backgrounds will conduct urban ecology research at one of four zoos in New York City under the guidance of a university professor, graduate and undergraduate students, and zoo education staff. One of the unique features of the urban ecology program will be a tiered mentorship model, in which university professors mentor graduate urban ecology students, who in turn mentor undergraduate students, and together they mentor high school students from communities underrepresented in STEM fields. Ultimately, this project will identify programmatic strategies and student support methods that can help expand and diversify the STEM workforce. This project is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program, which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research and development project will advance the field of STEM learning by investigating four key programmatic elements that previous studies have suggested increase interest and participation in STEM: 1) Hands-on STEM experience; 2) Awareness of the utility of STEM learning in the world; 3) Exposure to a role model; and 4) Interaction with peers with shared STEM interest. The research will develop survey-based measurement tools and use multivariate analysis to examine the influence of each programmatic element on short- and medium-term STEM-related outcomes over a five-year period. The research will further address questions to understand the impact of these four principles within a real-world context, including the degree to which non-project factors (e.g. parental support, school coursework, etc.) influence the model, thus limiting or enhancing impact. Additionally, the evaluation component of this project will examine the impacts of the tiered mentorship model in greater depth through a formal case study. The research and evaluation will be complementary, with the research looking across cohorts of participants over time, and the evaluation exploring participant experiences in depth.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1421017</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Don</FirstName>
<LastName>Lisowy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Don Lisowy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlisowy@wcs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7182204052</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000136094</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/16/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian@peerassociates.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6048394339</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Tingley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen Tingley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ktingley@wcs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7187418211</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662839</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Aloisio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Aloisio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jaloisio@wcs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7187418211</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000724695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wildlife Conservation Society</Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<ZipCode>104600000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7187418211</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2300 Southern Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075209650</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILDLIFE CONSERVATION SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075209650</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wildlife Conservation Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>104601099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2300 Southern Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~577573</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~280606</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~289024</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~266623</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project TRUE (Teens Researching Urban Ecology) was a summer research experience for New York City youth that focused on strengthening their STEM interest, skills, and ultimately, increasing diversity in STEM fields. We studied the impacts of two key parts of the program &ndash; conducting authentic science research and mentorship &ndash; on the STEM trajectories of almost 200 high school students who participated in the program from 2015 to 2018.</p> <p>During the 7-week summer program, teams of three to four high school students and one undergraduate mentor developed ecology research projects and conducted fieldwork in New York City parks and green spaces. Graduate students, science educators, and professional scientists provided mentorship to undergraduates throughout the projects. This tiered near-peer mentoring model deliberately paired mentors and mentees who were close in age and academic level, increasing their ability to identify with each other and form stronger mentoring relationships.</p> <p>Science research projects focused on urban ecology topics, with high school students identifying their own research questions nested within the undergraduate mentor&rsquo;s research question, thereby establishing a sense of ownership over the work. Research activities involved trapping eels, recording bat vocalizations, catching and sorting insects, and identifying invasive plant species, among others. The research experience culminated in the creation of research posters and teams presenting their posters to the public at a student science symposium.&nbsp;</p> <p>Over four summers, Project TRUE served 189 high school students, most of whom were from backgrounds traditionally underrepresented in the sciences. Specifically, 71% of high school students identified as female, 43% as Hispanic or Latinx, and 33% as Black or African American. Of the 60 undergraduate mentors, 88% were from backgrounds underrepresented in the sciences,</p> <p>The research explored short-term outcomes immediately after the program and followed up with students multiple years after participation to understand the impacts of the experience during and after the transition from high school to college. We found that the hands-on research experiences were effective at supporting youths&rsquo; science interest, intentions to pursue STEM majors in college, and perceptions that STEM would be part of their future careers. These positive effects on science engagement continued at least two years after participation in the program and were similar for youth who entered the program very interested in science, as well as those with relatively lower pre-program science interest. This study&rsquo;s focus on the transition from high school to college is a novel contribution to our understanding of STEM trajectories, indicating that authentic research experiences at the end of high school may increase retention of STEM scholars during a critical transitionary period. Previous research has recognized that high school STEM achievement is related to STEM success in college, however, there has been relatively little work to track predictors of STEM outcomes during the college transition. Longitudinal data like this is critical to understanding long-term impacts and the variety of pathways within the STEM pipeline.</p> <p>In contrast to research experiences, mentoring did not show strong impacts on science interest or intentions to pursue STEM. It did, however, have strong positive relationships with youths&rsquo; sense of social connection, suggesting a more indirect influence on youths&rsquo; STEM identities and trajectories. This indirect influence may occur because mentoring helped youth establish a sense of belonging in STEM by establishing social connections with their undergraduate mentors and like-minded peers. Feelings of integration or belongingness to the community appear closely associated with the perceived benefits of programs aimed at increased retention of underrepresented youth in college and are tied to academic outcomes.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Karen&nbsp;Tingley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346058186_232--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346058186_232--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampling macroinvertebrates"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346058186_232--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sampling macroinvertebrates"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Project TRUE students collect macroinvertebrates during fieldwork.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason Aloisio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;Tingley</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sampling macroinvertebrates</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346208944_IMG_7553--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346208944_IMG_7553--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sorting and identifying insects"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346208944_IMG_7553--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sorting and identifying insects"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Project TRUE students sort and identify insects caught during fieldwork.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason Aloisio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;Tingley</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sorting and identifying insects</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346346108_SamplingVegUdall'sCoverCPZ(wecompress.com)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346346108_SamplingVegUdall'sCoverCPZ(wecompress.com)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Measuring vegetation cover"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346346108_SamplingVegUdall'sCoverCPZ(wecompress.com)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Measuring vegetation cover"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Project TRUE students use quadrats to measure vegetation cover at a New York City park.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason Aloisio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;Tingley</div> <div class="imageTitle">Measuring vegetation cover</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346443234_IMG_5753--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346443234_IMG_5753--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Presenting Research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1421017/1421017_10333751_1594346443234_IMG_5753--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Presenting Research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Project TRUE students presenting their poster at a science symposium</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason Aloisio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;Tingley</div> <div class="imageTitle">Presenting Research</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project TRUE (Teens Researching Urban Ecology) was a summer research experience for New York City youth that focused on strengthening their STEM interest, skills, and ultimately, increasing diversity in STEM fields. We studied the impacts of two key parts of the program &ndash; conducting authentic science research and mentorship &ndash; on the STEM trajectories of almost 200 high school students who participated in the program from 2015 to 2018.  During the 7-week summer program, teams of three to four high school students and one undergraduate mentor developed ecology research projects and conducted fieldwork in New York City parks and green spaces. Graduate students, science educators, and professional scientists provided mentorship to undergraduates throughout the projects. This tiered near-peer mentoring model deliberately paired mentors and mentees who were close in age and academic level, increasing their ability to identify with each other and form stronger mentoring relationships.  Science research projects focused on urban ecology topics, with high school students identifying their own research questions nested within the undergraduate mentor’s research question, thereby establishing a sense of ownership over the work. Research activities involved trapping eels, recording bat vocalizations, catching and sorting insects, and identifying invasive plant species, among others. The research experience culminated in the creation of research posters and teams presenting their posters to the public at a student science symposium.   Over four summers, Project TRUE served 189 high school students, most of whom were from backgrounds traditionally underrepresented in the sciences. Specifically, 71% of high school students identified as female, 43% as Hispanic or Latinx, and 33% as Black or African American. Of the 60 undergraduate mentors, 88% were from backgrounds underrepresented in the sciences,  The research explored short-term outcomes immediately after the program and followed up with students multiple years after participation to understand the impacts of the experience during and after the transition from high school to college. We found that the hands-on research experiences were effective at supporting youths’ science interest, intentions to pursue STEM majors in college, and perceptions that STEM would be part of their future careers. These positive effects on science engagement continued at least two years after participation in the program and were similar for youth who entered the program very interested in science, as well as those with relatively lower pre-program science interest. This study’s focus on the transition from high school to college is a novel contribution to our understanding of STEM trajectories, indicating that authentic research experiences at the end of high school may increase retention of STEM scholars during a critical transitionary period. Previous research has recognized that high school STEM achievement is related to STEM success in college, however, there has been relatively little work to track predictors of STEM outcomes during the college transition. Longitudinal data like this is critical to understanding long-term impacts and the variety of pathways within the STEM pipeline.  In contrast to research experiences, mentoring did not show strong impacts on science interest or intentions to pursue STEM. It did, however, have strong positive relationships with youths’ sense of social connection, suggesting a more indirect influence on youths’ STEM identities and trajectories. This indirect influence may occur because mentoring helped youth establish a sense of belonging in STEM by establishing social connections with their undergraduate mentors and like-minded peers. Feelings of integration or belongingness to the community appear closely associated with the perceived benefits of programs aimed at increased retention of underrepresented youth in college and are tied to academic outcomes.       Last Modified: 07/09/2020       Submitted by: Karen Tingley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
