<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CIF: Small: Collaborative Research: Synergistic Exploitation of Network Dynamics and Knowledge Heterogeneity in Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>richard brown</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ubiquity and accelerated growth of wireless networks and services is critically dependent on the availability and efficient use of wireless spectrum. Increasing demand for spectrum is already pushing the current commercial wireless networks to their limits and accentuates the need for transformative approaches for wireless system design. In order to meet this demand, wireless networks are rapidly evolving towards a highly dense, user-deployed, heterogeneous infrastructure characterized by aggressive spectral reuse. Such evolutionary architectures can realize high data rates although they must operate in the presence of severe interference. In traditional system design, interference is viewed as a negative externality with the end goal being its suppression or mitigation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project develops new approaches for embracing interference through synergistic exploitation of feedback, network dynamics and network knowledge heterogeneity. The key angle leveraged in this work is to exploit interference as side information. The project will characterize the gain provided by feedback, and analyze the scalability and dependence of such gains on network topology. In addition, the researchers investigate the impact of dynamical variations in network topology and devise algorithms that harness such variations to enhance the overall network performance. The researchers also investigate the optimal utilization of heterogeneous channel knowledge for multi-flow multi-antenna wireless systems, by considering scenarios in which network channel knowledge exhibits variability in spatial and temporal domains and developing algorithms to exploit such variability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1422129</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sennur</FirstName>
<LastName>Ulukus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sennur Ulukus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ulukus@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014054909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000199367</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7797</Code>
<Text>Comm &amp; Information Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7935</Code>
<Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Wireless networks are rapidly evolving towards a highly dense, user-deployed, heterogeneous infrastructure characterized by aggressive spectral reuse. While such evolutionary architectures can realize high data rates, they must operate in the presence of severe interference. This project has developed new approaches that challenge the conventional wisdom of treating interference as a negative externality and instead it has revealed that interference can often be exploited leading to higher data rates and spectral efficiency. &nbsp;</p> <p>The major technical outcomes of this project are the development of novel interference management schemes that systematically exploit interference though three mechanisms, namely available feedback, network dynamics and the heterogeneity in the knowledge about wireless channel characteristics. This project developed such mechanisms for various multi-user wireless channel models, for instance, the multi-antenna broadcast channel in the presence of channel knowledge heterogeneity, interference alignment solutions for multi-antenna multiple access wiretap channels, multi-antenna interference channels, and multi-hop networks with confidentiality and secrecy constraints.</p> <p>Educational and outreach outcomes of this project include the development of a graduate-level course on network information theory at the University of Arizona, and the offering of a half-day tutorial&nbsp; on the new role of feedback for interference management in wireless networks at the 2015 IEEE ICC conference. In addition, the PIs have written a book chapter intended for general audiences to raise awareness on this topic.</p> <p>Human development and training outcomes of this project include the training of several PhD students at the University of Maryland, and at the University of Arizona (collaborative partner) on wireless communications and network information theory. The PhD students have had the opportunity to collaborate and interact with their peers and faculty at the two institutions through this project, which enhanced their learning and research experiences.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/12/2017<br>      Modified by: Sennur&nbsp;Ulukus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wireless networks are rapidly evolving towards a highly dense, user-deployed, heterogeneous infrastructure characterized by aggressive spectral reuse. While such evolutionary architectures can realize high data rates, they must operate in the presence of severe interference. This project has developed new approaches that challenge the conventional wisdom of treating interference as a negative externality and instead it has revealed that interference can often be exploited leading to higher data rates and spectral efficiency.    The major technical outcomes of this project are the development of novel interference management schemes that systematically exploit interference though three mechanisms, namely available feedback, network dynamics and the heterogeneity in the knowledge about wireless channel characteristics. This project developed such mechanisms for various multi-user wireless channel models, for instance, the multi-antenna broadcast channel in the presence of channel knowledge heterogeneity, interference alignment solutions for multi-antenna multiple access wiretap channels, multi-antenna interference channels, and multi-hop networks with confidentiality and secrecy constraints.  Educational and outreach outcomes of this project include the development of a graduate-level course on network information theory at the University of Arizona, and the offering of a half-day tutorial  on the new role of feedback for interference management in wireless networks at the 2015 IEEE ICC conference. In addition, the PIs have written a book chapter intended for general audiences to raise awareness on this topic.  Human development and training outcomes of this project include the training of several PhD students at the University of Maryland, and at the University of Arizona (collaborative partner) on wireless communications and network information theory. The PhD students have had the opportunity to collaborate and interact with their peers and faculty at the two institutions through this project, which enhanced their learning and research experiences.           Last Modified: 05/12/2017       Submitted by: Sennur Ulukus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
