<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER_IDBR: Development of a Two-Photon Circular Dichroism Spectrometer with Extreme Spectral Capabilities in the far UV (FUV-TPCD)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225010.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225010</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>During the last three decades electronic circular dichroism (ECD) spectroscopy has been the standard technique for the study of the conformational and physicochemical properties of optically active biomolecules such as proteins, nucleic acids and neurotransmitters, in solutions and at interfaces. The method presents important intrinsic limitations for the study of chiral molecules in solution and in inhomogeneous media in the far UV (FUV), a spectral region where important structural/conformational information can be obtained. In the FUV, the one-photon absorption (OPA) of standard aqueous buffer solutions and common solvents and the scattering present in inhomogeneous samples mask the ECD signal of chiral molecules, interfering with the acquisition of key information. In order to surmount the existent barriers, an analogous nonlinear approach based on two-photon absorption (TPA) has been proposed, i.e. two-photon circular dichroism (TPCD). The development of the novel TPCD spectrometer with spectral capability in the FUV (FUV-TPCD) will help expand the understanding of vital chiral biological molecules and macromolecules (amino acids, nucleotides, neurotransmitters, peptides, proteins, and nucleic acids), their interactions, dynamic changes, and mode of action in fundamental processes as never before. In addition, FUV-TPCD could assist chemist and engineers in the understanding of the properties of optically active asymmetric catalysts and novel chiral metamaterials, among others. Fulfilling the NSF mission, this project contemplates the training of graduate and undergraduate students, as well as the promotion of physical sciences to high school students and teachers in the central Florida area. This project also promotes inclusiveness through the specific involvement of members of underrepresented groups, i.e. three females and two Hispanics.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main goal of this project is to expand the spectral capability of the TPCD spectrometer down to the FUV and set the bases for the development of a fully automated, compact, and robust FUV-TPCD spectrometer that would allow to perform structural and conformational analysis of key chiral biological systems in a region of the electromagnetic spectrum inaccessible by existent ECD spectrometers. To validate the proposed instrument in the FUV, the four main aromatic amino acids (Tryptophan, Phenylalanine, Histidine and Tyrosine) will be used as model compounds. The rationale behind our primary goal is that the development and assessment of a tabletop FUV-TPCD spectrometer will set the bases for the construction of a fully automated, compact and robust spectrometer that could be commercialized and implemented in other labs, thus becoming accessible to a broad community of scientists in biology, chemistry, optics and nanosciences. Dissemination will be accomplished through facility tours offered to representatives of leader companies specialized in circular dichorism, development of new Wikibooks in FUV-TPCD, presentations at national and international meetings and through scientific publications, creating a unique instrument, open-access to potential users in central Florida through collaborations, and using the outreach program (BIOTEC) to reach the general public in central Florida.  This award is made jointly by the Instrument Development for Biological Research program (IDBR) in the Division of Biological Infrastructure (Directorate: Biology) and the Chemical Measurements and Imaging program (CMI) in the Division of Chemistry (Directorate: Math and Physical Sciences).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1422826</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Florencio</FirstName>
<LastName>Hernandez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Florencio E Hernandez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>florencio.hernandez@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078230843</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482590</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328263246</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~225010</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The activities described in this report are the result of a strong effort to push the spectral limits and extend the application of chiral spectroscopy, and advance the understanding of nonlinear optical chirality. During this period Dr. Hern&aacute;ndez looked over all the developmental aspects of the whole project. Working hand-by-hand with his graduate students he coordinated efforts to optimize and test the new setup in a spectral region never attempted before. Additionally, he worked on the educational/outreach aspects of the project to deliver a final product with a real broad impact.</p> <p>&nbsp;This last year we were able to push the experimental limits of FUV-TPCD in Tryptophan and demonstrated, for the very first time the potential application of this innovative technique to performed Nonlinear CD spectroscopy in the FUV. We also continued our initial theoretically and experimentally studies of the effect of the nature of intramolecular charge transfer onto the TPCD signal of molecules with helical chirality in a new series of molecules, and developed a novel computational approaches that allows to perform conformational studies of small molecules that can dock in specific receptor sites.</p> <p>With the IDBR support we have been able to open a new path to make important contributions to the understanding of the most fundamental mechanism of action in Alzheimer disease. Additionally, this last year the IDBR support helped us launch new investigations in a novel technique that would permit to measure, for the very first time, three-photon Circular Dichroism (3PCD). Our incursion into the field of 3PCD was originated by a recent a fruitful collaboration with theoretical groups in the Scandinavian countries.</p> <p>This NSF IDBR has served as a catapult for the development of two new STEM summer camps (BIOTEC and PhYSICOS) for low income and underrepresented groups high school students, and the continuation of OCTET. In 2017 we served almost 100 students from many different schools in the central Florida region.</p> <p>The outcomes of this initiative yielded three publications in peer-reviewed journals, three contribution to conferences, two invited talks, the training of two graduate students (One to graduation), and the interaction with a company dedicated to develop novel CD instrumentation, i.e. OLIS Inc.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Florencio&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hernandez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The activities described in this report are the result of a strong effort to push the spectral limits and extend the application of chiral spectroscopy, and advance the understanding of nonlinear optical chirality. During this period Dr. Hern&aacute;ndez looked over all the developmental aspects of the whole project. Working hand-by-hand with his graduate students he coordinated efforts to optimize and test the new setup in a spectral region never attempted before. Additionally, he worked on the educational/outreach aspects of the project to deliver a final product with a real broad impact.   This last year we were able to push the experimental limits of FUV-TPCD in Tryptophan and demonstrated, for the very first time the potential application of this innovative technique to performed Nonlinear CD spectroscopy in the FUV. We also continued our initial theoretically and experimentally studies of the effect of the nature of intramolecular charge transfer onto the TPCD signal of molecules with helical chirality in a new series of molecules, and developed a novel computational approaches that allows to perform conformational studies of small molecules that can dock in specific receptor sites.  With the IDBR support we have been able to open a new path to make important contributions to the understanding of the most fundamental mechanism of action in Alzheimer disease. Additionally, this last year the IDBR support helped us launch new investigations in a novel technique that would permit to measure, for the very first time, three-photon Circular Dichroism (3PCD). Our incursion into the field of 3PCD was originated by a recent a fruitful collaboration with theoretical groups in the Scandinavian countries.  This NSF IDBR has served as a catapult for the development of two new STEM summer camps (BIOTEC and PhYSICOS) for low income and underrepresented groups high school students, and the continuation of OCTET. In 2017 we served almost 100 students from many different schools in the central Florida region.  The outcomes of this initiative yielded three publications in peer-reviewed journals, three contribution to conferences, two invited talks, the training of two graduate students (One to graduation), and the interaction with a company dedicated to develop novel CD instrumentation, i.e. OLIS Inc.          Last Modified: 08/01/2017       Submitted by: Florencio E Hernandez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
