<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CHS: Small: Collaborative Research: Repair, Maintenance and Sustainability: Enhancing Sustainability by Strengthening the Design/Repair Nexus</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>201708.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>201708</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbainbri@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will advance core understanding of maintenance and repair practices and connect these to long-standing concerns around the design, innovation, and sustainability of new computational tools and infrastructures.  Technology maintenance and repair constitute central elements in the long-term impact and sustainability of computing tools and infrastructures.  While there is tremendous need for understanding their effects on engineering development, learning, and technological change, maintenance and repair have been systematically underrepresented in human-computer research to date.  By improving the design-repair nexus, this project seeks not only to study sustainability but also enhance it.  Pedagogically, it develops new repair-centered teaching and learning strategies for education in engineering and the social sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Deploying a mix of ethnographic, institutional, and participatory methods, the research team will explore and enhance the design-repair nexus across three crucial sites: (1) the rapidly growing amateur repair movements in North America and Europe; (2) global circulations of repair knowledge and innovation within livelihood repair communities in the global South (represented through field studies in Bangladesh and Sub-Saharan Africa); and (3) the growing sustainability or green computing programs and operations of large-scale information technology manufacturers.  This program of research and engagement will deliver both theoretical and practical benefits, and will extend the reach of computer and information science to previously neglected sites and practices key to emerging real-world computing practices and challenges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project gathers and extends a growing body of research on maintenance and repair to propose new approaches to the design, innovation and sustainability of computational artifacts and infrastructures.  The research makes three central contributions: (1) It charts novel forms of practice, value, and engagement embedded in repair, and their relationship to the better-analyzed practices of industrial engineering, hacking, and other design-centered or interventionist forms of engagement.  (2) It will offer new empirical and theoretical insight into the real-world mechanics of sustainability: the practices and institutions by which computing devices, systems and infrastructures are made sustainable in the world (or alternatively, discarded and replaced).  (3) It broadens the geographic and analytic reach of computer and information science by examining practices of repair, maintenance and sustainability in sites traditionally marginal to human-computer research that constitute the long tail of real world computing experience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1423074</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniela</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniela Rosner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dkrosner@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065434043</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981952500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~201708</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 9"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><strong>Summary</strong></p> <p>Technology maintenance and repair constitute central elements in the long-term impact and sustainability of computing tools and infrastructures. While there is tremendous need for understanding their effects on engineering development, learning, and technological change, maintenance and repair have been systematically underrepresented in CHS research to date. A mix of ethnographic, institutional, and participatory studies of repair practices promises to enhance core understanding the design/repair nexus and shed new light on emerging real-world computing practices and challenges.</p> <p>This grant supported a 5-year, interdisciplinary research program that sought to examine and strengthen the relationship between technology development and the ongoing work of maintenance and repair by which computational tools and infrastructures are sustained in the world ? a question with deep and fresh insight for long-standing CHS concerns around innovation, design, and sustainability. Deploying a mix of ethnographic, institutional, and participatory methods, this research had five primary goals:</p> <p>1. Investigate forms of practice, innovation, and learning that characterize maintenance and repair work as forms of creative human-computer interaction.</p> <p>2. Map local and global flows of information, resources, and artifacts through which repair skills and knowledge are transmitted.</p> <p>3. Enhance computational sustainability and innovation by strengthening the design- repair nexus, building better connections between amateur and livelihood repair communities and the design and manufacturing decisions of global IT firms.</p> <p>4. Develop new repair-centered pedagogies for education and industry that encourage alternative forms of learning and discovery through repair</p> <p>5. Establish programs of outreach and public engagement that draw both      scholarly and public attention to core problems of maintenance and repair      and their connections to wider values of design, innovation and      sustainability.</p> <p>Specifically, the research team supported by this grant conducted a detailed ethnographic study of IT repair practices among amateur fixer collectives across North America and Europe, and livelihood repair communities in Bangladesh and Sub-Saharan Africa, while connecting these to the design and manufacturing decisions of global IT firms. This study of maintenance and repair offered a fresh and promising approach to problems of sustainability within computing fields. Errors, omissions, and failures underlie almost everything we do. Software becomes outdated, systems fail, and appliances degrade. In response, people fix and maintain what they already have, updating software, replacing broken parts, and restoring function, often in creative and imaginative ways. These are long-standing, even ancient, cultural practices. Our fieldwork illustrated how local repair practices work as sites of innovation and learning, creative and engaged material practice, and as sources of alternative thinking around core HCI problems in sustainable computing and IT design.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong></p> <p>This project gathered and extended a growing body of research on maintenance and repair to propose new approaches to the design, innovation and sustainability of computational artifacts and infrastructures. The research made three central contributions to CHS scholarship. First, it charted novel forms of practice, value, and engagement embedded in repair, and their relationship to the better-analyzed practices of industrial engineering, hacking, and other design-centered or interventionist forms of engagement. Second, it offered new empirical and theoretical insight into the real-world mechanics of sustainability: the practices and institutions by which computing devices, systems and infrastructures are made sustainable in the world (or alternatively, discarded and replaced). Third, it broadened the geographic and analytic reach of CHS scholarship by examining practices of repair, maintenance and sustainability in sites traditionally marginal to CHS research that constitute the long tail of real world computing experience.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong></p> <p>By improving the design/repair nexus, this project sought not only to study sustainability but also enhance it. By building connections among our amateur, livelihood, and industrial partners, the research improved linkages between systems of technology design and manufacturing and downstream networks of maintenance and repair, enhancing the integration and sustainability of broader IT ecosystems. Pedagogically, it developed new repair-centered teaching and learning strategies for undergrad and graduate teaching in engineering and the social sciences. And by promoting new repair-centered approaches and values, it supported novel forms of user understanding, engagement and empowerment.</p> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Daniela&nbsp;Rosner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     Summary  Technology maintenance and repair constitute central elements in the long-term impact and sustainability of computing tools and infrastructures. While there is tremendous need for understanding their effects on engineering development, learning, and technological change, maintenance and repair have been systematically underrepresented in CHS research to date. A mix of ethnographic, institutional, and participatory studies of repair practices promises to enhance core understanding the design/repair nexus and shed new light on emerging real-world computing practices and challenges.  This grant supported a 5-year, interdisciplinary research program that sought to examine and strengthen the relationship between technology development and the ongoing work of maintenance and repair by which computational tools and infrastructures are sustained in the world ? a question with deep and fresh insight for long-standing CHS concerns around innovation, design, and sustainability. Deploying a mix of ethnographic, institutional, and participatory methods, this research had five primary goals:  1. Investigate forms of practice, innovation, and learning that characterize maintenance and repair work as forms of creative human-computer interaction.  2. Map local and global flows of information, resources, and artifacts through which repair skills and knowledge are transmitted.  3. Enhance computational sustainability and innovation by strengthening the design- repair nexus, building better connections between amateur and livelihood repair communities and the design and manufacturing decisions of global IT firms.  4. Develop new repair-centered pedagogies for education and industry that encourage alternative forms of learning and discovery through repair  5. Establish programs of outreach and public engagement that draw both      scholarly and public attention to core problems of maintenance and repair      and their connections to wider values of design, innovation and      sustainability.  Specifically, the research team supported by this grant conducted a detailed ethnographic study of IT repair practices among amateur fixer collectives across North America and Europe, and livelihood repair communities in Bangladesh and Sub-Saharan Africa, while connecting these to the design and manufacturing decisions of global IT firms. This study of maintenance and repair offered a fresh and promising approach to problems of sustainability within computing fields. Errors, omissions, and failures underlie almost everything we do. Software becomes outdated, systems fail, and appliances degrade. In response, people fix and maintain what they already have, updating software, replacing broken parts, and restoring function, often in creative and imaginative ways. These are long-standing, even ancient, cultural practices. Our fieldwork illustrated how local repair practices work as sites of innovation and learning, creative and engaged material practice, and as sources of alternative thinking around core HCI problems in sustainable computing and IT design.     Intellectual Merit:   This project gathered and extended a growing body of research on maintenance and repair to propose new approaches to the design, innovation and sustainability of computational artifacts and infrastructures. The research made three central contributions to CHS scholarship. First, it charted novel forms of practice, value, and engagement embedded in repair, and their relationship to the better-analyzed practices of industrial engineering, hacking, and other design-centered or interventionist forms of engagement. Second, it offered new empirical and theoretical insight into the real-world mechanics of sustainability: the practices and institutions by which computing devices, systems and infrastructures are made sustainable in the world (or alternatively, discarded and replaced). Third, it broadened the geographic and analytic reach of CHS scholarship by examining practices of repair, maintenance and sustainability in sites traditionally marginal to CHS research that constitute the long tail of real world computing experience.     Broader Impacts:   By improving the design/repair nexus, this project sought not only to study sustainability but also enhance it. By building connections among our amateur, livelihood, and industrial partners, the research improved linkages between systems of technology design and manufacturing and downstream networks of maintenance and repair, enhancing the integration and sustainability of broader IT ecosystems. Pedagogically, it developed new repair-centered teaching and learning strategies for undergrad and graduate teaching in engineering and the social sciences. And by promoting new repair-centered approaches and values, it supported novel forms of user understanding, engagement and empowerment.           Last Modified: 04/08/2019       Submitted by: Daniela Rosner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
