<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CNIC: US-Czech Project Development for Research on the Anatomy of Volcanic-Magmatic Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27106.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27106</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roxanne Nikolaus</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rnikolau@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927578</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award for Catalyzing New International Collaborations(CNIC) provides the PI, Michael Petronis, and two U.S. graduate students from New Mexico Highlands University with an opportunity to travel to the Czech Republic (CR) and initiate a collaboration with partners from the Czech Geological Survey and the Czech Academy of Sciences' Institute of Rock Structures and Mechanisms.  Together the U.S.-Czech team will examine the growth of ancient volcanoes in the Jièín Volcanic Field, CR, and compare those volcanoes to ones in northern New Mexico.  Their goal is to derive new paradigms for understanding the development of small volcanoes, known as cinder cones, which are the most common terrestrial volcanic feature on Earth.  Through laboratory studies and field research at two or more Czech volcanic sites, the US-Czech team intends to test common models of small volcano construction that treat the magma feeder system as a simple dike or pipe-like conduit that transports magma vertically from a reservoir to the eruptive vent.  Their alternative hypothesis maintains that feeder geometries beneath these apparently simple exteriors are considerably more complex.  This catalytic effort is expected to establish essential ground work for follow-on cooperative research and applications to NSF-Tectonics and NSF-Petrology and Geochemistry programs with the parallel goal of involving under-represented U.S. students in futue field and laboraroty aspects of such projects, thereby contributing to the next generation of geoscientists, with early career international research experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, new preliminary data should assist with defining the evolution of the anticipated, more complex magma feeder system, specifically, one that involves multiple, time-transgressive injections beneath the cone with magma transported vertically upward and downward and laterally toward and away from the central vent conduit. The team hypothesizes that magma supply rate (e.g., pulsed versus continuous), magma pressure as well as magma composition, influence the subvolcanic construction geometries and edifice deformation.  Their field methods will include primary field observations of eruption products, deposit characteristics, and structural measurements, as well as sample collection. Laboratory methods are to include thin section petrology, paleomagnetic, anisotropy of magnetic susceptibility analysis, and geophysical surveys to map the subsurface structure. The new data obtained during these activities in partnership with Czech colleagues will enable preliminary assessments of magmatic flow patterns, sub-volcanic deformation (microstructures and paleomagnetism), and the subsurface structure of the volcanoes (geophysics).  If the Czech Republic volcanoes yield results and data similar to that from sites previously studied by the PI, then the U.S.-Czech team maintains that this pattern of magma flow beneath small volcanoes may be established as a new norm, potentially transforming our fundamental  understanding of the most abundant volcanic construct on Earth.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1423396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Lindline</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Lindline</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lindlinej@nmhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5054262046</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000206425</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Petronis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael S Petronis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mspetro@nmhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5054543513</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Mexico Highlands University</Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<ZipCode>877019000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5054543571</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P. O. Box 9000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047134101</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW MEXICO HIGHLANDS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>047134101</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Mexico Highlands University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>877019000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5930</Code>
<Text>U.S.-CZECHOSLOVAKIA PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~27106</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Broader Impact </strong></p> <p>Broader Impact&nbsp;The PI and two New Mexico Highlands University (NMHU) students (one graduate and one undergraduate) conducted six weeks of field work in the Czech Republic and Poland from late April till mid June 2016. The NMHU graduate student (Ms. Sarah Shields), whose master&rsquo;s thesis focuses on the emplacement of diatremes in the Czech Republic, is 50% Hispanic, 10% Native American, and female. She spent a semester abroad in the spring 2016 in Blas&eacute;-Pascal University, France and conduct field work with the other students from NMHU in the Czech Republic and Poland in April 2016. Ms. Shields completed her Master's Degree with honors in the spring 2017. She is starting a PhD program in the fall 2017 at the University of Wisconsin &ndash; Madison conducting research on pluton emplacement in northwester Nevada; her advisor is Basil Tikoff. The undergraduate student (Mr. Jeff Falance) is 100% Hispanic and graduated in the fall 2016. &nbsp;He is now currently employed by the State of New Mexico Environment Department. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />During our 2016 field campaign, we collected over 200 paleomagnetic sampling sites at three monogenic volcanic systems (Z&aacute;kupy and Tlustec (CZ); Targowica (PL)), conducted high resolution ground magnetic surveys at these field sites, mapped the intrusive and extrusive faceis, collected samples for geochemistry, and networked with scientists from the Czech Geological Survey, the Czech Academy of Sciences, University of Wroclaw, Poland, and Charles University Prague. &nbsp;In addition, we conducted two weeks of field work in Poland at the Targowica Quarry. The Targowica project serves as Mr. Ejaz Kerim graduate thesis project. &nbsp;Mr. Kerim is an international student from Pakistan. The project goals are to conduct research on the growth of volcanoes "from the roots to the roof of the volcanic system". This research is a collaborative endeavor between NMHU Geology, Czech Geological Survey, Czech Academy of Sciences, Charles University in Prague, University of Wroclaw, Poland, and Universit&eacute; Blaise Pascal, France. This research builds on previously funded research awarded to Petronis and Lindline by the National Science Foundation and National Geographic Society to investigate the growth of volcanoes in New Mexico, Czech Republic, Poland, and France. We are pleased to report that the "seed funding" provided by the National Science Foundation has allowed us to secure additional funding: "NSF 12-551 - International Research Experiences for Students (IRES): From the Roots to the Roof - the Anatomy of the Volcanic-Magmatic-Plutonic System". This $249,122 award will allow us to bring 15 undergraduate and graduate students (5 per year) to the Czech Republic, Germany, and Poland over the next three years to conduct research projects at the host institutions. &nbsp;These international opportunities further advance a long history of research activities that the Geology faculty have secured for our NMHU Geology students building their global competency and preparing our students to compete in the local, national, and international job market. Over the life of this award since 2014, we have provided international research experience for six students.&nbsp;<br /><br />Intellectual Merit</p> <p>Common models of small volcano construction envision the magma feeder system as a simple dike or pipe-like conduit which transports magma vertically from a reservoir to the eruptive vent. Our preliminary data indicate that feeder geometries beneath these apparently simple exteriors are considerably more complex. Specifically, the evolution of the magma feeder system involves multiple, time-transgressive injections beneath the cone with magma transported vertically upward and downward and laterally toward and away from the central vent conduit. We argue that magma supply rate (e.g., pulsed versus continuous), magma pressure, as well as magma composition influence the subvolcanic construction geometries and edifice deformation. &nbsp;Over the life of the award, our students and the PIs have published twelve conference abstracts at national and international venues and have published two peer-reviewed manuscripts and have four additional manuscripts currently in review or in preparation.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petronis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494521647288_cl-lipa-vulkanologove_denik-630--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494521647288_cl-lipa-vulkanologove_denik-630--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The Team"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494521647288_cl-lipa-vulkanologove_denik-630--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The Team"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2016 Field Team: Volcanologists ( left) Benjamin van Wyk de Vries, Jeffrey Falance(NMHU undergraduate), Michael P. Petronis (PI), Sarah Shields ((NMHU graduate), Vladislav Rapprich, and Jennifer Lindline (co-PI). The Zákupy Diatreme is visible to the left of the Proton Magnetometer (green sensor)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Denik 630 News</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petronis</div> <div class="imageTitle">The Team</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1423396/1423396_10331754_1459374822391_sarah_zak--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1423396/1423396_10331754_1459374822391_sarah_zak--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Zakupy, Czech Republic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1423396/1423396_10331754_1459374822391_sarah_zak--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Zakupy, Czech Republic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ms. Sarah Shields, NMHU graduate student, orienting paleomagnetic samples at the Zakupy diatreme, Czech Republic in 2015. This study site is part of her master's degree understanding the growth of monogenetic volcanoes in rift systems.</div> <div class="imageCredit">none</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petronis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Zakupy, Czech Republic</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494526532179_Targowica_Quarry--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494526532179_Targowica_Quarry--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Targowica"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494526532179_Targowica_Quarry--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Targowica"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Targowica Quarry, Poland</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.Petronis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petronis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Targowica</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494526608389_Tlustec--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494526608389_Tlustec--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tlustec"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1423396/1423396_10331754_1494526608389_Tlustec--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tlustec"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tlustec Quarry, Czech Republic</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.Petronis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petronis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tlustec</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Broader Impact   Broader Impact The PI and two New Mexico Highlands University (NMHU) students (one graduate and one undergraduate) conducted six weeks of field work in the Czech Republic and Poland from late April till mid June 2016. The NMHU graduate student (Ms. Sarah Shields), whose master?s thesis focuses on the emplacement of diatremes in the Czech Republic, is 50% Hispanic, 10% Native American, and female. She spent a semester abroad in the spring 2016 in Blas&eacute;-Pascal University, France and conduct field work with the other students from NMHU in the Czech Republic and Poland in April 2016. Ms. Shields completed her Master's Degree with honors in the spring 2017. She is starting a PhD program in the fall 2017 at the University of Wisconsin &ndash; Madison conducting research on pluton emplacement in northwester Nevada; her advisor is Basil Tikoff. The undergraduate student (Mr. Jeff Falance) is 100% Hispanic and graduated in the fall 2016.  He is now currently employed by the State of New Mexico Environment Department.     During our 2016 field campaign, we collected over 200 paleomagnetic sampling sites at three monogenic volcanic systems (Z&aacute;kupy and Tlustec (CZ); Targowica (PL)), conducted high resolution ground magnetic surveys at these field sites, mapped the intrusive and extrusive faceis, collected samples for geochemistry, and networked with scientists from the Czech Geological Survey, the Czech Academy of Sciences, University of Wroclaw, Poland, and Charles University Prague.  In addition, we conducted two weeks of field work in Poland at the Targowica Quarry. The Targowica project serves as Mr. Ejaz Kerim graduate thesis project.  Mr. Kerim is an international student from Pakistan. The project goals are to conduct research on the growth of volcanoes "from the roots to the roof of the volcanic system". This research is a collaborative endeavor between NMHU Geology, Czech Geological Survey, Czech Academy of Sciences, Charles University in Prague, University of Wroclaw, Poland, and Universit&eacute; Blaise Pascal, France. This research builds on previously funded research awarded to Petronis and Lindline by the National Science Foundation and National Geographic Society to investigate the growth of volcanoes in New Mexico, Czech Republic, Poland, and France. We are pleased to report that the "seed funding" provided by the National Science Foundation has allowed us to secure additional funding: "NSF 12-551 - International Research Experiences for Students (IRES): From the Roots to the Roof - the Anatomy of the Volcanic-Magmatic-Plutonic System". This $249,122 award will allow us to bring 15 undergraduate and graduate students (5 per year) to the Czech Republic, Germany, and Poland over the next three years to conduct research projects at the host institutions.  These international opportunities further advance a long history of research activities that the Geology faculty have secured for our NMHU Geology students building their global competency and preparing our students to compete in the local, national, and international job market. Over the life of this award since 2014, we have provided international research experience for six students.   Intellectual Merit  Common models of small volcano construction envision the magma feeder system as a simple dike or pipe-like conduit which transports magma vertically from a reservoir to the eruptive vent. Our preliminary data indicate that feeder geometries beneath these apparently simple exteriors are considerably more complex. Specifically, the evolution of the magma feeder system involves multiple, time-transgressive injections beneath the cone with magma transported vertically upward and downward and laterally toward and away from the central vent conduit. We argue that magma supply rate (e.g., pulsed versus continuous), magma pressure, as well as magma composition influence the subvolcanic construction geometries and edifice deformation.  Over the life of the award, our students and the PIs have published twelve conference abstracts at national and international venues and have published two peer-reviewed manuscripts and have four additional manuscripts currently in review or in preparation.           Last Modified: 05/11/2017       Submitted by: Michael S Petronis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
