<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Small: An Integrated Approach to Characterizing Conformational Changes of Large Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>458128</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the major hurdles in the understanding of physiological processes and the design of new pharmaceutical drugs has been the understanding of the three-dimensional structure and flexibility of molecules, which hold key insight into their function and interactions. In many biological pathways conformational flexibility is known to play an essential role in driving functional mechanisms and has been the topic of both computational and experimental investigations. Modern experimental methods such as Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange coupled with Mass Spectroscopy (HDX-MS) can probe the flexibility of large proteins, but the findings are mapped on the available (static) crystal structures, thereby losing a considerable part of the dynamic information. This proposal will investigate the extent to which computational methods can help discover and visualize conformational changes of large proteins that are in agreement with experiment. Because of the specific proteins selected for study in the context of this proposal, the proposed work has a great societal impact: it helps advance the understanding of processes that are involved in a variety of immune, inflammatory, neurodegenerative, ischemic, and age-related diseases. This proposal will train undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral students at Rice and the University of Pennsylvania on interdisciplinary topics. It will also provide training opportunities to women students. All work will be disseminated not only through technical presentations at national meetings, publications in peer reviewed journals and book chapters, but also through visits and talks with researchers in academia and the biotechnology industry, as well as with open source development and distribution of the algorithms developed for widespread use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A central part of this proposal concerns the development of a computational framework that samples the conformational space of proteins. It relies on a new representation of the degrees of freedom of proteins and protein complexes and on the definition of sampling primitives at various resolutions. The framework draws from geometry-inspired sampling techniques that efficiently explore large search spaces while keeping track of the extent that the search space is covered. In parallel, HDX-MS experiments will be carried out and used as probes for conformational variability. The experimental results will be correlated with the results of the computational framework to select the conformations that most closely match experiments. A distinguishing feature of this work is the connection with experiment and the ways in which each can feed the other. This proposal lies at the intersection of algorithms, computational geometry, dimensionality reduction, data mining, and visualization methods and connects with modern experimental methods which are actively under development and hold great promise for the understanding of protein structure and function.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1423304</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lydia</FirstName>
<LastName>Kavraki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lydia Kavraki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kavraki@cs.rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133484834</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 Main St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8750</Code>
<Text>Bio &amp; Comp Shared Princ (BCSP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~8128</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the major hurdles in the understanding of physiological processes and the design of new drugs has been the understanding of the three-dimensional structure and flexibility of molecules which hold key insight into their function and interactions. Detailed structural information can be obtained via X-ray crystallography, while indirect evidence of flexibility can be obtained with other experimental methods such as Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange Mass Spectroscopy (HDX-MS). Often X-ray and HDX-MS data correspond to different states of a protein, though, which makes it difficult to interpret the HDX-MS data. We have developed a computational method that, starting from a crystal structure, computes a structure whose modeled HDX-MS data best matches given experimental HDX-MS data. The method has been evaluated on a number of well-studied proteins. We have shown that the modeled HDX-MS data from a crystal structure is a poor fit to experimental HDX-MS data. Interestingly, modeled HDX-MS data computed for an ensemble of structures selected from extended Molecular Dynamics simulations also fit the experimental HDX-MS data poorly. In contrast, our rapid conformational sampling framework provides a significantly better fit from just a single structure. We have shown that HDX-MS data is sensitive to small structural changes. Our computational method can identify a structure similar to the crystal structure in cases where the HDX-MS data is known to correspond to the same state, yet provide a significantly improved fit to the HDX-MS data. In one case where experimental HDX-MS is hypothesized to correspond to an intermediate state that is significantly different from the crystal structure, our method predicted a novel intermediate structure, which may lead to new structural insights. Within the context of this grant we have also further developed the experimental techniques for obtaining HDX-MS data and used this to gain new insights into proteins involved in the human immune system. We have published extensively our findings and we have trained undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral students at Rice and the University of Pennsylvania on interdisciplinary topics creating a coherent team of researchers who will tackle important problems in a variety of fields including drug design. Two students completed their M.S. thesis on topics related to this award and one of them is continuing on with Ph.D. work. This award trained two female researchers: one at the graduate and one at the postgraduate level. <br /><br />The development of new medicines is a difficult and expensive process. Our work has the potential to accelerate the design stage of the process by providing computational tools that in coordination with experiments reveal the protein epitopes that can be targeted by drugs. As proteins are dynamic structures these epitopes could be hidden in crystallographic studies but revealed by our work as the protein changes shape. More broadly, our work will help provide a more detailed picture of protein-ligand interactions which is paramount for the design of effective medicinal drugs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2017<br>      Modified by: Lydia&nbsp;Kavraki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the major hurdles in the understanding of physiological processes and the design of new drugs has been the understanding of the three-dimensional structure and flexibility of molecules which hold key insight into their function and interactions. Detailed structural information can be obtained via X-ray crystallography, while indirect evidence of flexibility can be obtained with other experimental methods such as Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange Mass Spectroscopy (HDX-MS). Often X-ray and HDX-MS data correspond to different states of a protein, though, which makes it difficult to interpret the HDX-MS data. We have developed a computational method that, starting from a crystal structure, computes a structure whose modeled HDX-MS data best matches given experimental HDX-MS data. The method has been evaluated on a number of well-studied proteins. We have shown that the modeled HDX-MS data from a crystal structure is a poor fit to experimental HDX-MS data. Interestingly, modeled HDX-MS data computed for an ensemble of structures selected from extended Molecular Dynamics simulations also fit the experimental HDX-MS data poorly. In contrast, our rapid conformational sampling framework provides a significantly better fit from just a single structure. We have shown that HDX-MS data is sensitive to small structural changes. Our computational method can identify a structure similar to the crystal structure in cases where the HDX-MS data is known to correspond to the same state, yet provide a significantly improved fit to the HDX-MS data. In one case where experimental HDX-MS is hypothesized to correspond to an intermediate state that is significantly different from the crystal structure, our method predicted a novel intermediate structure, which may lead to new structural insights. Within the context of this grant we have also further developed the experimental techniques for obtaining HDX-MS data and used this to gain new insights into proteins involved in the human immune system. We have published extensively our findings and we have trained undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral students at Rice and the University of Pennsylvania on interdisciplinary topics creating a coherent team of researchers who will tackle important problems in a variety of fields including drug design. Two students completed their M.S. thesis on topics related to this award and one of them is continuing on with Ph.D. work. This award trained two female researchers: one at the graduate and one at the postgraduate level.   The development of new medicines is a difficult and expensive process. Our work has the potential to accelerate the design stage of the process by providing computational tools that in coordination with experiments reveal the protein epitopes that can be targeted by drugs. As proteins are dynamic structures these epitopes could be hidden in crystallographic studies but revealed by our work as the protein changes shape. More broadly, our work will help provide a more detailed picture of protein-ligand interactions which is paramount for the design of effective medicinal drugs.       Last Modified: 07/12/2017       Submitted by: Lydia Kavraki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
