<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Institution, Development, and Democracy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98529.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98529</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is generally presumed that when rulers are constrained by law, when they are accountable to broad electorates, when personal security and property rights are assured, adn when capable bureaucracies are responsive to elected officials, good things will follow.  But how do we know this is true?  And how might we know which sorts of favorable outcomes of these institutional features is likely to foster?  Work on these topics has been constrained by the absence of fine-grained measure of democracy and governance.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the problem by enlisting a new database, Varieties of Democracy (V-Dem), that measures various aspects of democarcy and governance-including electoral contestation, rule of law, civil liberty, inclusion, decentralization, and legislative primacy-at a highly disaggregated level for all sizable countries in the world from 1900 to 2012.  With this immense database at its disposal, the researchers will test the relationship between these institutions and outcomes such as economic growth, infrastructure, health, and education over the past century.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The benefits of the project include enhancing current understandings of the impact of political institutions on development outcomes.  This should benefit governments, international organizations, and NGOs that aim to promote economic and social development around the world by providing guidance about the kinds of institutional interventions that tend to work, backfire, or have no effect.  Also, the data will be provided to development agencies, policy-makers, and scholars.  All the data will be freely available in a variety of interactive infterfaces on the project web site (v-dem.net). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a BIG DATA project.  However, unlike many big data projects, it is guided by theory.  It will use innovative Bayesian techniques as well as case studies to help examine the causal mechanisms that are behind the relationships that are found by the analysis.  Where appropriate other techniques will be used to examine the panel data such as Granger causalit, etc.  This project will then allow for the testing of a number of current theories in political science about the interaction between institutions, democracy and development.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1423944</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Pemstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Pemstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.pemstein@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7012318045</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662541</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1735 Research Park Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>803882299</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>803882299</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Dakota State University Fargo]]></Name>
<CityName>Fargo</CityName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Dept 2315 - PO Box 6050]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>Political Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~98529</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This portion of the collaborative award produced and evaluated methods for analyzing cross-national expert surveys of complex political phenomena. This work develops best practices for modeling expert disagreement, anchoring cross-national information to a consistent scale, and producing estimates of uncertainty in expert-generated measures of political institutions. It also develops tools and procedures for measure validation and uses experimental methods to examine questions of coder bias and to compare the quality of data produced by expert and crowd-sourced respondents. This work forms the basis of numerous research papers and two book manuscripts. The research also contributed substantially to the production of the Varieties of Democracy (V-Dem) Dataset, which won the American Political Science Association's Lijphart/Przeworski/Verba Dataset Award in 2016. These data, in turn, inform a large body of substantive research. This investigator, in particular, produced substantive papers examining the relationship between democracy promotion and electoral quality, and between clientelism and censorship.</p> <p>This work produced substantial broader impacts. The V-Dem data already feature in more than one hundred research papers, and the methods and best practices that the PI developed while supported by this award have broad applications across the social sciences. Policymakers also value the data and substantive research that this work helped to produce. Agencies including International IDEA, the Mo Ibrahim Foundation, Transparency International, and the World Bank have produced reports and datasets that rely heavily on V-Dem data and related research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Pemstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This portion of the collaborative award produced and evaluated methods for analyzing cross-national expert surveys of complex political phenomena. This work develops best practices for modeling expert disagreement, anchoring cross-national information to a consistent scale, and producing estimates of uncertainty in expert-generated measures of political institutions. It also develops tools and procedures for measure validation and uses experimental methods to examine questions of coder bias and to compare the quality of data produced by expert and crowd-sourced respondents. This work forms the basis of numerous research papers and two book manuscripts. The research also contributed substantially to the production of the Varieties of Democracy (V-Dem) Dataset, which won the American Political Science Association's Lijphart/Przeworski/Verba Dataset Award in 2016. These data, in turn, inform a large body of substantive research. This investigator, in particular, produced substantive papers examining the relationship between democracy promotion and electoral quality, and between clientelism and censorship.  This work produced substantial broader impacts. The V-Dem data already feature in more than one hundred research papers, and the methods and best practices that the PI developed while supported by this award have broad applications across the social sciences. Policymakers also value the data and substantive research that this work helped to produce. Agencies including International IDEA, the Mo Ibrahim Foundation, Transparency International, and the World Bank have produced reports and datasets that rely heavily on V-Dem data and related research.          Last Modified: 12/04/2017       Submitted by: Daniel Pemstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
