<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Health Lifestyles and the Reproduction of Inequality</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>172652.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184649</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Toby Parcel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Health is playing an increasing role in our understandings of social inequality. Researchers and policy makers recognize that health behaviors are often resistant to change. Seeking to understand this problem, some have begun focusing on health lifestyles. These are defined as groups of interrelated health behaviors, rooted in social identities related to understandings of health, responsibility, and risk, that are shaped by knowledge and resources and that have important consequences for health and other life outcomes. This lifestyle approach acknowledges that health behaviors do not happen in a vacuum; rather, they co-occur in sets and influence one another. These sets of health behaviors arise from deeply rooted identities that, if they do not themselves change, can undermine efforts to alter behaviors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research focuses on three major unanswered questions: (1) What received health lifestyles do children get from their parents? (2) How do those received health lifestyles evolve into achieved health lifestyles across early life? (3) What are the implications of young people's health lifestyles for their development and health? Combining qualitative and quantitative methods, this project bridges different "faces" of sociological social psychology in considering both behaviors and identities and the social norms, structures, and interactions that shape them. The project draws from and contributes to several areas of sociological theory besides health lifestyles: the intergenerational reproduction of inequalities, identity development in children and youth, the reciprocal process of socialization, cultural health capital, and the life course theoretical perspective. Quantitative analyses use three longitudinal surveys that cover different phases of the early life course: the Early Childhood Longitudinal Study's Birth and Kindergarten Cohorts, and the Add Health survey. The project also collects original qualitative data observing family interactions and interviewing parents, with supplemental parent focus groups and school personnel interviews. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to scholarly, academic, and public dissemination of findings, this research has the potential to benefit society. Understanding prevalent patterns of health behaviors and associated identity development among children and youth is important for ultimately improving their development, health, and well-being. Understanding their health lifestyles may help reduce inequalities in their life outcomes. Student training and learning is an integral part of the project, with research assistants heavily involved in data collection, analysis, and dissemination of findings. The project will be integrated into the principal investigator's undergraduate and graduate teaching, and findings will be presented in a graduate student workshop.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1423524</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Mollborn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefanie F Mollborn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mollborn@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037353796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000571611</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 479]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~172652</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~11997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Unhealthy behaviors are a major problem for well-being, health, and economic productivity in U.S. society. Yet people&rsquo;s health behaviors are often resistant to change. The idea of &ldquo;health lifestyles&rdquo; is promising for better understanding and improving individual health behaviors. A person&rsquo;s health lifestyle is their set of health behaviors that arises from group identities. For example, a high school athlete may engage in a wide variety of behaviors&mdash;not just exercise, but also diet, substance use patterns, and media consumption&mdash;that stem from their identity as a team member. While well theorized for adults, the health lifestyle concept has neither been adequately tested empirically nor applied to children and youth. Because many lifelong health behaviors are established early, it is important to understand how they arise, change with age, and are shaped by social contexts. To our knowledge, we were the first researchers to develop theory on children&rsquo;s health lifestyles or analyze them empirically.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project investigated how parents, children, communities, peers, and schools shape young people&rsquo;s health lifestyles, in many cases perpetuating social inequalities across generations. Existing data sources do not encompass both behaviors and identities, so we took a multimethod approach. We analyzed three nationally representative longitudinal surveys covering birth through age 32 to examine prevalent health lifestyles (measured by behaviors) in the U.S. population. To investigate how social identities, interactions, and norms shape health lifestyles, we collected new qualitative data from two middle-class communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>What are the characteristics of health lifestyles in early and middle childhood, adolescence, and young adulthood? We found that a person&rsquo;s health lifestyle behaviors are rarely all beneficial or all detrimental for health. Health lifestyles change substantially as strict parental control over infants&rsquo; health behaviors subsides and as other goals, such as social popularity or academic achievement, compete with health. As new, risky health behaviors (such as substance use and risky sex) become available in adolescence, predominant health lifestyles change. Young adults age out of many risky health behaviors at different times.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>How do families and other social contexts shape health lifestyles? In childhood, health lifestyles are influenced by sociodemographic background, family resources, parents&rsquo; health behaviors, and parenting practices. Early health lifestyles in turn predict the same children&rsquo;s later health lifestyles. High school students&rsquo; health lifestyles influence which friends they choose, and in some social settings friends subsequently shape teens&rsquo; health lifestyles. Social class advantage protects children from many risky behaviors, but this is not necessarily true at college age.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>How are health lifestyles associated with individual outcomes? We analyzed academic achievement, socioemotional behavior, physical and mental health, and socioeconomic outcomes. Throughout early life, health lifestyles independently predict people&rsquo;s outcomes after controlling for many other influences. When multiple time points are analyzed, a person&rsquo;s health lifestyle at each time point often independently predicts longer-term outcomes, justifying a longitudinal investigation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>How do behaviors and identities&mdash;shaped by social interactions, structures, and norms&mdash;form health lifestyles? We found that community-level identities, norms, and understandings of health and childhood are important. They vary across communities, even within a small geographical area. Children&rsquo;s health lifestyles are just one aspect of broader &ldquo;childhood lifestyles.&rdquo; Ideas about parenting, childhood, and future success tend to be at least as important for children&rsquo;s health lifestyles as ideas about health. Inculcating specific health behaviors in children not only shapes their health, but also instills class advantage, as health has become an increasingly fundamental aspect of cultural capital.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Research was conducted collaboratively with one professor, four Ph.D. student assistants, and four undergraduate assistants. The students (most coming from underrepresented groups in science) received training and mentoring that otherwise would not have been available. Several of the student team members will pursue careers as professors or in public health and medicine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Embedding health behaviors in a broader lifestyle leads to distinct policy implications. Specific health behaviors do not occur in a vacuum. Narrow policies intended to fix a particular health behavior, such as diet, are likely to miss interrelated behaviors that should be addressed together to improve development and health. These behaviors may have different implications for health, well-being, and economic productivity depending on the lifestyle in which they are embedded. For example, young people&rsquo;s heavy drinking is sometimes embedded in an otherwise healthy lifestyle that is not linked to many problematic outcomes. For others, heavy drinking is embedded in frequent use of many substances, leading to higher risk. Our analysis may help policymakers identify key ages for interventions. For example, we found that preschool health lifestyles strongly shape development at school start, more so than infant or toddler health lifestyles. Since children&rsquo;s development and health at school start are particularly important for later life, interventions to change health lifestyles around age 4 seem particularly promising.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Stefanie&nbsp;F&nbsp;Mollborn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Unhealthy behaviors are a major problem for well-being, health, and economic productivity in U.S. society. Yet people?s health behaviors are often resistant to change. The idea of "health lifestyles" is promising for better understanding and improving individual health behaviors. A person?s health lifestyle is their set of health behaviors that arises from group identities. For example, a high school athlete may engage in a wide variety of behaviors&mdash;not just exercise, but also diet, substance use patterns, and media consumption&mdash;that stem from their identity as a team member. While well theorized for adults, the health lifestyle concept has neither been adequately tested empirically nor applied to children and youth. Because many lifelong health behaviors are established early, it is important to understand how they arise, change with age, and are shaped by social contexts. To our knowledge, we were the first researchers to develop theory on children?s health lifestyles or analyze them empirically.     This project investigated how parents, children, communities, peers, and schools shape young people?s health lifestyles, in many cases perpetuating social inequalities across generations. Existing data sources do not encompass both behaviors and identities, so we took a multimethod approach. We analyzed three nationally representative longitudinal surveys covering birth through age 32 to examine prevalent health lifestyles (measured by behaviors) in the U.S. population. To investigate how social identities, interactions, and norms shape health lifestyles, we collected new qualitative data from two middle-class communities.     What are the characteristics of health lifestyles in early and middle childhood, adolescence, and young adulthood? We found that a person?s health lifestyle behaviors are rarely all beneficial or all detrimental for health. Health lifestyles change substantially as strict parental control over infants? health behaviors subsides and as other goals, such as social popularity or academic achievement, compete with health. As new, risky health behaviors (such as substance use and risky sex) become available in adolescence, predominant health lifestyles change. Young adults age out of many risky health behaviors at different times.     How do families and other social contexts shape health lifestyles? In childhood, health lifestyles are influenced by sociodemographic background, family resources, parents? health behaviors, and parenting practices. Early health lifestyles in turn predict the same children?s later health lifestyles. High school students? health lifestyles influence which friends they choose, and in some social settings friends subsequently shape teens? health lifestyles. Social class advantage protects children from many risky behaviors, but this is not necessarily true at college age.     How are health lifestyles associated with individual outcomes? We analyzed academic achievement, socioemotional behavior, physical and mental health, and socioeconomic outcomes. Throughout early life, health lifestyles independently predict people?s outcomes after controlling for many other influences. When multiple time points are analyzed, a person?s health lifestyle at each time point often independently predicts longer-term outcomes, justifying a longitudinal investigation.     How do behaviors and identities&mdash;shaped by social interactions, structures, and norms&mdash;form health lifestyles? We found that community-level identities, norms, and understandings of health and childhood are important. They vary across communities, even within a small geographical area. Children?s health lifestyles are just one aspect of broader "childhood lifestyles." Ideas about parenting, childhood, and future success tend to be at least as important for children?s health lifestyles as ideas about health. Inculcating specific health behaviors in children not only shapes their health, but also instills class advantage, as health has become an increasingly fundamental aspect of cultural capital.     Research was conducted collaboratively with one professor, four Ph.D. student assistants, and four undergraduate assistants. The students (most coming from underrepresented groups in science) received training and mentoring that otherwise would not have been available. Several of the student team members will pursue careers as professors or in public health and medicine.     Embedding health behaviors in a broader lifestyle leads to distinct policy implications. Specific health behaviors do not occur in a vacuum. Narrow policies intended to fix a particular health behavior, such as diet, are likely to miss interrelated behaviors that should be addressed together to improve development and health. These behaviors may have different implications for health, well-being, and economic productivity depending on the lifestyle in which they are embedded. For example, young people?s heavy drinking is sometimes embedded in an otherwise healthy lifestyle that is not linked to many problematic outcomes. For others, heavy drinking is embedded in frequent use of many substances, leading to higher risk. Our analysis may help policymakers identify key ages for interventions. For example, we found that preschool health lifestyles strongly shape development at school start, more so than infant or toddler health lifestyles. Since children?s development and health at school start are particularly important for later life, interventions to change health lifestyles around age 4 seem particularly promising.       Last Modified: 11/29/2017       Submitted by: Stefanie F Mollborn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
