<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Signals of Relative Sea Level perturbations: Defining the divide between signal shredding versus preservation in the stratigraphic record.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>166516.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>166516</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlawrenc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The tug of relative sea level change influences the evolution of coastal environments, including land growth or loss and changing river patterns in deltaic settings. Relative sea-level change also influences the architecture of sediments that form continental margin stratigraphy.  These sedimentary deposits frequently contain energy and water reserves and can serve as hosts for carbon capture and storage. Improved methods are needed for interpreting and predicting stratigraphic patterns in order to (i) manage these resources and (ii) invert the stratigraphic record for paleo-climatic records, which could inform predictions of future Earth system response to climate change. Recent theoretical work suggests that internally generated processes in sediment transport systems have the capacity to destroy, or "shred", external environmental signals prior to locking them into the stratigraphic record. Through a combination of experiments and analysis of field data, the team will determine the necessary rates and magnitudes of relative sea level cycles for them to be recorded in stratigraphy. This work will advance the ability to recover meaningful data about past climate change from coastal stratigraphic datasets and generate predictive models for coastal response to climate change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent theoretical work suggests that autogenic processes in sediment transport systems have the capacity to shred signals of environmental and tectonic perturbations prior to transfer to the stratigraphic record. Many argue that changes in Relative Sea Level (RSL) represent the most important boundary condition affecting continental margin transport systems. However, we still lack quantitative theory to explain the necessary properties of RSL cycles in order to store them in stratigraphy, thus limiting the usefulness of stratigraphy for defining paleo-environments.  Results from previous experiments suggest that RSL cycles with amplitudes less than one channel depth, and of periodicities less than the amount of time necessary to deposit one channel depth of stratigraphy over a delta-top, are susceptible to signal shredding. The team will test this hypothesis using existing data sets and new laboratory experiments. Quantitative theory and predictions produced from this work will be benchmarked against stratigraphy from the Late Miocene to Quaternary stratigraphy of the Mississippi Delta.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1424312</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Straub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Straub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmstraub@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5048623273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701185665</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6823 St. Charles Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~166516</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Reconstructing the history of Earth prior to the age of scientific instrumentation relies heavily on interpretations of layers of sedimentary rocks, collectively called the stratigraphic record. The composition, architecture, chemistry, and fossils contained in these rocks provide signals of past climate, tectonics, and biology on Earth. However, the storage of these environmental signals in stratigraphy is not straightforward. Environmental signals can be transformed by sediment transport through channels and the landscapes that surround them. This transformation continues as sediment is deposited and strata are formed. In some cases transformation of signals severely hampers paleo-environmental reconstruction.</p> <p>Focusing on sea level, sedimentary deposits preserve the most complete record of changing sea level over the greatest fraction of Earth&rsquo;s history. However, deciphering this record is difficult due to the intermingling of random processes, such as rapid changes in river course, with signals of changing sea level and climate. Using laboratory and numerical experiments, analysis of strata imaged with reflection seismic data, and theory we define the attributes that changes in sea level must have in order to be preserved in the largest deposits on Earth, deltas. This theory can also be expanded to describe thresholds for changes in sediment flux, associated with changes in climate at river sources, which determine if stratigraphic signals are stored. Combined, our reported observations aid our interpretation of deltaic response to past climate change, thus enhancing our ability to predict their response to on-going climate change.</p> <p>Work conducted during this project supported educational activities of undergraduate and graduate students (Masters and PhD) and supported activities to bring underrepresented minority students into Tulane&rsquo;s sediment dynamics laboratory to observe experiments on the processes that construct the landscape they live on in New Orleans and to support science fair projects conducted in Tulane&rsquo;s Sediment Dynamics and Stratigraphy Laboratory. All results associated with the project, including primary data have been archived on the SEAD environmental data repository.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Kyle&nbsp;Straub</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Reconstructing the history of Earth prior to the age of scientific instrumentation relies heavily on interpretations of layers of sedimentary rocks, collectively called the stratigraphic record. The composition, architecture, chemistry, and fossils contained in these rocks provide signals of past climate, tectonics, and biology on Earth. However, the storage of these environmental signals in stratigraphy is not straightforward. Environmental signals can be transformed by sediment transport through channels and the landscapes that surround them. This transformation continues as sediment is deposited and strata are formed. In some cases transformation of signals severely hampers paleo-environmental reconstruction.  Focusing on sea level, sedimentary deposits preserve the most complete record of changing sea level over the greatest fraction of Earth’s history. However, deciphering this record is difficult due to the intermingling of random processes, such as rapid changes in river course, with signals of changing sea level and climate. Using laboratory and numerical experiments, analysis of strata imaged with reflection seismic data, and theory we define the attributes that changes in sea level must have in order to be preserved in the largest deposits on Earth, deltas. This theory can also be expanded to describe thresholds for changes in sediment flux, associated with changes in climate at river sources, which determine if stratigraphic signals are stored. Combined, our reported observations aid our interpretation of deltaic response to past climate change, thus enhancing our ability to predict their response to on-going climate change.  Work conducted during this project supported educational activities of undergraduate and graduate students (Masters and PhD) and supported activities to bring underrepresented minority students into Tulane’s sediment dynamics laboratory to observe experiments on the processes that construct the landscape they live on in New Orleans and to support science fair projects conducted in Tulane’s Sediment Dynamics and Stratigraphy Laboratory. All results associated with the project, including primary data have been archived on the SEAD environmental data repository.          Last Modified: 12/03/2019       Submitted by: Kyle Straub]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
