<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Natural Trap Cave Revisited: Ancient DNA, Climate and the Megafaunal Extinction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>228259.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>471448</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dena Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmsmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927431</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical abstract&lt;br/&gt;The end of the ice age (about 11,000 years ago) was a time of radical change in North America. Many species of large mammals went extinct, along with their habitats. Climate played a major role in this extinction event and current climate change continues to affect and alter the world today. This project will analyze ancient DNA from ice age animals from Natural Trap Cave, Wyoming to examine how these past climate changes relate to genetic variability and extinction.  This research will lead to a better overall understanding of how climate change is related to population structure, changes in genetic variation, and ultimately extinction, which may have potential effects on how biologists think about and mitigate the current human-caused climate change occurring today. This project will also provide many opportunities for scientific engagement and outreach to both the general public and in classroom settings. The intriguing nature of the excavations and ultimate findings make this expedition a perfect opportunity to bring science to the general public through print and television media. Additionally, this is an excellent opportunity to give high school students real time experience on how field science is performed. Via remote participation on the web, this project will give students the opportunity to participate in the experience of what it is like to excavate a fossil site, live out in the field, and unearth bones of gigantic, long-dead beasts, but in a safe, virtual setting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical abstract&lt;br/&gt;The end-Pleistocene was a time of radical change in North America. Many species of large mammals went extinct, along with the loss of a variety of associated ecosystems. Climate played a major role in this extinction event and current climate change continues to affect and alter ecosystems today. This project will re-open Natural Trap Cave in northern Wyoming to investigate paleoecological responses to climate change and how this relates to the megafaunal extinction events at the end of the Pleistocene. The permanently cold and moist conditions at NTC have preserved a large collection of megafaunal bones which still contain ancient DNA (aDNA) and collagen molecules. This rare resource is optimal to perform population-level analyses of genetic variation in the critical phases before, during, and after the end-Pleistocene extinction events. Key questions investigated in this project include:  1) Was the Pleistocene extinction event preceded by, or concurrent with a large loss of genetic diversity? 2) Are morphological changes at the Pleistocene/Holocene boundary the product of adaptation, or immigration? 3) Are major shifts in morphological and genetic variation correlated with climate change? Using aDNA, AMS radiocarbon dates, stable isotope analyses, morphological analyses, and previous data from NTC this project will investigate changes in climatic conditions and how they correlate with genetic diversity and morphological change. This research will lead to a better understanding of how climate change drives extinction and may reveal correlations between climate change, metapopulation structure and changes in genetic and morphological variation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1425059</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Meachen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie A Meachen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>julie.meachen@dmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152711568</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000071108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Cooper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan Cooper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alan.cooper@adelaide.edu.au</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6188303517</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596618</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Des Moines University</Name>
<CityName>Des Moines</CityName>
<ZipCode>503124198</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152711657</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3200 Grand Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073480535</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DES MOINES UNIVERSITY OSTEOPATHIC MEDICAL CENTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073480535</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Des Moines University]]></Name>
<CityName>Des Moines</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>503124198</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3200 Grand Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>SEDIMENTARY GEO &amp; PALEOBIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~369804</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~101644</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has produced several significant scientific results: 1) A new finding that the wolves of Natural Trap Cave may have been one of the first lineages of wolves in continental North America to give rise to the coyote; 2) A better understanding of the genetics and ecology of the extinct American cheetah-like cat and the extinct American lion; 3) A better understanding of the past environment of Natural Trap Cave and the surrounding areas through cave sediments and pollen fossils; 4) A better understanding of the small mammals at Natural Trap Cave; 3 and 4 together facilitate better understanding of the past climate and how it affected animals, which led to, 5) lead investigators on this project are putting together a new proposal stemming from what was learned here, to study the effects of drying climate on animals, and to better understand how modern-day drying climate affects animals of economic importance such as livestock, and agricultural pests (rodents). This project has resulted in 2 other monetary awards to continue field work, 6 peer-reviewed publications to date, with at least 4 other publications in writing or submission stages, at least 26 invited public talks, and at least 23 professional talks.</p> <p>This project has trained numerous scientists and future professionals in the fields of paleontology and geology - important STEM fields, including 5 postdoctoral scholars, 9 graduate students, at least 12 undergraduate students, 3 D.O. students, and 2 technicians.</p> <p>The major part of this project that has impacted society beyond the scientific community has been in the outreach and broader impacts aspects. The non-scientist groups of people that have been positively impacted by this project include:</p> <p>1) The US caving community. Through the inclusion of skilled cavers in field work, this project has built a rapport with the caving community across the US. Most of the cavers come from the northwestern US (such as Montana and Wyoming), but are also involved from other places, namely Tennessee, Pennsylvania, and other locations in the US. This bridge-crossing between scientists and cavers has opened the world of paleontology to a group of individuals that would not have had these opportunities otherwise, and the cavers provided the research team with an indispensable safety service, resulting in a truly symbiotic relationship.</p> <p>2) Lab/field outreach. Jenny McGuire at Georgia Tech has used this project to establish a weekly outreach activity called Fossil Wednesdays. During this time, volunteers come into her lab at Georgia Tech and sort and ID small fossils from Natural Trap Cave. She gets repeat volunteers&nbsp;that really enjoy the work and become very skilled at fossil ID. They enjoy the cathartic activity of sorting tiny fossils and learn about anatomy and paleontology while doing so.</p> <p>3) Outreach-oriented videos, such as those produced by PBS have reached a much wider audience than would have been possible without these types of outreach. The link to the PBS video about the Natural Trap Cave expedition can be found here: https://www.pbs.org/video/natural-trap-cave-maaeyo/</p> <p>4) Local Native American tribes have been consulted and project PIs have given talks to the Crow Nation about this project.</p> <p>5) High school student outreach. Over the course of this grant, 31 high school students have been involved since 2014. The make-up of these students is quite diverse with 67% (21/31) girls, and 45% (14/31) BIPOC students. These students were trained in how to read literature, examine data, analyze data, and present the data in the form of a scientific poster. Some of the success stories from mentoring these students include: A student got into Notre Dame, in part from the research experiences she had on this project. In both 2018 and 2019, their teacher and the PI took the students to the Governor's Future Ready Iowa Summit. During the summit in 2018, the students explained their science projects to attendees, who included statewide business owners, financial backers, and the governor of Iowa. All of the students that attended this summit met the governor and had their picture taken with her. In 2018, 4 students presented the work they had done on this project at multiple science fairs across the state of Iowa. One student's project made it to the Iowa State Science Fair where she won a $500 college scholarship.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Meachen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593633820954_IMG_8685--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593633820954_IMG_8685--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The morning commute"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593633820954_IMG_8685--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The morning commute"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PI Julie Meachen rappels into Natural Trap Cave to start fossil excavation work each morning</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Sipla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Meachen</div> <div class="imageTitle">The morning commute</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593633726624_IMG_7978--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593633726624_IMG_7978--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Learning about fossils at Natural Trap Cave"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593633726624_IMG_7978--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Learning about fossils at Natural Trap Cave"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PI Julie Meachen shows an invertebrate fossil to an undergraduate student</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Sipla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Meachen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Learning about fossils at Natural Trap Cave</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593634036373_Kidswithgov--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593634036373_Kidswithgov--rgov-800width.jpg" title="High School Students with Iowa Governor Kim Reynolds"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593634036373_Kidswithgov--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="High School Students with Iowa Governor Kim Reynolds"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">High school students got to meet the Iowa Governor while presenting their work on Natural Trap Cave.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kacia Cain</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Meachen</div> <div class="imageTitle">High School Students with Iowa Governor Kim Reynolds</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593634397857_DSC03628a--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593634397857_DSC03628a--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Look what I found!"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1425059/1425059_10357869_1593634397857_DSC03628a--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Look what I found!"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Project investigator Jenny McGuire holds up a horse ankle bone she excavated</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eric Scott</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Meachen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Look what I found!</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has produced several significant scientific results: 1) A new finding that the wolves of Natural Trap Cave may have been one of the first lineages of wolves in continental North America to give rise to the coyote; 2) A better understanding of the genetics and ecology of the extinct American cheetah-like cat and the extinct American lion; 3) A better understanding of the past environment of Natural Trap Cave and the surrounding areas through cave sediments and pollen fossils; 4) A better understanding of the small mammals at Natural Trap Cave; 3 and 4 together facilitate better understanding of the past climate and how it affected animals, which led to, 5) lead investigators on this project are putting together a new proposal stemming from what was learned here, to study the effects of drying climate on animals, and to better understand how modern-day drying climate affects animals of economic importance such as livestock, and agricultural pests (rodents). This project has resulted in 2 other monetary awards to continue field work, 6 peer-reviewed publications to date, with at least 4 other publications in writing or submission stages, at least 26 invited public talks, and at least 23 professional talks.  This project has trained numerous scientists and future professionals in the fields of paleontology and geology - important STEM fields, including 5 postdoctoral scholars, 9 graduate students, at least 12 undergraduate students, 3 D.O. students, and 2 technicians.  The major part of this project that has impacted society beyond the scientific community has been in the outreach and broader impacts aspects. The non-scientist groups of people that have been positively impacted by this project include:  1) The US caving community. Through the inclusion of skilled cavers in field work, this project has built a rapport with the caving community across the US. Most of the cavers come from the northwestern US (such as Montana and Wyoming), but are also involved from other places, namely Tennessee, Pennsylvania, and other locations in the US. This bridge-crossing between scientists and cavers has opened the world of paleontology to a group of individuals that would not have had these opportunities otherwise, and the cavers provided the research team with an indispensable safety service, resulting in a truly symbiotic relationship.  2) Lab/field outreach. Jenny McGuire at Georgia Tech has used this project to establish a weekly outreach activity called Fossil Wednesdays. During this time, volunteers come into her lab at Georgia Tech and sort and ID small fossils from Natural Trap Cave. She gets repeat volunteers that really enjoy the work and become very skilled at fossil ID. They enjoy the cathartic activity of sorting tiny fossils and learn about anatomy and paleontology while doing so.  3) Outreach-oriented videos, such as those produced by PBS have reached a much wider audience than would have been possible without these types of outreach. The link to the PBS video about the Natural Trap Cave expedition can be found here: https://www.pbs.org/video/natural-trap-cave-maaeyo/  4) Local Native American tribes have been consulted and project PIs have given talks to the Crow Nation about this project.  5) High school student outreach. Over the course of this grant, 31 high school students have been involved since 2014. The make-up of these students is quite diverse with 67% (21/31) girls, and 45% (14/31) BIPOC students. These students were trained in how to read literature, examine data, analyze data, and present the data in the form of a scientific poster. Some of the success stories from mentoring these students include: A student got into Notre Dame, in part from the research experiences she had on this project. In both 2018 and 2019, their teacher and the PI took the students to the Governor's Future Ready Iowa Summit. During the summit in 2018, the students explained their science projects to attendees, who included statewide business owners, financial backers, and the governor of Iowa. All of the students that attended this summit met the governor and had their picture taken with her. In 2018, 4 students presented the work they had done on this project at multiple science fairs across the state of Iowa. One student's project made it to the Iowa State Science Fair where she won a $500 college scholarship.       Last Modified: 07/01/2020       Submitted by: Julie A Meachen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
