<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Social Change, Moral Decision-Making, and Resource Allocation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25011.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25011</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah Winslow</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Increasingly, local communities are challenged by the need to manage scarce natural resources and ecosystem services for the common good.  Social scientists have found that when management authority remains at the local level, it is often less expensive and more effective than policies established from the top down. However, as communities become larger and technologies become more complicated, local management may be replaced by programs and policies emanating from higher levels.  This raises the question of what it is that makes local control successful. With the guidance of Dr. Norbert O. Ross, Vanderbilt University doctoral student, Werner Hertzog, will undertake research to answer this question.  Findings will contribute to our theoretical understanding of the relationship between culture, economic behavior, and institutions. This, in turn, can help government and private organizations design resource management systems that build on existing ones, saving money and preserving local control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be conducted in a Tzotzil-Maya municipality of southern Mexico. This site was chosen because the region has undergone drastic changes over the past five decades.  Furthermore, modernization has affected Tzotzil villages unevenly, which allows investigators to compare communities differing in degree of access to markets and modern infrastructure within a single ecological setting and ethno-linguistic group. Pilot studies have revealed systematic differences between more traditional (rural) and more modern (urban) Tzotzil villages with respect to notions of fairness regulating resource allocation. These data suggest that modernization in these communities is tied to the emergence of new cultural models of justice and society, findings which are in line with results from related research documenting the cognitive effects of social change within the area. Therefore, the researcher will explore the dynamics and effects of cultural models and moral values in regulating economic and adaptive systems in cognition, social organization, and behavior. He will use a mixed methods approach combining: (1) detailed observational methods to document the processes through which communities and households make resource allocation decisions; and (2) economic and behavioral experiments to index moral preferences in how people solve hypothetical problems of resource allocation. By focusing on social change the research contributes to our understanding of how modernization affects traditional systems of knowledge and of how culture and moral notions affect resource management practices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1425141</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norbert</FirstName>
<LastName>Ross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norbert Ross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>norbert.o.ross@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153226114</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000329678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Werner</FirstName>
<LastName>Hertzog</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Werner B Hertzog</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>werner.b.hertzog@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6158756070</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000663284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372122809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 18th Avenue South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL IMPLICATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~25011</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Werner Hertzog has completed fieldwork research for his dissertation on the effect of notions of fairness and justice on decision-making regarding the allocation of common resources. The project set out to address this question by comparing Tzotzil-Maya communities of southern Mexico, an area that has been undergoing rapid social and economic change due to modernization and economic growth. As these communities become less dependent on subsistence agriculture and more integrated into modern markets they experience a series of cultural and social transformations in which traditional values and institutions adapt (or are replaced by) to new conceptual frameworks and forms of organization.</p> <p>Mr. Hertzog conducted a year of fieldwork during which he compared rural and urban Tzotzil communities of Chenalh&oacute; (Chiapas) by using a combination of economic experiments, surveys, and ethnographic observation of decision making events. Over the past decades &ndash; and increasingly so after the Zapatista rebellion of 1994 &ndash; Tzotzil-Maya municipalities have become decentralized, with governance centers moving from the municipality level to smaller communities. As these small communities grew in number and became increasingly fragmented, they also gained decision-making power regarding the allocation of resources (water, land, food, electricity, and government aid) and burdens (taxes, communal labor, and fees). Increasing decentralization gave rise to a diversity of systems for resource allocation and taxation working on a micro-scale. The project has sought to understand how these systems emerge and change in interaction with cultural notions of fairness during bargaining processes and resolution of conflicts. Since modernization has affected communities unevenly, a research design comparing urban vs. rural sites can help us understand how these processes of change affect traditional resource management systems. &nbsp;</p> <p>Results show that modernization in Tzotzil communities is tied to a shift from prestige- to need-based decision making frameworks. In prestige-based frameworks, individuals are rewarded by their social status and history of service to the community, while need-based frameworks prioritize individuals who lack material resources. The research was able to disentangle some of the factors driving these changes, amongst them: 1) expanding social networks and decreasing social knowledge, 2) the decline of traditional institutions for allocating resources, and 3) the increasing dependence on currencies in mediating exchange. The work shows that changing fairness frameworks affect decisions within different units of analysis similarly; in other words, both households and communities share similar decision-making patterns, and consistently differ across rural and urban sites. Moreover, results point to consistencies in who communities and households prioritize when allocating both material resources and burdens (communal duties and labor).</p> <p>Together, these results point to the importance of understanding decision-making and resource allocation processes within their specific cultural contexts and with attention to local values of fairness. Mr. Hertzog&rsquo;s dissertation demonstrates that distribution of burdens and labor are both manifestations of the same moral frameworks used individuals use to make decisions or evaluate the &lsquo;fairness&rsquo; of allocation outcomes. This indicates that a better integration between different behavioral sciences is needed for shedding light the common foundations of economic and social decisions. The work contributes to both anthropology and economics and proposes new methods for integrating both disciplines (adapting economic experiments to contextual factors and using ethnography to observe resource allocation processes). Finally, the work contributes to our understanding of how economic change and cul...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Werner Hertzog has completed fieldwork research for his dissertation on the effect of notions of fairness and justice on decision-making regarding the allocation of common resources. The project set out to address this question by comparing Tzotzil-Maya communities of southern Mexico, an area that has been undergoing rapid social and economic change due to modernization and economic growth. As these communities become less dependent on subsistence agriculture and more integrated into modern markets they experience a series of cultural and social transformations in which traditional values and institutions adapt (or are replaced by) to new conceptual frameworks and forms of organization.  Mr. Hertzog conducted a year of fieldwork during which he compared rural and urban Tzotzil communities of Chenalh&oacute; (Chiapas) by using a combination of economic experiments, surveys, and ethnographic observation of decision making events. Over the past decades &ndash; and increasingly so after the Zapatista rebellion of 1994 &ndash; Tzotzil-Maya municipalities have become decentralized, with governance centers moving from the municipality level to smaller communities. As these small communities grew in number and became increasingly fragmented, they also gained decision-making power regarding the allocation of resources (water, land, food, electricity, and government aid) and burdens (taxes, communal labor, and fees). Increasing decentralization gave rise to a diversity of systems for resource allocation and taxation working on a micro-scale. The project has sought to understand how these systems emerge and change in interaction with cultural notions of fairness during bargaining processes and resolution of conflicts. Since modernization has affected communities unevenly, a research design comparing urban vs. rural sites can help us understand how these processes of change affect traditional resource management systems.    Results show that modernization in Tzotzil communities is tied to a shift from prestige- to need-based decision making frameworks. In prestige-based frameworks, individuals are rewarded by their social status and history of service to the community, while need-based frameworks prioritize individuals who lack material resources. The research was able to disentangle some of the factors driving these changes, amongst them: 1) expanding social networks and decreasing social knowledge, 2) the decline of traditional institutions for allocating resources, and 3) the increasing dependence on currencies in mediating exchange. The work shows that changing fairness frameworks affect decisions within different units of analysis similarly; in other words, both households and communities share similar decision-making patterns, and consistently differ across rural and urban sites. Moreover, results point to consistencies in who communities and households prioritize when allocating both material resources and burdens (communal duties and labor).  Together, these results point to the importance of understanding decision-making and resource allocation processes within their specific cultural contexts and with attention to local values of fairness. Mr. HertzogÆs dissertation demonstrates that distribution of burdens and labor are both manifestations of the same moral frameworks used individuals use to make decisions or evaluate the æfairnessÆ of allocation outcomes. This indicates that a better integration between different behavioral sciences is needed for shedding light the common foundations of economic and social decisions. The work contributes to both anthropology and economics and proposes new methods for integrating both disciplines (adapting economic experiments to contextual factors and using ethnography to observe resource allocation processes). Finally, the work contributes to our understanding of how economic change and cultural values interact in contexts of rapid change and rapid modernization taking place in traditional s...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
