<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NRI/Collaborative Research: Models and Instruments for Integrating Effective Human-Robot Teams into Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>589959.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>589959</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Kramer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bkramer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925348</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Robots for application in collaborative manufacturing must perform manual work side-by-side with people. Such robots offer the flexibility to work on many different tasks and promise to transform manufacturing by improving the quality and efficiency of manual processes in small shops and in facilitates that manufacture highly customized products. However, in order to meet this promise, robots must be effectively integrated into existing manufacturing teams and practices. To enable this integration, this National Robotics Initiative (NRI) award supports fundamental research on the methods and instruments that manufacturing engineers will need to form effective human-robot teams based on task requirements and worker skills. These methods will also enable robots to adapt to changes in workflow to maximize safety and efficiency. The effective integration of collaborative robots into manufacturing promises improvements in many industries that have not yet benefited from robotic technology. Therefore, results from this research will contribute to the competitiveness of U.S. manufacturing and benefit the U.S. economy and society. The research will involve contributions from multiple disciplines, including robotics, human factors, computer science, and manufacturing, and by academic and industry collaborators. These collaborations will help the dissemination of research results into manufacturing organizations and the integration of research into undergraduate and graduate curriculum in engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advancements in robotics promise the use of collaborative robots that perform interdependent work with people in order to improve quality, efficiency, and safety in industrial manufacturing. However, integrating collaborative robots into these processes and ensuring their efficient operation pose significant research challenges, including the optimal allocation of work based on task requirements and constraints, the formation of human-robot teams, and the dynamic adaptation of teamwork to workflow changes. This research will address these research challenges, enabling the seamless integration of collaborative robots into these processes and achieving efficient and safe collaboration between human and robot workers. The research team will create novel methods for optimal allocation of tasks to human and robot workers based on task constraints and worker skills, design new tools that utilize these methods to facilitate workflow design for human-robot teams, and develop novel mechanisms that enable robots to more efficiently and safely collaborate with human workers in the planned manufacturing operations. These methods and instruments will be validated in real-world manufacturing operations and disseminated through industry workshops, engineering curricula, and a public outreach program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1426824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bilge</FirstName>
<LastName>Mutlu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bilge D Mutlu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bilge@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082623822</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546805</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061685</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1210 West Dayton Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092E</Code>
<Text>Control systems &amp; applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1786</Code>
<Text>MANFG ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~589959</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project aimed to facilitate the integration of collaborative robots&mdash;safe and flexible robots designed to work side by side with people&mdash;into manufacturing tasks that are currently performed manually by human workers, such as assembly, kitting, and packaging, in order to improve the efficiency and safety of these processes.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Three forms of technological and scientific products that have resulted from the project contribute to this goal. First, it developed a novel method to translate currently manual tasks into collaborative tasks that can be performed by human-robot teams and that improve the efficiency, the ergonomic safety, or both the efficiency and the ergonomic safety of the task. Second, the project developed a software tool that manufacturing engineers can use to model existing manual tasks; translate them to human-robot task plans; inspect these plans through visualization and simulation; and generate the software implementation that is necessary to control the robot in the planned task. Third, through a series of laboratory and field studies, the project developed a better understanding of the role and impact of collaborative robots in manufacturing organizations and generated design guidelines to turn robots into more effective and adaptive assistants and collaborators.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>In addition to its scientific and technological contributions, the project has made three types of key societal contributions. The novel methods, tools, and knowledge that have resulted from the project will improve manufacturing efficiency and ergonomics, benefiting both industrial production and the health and wellbeing of workers. Furthermore, the project supported the research training and professional development of several undergraduate and graduate students, preparing them for STEM careers. Finally, the outreach activities of the project, particularly open lab events and an annual summer program for K-12 students, contributed to improving public understanding of science and technology.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Bilge&nbsp;D&nbsp;Mutlu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1426824/1426824_10327394_1577123156744_1426824-Image1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1426824/1426824_10327394_1577123156744_1426824-Image1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Human-robot task allocation method"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1426824/1426824_10327394_1577123156744_1426824-Image1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Human-robot task allocation method"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A novel method to introduce a robotic collaborator into a manual manufacturing task in order to improve task efficiency and worker ergonomics.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bilge Mutlu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bilge&nbsp;D&nbsp;Mutlu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Human-robot task allocation method</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1426824/1426824_10327394_1577123211112_1426824-Image2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1426824/1426824_10327394_1577123211112_1426824-Image2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example human-robot collaborative task"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1426824/1426824_10327394_1577123211112_1426824-Image2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example human-robot collaborative task"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example human-robot team task in which a human worker and a robot worker collaboratively perform assembly and packaging of toys.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Majid Aksari</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bilge&nbsp;D&nbsp;Mutlu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example human-robot collaborative task</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aimed to facilitate the integration of collaborative robots&mdash;safe and flexible robots designed to work side by side with people&mdash;into manufacturing tasks that are currently performed manually by human workers, such as assembly, kitting, and packaging, in order to improve the efficiency and safety of these processes.   Three forms of technological and scientific products that have resulted from the project contribute to this goal. First, it developed a novel method to translate currently manual tasks into collaborative tasks that can be performed by human-robot teams and that improve the efficiency, the ergonomic safety, or both the efficiency and the ergonomic safety of the task. Second, the project developed a software tool that manufacturing engineers can use to model existing manual tasks; translate them to human-robot task plans; inspect these plans through visualization and simulation; and generate the software implementation that is necessary to control the robot in the planned task. Third, through a series of laboratory and field studies, the project developed a better understanding of the role and impact of collaborative robots in manufacturing organizations and generated design guidelines to turn robots into more effective and adaptive assistants and collaborators.   In addition to its scientific and technological contributions, the project has made three types of key societal contributions. The novel methods, tools, and knowledge that have resulted from the project will improve manufacturing efficiency and ergonomics, benefiting both industrial production and the health and wellbeing of workers. Furthermore, the project supported the research training and professional development of several undergraduate and graduate students, preparing them for STEM careers. Finally, the outreach activities of the project, particularly open lab events and an annual summer program for K-12 students, contributed to improving public understanding of science and technology.          Last Modified: 12/23/2019       Submitted by: Bilge D Mutlu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
