<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NRI: Collaborative Research: Efficient Algorithms for Contact-Aware State Estimation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>874928.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>874928</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924768</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project addresses the difficult theoretical, computational, and applied challenges required to exploit a deep mathematical relationship between recent advances in machine perception/estimation algorithms and recent advances in algorithms for planning/controlling systems undergoing frictional contact.  It explores the immediate applications of these algorithms to perception, robotic object manipulation and parts assembly, and humanoid robots performing complex, multi-contact, whole-body maneuvers. In order to showcase the generality of approach, and simultaneously reach out to the important under-represented minority population, the research team employs a new hands-on short-course curriculum in which students apply the proposed algorithms to predict the outcome of games using visual tracking. The course is being developed in partnership with the MIT Office of Minority Education (OME).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project brings together expertise in simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM), robot manipulation, robotic automation, legged robots, and optimization and nonlinear control, leading to a cross-fertilization of ideas and techniques.  The research team exploits sparsity in the complementarity formulations of contact in Lagrangian dynamics.  The project explores a new algebraic approach to nonlinear estimator design. The project produces new theorems, new algorithms, and experimental results on real robots.  The project also represents a new partnership with our industrial collaborator, ABB Robotics. The developed algorithms facilitate a broad range of new applications in which perception and control systems monitor and manipulate physical interactions with the world.  From palm-sized smart devices to environmental monitoring, sensors are becoming ubiquitous; to reach their full potential these sensor networks must be able to reason about contact - the basic building block of physical interaction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1427050</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
<LastName>Tedrake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Russell L Tedrake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>russt@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172531778</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000325632</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodriguez Garcia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto Rodriguez Garcia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>albertor@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123209638</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~874928</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the duration of this award, we have witnessed step change in the use of simulation in robotics.&nbsp; When the project started, nobody (not even our own students) truly believed that one could pursue research for robotic manipulation in simulation.&nbsp; There were two major reasons for this: 1) manipulation depends heavily on cameras/perception, which were generally considered impossible to simulate, and 2) the contact mechanics of manipulation were considered too difficult to simulate.&nbsp;</p> <p>The adoption by the robotics community of game-engine quality renderers for simulating cameras, along with the impressive robustness of deep learning approaches to perception, addressed (1) surprisingly well.&nbsp; But our work on this award helped overcome (2) in two major ways.&nbsp; Researchers on this award led the development of a major open-source simulator (http://drake.mit.edu), and have showed repeated demonstrations of algorithms in simulation successfully crossing the "sim 2 real" gap and working in reality.&nbsp; We have also established and disseminated clean datasets for careful study of frictional multibody contact.</p> <p>Many challenges still remain to more deeply integrate the best tools from state estimation and uncertainty quantification into the domain of non-smooth mechanics, as seen in robotic manipulation.&nbsp; But this award supported a number of early attempts, and earned best paper awards at some of the top robotics conferences.&nbsp; Many of the ideas and tools developed here now appear in our open robotics courses: http://manipulation.mit.edu and http://underactuated.mit.edu .</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2021<br>      Modified by: Russell&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tedrake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the duration of this award, we have witnessed step change in the use of simulation in robotics.  When the project started, nobody (not even our own students) truly believed that one could pursue research for robotic manipulation in simulation.  There were two major reasons for this: 1) manipulation depends heavily on cameras/perception, which were generally considered impossible to simulate, and 2) the contact mechanics of manipulation were considered too difficult to simulate.   The adoption by the robotics community of game-engine quality renderers for simulating cameras, along with the impressive robustness of deep learning approaches to perception, addressed (1) surprisingly well.  But our work on this award helped overcome (2) in two major ways.  Researchers on this award led the development of a major open-source simulator (http://drake.mit.edu), and have showed repeated demonstrations of algorithms in simulation successfully crossing the "sim 2 real" gap and working in reality.  We have also established and disseminated clean datasets for careful study of frictional multibody contact.  Many challenges still remain to more deeply integrate the best tools from state estimation and uncertainty quantification into the domain of non-smooth mechanics, as seen in robotic manipulation.  But this award supported a number of early attempts, and earned best paper awards at some of the top robotics conferences.  Many of the ideas and tools developed here now appear in our open robotics courses: http://manipulation.mit.edu and http://underactuated.mit.edu .          Last Modified: 02/22/2021       Submitted by: Russell L Tedrake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
