<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Further Studies of Lightning Initiation, Propagation, and Evolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>779045.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>779045</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Thunderstorms and their accompanying lightning flashes are responsible for a substantial number of casualties and property damage each year in the USA. However, we still do not understand the physical mechanisms that cause the first spark of a lightning flash or that allow the spark to grow into a conducting channel that travels to ground first through the cloud and then through the air.  Intracloud flashes, those which move only inside and around a cloud (but not to ground), are a hazard for aircraft and space-bound rockets just after launch.  This project aims to gain a better understanding of the important processes in lightning initiation, lightning propagation through cloud and air, and lightning evolution from a small spark to an electrical discharge that is miles long and can strike in multiple locations that are miles apart.  The project will use existing data from a unique array of sensors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;This project will utilize data collected in summer 2011 around NASA Kennedy Space Center (KSC) in Florida, under a prior NSF award.  The data come from a combination of six sensor sets, each of which reveals different information about a flash. Three systems were operated by KSC and provided data on the lightning paths (composed of short steps), the overall lightning charge, and lightning ground strike points. Two research arrays of electric field change sensors provided data on the location and amount of electric current for different parts of the flash; these currents can travel 50 yards to several miles in one-thousandth of a second or less.  The sixth sensor was a high-speed video camera (operating at 50,000 fps) which yields detailed information on any luminous features of the lightning, including flash initiation and positive and negative charge motion.  Seven scientific articles have already been published using this dataset and seven more are either under review or being written.  However, the available multi-sensor dataset remains very rich and deep.  For example, on one day (August 14, 2011) there were 25,500 intracloud and 1,700 cloud-to-ground flashes within 50 miles of KSC, and there are similarly good data on 15 storm days. Thus, there is much as-yet-unstudied data that can be used to learn new details about lightning initiation, propagation, and evolution.  The project will be aided by many computer tools developed in a prior NSF award; these tools will enhance the data analysis from day one of this project.  This project will also extend the previous dataset by including archived data from the Melbourne National Weather Service radar located near KSC. The additional radar data will allow comparisons of lightning initiation, propagation, and development to the thunderstorm reflectivity parameters (and other radar parameters) used by weather forecasters. Thus, the main intellectual merit of the study is that it will use existing data to advance the understanding of lightning mechanisms and better characterize the evolution of lightning structure throughout the thunderstorm lifecycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;Kennedy Space Center is located in a region with one of the largest numbers of lightning flashes per year; these flashes endanger the workers, space-bound vehicles, and special equipment at KSC. With its mission to safely launch rockets carrying satellites and astronauts, NASA is especially concerned about lightning. To continue reducing the lightning threat for the general public and for NASA, it is essential to better understand how lightning works; this project aims to advance that understanding.  The project will be important for the development and training of several new scientists, including one post-doctoral researcher, one research associate, two graduate students, and two undergraduate physics students interested in scientific research. The training involves data analysis techniques that are specific to electromagnetic measurements of lightning as well as techniques that are generally applicable in many situations (including computer programming, computational modeling, and oral and written dissemination of results). Four of the eight anticipated project personnel are women. The results of this project will also be broadly disseminated in the peer-reviewed literature. Thus, the main broader impacts of this project are the potential reduction in lightning threats based on better understanding of lightning and the training of new and diverse scientists and engineers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1427734</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Marshall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas C Marshall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marshall@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6629155325</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000346306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maribeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Stolzenburg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maribeth Stolzenburg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mstolzen@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6629155252</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000188911</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Mississippi</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6629157482</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 BARR HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 1848]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>067713560</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSISSIPPI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067713560</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Mississippi]]></Name>
<CityName>University</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Lewis Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~209000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~284535</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~285510</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goals of this project were to gain understanding of how lightning starts, how it travels through cloud, and how the locations of electric charges evolve in order to make lightning. Several different types of time-correlated data for natural lightning flashes, collected under a prior NSF award, were analyzed.</p> <p>Regarding lightning initiation, the high-speed video data for this project was first to show that luminosity occurs near the beginning time of flashes, in the so-called initial breakdown stage. Prior to the initial breakdown stage, this project discovered a very weak electrical current flows for a very short time. Using video and electromagnetic data, this project described the transition from initial breakdown to stepped leader of ground flashes and showed that cloud flashes also begin with luminous initial breakdown stages. The project has led to characterization of initial breakdown pulses, both in terms of parameters that can be derived from the data and in terms of additional parameters extracted using three numerical modeling techniques developed under this award. The project has defined, characterized, and quantified the initial field change in cloud and ground flashes. Together, these analyses are informing hypotheses of lightning initiation and also hypotheses of gamma-ray production by some cloud flashes.</p> <p>Regarding thunderstorm electrical structure, this project has shown that flash initiations over land and ocean on a single day can be quite similar in terms of altitude and type. However, ocean storms can take much longer after the first radar echo to make the first flash, which suggests that the mechanisms for electrification are the same but are working on different scales. The project has shown that some storm cells and some entire storms do not produce any lightning, while surrounding cells on the same day do make flashes. Thus, certain characteristics of the radar echo evolution can provide needed information for short-term forecasting of first lightning in these marginal situations.</p> <p>Regarding lightning propagation, this project focused on the downward leader portion of ground flashes and the attachment at ground. Modeling techniques and video data together yielded new estimates for the charge per unit length of highly branched stepped leaders. Brightly luminous but briefly lit abandoned branches were discovered and described, and they were shown to have critical effects on the overall leader propagation speed and on determining the winning branch. Another new discovery was that two downward propagating events, a re-illumination of the return stroke and a leader along a different path, can occur at the same time in a flash. Studies of lightning attachment to ground have yielded 18 length estimates for the upward connecting leader (which meets the downward leader before the return stroke), more than doubling the number of estimates in the literature for natural flashes to flat ground. For the first time, this project includes upward connecting leader length estimates for water attachments in which the detailed process has never been studied.&nbsp;</p> <p>Technique development has led to several important outcomes in understanding small but powerful discharges called Narrow Bipolar Events. The project has led to categorizing a large set of these events into four types having different shapes, and possibly different mechanisms, and has led to discovering the existence of relatively long duration field changes that follow the main pulse of the event. Characterizing the location of a large set of these discharge events in terms of the thunderstorm structure has led to describing them as occurring in three places: above or beside the main storm updraft or in the storm anvil region.</p> <p>Research training of two undergraduate and four graduate students and the professional development of one postdoctoral researcher were adjoining goals of the project. Three women students in physics and engineering were involved. One Ph.D. degree was entirely completed under this project and two others were started. The post-doctoral researcher was involved for two years until moving into a full-time academic position at a four-year college.</p> <p>The major outcomes of the project are contained in 15 peer-reviewed journal articles, one paper currently in revision for a journal, and one PhD dissertation in physics. Three of the papers were led by the post-doctoral researcher as part of his mentored professional development, three were led by graduate students as part of their research training, and two were led by undergraduate students after they had moved on to medical school. As of October 2018, citation counts for these 15 papers total 74, and the average is 7.1 for the 10 articles that are &gt;24 months past publication. This citation rate is very good for works in the relatively small field of atmospheric electricity and supports that this project is having an impact on the discipline. Another 10 papers are anticipated to stem directly from this project in the next two years.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Maribeth&nbsp;Stolzenburg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this project were to gain understanding of how lightning starts, how it travels through cloud, and how the locations of electric charges evolve in order to make lightning. Several different types of time-correlated data for natural lightning flashes, collected under a prior NSF award, were analyzed.  Regarding lightning initiation, the high-speed video data for this project was first to show that luminosity occurs near the beginning time of flashes, in the so-called initial breakdown stage. Prior to the initial breakdown stage, this project discovered a very weak electrical current flows for a very short time. Using video and electromagnetic data, this project described the transition from initial breakdown to stepped leader of ground flashes and showed that cloud flashes also begin with luminous initial breakdown stages. The project has led to characterization of initial breakdown pulses, both in terms of parameters that can be derived from the data and in terms of additional parameters extracted using three numerical modeling techniques developed under this award. The project has defined, characterized, and quantified the initial field change in cloud and ground flashes. Together, these analyses are informing hypotheses of lightning initiation and also hypotheses of gamma-ray production by some cloud flashes.  Regarding thunderstorm electrical structure, this project has shown that flash initiations over land and ocean on a single day can be quite similar in terms of altitude and type. However, ocean storms can take much longer after the first radar echo to make the first flash, which suggests that the mechanisms for electrification are the same but are working on different scales. The project has shown that some storm cells and some entire storms do not produce any lightning, while surrounding cells on the same day do make flashes. Thus, certain characteristics of the radar echo evolution can provide needed information for short-term forecasting of first lightning in these marginal situations.  Regarding lightning propagation, this project focused on the downward leader portion of ground flashes and the attachment at ground. Modeling techniques and video data together yielded new estimates for the charge per unit length of highly branched stepped leaders. Brightly luminous but briefly lit abandoned branches were discovered and described, and they were shown to have critical effects on the overall leader propagation speed and on determining the winning branch. Another new discovery was that two downward propagating events, a re-illumination of the return stroke and a leader along a different path, can occur at the same time in a flash. Studies of lightning attachment to ground have yielded 18 length estimates for the upward connecting leader (which meets the downward leader before the return stroke), more than doubling the number of estimates in the literature for natural flashes to flat ground. For the first time, this project includes upward connecting leader length estimates for water attachments in which the detailed process has never been studied.   Technique development has led to several important outcomes in understanding small but powerful discharges called Narrow Bipolar Events. The project has led to categorizing a large set of these events into four types having different shapes, and possibly different mechanisms, and has led to discovering the existence of relatively long duration field changes that follow the main pulse of the event. Characterizing the location of a large set of these discharge events in terms of the thunderstorm structure has led to describing them as occurring in three places: above or beside the main storm updraft or in the storm anvil region.  Research training of two undergraduate and four graduate students and the professional development of one postdoctoral researcher were adjoining goals of the project. Three women students in physics and engineering were involved. One Ph.D. degree was entirely completed under this project and two others were started. The post-doctoral researcher was involved for two years until moving into a full-time academic position at a four-year college.  The major outcomes of the project are contained in 15 peer-reviewed journal articles, one paper currently in revision for a journal, and one PhD dissertation in physics. Three of the papers were led by the post-doctoral researcher as part of his mentored professional development, three were led by graduate students as part of their research training, and two were led by undergraduate students after they had moved on to medical school. As of October 2018, citation counts for these 15 papers total 74, and the average is 7.1 for the 10 articles that are &gt;24 months past publication. This citation rate is very good for works in the relatively small field of atmospheric electricity and supports that this project is having an impact on the discipline. Another 10 papers are anticipated to stem directly from this project in the next two years.       Last Modified: 10/29/2018       Submitted by: Maribeth Stolzenburg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
