<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US - UK and Jamaica Planning Visits: Initiating an international collaborative network on the impacts of private yard management for people and urban biodiversity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>51162.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>51162</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maija Kukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkukla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924940</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>a non-technical explanation &lt;br/&gt;This CNIC establishes international collaborations and an international multi-city research network. It will lead to determine how yard management decisions influence urban bird populations, the rationale for these decisions and how they feedback to influence people through ecosystem service provision. This mentor led citizen science project runs in five US cities and has the dual objectives of scientific inquiry on avian demographics, and educating the public about bird biology and the scientific process. Funding is requested for two planning visits to Sheffield and one planning visit to Montego Bay, Jamaica for four US scientists. These will a) provide consultation with an international team (US, UK &amp; Jamaica) of expert urban ecologists and social scientists, b) collect pilot data demonstrating proof of concept and the feasibility of exporting NN to the UK and Jamaica, and c) deliver an outline CNH proposal. This CNIC proposal is led by Dr. Susannah Lerman (PI, University of Massachusetts) and Dr. Peter Marra (co-PI, Smithsonian Institution). Dr. Karl Evans, the primary foreign collaborator (University of Sheffield, UK) will be instrumental in establishing the international network by co-organizing and actively participating in all activities, and contributing his expertise in avian urban ecology and multi-disciplinary research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Due to rapid global urbanization the nature of urban areas will make a significant contribution to determining the globe?s biodiversity, and its ability to deliver ecosystem services to an urbanized population - 80% of people are predicted to live in urban areas by 2050. The research program will establish how yard management influences urban biodiversity and peoples? health and well-being through the provision of ecosystem services. The CNIC thus contributes to major societal goals of preserving biodiversity and quality of life. Its legacy will include an outstanding network of international collaborators from world-leading institutions, including academics, NGOs (BirdsCarribean &amp; British Trust for Ornithology) and government agencies (Forest Service &amp; Smithsonian). By exporting the NN to the UK and Jamaica, the CNIC will further increase scientific literacy within a global context and enable the public to increase their sense of place and understanding of ecological processes. US and UK graduate student participation provides outstanding training opportunities and an exposure to interdisciplinary research within vastly different cultural and ecological contexts. To draw wider attention to the CNIC?s activities the collaborators will submit a symposium proposal for the 2016 Ecological Society of America conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;a technical description &lt;br/&gt;Urban ecology has largely progressed as isolated studies that use divergent methodologies, hindering comparisons between cities and regions. To address this, the CNIC proposal establishes a consistent research methodology across an international network of urban research sites. The CNIC, and follow on research, will be the first study to address specifically how private yard management decisions (plant choices, use of chemical inputs etc.) influence avian survival, reproductive success, and health and physiological responses. The network will also explore the motivations driving yard management decisions, participation in citizen science and stewardship. Adapting the NN model enables the acquisition of in-depth knowledge of how yards function as a social-ecological system. The network of cities spans a range of cultural, socio-economic and climatic contexts. It thus has considerable potential to address a key knowledge gap in urban ecology at a global scale, i.e. the links between yard management, biodiversity responses and consequences for ecosystem service provision. Achieving this is essential for generating effective yard management programs that enhance urban sustainability for wildlife and people. To achieve this, the CNIC will establish uniform methodology for measuring avian biological responses and assessing human attitudes to yard management and participation in scientific research. Consistent methodologies will enable direct comparisons across international boundaries and assess how the linkages generalize across diverse cultural and ecological conditions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1427639</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Marra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter P Marra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Peter.Marra@georgetown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2026331594</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114789</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Lerman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susannah B Lerman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slerman@cns.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135455447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000515499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039285</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5977</Code>
<Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~51162</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Summary</strong></p> <p>The CNIC project established a new international collaboration with Dr. Karl Evans from the University of Sheffield, UK. The grant funded one planning visit to Sheffield, United Kingdom for four US research scientists with the primary goal&nbsp;to leverage the scientific expertise from the US and UK to establish an international multi-city network that addresses core knowledge gaps in the field of urban wildlife ecology using a citizen science approach. Dr. Susannah Lerman, University of Massachusetts (PI, now with the USDA Forest Service) led the international collaboration with co-PI Dr. Peter Marra from the Smithsonian Institution. Activities during the planning visit included site visits to private yards to test the feasibility of collecting bird data in the UK, conducting key informant interviews with 10 homeowners to assess the attitudes and motivations for yard care and wildlife, and sponsor a 1-day workshop with ten UK and five American scientists on the opportunities, challenges and barriers for promoting bird-friendly landscaping.&nbsp;The CNIC led to two competitive submissions to the Dynamics of Coupled Natural Human Systems grant (CNH) NSF program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The international collaboration&nbsp;provided an excellent opportunity to generate novel insights regarding patterns in the linkages between human management of yards within towns and cities, their impacts on biodiversity, and resultant feedbacks to people through the provision of ecosystem services.The collaborators assessed how these linkages generalize across diverse cultural and ecological conditions, which is increasingly crucial due to the projected growth of urban areas. The CNIC addressed three key research gaps: (1) how do different yard management strategies (e.g., plant choices, fertilizers, and presence of outdoor pets) influence avian survival, reproductive success, health and physiological responses, thus moving beyond patterns of distribution; (2) how do geographic and cultural variation in human attitudes and socioeconomic factors generate barriers or positively influence sustainable yard management and how do they feedback to attitudes towards urban wildlife; and (3) what information is necessary for facilitating development, promotion and delivery of programs that can change yard management.&nbsp;Explicitly linking yard management to mechanistic demographic responses of wildlife using a citizen science approach attempts to close the circle of interactions between people and wildlife by addressing how variation in wildlife populations ultimately feedback to determine the provision of ecosystem services (or disservices) to people. Our international multi-city network will enable us to better assess&nbsp;the extent to which patterns documented in one city are replicated in other urban areas, and to test whether any emerging paradigms and generalizations are robust to the often marked variation in urban systems across cities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The overarching research objective is to improve fundamental understanding of yard management impacts on wildlife populations and people, and find solutions to increasing wildlife friendly yard management. Achieving this is crucial as the ecological impacts of unsustainable yard management regimes have implications for human well-being as they erode the ability of urban green space to deliver ecosystem services. The main objective of the CNIC was to expand the US-based (five US cities) Smithsonian Institution&rsquo;s program Neighborhood Nestwatch (a citizen science program with the dual objective of scientific inquiry on the health and survival of common backyard birds, and educating the public about bird biology and the scientific process) to Sheffield, UK. Through the exportation of this successful program, the CNIC aimed to further increase scientific literacy within a global context, enable the public to increase their sense of place and understanding of ecological processes, and provide an opportunity for scientists to gain in-depth knowledge of how yards function as a social-ecological system. By including graduate student participation from the US and UK, the CNIC provided outstanding training opportunities and an exposure to interdisciplinary research within vastly different cultural and ecological contexts. By the year 2050, 80% of the world population will live in urban and suburban areas, with roughly 60% of the land slated for development, currently undeveloped. The international approach better captures some of the global variation found in urban cities and thus has the potential for broader application and relevance to urban yards within and beyond the US.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/25/2019<br>      Modified by: Susannah&nbsp;Lerman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Summary  The CNIC project established a new international collaboration with Dr. Karl Evans from the University of Sheffield, UK. The grant funded one planning visit to Sheffield, United Kingdom for four US research scientists with the primary goal to leverage the scientific expertise from the US and UK to establish an international multi-city network that addresses core knowledge gaps in the field of urban wildlife ecology using a citizen science approach. Dr. Susannah Lerman, University of Massachusetts (PI, now with the USDA Forest Service) led the international collaboration with co-PI Dr. Peter Marra from the Smithsonian Institution. Activities during the planning visit included site visits to private yards to test the feasibility of collecting bird data in the UK, conducting key informant interviews with 10 homeowners to assess the attitudes and motivations for yard care and wildlife, and sponsor a 1-day workshop with ten UK and five American scientists on the opportunities, challenges and barriers for promoting bird-friendly landscaping. The CNIC led to two competitive submissions to the Dynamics of Coupled Natural Human Systems grant (CNH) NSF program.     Intellectual Merit   The international collaboration provided an excellent opportunity to generate novel insights regarding patterns in the linkages between human management of yards within towns and cities, their impacts on biodiversity, and resultant feedbacks to people through the provision of ecosystem services.The collaborators assessed how these linkages generalize across diverse cultural and ecological conditions, which is increasingly crucial due to the projected growth of urban areas. The CNIC addressed three key research gaps: (1) how do different yard management strategies (e.g., plant choices, fertilizers, and presence of outdoor pets) influence avian survival, reproductive success, health and physiological responses, thus moving beyond patterns of distribution; (2) how do geographic and cultural variation in human attitudes and socioeconomic factors generate barriers or positively influence sustainable yard management and how do they feedback to attitudes towards urban wildlife; and (3) what information is necessary for facilitating development, promotion and delivery of programs that can change yard management. Explicitly linking yard management to mechanistic demographic responses of wildlife using a citizen science approach attempts to close the circle of interactions between people and wildlife by addressing how variation in wildlife populations ultimately feedback to determine the provision of ecosystem services (or disservices) to people. Our international multi-city network will enable us to better assess the extent to which patterns documented in one city are replicated in other urban areas, and to test whether any emerging paradigms and generalizations are robust to the often marked variation in urban systems across cities.     Broader Impacts   The overarching research objective is to improve fundamental understanding of yard management impacts on wildlife populations and people, and find solutions to increasing wildlife friendly yard management. Achieving this is crucial as the ecological impacts of unsustainable yard management regimes have implications for human well-being as they erode the ability of urban green space to deliver ecosystem services. The main objective of the CNIC was to expand the US-based (five US cities) Smithsonian Institution?s program Neighborhood Nestwatch (a citizen science program with the dual objective of scientific inquiry on the health and survival of common backyard birds, and educating the public about bird biology and the scientific process) to Sheffield, UK. Through the exportation of this successful program, the CNIC aimed to further increase scientific literacy within a global context, enable the public to increase their sense of place and understanding of ecological processes, and provide an opportunity for scientists to gain in-depth knowledge of how yards function as a social-ecological system. By including graduate student participation from the US and UK, the CNIC provided outstanding training opportunities and an exposure to interdisciplinary research within vastly different cultural and ecological contexts. By the year 2050, 80% of the world population will live in urban and suburban areas, with roughly 60% of the land slated for development, currently undeveloped. The international approach better captures some of the global variation found in urban cities and thus has the potential for broader application and relevance to urban yards within and beyond the US.           Last Modified: 02/25/2019       Submitted by: Susannah Lerman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
