<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strombolian and Hawaiian Explosions:  New Insights From Synchronizing Videos and Exsolved Volatiles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>86462.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>86462</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Kilauea, Stromboli and Etna are the three most intensely monitored, continually active basaltic volcanoes in the world. This continuity of eruptive activity and the existing and ongoing real-time geophysical and geochemical observations make these volcanoes ideal for this study. Using well-characterized volcanoes, the researchers expect results that can be applied to less well-constrained basaltic eruptions. K&amp;#299;lauea and Stromboli are also locations of large and growing volcano-tourism operations. Summit eruptions pose particular issues for management agencies because the sites are highly accessible and thus there is a need to balance the strong public interest in viewing the activity against the issue of public safety. The Hawaii Volcanoes National Park, for example, records over 5000 visitors per day to the summit of K&amp;#299;lauea. This group's aim is to assist with satisfying public thirst for information and a need for improved forecasting of the likely course of all future eruptions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Coupling high-speed photography and high-resolution analysis of released volcanic gas offers a powerful new way to first describe and then interpret volcanic explosions. This study will couple these two techniques in real-time for the first time at K&amp;#299;lauea, Hawaii and Stromboli, and, if activity permits, Etna, Italy. This has the potential to revolutionize ideas of the final stages of melt and bubble rise leading to an eruption. Researchers will examine a spectrum of types of activity, from short, widely spaced explosions (Strombolian) to fountains lasting hours to days (Hawaiian), via three synchronized high-speed cameras paired to volcanic gas studies using Fournier Transform Infrared techniques and low-cost, portable, and precise multicomponent gas sensors. They suggest that the exact form and duration of these eruptions is driven by the form and timing of pulses of meter-sized gas bubbles that rise, and interact in a highly dynamic fashion under the vent.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1427357</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Carey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca Carey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rebecca.carey@utas.edu.au</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089565960</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Houghton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce Houghton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bhought@soest.hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089562561</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000474200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~86462</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this small award was for proof of novel concepts and new techniques and to amass a database of very high speed camera footage in advance of a now submitted, larger, joint &nbsp;NSF and U.K. National Environmental Research Council proposal in 2017. Some key outcomes were:</p> <p><strong><em>3D measurements of the velocity of large volcanic projectiles</em></strong></p> <p>Traditional 2-D video observations cannot measure motion of volcanic projectiles in the directions both towards and away from the camera, strongly hindering the capability to fully determine crucial hazard-related parameters such as explosion direction and&nbsp; &nbsp;absolute velocity of bombs. For the first time, synchronized footage from two cameras was used to estimate the true (3D) velocity of pyroclasts at K?lauea , Stromboli and Yasur volcanoes. The 3D velocity measurements were a world-first and show predictably that true velocities are significantly higher than those inferred from 2D trajectories.</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong><em>Styles and shifts between Hawaiian and Strombolian styles of explosions</em></strong></p> <p>The project evolved a new and internally consistent classification scheme for all weak explosions of low intensity that depends on duration rather than event size. A large gap exists from 10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>4</sup> sec between the typical duration of Strombolian explosions and that of fountains at K?lauea, and Etna. In comparison, overlaps in terms of both erupted mass and mass discharge rate rule out either of these parameters as a principal basis to distinguish these two eruptive styles. A natural division between Strombolian explosions of all sizes and Hawaiian fountaining episodes is a duration of 300 s, close to the middle of this wide gap.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;<strong><em>Patterns and relationships between &lsquo;puffing&rsquo; escape of gas and Strombolian activities</em></strong></p> <p><em>D</em>ata from 35 erupting vents suggest that all Strombolian eruption activities form a continuum arising from a common mechanism, and controlled by: 1) the dimensions of the bursting gas bubbles with respect to the vent diameter, and 2) the presence/absence and thickness of a high-viscosity layer at the top of the volcanic conduit.</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong><em>Developing human resources</em></strong></p> <p>This project involved mentoring and training three undergraduates, four graduate student and three post-doctoral and emerging scientists. All visited and worked on the erupting volcanoes, developed new instrumentational, laboratory, and analytical skills, and travelled to key international meetings to present their findings.</p> <p><strong><em>Impacts on society </em></strong></p> <p>The work on the underlying causes of volcanic eruptions has strong societal relevance to resident populations and significant visitor numbers on Hawaii, and to those surrounding other active basaltic volcanoes (e.g., Stromboli, Etna, Cerro Negro).&nbsp; The recognition that Hawaii, normally thought to be a relatively peaceful volcano, can undergo abrupt transitions to explosive behavior &nbsp;is clearly of concern to administrators and the growing visitor population to Hawaii Volcano National Park who have been attracted by the 2008-2016 activity at the lava lake.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;F&nbsp;Houghton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this small award was for proof of novel concepts and new techniques and to amass a database of very high speed camera footage in advance of a now submitted, larger, joint  NSF and U.K. National Environmental Research Council proposal in 2017. Some key outcomes were:  3D measurements of the velocity of large volcanic projectiles  Traditional 2-D video observations cannot measure motion of volcanic projectiles in the directions both towards and away from the camera, strongly hindering the capability to fully determine crucial hazard-related parameters such as explosion direction and   absolute velocity of bombs. For the first time, synchronized footage from two cameras was used to estimate the true (3D) velocity of pyroclasts at K?lauea , Stromboli and Yasur volcanoes. The 3D velocity measurements were a world-first and show predictably that true velocities are significantly higher than those inferred from 2D trajectories.   Styles and shifts between Hawaiian and Strombolian styles of explosions  The project evolved a new and internally consistent classification scheme for all weak explosions of low intensity that depends on duration rather than event size. A large gap exists from 102 to 104 sec between the typical duration of Strombolian explosions and that of fountains at K?lauea, and Etna. In comparison, overlaps in terms of both erupted mass and mass discharge rate rule out either of these parameters as a principal basis to distinguish these two eruptive styles. A natural division between Strombolian explosions of all sizes and Hawaiian fountaining episodes is a duration of 300 s, close to the middle of this wide gap.    Patterns and relationships between ?puffing? escape of gas and Strombolian activities  Data from 35 erupting vents suggest that all Strombolian eruption activities form a continuum arising from a common mechanism, and controlled by: 1) the dimensions of the bursting gas bubbles with respect to the vent diameter, and 2) the presence/absence and thickness of a high-viscosity layer at the top of the volcanic conduit.   Developing human resources  This project involved mentoring and training three undergraduates, four graduate student and three post-doctoral and emerging scientists. All visited and worked on the erupting volcanoes, developed new instrumentational, laboratory, and analytical skills, and travelled to key international meetings to present their findings.  Impacts on society   The work on the underlying causes of volcanic eruptions has strong societal relevance to resident populations and significant visitor numbers on Hawaii, and to those surrounding other active basaltic volcanoes (e.g., Stromboli, Etna, Cerro Negro).  The recognition that Hawaii, normally thought to be a relatively peaceful volcano, can undergo abrupt transitions to explosive behavior  is clearly of concern to administrators and the growing visitor population to Hawaii Volcano National Park who have been attracted by the 2008-2016 activity at the lava lake.             Last Modified: 10/21/2017       Submitted by: Bruce F Houghton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
