<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the ACM MobiCom 2014 Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ACM MobiCom conference is the leading international conference on mobile computing and wireless networking. It invites research contributions addressing the challenges in the area of mobile computing, from the perspective of networks, wireless and mobile systems, algorithms, and applications. The conference features a high-quality technical program, with an acceptance rate of around 10% out of around 250 submissions. It has a single-track session, which offers significant opportunities for individual and small groups that foster technical and social interactions among a diverse set of participants. MobiCom is also an international conference that stimulates exchanges between various international research communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will help increase the representation and participation of United States-based students at the conference by providing 20 or more travel grants limited to a maximum of $1000 each. By creating new opportunities for graduate students, especially those from under-represented groups, to attend a high-quality conference, this award will benefit the students by giving them an opportunity to interact with world-class researchers, inspire them to try new research directions, providing mentoring opportunities, as well as the chance to seek out internships and post-doctoral positions which will help the students advance in their research career.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1429953</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dimitrios</FirstName>
<LastName>Koutsonikolas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dimitrios Koutsonikolas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dimitrio@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166454733</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000603759</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142602500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[338 Davis Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>ACM MobiCom is the flagship annual conference of the Special Interest Group on Mobility of Systems, Users, Data, and Computing, a special interest group of the Association for Computing Machinery. It invites&nbsp; research contributions addressing the challenges in the area of mobile computing, from the perspective of networks, wireless and mobile systems, algorithms, and applications. The conference features a high-quality technical program, with an acceptance rate of around 20% out of around 300 submissions. It has a single-track session, which offers significant opportunities for individual and small-group technical and social interactions among a diverse set of participants. MobiCom is also an international conference that stimulates exchanges between various international research communities.<br /><br />The ACM MobiCom 2014 Conference was held between September 7 and September 11, 2014, in Chicago, Illinois. The goal of this project was to provide financial assistance for graduate students from US institutions to attend the conference and the associated workshops. The primary objective of the project was to support as many students as possible while encouraging participation of women and under-represented minorities. We received 55 applications for the NSF travel grant. After removing non-qualified applicants, e.g., students from non-US-based institutions and undergrads (one exceptional undergrad was given a Google Travel Grant), we were left with 51 applications. We awarded 24 students, including 8 female students.<br /><br />This project integrated research and student education through exposure to a premier technical conference in wireless networking and mobile computing. By creating new opportunities for students -- especially those from under-represented groups -- to attend a high-quality conference, the project benefited the research community in several ways. The students themselves benefited from the opportunity to meet and interact with many other researchers in a favorable setting, and from seeing research presented that may be related to what they are working on, or may inspire them to try a new direction. The research community benefited from the improvement of the students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives. Everybody benefited from increased diversity of participants attending the conference. MobiCom is also a forum where researchers from academia and industry mix to discuss research topics and introduce to students future opportunities for internships. Furthermore, the truly international flavor of MobiCom is well-known and reflected in the composition of the Technical Program Committee as well as in the authors of the submitted and accepted papers. As such, it presented a great opportunity for students to increase their breadth of ideas and technical perspectives.<br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/23/2015<br>      Modified by: Dimitrios&nbsp;Koutsonikolas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ ACM MobiCom is the flagship annual conference of the Special Interest Group on Mobility of Systems, Users, Data, and Computing, a special interest group of the Association for Computing Machinery. It invites  research contributions addressing the challenges in the area of mobile computing, from the perspective of networks, wireless and mobile systems, algorithms, and applications. The conference features a high-quality technical program, with an acceptance rate of around 20% out of around 300 submissions. It has a single-track session, which offers significant opportunities for individual and small-group technical and social interactions among a diverse set of participants. MobiCom is also an international conference that stimulates exchanges between various international research communities.  The ACM MobiCom 2014 Conference was held between September 7 and September 11, 2014, in Chicago, Illinois. The goal of this project was to provide financial assistance for graduate students from US institutions to attend the conference and the associated workshops. The primary objective of the project was to support as many students as possible while encouraging participation of women and under-represented minorities. We received 55 applications for the NSF travel grant. After removing non-qualified applicants, e.g., students from non-US-based institutions and undergrads (one exceptional undergrad was given a Google Travel Grant), we were left with 51 applications. We awarded 24 students, including 8 female students.  This project integrated research and student education through exposure to a premier technical conference in wireless networking and mobile computing. By creating new opportunities for students -- especially those from under-represented groups -- to attend a high-quality conference, the project benefited the research community in several ways. The students themselves benefited from the opportunity to meet and interact with many other researchers in a favorable setting, and from seeing research presented that may be related to what they are working on, or may inspire them to try a new direction. The research community benefited from the improvement of the students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives. Everybody benefited from increased diversity of participants attending the conference. MobiCom is also a forum where researchers from academia and industry mix to discuss research topics and introduce to students future opportunities for internships. Furthermore, the truly international flavor of MobiCom is well-known and reflected in the composition of the Technical Program Committee as well as in the authors of the submitted and accepted papers. As such, it presented a great opportunity for students to increase their breadth of ideas and technical perspectives.         Last Modified: 07/23/2015       Submitted by: Dimitrios Koutsonikolas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
