<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Conservation Science--Two Case Studies in Wetland Monitoring and Management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>7100.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>7100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wetlands are at the forefront of national and international research, management, and advocacy addressing water futures, biodiversity,  development, and sustainability. As such, they have generated national and regional contestations over science, water, and livelihoods. Under the supervision of Prof. Stephan Helmreich, Ph.D. student Caterina Scaramelli will conduct ethnographic and archival research on two coastal wetland sites in order to better understand the role of conservation science in wetland monitoring and management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to producing a dissertation, the co-PI will share her findings by creating an online platform for hosting research data and video production. This aspect of the project promises to add innovative tools for research, communication, and public dissemination.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1429914</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
<LastName>Helmreich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefan Helmreich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sgh2@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172539343</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455132</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caterina</FirstName>
<LastName>Scaramelli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Caterina Scaramelli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scaramel@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178038682</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000635259</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachussets Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachussets Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7567</Code>
<Text>SOC STUDIES OF SCI, ENG &amp; TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~7100</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Caterina scaramelli&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>User name: Scaramelli, Caterina</p> <p>Organization Id: 0021782000</p> <p>NSF ID: 000635259&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Password: ciaociao87</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Wetlands are at the forefront of national and international projects addressing water futures, climate change, biodiversity, development, and sustainability. With the global rise of the scientific and legal category of wetland in Europe and in the US, wetlands have become ecologies of value but also sites of struggle between state institutions, environmental NGOs, universities and civil society. This research tracksa regional history of wetland conservation in Turkey, one that is often left outside of analysis of conservation science, often located in Euroamerican context. This research examined the applications of wetland science and conservation strategies through two case studies in Turkey&rsquo;s coastal wetlands, interrogating the biological, cultural, political, scientific, and economic interventions that produce wetlands as conservation ecologies. In contemporary Turkey, wetland science is entangled in the making of new ecological politics, concurrent with nationwide grassroots environmental movements and struggles for inclusion of diversity and for an expansion of rights in fact of what many perceive as increasing political centralization and authoritarianism. Debates over the implementation of wetland conservation measures gets mobilized in anti-authoritarian social movements, as well as in ongoing nationalist projects. The research focused on two Turkish coastal wetlands &mdash; the Gediz delta on the Aegean and the K?z?l?rmak delta on the Black Sea. The methodology was based on ethnographic fieldwork with environmental NGOs, wetland residents, Turkish and international experts, and state officials. It also drew on archival research on wetland science and conservation and on landscape histories.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The research developed new conversations between STS scholarship on field ecology, water and infrastructure, environmental history, and the anthropology of nationhood and identity in Turkey, and provides methodological and intellectual tools for documenting the relationships between scientists, activists, and residents around conservation science. Drawing environmental history into its methodology, it emphasized processes of changing wetland landscapes that host conservation projects. The dissertation made an intervention in anthropological and STS work on the construction of the chemical and hydrological materiality of water, proposing that scholars analyze the sites and networks in and through water becomes matter of scientific and political concern. This dissertation project takes water not as a starting point but, rather, as the outcome of social processes, by asking wetland scientists, activists and residents, frame wetland-making as projects of livelihood, identity, and community-making.</p> <p>This research will benefit wetland experts, members of non-governmental civil society organizations, and residents and visitors of wetland areas by showing how the creation of natural wetland spaces is inherently social process. In the two case studies the research showed how conservation decisions are based on varied answers to the question &ldquo;who is the wetland for?&rdquo;, a question that implies different notions of participation, value, and temporality, in the sense of environing the deep history and the environmental futures of degrading wetland areas at different temporal scales. During the research, findings were shared with state officials, environmental NGOs, university experts in the two ares. The research also supported the work of wetland educators, engaging with urban and rural civil society in participatory and educational activities that use emerging forms of &ldquo;wetland culture&rdquo; to bridge the n...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Caterina scaramelli       User name: Scaramelli, Caterina  Organization Id: 0021782000  NSF ID: 000635259         Password: ciaociao87     Wetlands are at the forefront of national and international projects addressing water futures, climate change, biodiversity, development, and sustainability. With the global rise of the scientific and legal category of wetland in Europe and in the US, wetlands have become ecologies of value but also sites of struggle between state institutions, environmental NGOs, universities and civil society. This research tracksa regional history of wetland conservation in Turkey, one that is often left outside of analysis of conservation science, often located in Euroamerican context. This research examined the applications of wetland science and conservation strategies through two case studies in TurkeyÆs coastal wetlands, interrogating the biological, cultural, political, scientific, and economic interventions that produce wetlands as conservation ecologies. In contemporary Turkey, wetland science is entangled in the making of new ecological politics, concurrent with nationwide grassroots environmental movements and struggles for inclusion of diversity and for an expansion of rights in fact of what many perceive as increasing political centralization and authoritarianism. Debates over the implementation of wetland conservation measures gets mobilized in anti-authoritarian social movements, as well as in ongoing nationalist projects. The research focused on two Turkish coastal wetlands &mdash; the Gediz delta on the Aegean and the K?z?l?rmak delta on the Black Sea. The methodology was based on ethnographic fieldwork with environmental NGOs, wetland residents, Turkish and international experts, and state officials. It also drew on archival research on wetland science and conservation and on landscape histories.     The research developed new conversations between STS scholarship on field ecology, water and infrastructure, environmental history, and the anthropology of nationhood and identity in Turkey, and provides methodological and intellectual tools for documenting the relationships between scientists, activists, and residents around conservation science. Drawing environmental history into its methodology, it emphasized processes of changing wetland landscapes that host conservation projects. The dissertation made an intervention in anthropological and STS work on the construction of the chemical and hydrological materiality of water, proposing that scholars analyze the sites and networks in and through water becomes matter of scientific and political concern. This dissertation project takes water not as a starting point but, rather, as the outcome of social processes, by asking wetland scientists, activists and residents, frame wetland-making as projects of livelihood, identity, and community-making.  This research will benefit wetland experts, members of non-governmental civil society organizations, and residents and visitors of wetland areas by showing how the creation of natural wetland spaces is inherently social process. In the two case studies the research showed how conservation decisions are based on varied answers to the question "who is the wetland for?", a question that implies different notions of participation, value, and temporality, in the sense of environing the deep history and the environmental futures of degrading wetland areas at different temporal scales. During the research, findings were shared with state officials, environmental NGOs, university experts in the two ares. The research also supported the work of wetland educators, engaging with urban and rural civil society in participatory and educational activities that use emerging forms of "wetland culture" to bridge the natural and social sciences, fieldwork and art, political participation and knowledge production.       Last Modified: 11/29/2015       Submitted by: Caterina Scaramelli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
