<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a High Performance Computing Cluster for Research at a Predominantly Undergraduate Institution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>304745.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>304745</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is co-funded by EPSCoR program.&lt;br/&gt;This MRI project is to acquire a computing resource (35 compute nodes each having 2, 8 core Intel Xeon processors, with two nodes having GPU accelerators) that will enable a number of interesting and carefully detailed research efforts at University of Central Oklahoma. Research includes projects on particle transport, stochastic modeling, ecological modeling, bio-informatics and spread of disease. A number of well-developed broadening participation activities in education and research are also proposed.&lt;br/&gt;This project is leveraging the established network of 2- and 4-year colleges for collaborations and is facilitating  integration of research and education through training opportunities for students and high school teachers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1429702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evan</FirstName>
<LastName>Lemley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evan C Lemley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elemley@uco.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4059745473</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000357050</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gang</FirstName>
<LastName>Qian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gang Qian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gqian@uco.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4059745716</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Central Oklahoma</Name>
<CityName>Edmond</CityName>
<ZipCode>730345209</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4059742538</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 N University Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ADM 228]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049401458</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049401458</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Oklahoma]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730345209</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~304745</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Major Research Instrumentation award enabled the University of Central Oklahoma (UCO) to deploy it's first high performance computing (HPC) cluster, Buddy, named for the UCO mascot Buddy Broncho. Computational modeling or simulation (often performed on HPC clusters) has become the third branch of the scientific method; complementing theory and experimentation with the ability to perform large scale extrapolation and prediction. Access to HPC has become a near necessity for a research enterprise.</p> <p>Buddy has enabled significant progress in research in analysis and design of biomedical devices, geographic information systems for spatial ecology, improvement of dental implants, cooling of fuel cells, genome annotation and sequencing, models of fibrinolysis, pathway and gene selection for breast cancer data, simulation of aneurysms in human kidneys, and electric field guided cell deformation.</p> <p>The acquisition of Buddy by the Center for Research and Education in Interdisciplinary Computation (CREIC), which is within UCO's College of Mathematics and Science (CMS), has led to a transformation on the UCO campus in the following ways:</p> <ol> <li>Local access to HPC capabilities and broadening of scope of ongoing research projects.</li> <li>Development of training for use of HPC</li> <li>Technical staff upskilling in system administration of HPC clusters</li> <li>Production of research output of theses, conference, and journal papers.</li> <li>Outreach to high schools and other groups with exposure to HPC.</li> <li>Expansion of cyberinfrastructure on the UCO campus.</li> </ol> <p>Local access to HPC has had a clear impact on use of HPC. Several researchers that had hit dead ends using desktop computing in their research now are using Buddy to advance their research. The time commitment by UCO staff to get them up and running in terms of software installation, training in HPC, scripting support, and other elements was required to move from desktop to cluster computing. This access and support has led to a broadening of scope of research projects to include larger scale prediction and finer resolution modeling.</p> <p>UCO staff and student interns have created a number of help documents on Buddy access and use as well as performed deskside assistance to faculty and their students. UCO does not have a <em>research computing </em>office that served this role in the past, so the ability to train faculty and staff in HPC has become a new service performed by CREIC staff and students. This new role has enabled training and internship for students interested in HPC, which are in very high demand in the workforce.</p> <p>Prior to the award of this grant CREIC and CMS had two staff members and several students focused mostly on general information technology support. One staff member, a Coordinator of Technical Services, has taken a new role to support HPC. As a result of the needs of this award, this staff member has earned a Red Hat Certified Engineer certificate and a promotion, with specific HPC duties, to Manager of Technical Services for the CMS.</p> <p>This award has enabled poster and oral conference presentations and journal articles. Five journal or juried conference papers have been published with two more submitted and several more in preparation. Five master's theses have been completed that were heavily dependent on Buddy and several others where Buddy was used to complete the project. Seven conference papers have been published and over fifteen conference posters have been presented.</p> <p>There have been a number of outreach activities, these have included tours focused of Buddy and hands-on activities in which participants performed simulations using Buddy. The groups involved in these tours and other activities have included:</p> <ol> <li>Staff members of an Oklahoma Senator.</li> <li>High School students participating in an art/science program.</li> <li>Technology center students in a game design program.</li> <li>High school students in underserved STEM populations.</li> <li>Iraqi scholars participating in a Fulbright summer program.</li> </ol> <p>There has been a significant improvements to the UCO campus cyberinfrastructure due to this award. Prior to the start of this award an NSF award, with the University of Oklahoma serving as the lead institution, created a new high speed dedicated scientific network in Oklahoma called the Oklahoma Friction Free Network (OFFN). OFFN connects the state's HPC resources and allows researchers to exchange data without "friction." UCO has now been added to this network allowing Buddy to connect to other state HPC centers at 10 Gigabits per second.</p> <p>The other major cyberinfrastructure improvement is the construction of a new STEM teaching and research center on campus. Opening in Fall 2018, this new facility houses Buddy in an research computing-focused data center, with power, cooling, backup power, and space for Buddy and UCO's growing cyberinfrastructure needs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2018<br>      Modified by: Evan&nbsp;C&nbsp;Lemley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Major Research Instrumentation award enabled the University of Central Oklahoma (UCO) to deploy it's first high performance computing (HPC) cluster, Buddy, named for the UCO mascot Buddy Broncho. Computational modeling or simulation (often performed on HPC clusters) has become the third branch of the scientific method; complementing theory and experimentation with the ability to perform large scale extrapolation and prediction. Access to HPC has become a near necessity for a research enterprise.  Buddy has enabled significant progress in research in analysis and design of biomedical devices, geographic information systems for spatial ecology, improvement of dental implants, cooling of fuel cells, genome annotation and sequencing, models of fibrinolysis, pathway and gene selection for breast cancer data, simulation of aneurysms in human kidneys, and electric field guided cell deformation.  The acquisition of Buddy by the Center for Research and Education in Interdisciplinary Computation (CREIC), which is within UCO's College of Mathematics and Science (CMS), has led to a transformation on the UCO campus in the following ways:  Local access to HPC capabilities and broadening of scope of ongoing research projects. Development of training for use of HPC Technical staff upskilling in system administration of HPC clusters Production of research output of theses, conference, and journal papers. Outreach to high schools and other groups with exposure to HPC. Expansion of cyberinfrastructure on the UCO campus.   Local access to HPC has had a clear impact on use of HPC. Several researchers that had hit dead ends using desktop computing in their research now are using Buddy to advance their research. The time commitment by UCO staff to get them up and running in terms of software installation, training in HPC, scripting support, and other elements was required to move from desktop to cluster computing. This access and support has led to a broadening of scope of research projects to include larger scale prediction and finer resolution modeling.  UCO staff and student interns have created a number of help documents on Buddy access and use as well as performed deskside assistance to faculty and their students. UCO does not have a research computing office that served this role in the past, so the ability to train faculty and staff in HPC has become a new service performed by CREIC staff and students. This new role has enabled training and internship for students interested in HPC, which are in very high demand in the workforce.  Prior to the award of this grant CREIC and CMS had two staff members and several students focused mostly on general information technology support. One staff member, a Coordinator of Technical Services, has taken a new role to support HPC. As a result of the needs of this award, this staff member has earned a Red Hat Certified Engineer certificate and a promotion, with specific HPC duties, to Manager of Technical Services for the CMS.  This award has enabled poster and oral conference presentations and journal articles. Five journal or juried conference papers have been published with two more submitted and several more in preparation. Five master's theses have been completed that were heavily dependent on Buddy and several others where Buddy was used to complete the project. Seven conference papers have been published and over fifteen conference posters have been presented.  There have been a number of outreach activities, these have included tours focused of Buddy and hands-on activities in which participants performed simulations using Buddy. The groups involved in these tours and other activities have included:  Staff members of an Oklahoma Senator. High School students participating in an art/science program. Technology center students in a game design program. High school students in underserved STEM populations. Iraqi scholars participating in a Fulbright summer program.   There has been a significant improvements to the UCO campus cyberinfrastructure due to this award. Prior to the start of this award an NSF award, with the University of Oklahoma serving as the lead institution, created a new high speed dedicated scientific network in Oklahoma called the Oklahoma Friction Free Network (OFFN). OFFN connects the state's HPC resources and allows researchers to exchange data without "friction." UCO has now been added to this network allowing Buddy to connect to other state HPC centers at 10 Gigabits per second.  The other major cyberinfrastructure improvement is the construction of a new STEM teaching and research center on campus. Opening in Fall 2018, this new facility houses Buddy in an research computing-focused data center, with power, cooling, backup power, and space for Buddy and UCO's growing cyberinfrastructure needs.             Last Modified: 11/14/2018       Submitted by: Evan C Lemley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
