<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an Integrated Scanning Probe - Raman Microscope</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>418011.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>418011</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanne Culbertson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jculbert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924602</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports the acquisition of a combined scanning probe-Raman microscope, which provides non-destructive imaging of materials structure, physical properties and molecular composition.  This instrumentation is critical to fundamental research in engineering, materials science, physics, chemistry and other fields, enabling advances ranging from the design of new materials and devices to the identification of the origins of human disease.  The combined SP-Raman microscope will enable high-resolution Raman techniques and will remedy a deficiency in the research and scientific training infrastructure at the State University of New York at Binghamton, which does not have a Raman facility. The proposed instrument will support fundamental research and education efforts on small-scale systems, materials, energy, and biomedical science. The fundamental knowledge from these projects will advance solar energy applications and next generation manufacturing and materials design and will help to broaden the participation of female and underrepresented groups in research. A new course on scanning probe and Raman microscopy will be developed for students in the University?s engineering and science programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A combined scanning probe-Raman microscope is a state-of-the-art research tool used to characterize structural, physical and chemical properties of materials at sub-micron scales. The sharp scanning probe synergistically enables high-resolution Raman techniques such as TERS (tip-enhanced Raman spectroscopy), which are essential for the proposed research plan. The research activities enabled by this instrumentation bring together 15 faculty members from the Mechanical Engineering, Bioengineering, Electrical and Computer Engineering, Physics and Chemistry Departments and form the basis for collaborative research projects and mentoring for junior faculty.  This instrumentation will also be shared with industry and other academic institutions for their research and development through the University?s Small-Scale Systems Integration and Packing Center (S3IP). The new knowledge gained through this research will have a transformative impact on advancing fundamental science and engineering and enabling new technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1429176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Junghyun</FirstName>
<LastName>Cho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Junghyun Cho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jcho@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077772897</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000296496</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Changhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Ke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Changhong Ke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cke@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077774782</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499182</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Chiarot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Chiarot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pchiarot@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077773208</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amber</FirstName>
<LastName>Doiron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amber L Doiron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amber.doiron@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8026563382</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Mativetsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Mativetsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmativet@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000642804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 6000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090189965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Binghamton]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~418011</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>MRI award, CMMI1429176, supports the acquisition of an Integrated Scanning Probe-Raman Microscope which has been delivered and installed in the Engineering and Science Building at the State University of New York at Binghamton in 2015, and is now fully functional and accessible. The instrument comprises a high resolution atomic force microscope from NT-MDT and a Renishaw inVia Raman spectrometer, and is capable of performing high resolution Raman measurements. The usage of the instrument has been increasing steadily and reached 80 hr/week in summer 2017. This microscope has greatly enhanced the infrastructure for our research and education programs. The developed learning modules based on the research activities supported by this instruments have been integrated into our traditional course offerings as well as recently developed courses in micro and nanotechnology. This instrument provides excellent scientific training and research opportunities to our undergraduate and graduate students and helps the campus attract students from female and underrepresented groups. This instrument also benefits other academic and industrial users in the greater Binghamton area. The instrument supports a number of research projects in the areas of small scale systems, materials, energy, and biomedical systems.<em> </em>The usage of the instrument has led to ten published peer-reviewed journal articles.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Changhong&nbsp;Ke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ MRI award, CMMI1429176, supports the acquisition of an Integrated Scanning Probe-Raman Microscope which has been delivered and installed in the Engineering and Science Building at the State University of New York at Binghamton in 2015, and is now fully functional and accessible. The instrument comprises a high resolution atomic force microscope from NT-MDT and a Renishaw inVia Raman spectrometer, and is capable of performing high resolution Raman measurements. The usage of the instrument has been increasing steadily and reached 80 hr/week in summer 2017. This microscope has greatly enhanced the infrastructure for our research and education programs. The developed learning modules based on the research activities supported by this instruments have been integrated into our traditional course offerings as well as recently developed courses in micro and nanotechnology. This instrument provides excellent scientific training and research opportunities to our undergraduate and graduate students and helps the campus attract students from female and underrepresented groups. This instrument also benefits other academic and industrial users in the greater Binghamton area. The instrument supports a number of research projects in the areas of small scale systems, materials, energy, and biomedical systems. The usage of the instrument has led to ten published peer-reviewed journal articles.       Last Modified: 11/29/2017       Submitted by: Changhong Ke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
