<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an Integrated Dynamic Nuclear Polarization (DNP) Solid-State NMR Instrument with Unprecedented Sensitivity for Studies of Functional Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1171588.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1171588</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical:   Recently developed dynamic nuclear polarization (DNP) nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy instrumentation provides new opportunities to measure the compositions and structures of technologically important solid-state materials at the level of their atoms. Such capabilities yield new insights that are central to the design, development, and engineering of novel solid-state materials with promise for far-reaching societal or industrial impacts. Specific materials and applications under investigation include high-performance and low-carbon-footprint cements, catalysts for converting biofuels and natural gas to high-value liquid products, organic photovoltaic thin films and nanoscale semiconductors for solar energy conversion, battery and fuel cell materials for electrochemical energy generation and storage, and bio-inorganic solids for sustainable structural materials. Use and understanding of state-of-the-art DNP-NMR instrumentation by students contribute to their education and training across the chemical, physical, materials, and biological sciences. The analyses and applications provide interdisciplinary training that prepares students to address continually-changing energy, environmental, and other needs of society in the broadest of terms. Independent or collaborative access to the integrated DNP-NMR spectrometer by researchers at other regional, national, and international universities extend user base and benefits of the instrument beyond UCSB, in particular to regional partner groups at UC Berkeley, UC Irvine, UCLA, UC Riverside, and Cal Poly. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical:  The DNP-NMR instrumentation provides an unprecedented combination of both high signal sensitivity and high spectral resolution for measuring molecular surface species that govern the functions of materials for a broad range of energy, structural, and environmental applications. Among the critical problems and challenges to improving the properties of such materials is the insufficient sensitivity of conventional methods, including NMR, especially for the detection of dilute or surface species. Integrated DNP-NMR measurements provide dramatic NMR signal enhancements of 2 orders of magnitude, resulting in time savings of up to 4 orders of magnitude over that achievable with previous state-of-the-art capabilities. The DNP-NMR instrument represents a breakthrough in molecular characterization that opens new opportunities to characterize and understand heterogeneous functional solids. The scope and goals of the research notably include materials with industrially relevant compositions, synthesized under industrially relevant conditions, and/or materials with low-surface areas or dilute or low-natural abundance species (e.g., 13C, 15N, 29Si, 77Se). The resulting DNP-NMR spectra and analyses are without precedent in the technical literature and enable, for the first time, the molecular-level characterization of complicated compositions and structures of material surfaces that till now have been entirely infeasible by conventional high-field NMR spectroscopy. Such solid-state DNP-NMR capabilities are expected to enable broad and transformative advancements in the materials and chemical sciences and become a standard for molecular characterization of complicated heterogeneous materials, whose surface functionalities are crucial to their properties, but whose molecular origins have previously been exceedingly challenging to establish.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1429710</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
<LastName>Chmelka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bradley F Chmelka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bradc@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058933673</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000422415</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
<LastName>Dahlquist</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frederick W Dahlquist</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dahlquist@chem.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058935326</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000302440</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Hawker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig J Hawker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hawker@mrl.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058937161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000168032</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Song-I</FirstName>
<LastName>Han</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Song-I Han</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>songi@chem.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058934858</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490309</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Regents of the Unversity of California]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931065080</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Chemical Engineering]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1171588</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The new state-of-the-art instrument integrates dynamic-nculear-polarization (DNP) capabilities with solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy to provide an unprecedented combination of high NMR signal sensitivity (1-2 orders of magnitude improvement over conventional NMR methods) and high spectral resolution. These capabilities represent a breakthrough in atomic-level characterization of complicated heterogeneous solids that are opening transformative opportunities to obtain new insights on novel functional materials.</p> <p>Installation of the new DNP-NMR instrument in the Central Facilities of the NSF-supported Materials Research Laboratory at UCSB was completed in January 2016. The major scientific goals fo the project have been to achieve atomic-level characterization of complicated compositions and structures of material surfaces that have prevously been infeasible to acquire&nbsp;by conventional high-field NMR spectroscopy. The new 400 MHz DNP-NMR instrument, shown in Figure 1, includes a gyrotron magnet that produces microwaves at 263 GHz, a microwave waveguide, a temperature control system and magic-angle-spinning NMR probehead for low-temperature operation at ca. 90 K. (The 9.4 Tesla superconduction magnet and NMR spectrometer console were previously available in the laboratory.)</p> <p>More than 14 diverse scientific projects have till now benefited from access to the new DNP-NMR instrumentation, which have already led to 2 noteworthy publications:</p> <p>Berkson, Chmelka, et al., "Non-topotactic transformation of silicate nanolayers into mesostructured MFI zeolite frameworks during crystallization," <em>Angew. Chem</em>., <em>56</em>, 5164-5169 (2017).</p> <p>Smeets, Berkson, Chmelka, et al., "Well-defined silanols in the structures of the calcined zeolite SSZ-70: new understanding of a successful catalytic material," <em>J. Am. Chem. Soc</em>., web-published (2017).</p> <p>In both of these publications, the high sensitivity provided by DNP-NMR enabled <sup>29</sup>Si sites at natural abundance (4.7%) to be detected and their through-covalent-bond <sup>29</sup>Si-O-<sup>29</sup>Si signals resolved and correlated in 2D NMR spectra. This allowed long-standing questions concerning fundamental crystallization mechanisms of technologically important zeolite catalysts to be solved. For example, Figure 2 shows correlated 2D NMR and electron microscopy results, which in combination with X-ray diffraction, provide for the first time, direct and unambiguous evidence for non-topotactic crystallization of a zeolite framework in the process of forming.</p> <p>In addition to the two papers already published, numerous other manuscripts are in preparation and will soon be submitted. In addition, more than 30 invited presentations have been made by UCSB students, the PIs, and post-doctoral researchers at national and international scientific conferences and seminars that included experimental results from the DNP-NMR instrumentation and which acknowledged this NSF funding. The availability of the DNP-NMR instrumentation has provided a tremendous opportunity for graduate students and post-doctoral researchers to be trained in this new state-of-the-art methodology, as well as its direct use for technologically important applications.</p> <p>DNP-enhanced NMR measurements and analyses are enabling the characterization of solid-state materials and comositions closer to their practical industrially relevant formulations than previously possible. Examples include heterogeneous catalysts, cementious and structural materials, electrochemical materials, separation resins for environmental applications, etc. It is expected that new molecular-design criteria will result or high-performance or low-CO<sub>2</sub>-footprint cements, biominerals, organic photovoltaic films, dilute surface moieties in nanoscale semiconductors, electrochemical materials, biomaterials, etc.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Bradley&nbsp;F&nbsp;Chmelka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1429710/1429710_10333703_1512023233045_Figure1,NSFAward1429710,ProjectOutcomes,Chmelka,Han,2017-11-29--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1429710/1429710_10333703_1512023233045_Figure1,NSFAward1429710,ProjectOutcomes,Chmelka,Han,2017-11-29--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UCSB DNP-NMR spectrometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1429710/1429710_10333703_1512023233045_Figure1,NSFAward1429710,ProjectOutcomes,Chmelka,Han,2017-11-29--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UCSB DNP-NMR spectrometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: New dynamic-nuclear-polarization (DNP) nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer instrumentation in the Central Facilities of the UCSB Materials Research Laboratory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brad Chmelka</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bradley&nbsp;F&nbsp;Chmelka</div> <div class="imageTitle">UCSB DNP-NMR spectrometer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1429710/1429710_10333703_1512023346975_Figure2,NSFFinalReport,DNP-NMRspectrometer,2017-11-29--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1429710/1429710_10333703_1512023346975_Figure2,NSFFinalReport,DNP-NMRspectrometer,2017-11-29--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mesostructured zeolite crystallization"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1429710/1429710_10333703_1512023346975_Figure2,NSFFinalReport,DNP-NMRspectrometer,2017-11-29--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mesostructured zeolite crystallization"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. (a) Solid-state 2D DNP-NMR 29Si{29Si} correlation spectrum and (b) TEM image of the intermediate product of crystallizing mesostructured MFI zeolite nanosheets, shown schematically in (c). Pairs of correlated signals are indicated by the solid blue, red, and green anti-diagonal lines.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brad Chmelka</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bradley&nbsp;F&nbsp;Chmelka</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mesostructured zeolite crystallization</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The new state-of-the-art instrument integrates dynamic-nculear-polarization (DNP) capabilities with solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy to provide an unprecedented combination of high NMR signal sensitivity (1-2 orders of magnitude improvement over conventional NMR methods) and high spectral resolution. These capabilities represent a breakthrough in atomic-level characterization of complicated heterogeneous solids that are opening transformative opportunities to obtain new insights on novel functional materials.  Installation of the new DNP-NMR instrument in the Central Facilities of the NSF-supported Materials Research Laboratory at UCSB was completed in January 2016. The major scientific goals fo the project have been to achieve atomic-level characterization of complicated compositions and structures of material surfaces that have prevously been infeasible to acquire by conventional high-field NMR spectroscopy. The new 400 MHz DNP-NMR instrument, shown in Figure 1, includes a gyrotron magnet that produces microwaves at 263 GHz, a microwave waveguide, a temperature control system and magic-angle-spinning NMR probehead for low-temperature operation at ca. 90 K. (The 9.4 Tesla superconduction magnet and NMR spectrometer console were previously available in the laboratory.)  More than 14 diverse scientific projects have till now benefited from access to the new DNP-NMR instrumentation, which have already led to 2 noteworthy publications:  Berkson, Chmelka, et al., "Non-topotactic transformation of silicate nanolayers into mesostructured MFI zeolite frameworks during crystallization," Angew. Chem., 56, 5164-5169 (2017).  Smeets, Berkson, Chmelka, et al., "Well-defined silanols in the structures of the calcined zeolite SSZ-70: new understanding of a successful catalytic material," J. Am. Chem. Soc., web-published (2017).  In both of these publications, the high sensitivity provided by DNP-NMR enabled 29Si sites at natural abundance (4.7%) to be detected and their through-covalent-bond 29Si-O-29Si signals resolved and correlated in 2D NMR spectra. This allowed long-standing questions concerning fundamental crystallization mechanisms of technologically important zeolite catalysts to be solved. For example, Figure 2 shows correlated 2D NMR and electron microscopy results, which in combination with X-ray diffraction, provide for the first time, direct and unambiguous evidence for non-topotactic crystallization of a zeolite framework in the process of forming.  In addition to the two papers already published, numerous other manuscripts are in preparation and will soon be submitted. In addition, more than 30 invited presentations have been made by UCSB students, the PIs, and post-doctoral researchers at national and international scientific conferences and seminars that included experimental results from the DNP-NMR instrumentation and which acknowledged this NSF funding. The availability of the DNP-NMR instrumentation has provided a tremendous opportunity for graduate students and post-doctoral researchers to be trained in this new state-of-the-art methodology, as well as its direct use for technologically important applications.  DNP-enhanced NMR measurements and analyses are enabling the characterization of solid-state materials and comositions closer to their practical industrially relevant formulations than previously possible. Examples include heterogeneous catalysts, cementious and structural materials, electrochemical materials, separation resins for environmental applications, etc. It is expected that new molecular-design criteria will result or high-performance or low-CO2-footprint cements, biominerals, organic photovoltaic films, dilute surface moieties in nanoscale semiconductors, electrochemical materials, biomaterials, etc.       Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Bradley F Chmelka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
