<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cultural And Biological Approaches To Domestic Animal Management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>279634.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>279634</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Researchers seek to understand how humans and animals adapt to changing environmental conditions and the roles they play in creating new environments. Archaeology is particularly well suited to provide relevant information on long-term environmental change and its effects on humans because it can identify the interplay between humans, animals, and landscapes over extended periods of time. Within this context this project will characterize the cultural, biological, and ecological impacts of the introduction of domesticated animals into Europe. The effects of small-scale introductions of domestic animals (sheep, goats, cattle, and pigs) into biodiverse regions are not well studied. This project focuses on the first directed and intentional animal introductions into the Balkans, a European Union biodiversity hotspot, ca. 8,000 years ago. By studying the effects of region's earliest farmers on local plant and animal communities, in particular their domestic animal management strategies, the investigators will establish baseline data on the environmental effects of deliberate mammal introductions as a comparative dataset for other regions. The results will help guide modern conservation efforts in regions that have witnessed decades, centuries, or millennia of herding activity, and will contribute relevant information to understanding the environmental and cultural impacts of domesticated animals in non-industrialized societies. This project will train undergraduate and graduate students in generating and using archaeological data to address important ecological questions and will expand the research capacities of multiple institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ecological and cultural underpinnings of the introduction of domesticated animals to Europe ca. 8000 years ago are still poorly understood. This project focuses on biological and cultural markers of domestic animal management (cattle, sheep, goats, pigs) by studying animal bones, pottery, soil, and botanical (seeds and wood charcoal) samples from archaeological sites on the central Dalmatian coast of Croatia as a case study for this research. Data generated through this research include stable isotopic analyses, Bayesian radiocarbon chronologies, functional morphology, ceramic residue analyses, botanical studies, and animal population dynamics, and will provide multiple lines of evidence to characterize animal management practices during this period. Results will identify the role of milk in early farming; the antiquity of historically important patterns of animal transhumance and environmental degradation; and the relative fragility or resilience of local ecosystems. Multiple lines of evidence will characterize early European domesticated animal use and further our understanding of human-animal relationships and their impacts on local ecosystems in general. Results will be published in international publications and through lectures, presentations, and exhibits to public audiences in the US and Croatia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1430823</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas J Kennett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kennett@anth.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8149542445</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000109494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>McClure</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah McClure</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcclure@anth.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058933477</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~279634</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examined the short- and long-term effects of sheep, goat, and cattle herding on the Dalmatian coast of Croatia. This is a region of the world where agriculture has been practiced for over 8000 years and, despite the rise and fall of different societies and climate change, agriculture and animal herding remained a sustainable practice. Research at the earliest farming villages in the area, dating to the Neolithic period (8000-6500 years ago), focused on reconstructing domestic animal management practices through time using a range of archaeological methods and tools. Identification of ancient bones and teeth from village trash pits resulted in reconstructing herding history. We found that the very first farmers in the Neolithic (8000 years ago) relied mostly on sheep and goats and only kept a few cattle. They also hunted local deer from forests surrounding their villages. Through time, the proportion of cattle increased, and by 6500 years ago, cattle and sheep and goats were equally represented on farms. Farmers also started keeping more pigs.</p> <p>Geochemical techniques known as stable isotope analysis allowed us to identify to what extent animals were moving around the landscape. We found that the earliest farmers kept animals close to home, while in the Middle Neolithic (about 7200 years ago), some shepherds began taking flocks into the high elevation mountains for summer pasture. It is at this time that we also see a number of other changes. First, we identified that farmers were creating multiple birthing seasons, with some animals born in early spring and others in the early summer. Together with evidence for milk and cheese production in residues on pottery used for serving and storing food, the animal data indicate a focus on dairy products and new ways to manage domestic animal herds. This evidence also documents the earliest known cheese production in the Mediterranean region. Second, changes in stone tool technologies and plants such as wheat and barley also indicate changes in how people were farming the land, using new harvesting techniques and manure-based fertilizers on their fields. Finally, farming strategies shifted again in the Late Neolithic (6500 years ago). Dairying continued to be important based on multiple birthing seasons of sheep and goats, and we see an increase in cattle in farming villages, but there is no evidence for moving flocks across the landscape and into higher elevation. It appears that farmers continued some animal management techniques, but abandoned others that were either not as effective or perhaps less suited to the landscape of the period.</p> <p>We found that the Middle Neolithic (7200 years ago) was a period of multiple changes in farming practices. One of the sites we worked on, Kriva&#269;e, was particularly important because we identified in this project that it was located by a lake that no longer exists today. Using geological techniques such as radiocarbon dating, mineralogy, sediment, and microfossil analyses, we discovered that this freshwater lake existed from 12,000-4,000 years ago, was up to 6 meters (18 feet) deep, likely attracted migrating birds and contained fish, and was a major feature of the landscape during the Neolithic period when farming was introduced. We also identified another ancient lake in the next valley, and together, these discoveries are changing the way we see both the ancient and modern landscapes. In the future we will be able to generate detailed information on the past environment through pollen analysis together with the information on ancient lakeside villages. This will allow us to investigate local cultural adaptations to changing climatic and environmental conditions, flooding and contraction of lakes, and movements of people and goods on the landscape.</p> <p>Today this region is internationally recognized as a biodiversity hotspot, yet little is known about its ecological history. Our research on the environmental effects of early farming has direct relevance for conservation initiatives because it examines the way the environment, dominated by livestock and agricultural fields, responded to changes in human societies and climate shifts in the past. This kind of information is needed to address larger questions about the timing and nature of the spread of agriculture into Europe and the sustainability of these farming practices in the past and into the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Mcclure</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1430823/1430823_10325329_1600837237707_sheepgoatsostravica--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1430823/1430823_10325329_1600837237707_sheepgoatsostravica--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sheep and goat grazing in ancient lake bed"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1430823/1430823_10325329_1600837237707_sheepgoatsostravica--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sheep and goat grazing in ancient lake bed"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sheep and goats grazing in Ostrovica paleolake bed, now open grassland used for grazing and hay production</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah McClure</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;Mcclure</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sheep and goat grazing in ancient lake bed</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1430823/1430823_10325329_1600837065605_KrivaceArrowPaleolakeFlooded--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1430823/1430823_10325329_1600837065605_KrivaceArrowPaleolakeFlooded--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ostrovica Valley"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1430823/1430823_10325329_1600837065605_KrivaceArrowPaleolakeFlooded--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ostrovica Valley"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Approximate location of Krivace with Ostrovica valley in the background. Winter rains create flooded area in part of the ancient lake basin</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nicholas Triozzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;Mcclure</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ostrovica Valley</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examined the short- and long-term effects of sheep, goat, and cattle herding on the Dalmatian coast of Croatia. This is a region of the world where agriculture has been practiced for over 8000 years and, despite the rise and fall of different societies and climate change, agriculture and animal herding remained a sustainable practice. Research at the earliest farming villages in the area, dating to the Neolithic period (8000-6500 years ago), focused on reconstructing domestic animal management practices through time using a range of archaeological methods and tools. Identification of ancient bones and teeth from village trash pits resulted in reconstructing herding history. We found that the very first farmers in the Neolithic (8000 years ago) relied mostly on sheep and goats and only kept a few cattle. They also hunted local deer from forests surrounding their villages. Through time, the proportion of cattle increased, and by 6500 years ago, cattle and sheep and goats were equally represented on farms. Farmers also started keeping more pigs.  Geochemical techniques known as stable isotope analysis allowed us to identify to what extent animals were moving around the landscape. We found that the earliest farmers kept animals close to home, while in the Middle Neolithic (about 7200 years ago), some shepherds began taking flocks into the high elevation mountains for summer pasture. It is at this time that we also see a number of other changes. First, we identified that farmers were creating multiple birthing seasons, with some animals born in early spring and others in the early summer. Together with evidence for milk and cheese production in residues on pottery used for serving and storing food, the animal data indicate a focus on dairy products and new ways to manage domestic animal herds. This evidence also documents the earliest known cheese production in the Mediterranean region. Second, changes in stone tool technologies and plants such as wheat and barley also indicate changes in how people were farming the land, using new harvesting techniques and manure-based fertilizers on their fields. Finally, farming strategies shifted again in the Late Neolithic (6500 years ago). Dairying continued to be important based on multiple birthing seasons of sheep and goats, and we see an increase in cattle in farming villages, but there is no evidence for moving flocks across the landscape and into higher elevation. It appears that farmers continued some animal management techniques, but abandoned others that were either not as effective or perhaps less suited to the landscape of the period.  We found that the Middle Neolithic (7200 years ago) was a period of multiple changes in farming practices. One of the sites we worked on, Kriva&#269;e, was particularly important because we identified in this project that it was located by a lake that no longer exists today. Using geological techniques such as radiocarbon dating, mineralogy, sediment, and microfossil analyses, we discovered that this freshwater lake existed from 12,000-4,000 years ago, was up to 6 meters (18 feet) deep, likely attracted migrating birds and contained fish, and was a major feature of the landscape during the Neolithic period when farming was introduced. We also identified another ancient lake in the next valley, and together, these discoveries are changing the way we see both the ancient and modern landscapes. In the future we will be able to generate detailed information on the past environment through pollen analysis together with the information on ancient lakeside villages. This will allow us to investigate local cultural adaptations to changing climatic and environmental conditions, flooding and contraction of lakes, and movements of people and goods on the landscape.  Today this region is internationally recognized as a biodiversity hotspot, yet little is known about its ecological history. Our research on the environmental effects of early farming has direct relevance for conservation initiatives because it examines the way the environment, dominated by livestock and agricultural fields, responded to changes in human societies and climate shifts in the past. This kind of information is needed to address larger questions about the timing and nature of the spread of agriculture into Europe and the sustainability of these farming practices in the past and into the future.          Last Modified: 09/23/2020       Submitted by: Sarah Mcclure]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
