<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PLDI 2014 Travel Support</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anindya Banerjee</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abanerje@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides student travel support for the 35th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI 2014) that will be held from June 9-13, 2014, in Edinburgh, Scotland. PLDI is the top technical forum for the presentation of new and exciting advances in programming languages and compiler research. The symposium covers a wide range of topics in the field, including: Language designs and extensions; Static and dynamic analysis of programs, Domain-specific languages and tools; Type systems and program logics; Program transformation and optimization; Checking or improving the security or correctness of programs; Memory management; Parallelism, both implicit and explicit; Performance analysis, evaluation, and tools; Novel programming models; Debugging techniques and tools; Program understanding; Interaction of compilers/runtimes with underlying systems; Program synthesis. Students will be able to attend all events associated with the conference, and a rich set of workshops and tutorials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF support ensures participation of US students while paying attention to underrepresented groups. To broaden participation, the grant is intended specifically to increase the numbers of students who cannot otherwise attend, that is, students who do not have any financial support whatsoever, e.g., from their advisors, departments, universities. The broader impacts include building international community and cooperation in the research areas of the conference, and enhancing education of students with exposure to and interaction with leading-edge research and researchers. This award will therefore help train the next generation of language designers, compiler implementers and systems researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1430129</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Santosh</FirstName>
<LastName>Nagarakatte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Santosh Nagarakatte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>santosh.nagarakatte@rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484458407</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630570</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548072</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Frelinghuysen Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7943</Code>
<Text>PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ACM Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) is the top technical forum for the presentation of new and exciting advances in programming languages and compiler research. The symposium covers a wide range of topics, including language design and novel programming models, static and dynamic analysis, domain-specific languages and tools, type systems and program logics, program transformation and optimization, checking or improving the security or correctness of programs, memory management, parallelism, debugging, program understanding, and program synthesis.</p> <p><br />PLDI 2014 and co-located events were held in Edinburgh, UK from June 9 to June 13, 2014. &nbsp;The lead organizers of PLDI'14 were Professor Michael O'Boyle of University of Edinburgh (general chair) and Professor Keshav Pingali of University of Texas Austin (program chair). &nbsp;NSF travel grants were administered by Santosh Nagarakatte, Assistant Professor at Rutgers University, New Brunswick &nbsp;who served as the sponsorship chair. The full organizing committees and detailed programs (for both conferences and satellite events) are available online at <a href="http://conferences.inf.ed.ac.uk/pldi2014/">http://conferences.inf.ed.ac.uk/pldi2014/</a>.&nbsp;The 2014 edition PLDI received 287 submissions; 52 paperswere accepted, yielding an acceptance rate of 18.1%.<br /><br /><strong>Travel Grant Details</strong><br /><br />The NSF provided $20,000 in travel support. &nbsp;ACM, via SIGPLAN( Special Interest Group on Programming Languages) provided additional travel support. NSF funds supported only students from US universities. &nbsp;The general strategy was to prioritize funding for women, underrepresented minorities, and student authors. All in all 18 students from US universities were funded.<br /><br />To manage the application process, we used a single application portal, PAC (see <a href="http://www.sigplan.org/PAC.htm">http://www.sigplan.org/PAC.htm</a>). The website was linked from the main PLDI website and advertised during the outreach effort. All applications were reviewed by PI Santosh Nagarakatte of Rutgers University and the two SIGPLAN PAC representatives, Julia Lawall and Crista Lopes.<br />Our goal was to fundamentally enhance the visibility of ComputerResearch, and to help create a more diverse community of students in this critical research area. &nbsp;Research has continually shown that STEM fields in general, and CS in particular, have lower rates of participation by women and minorities.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>This proposal had two primary direct benefits. First, the PLDI conference was strengthened as a result of the greater attendance that this travel support has enabled. Second, as per the numerous testimonials at <a href="http://students-pldi.blogspot.com/">http://students-pldi.blogspot.com/</a>, those students receiving travel support personally benefit from the opportunity to interact with peers and experts, as well as establish connections that will help their professional careers.&nbsp;Out of 18 awardees, 2 were underrepresented minority groups. The details of the awardees is given below:<br /><br /></p> <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="436"> <!--StartFragment--> <colgroup><col width="348"></col> <col width="88"></col> </colgroup>  <tbody> <tr height="28"> <td width="348" height="28">&nbsp;</td> <td class="xl24" width="88" align="right">&nbsp;actual reimbursement</td> </tr> <tr height="14"> <td height="14">(1) Ben Greenman- blg59@cornell.edu</td> <td class="xl25" align="right">&nbsp;$1,300.00</td> </tr> <tr height="14"> <td height="14">(2) Samuel Blackshear- samuel.blackshear@colorado.edu</td> <td class="xl25" align="right">&nbsp;$193.49</td> </tr> <tr height="14"> <td height="14">(3) Justin Pombrio - zallambo@gmail.com</td> <td class="xl25" align="right">&nbsp;$1,050.00</td> </tr> <tr heigh...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ACM Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) is the top technical forum for the presentation of new and exciting advances in programming languages and compiler research. The symposium covers a wide range of topics, including language design and novel programming models, static and dynamic analysis, domain-specific languages and tools, type systems and program logics, program transformation and optimization, checking or improving the security or correctness of programs, memory management, parallelism, debugging, program understanding, and program synthesis.   PLDI 2014 and co-located events were held in Edinburgh, UK from June 9 to June 13, 2014.  The lead organizers of PLDI'14 were Professor Michael O'Boyle of University of Edinburgh (general chair) and Professor Keshav Pingali of University of Texas Austin (program chair).  NSF travel grants were administered by Santosh Nagarakatte, Assistant Professor at Rutgers University, New Brunswick  who served as the sponsorship chair. The full organizing committees and detailed programs (for both conferences and satellite events) are available online at http://conferences.inf.ed.ac.uk/pldi2014/. The 2014 edition PLDI received 287 submissions; 52 paperswere accepted, yielding an acceptance rate of 18.1%.  Travel Grant Details  The NSF provided $20,000 in travel support.  ACM, via SIGPLAN( Special Interest Group on Programming Languages) provided additional travel support. NSF funds supported only students from US universities.  The general strategy was to prioritize funding for women, underrepresented minorities, and student authors. All in all 18 students from US universities were funded.  To manage the application process, we used a single application portal, PAC (see http://www.sigplan.org/PAC.htm). The website was linked from the main PLDI website and advertised during the outreach effort. All applications were reviewed by PI Santosh Nagarakatte of Rutgers University and the two SIGPLAN PAC representatives, Julia Lawall and Crista Lopes. Our goal was to fundamentally enhance the visibility of ComputerResearch, and to help create a more diverse community of students in this critical research area.  Research has continually shown that STEM fields in general, and CS in particular, have lower rates of participation by women and minorities.  Broader Impacts  This proposal had two primary direct benefits. First, the PLDI conference was strengthened as a result of the greater attendance that this travel support has enabled. Second, as per the numerous testimonials at http://students-pldi.blogspot.com/, those students receiving travel support personally benefit from the opportunity to interact with peers and experts, as well as establish connections that will help their professional careers. Out of 18 awardees, 2 were underrepresented minority groups. The details of the awardees is given below:              actual reimbursement   (1) Ben Greenman- blg59@cornell.edu  $1,300.00   (2) Samuel Blackshear- samuel.blackshear@colorado.edu  $193.49   (3) Justin Pombrio - zallambo@gmail.com  $1,050.00   (4) Xin Zhang -  xin.zhang@gatech.edu  $1,000.00   (5) Vineeth Kashyap- vineeth@cs.ucsb.edu  $1,300.00   (6) Khanh Nguyen - khanhtn1@uci.edu     (7) Jonathan Shidal - shidalj@wustl.edu  $1,300.00   (8) Shams Imam -  shams@rice.edu  $1,000.00   (9) Loris D'Antoni-  lorisdan@cis.upenn.edu  $1,300.00   (10) Jacob Brock -  jbrock@cs.rochester.edu  $1,300.00   (11) Subrata Mitra - mitra4@purdue.edu  $967.85   (12) Rishi Surendran-  rishi@rice.edu  $1,300.00   (13) Vu le - vmle@ucdavis.edu  $1,170.00   (14) zvonimir.pavlinovic-  zvonimir.pavlinovic@gmail.com  $1,300.00   (15) Emma Tosch - etosch@cs.umass.edu  $1,300.00   (16) Michal Carbin - mcarbin@csail.mit.edu  $1,300.00   (17) Jesse Huang -  jh3141@gmail.com  $630.00   (18) Adrian Sampson - asampson@cs.washington.edu  $1,300.00      $19,011.34        To increase PLDI visibility and foster interaction among the grant awar...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
