<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cognitive and neurocognitive individual differences in native and nonnative language processing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>391376.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>407876</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betty Tuller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>btuller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927238</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>High proficiency in multiple languages provides economic advantages, as linguistic flexibility in business and government discourse facilitates communication in an increasingly globalized world. However, the ability to reach high levels of proficiency and fluency in a second language (L2) during adulthood is notoriously variable, with individuals showing marked differences in the rate of L2 acquisition and the eventual level of proficiency. A complete understanding of the roots and implications of these differences - including documenting individual differences in the brain mechanisms supporting nonnative language comprehension and learning - is crucial for the development of targeted language instruction methods and interventions. Such targeted interventions can lead to tangible gains in language learning outcomes. Moreover, emerging research now shows that even monolinguals show systematic, qualitative individual differences in the neural mechanisms responsible for language comprehension. However, as with L2 learning, the causes and consequences of these differences are poorly understood.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will use a multidimensional approach to investigate individual differences in language comprehension and language learning across several populations: monolinguals, classroom-instructed L2 learners of Spanish, and Spanish-English bilinguals in the United States. The research will combine novel behavioral and brain-based measures of language processing, cognitive executive functions, and cortical organization for language. The investigators will link these with measures of language proficiency and language experience to isolate the cognitive, neural, linguistic, and experiential factors related to differences in how individuals build interpretations during the course of sentence comprehension. In particular, electroencephalographic recordings during language comprehension and executive processing will allow the investigators to document how these processes unfold in the brain millisecond-by-millisecond. Novel multivariate statistical models will be used to identify factors related to how different individuals make use of semantic and grammatical cues during reading. The aim is to elucidate the cognitive, neural, and linguistic bases of individual differences in language learning and language comprehension, and tie them closely to a neurobiological model of language. As such, the findings will have clear and practical implications for language training.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1431324</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Silvina</FirstName>
<LastName>Montrul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Silvina A Montrul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>montrul@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173338279</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darren</FirstName>
<LastName>Tanner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darren Tanner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dstanner@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000665317</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1397</Code>
<Text>Cross-Directorate  Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action &amp; Cognition</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~391376</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~6500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Second language learning is notoriously difficult, and there is widely-acknowledged inter-individual variability in the rate and ultimate success of learning. Much less is known, however, about how monolingual speakers differ from one other when processing their native language, or how the nature of individual variability may be similar or different among monolingual, bilingual, and adult language learner populations. This project was among the first to systematically investigate at large scale what cognitive, experiential, and linguistic factors are related to inter-individual variability in how the brain responds to linguistic information in monolingual and bilingual language users at different proficiency levels. Across a series of studies, electrical brain activity was recorded while participants engaged in language comprehension tasks. In particular, our team focused on how subtle cues to meaning and grammar in sentences guide how people process language, as well as how experiential variables, such as native and non-native language proficiency, and cognitive variables, like memory capacity, influence brain activity that supports language use. One study demonstrated that monolingual English speakers and native Chinese speakers of English as a second language show similar patterns of brain activity when processing English grammatical markings, which are known to be very difficult for Chinese learners of English to master (specifically subject-verb agreement markings, as in "I walk" versus "He walks"). This finding shows that, even in adult language learners, the brain remains highly plastic and able to incorporate new information for use in real-time language processing. Another series of studies investigated factors related to variability among language users in the processing of subject-verb agreement. We discovered that variability that had previously been documented only in speakers of English as a second language is also found among high-proficiency, literate, monolingual English speakers. Standard methods for analyzing brain activity associated with language comprehension failed to capture this variability; however, the novel methods for data analysis we used and shared with the research community show that there is far more variation in the neural systems supporting language use than had previously been thought. One study demonstrated that this variability is partly related to genetic differences that co-occur with handedness. Another study demonstrated that the variability was not related to general literacy and language experience, nor was it related to individuals' cognitive capacities. Overall, our findings showed that, contrary to most prior work in the cognitive neuroscience of language, variability in how the brain uses linguistic information is present and pervasive in the population -- even among monolinguals with relatively homogenous language experience, and that there are multiple viable neural routes to successful language use and language learning. This result has broad implications for the study of language use and language processing among people showing atypical language development (e.g., dyslexia, specific language impairment, developmental disabilities) and pathologies impacting language use among adults (e.g., neurological trauma, cognitive decline in aging), and the assessment and therapy of individuals from these groups. From a development perspective, this project supported the growth and training of a number of graduate and undergraduate student scientists, predominantly women, a number of whom come from ethnic minority groups who are under-represented in the cognitive and neural sciences.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Darren&nbsp;Tanner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Second language learning is notoriously difficult, and there is widely-acknowledged inter-individual variability in the rate and ultimate success of learning. Much less is known, however, about how monolingual speakers differ from one other when processing their native language, or how the nature of individual variability may be similar or different among monolingual, bilingual, and adult language learner populations. This project was among the first to systematically investigate at large scale what cognitive, experiential, and linguistic factors are related to inter-individual variability in how the brain responds to linguistic information in monolingual and bilingual language users at different proficiency levels. Across a series of studies, electrical brain activity was recorded while participants engaged in language comprehension tasks. In particular, our team focused on how subtle cues to meaning and grammar in sentences guide how people process language, as well as how experiential variables, such as native and non-native language proficiency, and cognitive variables, like memory capacity, influence brain activity that supports language use. One study demonstrated that monolingual English speakers and native Chinese speakers of English as a second language show similar patterns of brain activity when processing English grammatical markings, which are known to be very difficult for Chinese learners of English to master (specifically subject-verb agreement markings, as in "I walk" versus "He walks"). This finding shows that, even in adult language learners, the brain remains highly plastic and able to incorporate new information for use in real-time language processing. Another series of studies investigated factors related to variability among language users in the processing of subject-verb agreement. We discovered that variability that had previously been documented only in speakers of English as a second language is also found among high-proficiency, literate, monolingual English speakers. Standard methods for analyzing brain activity associated with language comprehension failed to capture this variability; however, the novel methods for data analysis we used and shared with the research community show that there is far more variation in the neural systems supporting language use than had previously been thought. One study demonstrated that this variability is partly related to genetic differences that co-occur with handedness. Another study demonstrated that the variability was not related to general literacy and language experience, nor was it related to individuals' cognitive capacities. Overall, our findings showed that, contrary to most prior work in the cognitive neuroscience of language, variability in how the brain uses linguistic information is present and pervasive in the population -- even among monolinguals with relatively homogenous language experience, and that there are multiple viable neural routes to successful language use and language learning. This result has broad implications for the study of language use and language processing among people showing atypical language development (e.g., dyslexia, specific language impairment, developmental disabilities) and pathologies impacting language use among adults (e.g., neurological trauma, cognitive decline in aging), and the assessment and therapy of individuals from these groups. From a development perspective, this project supported the growth and training of a number of graduate and undergraduate student scientists, predominantly women, a number of whom come from ethnic minority groups who are under-represented in the cognitive and neural sciences.        Last Modified: 01/12/2020       Submitted by: Darren Tanner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
