<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development and Assessment of Teaching Tools to Facilitate the Implementation of Construction Industry Simulation (COINS) in Lower Division Courses</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299926.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299926</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abby Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ailumoka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922703</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A knowledge and skills gap exists in the civil and construction engineering curricula in applying theoretical knowledge to practice and in extending this knowledge outside students' fields of study.  In an attempt to address this issue in civil and construction engineering curricula, investigators at California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo (CPSLO) have developed a virtual Construction Industry Simulation (COINS) to supplement traditional classroom instructional delivery methods.  COINS provides a virtual environment to immerse students in active learning by posing problems and situations that require them to engage in practical engineering problem solving.  Through the implementation of COINS, engineering faculty will be able to enhance their instructional repertoire and gain confidence in employing new, effective instructional approaches. In so doing, they will be better equipped to meet the learning styles and needs of a broader range of students.  Through COINS, students will learn how to communicate and overcome obstacles in a multidisciplinary team and they will gain valuable skills that are needed to transition to jobs in industry and to participate in advanced research projects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has two primary objectives: (1) to develop an instructor's module for effective COINS implementation in lower division engineering courses at two- and four-year institutions of higher education and (2) to study the impact of COINS on student learning.  The investigators seek to advance knowledge and understanding in the areas of project-based learning, multidisciplinary projects, undergraduate research, and teamwork by measuring the impact of COINS simulation on student learning, identifying effective implementation strategies, and developing materials to facilitate the use of COINS by faculty. This will increase access to the COINS approach so that more students will participate in project-based learning experiences using the COINS simulation thus enabling these students to experience true concurrent engineering through an integrated experience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will be assessed using student work, interviews, focus groups, reflection exercises and observations.  The expected outcomes are numerous; major contributions will be: introductory civil/construction engineering course content that will improve articulation between community colleges and four-year institutions; an online community of practice to facilitate sharing of ideas, solutions, and practices as well as providing feedback on instructional materials and methods; and improved student learning and capabilities in engineering problem solving, teamwork, and communication.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1431845</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Chadwell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles B Chadwell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chadwell@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8057561317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000467379</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Korman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas M Korman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tkorman@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8057565612</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527323</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Polytechnic State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
<ZipCode>934070830</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Grand Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>029326246</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAL POLY CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>029326246</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Polytechnic State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>934070001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Grand Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299926</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Three findings derived from this study are significant. First, student survey responses did not support the efficacy of the use of COINS, a multidisciplinary construction project-based learning simulation that embeds theory into simulated authentic practice, in their capstone civil engineering course.</p> <p>Second, feedback from instructors and class observations found that classroom management when employing new pedagogical strategies, such as simulation and multidisciplinary project-based learning, require significant professional development and coaching/mentoring for faculty. Based on this, a classroom management module was added to the instructor&rsquo;s materials; however, this proved insufficient. Further investigation suggests that most current instructor&rsquo;s educational experiences were more traditional, lacking models of more recent pedagogical strategies such as simulations and project-based learning.&nbsp; Further research needs to be conducted on methods of extending post-secondary faculty&rsquo;s pedagogical repertoire. Successful models from K-12 suggest coaching, mentoring, co-teaching with a skilled faculty member, classroom observation of successful colleagues, and direct instruction in classroom management when employing diverse pedagogical approaches, including multiple forms of assessment. Given RTP requirements, the addition of evaluation of the types and variety of pedagogical strategies employed by faculty and their success in implementing these strategies may also be an alternative.</p> <p>Lastly, the student population surveyed that expressed they derived significant value from using COINS was at the community college level. In examining the demographics of the two populations, California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo (Cal Poly, a highly selective four-year institution) and Hartnell College (a two-year Hispanic-Serving Institution), significant differences in socio-economic, ethnic, and age differences were noted. Cal Poly&rsquo;s student demographics were over 80% white, middle and upper class with nearly all students spanning ages 18-23.&nbsp; Conversely, Hartnell students were over 80% Hispanic, lower socio-economic status, and older, 20-37. Also, worth noting was class size, Cal Poly classes employing COINS typically had X number of students while Hartnell had 12-15. Smaller class size enabled the instructor to work more closely with student COINS teams which also resulted in easier classroom management and ensuring that all students were engaged in the simulation and not checking Facebook and Twitter or sending emails.</p> <p>Similarly, the students&rsquo; feedback from both the undergraduate Cal Poly students and those at Hartnell supported that they derived significant value from COINS. The COINS multidisciplinary construction project-based learning simulation experience enabled them to apply the theories that they learned in class and that they read in their texts to authentic, real-life contexts.&nbsp; The results of the project argue that engineering faculty, especially with undergraduates, should expand the pedagogical approaches that they employ. This was especially true for the Latino and older students at the community college and speaks to the value of such approaches to increasing diversity in the engineering fields.</p> <p>It should be noted that student feedback suggested that changes were necessary to the COINS interface and feedback provided students. These enhancements, however, when implemented appeared to add little to students&rsquo; valuing of the program. Further student interviews after the enhancements were added suggested that students&rsquo; familiarity with gaming software and online, commercial content influenced their expectations of what the look and feel of online content should be. However, in probing their answers, students concluded that the value of the COINS approach did not derive from its look and feel but from how the program enabled them to apply what they had learned from their texts and lectures to real-life construction problems and challenges.</p> <p>Based on faculty feedback, classroom observations by the evaluation team, and student surveys and interviews, as noted, classroom management strategies for effectively implementing project-based learning and simulations are a critical area of need for post-secondary construction engineering faculty. Post-secondary institutions of higher learning also need to provide incentives and support to encourage faculty to obtain the classroom management skills necessary to successfully employ project-based learning and simulations and then support them in the implementation of these strategies. Further research is needed as to what levels and types of support are most efficacious in expanding faculty&rsquo;s pedagogical strategies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;M&nbsp;Korman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Three findings derived from this study are significant. First, student survey responses did not support the efficacy of the use of COINS, a multidisciplinary construction project-based learning simulation that embeds theory into simulated authentic practice, in their capstone civil engineering course.  Second, feedback from instructors and class observations found that classroom management when employing new pedagogical strategies, such as simulation and multidisciplinary project-based learning, require significant professional development and coaching/mentoring for faculty. Based on this, a classroom management module was added to the instructor?s materials; however, this proved insufficient. Further investigation suggests that most current instructor?s educational experiences were more traditional, lacking models of more recent pedagogical strategies such as simulations and project-based learning.  Further research needs to be conducted on methods of extending post-secondary faculty?s pedagogical repertoire. Successful models from K-12 suggest coaching, mentoring, co-teaching with a skilled faculty member, classroom observation of successful colleagues, and direct instruction in classroom management when employing diverse pedagogical approaches, including multiple forms of assessment. Given RTP requirements, the addition of evaluation of the types and variety of pedagogical strategies employed by faculty and their success in implementing these strategies may also be an alternative.  Lastly, the student population surveyed that expressed they derived significant value from using COINS was at the community college level. In examining the demographics of the two populations, California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo (Cal Poly, a highly selective four-year institution) and Hartnell College (a two-year Hispanic-Serving Institution), significant differences in socio-economic, ethnic, and age differences were noted. Cal Poly?s student demographics were over 80% white, middle and upper class with nearly all students spanning ages 18-23.  Conversely, Hartnell students were over 80% Hispanic, lower socio-economic status, and older, 20-37. Also, worth noting was class size, Cal Poly classes employing COINS typically had X number of students while Hartnell had 12-15. Smaller class size enabled the instructor to work more closely with student COINS teams which also resulted in easier classroom management and ensuring that all students were engaged in the simulation and not checking Facebook and Twitter or sending emails.  Similarly, the students? feedback from both the undergraduate Cal Poly students and those at Hartnell supported that they derived significant value from COINS. The COINS multidisciplinary construction project-based learning simulation experience enabled them to apply the theories that they learned in class and that they read in their texts to authentic, real-life contexts.  The results of the project argue that engineering faculty, especially with undergraduates, should expand the pedagogical approaches that they employ. This was especially true for the Latino and older students at the community college and speaks to the value of such approaches to increasing diversity in the engineering fields.  It should be noted that student feedback suggested that changes were necessary to the COINS interface and feedback provided students. These enhancements, however, when implemented appeared to add little to students? valuing of the program. Further student interviews after the enhancements were added suggested that students? familiarity with gaming software and online, commercial content influenced their expectations of what the look and feel of online content should be. However, in probing their answers, students concluded that the value of the COINS approach did not derive from its look and feel but from how the program enabled them to apply what they had learned from their texts and lectures to real-life construction problems and challenges.  Based on faculty feedback, classroom observations by the evaluation team, and student surveys and interviews, as noted, classroom management strategies for effectively implementing project-based learning and simulations are a critical area of need for post-secondary construction engineering faculty. Post-secondary institutions of higher learning also need to provide incentives and support to encourage faculty to obtain the classroom management skills necessary to successfully employ project-based learning and simulations and then support them in the implementation of these strategies. Further research is needed as to what levels and types of support are most efficacious in expanding faculty?s pedagogical strategies.       Last Modified: 12/31/2018       Submitted by: Thomas M Korman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
