<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Can Student Characteristics be Used to Effectively Identify Students At-Risk in the Online STEM Environment?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>719108.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>719108</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Keene</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The EHR Core Research Program funds proposals that will help synthesize, build and/or expand research foundations in the following areas of STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics) Education: STEM learning, STEM learning environments, STEM workforce development, and broadening participation in STEM. The STEM education pipeline narrows significantly in college. Community colleges serve some of the most diverse audiences, and are increasingly using online learning as a cheaper way to provide STEM instruction; additionally Massive Open Online Courses (commonly known as MOOCs) are being proposed as alternatives to credit-bearing instruction. Prior research shows that online learning environments impact different kinds of students differently. This research project based at a community college asks questions such as the following: Is this move towards STEM learning online at the community college level likely to impact underrepresented groups more than others, and will it have positive or negative impact? Can we identify which students are best served by online vs. face-to-face instruction or conduct interventions for students 'at-risk' in the online environment? This project aims to answer these questions by using two important datasets: one is a dataset to be assembled from six schools in the CUNY (City University of New York) system, which serves one of the most diverse student bodies in the country, and in which over 50,000 students have taken STEM courses online. The second is a large-scale national dataset from the National Center for Education Statistics which contains demographic, academic, personal, and financial variables.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Only a small proportion of the research conducted on online learning has controlled for student self-selection into online courses in a rigorous way. This study will explore the extent to which students with particular characteristics fare better or more poorly not only in online STEM courses, but in college afterwards, with a matched comparison to students who take comparable face-to-face STEM courses. The project uses mixed methods. Quantitative analysis will include principal component factor analysis, logistic regression, linear regression, analysis of variance and covariance, generalized linear mixed models, propensity score matching, and sensitivity analysis to examine course and college outcomes including course retention (attendance through the end of the tenth week of classes) and successful course completion (earning a C- or better in the course), whether students re-enrolled in the semester immediately following the course, and persistence at one, two, three, and six years. Overall grade point average, the number of credits accumulated, and transfer and graduation rates at these intervals will also be used. Independent variables and covariates to be modeled include online vs. hybrid vs. offline STEM course format, and a variety of demographic variables including effort capital, social capital, cultural capital, financial capital, human capital, and habitus. Qualitative interviews and in-depth surveys will be used to explore the trends found in the large scale datasets, and a survey will be conducted specifically with online instructors in the CUNY system. Data will be explored to model what variables contribute to differential 'risk' online. The intellectual merit of the project rests on advancing our understanding of how online options differentially help or hinder different kinds of postsecondary STEM students. For broader impacts, the results of the model could be used as the basis for implementation of targeted interventions, either by providing at-risk students with additional mentoring, tutoring, technical support, advisement, or training in skills and behaviors necessary to succeed in an online course; or by advising them to enroll in a comparable face-to-face course instead. These policy implications will be discussed at a culminating one-day conference on elearning hosted by the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1431649</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
<LastName>Wladis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claire W Wladis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cwladis@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9172677578</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000379335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Conway</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine Conway</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kconway@bmcc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2122208010</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000615561</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alyse</FirstName>
<LastName>Hachey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alyse Hachey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ahachey@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2122201215</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000615562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Borough of Manhattan Community College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100071079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2122208010</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>199 Chambers Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>137840018</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Borough of Manhattan Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100071079</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[199 Chambers St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~719108</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Larger and larger numbers of STEM courses at colleges are being taught online.&nbsp; Because of this, retention and successful completion of online STEM courses will play an escalating role in STEM degree completion. This project sought to find out if differences exist between online and face-to-face STEM course and college outcomes and more specifically, if women or ethnic minorities are at great risk of course or college dropout in the online STEM environment compared to their male or white peers. To find out, we surveyed roughly 100,000 students and merged this with Institutional Research data to create the largest known dataset on online college students that includes important life factors such as work, family, and time use.</p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; For STEM Majors:</em></strong> After controlling for and matching on a large range of student characteristics, there was no significant difference in online course retention, successful course completion, or college persistence or degree attainment two years later.&nbsp; STEM majors who took an online course were significantly more likely to persist in the short-term (e.g. re-enroll in the subsequent semester), which may indicate that they were less likely to stop out than their comparable peers enrolled in a face-to-face course, although they were at no lower risk for longer-term dropout.&nbsp; Further, when controlling for and matching on the same wide range of student and course characteristics, the relationship between online course-taking and both course and college outcomes were not significantly different for women versus men, or for any specific groups of students of color (i.e. Black, Hispanic or Asian students) versus white students, suggesting that online course taking does not exacerbate existing achievement gaps by gender or ethnicity for STEM majors.<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong><em>For All Majors Taking STEM Courses:&nbsp; </em></strong>When controlling for and matching on only those characteristics routinely collected by Institutional Research departments at colleges but without controlling for more complex life factors such as work or family commitments, we found that students who took a specific STEM course in a fully online instead of face-to-face format had weaker course outcomes, although they were no less likely to persist in college or attain a degree. <em>However,</em> after controlling for and matching on other more complex characteristics such as whether a student had young children, their work hours, and other time poverty measures obtained through survey data, we found that students who took STEM courses online had course and college outcomes that were comparable to students in matched face-to-face sections of the same courses.&nbsp; They were, however, less likely to persist after two years.&nbsp; Yet, the student outcomes in their online course does not explain this difference, which suggests that there may be other differences in student characteristics between those students who enroll in STEM online courses versus those who do not, and that it may be these factors in particular that make online students more likely to drop out or stop out of college.&nbsp; In particular, we found through 49 in-depth interviews that students cited a number of significant life stressors such as serious family or personal illness, housing insecurity, divorce, unemployment, and domestic violence as stressors that occurred in the semester in which they took the online course in the study, and which impacted the time and/or energy they had for their studies.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We also surveyed over 1000 students to find out why they dropped out of online or matched sections of face-to-face STEM courses.&nbsp; While students in both online and face-to-face STEM classes cited quality of instruction as often or more often than any other reason for dropping out of the course, this reason was cited significantly more often by face-to-face than online students.&nbsp; They were almost one-and-a-half times as likely to cite quality of instruction as a reason for dropout as their fully online peers.&nbsp; In contrast, students enrolled in fully online STEM courses were significantly more likely to cite factors related to time poverty as a reason for dropping the course, with top reasons including work, other academic demands, and course workload.&nbsp; These three factors all individually tied for the second most commonly cited reason for withdrawal for fully online students.&nbsp;&nbsp; Taken together, our findings suggest that there may be a host of factors, not routinely captured by college data collection, and not routinely addressed by more traditional college services, that likely influence student enrollment, persistence and outcomes in STEM online courses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Claire&nbsp;W&nbsp;Wladis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             Larger and larger numbers of STEM courses at colleges are being taught online.  Because of this, retention and successful completion of online STEM courses will play an escalating role in STEM degree completion. This project sought to find out if differences exist between online and face-to-face STEM course and college outcomes and more specifically, if women or ethnic minorities are at great risk of course or college dropout in the online STEM environment compared to their male or white peers. To find out, we surveyed roughly 100,000 students and merged this with Institutional Research data to create the largest known dataset on online college students that includes important life factors such as work, family, and time use.              For STEM Majors: After controlling for and matching on a large range of student characteristics, there was no significant difference in online course retention, successful course completion, or college persistence or degree attainment two years later.  STEM majors who took an online course were significantly more likely to persist in the short-term (e.g. re-enroll in the subsequent semester), which may indicate that they were less likely to stop out than their comparable peers enrolled in a face-to-face course, although they were at no lower risk for longer-term dropout.  Further, when controlling for and matching on the same wide range of student and course characteristics, the relationship between online course-taking and both course and college outcomes were not significantly different for women versus men, or for any specific groups of students of color (i.e. Black, Hispanic or Asian students) versus white students, suggesting that online course taking does not exacerbate existing achievement gaps by gender or ethnicity for STEM majors.               For All Majors Taking STEM Courses:  When controlling for and matching on only those characteristics routinely collected by Institutional Research departments at colleges but without controlling for more complex life factors such as work or family commitments, we found that students who took a specific STEM course in a fully online instead of face-to-face format had weaker course outcomes, although they were no less likely to persist in college or attain a degree. However, after controlling for and matching on other more complex characteristics such as whether a student had young children, their work hours, and other time poverty measures obtained through survey data, we found that students who took STEM courses online had course and college outcomes that were comparable to students in matched face-to-face sections of the same courses.  They were, however, less likely to persist after two years.  Yet, the student outcomes in their online course does not explain this difference, which suggests that there may be other differences in student characteristics between those students who enroll in STEM online courses versus those who do not, and that it may be these factors in particular that make online students more likely to drop out or stop out of college.  In particular, we found through 49 in-depth interviews that students cited a number of significant life stressors such as serious family or personal illness, housing insecurity, divorce, unemployment, and domestic violence as stressors that occurred in the semester in which they took the online course in the study, and which impacted the time and/or energy they had for their studies.                  We also surveyed over 1000 students to find out why they dropped out of online or matched sections of face-to-face STEM courses.  While students in both online and face-to-face STEM classes cited quality of instruction as often or more often than any other reason for dropping out of the course, this reason was cited significantly more often by face-to-face than online students.  They were almost one-and-a-half times as likely to cite quality of instruction as a reason for dropout as their fully online peers.  In contrast, students enrolled in fully online STEM courses were significantly more likely to cite factors related to time poverty as a reason for dropping the course, with top reasons including work, other academic demands, and course workload.  These three factors all individually tied for the second most commonly cited reason for withdrawal for fully online students.   Taken together, our findings suggest that there may be a host of factors, not routinely captured by college data collection, and not routinely addressed by more traditional college services, that likely influence student enrollment, persistence and outcomes in STEM online courses.          Last Modified: 05/03/2019       Submitted by: Claire W Wladis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
