<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Advancing the Dissemination of the Creative Art of Structural/Civil Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>127167.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>127167</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abby Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ailumoka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922703</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent reports from the Office of the President of the United States and the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) urge the nation to increase student retention in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), and to educate a STEM-literate populace (i.e., STEM education for non-STEM majors). Uninspiring introductory courses, poor teaching, and lack of effective dissemination of best-practices are major obstacles that stand in the way of achieving these goals.  Faculty members from Princeton University, Virginia Tech and the University of Massachusetts Amherst are partnering on a project entitled "Advancing the Dissemination of the Creative Art of Structural/Civil Engineering" with the aim of overcoming these obstacles through supporting the dissemination and implementation of an introductory civil engineering course that is to be enhanced with research-based pedagogy. The target populations are both STEM and non-STEM majors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main objectives of this proposal are to: (1) transform an introductory engineering course with dramatically improved interactivity and accessibility for non-STEM students; (2) ensure that the course takes a form that can be readily adopted into the engineering and general education curricula of many types of institutions of higher education (e.g., undergraduate institutions, research universities, etc.); and (3) facilitate dissemination, adoption, and continuous improvement of the courses beyond the audience already being reached.  The objectives will be met by implementing four strategies, which include conducting customer development interviews that identify the challenges and needs for adoption in institutions of various cultures and curricula; creating course modules, comprised of different subjects (e.g. suspension bridges, towers, dams, etc.) and a library of lectures and active-learning activities; developing a website and central repository of information for teaching the course; and hosting annual workshops to mentor faculty who want to adopt the course.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An assessment and evaluation plan is proposed to measure the effectiveness of the course enhancements with active learning pedagogies and dissemination into other institutions.  The course to be disseminated will emphasize the creativity of the engineer along with the technical content. One thesis to be tested is if disseminating engineering as a creative art changes perceptions and increases the appreciation of engineering's role in society. The outcomes of the project hold potential to advance knowledge regarding the effect that false perceptions of engineers being "technicians" as opposed to creative artists has on STEM attrition and attraction; challenges and successes in teaching introductory engineering courses in institutions of different cultures and curricula; and strategies for supporting the successful adoption of an innovative course across diverse institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1431717</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjay</FirstName>
<LastName>Arwade</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjay Arwade</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arwade@umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135770926</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000149927</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[130 Natural Resources Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~127167</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Recent reports from the President&rsquo;s Office and the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) urge the nation to increase student retention in STEM, and to educate a STEM-literate populace (i.e., STEM education for non-STEM majors).&nbsp;&nbsp;Uninspiring introductory courses, poor teaching, and lack of effective dissemination of best-practices are major obstacles that stand in the way of achieving these goals.&nbsp;This project is an example of how the nation can overcome these obstacles by supporting the dissemination and implementation of an introductory civil engineering course that was enhanced with research-based pedagogy.&nbsp;&nbsp;The target population was both STEM and non-STEM majors.&nbsp;&nbsp;The three specific goals met were:&nbsp;</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;<em>Transformation and enhancement of an introductory civil engineering course with dramatically improved interactivity and accessibility for non-STEM students</em>: Evaluation of the methodology and course enhancements were made via student surveys, interviews, focus groups.&nbsp;&nbsp;The project exceeded the intended goals. Combining the Princeton University data from all four years (n=207),&nbsp;91% of students reported moderate to great gain in their enthusiasm for the subject and in their interest in discussing the subject area with friends or family;&nbsp;86% reported moderate to great gain in recognizing engineering as a creative profession; 84% reported moderate to great gain in understanding how engineering helps people address&nbsp;real world issues; 89% reported moderate to great gain in confidence that they understand the course material; and, on average, 98% reported a moderate to great grain in their ability to relate the forms of structures (bridges, buildings, vaults) they encounter in daily life to their function and to the forces in the structure.&nbsp; These results far exceed the project benchmark of &ldquo;75% of students will report greater interest in engineering, recognition that engineering involves creativity and impacts society, and confidence in STEM abilities.&rdquo; Furthermore, a large majority of students reported moderate, good, or great learning gains from lecture demonstrations (93%), from participating in discussion in lecture, precepts or labs (87%), and from the hands-on activities (86%). These last 3 results further highlight the efficacy of the active learning pedagogies being developed and implemented in this course. &nbsp;</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;<em>Facilitating dissemination and adoption of the courses beyond the audience already being reached</em>: Three workshops were held where the goals were to (a) understand the culture of various institutions and their challenges and barriers for adoption/adaption of the course content, (b) introduce learning objectives, course modules, and the various manners that the objectives and content can be taught; and (c) continue to build a community of educators around these educational objectives. A total of 38 faculty representing diverse academic institutions attended, where five of the institutions were HBCUs.&nbsp;&nbsp;During the workshop, several hours of one-on-one mentoring was available and the mentoring has continued and will continue as these colleagues adapt the course or modules of the course.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition, dissemination continues to grow via a comprehensive website developed by the grant:&nbsp;<a href="http://casce.princeton.edu/">http://casce.princeton.edu</a>. This website disseminates modularized course materials such as lecture slides, active learning exercises, &ldquo;structural studies&rdquo; (mini structural analysis lessons), learning goals and syllabi, reading assignments, problem sets, writing assignments, bibliographies, and other information to assist an instructor in adopting and implementing any part of the CASCE courses.&nbsp;</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;<em>Modularization of the course to take a form that can be readily adopted into the engineering and general education curricula of many types of institutions of higher learning (e.g., undergraduate institutions, research universities, etc.)</em>: As mentioned, the website content enables modularization of the course.&nbsp;&nbsp;Of the 38 faculty who attended the one of the summer workshops, 25 responded to post-workshop surveys. Surveys were administered every six months post summer workshop participation. Respondents provided the following information regarding the adoption of the course: 20 adapted and incorporated lectures and/or demonstrations into their college-level courses and 1 adapted the course materials for use during a summer workshop with K-12 teachers.</p> <p>As noted by the NAE it is important for all students to appreciate the central role of engineering in all facets of modern life.&nbsp;The civil engineering ideas disseminated by this course are vital to STEM non-majors and majors alike, because civil engineers design and build the systems that give us shelter (buildings), enable transportation (roads, bridges, ports, airports), and bring us water and power (dams and reservoirs).&nbsp;&nbsp;The project provides an example of an effective means of reducing attrition of STEM students by utilizing student-active pedagogies that have been proven effective in promoting retention and cultivate an appreciation for the role of engineering in everyday life.&nbsp;&nbsp;The societal outcomes of more STEM professionals in the USA are an improved national economy and therefore vitality.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/26/2019<br>      Modified by: Sanjay&nbsp;Arwade</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Recent reports from the President’s Office and the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) urge the nation to increase student retention in STEM, and to educate a STEM-literate populace (i.e., STEM education for non-STEM majors).  Uninspiring introductory courses, poor teaching, and lack of effective dissemination of best-practices are major obstacles that stand in the way of achieving these goals. This project is an example of how the nation can overcome these obstacles by supporting the dissemination and implementation of an introductory civil engineering course that was enhanced with research-based pedagogy.  The target population was both STEM and non-STEM majors.  The three specific goals met were:   (1) Transformation and enhancement of an introductory civil engineering course with dramatically improved interactivity and accessibility for non-STEM students: Evaluation of the methodology and course enhancements were made via student surveys, interviews, focus groups.  The project exceeded the intended goals. Combining the Princeton University data from all four years (n=207), 91% of students reported moderate to great gain in their enthusiasm for the subject and in their interest in discussing the subject area with friends or family; 86% reported moderate to great gain in recognizing engineering as a creative profession; 84% reported moderate to great gain in understanding how engineering helps people address real world issues; 89% reported moderate to great gain in confidence that they understand the course material; and, on average, 98% reported a moderate to great grain in their ability to relate the forms of structures (bridges, buildings, vaults) they encounter in daily life to their function and to the forces in the structure.  These results far exceed the project benchmark of "75% of students will report greater interest in engineering, recognition that engineering involves creativity and impacts society, and confidence in STEM abilities." Furthermore, a large majority of students reported moderate, good, or great learning gains from lecture demonstrations (93%), from participating in discussion in lecture, precepts or labs (87%), and from the hands-on activities (86%). These last 3 results further highlight the efficacy of the active learning pedagogies being developed and implemented in this course.    (2) Facilitating dissemination and adoption of the courses beyond the audience already being reached: Three workshops were held where the goals were to (a) understand the culture of various institutions and their challenges and barriers for adoption/adaption of the course content, (b) introduce learning objectives, course modules, and the various manners that the objectives and content can be taught; and (c) continue to build a community of educators around these educational objectives. A total of 38 faculty representing diverse academic institutions attended, where five of the institutions were HBCUs.  During the workshop, several hours of one-on-one mentoring was available and the mentoring has continued and will continue as these colleagues adapt the course or modules of the course.  In addition, dissemination continues to grow via a comprehensive website developed by the grant: http://casce.princeton.edu. This website disseminates modularized course materials such as lecture slides, active learning exercises, "structural studies" (mini structural analysis lessons), learning goals and syllabi, reading assignments, problem sets, writing assignments, bibliographies, and other information to assist an instructor in adopting and implementing any part of the CASCE courses.   (3) Modularization of the course to take a form that can be readily adopted into the engineering and general education curricula of many types of institutions of higher learning (e.g., undergraduate institutions, research universities, etc.): As mentioned, the website content enables modularization of the course.  Of the 38 faculty who attended the one of the summer workshops, 25 responded to post-workshop surveys. Surveys were administered every six months post summer workshop participation. Respondents provided the following information regarding the adoption of the course: 20 adapted and incorporated lectures and/or demonstrations into their college-level courses and 1 adapted the course materials for use during a summer workshop with K-12 teachers.  As noted by the NAE it is important for all students to appreciate the central role of engineering in all facets of modern life. The civil engineering ideas disseminated by this course are vital to STEM non-majors and majors alike, because civil engineers design and build the systems that give us shelter (buildings), enable transportation (roads, bridges, ports, airports), and bring us water and power (dams and reservoirs).  The project provides an example of an effective means of reducing attrition of STEM students by utilizing student-active pedagogies that have been proven effective in promoting retention and cultivate an appreciation for the role of engineering in everyday life.  The societal outcomes of more STEM professionals in the USA are an improved national economy and therefore vitality.          Last Modified: 12/26/2019       Submitted by: Sanjay Arwade]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
