<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  A Cell Analysis Platform for Low-cost, Rapid Diagnosis of Sepsis Using Microfluidic Technologies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>748007.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1419607</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is in detecting sepsis early in its course, before end organ damage when it is most treatable. Sepsis, an uncontrolled systemic response to local infection by bacteria or fungi, is responsible for more deaths than prostate cancer, breast cancer, and AIDS combined and is associated with ~$17B in annual U.S. healthcare expenditures. We anticipate that providing emergency department physicians with an earlier diagnostic will profoundly influence clinical outcomes (currently ~40% mortality), costs (&gt;$22,000/case), and the quality of life for survivors and their families. Accumulating evidence connects systemic immune activation ? a key process in sepsis ? with single-cell architectural changes that are mechanically measured by high-speed mechanical phenotyping technology. This technology is well-suited for adult sepsis screening in the emergency department (market size of $1.5B) due to: (1) the functional analysis of cell state the mechanical measurement provides, (2) its high achievable throughput and therefore statistical accuracy, (3) exceedingly short turnaround time, (4) low cost of goods, and (5) the clinically-actionable information it provides. Beyond the adult sepsis screening market, several additional indications include neonatal sepsis, bladder cancer detection, academic research tools, and drug development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project brings an innovative new class of biomarkers to bear on a problem that has been intractable with current biomarkers.  Briefly, the physical properties of cells have been known to be important for decades, but only with the advent of breakthrough microfluidic technology have we been able to measure these parameters in a high-throughput manner capable of diagnosing disease.  This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II award will be used to develop and validate innovative sample preparation and image analysis modules for a sepsis screening technology as well as performance of proof-of-concept clinical studies that would be a flagship offering in using biomechanical biomarkers to diagnose disease. The technical objectives are designed to improve sensitivity to white blood cells, activated during sepsis, by microfluidic automation of sample preparation and optimization of the microscopic imaging optics. In addition to preparing the test for practical implementation in the emergency department, the test will be validated with a proof-of-concept clinical study, and a clinical scoring system will be devised.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1431033</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Gossett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel R Gossett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.gossett@cytovale.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2405053768</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000635057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/30/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mara</FirstName>
<LastName>Macdonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mara Macdonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mara.macdonald@cytovale.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000695792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CytoVale, Inc</Name>
<CityName>South San Francisco</CityName>
<ZipCode>940801967</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5628816919</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>384 Oyster Point Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 7]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078418950</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CYTOVALE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CytoVale, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>South San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940801934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[385 Oyster Point Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7744</Code>
<Text>RAHSS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENSING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>Education Products</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~764007</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~155600</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our platform consists of a benchtop instrument (The Mechano-Phenotyping Cytometer, MPC) and a single-use test cartridge that together enable the SeptiVale assay. The system measures mechanical properties of cells at a throughput of over 2,000 cells per second. Our patent-protected measurement of biomechanical properties represents a paradigm shift in diagnostic technology which uniquely positions CytoVale to address unsolved problems in sepsis by using techniques orthogonal to those that have previously tried and failed.Crucially, by measuring the disease causing agent (rampant white blood cell activation) before permanent damage has been done, as opposed to measuring the damage itself, physicians will be able to initiate treatment protocols on the correct patients at an early point when they are most effective, drastically reducing morbidity and mortality associated with sepsis.</p> <p>The funding for SBIR Phase II: A Cell Analysis Platform for Low-cost, Rapid Diagnosis of Sepsis Using Microfluidic Technologies, led to important technical developments towards designing and engineering a more robust and reduced operational complexity of the Cytovale MPC. Cytovale has completed 100% of all milestones set forth in the research aims. Specifically, this funding supported the development of a custom sample preparation solution scaled for production, refinement in optical detection and biophysical features related to the activation of leukocytes, evaluation of the MPC on 200 patients for sepsis, and machine learning development of a diagnostic classifier for sepsis. The performance of the Cytovale MPC is within the range of clinically impactful performance, achieving AUC &gt; 0.85 for the classification of sepsis. We believe the MPC is positioned to have clinical impact in diagnosis and management of sepsis patient care.</p> <p>The period for SBIR Phase IIb supplemental funding supported Cytovale?s development of formal design control development for the MPC. In addition, the development and process qualification of cartridges was a major focus with the intent to achieve design freeze of the cartridge design. We had conducted user interviews with KOLs, clinicians, emergency room personnel, and laboratorians to establish the user requirements for the system and cartridges. Through this detailed research, we?ve established the design control guiding documents such as concept document and user needs document.&nbsp; Further, we translated these user needs to technical specifications and have engaged the development team to realize a clinical product based on the established requirements. The funding here supported analysis of engineering results to meeting identified marketing needs. Further, in this period we had evaluated cartridge design and molding implications to arrive to a final set of design drawings that addresses the need of the final product and design for manufacturing at scale. The project has engaged with manufacturers to build the first lot of design control production cartridges.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/26/2019<br>      Modified by: Mara&nbsp;Macdonald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our platform consists of a benchtop instrument (The Mechano-Phenotyping Cytometer, MPC) and a single-use test cartridge that together enable the SeptiVale assay. The system measures mechanical properties of cells at a throughput of over 2,000 cells per second. Our patent-protected measurement of biomechanical properties represents a paradigm shift in diagnostic technology which uniquely positions CytoVale to address unsolved problems in sepsis by using techniques orthogonal to those that have previously tried and failed.Crucially, by measuring the disease causing agent (rampant white blood cell activation) before permanent damage has been done, as opposed to measuring the damage itself, physicians will be able to initiate treatment protocols on the correct patients at an early point when they are most effective, drastically reducing morbidity and mortality associated with sepsis.  The funding for SBIR Phase II: A Cell Analysis Platform for Low-cost, Rapid Diagnosis of Sepsis Using Microfluidic Technologies, led to important technical developments towards designing and engineering a more robust and reduced operational complexity of the Cytovale MPC. Cytovale has completed 100% of all milestones set forth in the research aims. Specifically, this funding supported the development of a custom sample preparation solution scaled for production, refinement in optical detection and biophysical features related to the activation of leukocytes, evaluation of the MPC on 200 patients for sepsis, and machine learning development of a diagnostic classifier for sepsis. The performance of the Cytovale MPC is within the range of clinically impactful performance, achieving AUC &gt; 0.85 for the classification of sepsis. We believe the MPC is positioned to have clinical impact in diagnosis and management of sepsis patient care.  The period for SBIR Phase IIb supplemental funding supported Cytovale?s development of formal design control development for the MPC. In addition, the development and process qualification of cartridges was a major focus with the intent to achieve design freeze of the cartridge design. We had conducted user interviews with KOLs, clinicians, emergency room personnel, and laboratorians to establish the user requirements for the system and cartridges. Through this detailed research, we?ve established the design control guiding documents such as concept document and user needs document.  Further, we translated these user needs to technical specifications and have engaged the development team to realize a clinical product based on the established requirements. The funding here supported analysis of engineering results to meeting identified marketing needs. Further, in this period we had evaluated cartridge design and molding implications to arrive to a final set of design drawings that addresses the need of the final product and design for manufacturing at scale. The project has engaged with manufacturers to build the first lot of design control production cartridges.          Last Modified: 03/26/2019       Submitted by: Mara Macdonald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
