<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Deciphering Spatially and Temporally Complex High-Latitude Landscapes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15919.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15919</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>High-latitude landscapes in the Arctic and Antarctic contain evidence of how the world's largest glaciers and ice sheets have responded to past changes in climate, and they document how glaciers erode and transport sediments and nutrients.  This doctoral dissertation research project will examine an area of northwestern Greenland as a natural laboratory that can be used to study high-latitude landscape evolution on timescales of tens to hundreds of thousands of years.  The doctoral student will analyze two distinct units of glacial sediments that have been deposited in different but adjacent areas in the Thule region in order to determine how each of the sedimentary units has evolved over space and time and use these insights as a model for understanding landscape evolution and sediment transport in glaciated high-latitude regions, including locations in northern North America and other high-latitude landscapes where similar processes are functioning.  The project will provide valuable new information about the timing of past episodes of ice sheet advance and retreat.  It will help address the question of whether glacial ice has behaved as an agent of erosion, and it will enhance scientific understanding of the complex processes that shape high-latitude landscapes.  Cosmogenic data will be made accessible to other researchers via the NOAA paleoclimatology database, and project findings will be disseminated through both scholarly and popular media in order to broaden the range of individuals who may benefit from the new insights and information that will be generated.  As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this award also will provide support to enable a promising student to establish a strong independent research career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The high-latitude landscapes that are the focus of this project are shaped by a cyclic pattern of glacial advance and retreat.  During glacial periods, when ice sheets expand, the landscape can either be deeply eroded and sculpted by glacial ice (if the ice is at the melting point and liquid water is available) or preserved beneath non-erosive glacial ice (if the ice is below the melting point and frozen to the bed).  During interglacial periods when ice sheets shrink, weathering modifies the landscape through movement of material by wind, water, and freeze-thaw action.  Subsequent smaller ice advances may cover only part of the landscape, creating geographies where surfaces with different ages and histories are juxtaposed.  The doctoral student will reconstruct the complex landscape history in the Thule region through the analysis of three rare isotopes:  beryllium-10, aluminum-26, and carbon-14.  These isotopes build up slowly in rock surfaces only when the rocks are exposed and not covered by glaciers.  The analyses of the concentrations of these isotopes in rock surfaces will provide information about the age and exposure history of the landscape&lt;br/&gt;.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1433878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Bierman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul R Bierman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbierman@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8026564411</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000233520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Corbett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee B Corbett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ashley.Corbett@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8023802344</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667130</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
<CityName>Burlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>85 South Prospect Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066811191</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF VERMONT &amp; STATE AGRICULTURAL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066811191</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Vermont & State Agricultural College]]></Name>
<CityName>Burlington</CityName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[180 Colchester Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~15919</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Earth&rsquo;s high latitudes hold most of the planet&rsquo;s glacial ice, and thus have the potential to be significant contributors to sea level rise during times of warming climate. These same high-latitude areas are also forecasted to experience the greatest warming in the future due to anthropogenic climate change. The Greenland Ice Sheet alone contains seven meters of sea level equivalent, and in recent years outlet glaciers there have thinned and their flow rate has increased. There has been widespread surface melt and net mass loss, all signs of ice sheet instability in a warming world. For these reasons, it is particularly important to understand the response of high-latitude glaciers to past episodes of climate change in order to provide insight about possible effects of future climatic change.</p> <p>However, the high latitudes are also some of the most difficult areas for studying glacial history. At lower latitudes, glacial ice effectively erodes the land surface and removes loose sediment, leaving behind copious physical evidence about past ice extent. But at the higher latitudes, glacial ice can be so cold that it becomes frozen to its bed, prohibiting it from eroding the underlying landscape. These so-called "ghost glaciers", which are incapable of performing any erosion, leave behind no physical evidence of their presence. Therefore, studying past glacier extent (and therefore past climate change) in high latitude regions is complicated and most of the traditional approaches are not effective.</p> <p>To understand how "ghost glaciers" work, we turned to chemical evidence preserved in rock surfaces. We used rare, radioactive isotopes, called cosmogenic nuclides, that form at known rates in rock surfaces exposed to the sky. By quantifying the abundance of these istopes (including beryllium-10 and aluminum-26) in rock surfaces, we can determine how long ago the surface of interest was exposed from beneath retreating glaciers. Further, by pairing multiple radioactive isotopes with different half-lives, we can constrain the complex history of landscapes that have been alternately preserved beneath non-erosive "ghost glaciers" and exposed to the sky during periods of warmer climate and smaller ice extent. The goals of our work were to develop new approaches to using cosmogenic nuclides to constrain past glacier behavior in high-latitude areas characterized by non-erosive glacial ice, and to employ these new techniques to make inferences about past ice sheet behavior in the Arctic.</p> <p>Our work took us to the high Arctic, including Greenland and Arctic Canada, to study these unique landscapes that have been preserved beneath "ghost glaciers". By quantifying the amount of cosmogenic isotopes in rock surfaces, we learned about how "ghost glaciers" shape the underlying landscape. We discovered that some of the landscapes we studied have been preserved beneath non-erosive glaciers for hundreds of thousands to millions of years, marking them as valuable archives of long-term climate change information. By creating numerical models and using them to analyze our data, we discovered that the landscapes we studied have spent over three quarters of their history buried (but not eroded) by glacial ice, and only a small portion of their history exposed during past warm periods. Although determining the exact history of a rock surface is challenging because there are a large number of variables, our numerical models allowed us to simulate possible scenarios and therefore learn about the history of warm and cold periods in Earth's climate.</p> <p>In the face of modern climate change, we sought to refine methods for  constraining the timing of glacial events in areas preserved for long  durations beneath non-erosive glacial ice because these ancient surfaces  are archives of valuable long-term climatic and glacial information. Our work lead to the development of new t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ EarthÆs high latitudes hold most of the planetÆs glacial ice, and thus have the potential to be significant contributors to sea level rise during times of warming climate. These same high-latitude areas are also forecasted to experience the greatest warming in the future due to anthropogenic climate change. The Greenland Ice Sheet alone contains seven meters of sea level equivalent, and in recent years outlet glaciers there have thinned and their flow rate has increased. There has been widespread surface melt and net mass loss, all signs of ice sheet instability in a warming world. For these reasons, it is particularly important to understand the response of high-latitude glaciers to past episodes of climate change in order to provide insight about possible effects of future climatic change.  However, the high latitudes are also some of the most difficult areas for studying glacial history. At lower latitudes, glacial ice effectively erodes the land surface and removes loose sediment, leaving behind copious physical evidence about past ice extent. But at the higher latitudes, glacial ice can be so cold that it becomes frozen to its bed, prohibiting it from eroding the underlying landscape. These so-called "ghost glaciers", which are incapable of performing any erosion, leave behind no physical evidence of their presence. Therefore, studying past glacier extent (and therefore past climate change) in high latitude regions is complicated and most of the traditional approaches are not effective.  To understand how "ghost glaciers" work, we turned to chemical evidence preserved in rock surfaces. We used rare, radioactive isotopes, called cosmogenic nuclides, that form at known rates in rock surfaces exposed to the sky. By quantifying the abundance of these istopes (including beryllium-10 and aluminum-26) in rock surfaces, we can determine how long ago the surface of interest was exposed from beneath retreating glaciers. Further, by pairing multiple radioactive isotopes with different half-lives, we can constrain the complex history of landscapes that have been alternately preserved beneath non-erosive "ghost glaciers" and exposed to the sky during periods of warmer climate and smaller ice extent. The goals of our work were to develop new approaches to using cosmogenic nuclides to constrain past glacier behavior in high-latitude areas characterized by non-erosive glacial ice, and to employ these new techniques to make inferences about past ice sheet behavior in the Arctic.  Our work took us to the high Arctic, including Greenland and Arctic Canada, to study these unique landscapes that have been preserved beneath "ghost glaciers". By quantifying the amount of cosmogenic isotopes in rock surfaces, we learned about how "ghost glaciers" shape the underlying landscape. We discovered that some of the landscapes we studied have been preserved beneath non-erosive glaciers for hundreds of thousands to millions of years, marking them as valuable archives of long-term climate change information. By creating numerical models and using them to analyze our data, we discovered that the landscapes we studied have spent over three quarters of their history buried (but not eroded) by glacial ice, and only a small portion of their history exposed during past warm periods. Although determining the exact history of a rock surface is challenging because there are a large number of variables, our numerical models allowed us to simulate possible scenarios and therefore learn about the history of warm and cold periods in Earth's climate.  In the face of modern climate change, we sought to refine methods for  constraining the timing of glacial events in areas preserved for long  durations beneath non-erosive glacial ice because these ancient surfaces  are archives of valuable long-term climatic and glacial information. Our work lead to the development of new techniques, both in the laboratory and for data analysis, that will pave the way for similar work i...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
