<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC FRP:  Electrocoagulation for the Mitigation of Emerging Biological and Chemical Contaminants</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199679.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199679</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This I/UCRC Fundamental Research Program project seeks to address some of the critical knowledge gaps by elucidating the mechanisms of mitigation of Environmental Protection Agency's Contaminant Candidate List (CCL) viruses and estrogens using electrocoagulation (EC) as a sustainable alternative for drinking water treatment. This research provides the first fundamental assessment of the treatment efficacy of 3 CCL viruses (adenovirus, calicivirus, and enteroviruses) and 4 CCL estrogens (E1, E2, E3, and EE2) via EC. Understanding of system capabilities will advance through direct comparisons of EC, conventional coagulation, and oxidation using chlorine and reactive oxygen species (ROS). The role of floc adsorption followed by sedimentation or flotation will be quantified, as will the potential for oxidation by electrolytically-generated active chlorine or ROS species. These findings are intended to provide the scientific basis for improved water treatment process design, environmental regulatory framework, and deeper understanding of the potential of related treatment processes, including those that rely on adsorption as well as conventional and advanced oxidation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed effort effort has broader implications for improved water and wastewater infrastructure (with potential for implementation in municipal, household, and emergency potable use scenarios), public health, energy, and the associated economic implications. The work is supported by the Industry Advisory Board as well as individual industry members of the center and has the potential to extend the center's portfolio while potentially attracting new members. This industry-relevant research leverages participation of three PIs with diverse areas of expertise, two graduate student researchers, and industry mentors. Student interest and involvement in STEM education and careers is encouraged by connecting students with the effort's research as well as industry contacts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1433003</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Zitomer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel H Zitomer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.zitomer@mu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142885733</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000209374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brooke Mayer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Brooke.Mayer@marquette.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142882161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000556476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>McNamara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick McNamara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>patrick.mcnamara@marquette.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142887200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000666921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marquette University</Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1881</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046929621</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARQUETTE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006439962</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marquette University]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 1881]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7609</Code>
<Text>IUCRC FUNDAMENTAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7609</Code>
<Text>IUCRC FUNDAMENTAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199679</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Overview</span></strong></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">It is imperative to foster a deeper fundamental understanding of the emerging chemical and microbial contaminants on the Environmental Protection Agency&rsquo;s Contaminant Candidate List (CCL). The pollutants on the CCL are known or believed to occur in public water systems, yet there is currently insufficient knowledge of their risks to public health to support regulatory determinations. Additional data is needed to establish the treatment efficacy of these species, their health impacts, and their occurrence in water systems. This project addressed critical knowledge gaps by elucidating the mechanisms of mitigation of CCL viruses and estrogens using electrocoagulation to treat drinking water. Use of electrocoagulation in drinking water applications has historically been hindered by lack of scientific data, but is rapidly gaining momentum as it offers three potential routes of contaminant mitigation: floc adsorption followed by physical separation via sedimentation or flotation, and oxidation. This research showed that viruses can be physically removed as well as inactivated in the system, while estrogens were primarily removed via oxidation, and secondarily adsorbed to solid floc particles. Thus, electrocoagulation can offer multiple mechanisms of contaminant mitigation for a suite of microbial and chemical contaminants. This research advanced knowledge pertaining to CCL contaminants and their removal mechanisms, and also facilitates improved development and implementation of innovative approaches to drinking water treatment.</span></p> <p><strong><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><strong><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">There is currently little to no data establishing the mechanisms of removal of human enteric viruses and estrogenic micropollutants during electrocoagulation treatment. Existing reports have largely focused on empirical measures of treatment efficacy for surrogate parameters such as MS2 bacteriophage. In order to make informed evaluations of CCL or regulatory status, an improved understanding of the behavior and fate of these contaminants is essential. This study provides the first fundamental assessment of the treatment efficacy of viruses (adenovirus, calicivirus, and enteroviruses [as well as 4 potential bacteriophage virus surrogates]) and 4 CCL estrogens (estrone (E1), 17beta-estradiol (E2), estriol (E3), and 17alpha-ethynylestradiol (EE2)) via electrocoagulation. Understanding of system capabilities has advanced through direct comparisons of electrocoagulation, conventional coagulation, and oxidation using electrochemically-generated chlorine and reactive oxygen species. The roles of adsorption followed by physical separation of solids and oxidation were quantified for viruses and estrogens. The results demonstrate that inactivation, likely due to iron-enhanced oxidation, plays a large role in removal of a number of the viruses, depending on water quality and virus characteristics. Additionally, adsorption plays a secondary role in removing estrogens, whereas oxidation is the dominant estrogen removal pathway with water characteristics having little impact on removal. These findings provide the scientific basis needed to improve water treatment process design, environmental regulatory framework, and deeper understanding of the potential of related treatment processes, including other processes relying on adsorption as well as conventional and advanced oxidation.</span></p> <p><strong><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><strong><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Broader Impacts</span></strong></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">This research advances broader societal outcomes, including improved understanding of CCL virus and estrogen treatability, water and wastewater treatment technologies and developing a globally competitive STEM workforce. The results can be used to develop and implement improved drinking water treatment systems which leverage the concurrent mitigation pathways offered in electrocoagulation treatment. This effort has broader implications for water and wastewater infrastructure (with potential for implementation in municipal, household, and emergency potable use scenarios), public health, and energy, as well as the associated economic implications. </span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Brooke&nbsp;Mayer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  It is imperative to foster a deeper fundamental understanding of the emerging chemical and microbial contaminants on the Environmental Protection Agency?s Contaminant Candidate List (CCL). The pollutants on the CCL are known or believed to occur in public water systems, yet there is currently insufficient knowledge of their risks to public health to support regulatory determinations. Additional data is needed to establish the treatment efficacy of these species, their health impacts, and their occurrence in water systems. This project addressed critical knowledge gaps by elucidating the mechanisms of mitigation of CCL viruses and estrogens using electrocoagulation to treat drinking water. Use of electrocoagulation in drinking water applications has historically been hindered by lack of scientific data, but is rapidly gaining momentum as it offers three potential routes of contaminant mitigation: floc adsorption followed by physical separation via sedimentation or flotation, and oxidation. This research showed that viruses can be physically removed as well as inactivated in the system, while estrogens were primarily removed via oxidation, and secondarily adsorbed to solid floc particles. Thus, electrocoagulation can offer multiple mechanisms of contaminant mitigation for a suite of microbial and chemical contaminants. This research advanced knowledge pertaining to CCL contaminants and their removal mechanisms, and also facilitates improved development and implementation of innovative approaches to drinking water treatment.     Intellectual Merit  There is currently little to no data establishing the mechanisms of removal of human enteric viruses and estrogenic micropollutants during electrocoagulation treatment. Existing reports have largely focused on empirical measures of treatment efficacy for surrogate parameters such as MS2 bacteriophage. In order to make informed evaluations of CCL or regulatory status, an improved understanding of the behavior and fate of these contaminants is essential. This study provides the first fundamental assessment of the treatment efficacy of viruses (adenovirus, calicivirus, and enteroviruses [as well as 4 potential bacteriophage virus surrogates]) and 4 CCL estrogens (estrone (E1), 17beta-estradiol (E2), estriol (E3), and 17alpha-ethynylestradiol (EE2)) via electrocoagulation. Understanding of system capabilities has advanced through direct comparisons of electrocoagulation, conventional coagulation, and oxidation using electrochemically-generated chlorine and reactive oxygen species. The roles of adsorption followed by physical separation of solids and oxidation were quantified for viruses and estrogens. The results demonstrate that inactivation, likely due to iron-enhanced oxidation, plays a large role in removal of a number of the viruses, depending on water quality and virus characteristics. Additionally, adsorption plays a secondary role in removing estrogens, whereas oxidation is the dominant estrogen removal pathway with water characteristics having little impact on removal. These findings provide the scientific basis needed to improve water treatment process design, environmental regulatory framework, and deeper understanding of the potential of related treatment processes, including other processes relying on adsorption as well as conventional and advanced oxidation.     Broader Impacts  This research advances broader societal outcomes, including improved understanding of CCL virus and estrogen treatability, water and wastewater treatment technologies and developing a globally competitive STEM workforce. The results can be used to develop and implement improved drinking water treatment systems which leverage the concurrent mitigation pathways offered in electrocoagulation treatment. This effort has broader implications for water and wastewater infrastructure (with potential for implementation in municipal, household, and emergency potable use scenarios), public health, and energy, as well as the associated economic implications.               Last Modified: 10/30/2017       Submitted by: Brooke Mayer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
