<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - RA:  Glass Capacitors for Energy Storage and Conversion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>333333.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>356850</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Research Alliance project focuses on the translation and transfer of capacitor technology, derived from The Center for Dielectrics and Piezoelectrics expertise and discoveries in new insulating materials. Our glass capacitor technology has market-valued features including miniaturization and high-temperature operation.  These features provide more compact and reliable power conversion systems in electric vehicles and higher temperature electric systems for energy exploration when compared to the leading polymer film capacitors in this market space.   This glass capacitor technology is important because it will lead to higher performance, lower cost and more reliable hybrid electric and plug-in electric vehicles.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The innovation ecosystem that will be enhanced includes Penn State University, PolyK and the Department of Energy.  Penn State provides fundamental process and property knowledge of glass materials. PolyK is a startup company with a focus on the development and commercialization of advanced dielectric materials and smart materials.  The Department of Energy Office of Vehicle Technologies supports industry and national labs in the development of power electronics for hybrid vehicles.  The potential economic impact is expected to be the development of new high-temperature capacitors over the next three years. Graduate and undergraduate students will gain entrepreneurial and technology translation experience through learning about the supply chain from materials to components to systems.   In addition, students will learn about the intellectual property process from the invention disclosure to the issued patent.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application.  This project will establish the scientific and engineering foundations to deliver power electronic capacitors with high energy densities and reliable operation under harsh environments. Over the past decade, the display industry has revolutionized the production of thin glass sheet by down-draw methods.  A quite unexpected application has been found for thin glass dielectrics in the energy conversion arena. The research challenge for new energy storage materials can be distilled into a single figure-of-merit energy density, which captures the vital materials parameters of relative permittivity and dielectric breakdown strength (electric field).  Recently, it has been discovered that glass has among the highest energy densities (up to 35 J/cm3) among all dielectric materials, which will allow for significant capacitor miniaturization.   Glass becomes very flexible as the thickness decreases to the point where roll-to-roll processes becomes possible for manufacturing capacitors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1433993</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Lanagan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael T Lanagan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mxl46@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148656992</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000305787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramakrishnan</FirstName>
<LastName>Rajagopalan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramakrishnan Rajagopalan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rur12@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148631880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000524744</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shihai</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shihai Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>energy@polyktech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5186056897</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000621570</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~333333</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~23517</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ubiquitous nature of glass is apparent in architecture, electronics and transportation.&nbsp; One of the most important attributes of glass is the ability to form useful shapes, spanning a size range from twenty-ton telescope mirrors to microspheres for cancer therapy.&nbsp;&nbsp; Glass fibers have been an indispensable medium for high speed telecommunications for decades.&nbsp;&nbsp; Advances in ultrathin glass substrates have led to breakthroughs in flexible glass panels for displays that continue to revolutionize the way hand-held devices are used.&nbsp; Glass becomes flexible as the thickness decreases and roll-to-roll manufacturing becomes possible for creating display and electrical components (see Figure 1).&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;We have discovered that the electrostatic energy storage capacity of glass is among the highest known for any insulating material. High energy capacitors from thin glass were developed under the Partner for Innovation (PFI) program with the development team: Penn State University, PolyK LLC, and Argonne National Laboratory.</p> <p>The PFI program is affiliated with the NSF/IUCRC Center for Dielectrics and Piezoelectrics.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;As part of the PFI program, the team created a polymer coating technology to increase the flexibility of glass substrates (Figure 2).&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The coated-glass is incorporated into capacitors to increase reliability at high temperature.&nbsp;&nbsp; By the end of the program, it was proven that glass is a superior dielectric material in comparison to standard polypropylene for power capacitors.&nbsp; The high reliability and high temperature operation allows for capacitor miniaturization and that are used in hybrid electric vehicles (Figure 3).&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Intellectual Merit:</em>&nbsp; Knowledge has been advanced the areas of materials, electronic components and power systems.&nbsp; Nanoscale polymer coatings on glass were synthesized and the electrical properties were characterized over a broad temperature range.&nbsp; Fundamental electronic and ionic transport mechanisms were linked to capacitor reliability at high temperature.&nbsp;&nbsp; The superior electrical and thermal performance of glass in combination with the flexibility of thin glass, provides for the possibility of producing capacitors by a continuous roll-to-roll process.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts</em>: There is general agreement within the automotive and power electronics communities that revolutionary approaches, drawing on diverse disciplines, will be necessary to develop the next generation of power systems.&nbsp; In addition to renewable energy sources (solar, wind, etc.), hybrid electric vehicles rely on power converters to transform energy from batteries to motors and to the grid.&nbsp;&nbsp; A major component within the power converter is a DC bus capacitor which contributes a significant fraction of the volume, weight and cost.&nbsp;&nbsp; The focus of the NSF PFI was to create higher reliability capacitor components for power converters that are used in electric vehicles and renewable energy sources.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/21/2019<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;T&nbsp;Lanagan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096001151_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096001151_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096001151_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Lanagan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;T&nbsp;Lanagan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096030513_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096030513_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096030513_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Lanagan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;T&nbsp;Lanagan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096068960_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096068960_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1433993/1433993_10316185_1548096068960_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Lanagan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;T&nbsp;Lanagan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ubiquitous nature of glass is apparent in architecture, electronics and transportation.  One of the most important attributes of glass is the ability to form useful shapes, spanning a size range from twenty-ton telescope mirrors to microspheres for cancer therapy.   Glass fibers have been an indispensable medium for high speed telecommunications for decades.   Advances in ultrathin glass substrates have led to breakthroughs in flexible glass panels for displays that continue to revolutionize the way hand-held devices are used.  Glass becomes flexible as the thickness decreases and roll-to-roll manufacturing becomes possible for creating display and electrical components (see Figure 1).    We have discovered that the electrostatic energy storage capacity of glass is among the highest known for any insulating material. High energy capacitors from thin glass were developed under the Partner for Innovation (PFI) program with the development team: Penn State University, PolyK LLC, and Argonne National Laboratory.  The PFI program is affiliated with the NSF/IUCRC Center for Dielectrics and Piezoelectrics.    As part of the PFI program, the team created a polymer coating technology to increase the flexibility of glass substrates (Figure 2).     The coated-glass is incorporated into capacitors to increase reliability at high temperature.   By the end of the program, it was proven that glass is a superior dielectric material in comparison to standard polypropylene for power capacitors.  The high reliability and high temperature operation allows for capacitor miniaturization and that are used in hybrid electric vehicles (Figure 3).   Intellectual Merit:  Knowledge has been advanced the areas of materials, electronic components and power systems.  Nanoscale polymer coatings on glass were synthesized and the electrical properties were characterized over a broad temperature range.  Fundamental electronic and ionic transport mechanisms were linked to capacitor reliability at high temperature.   The superior electrical and thermal performance of glass in combination with the flexibility of thin glass, provides for the possibility of producing capacitors by a continuous roll-to-roll process.  Broader Impacts: There is general agreement within the automotive and power electronics communities that revolutionary approaches, drawing on diverse disciplines, will be necessary to develop the next generation of power systems.  In addition to renewable energy sources (solar, wind, etc.), hybrid electric vehicles rely on power converters to transform energy from batteries to motors and to the grid.   A major component within the power converter is a DC bus capacitor which contributes a significant fraction of the volume, weight and cost.   The focus of the NSF PFI was to create higher reliability capacitor components for power converters that are used in electric vehicles and renewable energy sources.         Last Modified: 01/21/2019       Submitted by: Michael T Lanagan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
