<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Integrating Complex Choice Behavior into Assortment, Inventory, and Pricing Decisions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gaklutke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Offering a diverse product assortment brings numerous benefits to a firm, such as larger market share, increased customer satisfaction and more repeat purchases.  However, determining the right assortment variety is difficult because products within the assortment maybe complementary or substitutes.  Thus, the demand of each product depends on the availability of all other products in the assortment, complicating inventory planning and pricing decisions.  A diverse product assortment also means that the demand is dispersed among a larger number of products, which may result in increased safety stocks and other additional operational expenses.   Given these complex tradeoffs, how should a firm deal with the operational consequences of product variety and customer choice behavior?   The goal of this project is to develop models and algorithms that allow decision-makers to offer the right assortment of products, stock the right amount of inventory, charge the right prices and sell to the right customer, while taking the customer choice behavior into consideration as they make these decisions.  By studying the state-of-the-art choice models to capture customer choice behavior and by incorporating these choice models into critical operations management problems, the project offers an integrative framework to address assortment planning, inventory management, pricing and product personalization decisions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project covers various problems that apply to numerous industries, with focus on assortment planning, inventory management, pricing, and product personalization decisions. (a) One focus of the project is assortment decisions when inventories are not a limiting concern, which is appropriate when selling products that do not require consumption of physical inventories. The project will develop exact and approximate algorithms to find the right assortment of products to offer under various choice models. (b) Offered assortment determines the demands for the different products, indicating that assortment decisions interact with stocking decisions. The project will study models that make joint assortment offer and stocking decisions, as well as models that make assortment offer decisions under fixed inventory availability. Standard formulations of these models require a separate decision variable for each possible assortment, which can get too many. The goal is to develop compact formulations under different choice models and investigate the structural properties of the optimal assortment. (c) The project covers pricing decisions when customers choose among the offered products. The project will investigate such pricing problems under a variety of choice models and incorporate various constraints on the prices. (d) Developments in availability of real-time data on customers allow personalizing the assortment offering to each customer. The challenge is to quickly assess the choice behavior of each customer and compute the optimal assortment to offer in real time based on choice behavior and inventory availability. The project will study assortment personalization models with performance guarantees and investigate how to incorporate customer forecasts. (e) An important step in building models under customer choice is the estimation of the choice model that drives the choice behavior. The project will investigate how to estimate choice models from sales data. When data is limited, there is a tradeoff between increasing the predictive accuracy by using complex models and over-fitting complex choice models to limited data. An important goal is to derive robust criteria to balance the tradeoffs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1433398</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huseyin</FirstName>
<LastName>Topaloglu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huseyin Topaloglu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ht88@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6469713825</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000202531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1786</Code>
<Text>MANFG ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1787</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>071E</Code>
<Text>MFG ENTERPRISE OPERATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>076E</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1786</Code>
<Text>MANFG ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1787</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9147</Code>
<Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~251000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this research project, we developed operational models and algorithms to help companies decide which assortment of products to offer to their customers, how to make the stocking decisions for these products, and how to set the prices for these products, in environments where the customers choose and substitute among the offered products.&nbsp; There are intricate interactions between the product assortment, inventory, and pricing decisions. For example, offering a diverse product assortment may allow a firm to capture a larger market share, but offering a diverse product assortment may also mean that the demand is dispersed among a larger number of products, which may result in increased safety stocks. Similarly, when customers choose and substitute among the available products, the price of one product may affect the demand for other products, which necessitates making the pricing decisions for all of the products under consideration jointly. We used sophisticated choice models to understand how customers choose and substitute among the available products. These choice models capture the fact that if a product is no longer offered to the customers, then some of the customers will simply leave without a purchase, but some will switch to a substitute product. The key is to incorporate choice models into operational models and algorithms to make product assortment, stocking, and pricing decisions. As we pursue this goal, a critical tradeoff is that while more sophisticated choice models may allow us to capture the customer choice process more accurately, such sophisticated choice models may render the corresponding assortment optimization, stocking, and pricing models intractable.</p> <p>We made contributions along three main dimensions. <em>First, we develop choice models to make up for the shortcomings of the existing ones.</em> For example, a common choice model used in the literature is the so-called the multinomial logit model, which assumes that the utilities that a customer attaches to different products are independent random quantities. Such a choice model does not capture the fact that knowing a customer likes a certain product gives an indication of whether this customer would like other similar products. We developed choice models that capture correlations between the utilities. These choice models allow the firm to understand what other products would be desirable for a customer given that she declared interest in a particular product.</p> <p><em>Second, we solve operational problems under the choice models that we develop.</em> An important question for many retailers is to choose the right assortment of products to offer to their customers. For brick-and-mortar retailers, the assortment of products offered to the customers is relatively static and remains on the shelf for some duration of time. For electronic retailers, the assortment of products offered to the customers is highly dynamic and it can be customized for each customer depending on what is known about the tastes of the customer and the remaining inventories of products. The problem of finding the revenue-maximizing assortment of products to offer is often a combinatorial, nonlinear optimization problem. We developed approximation algorithms with provable performance guarantees. Furthermore, as we incorporate the dynamic arrivals of the customers into the system, these problems take the form of control problems under uncertainty. We developed approximate dynamic programming algorithms with, again, provable performance guarantees.</p> <p><em>Third, we develop tractable methods to estimate the parameters of the choice models from the past purchase histories collected by the firms.</em> One of the critical challenges in estimating the parameters of the choice models is that if there is no purchase in the data over a certain duration of time, then it is not possible to know whether there were simply no customer arrivals or the arriving customers ended up not purchasing anything. We developed expectation-maximization algorithms that are able to discover the utilities that a customer attaches to the products and to the no-purchase option, even when the data does not clearly label the customers who do not make purchases. We validated our expectation-maximization algorithms on real data sets.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Huseyin&nbsp;Topaloglu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this research project, we developed operational models and algorithms to help companies decide which assortment of products to offer to their customers, how to make the stocking decisions for these products, and how to set the prices for these products, in environments where the customers choose and substitute among the offered products.  There are intricate interactions between the product assortment, inventory, and pricing decisions. For example, offering a diverse product assortment may allow a firm to capture a larger market share, but offering a diverse product assortment may also mean that the demand is dispersed among a larger number of products, which may result in increased safety stocks. Similarly, when customers choose and substitute among the available products, the price of one product may affect the demand for other products, which necessitates making the pricing decisions for all of the products under consideration jointly. We used sophisticated choice models to understand how customers choose and substitute among the available products. These choice models capture the fact that if a product is no longer offered to the customers, then some of the customers will simply leave without a purchase, but some will switch to a substitute product. The key is to incorporate choice models into operational models and algorithms to make product assortment, stocking, and pricing decisions. As we pursue this goal, a critical tradeoff is that while more sophisticated choice models may allow us to capture the customer choice process more accurately, such sophisticated choice models may render the corresponding assortment optimization, stocking, and pricing models intractable.  We made contributions along three main dimensions. First, we develop choice models to make up for the shortcomings of the existing ones. For example, a common choice model used in the literature is the so-called the multinomial logit model, which assumes that the utilities that a customer attaches to different products are independent random quantities. Such a choice model does not capture the fact that knowing a customer likes a certain product gives an indication of whether this customer would like other similar products. We developed choice models that capture correlations between the utilities. These choice models allow the firm to understand what other products would be desirable for a customer given that she declared interest in a particular product.  Second, we solve operational problems under the choice models that we develop. An important question for many retailers is to choose the right assortment of products to offer to their customers. For brick-and-mortar retailers, the assortment of products offered to the customers is relatively static and remains on the shelf for some duration of time. For electronic retailers, the assortment of products offered to the customers is highly dynamic and it can be customized for each customer depending on what is known about the tastes of the customer and the remaining inventories of products. The problem of finding the revenue-maximizing assortment of products to offer is often a combinatorial, nonlinear optimization problem. We developed approximation algorithms with provable performance guarantees. Furthermore, as we incorporate the dynamic arrivals of the customers into the system, these problems take the form of control problems under uncertainty. We developed approximate dynamic programming algorithms with, again, provable performance guarantees.  Third, we develop tractable methods to estimate the parameters of the choice models from the past purchase histories collected by the firms. One of the critical challenges in estimating the parameters of the choice models is that if there is no purchase in the data over a certain duration of time, then it is not possible to know whether there were simply no customer arrivals or the arriving customers ended up not purchasing anything. We developed expectation-maximization algorithms that are able to discover the utilities that a customer attaches to the products and to the no-purchase option, even when the data does not clearly label the customers who do not make purchases. We validated our expectation-maximization algorithms on real data sets.       Last Modified: 11/02/2017       Submitted by: Huseyin Topaloglu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
