<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EFRI 2-DARE Proposal: Spin-Valley Coupling for Photonic and Spintronic Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1602874</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>plane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical: The performance and capabilities of key present solid-state technologies, such as light-emitting diodes, solar cells, and other electro-optic components, are ultimately constrained by the fundamental properties of conventional semiconductors such as silicon and gallium arsenide. Monolayers of the layered transition-metal dichalcogenides (with formula MX2, such as MoS2 and WSe2) have recently been discovered to be a new class of semiconductors effectively at the atomically thin limit. They have dramatically different fundamental properties which can defy previous constraints, allowing observation and discovery of new physical phenomena and offering potential for unprecendented solid-state device possibilities. Fundamentally new properties in MX2 include the relationship between electron spin, the "valley index" specifying which of two equivalent momentum states the electron occupies in the 2D lattice, and the "layer index" specifying which layer the electron is in when two monolayers form a bilayer. The spin, valley and layer quantum numbers in this material are linked and can be manipulated jointly, as has already been demonstrated theoretically and experimentally by the investigators. The proposed work aims to study all aspects of this "spin-valley-layer coupling", ranging from its role in electrical transport to its interplay with optical cavities, with a view to novel yet practical device technologies with electrical, magnetic, and optical control. The work will be done by a mixed team of physics and engineers and will provide interdisciplinary research education to a large number of graduate and undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: In monolayer MX2 the strong spin-orbit coupling locks the real spin at the band edges to the valley index to produce spin-valley coupling. At the same time the valleys, and hence spins, are addressable using circularly polarized optical selection rules. Additionally, in bilayers and heterostructures the valley index is further coupled to the layer index for a given valley index, leading to new magnetoelectric effects. MX2s thus provide the first solid-state system in which electric and dynamical control of combined valley pseudospin and real spin are possible, opening up a wealth of hybrid spin and valley device possibilities. The focus of the proposed work is on the studying the unique spin, valley and layer pseudospin couplings in MX2 monolayers, bilayers and heterostructures with photonic and spintronic device applications in mind. The specific goals and methods are as follows: (1) develop microscopic theories for coupled spin-valley-charge transport to guide and model the experimental efforts and synthesis of monolayers, bilayers, heterostructures, and hybrid systems; (2) develop highest quality, large-area crystal growth with controllable charged and magnetic dopants; (3) combine electrical and optical investigation of intrinsic spin and valley properties to determine the fundamental parameters of monolayers and bilayers in various device geometries for hybrid spin-valleytronics; (4) investigate and demonstrate manipulation of spin and valley polarizations in heterostructures and hybrid photonic devices combining MX2s with structures such as photonic-crystal cavities, addressing aspects including spin-valley-charge transport across interfaces, interlayer exciton physics, exciton-polaritons in integrated cavity structures, and strong photon-valley exciton interactions within a nanocavity; and (5) develop MX2 lateral junction devices for efficient, controllable, and spin and valley specific light emitters, modulators and detectors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1433496</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Cobden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David H Cobden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cobden@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065432686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490387</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Mandrus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Mandrus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmandrus@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743609</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaodong Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xuxd@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065438444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000580398</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Di</FirstName>
<LastName>Xiao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Di Xiao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dixiao@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122689527</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650160</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arka</FirstName>
<LastName>Majumdar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arka Majumdar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arka@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066165558</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655939</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951560</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097E</Code>
<Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>107E</Code>
<Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~102874</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-66c51fc1-7fff-d893-6e88-8a06df21b356"><span>The goals of the project were to develop theories of the optical and electrical response of MX2 monolayers and bilayers, junctions, heterostructures and field-effect devices; to optimize growth and device fabrication; to investigate the range of physics rooted in the spin-valley coupling in monolayers and spin-valley-layer coupling in bilayers for spin-valleytronics and memory devices and to use hybrid photonic devices combining MX2 with structures such as photonic-crystal cavities, waveguides, and other materials for optical switching, mode and index control, and high speed electrical control. Numerous phenomena were investigated in a wide range of two-dimensional (2D) materials. Progress was made in the study of valley excitons in transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) and heterostructures; exploration of light-matter interactions in 2D magnets and potential new magnetoelectric schemes; coupling of 2D excitons with nanocavities and achieving strongly enhanced light-matter interaction using photonic crystal cavities; and exploration of photon blockade in the presence of strong absorptive loss from 2D materials. The development of techniques for making devices of air-sensitive materials under the grant enabled the first experimental investigations of 2D van der Waals magnets and topological insulators. It was found that the topological semimetal WTe2 exhibits the quantum spin Hall effect and gate-tuned superconductivity in monolayer form and ferroelectricity when in 2 or more layers, making it the first van der Waals ferroelectric and the first metallic ferroelectric. The remarkable variety of effects described above could be useful, either separately or in concert, for efficient multifunctional device applications in communication, computing and sensing. Thirteen graduate students and twenty undergraduate students received training under the grant.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/20/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;H&nbsp;Cobden</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of the project were to develop theories of the optical and electrical response of MX2 monolayers and bilayers, junctions, heterostructures and field-effect devices; to optimize growth and device fabrication; to investigate the range of physics rooted in the spin-valley coupling in monolayers and spin-valley-layer coupling in bilayers for spin-valleytronics and memory devices and to use hybrid photonic devices combining MX2 with structures such as photonic-crystal cavities, waveguides, and other materials for optical switching, mode and index control, and high speed electrical control. Numerous phenomena were investigated in a wide range of two-dimensional (2D) materials. Progress was made in the study of valley excitons in transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) and heterostructures; exploration of light-matter interactions in 2D magnets and potential new magnetoelectric schemes; coupling of 2D excitons with nanocavities and achieving strongly enhanced light-matter interaction using photonic crystal cavities; and exploration of photon blockade in the presence of strong absorptive loss from 2D materials. The development of techniques for making devices of air-sensitive materials under the grant enabled the first experimental investigations of 2D van der Waals magnets and topological insulators. It was found that the topological semimetal WTe2 exhibits the quantum spin Hall effect and gate-tuned superconductivity in monolayer form and ferroelectricity when in 2 or more layers, making it the first van der Waals ferroelectric and the first metallic ferroelectric. The remarkable variety of effects described above could be useful, either separately or in concert, for efficient multifunctional device applications in communication, computing and sensing. Thirteen graduate students and twenty undergraduate students received training under the grant.       Last Modified: 12/20/2018       Submitted by: David H Cobden]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
