<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Digital East St. Louis: An Urban Place-Based Learning Model to Promote Information Technology and Computer Science Career Interests of Minority Youth</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>846460.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>846460</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amy Baylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abaylor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925126</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A high quality, technical workforce requires that students, particularly those from underserved populations, have innovative experiences with computational tools and informational technology.  The main goal of this Strategies project is to experiment with new content and methods for engaging students who are underrepresented in STEM fields in the computing sciences via a place- based curriculum that asks students critical questions about the environment and culture of their own region. Working with East St. Louis teachers and project partners, students will produce a richly annotated web-based community map with associated images, texts, audio and video that highlight features and events deemed important by students and the community.  Partners include the Southern Illinois University (SIUE) STEM Center, the Interdisciplinary Research and Informatics Scholarship Center, and Curriculum and Instruction Center, the Department of Historical Studies, the Black Studies Program as well as the Virtual East St. Louis Historical Society, Harris Stowe State University and the East St. Louis School district.  Beginning in the sixth grade, a cohort of 40 students will progress though a three-year out-of-school program in which they will engage in increasingly complex projects that involve the use of information technology and computing tools.   Expected outcomes for the students include increased student self-efficacy, enhanced technological skills, and awareness of IT and computing careers.  The project will also provide extensive professional development for six teachers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will conduct a longitudinal quasi experiment that will follow students through the three years of their participation, including the transition to high school.  Data will also be collected from a comparison group, allowing for an assessment of any outcome differences from the student cohort participating in the program. Program evaluation data for answering research questions and assessing progress on the project objectives will be collected using instrumentation specifically designed for this study. Data sources include (a) student pre-/post-STEM questionnaires; (b) student interviews; (c) observations of program activities; (d) student-created artifacts; (e) annual coursework/career intentions questionnaires; and (f) parent/caregiver questionnaires and/or interviews.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1433660</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Locke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon M Locke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slocke@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186503452</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000172627</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liza</FirstName>
<LastName>Cummings</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liza Cummings</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lcummin@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186503459</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000665363</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>DeSpain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica DeSpain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdespai@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186502151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000665551</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville</Name>
<CityName>Edwardsville</CityName>
<ZipCode>620250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6186503010</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Campus Box 1046</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006331342</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>143941909</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville]]></Name>
<CityName>Edwardsville</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>620250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Campus Box 1046]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~846460</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Place-based education is the study of a place (local or regional) using a teaching method that emphasizes students asking questions, solving real-world problems, and using field work to gather information in a local setting. The Digital East St. Louis project took the stance that place-based learning in an urban environment empowers students to connect to their community and increases student engagement and understanding. Urban settings offer rich learning opportunities through examination of the relationship between humans and the built environment and cultural and environmental city histories. Such learning also has the potential to contribute to community well-being. Digital humanities is an innovative methodology for analyzing longstanding research questions in related fields. This digital research is often interdisciplinary in nature. It can involve the creation of dynamic online exhibits or archives or the development of new digital tools for analyzing languages, literature, images, spaces, and historical periods. These projects use the digital medium to offer audiences new insights.</p> <p>Digital East St. Louis combined the digital humanities with a place-based approach to interest middle-school students in content first in order to inspire their use of digital tools and interest in information technology and computing careers. Participants were thirty-three African American middle school students who attended the three-year out-of-school program for various durations and 20 African American high school students who participated in an after-school digital humanities club. Additionally, six middle/high school educators received over 500 hours of intensive training to teach using project-based learning, student-driven digital research, HTML/CSS coding projects, and digital humanities tools. These tools included Omeka, an open-source platform used by scholars for creating online archives.</p> <p>The project team conducted research using interviews, focus groups, and surveys to determine the program?s impacts on the youth participants. Interviews revealed that students thought they were able to show the world many good things about their community and disprove negative perceptions and stereotypes. Allowing students to choose topics of interest about their community on which to create their digital exhibit provided a degree of personal relevance that kept students coming to the program. This increased attendance gave students more opportunities to use the various technologies, helping them to gain experience and expertise. Students felt that coding typified a basic and essential technology skill, and that coding was a way to design and build meaningful and useful projects. Through the creation of websites, podcasts, and videos, students expanded their awareness of how using technology could be creative, artistic, and useful in careers.</p> <p>The project developed a modular curriculum that teachers, youth group organizers, and after-school program coordinators can adapt to their place of learning and student interests. Though the place-based model was a central element of the project design, any topic that gets students excited about using technology to communicate with others can be a starting point for the curriculum. The curriculum can be downloaded at <a href="https://eaststlouisculture.siue.edu/omeka/curriculum" target="_blank">https://eaststlouisculture.siue.edu/omeka/curriculum</a>. The project also created tools for assessing student learning and student outcomes in the areas of community, careers, technology, and digital humanities. These tools are available for use by other researchers by contacting the principal investigators.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2020<br>      Modified by: Sharon&nbsp;M&nbsp;Locke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Place-based education is the study of a place (local or regional) using a teaching method that emphasizes students asking questions, solving real-world problems, and using field work to gather information in a local setting. The Digital East St. Louis project took the stance that place-based learning in an urban environment empowers students to connect to their community and increases student engagement and understanding. Urban settings offer rich learning opportunities through examination of the relationship between humans and the built environment and cultural and environmental city histories. Such learning also has the potential to contribute to community well-being. Digital humanities is an innovative methodology for analyzing longstanding research questions in related fields. This digital research is often interdisciplinary in nature. It can involve the creation of dynamic online exhibits or archives or the development of new digital tools for analyzing languages, literature, images, spaces, and historical periods. These projects use the digital medium to offer audiences new insights.  Digital East St. Louis combined the digital humanities with a place-based approach to interest middle-school students in content first in order to inspire their use of digital tools and interest in information technology and computing careers. Participants were thirty-three African American middle school students who attended the three-year out-of-school program for various durations and 20 African American high school students who participated in an after-school digital humanities club. Additionally, six middle/high school educators received over 500 hours of intensive training to teach using project-based learning, student-driven digital research, HTML/CSS coding projects, and digital humanities tools. These tools included Omeka, an open-source platform used by scholars for creating online archives.  The project team conducted research using interviews, focus groups, and surveys to determine the program?s impacts on the youth participants. Interviews revealed that students thought they were able to show the world many good things about their community and disprove negative perceptions and stereotypes. Allowing students to choose topics of interest about their community on which to create their digital exhibit provided a degree of personal relevance that kept students coming to the program. This increased attendance gave students more opportunities to use the various technologies, helping them to gain experience and expertise. Students felt that coding typified a basic and essential technology skill, and that coding was a way to design and build meaningful and useful projects. Through the creation of websites, podcasts, and videos, students expanded their awareness of how using technology could be creative, artistic, and useful in careers.  The project developed a modular curriculum that teachers, youth group organizers, and after-school program coordinators can adapt to their place of learning and student interests. Though the place-based model was a central element of the project design, any topic that gets students excited about using technology to communicate with others can be a starting point for the curriculum. The curriculum can be downloaded at https://eaststlouisculture.siue.edu/omeka/curriculum. The project also created tools for assessing student learning and student outcomes in the areas of community, careers, technology, and digital humanities. These tools are available for use by other researchers by contacting the principal investigators.       Last Modified: 01/10/2020       Submitted by: Sharon M Locke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
