<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Work-Family Policies and Working Mothers: A Cross-National Comparative Study</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11785.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11785</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>SES-1434863&lt;br/&gt;Jennifer Glass&lt;br/&gt;Caitlyn Collins&lt;br/&gt;The University of Texas at Austin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In all industrialized countries, women have entered the paid labor force in unprecedented numbers over the past half-century while still maintaining primary responsibility for childrearing. Today, the majority of mothers with children are in the paid labor force. This study investigates how working mothers in the western world balance their work and family obligations. The investigators will conduct 100 in-depth interviews with working mothers from four countries: Germany, Sweden, Italy, and the United States¬. They will examine how different ideals of motherhood and gender equality are embedded in the work-family policy regimes of these four countries. Given their different policy regimes, the research examines how working mothers negotiate the constraints and opportunities facing them daily as they balance motherhood and employment. Interview topics include: workplace interactions with supervisors and colleagues, employment history and future plans, the transition to parenthood, use and perceptions of various work-family policies, conflict between work and home responsibilities, dividing family care with a partner, opinions about parenting, interpretations and understandings of their careers and families, personal successes and regrets, and general views on the status of working mothers in their respective countries.  This research is potentially the first comparative study to incorporate mothers' voices into the scholarly debates about work-family policy around the world. Understanding women's perspectives about what works (and what hinders) their achievement of work-family balance should be central to any scholarly endeavor to craft, advocate for, and implement work-family policy as a force for social change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Findings from this project will contribute to policy debates about improving mothers' work and family lives in 21st century Western industrialized countries. With many countries spending a sizeable portion of their GDP on work-family policies, this study will provide crucial insight into the most effective targets for these expenditures, benefitting both mothers and governments. This project will provide vital knowledge for policy debates about how to better support mothers in their careers and families given that the vast majority of mothers participate in the globalized economy while raising children today.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1434863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Glass</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer L Glass</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jennifer-Glass@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3196216304</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000374200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caitlyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Collins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Caitlyn M Collins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>c.collins@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5038804085</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662061</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~11785</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Despite women&rsquo;s common struggles to balance motherhood and employment, western countries have responded with drastically different work-family policies. These policies include paid parental leave, affordable universal childcare and healthcare, part-time and flexible work, and cash allowances to parents, among others. The goal of this research was to examine how middle-income working mothers in Germany, Sweden, Italy, and the United States perceive these work-family policies in their daily lives. This NSF Grant funded the Italy portion of this study.</p> <p>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>We conducted in-depth interviews in Rome, Italy with working mothers and spent time with women in their homes, workplaces, and neighborhoods, meeting their children, partners, colleagues, and friends when invited to do so. The Italian mothers we spoke with were largely unwavering in their disappointment at the government&rsquo;s unreliability as a source of support. Italy has a relatively weak welfare state, and the traditional breadwinner/ homemaker family model, heavy Catholic influence, and strong intergenerational solidarity amongst Italians mean that families are expected to provide the support and protection citizens need if and when the government fails. Many of the work-family policies in Italy are helpful in theory but not in practice in the eyes of respondents.</p> <p>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Legal protections surrounding pregnancy and childbirth did not always prevent women from being pushed out. Half the women lamented the lack of space in high quality public daycare, or found their opening hours were far too short and inflexible. All Italian respondents felt that gender equality in earning and caring should be a given, but few actually achieved it. The available parental leave could legally be used by both parents, but was overwhelmingly used only by mothers. Although Italian women had far more policy supports than the American mothers I interviewed, they perceived the Italian welfare state as a broken system. In response, Italian interviewees tried to solve the tension between their work and family lives in two ways: by 1) &ldquo;working the system&rdquo; or 2) outsourcing some of their responsibilities to housekeepers, babysitters, and grandparents. Women felt they had to be proactive, entrepreneurial, and creative in seeking out their own solutions. They placed blame for their inability to balance their work and family commitments squarely on the shoulders of employers and the state and rarely blamed themselves or their partners for their work-family conflict.</p> <p>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Overall, we find that work-family policies may be ineffective at helping women resolve the incompatibility between women and work if (a) they are unevenly or unreliably implemented; (b) they are enacted in an unsupportive cultural environment; and (c) when they are used unevenly by men and women. Across all four countries, mothers were in agreement that the policies most helpful in reducing their work-family conflict were high-quality, affordable childcare, moderate-length parental leave with a high wage replacement, and policies aimed to explicitly encourage men&rsquo;s involvement in childrearing. Because these policies are not currently offered in the U.S., and the American mothers we interviewed as a group experienced more stress, exhaustion, and conflict trying to reconcile paid work and childrearing compared to our European respondents, these three policies are promising targets for public expenditures.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2015<br>      Modified by: Caitlyn&nbsp;M&nbsp;Collins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Despite womenÆs common struggles to balance motherhood and employment, western countries have responded with drastically different work-family policies. These policies include paid parental leave, affordable universal childcare and healthcare, part-time and flexible work, and cash allowances to parents, among others. The goal of this research was to examine how middle-income working mothers in Germany, Sweden, Italy, and the United States perceive these work-family policies in their daily lives. This NSF Grant funded the Italy portion of this study.    We conducted in-depth interviews in Rome, Italy with working mothers and spent time with women in their homes, workplaces, and neighborhoods, meeting their children, partners, colleagues, and friends when invited to do so. The Italian mothers we spoke with were largely unwavering in their disappointment at the governmentÆs unreliability as a source of support. Italy has a relatively weak welfare state, and the traditional breadwinner/ homemaker family model, heavy Catholic influence, and strong intergenerational solidarity amongst Italians mean that families are expected to provide the support and protection citizens need if and when the government fails. Many of the work-family policies in Italy are helpful in theory but not in practice in the eyes of respondents.    Legal protections surrounding pregnancy and childbirth did not always prevent women from being pushed out. Half the women lamented the lack of space in high quality public daycare, or found their opening hours were far too short and inflexible. All Italian respondents felt that gender equality in earning and caring should be a given, but few actually achieved it. The available parental leave could legally be used by both parents, but was overwhelmingly used only by mothers. Although Italian women had far more policy supports than the American mothers I interviewed, they perceived the Italian welfare state as a broken system. In response, Italian interviewees tried to solve the tension between their work and family lives in two ways: by 1) "working the system" or 2) outsourcing some of their responsibilities to housekeepers, babysitters, and grandparents. Women felt they had to be proactive, entrepreneurial, and creative in seeking out their own solutions. They placed blame for their inability to balance their work and family commitments squarely on the shoulders of employers and the state and rarely blamed themselves or their partners for their work-family conflict.    Overall, we find that work-family policies may be ineffective at helping women resolve the incompatibility between women and work if (a) they are unevenly or unreliably implemented; (b) they are enacted in an unsupportive cultural environment; and (c) when they are used unevenly by men and women. Across all four countries, mothers were in agreement that the policies most helpful in reducing their work-family conflict were high-quality, affordable childcare, moderate-length parental leave with a high wage replacement, and policies aimed to explicitly encourage menÆs involvement in childrearing. Because these policies are not currently offered in the U.S., and the American mothers we interviewed as a group experienced more stress, exhaustion, and conflict trying to reconcile paid work and childrearing compared to our European respondents, these three policies are promising targets for public expenditures.           Last Modified: 09/23/2015       Submitted by: Caitlyn M Collins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
