<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DMREF/Collaborative Research: Designing Tunable Au-Based Bimetallic Nanocatalysts</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>287118.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>287118</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy Patten</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tpatten@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Division of Chemistry, through the Designing Materials to Revolutionize and Engineer our Future (DMREF) Program, Professor James Lewis of West Virginia University and Professor Rongchao Jin of Carnegie-Mellon University are studying how to make new, precisely defined metal alloy catalysts.  The chemical industry relies on inexpensive and re-usable catalysts to convert chemical feedstock into viable products. In addition, reducing harmful byproducts in combustion processes (e.g. carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide) also requires inexpensive and re-usable catalysts, such as those found in a catalytic converter of an automobile. Gold-based catalysts at the size of a few nanometers in diameter are proven to be very efficient in many chemically converting processes; however, they are expensive particularly, as the price of gold continues to increase over time. Mixing in other less expensive metal constituents, such as copper, would drive down the cost and possibly increase activity in some cases, but the scientific challenge is to determine how to add in such metals without losing the efficiency and stability of the catalyst. Computational searching algorithms are being developed to assist the materials development of catalysts of gold mixed with other metals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team is comprehensively advancing both technical and conceptual understanding of the structure-function mapping in bi-metallic catalysts. They are building a guidance framework to design and develop bimetallic catalysts from first principles rather than trial-and-error by decreasing the number of potential nanoparticles for tests to an experimentally manageable number. The proposed research will continue to impact energy technologies that are currently being pursued by experienced researchers at the National Energy Technology Laboratory. In terms of the broader impacts of this proposed research, the current interdisciplinary collaborations will boost regional outreach and educational impact for students. Lewis and Jin are continuing to engage under-represented student populations in their research programs and they will continue to cultivate broadened participation for student's professional preparations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1434486</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rongchao</FirstName>
<LastName>Jin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rongchao Jin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rongchao@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122689448</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000302790</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8676</Code>
<Text>Critical Elements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~287118</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merits:</strong></p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The central goal of this project is to investigate atomically precise metal nanoclusters for catalysis. The catalytic activity of small particles arises from several factors such as high surface-to-volume ratio, surface geometric effect and electronic effects. However, the elusive surface structure of conventional nanoparticles poses a major challenge in fundamental studies due to the polydispersity issue. This motivated the creation of atomically precise nanoclusters for fundamental studies of catalysis.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In this project, aromatic-thiolate-protected 25-atom nanoclusters, formulated [Au<sub>25</sub>(SNap)<sub>18</sub>]<sup>-</sup><sup> </sup>(where SNap = 1-naphthalenethiolate), are synthesized and characterized by X-ray crystallography and further investigated for carbon-carbon coupling reactions. The introduction of aromatic ligand is found to modulate the electronic structure of the cluster and largely enhance the catalytic activity/selectivity in the Ullmann hetero-coupling reaction as compared to other Au<sub>25</sub>(SR)<sub>18</sub> with R = CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>Ph and<em> n</em>-C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>13</sub>. This study offers guidelines for tailoring nanocluster properties by ligand engineering and also sheds light on the structure-activity relationships of the Au<sub>25</sub> nanoclusters.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Doping gold nanoclusters with a second type of metal is a powerful method for tuning the physicochemical properties of nanoclusters at atomic level and provides opportunities for fundamental understanding of alloying rules as well as new applications. In this project, bimetal 25-atom nanoclusters (e.g. Ag, Cu, Pd, Pt, and Hg doped) are prepared and investigated for catalysis. In the styrene oxidation reaction, different types of dopants are found to increase the conversion of styrene or the product selectivity. In the reduction of 4-nitrobenzaldehyde with H<sub>2</sub>, both Au<sub>25</sub> and doped nanoclusters show 100% chemoselectivity towards 4-nitrobenzyl alcohol, whereas the doped nanoclusters show enhanced activity. Mercury doping is particularly effective in booting the activity.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Silver is known to alloy with gold at any ratio (0 to 100%), resulting in a distribution of the number of Ag dopants in Au/Ag alloy nanoclusters (e.g. Ag<sub>x</sub>Au<sub>25-x</sub>), thus, doping with a specific number of Ag atoms remains a challenge. In this project, a new method has been developed for single Ag atom doping, which consists of steps of hollowing and refilling. This sequence gives rise to single-Ag doped nanoclusters. In addition, this strategy is also applicable to copper doping. A one-phase strategy is further devised for achieving heavy doping of Ag into Au<sub>25</sub>(SR)<sub>18</sub> nanoclusters. This strategy overcomes the light doping of silver by previous methods. X-ray crystallographic analysis has mapped out that Ag dopants are distributed in both the icosahedral M<sub>13</sub> core and the six S-Ag-S-Ag(Au)-S staple motifs, with the composition of the product determined to be [Ag<sub>x</sub>Au<sub>25-x</sub>(SC<sub>6</sub>H<sub>11</sub>)<sub>18</sub>]<sup>&ndash;</sup> with x~21. Computational analysis (collaboration with J. Lewis) on the preferred Ag doping sites is consistent with experimental results. Furthermore, the electrocatalytic performance of such heavily Ag-doped nanoclusters is investigated for oxygen reduction in alkaline solutions.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Building on the success in Au<sub>25</sub> and bimetal nanoclusters, the cluster size effect is investigated using the structurally characterized Au<sub>38</sub>(SR)<sub>24</sub> (R= SC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>Ph) nanoclusters for the three-component coupling of an aldehyde, an alkyne and an amine (generally called A<sup>3</sup>-coupling). The A<sup>3</sup>-coupling reaction is an important process for the synthesis of propargylamines &mdash; highly valuable synthetic building blocks for the synthesis of natural products and biologically active compounds. High catalytic efficiency (yield &gt;98%) is obtained, even with a very low loading (0.01 mol %). Spectroscopic characterization of the catalyst after the A<sup>3</sup>-coupling reaction confirmed that the Au<sub>38</sub>(SC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>Ph)<sub>24</sub> cluster is intact. To gain further insight, ligand-off Au<sub>38</sub> clusters supported on CeO<sub>2</sub> is made by a thermal method.<sup> </sup>The catalytic performance of the ligand-off Au<sub>38</sub>/CeO<sub>2</sub> is found to drop significantly compared with the ligand-on Au<sub>38</sub>(SC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>Ph)<sub>24</sub>. The results imply a synergetic effect betweem the electron-deficient surface (i.e. Au<sup>&delta;+</sup>, 0&lt;&delta;<sup>+</sup>&lt;1) and electron-rich Au<sub>23</sub> core of ligand-protected nanoclusters, which is critical for the A<sup>3</sup>-coupling reaction.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Overall, the synthetic strategies and the nanocluster materials developed in this project hold great promise in catalysis. Their precise size and well defined atomic structure permit fundamental studies on the catalytic mechanism at an unprecedented level, that is, <em>atom-by-atom</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The project results were conveyed by PI Jin and his students at ACS national meetings (2016 Fall in Philadelphia and 2017 Fall in Washington DC), with the number of people impacted by the work (attendees at conferences) estimated to be about 500. The research results from the project were also incorporated into the courses (&ldquo;Nanoparticles&rdquo; and &ldquo;Introduction to Sustainable Energy&rdquo;) taught by Jin. Jin also designed a lab module for both undergraduate and high school students. In addition, PI Jin was invited to give a number of seminars during the NSF funding period. Three graduate students were trained (partial support). One has successfully obtained a MS degree, one with a PhD degree, and another approaching a PhD degree.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The collaborative process greatly enhanced the project outcomes in both the experimental work (the discovery of new Au-Ag bimetal nanoclusters and the Au-Ag synergy in catalytic reactions) and the optimization of the FIREBALL software package.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Rongchao&nbsp;Jin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merits:   The central goal of this project is to investigate atomically precise metal nanoclusters for catalysis. The catalytic activity of small particles arises from several factors such as high surface-to-volume ratio, surface geometric effect and electronic effects. However, the elusive surface structure of conventional nanoparticles poses a major challenge in fundamental studies due to the polydispersity issue. This motivated the creation of atomically precise nanoclusters for fundamental studies of catalysis.   In this project, aromatic-thiolate-protected 25-atom nanoclusters, formulated [Au25(SNap)18]- (where SNap = 1-naphthalenethiolate), are synthesized and characterized by X-ray crystallography and further investigated for carbon-carbon coupling reactions. The introduction of aromatic ligand is found to modulate the electronic structure of the cluster and largely enhance the catalytic activity/selectivity in the Ullmann hetero-coupling reaction as compared to other Au25(SR)18 with R = CH2CH2Ph and n-C6H13. This study offers guidelines for tailoring nanocluster properties by ligand engineering and also sheds light on the structure-activity relationships of the Au25 nanoclusters.   Doping gold nanoclusters with a second type of metal is a powerful method for tuning the physicochemical properties of nanoclusters at atomic level and provides opportunities for fundamental understanding of alloying rules as well as new applications. In this project, bimetal 25-atom nanoclusters (e.g. Ag, Cu, Pd, Pt, and Hg doped) are prepared and investigated for catalysis. In the styrene oxidation reaction, different types of dopants are found to increase the conversion of styrene or the product selectivity. In the reduction of 4-nitrobenzaldehyde with H2, both Au25 and doped nanoclusters show 100% chemoselectivity towards 4-nitrobenzyl alcohol, whereas the doped nanoclusters show enhanced activity. Mercury doping is particularly effective in booting the activity.   Silver is known to alloy with gold at any ratio (0 to 100%), resulting in a distribution of the number of Ag dopants in Au/Ag alloy nanoclusters (e.g. AgxAu25-x), thus, doping with a specific number of Ag atoms remains a challenge. In this project, a new method has been developed for single Ag atom doping, which consists of steps of hollowing and refilling. This sequence gives rise to single-Ag doped nanoclusters. In addition, this strategy is also applicable to copper doping. A one-phase strategy is further devised for achieving heavy doping of Ag into Au25(SR)18 nanoclusters. This strategy overcomes the light doping of silver by previous methods. X-ray crystallographic analysis has mapped out that Ag dopants are distributed in both the icosahedral M13 core and the six S-Ag-S-Ag(Au)-S staple motifs, with the composition of the product determined to be [AgxAu25-x(SC6H11)18]&ndash; with x~21. Computational analysis (collaboration with J. Lewis) on the preferred Ag doping sites is consistent with experimental results. Furthermore, the electrocatalytic performance of such heavily Ag-doped nanoclusters is investigated for oxygen reduction in alkaline solutions.   Building on the success in Au25 and bimetal nanoclusters, the cluster size effect is investigated using the structurally characterized Au38(SR)24 (R= SC2H4Ph) nanoclusters for the three-component coupling of an aldehyde, an alkyne and an amine (generally called A3-coupling). The A3-coupling reaction is an important process for the synthesis of propargylamines &mdash; highly valuable synthetic building blocks for the synthesis of natural products and biologically active compounds. High catalytic efficiency (yield &gt;98%) is obtained, even with a very low loading (0.01 mol %). Spectroscopic characterization of the catalyst after the A3-coupling reaction confirmed that the Au38(SC2H4Ph)24 cluster is intact. To gain further insight, ligand-off Au38 clusters supported on CeO2 is made by a thermal method. The catalytic performance of the ligand-off Au38/CeO2 is found to drop significantly compared with the ligand-on Au38(SC2H4Ph)24. The results imply a synergetic effect betweem the electron-deficient surface (i.e. Au&delta;+, 0&lt;&delta;+&lt;1) and electron-rich Au23 core of ligand-protected nanoclusters, which is critical for the A3-coupling reaction.   Overall, the synthetic strategies and the nanocluster materials developed in this project hold great promise in catalysis. Their precise size and well defined atomic structure permit fundamental studies on the catalytic mechanism at an unprecedented level, that is, atom-by-atom.     Broader Impacts:   The project results were conveyed by PI Jin and his students at ACS national meetings (2016 Fall in Philadelphia and 2017 Fall in Washington DC), with the number of people impacted by the work (attendees at conferences) estimated to be about 500. The research results from the project were also incorporated into the courses ("Nanoparticles" and "Introduction to Sustainable Energy") taught by Jin. Jin also designed a lab module for both undergraduate and high school students. In addition, PI Jin was invited to give a number of seminars during the NSF funding period. Three graduate students were trained (partial support). One has successfully obtained a MS degree, one with a PhD degree, and another approaching a PhD degree.   The collaborative process greatly enhanced the project outcomes in both the experimental work (the discovery of new Au-Ag bimetal nanoclusters and the Au-Ag synergy in catalytic reactions) and the optimization of the FIREBALL software package.       Last Modified: 12/29/2017       Submitted by: Rongchao Jin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
