<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 2nd Workshop on Sustainable Software: Best Practices and Experiences (WSSSPE 2)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24758.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24758</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajiv Ramnath</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The WSSSPE 2 workshop is part of a community driven effort to address the many new challenges facing development, deployment and maintenance of reusable software for academic research and education. These challenges include the software development process, the support and maintenance of software, governance and business models particularly for sustainability, the role of software in building science communities, the need for software to lead to science which is verifiable and reproducible, policy issues such as how to measure software impact, choose licensing, or assign software credit, and the education and nurturing of early stage researchers in scientific software. &lt;br/&gt;The workshop is building upon a successful WSSSPE 1 meeting at SC13 in Denver in November 2013; the organizers expect over 60 submitted papers and around 150 attendees at the WSSSPE 2 meeting that is anticipated to be held at SC14 in New Orleans in November 2014. As with WSSSPE 1, WSSSPE 2 will provide an open and dynamic forum for the community to discuss experiences and approaches in the areas listed above. This proposal requests funds to support attendance at WSSSPE 2 for US based researchers, particularly targeted at encouraging attendance by early stage researchers with attention to diversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1434218</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manish</FirstName>
<LastName>Parashar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manish Parashar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>parashar@rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484455388</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148826</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabrielle</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabrielle D Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gdallen@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2253020549</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright St. Suite A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~24758</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Progress in scientific research is dependent on the quality and accessibility of software at all levels. Hence it is critical to address challenges related to the development, deployment, maintenance, and overall sustainability of reusable software as well as education around software practices. These challenges can be technological, policy based, organizational, and educational, and are of interest to developers (the software community), users (science disciplines), software-engineering researchers, and researchers studying the conduct of science (science of team science, science of organizations, science of science and innovation policy, and social science communities).</p> <p>To address these challenges, this project contributed to bringing together diverse stakeholders in &ldquo;Working Towards Sustainable Software for Science: Practice and Experiences&rdquo;, or WSSSPE. Through WSSSPE, this grant funded several meetings and workshops - two general workshops WSSSPE2 (at SC16 in New Orleans, LA) and WSSSPE3 (in Boulder, CO) and one meeting as part of SciPy2016, WSSSPE3.1.</p> <p>These meetings used highly interactive sessions targeted at moving groups through a process of defining and describing challenges, discussing solutions, and then moving to working groups to address software sustainability through actions. The meetings included peer-reviewed papers, lightening talks, keynotes, along with a number of working group sessions.</p> <p>Outcomes of these meetings include full reports written collaboratively by many participants of the meeting, along with ongoing work in several of the working groups spawned at WSSSPE3. Publications from WSSSPE meetings are published in open access journals. A further workshop, WSSSPE4, in Manchester, UK in September 2016 will continue the momentum in addressing issues in sustainable software. More information about the WSSSPE initiative, the workshops, and the outcomes, including links to published material, are available on the WSSSPE web site at http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Gabrielle&nbsp;D&nbsp;Allen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Progress in scientific research is dependent on the quality and accessibility of software at all levels. Hence it is critical to address challenges related to the development, deployment, maintenance, and overall sustainability of reusable software as well as education around software practices. These challenges can be technological, policy based, organizational, and educational, and are of interest to developers (the software community), users (science disciplines), software-engineering researchers, and researchers studying the conduct of science (science of team science, science of organizations, science of science and innovation policy, and social science communities).  To address these challenges, this project contributed to bringing together diverse stakeholders in "Working Towards Sustainable Software for Science: Practice and Experiences", or WSSSPE. Through WSSSPE, this grant funded several meetings and workshops - two general workshops WSSSPE2 (at SC16 in New Orleans, LA) and WSSSPE3 (in Boulder, CO) and one meeting as part of SciPy2016, WSSSPE3.1.  These meetings used highly interactive sessions targeted at moving groups through a process of defining and describing challenges, discussing solutions, and then moving to working groups to address software sustainability through actions. The meetings included peer-reviewed papers, lightening talks, keynotes, along with a number of working group sessions.  Outcomes of these meetings include full reports written collaboratively by many participants of the meeting, along with ongoing work in several of the working groups spawned at WSSSPE3. Publications from WSSSPE meetings are published in open access journals. A further workshop, WSSSPE4, in Manchester, UK in September 2016 will continue the momentum in addressing issues in sustainable software. More information about the WSSSPE initiative, the workshops, and the outcomes, including links to published material, are available on the WSSSPE web site at http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk          Last Modified: 08/02/2016       Submitted by: Gabrielle D Allen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
