<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project: Building a Learner-centered Cyberlearning Environment in Computer-Aided Design Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. Prairie View A &amp; M University will implement a project entitled: Building a Learner-centered Cyberlearning Environment in Computer-Aided Design Education. Engineering students in the 21st century enter a professional environment where computer-aided design (CAD) tools are ubiquitous. Today's industries demand that universities graduate engineers who are prepared with the skills to use modern computer-aided design tools. This project will enhance students' learning of computer-aided design through learner-centered strategies. The project will build an electronic library of CAD software screencast tutorials created by students; teach students CAD with the screencast tutorials created by their peers; and investigate the effects of the student generated tutorials on student learning of CAD, as well as their interest and motivation towards engineering. The screencast tutorials repository developed through this project will be made publicly accessible through an Internet website for use by other engineering students and faculty. The screencast tutorials will also be disseminated through the Partners for the Advancement of Collaborative Engineering Education program - a collaboration among 50 universities around the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will be implemented in the freshman Mechanical Engineering Drawing lab-based course designed to teach students engineering graphics and 3D modeling based on computer-aided design. Engineering students will develop and utilize screencasts, record the supported audio, post the screencasts on an electronic repository, and organize the peer-to-peer learning process. Screencast is a digitally recorded playback of a computer screen output which often contains audio narration, to visually present procedural information.  A screencast is a unique tool for e-learning design because it promotes an affordable way of producing multimedia instruction that is authentic and motivating and can be applied in various educational settings. Project efforts will advance the current state of knowledge on how to effectively utilize cyberlearning in engineering education. The project will provide students with hands-on experience on the same advanced computer-aided design software used by industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1435073</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaobo</FirstName>
<LastName>Peng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaobo Peng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xipeng@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362619959</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396107</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bugrahan</FirstName>
<LastName>Yalvac</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bugrahan Yalvac</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yalvac@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798621713</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000221117</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dongdong</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dongdong Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dozhang@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362619952</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/09/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chang</FirstName>
<LastName>Duan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chang Duan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chduan@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362619954</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000704068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Prairie View A &amp; M University</Name>
<CityName>Prairie View</CityName>
<ZipCode>774460519</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9362611689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 519</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MS 1230]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRAIRIE VIEW A&amp;M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Prairie View A & M University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>774460667</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of the Targeted Infusion Project are to enhance the students' learning of computer-aided design (CAD), promote their life-long learning skills, and cultivate positive engineering attitudes by building a learner-centered cyberlearning environment.</p> <p>The project was implemented in a freshman "Mechanical Engineering Drawing" class offered in Mechanical Engineering Department at Prairie View A&amp;M University from Fall 2014 to Fall 2019. This study was a quasi-experimental pre-and-post test design. In the experimental group, students were asked to generate screencast tutorials and record their explanations at the same time. These video tutorials with the students' explanations recorded on were shared with other students during the semester. Students who viewed the peer-generated tutorials learned from the tutorial and also provided comments about the quality of the tutorials. In order to examine the effects of the screencast tutorial exercises (as well as the number of exercises) on students' learning outcomes, we collected data from students using five different research instruments. The instruments were a demographic questionnaire, a life-long learning (LLL) scale, an engineering attitude (EA) survey, a CAD modeling exam, and an exit project survey.</p> <p>Three instructors taught the 17 sections of the same course between the years 2014 and 2019. A total of 255 students volunteered participating in the present study and completed all research instruments. 80 students were in the control groups and 175 students were in the experimental groups. Among the experimental group students, 84 of them completed one to three screencast exercises ("less" screencast exercise group), and 89 of them completed more than three exercises over the semester ("more" screencast exercise group). Among 255 students, 76.8% of them are male and 23.2% of them are female students; 34.1% are first generation college students and 65.9% of them are not-first generation college student. 73.7% of the students are African-American, 9.8% of the students are Latino/Hispanic.</p> <p>Our research findings showed that the screencast exercises were most impactful to the female and first-generation college students. This is a breakthrough finding in the fields of learning sciences and engineering education because it shows that female and first-generation college students are more receptive to a student-centered and learner-oriented instructional strategy than their counterparts, the male students and not first-generation college students. For the purpose to close the gap between the male and female students' participation in engineering, our research findings provide a clear answer. The traditional lecture based instruction does not allow the gender differences to be eliminated in engineering. To provide equal educational opportunities to all genders and college students, student-centered learning strategies should be implemented. This finding has potential to make an impact in other disciplines in education, for example, science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) education or learning sciences.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The TIP project has provided students the opportunities for training and professional development. Thirteen (13) undergraduate research assistants and four (4) graduate students were mentored by the PIs to take on some of the project tasks. The results of the project have been disseminated through one journal paper, five conferences papers, three conference posters, and one conference presentation. Each year the NX software was introduced to K-12 students and incoming freshmen in the summer program called College of Engineering Enhancement Institute (CE2I). 155 K-12 students participated in the CE2I programs.</p> <p><strong>Selected Publications</strong></p> <ul> <li>Zhang, D., Peng, X., Yalvac, B., Eseryel, D., Nadeem, U., and Islam, A., 2017, "Integrating Student-Made Screencasts into Computer-Aided Design Education." Computer-Aided Design and Applications, 14 (sup1), pp. 41-50.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Peng, X., Jackson, M., Duan, C., Han, M., Yalvac, B., Hing, E. L., Ketsetzi, A., and Eseryel, D., 2020, "Evaluating the Effect of a Student-centered Pedagogical Approach on Students' Skills and Knowledge in Computer-Aided Design (CAD) Course," in the Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition, Portland, Oregon, November 16-19. (Accepted)</li> <li>Duan, C., Peng, X., Yuan, T., Yalvac, B., Ketsetzi, A., Hing, E. L., Eseryel, D., and Eyupoglu, T. F., 2017, "Promoting Life-Long Learning Skills in CAD using the Peer-Generated Screencast Tutorials," in the Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition, Tampa, Florida, November 3-9.</li> <li>Zhang, D., Peng, X., Yalvac, B., Eseryel, D., Nadeem, U., Islam, A, Eyupoglu, T. F., and Yuan, T., "Using Peer-Generated Screencasts in Teaching Computer-Aided Design", 123<sup>rd</sup> ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition, New Orleans, LA, June 26-29, 2016. </li> <li> Eseryel, D., Yalvac, B., Peng, X., Zhang, D., and Eyupoglu, T. F., "Implementing Evidence-Based Pedagogies in Computer-Aided Design Education with Undergraduate Mechanical Engineering Students", 2016 American Educational Research Association (AERA) annual meeting, Washington, DC, April 8-12, 2016</li> <li> Zhang, D., Peng, X., Yalvac, B., Eseryel, D., Nadeem, U., Islam, A., and Arceneaux, D., 2015, "Exploring the Impact of Peer-Generated Screencast Tutorials on Computer-Aided Design Education," in the Proceedings of the 122<sup>nd</sup> ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition, June 14 -17, Seattle, WA. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/08/2020<br>      Modified by: Xiaobo&nbsp;Peng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of the Targeted Infusion Project are to enhance the students' learning of computer-aided design (CAD), promote their life-long learning skills, and cultivate positive engineering attitudes by building a learner-centered cyberlearning environment.  The project was implemented in a freshman "Mechanical Engineering Drawing" class offered in Mechanical Engineering Department at Prairie View A&amp;M University from Fall 2014 to Fall 2019. This study was a quasi-experimental pre-and-post test design. In the experimental group, students were asked to generate screencast tutorials and record their explanations at the same time. These video tutorials with the students' explanations recorded on were shared with other students during the semester. Students who viewed the peer-generated tutorials learned from the tutorial and also provided comments about the quality of the tutorials. In order to examine the effects of the screencast tutorial exercises (as well as the number of exercises) on students' learning outcomes, we collected data from students using five different research instruments. The instruments were a demographic questionnaire, a life-long learning (LLL) scale, an engineering attitude (EA) survey, a CAD modeling exam, and an exit project survey.  Three instructors taught the 17 sections of the same course between the years 2014 and 2019. A total of 255 students volunteered participating in the present study and completed all research instruments. 80 students were in the control groups and 175 students were in the experimental groups. Among the experimental group students, 84 of them completed one to three screencast exercises ("less" screencast exercise group), and 89 of them completed more than three exercises over the semester ("more" screencast exercise group). Among 255 students, 76.8% of them are male and 23.2% of them are female students; 34.1% are first generation college students and 65.9% of them are not-first generation college student. 73.7% of the students are African-American, 9.8% of the students are Latino/Hispanic.  Our research findings showed that the screencast exercises were most impactful to the female and first-generation college students. This is a breakthrough finding in the fields of learning sciences and engineering education because it shows that female and first-generation college students are more receptive to a student-centered and learner-oriented instructional strategy than their counterparts, the male students and not first-generation college students. For the purpose to close the gap between the male and female students' participation in engineering, our research findings provide a clear answer. The traditional lecture based instruction does not allow the gender differences to be eliminated in engineering. To provide equal educational opportunities to all genders and college students, student-centered learning strategies should be implemented. This finding has potential to make an impact in other disciplines in education, for example, science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) education or learning sciences.   The TIP project has provided students the opportunities for training and professional development. Thirteen (13) undergraduate research assistants and four (4) graduate students were mentored by the PIs to take on some of the project tasks. The results of the project have been disseminated through one journal paper, five conferences papers, three conference posters, and one conference presentation. Each year the NX software was introduced to K-12 students and incoming freshmen in the summer program called College of Engineering Enhancement Institute (CE2I). 155 K-12 students participated in the CE2I programs.  Selected Publications  Zhang, D., Peng, X., Yalvac, B., Eseryel, D., Nadeem, U., and Islam, A., 2017, "Integrating Student-Made Screencasts into Computer-Aided Design Education." Computer-Aided Design and Applications, 14 (sup1), pp. 41-50.   Peng, X., Jackson, M., Duan, C., Han, M., Yalvac, B., Hing, E. L., Ketsetzi, A., and Eseryel, D., 2020, "Evaluating the Effect of a Student-centered Pedagogical Approach on Students' Skills and Knowledge in Computer-Aided Design (CAD) Course," in the Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition, Portland, Oregon, November 16-19. (Accepted) Duan, C., Peng, X., Yuan, T., Yalvac, B., Ketsetzi, A., Hing, E. L., Eseryel, D., and Eyupoglu, T. F., 2017, "Promoting Life-Long Learning Skills in CAD using the Peer-Generated Screencast Tutorials," in the Proceedings of the ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition, Tampa, Florida, November 3-9. Zhang, D., Peng, X., Yalvac, B., Eseryel, D., Nadeem, U., Islam, A, Eyupoglu, T. F., and Yuan, T., "Using Peer-Generated Screencasts in Teaching Computer-Aided Design", 123rd ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition, New Orleans, LA, June 26-29, 2016.   Eseryel, D., Yalvac, B., Peng, X., Zhang, D., and Eyupoglu, T. F., "Implementing Evidence-Based Pedagogies in Computer-Aided Design Education with Undergraduate Mechanical Engineering Students", 2016 American Educational Research Association (AERA) annual meeting, Washington, DC, April 8-12, 2016  Zhang, D., Peng, X., Yalvac, B., Eseryel, D., Nadeem, U., Islam, A., and Arceneaux, D., 2015, "Exploring the Impact of Peer-Generated Screencast Tutorials on Computer-Aided Design Education," in the Proceedings of the 122nd ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition, June 14 -17, Seattle, WA.            Last Modified: 07/08/2020       Submitted by: Xiaobo Peng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
