<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Lubrication by Chemical Reaction Products at Sliding Interface</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Toney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sliding and rubbing interfaces of machineries, whether they are big or small, need lubrication to mitigate friction and wear for reliable operation. Otherwise, these interfaces are bound to fail eventually. The last defense of the sliding interface from such failure is boundary lubrication layers which are chemically or physically adhered to solid surfaces. This layer can be applied to the tribological interface before the assembly and full operation of mechanical devices, or formed in-situ during the operation of the devices. This work focuses on in-situ synthesis of boundary lubrication films directly at the sliding interfaces during the device operation. This research can generate a new lubricant additive chemistry which can reduce parasitic frictional energy losses for automobile industries. This work could also revive the microscale electromechanical technology requiring reliable operations of moving and sliding structural components. This project will train students with multidisciplinary skills covering surface science, molecular characterization and imaging, and tribology; these students will make substantial contributions to newly emerging nano-engineering fields as well as traditional lubrication sectors. The research outcome will be incorporated into a graduate surface characterization course and disseminated through to a broad range of science and engineering fields covering chemistry, chemical engineering, mechanical engineering, materials science, and tribology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mechanochemical reactions readily occur at all length scales; however, key parameters governing the reaction yield and selectivity are not well documented or understood. This study aims at advancing mechanistic understanding of mechanochemical reactions that can produce reliable boundary lubrication films with complementary properties such as low interfacial shear and high load-bearing. Two specific systems to be studied are (i) mechanochemical polymerization of unsaturated alcohols and esters adsorbed from the vapor phase for synthesis of multilayer films of polyols and polyolesters and (ii) ferrocene-catalyzed mechanochemical reactions of organic precursors in lubricant oils and their graphitization at the sliding interface. This work will undertake systematic studies to understand how contact pressure, shear rate, structure of reactant molecules, and chemistry of substrate materials affect the mechanochemical reaction yield and selectivity as well as the lubrication properties of the produced films. The outcome of this study will not only make breakthroughs in surface engineering for extreme-condition lubrications, but also advance fundamental knowledge of tribochemistry which is still empirical and qualitative.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1435766</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seong</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seong H Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shk10@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148634809</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165854</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8022</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Infrastructure Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~350000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>Tribochemistry encompasses various types of chemical reactions occurring or initiated due to interfacial shear. In nearly all mechanical systems, interfacial shear is directly responsible for formation of protective films from lubricants or wear of solid surfaces. However, despite its importance in many engineering systems, mechanistic understanding in tribochemistry is far less than other branches of chemistry such as thermal, photochemical, and electrochemical reactions. This project specifically focused on identifying and understanding chemical factors governing shear-induced reactions of interfacial molecules.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merits:</strong> Tribochemical reactions readily occur at all length scales; however, key parameters governing the reaction yield and selectivity are not well documented or understood. Two specific systems studied in this project are (i) tribochemical polymerization of organic molecules adsorbed from the vapor phase and (ii) tribochemical reactions of water molecules on silicon surfaces in humid air. In the tribochemical polymerization study, it was found that physisorbed molecules are not readily activated by shear and chemisorption is the prerequisite for tribochemical activation. When molecules are just physisorbed, mechanical shear stress or energy is not efficiently transferred to molecules. But, when molecules are chemically anchored to the solid surface, then the shear stress of the substrate can easily be transferred to the molecule. The mechanical shear deforms the molecules in the contact region from the equilibrium conformation, which force them to undergo chemical reactions that normally would not occur in thermally-activated conditions. This work enabled tribochemical synthesis of nanoscale polymeric films that provide reliable boundary lubrication. In tribochemistry, only the topmost atomic layer of the substrate is involved unless the applied load is too high to induce subsurface structural. Utilizing this principle, tribochemical etching of single atomic layer of silicon was demonstrated with scanning probe microscopy in humid air. In addition, the effects of adsorbed water molecules on nano-scale friction and wear of the silicon surface were elucidated. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts: </strong>The development of in-situ tribochemical synthetic routes for direct deposition of nano-lubricant films at the sliding interfaces can revive the development of microelectromechanical systems (MEMS) requiring reliable operations of moving and sliding structural components. The selective etching of silicon surface using tribochemical reactions can open a new paradigm of mask-free and solvent-free nanofabrication of silicon surfaces. &nbsp;The team also contributed to understanding of mechanical properties of solid electrolyte interface (SEI) being developed for more stable and reliable lithium ion battery technology. Two graduate students were supported. Dr. Anthony Barthel, who was partially supported with this grant, is now a research engineer at the CPI Fluid Engineering of Lubrizol Corp. Xin He is very close to his PhD defense; he is currently working as an intern in a tribology group at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory. Through the duration of this project, three undergraduate students had opportunity of conducting research. Among them, Austin Pollack co-author a paper submitted for publication.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/22/2018<br>      Modified by: Seong&nbsp;H&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes  Tribochemistry encompasses various types of chemical reactions occurring or initiated due to interfacial shear. In nearly all mechanical systems, interfacial shear is directly responsible for formation of protective films from lubricants or wear of solid surfaces. However, despite its importance in many engineering systems, mechanistic understanding in tribochemistry is far less than other branches of chemistry such as thermal, photochemical, and electrochemical reactions. This project specifically focused on identifying and understanding chemical factors governing shear-induced reactions of interfacial molecules.  Intellectual Merits: Tribochemical reactions readily occur at all length scales; however, key parameters governing the reaction yield and selectivity are not well documented or understood. Two specific systems studied in this project are (i) tribochemical polymerization of organic molecules adsorbed from the vapor phase and (ii) tribochemical reactions of water molecules on silicon surfaces in humid air. In the tribochemical polymerization study, it was found that physisorbed molecules are not readily activated by shear and chemisorption is the prerequisite for tribochemical activation. When molecules are just physisorbed, mechanical shear stress or energy is not efficiently transferred to molecules. But, when molecules are chemically anchored to the solid surface, then the shear stress of the substrate can easily be transferred to the molecule. The mechanical shear deforms the molecules in the contact region from the equilibrium conformation, which force them to undergo chemical reactions that normally would not occur in thermally-activated conditions. This work enabled tribochemical synthesis of nanoscale polymeric films that provide reliable boundary lubrication. In tribochemistry, only the topmost atomic layer of the substrate is involved unless the applied load is too high to induce subsurface structural. Utilizing this principle, tribochemical etching of single atomic layer of silicon was demonstrated with scanning probe microscopy in humid air. In addition, the effects of adsorbed water molecules on nano-scale friction and wear of the silicon surface were elucidated.    Broader impacts: The development of in-situ tribochemical synthetic routes for direct deposition of nano-lubricant films at the sliding interfaces can revive the development of microelectromechanical systems (MEMS) requiring reliable operations of moving and sliding structural components. The selective etching of silicon surface using tribochemical reactions can open a new paradigm of mask-free and solvent-free nanofabrication of silicon surfaces.  The team also contributed to understanding of mechanical properties of solid electrolyte interface (SEI) being developed for more stable and reliable lithium ion battery technology. Two graduate students were supported. Dr. Anthony Barthel, who was partially supported with this grant, is now a research engineer at the CPI Fluid Engineering of Lubrizol Corp. Xin He is very close to his PhD defense; he is currently working as an intern in a tribology group at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory. Through the duration of this project, three undergraduate students had opportunity of conducting research. Among them, Austin Pollack co-author a paper submitted for publication.       Last Modified: 10/22/2018       Submitted by: Seong H Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
