<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Control of Robust Micro-Robots in Uncertain Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Autonomous micro-robots a few millimeters in size have transformative potential for applications ranging from infrastructure monitoring to disaster response to exploration of hostile or inaccessible locales. Such tasks will require robots that can successfully navigate complicated and unpredictable terrain and environments. Given limitations on moving parts in micro-scale systems, legged locomotion offers the best combination of adaptability and efficiency. Standard features of full-scale walking robots, such as motorized and instrumented knee and ankle joints, are impossible or impractical to realize with current micro-fabrication techniques, making flexible linkages the most promising approach to articulated limbs. But, because of differences between the ways that leg stiffness and body mass scale as robot dimensions decrease, the natural springiness of the legs cannot be relied on to keep all feet in contact with uneven ground, which can greatly degrade gait effectiveness. These challenges make legged locomotion an essentially different and more difficult problem at the micro-scale. This project will advance the fundamental state of the art towards high-speed, high-mobility legged micro-robots navigating in an uncertain environment. It will develop models of the leg-surface interaction, and use these models to derive efficient and effective walking gaits. To maximize adaptability in changing conditions, internal sensors capable of monitoring gait effectiveness will be added to existing micro-robot leg designs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will study the complex contact interaction of walking micro-robots with multiple feet moving at high-speeds on varying surfaces. The resulting dynamic models will be used to identify walking gaits that produce efficient forward motion over a range of environmental conditions. The investigators have previously combined thin-film lead-zirconate-titanate (PZT) with resilient polymer materials to demonstrate micro-fabricated legs with an unusually large range of motion and actuation speed. In this project, sensing elements will be integrated into the thin-film PZT/polymer legs to allow basic estimation of robot motion. Actuation and estimator design will meet constraints imposed by small-scale power sources, through input sequences based on a limited number of switched input voltages and leg and robot movement estimates based on limited sensor samples. Once estimation of robot walking effectiveness has been demonstrated using on-chip measurements, adaptive control algorithms will be tailored to respond to environmental conditions that change over time.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1435222</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenn</FirstName>
<LastName>Oldham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenn Oldham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>oldham@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641817</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508442</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031E</Code>
<Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award has supported the development of micro-mirrors for use in advanced endoscopic microscopy. &nbsp; The actuators developed under this work achieve large vertical displacements (hundreds of microns) relative to their size of just three millimeters on a side.&nbsp; Such actuators may be used to acquire cross-sectional images of tissue from small biomedical endoscopy instruments by scanning a laser in multiple axes through the tissue.&nbsp; Activities supported by this award include development of systemmatic procedures for designing the mirrors, refinement of mirror microfabrication, modeling of mirror dynamics, and exploration of sensing and control strategies to regulate mirror motion.&nbsp; From an original focus on mirrors driven by piezoelectric materials, modeling and analysis was extended to other micro-scale transduction techniques, including electromagnetic and electrothermal actuation. &nbsp; Actuators have been integrated into a benchtop prototype of a miniature optical microscopy system based on the multi-photon effect for fluorescent imaging.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp; Due to the large displacements and high speed of these micro-mirrors compared to existing technologies, dynamic mirror motion can be highly complicated. &nbsp;&nbsp; This award supported the development of analytical models explaining various nonlinear and multi-axis motions of the micro-mirrors.&nbsp; In addition, underlying material properties of piezoelectric and magnetic materials used in certain actuator designs have been studied for their contributions to nonlinear dynamic phenomena. &nbsp; Opportunities for on-chip sensor integration were assessed and a novel strategy for improving position measurement accuracy in micro-mirrors using capacitive sensing was developed.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts:&nbsp; Novel optical microscopy techniques such as multi-photon and confocal microscopy can produce high resolution images of cellular structure beneath the surface of biological tissue. &nbsp; To build up images from these laser-based techniques, a laser must be rapidly scanned through the tissue in multiple axes, including vertically or "into-tissue".&nbsp; The actuators developed under this award provide unique capabilities for fast into-tissue scanning. &nbsp; Resulting vertical cross-sectional or 3D images may one day permit "optical biopsy" of tissue in hollow organs, without a need to remove physical tissue samples, for medical procedures such as diagnosis and monitoring or esophageal or colon cancer.&nbsp; In addition, this award supported outreach activities to elementary and secondary studens to relate basic principles of mechanical engineering, such as simple machines, forces, and motion, to mechanisms that allow doctors and engineers to create medial endoscopy tools.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Kenn&nbsp;Oldham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511978670671_Endoscopy_Fig1_Actuators--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511978670671_Endoscopy_Fig1_Actuators--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Thin-film piezoelectric vertical actuators for endomicroscopy"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511978670671_Endoscopy_Fig1_Actuators--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Thin-film piezoelectric vertical actuators for endomicroscopy"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A selection of microactuators based on thin-film piezoelectric actuation for fast laser scanning into tissue; size: 3 mm by 3 mm.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jongsoo Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenn&nbsp;Oldham</div> <div class="imageTitle">Thin-film piezoelectric vertical actuators for endomicroscopy</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979012696_Endoscopy_Fig3_ImagingSystem--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979012696_Endoscopy_Fig3_ImagingSystem--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MEMS-based multi-photon imaging system"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979012696_Endoscopy_Fig3_ImagingSystem--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MEMS-based multi-photon imaging system"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic view of MEMS mirrors arranged to provide vertical cross-sectional imaging of biological tissue.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jongsoo Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenn&nbsp;Oldham</div> <div class="imageTitle">MEMS-based multi-photon imaging system</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979130607_Endoscopy_Fig3_BeadsTissue--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979130607_Endoscopy_Fig3_BeadsTissue--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MEMS-based multi-photon vertical cross-section"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979130607_Endoscopy_Fig3_BeadsTissue--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MEMS-based multi-photon vertical cross-section"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vertical cross-sectional images of fluorescent beads and excised mouse colon tissue taken using the multi-photon effect with laser scanning by MEMS micro-mirrors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiyu Duan, Jongsoo Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenn&nbsp;Oldham</div> <div class="imageTitle">MEMS-based multi-photon vertical cross-section</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979215515_Endoscopy_Fig2_Electrotherma--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979215515_Endoscopy_Fig2_Electrotherma--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Vertical translational micro-mirror"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979215515_Endoscopy_Fig2_Electrotherma--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Vertical translational micro-mirror"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of electrothermally-actuated MEMS micro-mirrors undergoing uniform vertical translation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mayur Birla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenn&nbsp;Oldham</div> <div class="imageTitle">Vertical translational micro-mirror</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979324585_Pollen_Image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979324585_Pollen_Image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MEMS-based 3D pollen image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1435222/1435222_10320487_1511979324585_Pollen_Image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MEMS-based 3D pollen image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sample 3D image reconstruction of a pollen grain generated by the multi-photon effect with laser scanning from MEMS microactuators.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Junyu Zou, Mayur Birla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenn&nbsp;Oldham</div> <div class="imageTitle">MEMS-based 3D pollen image</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award has supported the development of micro-mirrors for use in advanced endoscopic microscopy.   The actuators developed under this work achieve large vertical displacements (hundreds of microns) relative to their size of just three millimeters on a side.  Such actuators may be used to acquire cross-sectional images of tissue from small biomedical endoscopy instruments by scanning a laser in multiple axes through the tissue.  Activities supported by this award include development of systemmatic procedures for designing the mirrors, refinement of mirror microfabrication, modeling of mirror dynamics, and exploration of sensing and control strategies to regulate mirror motion.  From an original focus on mirrors driven by piezoelectric materials, modeling and analysis was extended to other micro-scale transduction techniques, including electromagnetic and electrothermal actuation.   Actuators have been integrated into a benchtop prototype of a miniature optical microscopy system based on the multi-photon effect for fluorescent imaging.  Intellectual Merit:  Due to the large displacements and high speed of these micro-mirrors compared to existing technologies, dynamic mirror motion can be highly complicated.    This award supported the development of analytical models explaining various nonlinear and multi-axis motions of the micro-mirrors.  In addition, underlying material properties of piezoelectric and magnetic materials used in certain actuator designs have been studied for their contributions to nonlinear dynamic phenomena.   Opportunities for on-chip sensor integration were assessed and a novel strategy for improving position measurement accuracy in micro-mirrors using capacitive sensing was developed.   Broader Impacts:  Novel optical microscopy techniques such as multi-photon and confocal microscopy can produce high resolution images of cellular structure beneath the surface of biological tissue.   To build up images from these laser-based techniques, a laser must be rapidly scanned through the tissue in multiple axes, including vertically or "into-tissue".  The actuators developed under this award provide unique capabilities for fast into-tissue scanning.   Resulting vertical cross-sectional or 3D images may one day permit "optical biopsy" of tissue in hollow organs, without a need to remove physical tissue samples, for medical procedures such as diagnosis and monitoring or esophageal or colon cancer.  In addition, this award supported outreach activities to elementary and secondary studens to relate basic principles of mechanical engineering, such as simple machines, forces, and motion, to mechanisms that allow doctors and engineers to create medial endoscopy tools.           Last Modified: 11/29/2017       Submitted by: Kenn Oldham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
