<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DMREF/Collaborative Research: Collaboration to Accelerate the Discovery of New Alloys for Additive Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>345000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>345000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Schlueter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jschluet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927766</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical:  Recently, there has been significant interest in additive manufacturing, also known as 3-D printing. While there have been many efforts aimed at exploring the geometric design space, thus enabling innovative components, such efforts invariably use legacy materials (e.g., Ti-6Al-4V) that were designed and optimized decades ago for conventional manufacturing approaches. When the material is not part of the design strategy, there is both an intrinsic risk and an opportunity lost. With respect to risk, such legacy materials may exhibit properties that are inferior to the same material prepared using conventional approaches. For example, when Ti-6-4 is arbitrarily selected for additive manufacturing processes, the resultant material exhibits properties that vary according to both testing direction and spatial location. With respect to the lost opportunity, there are unique characteristics of the additive manufacturing processes, such as very high solidification rates, that can result in superior properties for the right materials.  Thus, there is a need to design new materials that leverage the unique characteristics of additive manufacturing processes to achieve a balance of properties that exceeds what is currently possible when legacy materials are used. The titanium alloys developed under this Designing Materials to Revolutionize and Engineer our Future (DMREF) program, as well as the general framework of accelerated alloy development, will be disseminated through a series of industry dissemination workshops. This dissemination will impact a wide range of economic sectors, including, for example, aerospace, automotive, and biomedical.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical:  This project is directed toward the design of a modern creep-resistant beta-titanium alloy to be produced via additive manufacturing. This will be achieved by integrating high-throughput combinatorial materials science, state-of-the-art materials characterization, computational materials science, and data-science. The project seeks to: (1) discover and model the fundamental interrelationship between the far-from equilibrium conditions of additive manufacturing processes and materials composition on the resulting microstructure and properties; (2) fully describe the materials composition and structure using multi-dimensional, multi-spatial, and multi-spectral approaches; (3) determine, via powerful data science approaches, hidden correlations (e.g., mechanisms) between composition, structure, and properties as assessed using both computational and experimental techniques; (4) validate the mechanisms via computational modeling and critical experimentation; and (5) design, as a multi-university team, a new material for additive manufacturing processes. Along the way, the team will develop both an ontology and data science standards so that the information can be shared easily amongst the four universities during the program and disseminated more broadly at the conclusion of the effort.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1435237</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Surya</FirstName>
<LastName>Kalidindi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Surya R Kalidindi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>surya.kalidindi@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158951311</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000269633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~345000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Technical Outcomes: This project has developed and demonstrated completely new high throughput assays capable of exploring the materials and process design spaces for additively manufactured metal alloys. These novel protocols include prototyping of large sample libraries by exploiting intentional compositional gradients/process history differences, high-throughput mechanical characterization using novel spherical indentation stress-strain protocols, and building reduced-order process-structure-property linkages using Gaussian Process models. The models obtained in these protocols were found to be quite valuable in providing objective guidance on where the next effort needs to be invested to arrive at the desired property combinations in the final sample. &nbsp;We have already published five papers in reputed archival journals, and plan to submit at least two more in the near future. Part of this work was recognized as the Runner-up Winner in the national 2016 Materials Science and Engineering Data Challenge supported by Air Force Research Laboratory, National Institute of Standards and Technology, and National Science Foundation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact Outcomes: One PhD graduate student was fully supported and trained in advanced materials characterization techniques involving electron back-scattered diffraction, energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy and spherical indentation stress-strain curves at different length scales. Additionally, three other graduate students and two undergraduate students also participated in various components of this research. All of the students have been exposed to a broad suite of emergent tools in high throughput exploration of process-structure-property linkages; this is one of the currently missing technological foundations needed to support the national Materials Genome Initiative (MGI).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Surya&nbsp;R&nbsp;Kalidindi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1435237/1435237_10333596_1543369880315_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1435237/1435237_10333596_1543369880315_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="High Throughput Experimental Assays for Additive Manufacturing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1435237/1435237_10333596_1543369880315_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="High Throughput Experimental Assays for Additive Manufacturing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of the conventional approach (top row) and a high throughput (HT) approach (bottom row) to explore materials with different combinations of compositional and/or additive manufacturing process conditions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">X. Gong and S. R. Kalidindi</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Surya&nbsp;R&nbsp;Kalidindi</div> <div class="imageTitle">High Throughput Experimental Assays for Additive Manufacturing</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1435237/1435237_10333596_1543370290214_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1435237/1435237_10333596_1543370290214_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Data-driven framework for process-structure-property linkages"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1435237/1435237_10333596_1543370290214_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Data-driven framework for process-structure-property linkages"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic depiction of the new data-driven framework developed and demonstrated in this work for the rapid exploration of the process-structure-property linkages from the small experimental datasets obtained during optimization of additive manufacturing processes</div> <div class="imageCredit">X. Gong, Y. Yabansu, and S. R. Kalidindi</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Surya&nbsp;R&nbsp;Kalidindi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Data-driven framework for process-structure-property linkages</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Technical Outcomes: This project has developed and demonstrated completely new high throughput assays capable of exploring the materials and process design spaces for additively manufactured metal alloys. These novel protocols include prototyping of large sample libraries by exploiting intentional compositional gradients/process history differences, high-throughput mechanical characterization using novel spherical indentation stress-strain protocols, and building reduced-order process-structure-property linkages using Gaussian Process models. The models obtained in these protocols were found to be quite valuable in providing objective guidance on where the next effort needs to be invested to arrive at the desired property combinations in the final sample.  We have already published five papers in reputed archival journals, and plan to submit at least two more in the near future. Part of this work was recognized as the Runner-up Winner in the national 2016 Materials Science and Engineering Data Challenge supported by Air Force Research Laboratory, National Institute of Standards and Technology, and National Science Foundation.     Broader Impact Outcomes: One PhD graduate student was fully supported and trained in advanced materials characterization techniques involving electron back-scattered diffraction, energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy and spherical indentation stress-strain curves at different length scales. Additionally, three other graduate students and two undergraduate students also participated in various components of this research. All of the students have been exposed to a broad suite of emergent tools in high throughput exploration of process-structure-property linkages; this is one of the currently missing technological foundations needed to support the national Materials Genome Initiative (MGI).           Last Modified: 11/27/2018       Submitted by: Surya R Kalidindi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
