<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for student travel to the 35th International Symposium on Combustion, San Francisco, CA  / August 2-6, 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruey-Hung Chen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed funding will be used to offset costs for student to travel to the 35th International Symposium on Combustion, San Francisco, CA August 2 - 6, 2014.  The supported students are expected to have authored or co-authored an accepted paper and to presented it in person at the Symposium.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1436895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Ronney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Ronney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ronney@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137400490</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000453158</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>148E</Code>
<Text>Combustion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over 80% of the world&rsquo;s energy production and use is based on the combustion of fossil fuels.&nbsp; Combustion is ubiquitous in traditional energy conversion systems such as automotive engines, stationary and aircraft gas turbines, rocket and space propulsion, electrical power generation, industrial furnaces, and home and institutional space heating.&nbsp; Moreover, emerging technology areas such as hypersonic propulsion, microscale power generation and material synthesis depend critically on chemically reacting flow processes.&nbsp; The world&rsquo;s dependence on combustion processes has led to many technological challenges including air quality, energy efficiency, global warming, and fire/explosion safety.&nbsp; Thus, combustion is still an active, vital area of research.</p> <p>The International Symposium on Combustion is by far the largest and most important international meeting for dissemination of the results of basic and applied combustion research.&nbsp; It is held biannually, in a different location each time. &nbsp;Practically all of the most published, most cited and most respected members of the international combustion research community attend this Symposium.&nbsp; Students attending this Symposium have a unique opportunity to meet these members of the community, discuss their research with them, and exchange ideas with both senior researchers as well as their student peers from around the world.&nbsp; Thus, it is almost essential that fledgling combustion researchers attend the Symposium and present their work therein.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project supported travel for 47 students to the 35th&nbsp;International Symposium on Combustion, held from August 3 - 8, 2014. &nbsp;The Symposium included a full 5-day agenda including 1 keynote speaker, 4 plenary lectures, 4 topical review lectures, more than 350 contributed oral presentations (which had undergone a full rigorous peer review process; less than 40% of the submitted papers were accepted) and more than 800 poster presentations. &nbsp;All students supported by this grant were</p> <ul> <li>US Citizens or permanent residents</li> <li>Full-time students (priority was given to Ph.D. students) at an accredited U. S. university</li> <li>Supported by their academic advisor, as evidenced by a letter of recommendation</li> <li>An author or co-author of a contributed paper or poster accepted by the Symposium Program Committee.</li> </ul> <p>A request for applications was advertised via the Combustion Institute website (http://www.combustioninstitute.org)&nbsp;and email announcements were sent to the US section members of the Combustion Institute.&nbsp; The applications included:</p> <ul> <li>A letter of endorsement by the academic advisor&nbsp;</li> <li>A list of other potential funding available to attend the Symposium&nbsp;</li> <li>Complete mailing address and e-mail address</li> </ul> <p>The Combustion Institute supported this project by</p> <ol> <li>Posting the announcement on its server</li> <li>Sending emails advertising the support to the appropriate US members</li> <li>Collecting the applications and forward them to the PI for approval and payment via USC</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2015<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ronney</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over 80% of the worldÆs energy production and use is based on the combustion of fossil fuels.  Combustion is ubiquitous in traditional energy conversion systems such as automotive engines, stationary and aircraft gas turbines, rocket and space propulsion, electrical power generation, industrial furnaces, and home and institutional space heating.  Moreover, emerging technology areas such as hypersonic propulsion, microscale power generation and material synthesis depend critically on chemically reacting flow processes.  The worldÆs dependence on combustion processes has led to many technological challenges including air quality, energy efficiency, global warming, and fire/explosion safety.  Thus, combustion is still an active, vital area of research.  The International Symposium on Combustion is by far the largest and most important international meeting for dissemination of the results of basic and applied combustion research.  It is held biannually, in a different location each time.  Practically all of the most published, most cited and most respected members of the international combustion research community attend this Symposium.  Students attending this Symposium have a unique opportunity to meet these members of the community, discuss their research with them, and exchange ideas with both senior researchers as well as their student peers from around the world.  Thus, it is almost essential that fledgling combustion researchers attend the Symposium and present their work therein.   This project supported travel for 47 students to the 35th International Symposium on Combustion, held from August 3 - 8, 2014.  The Symposium included a full 5-day agenda including 1 keynote speaker, 4 plenary lectures, 4 topical review lectures, more than 350 contributed oral presentations (which had undergone a full rigorous peer review process; less than 40% of the submitted papers were accepted) and more than 800 poster presentations.  All students supported by this grant were  US Citizens or permanent residents Full-time students (priority was given to Ph.D. students) at an accredited U. S. university Supported by their academic advisor, as evidenced by a letter of recommendation An author or co-author of a contributed paper or poster accepted by the Symposium Program Committee.   A request for applications was advertised via the Combustion Institute website (http://www.combustioninstitute.org) and email announcements were sent to the US section members of the Combustion Institute.  The applications included:  A letter of endorsement by the academic advisor  A list of other potential funding available to attend the Symposium  Complete mailing address and e-mail address   The Combustion Institute supported this project by  Posting the announcement on its server Sending emails advertising the support to the appropriate US members Collecting the applications and forward them to the PI for approval and payment via USC           Last Modified: 02/08/2015       Submitted by: Paul D Ronney]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
