<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multidisciplinary Design of Microvascular Composites Based on a Hierarchical Approach</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>kara peters</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Inspired by the circulatory systems present in a wide range of living organisms, microvascular composites are a new class of fiber-reinforced polymers that possess a network of embedded microchannels. The focus of this work is placed on circulating a coolant through these microchannels to allow for the use of composite components in high temperature conditions, well beyond their traditional use. The design of these materials naturally leads to a multidisciplinary optimization problem: from a thermal point of view, more efficient active cooling can be achieved by multiplying the number of microchannels in which flows the coolant. But from a structural point of view, every channel represents a small void that may lead to stress concentration and negatively affect the stiffness and strength of the composite. Although the multidisciplinary computational design method to be developed as part of this project focuses on high temperature applications, microvascular composites are being considered for a wide range of multidisciplinary applications, including new electrical, electromagnetic or sensing properties. The combined computational and experimental research project will provide a unique multidisciplinary training experience for two graduate students and one summer undergraduate research assistant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The hierarchical computational design method to be developed in this project will lead to important advances in the efficient and accurate modeling of heterogeneous materials, and in the formulation of a robust gradient-based shape optimization approach that eludes issues associated with mesh distortion often associated with conventional finite element methods. At the heart of the modeling effort is an isogeometric interface-enriched generalized finite element method (IIGFEM) that allows for the thermal and structural modeling of microvascular composites with finite element discretizations that do not conform to the embedded microchannel network and the composite microstructure. The IIGFEM is then combined with a hierarchical, gradient-based shape optimization scheme to compute the optimal shape of the microchannel network based on a set of objective functions and constraints associated with the thermal performance and flow efficiency of the embedded network, and its impact on the structural properties of the microvascular composite. Building on state-of-the-art computational and experimental tools, this top-down design method, which relies on a hierarchy of thermo-mechanical models and length scales, offers an efficient approach to tackle the size and complexity of a design process characterized by multiple, conflicting, multi-disciplinary objective functions and constraints.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1436720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott R White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>swhite@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173331077</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397856</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philippe</FirstName>
<LastName>Geubelle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philippe H Geubelle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>geubelle@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172447648</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488606</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618012957</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[SUITE A 1901 SOUTH FIRST ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>DEMS-Design Eng Material Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>067E</Code>
<Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>073E</Code>
<Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~350000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Microvascular composite materials are a new class of fiber-reinforced polymer-matrix composites containing a network of embedded microchannels that act like a circulatory system, i.e., like the veins and arteries present in many living organisms. In this project, we developed a novel computational approach to analyze and design microvascular composites to be used in applications where the material is exposed to high thermal loads and needs to be actively cooled. In particular, we designed and manufactured microvascular composite panels to be used in the active cooling of electric car batteries. The basic idea is to replace the current heavier and bulkier systems, which combine microvascular aluminum panels with fiberglass or steel layers used for crash protection, by lighter microvascular carbon-fiber composite systems that provide both active cooling and structural protection to the battery.</p> <p>This NSF-supported collaborative experimental/computational project has led to important advances in the manufacturing of microvascular composites and in the development of a novel design tool for microvascular materials and structures. On the manufacturing side, complex microchannel networks were created using a novel technique based on sacrificial fibers or templates embedded in the composite panels. Detailed tests showed the ability of the cooling agent flowing in microvascular network to extract a substantial amount of heat, and that the embedded microchannels had very limited impact on the crushing resistance of the composite panels.</p> <p>On the computational side, two major advances were made. Firstly, a new enriched finite element scheme was developed to model the thermal impact of the embedded microchannels based on dimensionally reduced models of the microvascular network and using a discretization that does not conform to the microchannels. The new numerical scheme was verified against more complex, 3D, nonlinear simulations performed with the FLUENT commercial software, and validated against infrared thermal measurements. The second advance consists in the formulation and implementation of a gradient-based shape optimization scheme that allows to design the configuration of the microchannel network to minimize the maximum temperature of the actively cooled panel while reducing the pressure drop needed to circulate the coolant and/or minimize the impact of a potential microchannel blockage.</p> <p>We demonstrated the ability of the optimized microchannel network to keep the maximum temperature of the panel below 40&deg;C under a thermal loading (about 500 W/m<sup>2</sup>) equivalent to that generated by the two adjacent lithium-ion cell pouches. This temperature is considered as an upper limit of the operating temperature needed to preserve the performance of the battery. The thermal performance of the optimized network was confirmed experimentally through IR measurements.</p> <p>To demonstrate the generality of the method, we also applied it for the analysis and design of a microvascular radiative cooling panel for a nanosatellite scheduled to be deployed over the next couple of years. Some of the challenges associated with this particular application involved the nonlinear nature of the radiation term, and the constraints associated with the freezing temperature of the coolant.</p> <p>Beyond the thermal design and assessment of microvascular composites for high temperature applications, this project has impact on the many potential applications of this new class of materials: depending on the type of fluid flowing through the microchannels, composite materials with unique electrical, magnetic or sensing properties can be created.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241355924_Picture6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241355924_Picture6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Validation of optimum design"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241355924_Picture6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Validation of optimum design"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">. Comparison between the numerical prediction (left) and experimental measurement (right) of the thermal field for the optimized 8-branch network.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Validation of optimum design</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241002420_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241002420_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IGFEM Validation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241002420_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IGFEM Validation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Validation of 2D IGFEM solver. Comparison of surface thermal fields obtained experimentally (second row) and numerically (bottom row) for the four network configurations shown in the top row. The arrows denote the inlet and outlet locations for the coolant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">IGFEM Validation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241071388_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241071388_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Manufacturing process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241071388_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Manufacturing process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Manufacturing process for microvascular composite panel, with the sacrificial PLA template introduced in the prepreg layup prior to the VARTM process.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Manufacturing process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241149406_Picture4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241149406_Picture4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Microvascular composite panel"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241149406_Picture4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Microvascular composite panel"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Microvascular composite panel containing a 9-channel ?rectangular? network configuration.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Microvascular composite panel</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241256922_Picture5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241256922_Picture5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Network optimization"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502241256922_Picture5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Network optimization"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Gradient-based optimization of a 5-branch network, showing the initial configuration (left) and the final, optimized one (right). The thermal solutions show a 6 degree drop in the maximum temperature.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Network optimization</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502240925851_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502240925851_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IGFEM method"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1436720/1436720_10316755_1502240925851_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IGFEM method"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Enrichment functions used in the IGFEM approximation of the thermal solution in a quadrilaterial element traversed by a curved microchannel modeled with a quadratic NURBS. The enrichment functions have the weak discontinuity of the temperature solution across the microchannel.</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philippe&nbsp;H&nbsp;Geubelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">IGFEM method</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Microvascular composite materials are a new class of fiber-reinforced polymer-matrix composites containing a network of embedded microchannels that act like a circulatory system, i.e., like the veins and arteries present in many living organisms. In this project, we developed a novel computational approach to analyze and design microvascular composites to be used in applications where the material is exposed to high thermal loads and needs to be actively cooled. In particular, we designed and manufactured microvascular composite panels to be used in the active cooling of electric car batteries. The basic idea is to replace the current heavier and bulkier systems, which combine microvascular aluminum panels with fiberglass or steel layers used for crash protection, by lighter microvascular carbon-fiber composite systems that provide both active cooling and structural protection to the battery.  This NSF-supported collaborative experimental/computational project has led to important advances in the manufacturing of microvascular composites and in the development of a novel design tool for microvascular materials and structures. On the manufacturing side, complex microchannel networks were created using a novel technique based on sacrificial fibers or templates embedded in the composite panels. Detailed tests showed the ability of the cooling agent flowing in microvascular network to extract a substantial amount of heat, and that the embedded microchannels had very limited impact on the crushing resistance of the composite panels.  On the computational side, two major advances were made. Firstly, a new enriched finite element scheme was developed to model the thermal impact of the embedded microchannels based on dimensionally reduced models of the microvascular network and using a discretization that does not conform to the microchannels. The new numerical scheme was verified against more complex, 3D, nonlinear simulations performed with the FLUENT commercial software, and validated against infrared thermal measurements. The second advance consists in the formulation and implementation of a gradient-based shape optimization scheme that allows to design the configuration of the microchannel network to minimize the maximum temperature of the actively cooled panel while reducing the pressure drop needed to circulate the coolant and/or minimize the impact of a potential microchannel blockage.  We demonstrated the ability of the optimized microchannel network to keep the maximum temperature of the panel below 40&deg;C under a thermal loading (about 500 W/m2) equivalent to that generated by the two adjacent lithium-ion cell pouches. This temperature is considered as an upper limit of the operating temperature needed to preserve the performance of the battery. The thermal performance of the optimized network was confirmed experimentally through IR measurements.  To demonstrate the generality of the method, we also applied it for the analysis and design of a microvascular radiative cooling panel for a nanosatellite scheduled to be deployed over the next couple of years. Some of the challenges associated with this particular application involved the nonlinear nature of the radiation term, and the constraints associated with the freezing temperature of the coolant.  Beyond the thermal design and assessment of microvascular composites for high temperature applications, this project has impact on the many potential applications of this new class of materials: depending on the type of fluid flowing through the microchannels, composite materials with unique electrical, magnetic or sensing properties can be created.          Last Modified: 08/08/2017       Submitted by: Philippe H Geubelle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
