<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DMREF/Collaborative Research: Acoustically Transformative Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>650000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>779999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Schlueter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jschluet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927766</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;Many studies have focused on developing materials for conventional acoustic applications, such as ultrasound imaging, sound insulation, and geological logging.  However, the design of materials that actively respond to sound and concurrently shift their acoustic and optical characteristics remains in its infancy.  The goal of this project is to design acoustically responsive materials that alter their chemical structure, physical properties, and object shapes whenever they interact with sound waves enabling active modulation of acoustic properties including speed of sound, attenuation, and phononic band gaps.  If compared to electromagnetic radiation, sound waves possess unique physical characteristics as they readily propagate through optically non-transparent materials, including liquids, solids, and gels (e.g., human body), where direct application of conventional stimuli, such as light and electric fields, is either physically or physiologically prohibited.  This enables non-invasive interrogation of a wide range of materials properties and remote activation of various mechanochemical processes.  Moreover, similar to electromagnetic radiation, sound can be focused both in space and in time.  This opens intriguing opportunities to perform local modifications in a time-controlled, sequential manner.  These materials may be utilized both in materials engineering for acoustic lithography and self-healing and in biomedical applications including non-invasive surgery, diagnostics, and drug-delivery. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;The project goal is to develop a new direction in materials design wherein fundamental changes in materials properties are activated by sound waves that concurrently shift acoustic, optical, and geometric characteristics of macroscopic objects.  The research activities pursue three strategic objectives.  First, develop fundamental understanding of hierarchic correlations between the multi-scale architecture of complex macromolecules and mechanical properties of materials assembled of these molecular mesoblocks.  Theoretical studies will provide guidelines for synthesis of materials with an extraordinarily broad range of elasticity, strength, and toughness that are currently not available in conventional polymer systems.  Second, study the interaction of sound waves with stimuli responsive polymer systems and explore different activation mechanisms that shift density, modulus, compressibility, and shape.  Understanding the feedback between acoustically triggered changes in materials properties and the corresponding shifts in acoustic characteristics represents an intellectual challenge of this proposal.  Third, create a novel class of materials that can be activated, actuated, and navigated remotely using acoustic fields in a programmable and time-resolved manner.  An anticipated culmination of this project is acoustically transformative materials that not only respond to sound but also fundamentally change their physical properties, object dimensions, and acoustic and optical characteristics.  The collaborative nature of this project will ensure interdisciplinary training of junior researchers in polymer synthesis, physical experiments, and theory.  The project also provides opportunity for broadening participation of underrepresented groups and fostering infrastructure for collaborative research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1436201</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Rubinstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Rubinstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mr351@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196605365</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergei</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheiko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergei S Sheiko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sergei@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9198435270</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000001111</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275993290</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[903 Oxbow Crossing Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>054Z</Code>
<Text>(MGI) Materials Genome Initiative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~650000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~129999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to create novel classes of materials that can be activated and navigated by an acoustic field.<strong> </strong>Fundamental findings were reported in top scientific journals, such as <em>Nature</em>, <em>Science</em>, <em>Nature Materials</em>, <em>Nature Communications</em>, <em>Science Advances</em>, and <em>Advanced Materials</em>. Our research accomplishments were highlighted in <em>BBC News, The Guardian, Newsweek, Nature</em>, and <em>Chemical &amp; Engineering News</em> and covered by over 50 media outlets worldwide. The most significant achievements are described below.</p> <p><strong>Solvent-free, super-soft, and super-elastic elastomers.</strong> Currently, swollen polymer gels are the only viable class of synthetic materials with a Young?s modulus &lt; 100 kPa, but their solvent fraction leads to many practical problems including phase separation and leakage on deformation. We took advantage of architecturally disentangled macromolecules to develop a universal materials design platform, which allows precise programming of gel mechanics into brush-like polymer networks, with side chains playing a multifaceted role as ?solvent?, ?reactants?, and stiffness mediators. Within a <em>single chemical-component</em> system, the platform harnesses three independently controlled architectural parameters to encode the mechanical response of hydrogels. Applying this platform to ordinary silicone, we reduced its stiffness down to the biological level of ~10<sup>2</sup> Pa and increased extensibility up to 10-fold <em>without using solvent</em> as a material ?softener?. Furthermore, we enabled simultaneous increase of stiffness and extensibility by decreasing the grafting density, which breaks down one of the Golden Rules in materials engineering that stiffer materials are less extendable. This behavior was corroborated by coarse-grained molecular dynamics simulations and applied to the design of free-standing dielectric actuators.</p> <p><strong>Acoustically-responsive materials</strong> were designed by embedding expandable microcapsules in bottlebrush elastomers. We have synthesized unique microcapsules that allow tuning both the expansion temperature and dimensions of expanded capsules ? key parameters of echogenicity. These super-soft composites allowed internal expansion that empowers many unique applications such as acoustic switching of materials stiffness and acoustic lithography.<strong> </strong>The latter was demonstrated by 3D scanning of a sample with a high intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) beam, resulting in both surface and interior patterning with millimeter spatial resolution. The inductive heating effect by pulsed HIFU was studied as a function of acoustic pressure, frequency, and pulse duration to demonstrate accurate control over temperature and spatial resolution. The acoustically responsive capsules and the new lithographic technique have potential applications as acoustic contrast agents in oil exploration and medical diagnostics.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact. </strong>This project has inspired a <em>new direction in materials design,</em> wherein fundamental changes in physical properties are activated by sound waves that concurrently shift the acoustic, optical, and geometric characteristics of macroscopic objects. The interdisciplinary nature of the project ensured maximum opportunity for (i) integrating science and education through interdisciplinary training of junior researchers, (ii) enhancing diversity by involving underrepresented groups, and (iii) fostering infrastructure for collaborative research.&nbsp; The most essential accomplishments include: A) I<em>nterdisciplinary training</em>: each student in our group mastered synthesis, physics, and engineering. B) <em>Active partnership with industry and national labs including </em>Halliburton company, Controlled Radical Polymerization Consortium, Brookhaven National Lab, and Applied Research Laboratory. C) <em>International collaborations</em> between UNC, CMU, University of Hokkaido, University of Toronto, CNRS (France), and the Russian Academy of Sciences. Rubinstein (co-PI) leads the US Unit of the Global Station for Soft Matter (GSS) of GI-CoRE - Global Institution for Collaborative Research and Education at Hokkaido University. The project has provided an attractive platform for hosting five international exchange students from the Universities of Lyon, Coimbra, and Hamburg. D) <em>International recognitions</em>: Matyjaszewski<strong> </strong>received The Hermann Mark Medal (Austria, 2018), The Franklin Medal in Chemistry (2017), The International Dreyfus Prize in the Chemical Sciences (2015), Charles Overberger Award (ACS) (2015) and four honorary degrees (honoris causa) in Coimbra (2018), Padova (2017), Poznan (2016) and Haifa (2015). Rubinstein was elected as Chair of the Editorial Board of Soft Matter (2013-2017).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Sergei&nbsp;S&nbsp;Sheiko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to create novel classes of materials that can be activated and navigated by an acoustic field. Fundamental findings were reported in top scientific journals, such as Nature, Science, Nature Materials, Nature Communications, Science Advances, and Advanced Materials. Our research accomplishments were highlighted in BBC News, The Guardian, Newsweek, Nature, and Chemical &amp; Engineering News and covered by over 50 media outlets worldwide. The most significant achievements are described below.  Solvent-free, super-soft, and super-elastic elastomers. Currently, swollen polymer gels are the only viable class of synthetic materials with a Young?s modulus &lt; 100 kPa, but their solvent fraction leads to many practical problems including phase separation and leakage on deformation. We took advantage of architecturally disentangled macromolecules to develop a universal materials design platform, which allows precise programming of gel mechanics into brush-like polymer networks, with side chains playing a multifaceted role as ?solvent?, ?reactants?, and stiffness mediators. Within a single chemical-component system, the platform harnesses three independently controlled architectural parameters to encode the mechanical response of hydrogels. Applying this platform to ordinary silicone, we reduced its stiffness down to the biological level of ~102 Pa and increased extensibility up to 10-fold without using solvent as a material ?softener?. Furthermore, we enabled simultaneous increase of stiffness and extensibility by decreasing the grafting density, which breaks down one of the Golden Rules in materials engineering that stiffer materials are less extendable. This behavior was corroborated by coarse-grained molecular dynamics simulations and applied to the design of free-standing dielectric actuators.  Acoustically-responsive materials were designed by embedding expandable microcapsules in bottlebrush elastomers. We have synthesized unique microcapsules that allow tuning both the expansion temperature and dimensions of expanded capsules ? key parameters of echogenicity. These super-soft composites allowed internal expansion that empowers many unique applications such as acoustic switching of materials stiffness and acoustic lithography. The latter was demonstrated by 3D scanning of a sample with a high intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) beam, resulting in both surface and interior patterning with millimeter spatial resolution. The inductive heating effect by pulsed HIFU was studied as a function of acoustic pressure, frequency, and pulse duration to demonstrate accurate control over temperature and spatial resolution. The acoustically responsive capsules and the new lithographic technique have potential applications as acoustic contrast agents in oil exploration and medical diagnostics.  Broader Impact. This project has inspired a new direction in materials design, wherein fundamental changes in physical properties are activated by sound waves that concurrently shift the acoustic, optical, and geometric characteristics of macroscopic objects. The interdisciplinary nature of the project ensured maximum opportunity for (i) integrating science and education through interdisciplinary training of junior researchers, (ii) enhancing diversity by involving underrepresented groups, and (iii) fostering infrastructure for collaborative research.  The most essential accomplishments include: A) Interdisciplinary training: each student in our group mastered synthesis, physics, and engineering. B) Active partnership with industry and national labs including Halliburton company, Controlled Radical Polymerization Consortium, Brookhaven National Lab, and Applied Research Laboratory. C) International collaborations between UNC, CMU, University of Hokkaido, University of Toronto, CNRS (France), and the Russian Academy of Sciences. Rubinstein (co-PI) leads the US Unit of the Global Station for Soft Matter (GSS) of GI-CoRE - Global Institution for Collaborative Research and Education at Hokkaido University. The project has provided an attractive platform for hosting five international exchange students from the Universities of Lyon, Coimbra, and Hamburg. D) International recognitions: Matyjaszewski received The Hermann Mark Medal (Austria, 2018), The Franklin Medal in Chemistry (2017), The International Dreyfus Prize in the Chemical Sciences (2015), Charles Overberger Award (ACS) (2015) and four honorary degrees (honoris causa) in Coimbra (2018), Padova (2017), Poznan (2016) and Haifa (2015). Rubinstein was elected as Chair of the Editorial Board of Soft Matter (2013-2017).       Last Modified: 01/28/2020       Submitted by: Sergei S Sheiko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
