<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Improving the Sampling and Characterization of Intermediate Soils</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>310001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>310001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intermediate soils, which consist of varying mixtures of silts, clays, and sands, are common, naturally occurring deposits that can create design challenges for infrastructure projects involving dams, levees, highways, and building and bridge foundations. Geotechnical engineering practice is able to characterize clays and sands well, but it is the mixture of these two materials in combination with silt that can be particularly problematic. In some cases intermediate soils behave like clays and in others the behavior is like sands, and this uncertain transitional behavior violates the well-established knowledge base and standard of engineering practice used for clays and sands. The uncertainty in the characterization of intermediate soils forces engineers to be overly conservative (i.e., uneconomical) in the design of infrastructure projects to ensure the safety of society. This award supports research that will develop new methodologies for collecting intermediate soil samples by drilling and sampling, evaluating the quality of soil samples obtained, and accurately measuring their engineering properties in the laboratory for design of infrastructure. Outcomes from the research will provide practical guidance to the engineering profession leading to more reliable and economical design of infrastructure built upon intermediate soils. The project will also result in workforce development through the education and training of students and practicing engineers by incorporation of project findings into the classroom and professional short courses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary objective of this collaborative research project is to improve the understanding of how sampling influences the measured behavior of intermediate soils. The scope involves advanced triaxial testing that will simulate the sampling process, numerical modeling of the influence of various sampler geometries on sample state, creation of a conceptual sample disturbance framework, and implementation and validation of research findings at two field sites. The intellectual merit originates from three aspects: (1) research data and findings that will expand our knowledge of the effects of sampling on intermediate soils and their measured behavior; (2) formulation of a new conceptual framework that tracks the effect of sample disturbance on intermediate soils and creation of a corresponding new sample quality "index" parameter; and (3) development and validation via field testing of practice guidelines. The project will provide new scientific understanding and practical guidance that is urgently needed by the geotechnical engineering community. It is also anticipated that the research findings will be applicable to a broader range of materials, most notably fly ash, dredge materials, and mine tailings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1436617</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ross</FirstName>
<LastName>Boulanger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ross W Boulanger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rwboulanger@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307522947</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>DeJong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason T DeJong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdejong@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307548995</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000437976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1634</Code>
<Text>GEOMECHANICS &amp; GEOMATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>172E</Code>
<Text>Geomechanics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~310001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intermediate soils encompass an array of natural deposits, such as sandy clays, silty clays, clayey silt, silty sands, among others, and they usually exhibit transitional behavior with some properties being clay-like and others being sand-like. Such intermediate behavior violates assumptions inherent in the geotechnical engineering profession&rsquo;s standard of practice for characterization of sands and clays. Despite intermediate soils being frequently encountered on infrastructure projects worldwide, prior research on their behavior and characterization is limited. Such a knowledge gap leaves geotechnical engineering practitioners and researchers with a dilemma when dealing with intermediate soils on a project: What field sampling methods should be used? How should the quality of those samples be assessed? Given varying degrees of sample quality due to sampling disturbance, how accurate and reliable are laboratory measured parameters for design? These questions arise across a broad spectrum of infrastructure, including dams, levees, deep foundations, slopes, mine tailings, and embankments, among others. This research project tackled these issues through a collaborative effort between the University of California (UC) Davis and the University of Massachusetts (UMass) Amherst. The research integrated laboratory testing, numerical modeling and in-situ sampling and testing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Research outcomes from this project advanced both scientific knowledge and provided practical guidance to the geotechnical engineering profession in improving the characterization of intermediate soils. A new method for creating uniform, non-segregated, samples of low plasticity index (PI) intermediate soils for laboratory research testing was developed. Field sampling methods were simulated in the laboratory and the results generated new knowledge in understanding the presence of silt on the sampling process for intermediate soils.&nbsp; Most significantly the results showed that traditional clay based methods of evaluating sample disturbance for low PI intermediate soils does not work and furthermore the strength behavior of these soils responds markedly different than clays. These findings have important implications for practice and if not considered could lead to unsafe designs. Accordingly a new method of evaluating the quality of field collected samples of intermediate soils was created and shows promise when applied to a broad set of published data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The US NSF Team also collaborated with the Norwegian Geotechnical Institute (NGI; Oslo, Norway) on interpretation of our respective research results on sampling, evaluation of sample quality and testing of intermediate soils, and the practical implications of these results. NGI is also the lead institution on the Norwegian Research Council funded Norwegian GeoTest Sites (NGTS) project of which one of the research sites is the intermediate soil known as Halden silt.&nbsp; NGI hosted the NSF US team in the Winter 2019 for one week of sampling and in situ testing at the Halden research site. The US Team successfully collected tube soil samples of the Halden silt and conducted laboratory tests at NGI and on samples transported to UMass Amherst to validate the new sample quality criteria.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Research findings were disseminated to students in the classroom at UC Davis and UMass Amherst and more broadly to other students, practitioners, and the public through the conduct of short courses, invited seminars, journal publications, and conference presentations and publications. Additional broader impacts included the training and mentoring of undergraduate and graduate students in basic and advanced geotechnical laboratory testing, field sampling, and in situ testing. Successful advancement and improvement of approaches developed in this project for characterizing intermediate soils could result in increased safety of constructed geosystems, reduced conservatism, and economic benefits.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;T&nbsp;Dejong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intermediate soils encompass an array of natural deposits, such as sandy clays, silty clays, clayey silt, silty sands, among others, and they usually exhibit transitional behavior with some properties being clay-like and others being sand-like. Such intermediate behavior violates assumptions inherent in the geotechnical engineering profession?s standard of practice for characterization of sands and clays. Despite intermediate soils being frequently encountered on infrastructure projects worldwide, prior research on their behavior and characterization is limited. Such a knowledge gap leaves geotechnical engineering practitioners and researchers with a dilemma when dealing with intermediate soils on a project: What field sampling methods should be used? How should the quality of those samples be assessed? Given varying degrees of sample quality due to sampling disturbance, how accurate and reliable are laboratory measured parameters for design? These questions arise across a broad spectrum of infrastructure, including dams, levees, deep foundations, slopes, mine tailings, and embankments, among others. This research project tackled these issues through a collaborative effort between the University of California (UC) Davis and the University of Massachusetts (UMass) Amherst. The research integrated laboratory testing, numerical modeling and in-situ sampling and testing.     Research outcomes from this project advanced both scientific knowledge and provided practical guidance to the geotechnical engineering profession in improving the characterization of intermediate soils. A new method for creating uniform, non-segregated, samples of low plasticity index (PI) intermediate soils for laboratory research testing was developed. Field sampling methods were simulated in the laboratory and the results generated new knowledge in understanding the presence of silt on the sampling process for intermediate soils.  Most significantly the results showed that traditional clay based methods of evaluating sample disturbance for low PI intermediate soils does not work and furthermore the strength behavior of these soils responds markedly different than clays. These findings have important implications for practice and if not considered could lead to unsafe designs. Accordingly a new method of evaluating the quality of field collected samples of intermediate soils was created and shows promise when applied to a broad set of published data.     The US NSF Team also collaborated with the Norwegian Geotechnical Institute (NGI; Oslo, Norway) on interpretation of our respective research results on sampling, evaluation of sample quality and testing of intermediate soils, and the practical implications of these results. NGI is also the lead institution on the Norwegian Research Council funded Norwegian GeoTest Sites (NGTS) project of which one of the research sites is the intermediate soil known as Halden silt.  NGI hosted the NSF US team in the Winter 2019 for one week of sampling and in situ testing at the Halden research site. The US Team successfully collected tube soil samples of the Halden silt and conducted laboratory tests at NGI and on samples transported to UMass Amherst to validate the new sample quality criteria.     Research findings were disseminated to students in the classroom at UC Davis and UMass Amherst and more broadly to other students, practitioners, and the public through the conduct of short courses, invited seminars, journal publications, and conference presentations and publications. Additional broader impacts included the training and mentoring of undergraduate and graduate students in basic and advanced geotechnical laboratory testing, field sampling, and in situ testing. Successful advancement and improvement of approaches developed in this project for characterizing intermediate soils could result in increased safety of constructed geosystems, reduced conservatism, and economic benefits.          Last Modified: 11/04/2019       Submitted by: Jason T Dejong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
