<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Collaborative Research: Development and Application of Piezoelectric Nanoheterostructures to Reduce the Chemical and Energy Demand of Water Treatment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>205999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Shuai&lt;br/&gt;1437989&lt;br/&gt;Cwiertny&lt;br/&gt;1437122&lt;br/&gt;Nam&lt;br/&gt;1437923&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SusChEM: Collaborative Research: Development and Application of Piezoelectric Nanoheterostructures to Reduce the Chemical and Energy Demand of Water Treatment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Water and wastewater treatment account for approximately 5 % of all of the energy consumption in the US. Therefore, in response to the tremendous chemical and energy demands associated with clean water production, this project will develop nanostructured piezoelectric catalysts for converting the abundance of waste mechanical energy available in water treatment (e.g., pump vibrations) into useable forms of chemical energy for pollutant degradation.  The scientific goals are coupled to educational goals are to train three graduate and several undergraduate students at the interface of catalysis, environmental chemistry, nanotechnology, materials science and sustainability science, helping better prepare the research leaders of tomorrow to address the complex, multi-faceted problems posed by the energy-water nexus. The education and outreach initiatives center on underrepresented groups in STEM and K-12, promoting their involvement in research activities at the George Washington University (GW), U.C. Riverside (UCR; a Hispanic serving institution (HSI)), and the University of Iowa (UI). This includes an undergraduate research partnership between UCR and Cal Poly Pomona (a primarily undergraduate institution and HSI), and PI involvement in existing mentoring activities at GW (School Without Walls) and UI (Summer Research Opportunities Scholars Program).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The motivation for this study is the overriding hypothesis that inefficiencies in current piezocatalysts can be overcome by the smart design of one-dimensional (1D) hybrid nanostructures optimized for (i) potential and current generation via the direct piezoelectric effect and (ii) efficient piezogenerated charge separation via co-catalysts that promote ROS production. The research plan centers on two main tasks to (i) rationally design, fabricate and optimize the performance of piezoelectric catalysts, and (ii) demonstrate their application as versatile, next-generation technologies for pollutant oxidation, disinfection, antimicrobial surfaces, and chemically reactive filtration membranes. The studies proposed will focus primarily on a novel class of composite nanofibers prepared via electro-spinning that blend the resiliency and strength of polymeric piezoelectric materials (e.g., PVDF) with more reactive inorganic phases (e.g., ZnO, BaTiO3) that are otherwise too rigid and chemically less stable to function as stand-alone piezocatalysts. This work is potentially transformative in that catalytic nanofiber platforms developed will provide a more sustainable route to advanced oxidation processes (AOPs) and membrane filtration, high performance technologies that currently are limited in application due to concerns associated with their chemical demand, cost and carbon footprint.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1437989</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tianshu</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tianshu Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tsli@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029943809</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danmeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Shuai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danmeng Shuai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>danmengshuai@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029940506</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000641485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 22nd Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 19"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Paramount to our sustainable water future will be developing new technologies that minimize the energy intensity associated with production of next generation water resources (e.g., wastewater reuse). Advanced oxidation processes (AOPs) that are currently used in industrial processes for water and wastewater treatment are energy and chemical intensive, and they could compromise our future of sustainable development. Our study has investigated two processes, piezocatalysis and photocatalysis, that can potentially use waste and renewable energy for promoting sustainable water purification.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>We first fabricated ultralong nanowires of barium titanate, which is a piezocatalysts, for utilizing ultrasonic vibrations and ambient vibrations for organic contaminant degradation. We have founded that the contaminants could be degraded under mechanical vibrations, yet the efficiency was low. We next evaluated a visible-light-responsive photocatalyst, graphitic carbon nitride, that can use a larger amount of renewable solar energy for contaminant transformation. We quantitiavely analyzed the production of reactive oxygen spcies, and found that these oxidative species did not contribute to contaminant degradation substantially. In contrast, the holes generated in photocatalysis, which were largely overlooked in previous studies, determined the reaction kinteics of contaminant transformation, as suggested by molecular simulations.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our research findings not only shed light on advanced oxidation and sustainable water purification, but also provide guidelines to design advanced materials for water and energy applications. Graduate and undergraduate research assistants, some of whom are from underrepresented groups in STEM, were trained under the project, and they will be future leading workforce in water quality engineering.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Danmeng&nbsp;Shuai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1437989/1437989_10321362_1535817051452_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1437989/1437989_10321362_1535817051452_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="barium titanate nanowires"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1437989/1437989_10321362_1535817051452_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="barium titanate nanowires"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">barium titanate nanowires</div> <div class="imageCredit">Danmeng Shuai</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Danmeng&nbsp;Shuai</div> <div class="imageTitle">barium titanate nanowires</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1437989/1437989_10321362_1535817102199_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1437989/1437989_10321362_1535817102199_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="hole oxidation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1437989/1437989_10321362_1535817102199_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="hole oxidation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">hole oxidation of organic contaminant phenol and atrazine on graphitic carbon nitride</div> <div class="imageCredit">Danmeng Shuai</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Danmeng&nbsp;Shuai</div> <div class="imageTitle">hole oxidation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Paramount to our sustainable water future will be developing new technologies that minimize the energy intensity associated with production of next generation water resources (e.g., wastewater reuse). Advanced oxidation processes (AOPs) that are currently used in industrial processes for water and wastewater treatment are energy and chemical intensive, and they could compromise our future of sustainable development. Our study has investigated two processes, piezocatalysis and photocatalysis, that can potentially use waste and renewable energy for promoting sustainable water purification.   We first fabricated ultralong nanowires of barium titanate, which is a piezocatalysts, for utilizing ultrasonic vibrations and ambient vibrations for organic contaminant degradation. We have founded that the contaminants could be degraded under mechanical vibrations, yet the efficiency was low. We next evaluated a visible-light-responsive photocatalyst, graphitic carbon nitride, that can use a larger amount of renewable solar energy for contaminant transformation. We quantitiavely analyzed the production of reactive oxygen spcies, and found that these oxidative species did not contribute to contaminant degradation substantially. In contrast, the holes generated in photocatalysis, which were largely overlooked in previous studies, determined the reaction kinteics of contaminant transformation, as suggested by molecular simulations.   Our research findings not only shed light on advanced oxidation and sustainable water purification, but also provide guidelines to design advanced materials for water and energy applications. Graduate and undergraduate research assistants, some of whom are from underrepresented groups in STEM, were trained under the project, and they will be future leading workforce in water quality engineering.                 Last Modified: 09/01/2018       Submitted by: Danmeng Shuai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
