<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Understanding Excitons for Lead-Free Perovskite Photovoltaics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>329395.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>329395</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Principal Investigator: André Schleife&lt;br/&gt;Number: 1437230&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nontechnical Description&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The sun represents the most abundant potential source of pollution-free energy on earth.  Solar cells for producing electricity require materials that absorb the sun?s energy and convert its photons to electrons, a process called photovoltaics.  The search for the best photovoltaic material is an active area of solar cell research.  Recently, an exciting new class of photovoltaic materials called organo-metal perovskites has emerged. These materials are promising because they have low production cost, use elements and materials abundant in the earth?s crust, and currently possess solar energy conversion efficiencies of over 15%.  Further research is needed to tune the optical properties of these materials to improve light absorption needed to push the efficiencies over 20% to be competitive with silicon solar cells, and to remove lead, which is toxic, from the material matrix.  The goal of this project is to gain a fundamental understanding of the beneficial electronic and optical properties of organo-metal perovskites to address these two issues.  Advanced computational approaches will be used to predict electronic and optical properties of organo-metal perovskites at the atomic level to study how quantum mechanics plays a role in the performance of these materials for solar photovoltaic applications.  Model simulations will be performed to identify replacements for lead that maintain desirable solar energy absorption characteristics. Scientific results will be made available to the public in blog-style updates, and a database will be provided to the scientific community to confirm the findings and make use of this information. In addition, in this project will provide training of material science graduate and undergraduate students in advanced supercomputer techniques needed to provide a pipeline of trained scientists in this critical area of national workforce need. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, organo-metal perovskites, especially those based on lead, have emerged as an exciting new class of earth-abundant photovoltaic materials with solar energy conversion efficiencies exceeding 15% and potential for low manufacturing cost. The goal of this project is to gain a fundamental understanding of the excitonic and optical properties of organo-metal perovskites through advanced computational models, and then use this approach to identify replacements for lead in the material matrix.  The perovskite material system offers a large phase space for improvement by replacing different constituent atoms. However, for targeted development, a fundamental understanding of electronic correlations, particularly the physics that governs the excitonic and charge-transport properties, is needed.  In this regard, the interplay between free carriers in systems with perovskite crystal structures that possess optical and excitonic properties is unknown.  Theoretical spectroscopy techniques based on many-body perturbation theory will be used to achieve a fundamental understanding of light-matter interaction in perovskite-halide materials with different constituent ions. First-principles techniques based on Hedin?s approximation and the Bethe-Salpeter equation, which accurately computes quantum-mechanical, electron-electron, and electron-hole interactions, will be used to predict band gaps, effective carrier masses, and optical absorption spectra.  By taking into account quasi-particle energies, excitonic effects, and the interplay with free carriers, this approach will provide mechanistic insights into the optical absorption process in perovskites. This project will also investigate the influence of different constituents, particularly systems with and without lead ions, on these optical absorption processes.  The research outcomes will be made available to the public in blog-style updates, and the computational results will be provided to the scientific community for continued validation. In addition, in this project will provide training of material science graduate and undergraduate students in advanced atomistic modeling techniques on supercomputing platforms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1437230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andre</FirstName>
<LastName>Schleife</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andre Schleife</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schleife@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172440339</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000657211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618012920</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>146E</Code>
<Text>Solar energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~329395</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>We used highly accurate quantum-mechanical simulations to understand the optical properties of several representative materials that belong to the class of <span>organo</span>-metal halide <span>perovskites</span>. Since their crystal structures sensitively depend on temperature, we include three different <span>polymorphs</span> in this study and compute lattice parameters, electronic band structure, density of states, and optical properties. Spin-orbit coupling is accounted for in these simulations.</span></p> <p><br /><span>The main intellectual merit of this work is our quantification of the influence of free electrons in these <span>photovoltaic</span> materials on optical properties and binding energies of electron-hole pairs. By thoroughly simulating this effect for methyl-ammonia lead iodide, we show that free electrons contribute significantly to dielectric screening and strongly reduce the exciton binding energy. This can help reconcile exciton binding energies from first-principles simulations and those measured in experiment. It also allows us to directly compare experimental and computational results for optical properties, which ultimate can be useful to establish a close relation between structural and optical properties. In addition, we apply similarly accurate simulation techniques to various other hybrid <span>perovskites</span> and explore their optical properties in detail, enabling us to propose better candidate materials for their respective applications. This includes lead-free alternative materials to <span>MAPI</span>, and gives a good overview of their electronic and optical properties. Finally, we also employ a novel data-base driven scheme for material selection to methyl-ammonia lead iodide, in order to identify well-suited electron- and hole-transport layer materials, if used in a solar cell. This scheme indeed predicts several candidates for these contact materials.</span></p> <p><br /><span>This project more broadly also has impact in the data-science area, since simulation input and output data will be made publicly accessible and out database-driven screening made use of publicly accessible data. We envision that this will lead to yet <span>onforeseen</span> use of our simulation results. Results from this project were also presented to high-school students, in order to attract them to scientific and engineering fields. Atomic geometries were particularly useful in this context, e.g. for the <span>GLAM</span> summer camp or the <span>Engeering</span> Open House. The participating high-school students were excited and curious about what was shown. Our presentation team received many questions and better explained the STEM life to the audience. The project trained grad and undergrad students, who are now excellently equipped for finding a position after. This work also lead to several new and fruitful collaborations that we will continue.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Andre&nbsp;Schleife</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We used highly accurate quantum-mechanical simulations to understand the optical properties of several representative materials that belong to the class of organo-metal halide perovskites. Since their crystal structures sensitively depend on temperature, we include three different polymorphs in this study and compute lattice parameters, electronic band structure, density of states, and optical properties. Spin-orbit coupling is accounted for in these simulations.   The main intellectual merit of this work is our quantification of the influence of free electrons in these photovoltaic materials on optical properties and binding energies of electron-hole pairs. By thoroughly simulating this effect for methyl-ammonia lead iodide, we show that free electrons contribute significantly to dielectric screening and strongly reduce the exciton binding energy. This can help reconcile exciton binding energies from first-principles simulations and those measured in experiment. It also allows us to directly compare experimental and computational results for optical properties, which ultimate can be useful to establish a close relation between structural and optical properties. In addition, we apply similarly accurate simulation techniques to various other hybrid perovskites and explore their optical properties in detail, enabling us to propose better candidate materials for their respective applications. This includes lead-free alternative materials to MAPI, and gives a good overview of their electronic and optical properties. Finally, we also employ a novel data-base driven scheme for material selection to methyl-ammonia lead iodide, in order to identify well-suited electron- and hole-transport layer materials, if used in a solar cell. This scheme indeed predicts several candidates for these contact materials.   This project more broadly also has impact in the data-science area, since simulation input and output data will be made publicly accessible and out database-driven screening made use of publicly accessible data. We envision that this will lead to yet onforeseen use of our simulation results. Results from this project were also presented to high-school students, in order to attract them to scientific and engineering fields. Atomic geometries were particularly useful in this context, e.g. for the GLAM summer camp or the Engeering Open House. The participating high-school students were excited and curious about what was shown. Our presentation team received many questions and better explained the STEM life to the audience. The project trained grad and undergrad students, who are now excellently equipped for finding a position after. This work also lead to several new and fruitful collaborations that we will continue.       Last Modified: 02/07/2019       Submitted by: Andre Schleife]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
