<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Advanced Discretization Techniques and Applications (ADTA)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Advanced Discretization Techniques and Applications (ADTA) workshop will be held at Texas A&amp;M University, May 11-15, 2015. During the last few decades, finite element methods (FEM) have come to be among the most important tools for numerically approximating solutions of partial differential equations. FEM are a powerful research tool in subsurface engineering, structural engineering, failure analysis, earthquake engineering, progressive collapse, biophysics, electromagnetics, acoustics, solar and fuel cell, batteries, and material sciences, to mention but a few. Despite considerable work on their analysis, many aspects of the method continue to be improved. The novel techniques allow us to pursue comprehensive understanding and reliability of the numerical results, to improve the accuracy, reduce computational costs, and guarantee product credibility. The objective of this workshop is to bring researchers working on advanced discretization techniques and multiscale algorithms and promote interaction among these different groups. By bringing these researchers together, we expect to have an impact in many areas and promote progress in designing efficient multiscale discretization techniques for a wide range of problems. By holding this conference at Texas A&amp;M University, a university traditionally strong in engineering and natural sciences, we expect to disseminate the know-how to researchers not only in mathematics, but also in other disciplines. We will actively pursue participation by non-mathematicians. This conference will therefore help researchers and practitioners improve their theoretical tools and deepen their knowledge of modern trends in numerical analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will cover a range of topics in finite element methods (FEM) and applications. Recent advances in finite element methodologies, in particular, the discontinuous Galerkin method (DG-FEM), weak Galerkin finite element methods (WG-FEM), and multiscale methods, will be some of the central workshop topics. The workshop will bring together researchers working on various finite element discretization techniques and multiscale methods and promote interaction among different groups.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1438451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raytcho</FirstName>
<LastName>Lazarov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raytcho D Lazarov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lazarov@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7862021878</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000413976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yalchin</FirstName>
<LastName>Efendiev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yalchin Efendiev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>efendiev@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798451972</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ke</FirstName>
<LastName>Shi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ke Shi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shike@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798626777</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660568</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/07/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433368</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 6"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>Computational mathematics are important for many applied disciplines. A strong knowledge of discretization techniques are cruicial for solving many challenging important problems in the area of engineering, biology, medicine, environment, geosciences, and so on.The tools and methods of computational mathematics create a rich and powerful environment for solving industrial problems with high efficiency and reliability. However, successfully using this environment requires knowledge, common language, interaction and mutual understanding among mathematicians, engineers, computer scientists and practitioners. The workshop brought together experts from academia, national labs, and the industry in order to exchange ideas in numerical discretizations that are common in numeruous applications.Through proper training, dissemination new ideas and through interaction of academia with industry and better understanding of the engineering community&rsquo;s needs, the new methods can be widely used for many application areas and these areas can tremendously benefit from these approaches.The workshop attracted applied and theoretical computational mathematicians and brought together researchers from academia and industry as well as junior and senior scientists. Novel methods and ideas are discussed. An active poster session created an environment for the exchange of ideas. &nbsp;The conference helped researchers and practitioners to improve their theoretical tools and deepen their knowledge in modern trends of numerical analysis. Beyond targeting faculty and postdocs, the conference&rsquo;s topics aimed at graduate students by organizing tutorial sessions.</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Yalchin&nbsp;Efendiev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Computational mathematics are important for many applied disciplines. A strong knowledge of discretization techniques are cruicial for solving many challenging important problems in the area of engineering, biology, medicine, environment, geosciences, and so on.The tools and methods of computational mathematics create a rich and powerful environment for solving industrial problems with high efficiency and reliability. However, successfully using this environment requires knowledge, common language, interaction and mutual understanding among mathematicians, engineers, computer scientists and practitioners. The workshop brought together experts from academia, national labs, and the industry in order to exchange ideas in numerical discretizations that are common in numeruous applications.Through proper training, dissemination new ideas and through interaction of academia with industry and better understanding of the engineering communityÆs needs, the new methods can be widely used for many application areas and these areas can tremendously benefit from these approaches.The workshop attracted applied and theoretical computational mathematicians and brought together researchers from academia and industry as well as junior and senior scientists. Novel methods and ideas are discussed. An active poster session created an environment for the exchange of ideas.  The conference helped researchers and practitioners to improve their theoretical tools and deepen their knowledge in modern trends of numerical analysis. Beyond targeting faculty and postdocs, the conferenceÆs topics aimed at graduate students by organizing tutorial sessions.          Last Modified: 03/03/2016       Submitted by: Yalchin Efendiev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
