<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM:  Using theory-driven design to tailor novel nanocomposite oxides for solar fuel production</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>550000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title:  SusChEM.  The Design of Materials to Harvest and Store Solar Energy in Chemical Bonds: Tailoring nanocomposite catalytic structures for artificial photosynthesis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The basis for this proposed research is the fact that more of the sun's energy hits the face of the earth in two hours than is consumed globally in a year.  Yet only minor amounts of sunlight are currently harvested to meet an ever-growing energy demand.  The conversion of sunlight to chemical energy is a promising strategy to deliver greater use of solar energy and to provide a variety of possibilities for local, off-the-grid energy storage.  The particular focus of this research is the light-driven conversion of CO2 that opens up new strategies for developing closed loop carbon cycles, a key aim of sustainability.  To undertake this effort, an award is made to Professors Kimberly Gray, Justin Notestein and Eric Weitz of Northwestern University in line with the SusChEM initiative. An international and interdisciplinary team of catalysis experts has been assembled utilizing the US-Ireland R&amp;D Partnership program. This international R&amp;D Partnership leverages funding from the Irish and UK governments. This team has unparalleled capabilities to carry out theory-driven design, synthesis and testing of multifunctional catalysts that will separate and control the distinct steps of the complex series of reactions around sunlight-driven CO2 conversion. The goal is to improve the fundamental understanding of the mechanisms of CO2 photo-reduction and as a result, the achievement of much higher product yields and energy conversion efficiencies than is currently possible. Researchers on this project will also participate in a Climate Change and Sustainability Professional Development Series that connects middle and high school teachers to cutting-edge academic research and provide STEM enrichment to a racially and economically diverse student population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The photochemical fixation of CO2 to energy rich products, essentially artificial photosynthesis, whether for solar energy storage or the production of potential feedstock chemicals, involves an exceedingly complex system of reactions requiring novel, multifunctional nanoarchitectures that can harvest visible light, stabilize charge separation, reduce the heterogeneity of surface sites, activate CO2, and control the reaction pathway. The overarching hypothesis of the proposed work is that multi-functional nanocomposite metal oxide clusters supported on a semiconductor surface that couple photo- and thermal catalysis can be designed from first principles, and then synthesized and engineered in order to convert CO2 to useful two-electron reduction products selectively and with greatly improved efficiency. The research integrates theory, synthesis, characterization, mechanism interrogation and application and links the efforts of three research teams in a coordinated fashion providing feedback to inform next steps. First principles modeling will be used to design nanostructures tailored to CO2 conversion, followed by sophisticated and controlled synthesis techniques to execute these designs and then, the verification of their efficacy by rigorous structural and functional characterization and scaled-up engineering testing. This is feasible only through a team effort, which will then offer a compelling and potentially transformative strategy to improve fundamentally the efficiency and selectivity of CO2 reduction chemistry and process engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1438721</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Weitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Weitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>weitz@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474915583</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000164244</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Gray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly A Gray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>k-gray@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474674252</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000289403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Notestein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin M Notestein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j-notestein@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474915357</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527478</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602083109</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>044E</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>046E</Code>
<Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~550000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many consider CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>the most pressing pollutant of our time, and routes are needed to integrate CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>utilization into the chemical industry.&nbsp;The overarching goal of this research was to develop photoactive materials that could be used to convert CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>to products selectively and with high yields and thereby, create carbon neutral resource cycles. In addition, our aim was to understand the underlying chemical mechanisms by which such reactions occurred. We assembled an international and interdisciplinary team&nbsp;to carry out theory-driven design, material synthesis and reaction testing of multifunctional catalysts, efforts that are consistent with the goals of the US-Ireland R&amp;D Partnership&nbsp;and the Sustainable Chemistry, Engineering and Materials initiative. &nbsp;</p> <p>Many different approaches to CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>reduction have been investigated, but the ability of high energy light (vacuum UV (VUV) irradiation at 185 nm) to cleave C-O bonds remains largely unexplored for use in processes that convert CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>into useful products. Compared with other photo-driven CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>conversion processes, we have demonstrated that VUV-initiated CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>reduction can achieve much greater conversion under common photochemical reaction conditions when H<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>and non-reducible oxides are present.&nbsp;&nbsp;For instance, when the reaction is carried out in the presence of silica or alumina surfaces, CO yields are increased and small amounts of CH<sub>4&nbsp;</sub>are formed as the only other detected product.&nbsp;We found that nearly 30% conversion of CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>to CO and CH<sub>4&nbsp;</sub>occurs under these relatively simple conditions via a radical chain reaction initiated by the photolysis of CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>and accelerated by the addition of H<sub>2.&nbsp;</sub>&nbsp;This is an entirely different mechanism of reaction than that of photocatalytically driven CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>conversion.&nbsp;Assuming improvements in lamp and reactor efficiencies with scale up, or coupling with other available CO/CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>hydrogenation techniques, these results reveal a simple strategy by which CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>could be valorized.&nbsp;Our investigation, then, demonstrates an alternative way to achieve the photoreduction of CO<sub>2</sub>, with high and selective product yields, pointing to potential practical applications of CO<sub>2 </sub>conversion.</p> <p>The reverse water-gas shift (RWGS) is a common route of CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>utilization. Copper-based catalysts are well-known for CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>conversion, but our work has shown unusual and superior performance of Cu supported on TiO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>nanotubes, as compared to a conventional TiO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>support. We have previously shown the strained surface of TiO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>nanotubes promotes high performance in CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>photoreduction, but its role in shaping metal-based conversions has not been explored. Here, through a combination of analytical techniques, we discovered three distinct behaviors as the Cu surface density increases and showed that surface reconstruction during H<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>pretreatment of the catalysts plays a significant role in determining the reactivity of these materials. Specifically, at intermediate Cu loadings, Cu nanoparticles are completely engulfed by a TiOx overlayer, and the subsequent catalytic activity appears to occur at (numerous) defects on the TiOx surface. In contrast, at both higher loadings where nanoparticles are not completely engulfed, and at the lowest loadings where Cu nanoparticles do not form, catalytically relevant Cu-O-Ti interfaces are responsible for the observed reactivity.&nbsp;&nbsp;These findings provide important insights for creating effective interfaces on supported metal catalysts in CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>activation and conversion.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Kimberly&nbsp;A&nbsp;Gray</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many consider CO2 the most pressing pollutant of our time, and routes are needed to integrate CO2 utilization into the chemical industry. The overarching goal of this research was to develop photoactive materials that could be used to convert CO2 to products selectively and with high yields and thereby, create carbon neutral resource cycles. In addition, our aim was to understand the underlying chemical mechanisms by which such reactions occurred. We assembled an international and interdisciplinary team to carry out theory-driven design, material synthesis and reaction testing of multifunctional catalysts, efforts that are consistent with the goals of the US-Ireland R&amp;D Partnership and the Sustainable Chemistry, Engineering and Materials initiative.    Many different approaches to CO2 reduction have been investigated, but the ability of high energy light (vacuum UV (VUV) irradiation at 185 nm) to cleave C-O bonds remains largely unexplored for use in processes that convert CO2 into useful products. Compared with other photo-driven CO2 conversion processes, we have demonstrated that VUV-initiated CO2 reduction can achieve much greater conversion under common photochemical reaction conditions when H2 and non-reducible oxides are present.  For instance, when the reaction is carried out in the presence of silica or alumina surfaces, CO yields are increased and small amounts of CH4 are formed as the only other detected product. We found that nearly 30% conversion of CO2 to CO and CH4 occurs under these relatively simple conditions via a radical chain reaction initiated by the photolysis of CO2 and accelerated by the addition of H2.  This is an entirely different mechanism of reaction than that of photocatalytically driven CO2 conversion. Assuming improvements in lamp and reactor efficiencies with scale up, or coupling with other available CO/CO2 hydrogenation techniques, these results reveal a simple strategy by which CO2 could be valorized. Our investigation, then, demonstrates an alternative way to achieve the photoreduction of CO2, with high and selective product yields, pointing to potential practical applications of CO2 conversion.  The reverse water-gas shift (RWGS) is a common route of CO2 utilization. Copper-based catalysts are well-known for CO2 conversion, but our work has shown unusual and superior performance of Cu supported on TiO2 nanotubes, as compared to a conventional TiO2 support. We have previously shown the strained surface of TiO2 nanotubes promotes high performance in CO2 photoreduction, but its role in shaping metal-based conversions has not been explored. Here, through a combination of analytical techniques, we discovered three distinct behaviors as the Cu surface density increases and showed that surface reconstruction during H2 pretreatment of the catalysts plays a significant role in determining the reactivity of these materials. Specifically, at intermediate Cu loadings, Cu nanoparticles are completely engulfed by a TiOx overlayer, and the subsequent catalytic activity appears to occur at (numerous) defects on the TiOx surface. In contrast, at both higher loadings where nanoparticles are not completely engulfed, and at the lowest loadings where Cu nanoparticles do not form, catalytically relevant Cu-O-Ti interfaces are responsible for the observed reactivity.  These findings provide important insights for creating effective interfaces on supported metal catalysts in CO2 activation and conversion.                 Last Modified: 12/01/2018       Submitted by: Kimberly A Gray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
