<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Municipal Solid Waste Leachate Organic Matter Generation and Removal</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>315356.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>371410</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927066</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET-1438416 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses the management of a particularly challenging constituent of leachate from landfills, leachate organic matter (LOM), with the goal of reducing the long-term risks and costs associated with landfill operation. Through this research, for the first time, information will be provided that may lead to the control of LOM that passes through biological treatment systems. Further, by providing information regarding the potential for natural systems to assimilate low level contributions of non-biodegradable LOM from closed landfills, society may be relieved from long-term financial burdens of landfill post-closure care (PCC). A better understanding of LOM fate and behavior can provide regulators with the information needed to confidently approve reducing or terminating landfill PCC. The proposed research has clear societal benefits associated with reduced cost and risk of landfills, a greater understanding of leachate discharges to the environment, and more sustainable solid waste management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will examine the chemical nature of leachate organic matter (LOM) to better understand the humification of landfilled waste and the fate of discharged LOM to the environment after in situ landfill treatment, co-treatment at a Waste Water Treatment Plant, or on-site biological treatment. The hypothesis is that recalcitrant LOM production is associated with specific components of solid waste, therefore the avoidance of these components in future landfills could result in enhanced leachate treatability and reduced treatment cost. It is further hypothesized that the consequences of discharging LOM in treated leachate from existing landfills can be attenuated through passive sunlight-driven photolysis. Specific research questions to be addressed include the following: (1) which waste components contribute to recalcitrant LOM; (2) can we use advanced characterization tools to better understand the potential for LOM biodegradation, photolysis, or contaminant transport; and (3) what is the fate of recalcitrant LOM in aquatic environments (e.g., wetlands and surface waters), with a focus on photolysis? This research will be accomplished by well characterizing LOM, conducting microcosms examining the evolution of LOM from waste components, and evaluating LOM photolysis of leachate samples irradiated by natural sunlight and a solar simulator. The broader impacts of this proposed research also include the advancement of understanding of chemistry and photochemistry of organic matter. The proposed research is a multidisciplinary project that involves a diverse group of female researchers, bridging environmental engineering and physical science fields and impacting multiple areas of the scientific community. The doctoral researcher assigned to this project is a female minority student, contributing to diversity in the science and engineering workforce. Outreach to art and design students through UCFSTEAM (Science, Technology, Engineering, Art, and Mathematics) activities will also provide broader impacts. Researcher involvement with K-16 students through school visitations provides an opportunity to increase STEM understanding.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1438416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Cottrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara A Cottrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bcottrel@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6193065292</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000661953</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Debra</FirstName>
<LastName>Reinhart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Debra R Reinhart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>reinhart@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078232315</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000267023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Kibler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly Kibler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kelly.Kibler@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078234150</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000702072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8026</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Energy Pathways</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004Z</Code>
<Text>Innovations at the Nexus of Food-Energy-</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8020</Code>
<Text>Green Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~315356</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~49954</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~6100</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This research examined the chemical nature of leachate organic matter (LOM) to better understand the humification of landfilled waste and the fate of discharged LOM to the environment after in situ landfill treatment, co-treatment at a wastewater treatment facility, or on-site biological treatment. Specific research questions addressed included the following: (1) which waste components contribute to recalcitrant LOM; (2) can we use advanced characterization tools to better understand the potential for LOM biodegradation, photolysis, or contaminant transport; (3) what are the energy and water footprints of wasted food, with particular attention to the uncharted and highly coupled water and energy impacts of food waste management, and (4) what is the fate of recalcitrant LOM in aquatic environments (e.g., wetlands and surface waters), with a focus on photolysis? This research was accomplished by well characterizing LOM, conducting microcosms examining the evolution of LOM from waste components, and evaluating LOM photolysis of leachate samples irradiated by natural sunlight. Major findings include: (1) rapid spectroscopic analysis can be used to understand the humification of LOM generated by landfilling of organics better than conventional analytics measurements such as BOD, COD, and TOC, (2) Lom generated during degradation of various waste components (e.g., paper, cotton, wood waste, and food waste) can be differentiated by their fluorescence, uv-absorption, methane generation potential, and molecular size, (3) conceptual mapping of energy and water requirements related to various food waste management alternatives allows gaps in information related to the post-disposal phase of food production to be identified; reducing food waste can save energy, not only in the food production phase, but in the post-disposal phase, and (4) sunlight-driven processes are possible for the treatment of LOM through the degradation of high molecular weight recalcitrant material into lower molecular weight material.</span></p> <p><span>This research addressed the management of a particularly challenging constituent of leachate from landfills, leachate organic matter (LOM), with the goal of reducing the long-term risks and costs associated with landfill operation. Through this research, for the first time, information was provided that may lead to the control of LOM that passes through biological treatment systems. Further, by providing information regarding the potential for natural systems to assimilate low level contributions of non-biodegradable LOM from closed landfills, society may be relieved from long-term financial burdens of landfill post-closure care (PCC). A better understanding of LOM fate and behavior can provide regulators with the information needed to confidently approve reducing or terminating landfill PCC. The clear societal benefits associated with the research include reduced cost and risk of landfills, a greater understanding of leachate discharges to the environment, and more sustainable solid waste management. The broader impacts of this proposed research also include the advancement of understanding of chemistry and photochemistry of organic matter. The research was a multidisciplinary project that involved a diverse group of female researchers, bridging environmental engineering and physical science fields and impacting multiple areas of the scientific community. The doctoral researcher assigned to this project is a female minority now a practicing engineer. All Principal Investigators were female, including two engineers and one chemist.&nbsp; Outreach to art and design students through UCFSTEAM (Science, Technology, Engineering, Art, and Mathematics) activities also provided broader impacts (see Figures). PIs have published one paper, submitted two manuscripts to peer-reviewed publications, and presented findings at seven international conferences.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2018<br>      Modified by: Debra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Reinhart</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1438416/1438416_10320297_1545084213624_STEAM2015Exhibit--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1438416/1438416_10320297_1545084213624_STEAM2015Exhibit--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STEAM 2015 Exhibit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1438416/1438416_10320297_1545084213624_STEAM2015Exhibit--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STEAM 2015 Exhibit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Annual exhibit of UCFSTEAM (Science, Technology, Engineering, Art, and Mathematics) art works visited by 100s of Central Floridians</div> <div class="imageCredit">Debra Reinhart</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Debra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Reinhart</div> <div class="imageTitle">STEAM 2015 Exhibit</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1438416/1438416_10320297_1545084499665_Artworkinspiredbysolidwastepresentation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1438416/1438416_10320297_1545084499665_Artworkinspiredbysolidwastepresentation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Art Work Inspired by Solid Waste Presentation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1438416/1438416_10320297_1545084499665_Artworkinspiredbysolidwastepresentation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Art Work Inspired by Solid Waste Presentation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This art work was created by a UCF student as part of the UCFSTEAM project following a presentation by PI Reinhart and student Stephanie Bolyard</div> <div class="imageCredit">Debra Reinhart</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Debra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Reinhart</div> <div class="imageTitle">Art Work Inspired by Solid Waste Presentation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research examined the chemical nature of leachate organic matter (LOM) to better understand the humification of landfilled waste and the fate of discharged LOM to the environment after in situ landfill treatment, co-treatment at a wastewater treatment facility, or on-site biological treatment. Specific research questions addressed included the following: (1) which waste components contribute to recalcitrant LOM; (2) can we use advanced characterization tools to better understand the potential for LOM biodegradation, photolysis, or contaminant transport; (3) what are the energy and water footprints of wasted food, with particular attention to the uncharted and highly coupled water and energy impacts of food waste management, and (4) what is the fate of recalcitrant LOM in aquatic environments (e.g., wetlands and surface waters), with a focus on photolysis? This research was accomplished by well characterizing LOM, conducting microcosms examining the evolution of LOM from waste components, and evaluating LOM photolysis of leachate samples irradiated by natural sunlight. Major findings include: (1) rapid spectroscopic analysis can be used to understand the humification of LOM generated by landfilling of organics better than conventional analytics measurements such as BOD, COD, and TOC, (2) Lom generated during degradation of various waste components (e.g., paper, cotton, wood waste, and food waste) can be differentiated by their fluorescence, uv-absorption, methane generation potential, and molecular size, (3) conceptual mapping of energy and water requirements related to various food waste management alternatives allows gaps in information related to the post-disposal phase of food production to be identified; reducing food waste can save energy, not only in the food production phase, but in the post-disposal phase, and (4) sunlight-driven processes are possible for the treatment of LOM through the degradation of high molecular weight recalcitrant material into lower molecular weight material.  This research addressed the management of a particularly challenging constituent of leachate from landfills, leachate organic matter (LOM), with the goal of reducing the long-term risks and costs associated with landfill operation. Through this research, for the first time, information was provided that may lead to the control of LOM that passes through biological treatment systems. Further, by providing information regarding the potential for natural systems to assimilate low level contributions of non-biodegradable LOM from closed landfills, society may be relieved from long-term financial burdens of landfill post-closure care (PCC). A better understanding of LOM fate and behavior can provide regulators with the information needed to confidently approve reducing or terminating landfill PCC. The clear societal benefits associated with the research include reduced cost and risk of landfills, a greater understanding of leachate discharges to the environment, and more sustainable solid waste management. The broader impacts of this proposed research also include the advancement of understanding of chemistry and photochemistry of organic matter. The research was a multidisciplinary project that involved a diverse group of female researchers, bridging environmental engineering and physical science fields and impacting multiple areas of the scientific community. The doctoral researcher assigned to this project is a female minority now a practicing engineer. All Principal Investigators were female, including two engineers and one chemist.  Outreach to art and design students through UCFSTEAM (Science, Technology, Engineering, Art, and Mathematics) activities also provided broader impacts (see Figures). PIs have published one paper, submitted two manuscripts to peer-reviewed publications, and presented findings at seven international conferences.          Last Modified: 12/18/2018       Submitted by: Debra R Reinhart]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
