<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Enhanced Flow and Shear of Irregular Grains and Powders</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>185024.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>185024</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wolbrich@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924842</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET 1438077/1435861&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports experimental and computational studies of the flow of granular materials composed of mixtures of particles.  The project will investigate the surprising observation that adding a small number of needle-like particles in a granular material composed of spherical particles significantly increases the ability of the material to flow.  For very small particles, the investigators hypothesize that the needles and spheres stick together in a way that results in an effective particle shape and size that enables the material to flow more easily. For larger particles less likely to adhere, other lubrication mechanisms are suspected. A series of experiments will be conducted to show how the particle size and the mixture ratio affects flow characteristics.  The experiments will be complemented by numerical simulations that can predict the arrangements of particles and correlate particle arrangements with flow behavior in well-defined model flows.  The project will provide an environment for graduate and undergraduate students to participate in the research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project studies the flow and shear of mixtures of particles consisting of spherical and irregularly-shaped particles.  Experiments will be conducted with canonical geometries, such as hoppers, cylindrical column collapse, and annular-Couette shear, to study the flow behavior as functions of particles size and mixture ratio.  The experiments will tie together several quantities currently used to quantify flow, including the static and dynamic angles of repose, dynamic deflection modulus and flowability index.  Computer simulations will study shear in dense systems of rods and mixtures of rods and spheres to reveal the fundamental mechanisms for enhanced flow whether it is changes in the effective morphology or segregation-induced lubrication.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1438077</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Franklin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott V Franklin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>svfsps@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854752536</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Bachmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Bachmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bachmann@cis.rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854757238</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667257</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rochester Institute of Tech]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>149E</Code>
<Text>Granular systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~185024</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project looked at how granular particles of irregular shapes packed and flows. The motivation stemmed from processing issues involving needle-shaped pharmaceutical powders such as acetaminophen and Theophylline (used to treat asthma) and erosion properties of irregular sand and silt. Experiments systematically measured the ability of mixtures to flow through hoppers, funnels and other apertures and found an optimum mixture ratio that flowed most readily. A new apparatus --- a field-ready goniometer --- was designed, developed and tested that allows us to measure the reflective properties of soils, sands and silts in-situ. This now allows us to connect mechanical properties such as density, fluidity and flowability with reflection, raising the possibility of eventually a purely remote measurement (e.g. from a drone) of beach solidity.</p> <p>Two different computer simulations were developed. The first looked at two-dimensional flow of mixtures of discs, in particular focusing on how the pile rigidity changed under pure shear as the pile height decreased. It had been observed elsewhere that shorter piles were more resistant to flow, a result confirmed in our simulations and matched experiments. Experiments and simulations controlled pressure and tracked all particle motion as the system was sheared from the top. Particle motion decayed exponentially with depth, as expected, and the decay length increased with increasing confining pressure. The slope of this dependence is a new quantity that can be used to characterize pile rigidity.</p> <p>An unexpected outcome of this project was a surprising connection with biological systems. U-shaped granular particles entangle and form solid-like masses that bear a striking resemblance to "rafts" formed by fire ants. Our simulations were adapted to reproduce interesting behavior observed in ant rafts, explaining why larger rafts are are not proportionately stronger. Another collaboration investigated the mechanics of how elephants pick up particulate food. This could have implications for the development of flexible robotic appendages capable of manipulating a wide range of objects.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;V&nbsp;Franklin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project looked at how granular particles of irregular shapes packed and flows. The motivation stemmed from processing issues involving needle-shaped pharmaceutical powders such as acetaminophen and Theophylline (used to treat asthma) and erosion properties of irregular sand and silt. Experiments systematically measured the ability of mixtures to flow through hoppers, funnels and other apertures and found an optimum mixture ratio that flowed most readily. A new apparatus --- a field-ready goniometer --- was designed, developed and tested that allows us to measure the reflective properties of soils, sands and silts in-situ. This now allows us to connect mechanical properties such as density, fluidity and flowability with reflection, raising the possibility of eventually a purely remote measurement (e.g. from a drone) of beach solidity.  Two different computer simulations were developed. The first looked at two-dimensional flow of mixtures of discs, in particular focusing on how the pile rigidity changed under pure shear as the pile height decreased. It had been observed elsewhere that shorter piles were more resistant to flow, a result confirmed in our simulations and matched experiments. Experiments and simulations controlled pressure and tracked all particle motion as the system was sheared from the top. Particle motion decayed exponentially with depth, as expected, and the decay length increased with increasing confining pressure. The slope of this dependence is a new quantity that can be used to characterize pile rigidity.  An unexpected outcome of this project was a surprising connection with biological systems. U-shaped granular particles entangle and form solid-like masses that bear a striking resemblance to "rafts" formed by fire ants. Our simulations were adapted to reproduce interesting behavior observed in ant rafts, explaining why larger rafts are are not proportionately stronger. Another collaboration investigated the mechanics of how elephants pick up particulate food. This could have implications for the development of flexible robotic appendages capable of manipulating a wide range of objects.       Last Modified: 11/29/2018       Submitted by: Scott V Franklin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
