<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Role of Attractions in Modifying the Confined Flow of Colloids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299479.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299479</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wolbrich@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924842</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET 1438204&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When a concentrated suspension of particles such as rigid spheres flows through a narrow channel, there is a tendency for the particles to migrate away from the walls and toward the center of the channel.  This phenomenon is called shear-induced migration.  It affects the arrangement of the particles flowing through the channel and the structures that the particles form as a result of the flow.  Flows of concentrated suspensions in narrow channels occur in several novel technological applications, including semi-solid flow batteries and concentrated nanoparticle inks for 3D printing.  This project will investigate the effects of attractive forces between the particles.  Preliminary data show that interparticle attractions can suppress shear-induced migration.  A series of experiments will be conducted to determine whether attractive forces between particles give rise to transient clusters or aggregates of particles that reduce migration, which could provide a way to better tailor particulate materials for specific applications of interest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Experiments will quantify effects of interparticle attraction on shear-induced migration and will correlate suspension microstructure with the extent of shear-induced migration.  The interparticle attraction will be achieved by adding small amounts of polymer to suspensions of hard spheres to create a depletion force between particles.  The effects of attraction range and strength, colloid volume fraction, and flow rate on shear-induced migration and the structure of the resulting suspension will be measured.  Deviations from phenomenological models for shear-induced migration that involve only hard sphere interactions will be determined.  Suspension microstructure will be correlated with the extent of shear-induced migration by using 3-D confocal imaging and tracking to measure particle distribution functions, cluster sizes, and velocity fluctuations during flow.  Effects of boundary conditions at channel walls will also be investigated by chemically modifying the walls to change their surface energy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1438204</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacinta</FirstName>
<LastName>Conrad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacinta Conrad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jcconrad@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137433829</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000554237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>056E</Code>
<Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299479</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Overview: This objective of this proposal was to determine the role of attractive interparticle interactions on the confined flow of colloid/polymer mixtures. Colloids are particles of a small enough size (typically between 50 nm and 5 microns) such that thermal fluctuations can cause the particles to move and vibrate when dispersed in solutions. They are widely used in industrial products (such as inks, paints, coatings, and personal care products) and are increasingly employed in feedstocks for 3-d printing and other rapid prototyping processes to impart novel functionality (optical, electrical, mechanical properties). In these formulations colloidal particles are commonly mixed with complex fluids (containing polymers, surfactants, and/or other macromolecules) that, in turn, can modify the interactions between the colloidal particles. Attractive interactions between colloids can led to the formation of clusters of particles or space-spanning networks. Obtaining desired properties in an industrial product or rapid-prototyping feedstock requires controlling the dispersion of colloidal particles in these complex mixtures during processing steps, which typically involve flow. Thus this project&rsquo;s original goal was to understand how the strength and range of attractions between micron-size colloidal particles, imparted by non-adsorbing polymers, affected the distribution of particles during confined flow. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: The outcomes from our project were focused on two main areas. First, we explored the development of colloid/polymer model systems for advanced measurements of their flow properties. (1) We showed that the standard colloid-polymer model system for rheology and microscopic imaging would not allow measurements of normal stress, required for testing the models for confined flow that underpin this project. (2) In an unsuccessful attempt towards a new model system, we showed that adding very small polymers to this system (to increase the viscosity and hence aid the normal stress measurements) led to changes in the phase behavior that arose from partitioning of polymers of different size near the particle surface. (3) We then engineered a new particle system that could be refractive-index- and density-matched to a high-viscosity mixture of glycerol and water, and showed that polyacrylamide could be used as a non-adsorbing depletant to control the interparticle attractions. This system enabled confocal microscopy measurements as well as the normal stress rheological measurements. (4) Finally, we showed that we could induce a different type of attractions, physical bridging, by changing the added polymer to poly(acrylic acid). The strength of the attractions could be tuned through solution pH, enabling controlled imaging and rheological measurements of a very different class of colloidal gels.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Second, we explored the consequences of polymer addition on particle transport in a variety of contexts relevant for applications (industrial processing, enhanced oil recovery). (1) We showed that polymers added to nanoparticle suspensions flowed through porous media affected the dispersion of the particles only when the medium was geometrically ordered. (2) We showed that polymers added to nanoparticle suspensions could induce transition attractions between the nanoparticles and the surface of a porous medium. Both these results affect the efficacy of nanoparticle-based strategies for enhanced oil recovery. (3) We showed that polymers added to nanoparticle suspensions could generate energy barriers that hinded the nanoparticle diffusion. (4) Finally, we explored the dynamics of polymers grafted to nanoparticle surfaces, and reviewed polymer-brush-grafting for mimicking of biological structures.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts: The development of our new model system for rheology and microscopic imaging will enable a wide variety of fundamental studies linking microstructure to flow properties, a key goal of soft materials science. Insights obtained from the fundamental studies of the flow of nanoparticles through polymer solutions have significant implications for nanocomposite processing and for enhanced oil recovery, among other applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This proposal supported the training of four PhD students, three undergraduate researchers, and one high school student in experimental and analytical methods in colloidal synthesis, suspension formulation, microscopy, rheology, and imaging analysis. The PI and her students participated in three outreach events for K-12 students hosted through the University of Houston (STEP Forward, aimed at rising 12<sup>th</sup> grade students; GRADE Camp, for women in grades 8 &ndash; 12 interested in engineering; and Mars Rover, at which K &ndash; 6 grade students construct a model of a rover for planetary exploration) and two outreach events for the general public (Houston Energy Day, a public science festival; and the Society of Rheology (SoR) Outreach event, held annually at local science museums in conjunction with the SoR Annual Meeting). The PI and her students presented these results at seminars at local companies, to industrial researchers through two local annual symposia (SmartFlow and Oil and Gas Chemistry), and with academic scientists at universities across the country through invited and contributed presentations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Jacinta&nbsp;Conrad</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview: This objective of this proposal was to determine the role of attractive interparticle interactions on the confined flow of colloid/polymer mixtures. Colloids are particles of a small enough size (typically between 50 nm and 5 microns) such that thermal fluctuations can cause the particles to move and vibrate when dispersed in solutions. They are widely used in industrial products (such as inks, paints, coatings, and personal care products) and are increasingly employed in feedstocks for 3-d printing and other rapid prototyping processes to impart novel functionality (optical, electrical, mechanical properties). In these formulations colloidal particles are commonly mixed with complex fluids (containing polymers, surfactants, and/or other macromolecules) that, in turn, can modify the interactions between the colloidal particles. Attractive interactions between colloids can led to the formation of clusters of particles or space-spanning networks. Obtaining desired properties in an industrial product or rapid-prototyping feedstock requires controlling the dispersion of colloidal particles in these complex mixtures during processing steps, which typically involve flow. Thus this project?s original goal was to understand how the strength and range of attractions between micron-size colloidal particles, imparted by non-adsorbing polymers, affected the distribution of particles during confined flow.       Intellectual Merit: The outcomes from our project were focused on two main areas. First, we explored the development of colloid/polymer model systems for advanced measurements of their flow properties. (1) We showed that the standard colloid-polymer model system for rheology and microscopic imaging would not allow measurements of normal stress, required for testing the models for confined flow that underpin this project. (2) In an unsuccessful attempt towards a new model system, we showed that adding very small polymers to this system (to increase the viscosity and hence aid the normal stress measurements) led to changes in the phase behavior that arose from partitioning of polymers of different size near the particle surface. (3) We then engineered a new particle system that could be refractive-index- and density-matched to a high-viscosity mixture of glycerol and water, and showed that polyacrylamide could be used as a non-adsorbing depletant to control the interparticle attractions. This system enabled confocal microscopy measurements as well as the normal stress rheological measurements. (4) Finally, we showed that we could induce a different type of attractions, physical bridging, by changing the added polymer to poly(acrylic acid). The strength of the attractions could be tuned through solution pH, enabling controlled imaging and rheological measurements of a very different class of colloidal gels.     Second, we explored the consequences of polymer addition on particle transport in a variety of contexts relevant for applications (industrial processing, enhanced oil recovery). (1) We showed that polymers added to nanoparticle suspensions flowed through porous media affected the dispersion of the particles only when the medium was geometrically ordered. (2) We showed that polymers added to nanoparticle suspensions could induce transition attractions between the nanoparticles and the surface of a porous medium. Both these results affect the efficacy of nanoparticle-based strategies for enhanced oil recovery. (3) We showed that polymers added to nanoparticle suspensions could generate energy barriers that hinded the nanoparticle diffusion. (4) Finally, we explored the dynamics of polymers grafted to nanoparticle surfaces, and reviewed polymer-brush-grafting for mimicking of biological structures.     Broader Impacts: The development of our new model system for rheology and microscopic imaging will enable a wide variety of fundamental studies linking microstructure to flow properties, a key goal of soft materials science. Insights obtained from the fundamental studies of the flow of nanoparticles through polymer solutions have significant implications for nanocomposite processing and for enhanced oil recovery, among other applications.     This proposal supported the training of four PhD students, three undergraduate researchers, and one high school student in experimental and analytical methods in colloidal synthesis, suspension formulation, microscopy, rheology, and imaging analysis. The PI and her students participated in three outreach events for K-12 students hosted through the University of Houston (STEP Forward, aimed at rising 12th grade students; GRADE Camp, for women in grades 8 &ndash; 12 interested in engineering; and Mars Rover, at which K &ndash; 6 grade students construct a model of a rover for planetary exploration) and two outreach events for the general public (Houston Energy Day, a public science festival; and the Society of Rheology (SoR) Outreach event, held annually at local science museums in conjunction with the SoR Annual Meeting). The PI and her students presented these results at seminars at local companies, to industrial researchers through two local annual symposia (SmartFlow and Oil and Gas Chemistry), and with academic scientists at universities across the country through invited and contributed presentations.       Last Modified: 08/31/2019       Submitted by: Jacinta Conrad]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
