<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Time-scale analysis for the synthesis of thin-film deposition reaction kinetics models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandi Schottel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschotte@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924798</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1438375&lt;br/&gt;PI: Raymond Adomaitis&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Maryland College Park&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Some electronic materials, such as photovoltaic materials for solar cells, are manufactured in specialized chemical reactors in which gas-phase reactant molecules deposit on a surface to form a thin film of the product material.  The routes that molecules take from the gas phase to the thin film involve a complex set of chemical reactions that must be well understood in order to produce materials with the desired properties.  To describe mathematically the overall process of film growth, a system of equations can be derived to track the various chemical species inside the reactor and on the surface of the growing film.  This project involves developing new methods for analyzing the system of equations, and comparing the results of the analysis with experimental data for deposition processes such as atomic layer deposition (ALD) and chemical vapor deposition (CVD).  The results of the project will provide scientists and engineers with a new tool for predicting the performance of ALD and CVD reactors.  The project will provide a training ground for graduate students in an important area of reaction engineering and will provide research opportunities for interested undergraduate students as well.  Software that is developed during the project will be made available to the research and industrial communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate the mathematical structure of differential-algebraic (DAE) systems of equations describing surface reaction species during ALD and CVED thin film deposition processes. A reaction network factorization procedure will be developed that partitions surface reaction and deposition species dynamic balances into sets of relatively slow (deposition), fast (equilibrium), and instantaneous (conserved) modes.  The project will determine conditions under which the factorization works, the importance of fixed points of the equations, and reaction fluxes of chemical species.  Example deposition processes of varying complexity will be analyzed, including some with spatially distributed deposition.  Results that correlate rates of film growth with reactor conditions will be compared with experimental data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1438375</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
<LastName>Adomaitis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raymond A Adomaitis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adomaiti@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014052969</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000313045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/19/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chen Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>czhang71@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014058566</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000789355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/19/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>047E</Code>
<Text>REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>049E</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL PROCESS CONTROL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Atomic Layer Deposition (ALD) and Chemical Vapor Deposition (CVD) are gas-phase thin-film manufacturing processes that make possible atomic-level control of film properties, with applications in microelectronic devices, solar cells, flat-panel displays, and spacecraft optical and structural components. Understanding the deposition reaction mechanisms and rates through mathematical modeling and computer simulation is critical to the design and optimization of the chemical reactor systems used to deposit thin films by ALD and CVD. Despite the utility of these deposition process simulators, tools for systematically identifying the correct set of modeling equations that undergird the simulators were lacking prior to this work.</p> <p>Based on the concept of chemical reaction factorization, we have developed those tools that make possible the systematic enumeration of the required modeling equations, and further, allow for the reduction of the original set of modeling equations into the correct sets of differing timescales and conserved quantities. Our methods allow us to take a deposition reaction network (RN) in the form of a graph (please see attached image for an example), and identify graph features corresponding to the different time scales and conserved quantities, such as the path indicating oxygen conservation in the attached figure. The Intellectual Merit of our work is that we now have the ability to rigorously determine the minimal model dimension, what reaction rates can theoretically be measured, and whether the proposed RN is properly formed, all before a single experiment is run to check the model validity.</p> <p>Through collaboration with NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center, we have demonstrated the utility of our methods by developing a range of spacecraft-relevant ALD films, including a static-electricity dissipating ALD film currently being tested on the International Space Station. In terms of Broader Impacts, we have actively made use of our reaction modeling techniques for a range of reaction systems in capstone senior Chemical Engineering process design classes. Elements of our computational tools have even made their way into simulations used as part of Team Maryland's entry in the 2017 US Solar Decathlon and our partnering with Team DarnaSol in the 2019 Solar Decathlon Africa.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Chen&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1438375/1438375_10310423_1604326128399_Figure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1438375/1438375_10310423_1604326128399_Figure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Species-reaction graph"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1438375/1438375_10310423_1604326128399_Figure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Species-reaction graph"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A species-reaction graph of an archetype metal oxide atomic layer deposition reaction network with the oxygen conservation reaction path highlighted.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Raymond A. Adomaitis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chen&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Species-reaction graph</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Atomic Layer Deposition (ALD) and Chemical Vapor Deposition (CVD) are gas-phase thin-film manufacturing processes that make possible atomic-level control of film properties, with applications in microelectronic devices, solar cells, flat-panel displays, and spacecraft optical and structural components. Understanding the deposition reaction mechanisms and rates through mathematical modeling and computer simulation is critical to the design and optimization of the chemical reactor systems used to deposit thin films by ALD and CVD. Despite the utility of these deposition process simulators, tools for systematically identifying the correct set of modeling equations that undergird the simulators were lacking prior to this work.  Based on the concept of chemical reaction factorization, we have developed those tools that make possible the systematic enumeration of the required modeling equations, and further, allow for the reduction of the original set of modeling equations into the correct sets of differing timescales and conserved quantities. Our methods allow us to take a deposition reaction network (RN) in the form of a graph (please see attached image for an example), and identify graph features corresponding to the different time scales and conserved quantities, such as the path indicating oxygen conservation in the attached figure. The Intellectual Merit of our work is that we now have the ability to rigorously determine the minimal model dimension, what reaction rates can theoretically be measured, and whether the proposed RN is properly formed, all before a single experiment is run to check the model validity.  Through collaboration with NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center, we have demonstrated the utility of our methods by developing a range of spacecraft-relevant ALD films, including a static-electricity dissipating ALD film currently being tested on the International Space Station. In terms of Broader Impacts, we have actively made use of our reaction modeling techniques for a range of reaction systems in capstone senior Chemical Engineering process design classes. Elements of our computational tools have even made their way into simulations used as part of Team Maryland's entry in the 2017 US Solar Decathlon and our partnering with Team DarnaSol in the 2019 Solar Decathlon Africa.          Last Modified: 11/02/2020       Submitted by: Chen Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
