<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Trace Element Cycling in Dan River Sediments following Coal Fly Ash Release</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49909.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49909</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wjcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1439743&lt;br/&gt;Heyes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On February 2, 2014, the third-largest coal ash spill in the Nation occurred at Eden, North Carolina where a drainage pipe under a 27-acre Duke Energy Dan River Steam Plant waste pond collapsed, discharging coal ash and millions of gallons of contaminated water into the Dan River. The Dan River originates in Virginia and flows into North Carolina and then flows north back into Virginia crossing the state lines eight times.  It eventually flows into the Roanoke River, and into Lake Kerr then Lake Gaston and eventually into the Albemarle Sound, NC.  The waters serve as a highly used recreation system and as a source of drinking water for cities from Danville, VA to as far away as Virginia Beach. The toxic constituents of coal ash include various contaminants from metals such as arsenic (As), lead (Pb), mercury (Hg) to selenium (Se) along with a suite of organic compounds. While the element concentrations in impoundment water can exceed drinking water criteria and aquatic life water quality criteria, less is known about the fate of trace elements bound to ash in the new biogeochemical environment of the Dan River. Dissolution and changes in speciation can increase metal toxicity thus threaten wild life and water usability for years to come. To answer some of these questions a multidisciplinary approach is necessary. This study will provide information to policy makers on the extent to which coal fly ash releases present a hazard to humans and wildlife. Specifically it will address the extent to which trace elements continue to be released from ash enriched sediments and if the depositional environment influences such release. This research will help determine if sediment removal is warranted and to prioritize any removal efforts based on the environment of deposition and proximity to targets of concern such as drinking water intakes and sensitive areas for the rivers fishery and recreational use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposed research seeks to assess the impact of ash on sediment biogeochemistry as it pertains to the bioavailability and toxicity of ash born trace elements. Particular emphasis is placed on the sediment redox condition as this impacts metal speciation and mobility in sediments. It is understood that development of anoxic conditions in sediments promotes the release of trace elements through changes in speciation. It is hypothesized this will occur in the case of coal fly ash. The research will focus on the release of trace elements As, Se, Hg and MeHg to porewater as indicators of trace element mobility, transformation and bioavailability. It has also been proposed that trace element mobility is enhanced through a direct interaction with sulfur or indirectly through sulfurized organic matter. The research will investigate the degree of sulfurization of DOM in sediment porewater to assess if this is a potential mechanism for trace element mobilization and transport.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1439743</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Heyes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Heyes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>heyes@umces.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4103267439</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000235507</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>216130775</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4102212014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 775</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>021463831</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND CENTER FOR ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Chesapeake Biological Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>Solomons</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>206880038</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[146 William St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>015E</Code>
<Text>Pollutant fate and transport</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>016E</Code>
<Text>POLLUTION AVOIDANCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~49909</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research was conducted as a &ldquo;Rapid Response&rdquo; to a particular event in order to gain basic scientific knowledge about our environment when it is placed under stress, and to gather knowledge that we might use in response to such future events. In this case, the event was the release of fly ash residue into the Dan River, NC. Fly ash is the residue left after coal combustion. It is often stored on the power plant site in wet ponds to stop it from blowing away. This fine material is enriched in metals such as mercury and arsenic. Power plants are located adjacent to water bodies because of the need for water in power generation. &nbsp;However due to their proximity to water, the fate of fly ash ponds has been a concern. The unfortunate release of fly ash into the Dan River presented an opportunity for scientists to investigate the fate of this material in a river ecosystem.</p> <p>Sediment and water were collected from the Dan River in the weeks and months following the spill. Experiments were performed in order to further investigate some of the things we observed during the field collections. Mercury was of particular interest because it is a neurotoxin. Mercury contamination restricts the human consumption of fish from many waterways and mercury exposure is a concern for predatory birds and mammals.&nbsp; For mercury to enter the food web and be bioaccumulated to levels of concern, it must first be transformed into methylmercury. Mercury is inadvertently methylated by some types of bacteria. The type of bacteria that methylate mercury occupy areas where there is no oxygen and use iron or sulfur in their metabolism.</p> <p>Like many American rivers, the Dan River has a legacy of pollution. Mercury was already present in sediment and in organisms at concentrations of concern, thus the influx of fly ash may exacerbate an existing problem. However, the release of fly ash may not necessarily increase mercury levels in organisms. Materials, such as activated carbon, can adsorb and trap compounds on their surfaces making them unavailable to organisms. Like activated carbon fly ash has a highly reactive surface capable of trapping as well as releasing metals and organic compounds such as polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs). Fly ash contains other elements such as nitrogen and sulfur that influence mercury cycling.</p> <p>In the Dan River spill, the fly ash was spread out across many miles of river channel in thicknesses from zero to a few centimeters. This fly ash is a fine particle technically described as fine silt. When separated from the sediment, the fly ash was easily identified by its enrichment in mercury compared to other particles of the same size class. The Dan River is dynamic and has a high sediment load. As a result, the fly ash was buried or mixed into river sediment. Where significant fly ash accumulated, concentrations of mercury in the sediment were elevated 3 to 5 times that of background. In places were fly ash was buried, sediment concentrations of methylmercury were slightly elevated compared to sites containing no ash. However, if such an increase would have any impact on ecosystems production of methylmercury is difficult to estimate from our very small sample size. In hopes of addressing this question, further samples are being obtained to expand our sample size.</p> <p>To directly assess if mercury methylation in sediment could be increased by inputs of fly ash, we performed controlled experiments. In the laboratory we added fly ash to sediment taken from an uncontaminated river. The fly ash was mixed into the sediment mimicking the way the fly ash appeared in Dan River sediment. From the results of the short term experiments, methylmercury concentrations in sediment receiving fly ash were slightly elevated; an observation that matches the field observations. What we don&rsquo;t know from our experiment is how the presence of ash will...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research was conducted as a "Rapid Response" to a particular event in order to gain basic scientific knowledge about our environment when it is placed under stress, and to gather knowledge that we might use in response to such future events. In this case, the event was the release of fly ash residue into the Dan River, NC. Fly ash is the residue left after coal combustion. It is often stored on the power plant site in wet ponds to stop it from blowing away. This fine material is enriched in metals such as mercury and arsenic. Power plants are located adjacent to water bodies because of the need for water in power generation.  However due to their proximity to water, the fate of fly ash ponds has been a concern. The unfortunate release of fly ash into the Dan River presented an opportunity for scientists to investigate the fate of this material in a river ecosystem.  Sediment and water were collected from the Dan River in the weeks and months following the spill. Experiments were performed in order to further investigate some of the things we observed during the field collections. Mercury was of particular interest because it is a neurotoxin. Mercury contamination restricts the human consumption of fish from many waterways and mercury exposure is a concern for predatory birds and mammals.  For mercury to enter the food web and be bioaccumulated to levels of concern, it must first be transformed into methylmercury. Mercury is inadvertently methylated by some types of bacteria. The type of bacteria that methylate mercury occupy areas where there is no oxygen and use iron or sulfur in their metabolism.  Like many American rivers, the Dan River has a legacy of pollution. Mercury was already present in sediment and in organisms at concentrations of concern, thus the influx of fly ash may exacerbate an existing problem. However, the release of fly ash may not necessarily increase mercury levels in organisms. Materials, such as activated carbon, can adsorb and trap compounds on their surfaces making them unavailable to organisms. Like activated carbon fly ash has a highly reactive surface capable of trapping as well as releasing metals and organic compounds such as polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs). Fly ash contains other elements such as nitrogen and sulfur that influence mercury cycling.  In the Dan River spill, the fly ash was spread out across many miles of river channel in thicknesses from zero to a few centimeters. This fly ash is a fine particle technically described as fine silt. When separated from the sediment, the fly ash was easily identified by its enrichment in mercury compared to other particles of the same size class. The Dan River is dynamic and has a high sediment load. As a result, the fly ash was buried or mixed into river sediment. Where significant fly ash accumulated, concentrations of mercury in the sediment were elevated 3 to 5 times that of background. In places were fly ash was buried, sediment concentrations of methylmercury were slightly elevated compared to sites containing no ash. However, if such an increase would have any impact on ecosystems production of methylmercury is difficult to estimate from our very small sample size. In hopes of addressing this question, further samples are being obtained to expand our sample size.  To directly assess if mercury methylation in sediment could be increased by inputs of fly ash, we performed controlled experiments. In the laboratory we added fly ash to sediment taken from an uncontaminated river. The fly ash was mixed into the sediment mimicking the way the fly ash appeared in Dan River sediment. From the results of the short term experiments, methylmercury concentrations in sediment receiving fly ash were slightly elevated; an observation that matches the field observations. What we donÆt know from our experiment is how the presence of ash will influence mercury cycling over the longer term.    Fly ash composition varies and its makeup depends on the paren...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
