<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>INCISE (Integrated Certificate in STEM Education)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299974.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299974</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jhaddock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922671</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>National calls for improved education in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) point to the challenges of an ever-changing, increasingly global society. In line with this, there is an identified need for integration of multiple STEM concepts across disciplines to solve complex, global problems. Based on this situation and with funding from the National Science Foundation's Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program, this Noyce Capacity Building project will address the national shortage of high quality STEM teachers, and especially teachers who can teach across disciplines. Investigators at the University of North Carolina Wilmington (UNCW) will build capacity to contribute to STEM teacher workforce development by creating and implementing two teacher preparation programs at UNCW that will provide participants with an ability to teach integration of important concepts across STEM disciplines. The overall programs will integrate engineering and technology, interdisciplinary STEM material, critical thinking, problem solving, and inquiry in science to enhance teacher training, which, in turn, will help future teachers prepare students to enter the workforce as problem solvers, innovators, inventors, and logical thinkers, who will be self-reliant and technologically literate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These discipline integrated programs to be developed will consist of: (a) an undergraduate STEM teaching certification program for students majoring in a STEM discipline and (b) a graduate STEM teaching certification program for individuals who already hold a STEM degree. The intentional integration of the STEM disciplines in the curriculum, new teacher preparation practices, and other components of the UNCW certificate programs will be designed to serve as a catalyst to: (i) increase the number of STEM majors; (ii) encourage and train STEM majors to become effective K-12 STEM teachers; (iii) provide opportunities for current K-12 educators to improve overall teaching practices; (iv) provide a pathway for mid-career STEM professionals to become effective K-12 teachers, and (v) provide the participant preservice teachers, current teachers, and mid-Career professionals with the background and ability to teach K-12 students the integration of important concepts across STEM disciplines. Evaluation and collaborative research will be conducted to address the effectiveness of the curriculum and the overall design, implementation, and results of the INCISE program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1439632</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lugo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriel G Lugo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lugo@uncwil.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9109623246</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000450333</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sridhar</FirstName>
<LastName>Narayan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sridhar Narayan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>narayans@uncw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9109623695</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000256628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gene</FirstName>
<LastName>Tagliarini</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gene A Tagliarini</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tagliarinig@uncw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9109627572</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000264148</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mahnaz</FirstName>
<LastName>Moallem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mahnaz Moallem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmoallem@towson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4107045822</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000363071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Reamer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy Reamer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>reamera@uncw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9109623167</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000644116</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Wilmington</Name>
<CityName>Wilmington</CityName>
<ZipCode>284033201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9109623167</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 South College Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>040036584</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT WILMINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina Wilmington]]></Name>
<CityName>Wilmington</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>284033201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 South College Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299974</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The following two overarching goals of the INCISE project have been achieved:</p> <ol> <li>Designed      and developed an <span style="text-decoration: underline;">undergraduate</span> integrated STEM <em>teaching      licensure program</em> for students majoring in a STEM discipline to be      implemented in fall 2017; </li> <li>Designed      and developed a <span style="text-decoration: underline;">graduate</span> STEM <em>teaching certification program</em> for individuals who hold a STEM degree to be implemented in fall 2017.</li> </ol> <p>The INCISE team (consisting of eight STEM scientists and six STEM educators) collaborated to create STEM teacher preparation programs that emphasize the concept of interconnectedness among STEM disciplines.<strong> The goal of the programs was to</strong> <strong>integrate content</strong> across two or more STEM&nbsp;disciplines and <strong>foster scientific thinking with approaches such as modeling, experimentation, simulation, optimization, computation, and invention. This goal was also achieved by:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Integrating      STEM content, concepts, and skills across multiple discipline-specific      courses.</li> <li>Underscoring      scientific thinking and approaches in all integrated STEM courses.</li> <li>Emphasizing      problem-based, project-based or inquiry-based methods to teaching and      learning STEM courses.</li> <li>Making      the connections among STEM disciplines explicit to learners.</li> <li>Integrating      STEM content with the pedagogy of teaching.</li> <li>Integrating      the engineering design process as a problem-solving approach. </li> </ul> <p>Furthermore, the identified integrated STEM (iSTEM) designated courses (biology, chemistry, physics, computer science, mathematics, and environmental studies) offer an integrated approach to teaching and learning Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics. The development team believes the richness of the interconnected model of STEM education comes not from deep knowledge in each area, but from a relatively modest knowledge base in each field, <em>coupled </em>with the capacity to weave that knowledge into a cohesive fabric of STEM.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Mahnaz&nbsp;Moallem</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The following two overarching goals of the INCISE project have been achieved:  Designed      and developed an undergraduate integrated STEM teaching      licensure program for students majoring in a STEM discipline to be      implemented in fall 2017;  Designed      and developed a graduate STEM teaching certification program for individuals who hold a STEM degree to be implemented in fall 2017.   The INCISE team (consisting of eight STEM scientists and six STEM educators) collaborated to create STEM teacher preparation programs that emphasize the concept of interconnectedness among STEM disciplines. The goal of the programs was to integrate content across two or more STEM disciplines and foster scientific thinking with approaches such as modeling, experimentation, simulation, optimization, computation, and invention. This goal was also achieved by:  Integrating      STEM content, concepts, and skills across multiple discipline-specific      courses. Underscoring      scientific thinking and approaches in all integrated STEM courses. Emphasizing      problem-based, project-based or inquiry-based methods to teaching and      learning STEM courses. Making      the connections among STEM disciplines explicit to learners. Integrating      STEM content with the pedagogy of teaching. Integrating      the engineering design process as a problem-solving approach.    Furthermore, the identified integrated STEM (iSTEM) designated courses (biology, chemistry, physics, computer science, mathematics, and environmental studies) offer an integrated approach to teaching and learning Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics. The development team believes the richness of the interconnected model of STEM education comes not from deep knowledge in each area, but from a relatively modest knowledge base in each field, coupled with the capacity to weave that knowledge into a cohesive fabric of STEM.       Last Modified: 09/02/2017       Submitted by: Mahnaz Moallem]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
