<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BCC - Building Community and Capacity for Transformative Data-Intensive Criminal Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499395.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499395</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Crime records are housed in hundreds of counties across the nation, each employing local laws and idiosyncratic information management systems. As a result, it is difficult to analyze detailed crime records across time and place. To address this challenge, the researcher proposes to build a database for integrating 23 million crime records in Houston, NY and Miami. The researcher proposes a workshop strategy to address three distinct aims: 1) Build an interdisciplinary community including statisticians, criminologists, legal scholars, behavioral scientists, neuroscientists, economists, sociologists and programmers, all of whom share an interest in the intersection of crime and their fields. 2) Work with the community to prototype a database of deep criminal records obtained via public access laws. 3) Work with the community to design advanced interface and visualization tools for the data, opening the data to the widest possible audience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project builds capacity for data-intensive research on national criminal records, guided at all stages by the stakeholder research communities. Previously, criminal research has relied on the FBI's Uniform Crime Reports, a tool with two weaknesses: no unique identifiers to identify re-offense rates, and a lack of detail that dilutes the ability to use 21st century tools and analysis techniques. The project breaks the information bottleneck by building a community of quantitative researchers - from a range of disciplines in the social, behavioral, and economic sciences - with a shared interest in next-generation questions at the intersection of crime and their fields. Through multiple workshops, the community establishes database ontologies and prototypes a transformative database of millions of criminal records spanning several decades (obtained via public access laws). The researchers also implement advanced interface and visualization tools to maximize the user audience for the database. This project provides an unprecedented level of detail about offenders, their crimes, and their interactions with the criminal justice system.  By enabling an exploration of the relationships between external factors like legal policies and a decision to commit a crime, this project promises results across and beyond the contributing disciplines. Critically, the prototype database will include anonymized identifiers to enable exploration of desistance from crime, greatly advancing the study of recidivism (reoffenses). Such advances should in turn help efforts to identify high-risk offenders, allowing policy makers to base law enforcement decisions on direct, proven, open-source assessments of human behavior.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1439453</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Eagleman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Eagleman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eagleman@scilaw.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4159932453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000523013</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Baylor College of Medicine</Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>770303411</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137981297</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE BAYLOR PLAZA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MS-310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>051113330</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BAYLOR COLLEGE OF MEDICINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>051113330</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Baylor College of Medicine]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770303411</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8294</Code>
<Text>Data Infrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8819</Code>
<Text>Forensic Science</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~499395</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project consists of a workshop&shy;centric approach to (1) building a community from a range of disciplines around (2) an original, transformative data resource of national law enforcement record. &nbsp;The community has been established via three workshops held at Baylor College of Medicine on Dec. 6, 2014, Feb. 28, 2015, and Feb. 6, 2016. &nbsp;Together, we developed a prototype dataset with public&shy;facing visualization tools (http://www.neulaw.org) and with a powerful export tool (http://export.neulaw.org). &nbsp;The prototype dataset has also been uploaded to ICPSR.</p> <p>The first workshop was attended by 15+ academic researchers from a variety of disciplines. &nbsp;Its objective was to establish a community drawing equally from established and early career researchers. &nbsp;It focused on strategy formulation to outline the sample data resource, consider standards, and address replicability along with other relevant community concerns. The second workshop was attended by 20+ academic researchers, including the 15 from the original meeting. &nbsp;Its objective was to increase the community and to communicate the vision and translate the broad intentions into specific plans for prototyping the data resource. &nbsp;The third workshop was attended by 30+ academic reearchers, including the vast majority of the 20 from the second meeting. &nbsp;Its primary objective was to share lessons learned by the many researchers who were actively using the dataset. &nbsp;Those lessons were incorporated into the prototype. &nbsp;The secondary objectives were to use preliminary findings to implement visualization and export tools. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Undergraduate and recently graduated students assisted with the implementation and communication for each of the workshops. &nbsp;Their exposure to high&shy;level researchers has contributed to the development of their research skills. &nbsp;Each workshop included posters to provide a sense of the applicability of the data to a wide range of questions. &nbsp;These student researchers received extensive mentoring in the development of six different scientific posters. &nbsp;The two postdoctoral researchers and the PI held regular weekly meetings that included career counseling, instruction in professional practices, and technology transfer activities. &nbsp;The prototype database has already yielded a paper under peer review, which involved extensive guidance and training by the PI in the preparation of manuscripts for scientific journals and presentations at conferences.</p> <p>We have developed the NeuLaw Criminal Record Database (NCRD), a rich and growing collection of tens of millions of crime records. The NCRD provides an unprecedented level of detail about individual offenders, their crimes, and their interactions with the criminal justice system? additionally, it translates court records into a common framework for cross&shy;jurisdiction comparison. In particular, the database includes anonymized identifiers to enable large&shy;scale exploration of criminal re&shy;offense (recidivism). The NCRD is growing monthly? as of this writing it contains 18+ million records from 1977 to 2014 from Harris County in Texas, New York City, and MiamiDade County in Florida. &nbsp; &nbsp;We have also developed a rich and vibrant community of researchers interested in the intersection of crime and their respective field. &nbsp;This network has been actively collaborating on a range of research questions that use the CRD.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Eagleman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project consists of a workshop&shy;centric approach to (1) building a community from a range of disciplines around (2) an original, transformative data resource of national law enforcement record.  The community has been established via three workshops held at Baylor College of Medicine on Dec. 6, 2014, Feb. 28, 2015, and Feb. 6, 2016.  Together, we developed a prototype dataset with public&shy;facing visualization tools (http://www.neulaw.org) and with a powerful export tool (http://export.neulaw.org).  The prototype dataset has also been uploaded to ICPSR.  The first workshop was attended by 15+ academic researchers from a variety of disciplines.  Its objective was to establish a community drawing equally from established and early career researchers.  It focused on strategy formulation to outline the sample data resource, consider standards, and address replicability along with other relevant community concerns. The second workshop was attended by 20+ academic researchers, including the 15 from the original meeting.  Its objective was to increase the community and to communicate the vision and translate the broad intentions into specific plans for prototyping the data resource.  The third workshop was attended by 30+ academic reearchers, including the vast majority of the 20 from the second meeting.  Its primary objective was to share lessons learned by the many researchers who were actively using the dataset.  Those lessons were incorporated into the prototype.  The secondary objectives were to use preliminary findings to implement visualization and export tools.     Undergraduate and recently graduated students assisted with the implementation and communication for each of the workshops.  Their exposure to high&shy;level researchers has contributed to the development of their research skills.  Each workshop included posters to provide a sense of the applicability of the data to a wide range of questions.  These student researchers received extensive mentoring in the development of six different scientific posters.  The two postdoctoral researchers and the PI held regular weekly meetings that included career counseling, instruction in professional practices, and technology transfer activities.  The prototype database has already yielded a paper under peer review, which involved extensive guidance and training by the PI in the preparation of manuscripts for scientific journals and presentations at conferences.  We have developed the NeuLaw Criminal Record Database (NCRD), a rich and growing collection of tens of millions of crime records. The NCRD provides an unprecedented level of detail about individual offenders, their crimes, and their interactions with the criminal justice system? additionally, it translates court records into a common framework for cross&shy;jurisdiction comparison. In particular, the database includes anonymized identifiers to enable large&shy;scale exploration of criminal re&shy;offense (recidivism). The NCRD is growing monthly? as of this writing it contains 18+ million records from 1977 to 2014 from Harris County in Texas, New York City, and MiamiDade County in Florida.    We have also developed a rich and vibrant community of researchers interested in the intersection of crime and their respective field.  This network has been actively collaborating on a range of research questions that use the CRD.       Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: David M Eagleman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
