<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The California State University, Northridge Noyce Scholarship Phase II Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>797355.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>797355</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Kim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924458</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The California State University, Northridge (CSUN) Noyce Scholarship Phase II project will build on lessons learned from its Phase I project.  CSUN will work closely with Local Districts of the Los Angeles Unified School District (LAUSD) and other area Districts (Glendale, Pasadena, and Antelope Valley), to place program graduates into middle and secondary school mathematics and science classrooms. The overall goal is to increase the quality and quantity of mathematics and science majors entering and remaining in teaching careers, and to track graduates of the CSUN Phase I project. By increasing the number of highly qualified middle and high school math and science teachers (27 new teachers are targeted), the program will help ease acute teacher shortages in these disciplines in the greater Los Angeles area, and increase the diversity of the teacher workforce by especially encouraging the participation of students from underrepresented minority groups in seeking scholarship support. The Phase II Noyce scholars will also benefit from relationships established by working with underprivileged secondary students in Upward Bound and Project GRAD Los Angeles (PGLA) in summer enrichment programs. The program will have a multiplier effect, as those teachers will influence future generations of students in their classrooms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;New to the program will be support offered to freshmen and sophomore math and science majors to participate in summer field experiences, with a goal of interesting these STEM majors in teaching careers through early clinical/field experiences. Also new is support for teachers during their initial teaching years.  The project aims to provide professional development opportunities and professional learning communities that keep new teachers connected to one another and to experienced group of teacher leaders. By expanding the conduit for new teachers through Noyce-supported pre-service and in-service activities, new math and science teachers will help to build a robust community of teacher/learners.  Specific components of the program include: (1) academic coursework for the California single subject credential in math or science; (2) summer and academic year practicum/clinical (or field) experiences for freshmen, sophomores and participating scholars; (3) monthly meetings and regional/national meetings; and (4) mentoring during the first year of teaching. All aspects of the Phase I project will be enhanced, including outreach, recruitment, research, and evaluation efforts. Specific research questions the PIs intend to tackle include: 1) How does student teaching (clinical) experience (including school and master teacher placement) impact a preservice teacher during the initial teaching years?; 2) Are there requirements for pre-service math majors (in CSUN's Freshman Year/Junior Year/Secondary Teaching Options) that can be modified to better serve the needs of these students over the long-term and why? (e.g., Would additional field experiences benefit them? How? Which aspects are most useful? Why?); 3) How can CCSSM and NGSS be integrated into pre-service mathematics and science content courses?; and 4) Which professional development activities best train pre- and in-service teachers to teach the new standards of mathematical and science practice? Finally, long-term tracking of graduates will be an important component of the program with respect to formative and summative evaluation, determining if teaching commitments are being fulfilled, and assessing the achievement of project objectives.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1439926</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Oberholzer-Vandergon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia Oberholzer-Vandergon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>virginia.vandergon@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186776362</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444467</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kellie</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kellie Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kellie.m.evans@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186772705</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000039870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Foley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian J Foley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian.foley@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186774005</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000442513</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
<LastName>Herr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norman Herr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>norm.herr@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186772505</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University Corporation, Northridge</Name>
<CityName>Northridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>913308309</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8186771403</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>18111 Nordhoff Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>055752331</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055752331</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Northridge]]></Name>
<CityName>Northridge</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>913308303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[18111 Nordhoff St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~797355</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-f317c925-7fff-829f-bd76-1296f5448984">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Project Goals and Objectives&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CSUNoyce Phase II project was an effort to identify, recruit, support, prepare, and inspire excellent STEM undergraduates and credential students to teach in high-need school districts in the Los Angeles area. A team of scientists and educators collaborated to develop a community dedicated to supporting all students' learning. Noyce Scholars were supported through the process of earning single subject teaching credentials. Freshman and sophomores were supported to work in STEM high school summer&nbsp; programs to learn about teaching. Juniors, seniors and credential students were supported as Noyce Scholars and received stipends. Monthly meetings and work with local students through activities such as Pi Day and Earth Day celebrations helped prepare Noyce scholars to be outstanding teachers.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>OBJECTIVE ONE: Provide 40 funding-year scholarships</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CSUNoyce Phase II project funded 51 year-long scholarships since the program launch in 2015 with an average of two semesters of funding each.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>OBJECTIVE TWO: Prepare ~ 27 STEM scholars to teach in high-need schools</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Noyce program supplemented students' classes with monthly Noyce Scholar meetings, professional development workshops, special events, fieldwork experiences, and continued support. One of the key features of the Noyce meetings was that students further along in the process let newer students know what to expect. This socialization is a key way that new teachers develop their identities.&nbsp; Scholar survey feedback referenced the value of practical discussions of teaching methods, ways to engage students, approaches to improving math and science learning, and the opportunity to form bonds with other math and science teachers that they expect will endure.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>OBJECTIVE THREE: Produce ~27 Scholars who are employed in high-need schools</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Of the 34 Scholars who have earned credentials, 31 have been hired by high-needs schools in Los Angeles and surrounding areas.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>OBJECTIVE FOUR: Ensure Scholars fulfill 2 year teaching commitment per year of support.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As of the end of Project Year six, 15 Noyce Scholars had taught for two-years in high-need districts per year of support and most others were making progress toward that goal. Of the 51 scholars funded, 34 had completed credential coursework, 8 were in progress, and 33 were employed full-time teaching math or science.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><br /><br /></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Scholar Profile</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Most students recruited as Scholars from the CSUN student body are themselves graduates from high-need high schools and are traditionally underrepresented in higher education. Preparing teachers for employment in the Los Angeles area who reflect the students they are teaching is expected to positively impact children who might not see themselves in such powerful roles, who are in families where there are lower levels of college attainment, and who suffer from a lack of role models.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>"I want to be a biology teacher because latinx teachers are extremely underrepresented in STEM fields and I want to help break that cycle. Also, I am passionate about helping others and giving back to the community. I want to encourage students from underprivileged communities, like ones that I grew up in, to pursue careers in stem fields."&nbsp;</span><span>- </span><span>Noyce Scholar</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The number of new teachers produced through this project are an important impact, but more importantly these teachers are highly prepared to work with students in high-need schools and make an impact in the lives of students. We are extremely proud of the Noyce alumni and the impact they are having in the community. One alumnus won an award as a top student teacher from the California Association of Science Educators. Another was awarded as a top student in his master?s program and has been invited back to the university as a teacher-in-residence to help mentor new math teachers.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Worth noting is the impact on faculty and students at the university. Information about math and science teaching is now disseminated more broadly throughout the Colleges of Education and Science and Mathematics. This increased profile of teaching careers, particularly in the College of Science and Mathematics, is very important and due to the number of years the program has been supported at CSUN and the positive feedback about student experiences in the project.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Two critical elements of the CSUNoyce Phase II Program were its focus on implementing the new math and science standards, and the introduction of early clinical experiences for freshmen and sophomores, as they explored and committed to teaching. The project led to pilot versions of a Noyce Intern Program, a Teacher-in-Residence Program, and a Lesson Study Program. </span><span>All of these innovations contribute to making a richer community of practice in which we engage new teachers in different ways at different points on their paths to becoming excellent teachers. These results allow us to provide guidance for future efforts to engage new teachers early, develop their skills effectively, and support them along the way.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/20/2021<br>      Modified by: Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172281549_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172281549_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CSUNoyce Social 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172281549_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CSUNoyce Social 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We socialize usually at a local restaurant at the end of each semester.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Virginia Vandergon</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</div> <div class="imageTitle">CSUNoyce Social 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172472403_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(3)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172472403_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(3)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poster Session Annual Noyce conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172472403_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(3)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poster Session Annual Noyce conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CSUNoyce scholars and PI at the annual Noyce meetings in Washington DC in summer 2019</div> <div class="imageCredit">Virginia Vandergon</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poster Session Annual Noyce conference</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172793560_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(4)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172793560_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(4)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CSUNoyce Pi Day"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611172793560_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(4)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CSUNoyce Pi Day"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CSUN Noyce scholars helping at the annual Pi Day event where they ran the photo booth as well as other Pi day activities.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kellie Evans</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</div> <div class="imageTitle">CSUNoyce Pi Day</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173073778_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(5)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173073778_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(5)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CSUN Earth Day and march for science"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173073778_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(5)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CSUN Earth Day and march for science"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">On the steps of the CSUN library where we had our march for science which was part of our annual Earth Day event with local 3-12 graders, Noyce scholars helped run the day.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Virginia Vandergon</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</div> <div class="imageTitle">CSUN Earth Day and march for science</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173255385_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(6)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173255385_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(6)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CSUNoyce scholars at Western Noyce conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173255385_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes(6)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CSUNoyce scholars at Western Noyce conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CSUN Noyce scholars at the Western Noyce conference in Portland OR outside of Powell's bookstore. Last trip before COVID shutdown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brian Foley</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</div> <div class="imageTitle">CSUNoyce scholars at Western Noyce conference</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173518000_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173518000_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CSUNoyce scholars Zoom social"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1439926/1439926_10326513_1611173518000_ImagesusedforNoyceoutcomes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CSUNoyce scholars Zoom social"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Our end of the year social over Zoom after Covid shutdown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kellie Evans</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Virginia&nbsp;Oberholzer-Vandergon</div> <div class="imageTitle">CSUNoyce scholars Zoom social</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Project Goals and Objectives  The CSUNoyce Phase II project was an effort to identify, recruit, support, prepare, and inspire excellent STEM undergraduates and credential students to teach in high-need school districts in the Los Angeles area. A team of scientists and educators collaborated to develop a community dedicated to supporting all students' learning. Noyce Scholars were supported through the process of earning single subject teaching credentials. Freshman and sophomores were supported to work in STEM high school summer  programs to learn about teaching. Juniors, seniors and credential students were supported as Noyce Scholars and received stipends. Monthly meetings and work with local students through activities such as Pi Day and Earth Day celebrations helped prepare Noyce scholars to be outstanding teachers.    OBJECTIVE ONE: Provide 40 funding-year scholarships The CSUNoyce Phase II project funded 51 year-long scholarships since the program launch in 2015 with an average of two semesters of funding each.     OBJECTIVE TWO: Prepare ~ 27 STEM scholars to teach in high-need schools The Noyce program supplemented students' classes with monthly Noyce Scholar meetings, professional development workshops, special events, fieldwork experiences, and continued support. One of the key features of the Noyce meetings was that students further along in the process let newer students know what to expect. This socialization is a key way that new teachers develop their identities.  Scholar survey feedback referenced the value of practical discussions of teaching methods, ways to engage students, approaches to improving math and science learning, and the opportunity to form bonds with other math and science teachers that they expect will endure.     OBJECTIVE THREE: Produce ~27 Scholars who are employed in high-need schools Of the 34 Scholars who have earned credentials, 31 have been hired by high-needs schools in Los Angeles and surrounding areas.   OBJECTIVE FOUR: Ensure Scholars fulfill 2 year teaching commitment per year of support. As of the end of Project Year six, 15 Noyce Scholars had taught for two-years in high-need districts per year of support and most others were making progress toward that goal. Of the 51 scholars funded, 34 had completed credential coursework, 8 were in progress, and 33 were employed full-time teaching math or science.      Scholar Profile Most students recruited as Scholars from the CSUN student body are themselves graduates from high-need high schools and are traditionally underrepresented in higher education. Preparing teachers for employment in the Los Angeles area who reflect the students they are teaching is expected to positively impact children who might not see themselves in such powerful roles, who are in families where there are lower levels of college attainment, and who suffer from a lack of role models.    "I want to be a biology teacher because latinx teachers are extremely underrepresented in STEM fields and I want to help break that cycle. Also, I am passionate about helping others and giving back to the community. I want to encourage students from underprivileged communities, like ones that I grew up in, to pursue careers in stem fields." - Noyce Scholar     Broader Impacts The number of new teachers produced through this project are an important impact, but more importantly these teachers are highly prepared to work with students in high-need schools and make an impact in the lives of students. We are extremely proud of the Noyce alumni and the impact they are having in the community. One alumnus won an award as a top student teacher from the California Association of Science Educators. Another was awarded as a top student in his master?s program and has been invited back to the university as a teacher-in-residence to help mentor new math teachers.    Worth noting is the impact on faculty and students at the university. Information about math and science teaching is now disseminated more broadly throughout the Colleges of Education and Science and Mathematics. This increased profile of teaching careers, particularly in the College of Science and Mathematics, is very important and due to the number of years the program has been supported at CSUN and the positive feedback about student experiences in the project.    Intellectual Merit Two critical elements of the CSUNoyce Phase II Program were its focus on implementing the new math and science standards, and the introduction of early clinical experiences for freshmen and sophomores, as they explored and committed to teaching. The project led to pilot versions of a Noyce Intern Program, a Teacher-in-Residence Program, and a Lesson Study Program. All of these innovations contribute to making a richer community of practice in which we engage new teachers in different ways at different points on their paths to becoming excellent teachers. These results allow us to provide guidance for future efforts to engage new teachers early, develop their skills effectively, and support them along the way.                Last Modified: 01/20/2021       Submitted by: Virginia Oberholzer-Vandergon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
