<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative: SI2-SSE - A Plug-and-Play Software Platform of Robotics-Inspired Algorithms for Modeling Biomolecular Structures and Motions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>67235.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>67235</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajiv Ramnath</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to develop a novel plug-and-play platform of open-source software elements to advance algorithmic research in molecular biology. The focus is on addressing the algorithmic impasse faced by computational chemists and biophysicists in structure-function related problems involving dynamic biomolecules central to our biology. The software platform resulting from this project provides the critical software infrastructure to support transformative research in molecular biology and computer science that benefits society at large by advancing our modeling capabilities and in turn our understanding of the role of biomolecules in critical mechanisms in a living and diseased cell.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project addresses the current impasse on the length and time scales that can be afforded in biomolecular modeling and simulation. It does so by integrating cutting-edge knowledge from two different research communities, computational chemists and biophysicists focused on detailed physics-based simulations, and AI researchers focused on efficient search and optimization algorithms. The software elements integrate sophisticated energetic models and molecular representations with powerful search and optimization algorithms for complex modular systems inspired from robot motion planning. The plug-and-play feature of the software platform supports putting together novel algorithms, such as wrapping Molecular Dynamics or Monte Carlo as local search operators within larger robotics-inspired exploration frameworks, and adding emerging biomolecular representations, models, and search techniques even beyond the timeline of this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1440523</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Roitberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian E Roitberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>roitberg@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523926972</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297486</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326117200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CCF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CCF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8005</Code>
<Text>Scientific Software Elements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~67235</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The University of Florida part of this Collaborative award consisted in helping our two co-PIs (<span>Dr. Amarda Shehu from George Mason U and&nbsp;<span>Dr. Erion Plaku from Catholic University of America)&nbsp;</span></span>in interfacing the suite of programs AMBER with the robotics programs used by the other two groups.</p> <p>Dr Roitberg, the PI of this award, is one of the core developers of AMBER, a program widely used in the biochemical community, with a user base of roughly 5000 users. As a side-effect of this collaborative award (but not funded by it), a more general python interface to AMBER was developed and has been made publicly available through ambermd.org.</p> <p>The annual and final reports by our co-PIs present a series of products and outcomes in terms of publications, talks and posters, describing applications to biological and materials systems</p> <p>The University of Florida work was intended as advisory and as helping interface our programs with the ones the co-PIs develop. The PI has fulfilled its role and was never intended to co-author publications in this area, since our role was mainly in advising and discussing interfaces.</p> <p>The associated awards from the co-PIs are still funded, and there might be a co-authorship opportunity during the next year.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Adrian&nbsp;E&nbsp;Roitberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The University of Florida part of this Collaborative award consisted in helping our two co-PIs (Dr. Amarda Shehu from George Mason U and Dr. Erion Plaku from Catholic University of America) in interfacing the suite of programs AMBER with the robotics programs used by the other two groups.  Dr Roitberg, the PI of this award, is one of the core developers of AMBER, a program widely used in the biochemical community, with a user base of roughly 5000 users. As a side-effect of this collaborative award (but not funded by it), a more general python interface to AMBER was developed and has been made publicly available through ambermd.org.  The annual and final reports by our co-PIs present a series of products and outcomes in terms of publications, talks and posters, describing applications to biological and materials systems  The University of Florida work was intended as advisory and as helping interface our programs with the ones the co-PIs develop. The PI has fulfilled its role and was never intended to co-author publications in this area, since our role was mainly in advising and discussing interfaces.  The associated awards from the co-PIs are still funded, and there might be a co-authorship opportunity during the next year.       Last Modified: 05/21/2018       Submitted by: Adrian E Roitberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
