<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Integrative analysis of ingestive biomechanics and dental microwear in evolutionary and ecological context</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>69922.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>69922</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Modern humans exhibit small teeth, lightly built jaws and weak chewing muscles - anatomical features which have been shaped by evolutionary processes related to dietary intake and the processing of foods. The fossil record demonstrates that our morphology stands in contrast to that of our ancestors, who evolved to have large, strong teeth, massive jaws and powerful chewing muscles. Evolutionary explanations for this change include competing hypotheses as to how natural selection on diet drove adaptation over the course of human evolution.  These hypotheses suggest that the presence or absence of either very hard or very tough foods may have been a critical factor influencing the evolution of our ancestors.  Alternatively, the hardness or toughness of foods may have been less important than the behaviors (i.e., biting, puncturing, crushing, twisting, grinding) used to process foods of various shape and size with the jaws and teeth. This project will provide evidence to differentiate between these selective scenarios, thereby contributing to a fuller understanding of the evolutionary processes that have shaped this important aspect of modern human anatomy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will require focus on a primate model, South American capuchins, which exhibit the relevant diversity in musculoskeletal anatomy and diet requisite to testing hypotheses regarding how food properties (i.e., hardness, toughness) or feeding behaviors influence the evolution of feeding adaptations.  The study integrates observations of capuchin feeding behavior in the wild with laboratory experiments, advanced computer modeling using engineering methods, examination of the microscopic damage done to teeth by food and other items (i.e., dental microwear), the determination of the material properties (i.e., hardness, toughness) of food resources in the wild, and the collection and analysis of abrasive particles adhering to those foods (that might be influencing microwear patterns).  Collectively, these data in capuchins will allow us to evaluate the assumptions underlying our interpretations of the interrelationships between dietary behavior, food resources, and the biology of our human ancestors, thereby transforming our understanding of human evolutionary history.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research are considerable.  In relation to the public understanding of science, the research provides information that will address a topic of great public interest; namely, our own evolutionary history.  As a related benefit, the project illustrates how ecological factors affecting other animals may be equally relevant and impactful for our own species.  In terms of STEM training, research training opportunities are provided for high school students, undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows, many of whom are expected (based on past history at the collaborating institutions) to be young female scientists.  The project also contributes to environmental awareness by collecting basic ecological data relevant to rainforest conservation.  In the process of doing so, it further develops collaborative ties with international counterparts and institutions.  Lastly, the project illustrates to the engineering community how their methods can be used to answer evolutionary questions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1440545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barth</FirstName>
<LastName>Wright</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barth W Wright</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bwright@kcumb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8162832243</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wright</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristin Wright</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wrightkris@umkc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8162356619</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000073557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kansas City University of Medicine and Biosciences</Name>
<CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
<ZipCode>641061453</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8166547604</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1750 Independence Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>067952572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KANSAS CITY UNIVERSITY OF MEDICINE AND BIOSCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067952572</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kansas City University of Medicine and Biosciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>641061453</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1750 Independence Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~69922</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes discussed here apply only to data derived from field observation and data collection. The lead PI for this collaborative grant, Dr. David Strait, will provide a statement which applies to the total collaboration when his final report is submitted. We have found that the interface between feeding behavior and food material properties in craniofacially robust tufted capuchin monkeys is complex and mitigated by the use of tools. The toughest items are exploited by tufted capuchins with tools, intermediately tough food tissues are typically processed orally and manually, and the least tough items are typically chewed with limited manual assistance. These findings have made it obvious that adequate laboratory testing of craniofacial strain in primates must include manual-oral processing, particularly with the use of the anterior dentition. This finding is particularly relevant given that much previous laboratory work investigating facial strain focused solely on cheek tooth chewing and not anterior dental processing with the assistance of the forelimb and hand. It has also become apparent that food toughness, and thus the ability to produce work that will continue cracks in food items, is the variable that is most limiting to tufted capuchins. Thus they may be best referred to as tough food, as opposed to hard food, feeders. This has particular implications for interpreting the diets of suspected hard food feeding fossil primates, particularly our ape-like ancestors.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Barth&nbsp;W&nbsp;Wright</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes discussed here apply only to data derived from field observation and data collection. The lead PI for this collaborative grant, Dr. David Strait, will provide a statement which applies to the total collaboration when his final report is submitted. We have found that the interface between feeding behavior and food material properties in craniofacially robust tufted capuchin monkeys is complex and mitigated by the use of tools. The toughest items are exploited by tufted capuchins with tools, intermediately tough food tissues are typically processed orally and manually, and the least tough items are typically chewed with limited manual assistance. These findings have made it obvious that adequate laboratory testing of craniofacial strain in primates must include manual-oral processing, particularly with the use of the anterior dentition. This finding is particularly relevant given that much previous laboratory work investigating facial strain focused solely on cheek tooth chewing and not anterior dental processing with the assistance of the forelimb and hand. It has also become apparent that food toughness, and thus the ability to produce work that will continue cracks in food items, is the variable that is most limiting to tufted capuchins. Thus they may be best referred to as tough food, as opposed to hard food, feeders. This has particular implications for interpreting the diets of suspected hard food feeding fossil primates, particularly our ape-like ancestors.        Last Modified: 03/28/2019       Submitted by: Barth W Wright]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
