<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Curriculum and Community Enterprise for New York Harbor Restoration in New York City Public Schools</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4966960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5374972</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Haury</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Research consistently shows that children who have opportunities to actively investigate natural settings and engage in problem-based learning greatly benefit from the experiences.  They gain skills, interests, knowledge, aspirations, and motivation to learn more.  But how can we provide these rich opportunities in densely populated urban areas where resources and access to natural areas are limited?  This project will develop and test a model of curriculum and community enterprise to address that issue within the nation's largest urban school system.  Middle school students will study New York harbor and the extensive watershed that empties into it, and they will conduct field research in support of restoring native oyster habitats.  The project builds on the existing Billion Oyster Project, and will be implemented by a broad partnership of institutions and community resources, including Pace University, the New York City Department of Education, the Columbia University Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, the New York Academy of Sciences, the New York Harbor Foundation, the New York Aquarium, and others.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project focuses on an important concept in the geological, environmental, and biological sciences that typically receives inadequate attention in schools: watersheds.  This project builds on and extends the Billion Oyster Project of the New York Harbor School.  The project model includes five interrelated components:  A teacher education curriculum, a student learning curriculum, a digital platform for project resources, an aquarium exhibit, and an afterschool STEM mentoring program.  The project targets middle-school students in low-income neighborhoods with high populations of English language learners and students from groups underrepresented in STEM fields and education pathways.  The project will directly involve over forthy schools, eighty teachers, and 8,640 students over a period of three years.  A quasi-experimental, mixed-methods research plan will be used to assess the individual and collective effectiveness of the five project components.  Regression analyses will be used to identify effective program aspects and assess the individual effectiveness of participation in various combinations of the five program components.  Social network mapping will be used to further asses the overall "curriculum plus community" model.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1440869</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Newton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Newton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bnewton@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000182415</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhill@pace.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123461864</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000068158</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Birney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lauren Birney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lbirney@pace.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123461889</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000561076</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denise</FirstName>
<LastName>McNamara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Denise McNamara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>DMcNama@schools.nyc.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000568680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/18/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meghan</FirstName>
<LastName>Groome</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meghan Groome</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mgroome@nyas.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2122988600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000570000</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/23/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Woods</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy Woods</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>NWoods@schools.nyc.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123461200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000740066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Wortel-London</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie B Wortel-London</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Stephanie@csforall.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3155593480</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000791591</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pace University New York Campus</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100381502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2123461200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 Pace Plaza</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064961022</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PACE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064961022</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pace University New York Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100381502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~4966960</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~408012</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Curriculum and Community Enterprise for the Restoration of New York Harbor with New York City Public Schools NSF EHR DRL 1440869/PI Lauren Birney</em></strong></p> <p><br /> The Curriculum + Community Enterprise for Restoration Sciences (CCERS) partnership is four-year education research project. Ten organizations are collaborating to develop a curriculum to enhance STEM+C education in public middle schools by engaging participants in long-term restoration ecology and environmental monitoring projects, while developing a replicable educational model incorporating other restoration projects as suited to local environmental conditions. CCERS is a community of students and teachers, professional scientists and citizen scientist volunteers, schools, universities, businesses, and community organizations, all working together to conduct oyster restoration-based scientific research in New York Harbor. Our work is premised on a&nbsp;fundamental principle that schools and communities can and should play direct, active, and authentic roles in the ecological restoration and stewardship of the planet, especially in places where local habitats and species have been severely degraded by human development. Our theory of change is that school is made more meaningful and student learning enhanced when curricula are aligned to a local restoration ecology project that requires students to conduct authentic problem solving, data collection, experimentation, and research. Our work is funded through a four-year educational research grant from the National Science Foundation, Division of Research on Learning in Formal and Informal Settings.&nbsp;The NSF funded research consortium (NSF EHR DRL 1440869/PI Lauren Birney) has articulated an educational model known as ?Curriculum and Community Enterprise for Restoration Science? (CCERS).&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="http://bop.nyc/schools">BOP (Billion Oyster Project) Schools and Citizen Science</a>&nbsp;serves as the&nbsp;local&nbsp;anchor project&nbsp;of&nbsp;CCERS.&nbsp;The CCERS project is led by; principal investigators and senior personnel from Pace University School of Education, New York Harbor Foundation d/b/a Billon Oyster Project, New York City Department of Education?s Office of STEM, Columbia University?s Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, New York Academy of Sciences, and the University of Maryland?s Center for Environmental Science. Local implementing partners include Good Shepherd Services, New York Aquarium-WCS, The River Project, and Cell Motion Labs/BioBase. In total, our ten core partners are collectively responsible for development of the CCERS model, its five programmatic pillars, and for helping to chart the course of the BOP Schools and Citizen Science Program, the long-term anchor project of the model. The five BOPCCERS programmatic Pillars include:&nbsp; Pillar 1 Teaching Training Fellowship, Pillar 2 Field Science Research Training, Pillar 3 The BOP CCERS Digital Platform, Pillar 4 Afterschool Mentoring Program, Pillar 5 Museum Exhibitions. Significant outcomes and project deliverables of the project include the following global and national impacts:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Creation of the BOP CCERS Digital Platform</strong></li> <li><strong>Establishment the BOPCCERS Ecosystem Teaching and Learning STEM Model; replicable in other locale with various species </strong></li> <li><strong>Design Middle School Curriculum for Environmental Science</strong></li> <li><strong>Publication of Field Science Manual for Oyster Restoration</strong></li> <li><strong>Construction of BOP CCERS Community Exhibits </strong></li> <li><strong>14 Scholarly Journal Publications</strong></li> <li><strong>84 Conference Presentations &nbsp;</strong></li> <li><strong>BOP CCERS Project White Paper</strong></li> <li><strong>Project Impact: 127 NYCDOE Middle Schools, 84 NYCDOE Teachers 5600 Students</strong></li> <li><strong>Establishing a modality to engage students within inquiry based learning through restoration science thus increasing the quality of STEM + C teaching and learning</strong></li> <li><strong>Providing NYCDOE teachers with the necessary training and tools that will stimulate students? interest in STEM Careers and Industry fields</strong></li> <li><strong>Increasing students knowledge of STEM careers through experiential teaching and learning within New York Harbor</strong></li> </ul> <p>Conclusively, the New York City public school system, the nation?s largest and most urbanized system, face unique institutional and physical challenges to teaching and learning outside of the classroom. One of the most fundamental of these is access to the natural world. Most neighborhoods, especially those which are predominantly poor, have few green spaces accessible by foot. In fact, most middle schools have no field or adjacent natural surfaces. Where there are patches of green, teachers must contend with pollution, permissions from private or public entities, and competition for use of limited facilities. Thus, for the average New York City public school teacher, enabling students to learn or carry out inquiry-based research in the natural world is a logistical and physical challenge too difficult to overcome independently.</p> <p>The BOP CCERS model and methodology described herein offers a practical approach to begin overcoming systematic inequities within and between our nation?s school systems. The model is premised on the belief that authentic environmental problem solving?in the form of species and habitat restoration?engages students? interest thereby motivating them to learn more; and also that teachers must be equipped with a fully developed curriculum, training, and other relevant resources in order to successfully carry out restoration-based STEM+C teaching, and facilitate student learning across multiple community and field-based settings. Thus, the CCERS integrated methodology has been developed to generate significant increases in student and teacher engagement with STEM + Computing principles and content.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Lauren&nbsp;Birney</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540646186343_ScreenShot2018-10-27at9.14.11AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540646186343_ScreenShot2018-10-27at9.14.11AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CCERS Project Model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540646186343_ScreenShot2018-10-27at9.14.11AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CCERS Project Model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">"Curriculum and Community Enterprise for the Restoration of New York Harbor with New York City Public Schools"</div> <div class="imageCredit">Smartstart Evaluation and Research</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Birney</div> <div class="imageTitle">CCERS Project Model</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540647148106_ScreenShot2018-10-27at9.14.28AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540647148106_ScreenShot2018-10-27at9.14.28AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CCERS Project program Phase II"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540647148106_ScreenShot2018-10-27at9.14.28AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CCERS Project program Phase II"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Billion Oyster Project Curriculum and Community Enterprise for Restoration Science (BOP-CCERS) Phase II Expansion; Career and Technical Education Pathways</div> <div class="imageCredit">Smartstart Evaluation and Research</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Birney</div> <div class="imageTitle">CCERS Project program Phase II</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540737319663_BOPCCERS2018IMPACTOUTCOMESpng--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540737319663_BOPCCERS2018IMPACTOUTCOMESpng--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BOP CCERS Impact Outcomes 2018"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540737319663_BOPCCERS2018IMPACTOUTCOMESpng--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BOP CCERS Impact Outcomes 2018"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Partners are confident the CCERS Model is replicable with various keystone species in a wide range of global settings and venues. Project leaders recognize that the work set forth is ambitious and complex, but as an invested, experienced, and a vastly knowledgeable team, they accomplished the goals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Smartstart Evaluation and Research</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Birney</div> <div class="imageTitle">BOP CCERS Impact Outcomes 2018</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540738082445_DigitalPlatfromCitizenScienceCommunityEvents--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540738082445_DigitalPlatfromCitizenScienceCommunityEvents--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BOP CCERS Digital Platform Citizen Science and Community Events"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540738082445_DigitalPlatfromCitizenScienceCommunityEvents--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BOP CCERS Digital Platform Citizen Science and Community Events"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Research consistently shows that children who have opportunities to actively investigate natural settings and engage in problem-based learning greatly benefit from the experiences. They gain skills, interests, knowledge, aspirations, and motivation to learn more through Citizen Science stewardships.</div> <div class="imageCredit">BOP CCERS Project NSF</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Birney</div> <div class="imageTitle">BOP CCERS Digital Platform Citizen Science and Community Events</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540936752320_ProjectLogos--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540936752320_ProjectLogos--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BOP CCERS Project Logos"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540936752320_ProjectLogos--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BOP CCERS Project Logos"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">BOP CCERS Partner Logos</div> <div class="imageCredit">All BOP CCERS Project Partners</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Birney</div> <div class="imageTitle">BOP CCERS Project Logos</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540946324714_CCERSOrganizationalChart2018--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540946324714_CCERSOrganizationalChart2018--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BOP CCER Organizational Chart 2018"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440869/1440869_10337059_1540946324714_CCERSOrganizationalChart2018--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BOP CCER Organizational Chart 2018"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Organizational Chart for BOP -  CCERS 2018</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lauren B. Birney</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Birney</div> <div class="imageTitle">BOP CCER Organizational Chart 2018</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Curriculum and Community Enterprise for the Restoration of New York Harbor with New York City Public Schools NSF EHR DRL 1440869/PI Lauren Birney    The Curriculum + Community Enterprise for Restoration Sciences (CCERS) partnership is four-year education research project. Ten organizations are collaborating to develop a curriculum to enhance STEM+C education in public middle schools by engaging participants in long-term restoration ecology and environmental monitoring projects, while developing a replicable educational model incorporating other restoration projects as suited to local environmental conditions. CCERS is a community of students and teachers, professional scientists and citizen scientist volunteers, schools, universities, businesses, and community organizations, all working together to conduct oyster restoration-based scientific research in New York Harbor. Our work is premised on a fundamental principle that schools and communities can and should play direct, active, and authentic roles in the ecological restoration and stewardship of the planet, especially in places where local habitats and species have been severely degraded by human development. Our theory of change is that school is made more meaningful and student learning enhanced when curricula are aligned to a local restoration ecology project that requires students to conduct authentic problem solving, data collection, experimentation, and research. Our work is funded through a four-year educational research grant from the National Science Foundation, Division of Research on Learning in Formal and Informal Settings. The NSF funded research consortium (NSF EHR DRL 1440869/PI Lauren Birney) has articulated an educational model known as ?Curriculum and Community Enterprise for Restoration Science? (CCERS).   BOP (Billion Oyster Project) Schools and Citizen Science serves as the local anchor project of CCERS. The CCERS project is led by; principal investigators and senior personnel from Pace University School of Education, New York Harbor Foundation d/b/a Billon Oyster Project, New York City Department of Education?s Office of STEM, Columbia University?s Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, New York Academy of Sciences, and the University of Maryland?s Center for Environmental Science. Local implementing partners include Good Shepherd Services, New York Aquarium-WCS, The River Project, and Cell Motion Labs/BioBase. In total, our ten core partners are collectively responsible for development of the CCERS model, its five programmatic pillars, and for helping to chart the course of the BOP Schools and Citizen Science Program, the long-term anchor project of the model. The five BOPCCERS programmatic Pillars include:  Pillar 1 Teaching Training Fellowship, Pillar 2 Field Science Research Training, Pillar 3 The BOP CCERS Digital Platform, Pillar 4 Afterschool Mentoring Program, Pillar 5 Museum Exhibitions. Significant outcomes and project deliverables of the project include the following global and national impacts:  Creation of the BOP CCERS Digital Platform Establishment the BOPCCERS Ecosystem Teaching and Learning STEM Model; replicable in other locale with various species  Design Middle School Curriculum for Environmental Science Publication of Field Science Manual for Oyster Restoration Construction of BOP CCERS Community Exhibits  14 Scholarly Journal Publications 84 Conference Presentations   BOP CCERS Project White Paper Project Impact: 127 NYCDOE Middle Schools, 84 NYCDOE Teachers 5600 Students Establishing a modality to engage students within inquiry based learning through restoration science thus increasing the quality of STEM + C teaching and learning Providing NYCDOE teachers with the necessary training and tools that will stimulate students? interest in STEM Careers and Industry fields Increasing students knowledge of STEM careers through experiential teaching and learning within New York Harbor   Conclusively, the New York City public school system, the nation?s largest and most urbanized system, face unique institutional and physical challenges to teaching and learning outside of the classroom. One of the most fundamental of these is access to the natural world. Most neighborhoods, especially those which are predominantly poor, have few green spaces accessible by foot. In fact, most middle schools have no field or adjacent natural surfaces. Where there are patches of green, teachers must contend with pollution, permissions from private or public entities, and competition for use of limited facilities. Thus, for the average New York City public school teacher, enabling students to learn or carry out inquiry-based research in the natural world is a logistical and physical challenge too difficult to overcome independently.  The BOP CCERS model and methodology described herein offers a practical approach to begin overcoming systematic inequities within and between our nation?s school systems. The model is premised on the belief that authentic environmental problem solving?in the form of species and habitat restoration?engages students? interest thereby motivating them to learn more; and also that teachers must be equipped with a fully developed curriculum, training, and other relevant resources in order to successfully carry out restoration-based STEM+C teaching, and facilitate student learning across multiple community and field-based settings. Thus, the CCERS integrated methodology has been developed to generate significant increases in student and teacher engagement with STEM + Computing principles and content.       Last Modified: 10/30/2018       Submitted by: Lauren Birney]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
