<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CC*IIE IAM: Data at the Speed of Trust: Matching Computational Resources to Researchers using Sensitive Data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Increasingly, scientists use data that are considered sensitive as they conduct research, and protecting these sensitive data significantly adds to the complexity of doing research. This project reduces that complexity. Sensitive data requires strict security and confidentiality, complicating scientific collaboration vital to conducting research. Secure computing environments that protect data also tend to be inflexible, burdensome to use, and difficult to expand, reducing research efficiency.  To safeguard sensitive data while supporting scientific collaborations, the project uses software-defined networking (SDN) technologies that allow researchers to establish customized network routes with special provisions for security and performance, creating (for example) a high-speed, secure, and exclusive data connection between distant computers and storage devices. Attribute-based access control systems allow facts (as certified by a trusted entity) about a potential user to determine whether and what access should be granted to the user. This project combines emerging SDN networking technologies and the attribute-based access control systems arising from Internet2's Scalable Privacy initiative. Together, they secure data while also simplifying the granting of data access to collaborators from different organizations federated by a trusted attribute registry. Duke's existing protected network for sensitive research data serves as the project testbed, leveraging Duke's past experience with SDN and open source identity and access management tools widely deployed in academic research institutions. Thus, the project expects to safely enable research collaborations across institutions that use sensitive data, while providing an easy-to-use means to network powerful, diverse, and even geographically remote computational resources necessary to analyze the sensitive data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1440588</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tracy</FirstName>
<LastName>Futhey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tracy Futhey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>futhey@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196845300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277084010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8027</Code>
<Text>Cybersecurity Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="BodyA">This project established an advanced infrastructure for extending access to sensitive and protected research data and infrastructure on the Duke campus to collaborators outside of Duke.&nbsp; In doing so, it provided authorized Duke researchers with the ability to establish and control collaborator access directly, while maintaining the extensive security controls afforded by Duke&rsquo;s Protected Network.</p> <p class="BodyA">The project approach leveraged prior NSF-supported work at Duke that established a campus-wide Software Defined Network, SDN, (NSF OCI-1246042)<strong> </strong>and extended those capabilities into the realm of Software Defined Infrastructure (SDI) by federating identities <span style="text-decoration: underline;">and</span> resources (storage, computational cycles, and applications) that enable secure collaboration.&nbsp; By applying tools from Internet2's Scalable Privacy and leveraging NSF-funded Shibboleth identity management infrastructures, the project delivered federation of identities and infrastructures that is broadly extensible.&nbsp; Encompassing not only hardware and network resources, the project also enabled access to powerful software analysis environments by making common statistical packages and other analysis tools securely available to collaborators via only a web browser.&nbsp; Additionally, Duke has provisioned a Science DMZ with a dedicated 10G public internet connection to our SDI.&nbsp; This connection, along with Duke&rsquo;s connections to NCREN&rsquo;s regional SDN network and Internet2&rsquo;s AL2S network, allows Duke researchers &nbsp;to use trusted high bandwidth connections nationally and internationally that bypass campus traffic inspection services that reduce transfer rates and increase latency.</p> <p class="BodyA">The primary use case for the project was the provision of secure access to confidential large-scale social science data for inter-institutional collaboration and analysis (NSF ACI-1443014).&nbsp; Inter-institutional access was enabled through federated access to Duke&rsquo;s Protected Network, a highly secure network segment that requires further protections beyond the standard network (e.g., multifactor authentication, secure network connections, data ingress/egress limits). Extensions to the Duke identity management system and cross-university coordination regarding the designation and exchange of attributes now allow a researcher at Duke with appropriate credentials to authorize access for a non-Duke collaborator (e.g. from Princeton) for data and project resources within the Duke Protected Network.&nbsp; This access is using the collaborator&rsquo;s remote (Princeton) login credentials and requires no local (Duke) account credentialing, thereby obviating the prior need to sponsor a &ldquo;guest&rdquo; account for login at Duke.&nbsp; Because credentialing is via the collaborator&rsquo;s home account, the result is a more secure means of access that is simpler for researchers to manage.</p> <p class="BodyA">The project further enabled SDI through the &ldquo;web domestication&rdquo; of operating systems (Linux and Windows) and applications (RStudio, Matlab, Mathematica, SAS, Stata) to permit research software products on a Virtual Machine (VM) to be delivered via a web browser. Authorized researchers from any web browser and on any device (laptops, tablets, even smartphones) can access Duke secure research VM environments within the Duke Protected Network. As a result, authorized collaborators not only have their access initiated directly by the researcher, but their computational environments are automatically and dynamically provisioned, allowing them to be productive in a matter of minutes and without the need for local management or configuration or any software installation.</p> <p class="BodyA">In addition, this project extended Duke's Switchboard tool (initially developed via NSF CNS-1243315), a mature, open-source system that allows SDN switch configurations and networking rules to be created by authorized people to control machines at SDN-connected endpoints.&nbsp; This gives researchers &ldquo;on the fly&rdquo; control of the policies that determine how their traffic moves through the Duke and other SDN networks regionally, nationally and internationally.&nbsp; Switchboard authenticates such requests using Shibboleth.&nbsp; Once validated, it seamlessly reconfigures the network via SDN controls, resulting in the provisioning of routes onto the network via a publicly connected, but fully protected, control plane.</p> <p class="BodyA">Duke has applied these developments to extend SDN-enabled network connections regionally, nationally and internationally.&nbsp; For example, in collaboration with Internet2 and RENCI (Renaissance Computing Institute) Duke now provides connectivity to LHCONE (a private Layer3 network managed by CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research, for rapid distribution of LHC data) for researchers in Duke&rsquo;s Department of Physics. Duke's connection to LHCONE uses the technologies developed specifically in this grant, including Plexus, a Layer 2 circuit provision capability that plumbs an AL2S-provisioned VLAN through the regional SDN. Duke has been able to leverage MCNC&rsquo;s regional network and Internet2&rsquo;s AL2S to provide connectivity to national and regional resources.&nbsp; The dataplane used to move the bits between sites is separated from the control plane which operates over secure links between sites that can control traffic flows.&nbsp; Plexus, the SDN controller developed as a fork from Ryu at Duke, is used to direct traffic based on validation from Switchboard.</p> <p class="BodyA">The outcome of this project has been greater control in the hands of researchers to enable quick, flexible and secure provisioning of powerful SDI that encompasses individual machines and the networks that connect them.&nbsp; This powerful and secure access to highly sensitive research data extends for authorized Duke users and to collaborators outside of Duke.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Tracy&nbsp;Futhey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project established an advanced infrastructure for extending access to sensitive and protected research data and infrastructure on the Duke campus to collaborators outside of Duke.  In doing so, it provided authorized Duke researchers with the ability to establish and control collaborator access directly, while maintaining the extensive security controls afforded by Duke?s Protected Network. The project approach leveraged prior NSF-supported work at Duke that established a campus-wide Software Defined Network, SDN, (NSF OCI-1246042) and extended those capabilities into the realm of Software Defined Infrastructure (SDI) by federating identities and resources (storage, computational cycles, and applications) that enable secure collaboration.  By applying tools from Internet2's Scalable Privacy and leveraging NSF-funded Shibboleth identity management infrastructures, the project delivered federation of identities and infrastructures that is broadly extensible.  Encompassing not only hardware and network resources, the project also enabled access to powerful software analysis environments by making common statistical packages and other analysis tools securely available to collaborators via only a web browser.  Additionally, Duke has provisioned a Science DMZ with a dedicated 10G public internet connection to our SDI.  This connection, along with Duke?s connections to NCREN?s regional SDN network and Internet2?s AL2S network, allows Duke researchers  to use trusted high bandwidth connections nationally and internationally that bypass campus traffic inspection services that reduce transfer rates and increase latency. The primary use case for the project was the provision of secure access to confidential large-scale social science data for inter-institutional collaboration and analysis (NSF ACI-1443014).  Inter-institutional access was enabled through federated access to Duke?s Protected Network, a highly secure network segment that requires further protections beyond the standard network (e.g., multifactor authentication, secure network connections, data ingress/egress limits). Extensions to the Duke identity management system and cross-university coordination regarding the designation and exchange of attributes now allow a researcher at Duke with appropriate credentials to authorize access for a non-Duke collaborator (e.g. from Princeton) for data and project resources within the Duke Protected Network.  This access is using the collaborator?s remote (Princeton) login credentials and requires no local (Duke) account credentialing, thereby obviating the prior need to sponsor a "guest" account for login at Duke.  Because credentialing is via the collaborator?s home account, the result is a more secure means of access that is simpler for researchers to manage. The project further enabled SDI through the "web domestication" of operating systems (Linux and Windows) and applications (RStudio, Matlab, Mathematica, SAS, Stata) to permit research software products on a Virtual Machine (VM) to be delivered via a web browser. Authorized researchers from any web browser and on any device (laptops, tablets, even smartphones) can access Duke secure research VM environments within the Duke Protected Network. As a result, authorized collaborators not only have their access initiated directly by the researcher, but their computational environments are automatically and dynamically provisioned, allowing them to be productive in a matter of minutes and without the need for local management or configuration or any software installation. In addition, this project extended Duke's Switchboard tool (initially developed via NSF CNS-1243315), a mature, open-source system that allows SDN switch configurations and networking rules to be created by authorized people to control machines at SDN-connected endpoints.  This gives researchers "on the fly" control of the policies that determine how their traffic moves through the Duke and other SDN networks regionally, nationally and internationally.  Switchboard authenticates such requests using Shibboleth.  Once validated, it seamlessly reconfigures the network via SDN controls, resulting in the provisioning of routes onto the network via a publicly connected, but fully protected, control plane. Duke has applied these developments to extend SDN-enabled network connections regionally, nationally and internationally.  For example, in collaboration with Internet2 and RENCI (Renaissance Computing Institute) Duke now provides connectivity to LHCONE (a private Layer3 network managed by CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research, for rapid distribution of LHC data) for researchers in Duke?s Department of Physics. Duke's connection to LHCONE uses the technologies developed specifically in this grant, including Plexus, a Layer 2 circuit provision capability that plumbs an AL2S-provisioned VLAN through the regional SDN. Duke has been able to leverage MCNC?s regional network and Internet2?s AL2S to provide connectivity to national and regional resources.  The dataplane used to move the bits between sites is separated from the control plane which operates over secure links between sites that can control traffic flows.  Plexus, the SDN controller developed as a fork from Ryu at Duke, is used to direct traffic based on validation from Switchboard. The outcome of this project has been greater control in the hands of researchers to enable quick, flexible and secure provisioning of powerful SDI that encompasses individual machines and the networks that connect them.  This powerful and secure access to highly sensitive research data extends for authorized Duke users and to collaborators outside of Duke.       Last Modified: 09/15/2016       Submitted by: Tracy Futhey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
