<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CC*IIE Networking Infrastructure: FLowell: Accelerating Data-Driven Scientific Research at the University of Massachusetts Lowell</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>512000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The FLowell project accelerates a set of data-driven science projects at the University of Massachusetts Lowell (UML) by enhancing campus cyberinfrastructure (CI) with a software defined 10Gbps science network, deploying an advanced and fully network (SDN) integrated computing/storage rack at the Massachusetts Green High Performance Computing Center (MGHPCC), and connecting researchers labs at 10Gbps rate to the MGHPCC as well as external collaborators for highly efficient data sharing and transfer. The UML campus has seen a tremendous growth of data intensive research in many disciplines such as atmospheric science, network science, biomedical science and data management. To fulfill the data transfer needs from these projects, there is a strong call to address the slow network access speed, constraints on network management policies, and inefficient connectivity to MGHPCC and other external computing/storage resources. The UML campus network embraces software defined network technologies and the dedicated science Demilitarized Zone (DMZ) concept, which remove the bottlenecks for transferring large datasets. Layer 2 software defined control, perfSONAR (PERFormance Service Oriented Network monitoring ARchitecture) based measurement, and data transfer nodes are leveraged to enable state-of-the-art network control and operations. FLowell is an excellent network environment for PIs to evaluate and take advantage of novel networking technologies and welcomes a broader participation from other researchers. Based on the ongoing collaboration between the PI and campus IT and the pilot deployment of OpenFlow switches, the science teams, IT department, vendors, and MGHPCC personnel form a strong partnership to establish the advanced infrastructure and accelerate data centric knowledge discovery in a global context.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1440737</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vinod</FirstName>
<LastName>Vokkarane</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vinod M Vokkarane</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vinod_vokkarane@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789343345</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000060991</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yan</FirstName>
<LastName>Luo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yan Luo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Yan_Luo@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789342592</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tingjian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tingjian Ge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ge@cs.uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789343957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000534537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Galkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan Galkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ivan_Galkin@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789344912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000564120</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
<LastName>Cao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yu Cao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ycao@cs.uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789343628</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000584348</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Lowell</Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<ZipCode>018543692</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9789344170</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[600 Suffolk Street - Suite 212]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>956072490</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Lowell]]></Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018542827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We have established FLowell, an enhanced network infrastructure with science DMZ and Software Defined Networking to support a variety of data-driven scientific research at the University of Massachusetts Lowell (UML). Leveraging the existing computing resources, upgrading network equipment and connections, and bringing state-of-the-art technologies, the Flowell network infrastructure has been built with computing cluster racks, OpenFlow switches and controllers to enable fine-grained network resource control and sharing, and respond in real time to emerging network needs of researchers in atmospheric science, database science, biomedical science?and engineering, computer networking and architecture, representing the science and engineering research activities at UML.</p> <p>FLowell is an enhanced campus cyberinfrastructure for facilitating data-driven scientific? research. FLowell introduces science DMZ and SDN enabled high-performance network connectivity (10Gbps) between the science computing/storage resources at Massachusetts Green High Performance Computing Center (MGHPCC), and the researchers, as well as the resources to the collaborators outside campus, meeting the network requirements ?for data movement in science projects. The instrumentation and measurement of science data flows using perfSONAR have given the researchers and campus IT detailed performance data for cyberinfrastructure optimization and planning. Our extensive performance testing and tuning have led to <strong>100 times speedup</strong> on the data transfer rate between MGHPCC and UML: the iperf testing has shown the data transfer can reach up to 9.40Gbps with Flowell science network, whereas only 95.6Mbps on the campus non-science network.</p> <p>We have established a synergistic and state-of-the-art network infrastructure for facilitating data driven research by the faculty and students at UMass Lowell, reinforcing the institution&rsquo;s mission to broadening multidisciplinary research and improving research quality nationally and internationally. With this project, we have broadened the participation of underrepresented groups. The project has created research opportunities for both undergraduate and graduate students, and generated new knowledge for the networking community at large. Over the three years of this project, there are total five graduate students and four undergraduate students (one female) involved in the research, development and training activities. The project has supported the research work leading to four peer reviewed journal papers and five conference papers.</p> <p>This project also provided an unprecedented opportunity for the campus researchers to work closely with campus IT staff. Stephen Drescher was the senior network engineer who had been working closely with the PI and the team in the design and implementation of the Flowell infrastructure, and functioned as the interface between researchers and IT department. The project also provided opportunities for cross campus collaboration. For example, the network engineers at collaborating institution/organization (MGHPCC, Florida International University, Northwestern University) provided many help in the forms of technical consultation and coordinated network testing. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Yan&nbsp;Luo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We have established FLowell, an enhanced network infrastructure with science DMZ and Software Defined Networking to support a variety of data-driven scientific research at the University of Massachusetts Lowell (UML). Leveraging the existing computing resources, upgrading network equipment and connections, and bringing state-of-the-art technologies, the Flowell network infrastructure has been built with computing cluster racks, OpenFlow switches and controllers to enable fine-grained network resource control and sharing, and respond in real time to emerging network needs of researchers in atmospheric science, database science, biomedical science?and engineering, computer networking and architecture, representing the science and engineering research activities at UML.  FLowell is an enhanced campus cyberinfrastructure for facilitating data-driven scientific? research. FLowell introduces science DMZ and SDN enabled high-performance network connectivity (10Gbps) between the science computing/storage resources at Massachusetts Green High Performance Computing Center (MGHPCC), and the researchers, as well as the resources to the collaborators outside campus, meeting the network requirements ?for data movement in science projects. The instrumentation and measurement of science data flows using perfSONAR have given the researchers and campus IT detailed performance data for cyberinfrastructure optimization and planning. Our extensive performance testing and tuning have led to 100 times speedup on the data transfer rate between MGHPCC and UML: the iperf testing has shown the data transfer can reach up to 9.40Gbps with Flowell science network, whereas only 95.6Mbps on the campus non-science network.  We have established a synergistic and state-of-the-art network infrastructure for facilitating data driven research by the faculty and students at UMass Lowell, reinforcing the institution?s mission to broadening multidisciplinary research and improving research quality nationally and internationally. With this project, we have broadened the participation of underrepresented groups. The project has created research opportunities for both undergraduate and graduate students, and generated new knowledge for the networking community at large. Over the three years of this project, there are total five graduate students and four undergraduate students (one female) involved in the research, development and training activities. The project has supported the research work leading to four peer reviewed journal papers and five conference papers.  This project also provided an unprecedented opportunity for the campus researchers to work closely with campus IT staff. Stephen Drescher was the senior network engineer who had been working closely with the PI and the team in the design and implementation of the Flowell infrastructure, and functioned as the interface between researchers and IT department. The project also provided opportunities for cross campus collaboration. For example, the network engineers at collaborating institution/organization (MGHPCC, Florida International University, Northwestern University) provided many help in the forms of technical consultation and coordinated network testing.                Last Modified: 01/17/2018       Submitted by: Yan Luo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
