<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EarthCube Building Blocks:  Collaborative Proposal:  Enabling Scientific Collaboration and Discovery through Semantic Connections</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>386875.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>386875</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Data, information, ideas, and technologies diffuse through social and organizational networks, if the impediments to their adoption are low and the benefits of new approaches are clear. This project brings together the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), UNAVCO, and Cornell University to understand how to improve the processes of collaboration and resource sharing in the geosciences by demonstrating and encouraging the adoption of structured information systems rooted in common standards. Using two large geoscience research programs as case studies, this effort will demonstrate how semantic web and linked data technology can play an essential role in the coordination and organization of scientific virtual organizations and their products, thereby accelerating the pace of scientific discovery and innovation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will use a well-developed open source web application as an integrating data layer to expose the informational relationships and organizational collaborations within the case studies. This project will be an exemplar of using linked data to support virtual organizations in the geosciences. These efforts will feed into new tools that leverage linked data to support information and data exchange, and will produce recommendations on engaging user communities in linked data projects. This project will provide insight into how the geosciences can leverage linked data to produce more coherent methods of information and data discovery for large multi-disciplinary projects and virtual organizations. They will use the open source VIVO software application to illustrate how linked data can transform scientific project communication and dissemination via front end discovery based on rich networked metadata. The VIVO platform provides new capabilities for researchers and educators to use structured, interpretable data, permitting direct interlinking of information and data across platforms and projects. The project will structure data into an ontology-based, standard data format (RDF) for re-use, leveraging web identifier and vocabulary structures that have been well developed and widely adopted in the geoscience and cyberinfrastructure communities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1440213</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Rowan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda R Rowan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rowan@unavco.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3033817461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000645472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>UNAVCO, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803015394</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3033817500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6350 Nautilus Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>142357032</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNAVCO, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UNAVCO]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803015394</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6350 Nautilus Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8074</Code>
<Text>EarthCube</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~386875</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The EarthCollab project, officially titled <em>EarthCube Building Blocks: Collaborative Proposal: Enabling Scientific Collaboration and Discovery through Semantic Connections</em>, is focused on using Semantic Web and linked data technology to facilitate the coordination and organization of complex scientific projects and their products. The premise of EarthCollab is that many relationships exist among (and within) scientific resources, projects, and people and organizations, and these relationships provide an important means for people to discover and use geoscience data resources. From a technology point of view, the project has developed information systems that leverage linked data to produce more coherent methods of information and data discovery for large multi-disciplinary projects and virtual organizations. These systems enable researchers to more easily find people, organizations, and research resources that are relevant to their work, which could spark new scientific discoveries.<br /> &nbsp;<br /> The project has used the open source VIVO semantic software suite (http://vivoweb.org) to provide interfaces for researchers within two targeted scientific research areas to explore the people, publications, platforms, and data sets within their respective communities. These systems, called Connect UNAVCO (https://connect.unavco.org/) and Arctic Data Connects (http://vivo.eol.ucar.edu), are both live for public use. As an illustration of the kinds of information that these systems contain, as of 31 August 2018, Connect UNAVCO contains records for nearly 6,000 scientific documents, 4,620 datasets, 3,920 research sites, 236 grants, 846 people, and 381 organizations. Arctic Data Connects, with a more focused case study on select arctic research projects, contains records for 354 datasets, 26 grants, 146 people, and 53 organizations. We used multiple user-centered design methodologies to inform the development and iteration of Connect UNAVCO and&nbsp; Arctic Data Connects, including targeted surveys, small focus groups, and individual interviews and usability tests.</p> <p>The information in these systems comes from a combination of existing metadata databases and newly created metadata. The resources are represented via the Semantic Web data model, in which ontologies are used to define entity types (classes), and the relationships between them (properties). To facilitate easier integration and data sharing across geoscience communities, our goal within this project has been to reuse existing ontologies as much as possible when developing project ontologies and web applications. This effort involved conceptual modeling of the key entities and relationships of interest, and finding relevant existing ontologies that map to our conceptual model. To create the EarthCollab ontology model, we combined components from multiple ontologies, and created custom ontology extensions as necessary to fill gaps.</p> <p>The result is networked sets of information, in which researchers, datasets, publications, scientific instruments, research projects, and research locations are each represented in the data model as distinct entities that have specific types of relationships with other entities. Practically, the VIVO software displays a web page for each entity, which provides information about the entity along with links to other entities that are related via explicitly declared relationships. For example, the web page for a particular dataset within one of the systems will potentially display links to associated publications, organizations, grants, creators, and instruments.</p> <p>Another component of this project has been to add capabilities to the VIVO software suite itself. In the first two years of the project, we developed a prototype cross-linking approach to exchange information across VIVO instances. The motivation for this work was that scientific research is increasingly multi-organizational. The new VIVO cross-linking feature was developed to enable the exchange of information about specific people or entities that are in common across different VIVO instances. This new feature reduces duplication of information across systems and enables the distribution of authoritative information about specific entities, such a single individual who has VIVO profiles at different organizations. The cross-linking capability has been deployed to operational VIVO systems, and is being contributed to the VIVO open source code community.</p> <p>In summary, some of the advances of the project include further development and enhancement of the open source VIVO software for sharing and discovering research; development of VIVO instances at two university consortia (UNAVCO and NCAR EOL) with the unique challenges of extending VIVO beyond a single organization use case; consideration, discussion, and advancement of geoscience semantics to improve connectivity of research outputs; consideration and extension of appropriate ontologies into the geoscience research space; advancing the use of persistent identifiers for researchers, publications, datasets, data products, and institutions to improve research discovery; significantly enhancing the connectivity of people, publications, and products within the two consortia; consulting, advising, and informing researchers about ways to connect and discover research; and most importantly building two significant VIVO instances, Connect UNAVCO and Arctic Data Connects, to enhance sharing and discovery.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Linda&nbsp;R&nbsp;Rowan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849268700_expertise-unavco--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849268700_expertise-unavco--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Connect UNAVCO list of expertise in different categories"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849268700_expertise-unavco--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Connect UNAVCO list of expertise in different categories"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A screenshot of the Connect UNAVCO VIVO instance expertise index page. We developed a list of concepts based on known and well recognized geoscience semantics. We requested researchers and others to choose from these various concepts to define areas of expertise. These concepts were added to the res</div> <div class="imageCredit">UNAVCO</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Linda&nbsp;R&nbsp;Rowan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Connect UNAVCO list of expertise in different categories</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849348709_profile-unavco--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849348709_profile-unavco--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Connect UNAVCO example person profile page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849348709_profile-unavco--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Connect UNAVCO example person profile page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A screenshot of the Connect UNAVCO VIVO instance, showing a researcher profile. We asked researchers to fill out a survey about their expertise and to send us their ORCID. Both are new initiatives for our data services program and will help us to connect and discover research much better.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UNAVCO</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Linda&nbsp;R&nbsp;Rowan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Connect UNAVCO example person profile page</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849451973_unavco-connecteditems--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849451973_unavco-connecteditems--rgov-800width.jpg" title="List of products in an example Connect UNAVCO person profile page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1440213/1440213_10328006_1540849451973_unavco-connecteditems--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="List of products in an example Connect UNAVCO person profile page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screenshot of the Connect UNAVCO VIVO instance, showing some of the products of a particular researcher. Here the researcher?s publications are integrated with Altmetrics and ReadCube, which are external tools for looking at the impact of a publication. More importantly, besides publications we can</div> <div class="imageCredit">UNAVCO</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Linda&nbsp;R&nbsp;Rowan</div> <div class="imageTitle">List of products in an example Connect UNAVCO person profile page</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The EarthCollab project, officially titled EarthCube Building Blocks: Collaborative Proposal: Enabling Scientific Collaboration and Discovery through Semantic Connections, is focused on using Semantic Web and linked data technology to facilitate the coordination and organization of complex scientific projects and their products. The premise of EarthCollab is that many relationships exist among (and within) scientific resources, projects, and people and organizations, and these relationships provide an important means for people to discover and use geoscience data resources. From a technology point of view, the project has developed information systems that leverage linked data to produce more coherent methods of information and data discovery for large multi-disciplinary projects and virtual organizations. These systems enable researchers to more easily find people, organizations, and research resources that are relevant to their work, which could spark new scientific discoveries.     The project has used the open source VIVO semantic software suite (http://vivoweb.org) to provide interfaces for researchers within two targeted scientific research areas to explore the people, publications, platforms, and data sets within their respective communities. These systems, called Connect UNAVCO (https://connect.unavco.org/) and Arctic Data Connects (http://vivo.eol.ucar.edu), are both live for public use. As an illustration of the kinds of information that these systems contain, as of 31 August 2018, Connect UNAVCO contains records for nearly 6,000 scientific documents, 4,620 datasets, 3,920 research sites, 236 grants, 846 people, and 381 organizations. Arctic Data Connects, with a more focused case study on select arctic research projects, contains records for 354 datasets, 26 grants, 146 people, and 53 organizations. We used multiple user-centered design methodologies to inform the development and iteration of Connect UNAVCO and  Arctic Data Connects, including targeted surveys, small focus groups, and individual interviews and usability tests.  The information in these systems comes from a combination of existing metadata databases and newly created metadata. The resources are represented via the Semantic Web data model, in which ontologies are used to define entity types (classes), and the relationships between them (properties). To facilitate easier integration and data sharing across geoscience communities, our goal within this project has been to reuse existing ontologies as much as possible when developing project ontologies and web applications. This effort involved conceptual modeling of the key entities and relationships of interest, and finding relevant existing ontologies that map to our conceptual model. To create the EarthCollab ontology model, we combined components from multiple ontologies, and created custom ontology extensions as necessary to fill gaps.  The result is networked sets of information, in which researchers, datasets, publications, scientific instruments, research projects, and research locations are each represented in the data model as distinct entities that have specific types of relationships with other entities. Practically, the VIVO software displays a web page for each entity, which provides information about the entity along with links to other entities that are related via explicitly declared relationships. For example, the web page for a particular dataset within one of the systems will potentially display links to associated publications, organizations, grants, creators, and instruments.  Another component of this project has been to add capabilities to the VIVO software suite itself. In the first two years of the project, we developed a prototype cross-linking approach to exchange information across VIVO instances. The motivation for this work was that scientific research is increasingly multi-organizational. The new VIVO cross-linking feature was developed to enable the exchange of information about specific people or entities that are in common across different VIVO instances. This new feature reduces duplication of information across systems and enables the distribution of authoritative information about specific entities, such a single individual who has VIVO profiles at different organizations. The cross-linking capability has been deployed to operational VIVO systems, and is being contributed to the VIVO open source code community.  In summary, some of the advances of the project include further development and enhancement of the open source VIVO software for sharing and discovering research; development of VIVO instances at two university consortia (UNAVCO and NCAR EOL) with the unique challenges of extending VIVO beyond a single organization use case; consideration, discussion, and advancement of geoscience semantics to improve connectivity of research outputs; consideration and extension of appropriate ontologies into the geoscience research space; advancing the use of persistent identifiers for researchers, publications, datasets, data products, and institutions to improve research discovery; significantly enhancing the connectivity of people, publications, and products within the two consortia; consulting, advising, and informing researchers about ways to connect and discover research; and most importantly building two significant VIVO instances, Connect UNAVCO and Arctic Data Connects, to enhance sharing and discovery.          Last Modified: 10/31/2018       Submitted by: Linda R Rowan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
