<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Continuing Theoretical Studies of Dynamical Processes in the Ionosphere</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmeriwet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927212</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Changes in the upper atmosphere and in its ionized part (ionosphere) can be detrimental to human activities. They can affect satellite drag, which in turn affects satellite lifetimes. Short term changes can lead the formation of storm-enhanced densities, rising atmospheric bubbles, solar flare-induced ionization enhancements, and propagating atmospheric holes and plasma patches. These upper atmospheric disturbances have adverse effects on GPS navigation systems, power grids, over-the-horizon radar systems, and High Frequency (HF) communications used by the military, emergency responders, and airlines. This research is focused on elucidating the physics that governs these processes, leading to improved specification and forecast models, and better mitigation strategies for adverse upper atmosphere weather disturbances. Space 'climate' studies will involve the use of long-duration radar and satellite datasets and model studies to determine the reasons for long-term upper atmosphere changes. &lt;br/&gt;The primary goals of this research are to study the effects that various plasma and neutral gas transport processes have on the ionosphere-thermosphere system, and to study coupling mechanisms that are relevant to the near-Earth space environment. The research involves an extensive use of data from NSF-funded and other ground-based facilities and satellites, including data from Incoherent Scatter Radars [Arecibo, Millstone Hill, Poker Flat (PFISR), Resolute Bay (RISR) and EISCAT], SuperDARN radars, ionosondes, and satellites (DMSP, ACE and SDO). The research will be conducted with the aid of high-resolution, global-scale, physics-based models of the ionosphere, thermosphere, and electrodynamics. The project will focus on long-term ionospheric changes and observation and modeling of the space-atmosphere interaction region.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1441774</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Schunk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert W Schunk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rws4405@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357972978</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000168907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sojka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan J Sojka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jan.sojka@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357972964</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423516</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1415 Old Main Hill ~ Room 64]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Center for Atmospheric and Space Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843224405</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4405 Old Main Hill]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The upper atmosphere and embedded ionosphere display space weather features, including sharp ridges of ionization, supersonic neutral winds, propagating ionization patches, rapidly rising bubble depletions, sporadic ionization layers, and enhanced aurora borealis displays. The space weather disturbances can occur over a wide range of spatial and temporal scales, and they can arise as a result of generation mechanisms on the Sun, in the solar wind, in the lower atmosphere, and by instability processes in the upper atmosphere - ionosphere system. Unfortunately, space weather can have a detrimental effect on numerous operations and systems. Because of the increasing reliance on technology, there is a strong need to elucidate the basic physics governing space weather effects in the upper atmosphere-ionosphere system.</p> <p>&nbsp;Our overall research goal was to elucidate the causes of plasma density gradients and structures in the terrestrial upper atmosphere-ionosphere system, and to study coupling mechanisms that are relevant to the near-Earth space environment. The emphasis was on the plasma density gradients in the ionosphere associated with polar cap patches, tongues of ionization, field-aligned currents, localized electric fields, traveling atmospheric waves, and geomagnetic storms. A better understanding of the creation and evolution of these features will lead to improved specifications and forecasts of upper atmosphere-ionosphere weather. The research was conducted with global, time-dependent, high-resolution models of the upper atmosphere-ionosphere system. The research also involved extensive use of data from NSF-funded instruments and NASA satellites.</p> <p>&nbsp;Our modeling and measurement studies have led to several important research results:</p> <p class="Pa4">&nbsp;1. We generated a new high-resolution dataset of ionospheric Total Electron Content (TEC) measurements. The data files for the TEC mapping were downloaded from the Madrigal web server at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) for the years 2009 to 2018. To optimize the usefulness of the data in the context of our project to study ionospheric density patches in the polar region, it was necessary to re-cast the raw data into a form that consists of TEC maps in a rectangular grid in magnetic coordinates of 105 x 105 elements, covering the high-latitude ionosphere. The 105 x 105 grids are at a time cadence of 5 minutes. The number of files per year is 105,120. The entire dataset, consisting of more than one million data files has been stored on the publicly accessible Digital Commons server at Utah State University (<a href="https://doi.org/10.26078/a7g8-5m30)">https://doi.org/10.26078/a7g8-5m30)</a> for use by the scientific community.</p> <p>&nbsp;2. We found that some long-held beliefs about ionospheric plasma patches and Tongues of Ionization (TOI; Figure) are not supported by our new database of ionospheric TEC maps (Item 1). Before our work all studies involving patches and TOI were based on data covering a limited area, such as radar observations from fixed locations. In contrast, we were able to look at the issue with continuous data coverage of the entire polar region over a period of years, via the ionospheric TEC maps (Item 1).&nbsp; This has put us in a position to correct certain views on the subject that have long been considered to be common knowledge, but which are in fact wrong. For example, that the tongue of ionization is to be considered as being primarily a storm-time feature.</p> <p>&nbsp;3. Numerous studies have been conducted of polar cap plasma patches in the northern hemisphere, but in contrast, a relatively small number of studies have been devoted to plasma patches in the southern hemisphere. We believe that satellite-based patch searchers have led some researchers to draw conclusions that are incorrect. In particular, we found that the southern hemisphere plasma patch occurrence is very similar to that of the northern hemisphere with a half-year offset, plus an offset in universal time of approximately 12 hours. This was further supported by running our physics-based ionospheric model for both hemispheres and applying the same patch-to-background technique.</p> <p>&nbsp;4. Our study of the variability of the auroral oval as seen in the ionospheric TEC maps indicates that the source of this variability is most likely variations in the neutral wind in the upper atmosphere. This points to the important fact that our comparatively poor observation and understanding of upper atmospheric neutral winds is one of the greatest obstacles to improving our capacity to forecast and model the ionosphere.</p> <p>&nbsp;5. Previously, we predicted the existence of a new field-aligned current system in the high-latitude ionosphere that is associated with the solar terminator (Figure, right dial). The discovery was based on the reconstructions from a physics-based data assimilation model.&nbsp;In this research, the existence of the terminator field-aligned current was confirmed via direct observations. Specifically, measurements of ion and electron precipitation, plasma velocity and density, as well as derived field-aligned currents from satellite polar passes were examined. Several important dynamical/climatological features of the terminator field-aligned current discovered via our data-assimilation studies were also confirmed by the satellite observations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2020<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schunk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1441774/1441774_10369754_1579033657278_ScreenShot2020-01-14at1.16.33PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1441774/1441774_10369754_1579033657278_ScreenShot2020-01-14at1.16.33PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Snapshots of ionospheric features in the winter northern polar region"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1441774/1441774_10369754_1579033657278_ScreenShot2020-01-14at1.16.33PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Snapshots of ionospheric features in the winter northern polar region"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The snapshots are in a geomagnetic coordinate system. Red corresponds high densities and blue to low densities. TOI extends across the polar cap (left), plasma patches appear in the dark polar cap (middle), and the terminator current is the blue current on the dayside aligned dusk-to-dawn (right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Utah State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schunk</div> <div class="imageTitle">Snapshots of ionospheric features in the winter northern polar region</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The upper atmosphere and embedded ionosphere display space weather features, including sharp ridges of ionization, supersonic neutral winds, propagating ionization patches, rapidly rising bubble depletions, sporadic ionization layers, and enhanced aurora borealis displays. The space weather disturbances can occur over a wide range of spatial and temporal scales, and they can arise as a result of generation mechanisms on the Sun, in the solar wind, in the lower atmosphere, and by instability processes in the upper atmosphere - ionosphere system. Unfortunately, space weather can have a detrimental effect on numerous operations and systems. Because of the increasing reliance on technology, there is a strong need to elucidate the basic physics governing space weather effects in the upper atmosphere-ionosphere system.   Our overall research goal was to elucidate the causes of plasma density gradients and structures in the terrestrial upper atmosphere-ionosphere system, and to study coupling mechanisms that are relevant to the near-Earth space environment. The emphasis was on the plasma density gradients in the ionosphere associated with polar cap patches, tongues of ionization, field-aligned currents, localized electric fields, traveling atmospheric waves, and geomagnetic storms. A better understanding of the creation and evolution of these features will lead to improved specifications and forecasts of upper atmosphere-ionosphere weather. The research was conducted with global, time-dependent, high-resolution models of the upper atmosphere-ionosphere system. The research also involved extensive use of data from NSF-funded instruments and NASA satellites.   Our modeling and measurement studies have led to several important research results:  1. We generated a new high-resolution dataset of ionospheric Total Electron Content (TEC) measurements. The data files for the TEC mapping were downloaded from the Madrigal web server at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) for the years 2009 to 2018. To optimize the usefulness of the data in the context of our project to study ionospheric density patches in the polar region, it was necessary to re-cast the raw data into a form that consists of TEC maps in a rectangular grid in magnetic coordinates of 105 x 105 elements, covering the high-latitude ionosphere. The 105 x 105 grids are at a time cadence of 5 minutes. The number of files per year is 105,120. The entire dataset, consisting of more than one million data files has been stored on the publicly accessible Digital Commons server at Utah State University (https://doi.org/10.26078/a7g8-5m30) for use by the scientific community.   2. We found that some long-held beliefs about ionospheric plasma patches and Tongues of Ionization (TOI; Figure) are not supported by our new database of ionospheric TEC maps (Item 1). Before our work all studies involving patches and TOI were based on data covering a limited area, such as radar observations from fixed locations. In contrast, we were able to look at the issue with continuous data coverage of the entire polar region over a period of years, via the ionospheric TEC maps (Item 1).  This has put us in a position to correct certain views on the subject that have long been considered to be common knowledge, but which are in fact wrong. For example, that the tongue of ionization is to be considered as being primarily a storm-time feature.   3. Numerous studies have been conducted of polar cap plasma patches in the northern hemisphere, but in contrast, a relatively small number of studies have been devoted to plasma patches in the southern hemisphere. We believe that satellite-based patch searchers have led some researchers to draw conclusions that are incorrect. In particular, we found that the southern hemisphere plasma patch occurrence is very similar to that of the northern hemisphere with a half-year offset, plus an offset in universal time of approximately 12 hours. This was further supported by running our physics-based ionospheric model for both hemispheres and applying the same patch-to-background technique.   4. Our study of the variability of the auroral oval as seen in the ionospheric TEC maps indicates that the source of this variability is most likely variations in the neutral wind in the upper atmosphere. This points to the important fact that our comparatively poor observation and understanding of upper atmospheric neutral winds is one of the greatest obstacles to improving our capacity to forecast and model the ionosphere.   5. Previously, we predicted the existence of a new field-aligned current system in the high-latitude ionosphere that is associated with the solar terminator (Figure, right dial). The discovery was based on the reconstructions from a physics-based data assimilation model. In this research, the existence of the terminator field-aligned current was confirmed via direct observations. Specifically, measurements of ion and electron precipitation, plasma velocity and density, as well as derived field-aligned currents from satellite polar passes were examined. Several important dynamical/climatological features of the terminator field-aligned current discovered via our data-assimilation studies were also confirmed by the satellite observations.                Last Modified: 01/14/2020       Submitted by: Robert W Schunk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
