<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Zygomycetes Genealogy of Life (ZyGoLife)- the conundrum of Kingdom Fungi</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>690389.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>690389</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Ingram</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aingram@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924811</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fungi comprise one of the most successful groups of life on Earth. They inhabit most of the world's environments, where they perform numerous functions (e.g., nutrient cycling, foundations of food webs, etc.) that are central to healthy ecosystems. Importantly, fungi interact with all other forms of life, including plants, animals and bacteria -- in associations that range from beneficial to antagonistic. Zygomycete fungi, the focus of this research project, are an ancient group in which most of the morphological and ecological traits associated with Kingdom Fungi first arose, but their evolutionary history and ecological associations have not yet been well resolved. This project will reconstruct the genealogical relationships of this earliest branch in fungal evolutionary history, resolve the origins of symbiotic relationships between plants and zygomycetes, reveal how complex body plans evolved in the group, elucidate mechanisms of mating genetics between organisms with complex and differing life cycles, and develop genomic barcodes to facilitate identification of unknown fungi. The results of this research will contribute to many scientific disciplines and to society. Expanding and maintaining expertise on these fungi is critical for the field of biology, human health and productivity, and safe food production. This project includes training of the next generation of mycologists, dissemination of information on basic fungal biology, development of teaching resources, expansion of biological database and web resources, development of research materials including strain cultures and genomes for the wider scientific community, and broadening of participation of underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Zygomycetes are filamentous fungi that lack flagella and that produce simple but defined reproductive structures. An initial analysis of zygomycete genomes support the hypothesis that the group is a pivotal transition point between certain flagellated Fungi and their specific life histories, and what became the dominant eukaryotic terrestrial clade of Fungi (the fleshy fungi, e.g., mushrooms).  Because the zygomycetes are the first terrestrial fungi that exhibit fruiting bodies, understanding how these structures evolved will provide a basis for understanding the origins of complex morphogenesis (e.g., multicellularity) in the Fungi, as well as the evolution of complex life histories.  Zygomycetes also display a diversity of ecological relationships with plants (mycorrhizae), animals (pathogens) and bacteria (endosymbionts). Resolving the phylogenetic origins of these interactions will provide an evolutionary framework for elucidating molecular and biochemical mechanisms that govern these interactions, and in doing so, will have direct impacts on research into natural and managed ecosystems and human welfare.  This research will also refine molecular environmental sampling techniques, resulting in a more accurate census of zygomycete biodiversity, especially in soil ecosystems. By gathering orders of magnitude more genome-scale data and integrating it with biochemical, morphological, subcellular, and fossil data layers, this elusive region of the fungal genealogy of life will be illuminated and will provide a foundation for broad scale biological research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1441677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>James</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy James</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tyjames@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641817</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000521823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew E Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trufflesmith@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523923516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000613284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091048</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6133</Code>
<Text>GoLife</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6133</Code>
<Text>GoLife</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~690389</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Zygomycetes are a group of microscopic fungi that play diverse and economically important roles across the planet?s artificial and natural ecosystems. For example, a group of Zygomycetes known as Glomeromycotina forms an underground association with the roots of 80% of all the species of land plants, including most crops. Others play pivotal roles as agents of decay, such as those causing food storage rot, or parasites of animals ranging from insects to humans. However, research on this group has recently lagged, in part because many species are difficult to work with, some being hard to find and isolate or others growing only in the presence of another host species. This project led to the formation of a consortium of researchers (ZyGoLife) with expertise on this forgotten group of fungi, aiming to develop a better understanding of the diversity of species, their ecological potential, and evolutionary history, while stimulating the next generation of researchers and the broader scientific community to research these organisms. This specific portion of the Collaborative project involved the University of Michigan, the University of Florida, and the University of Ottawa. This specific team focused on members of the Zygomycetes that cannot be cultured without their hosts, i.e., obligate symbionts. These include fungi that are obligately predatory on microinvertebrates or amoebae, fungi that parasitize other fungi (mycoparasites), fungi that obligately parasitize insects (Entomophthoromycotina), and the Glomeromycotina, which cannot be propagated without their plant hosts. The team focused on developing methods and analysis pipelines for inferring the evolution and ecology of these organisms accessing their genome sequences. The results developed pipelines for creating evolutionary trees of fungi using data from sequencing of the entire pool of RNA of the cell (transcriptomics), sequencing all the DNA from a single cell (single cell genomics), and sequencing the DNA of both the host and parasite (metagenomics). The pieces of these individual studies are being put together to complete the puzzle of the Zygomycete Tree of Life to understand how the organisms have diversified in form and function over evolutionary history.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project supported the science behind 20&nbsp;&nbsp;scientific articles published in research journals or books and dozens of research presentations at scientific meetings. Important results include a large collaborative publication that illustrates the promise of using single-cell genomes to more fully understand the Fungal Tree of Life and several analyses of the biology and genomics of Glomeromycotina. There were also a wide range of more specialized taxonomic and phylogenetic analyses that shed light on the evolution of particular groups, including&nbsp;<em>Syncephalis</em>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<em>Piptocephalis&nbsp;</em>which are two diverse genera of obligate mycoparasites, collaborative work to understand the biology of plant-symbiotic Endogonaceae, and the first phylogenomic analysis of Zoopagales.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project also supported research and training of 4 postdoctoral fellows, 3 graduate students, and 4 undergraduates. The ZyGoLife group held a workshop on the fungi at the Mycological Society of America Annual Meeting in Athens, GA 2017. A companion laboratory guide was developed and will be made freely available as a reference for scientists looking for practical guidelines for working on these fungi. Over the course of the project we also worked to contribute well researched and referenced educational materials for more than 125 species and genera of zygomycetes for the Encyclopedia of Life, an online resource that is freely available on the internet. These EOL ?species pages? were created as part of student education and training projects in fungal biology courses at the University of Florida and several collaborating institutions. These web pages provide an overview on the biology and phylogenetic relationships of zygomycete fungi that can now be used by the public for educational purposes at any time.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;James</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Zygomycetes are a group of microscopic fungi that play diverse and economically important roles across the planet?s artificial and natural ecosystems. For example, a group of Zygomycetes known as Glomeromycotina forms an underground association with the roots of 80% of all the species of land plants, including most crops. Others play pivotal roles as agents of decay, such as those causing food storage rot, or parasites of animals ranging from insects to humans. However, research on this group has recently lagged, in part because many species are difficult to work with, some being hard to find and isolate or others growing only in the presence of another host species. This project led to the formation of a consortium of researchers (ZyGoLife) with expertise on this forgotten group of fungi, aiming to develop a better understanding of the diversity of species, their ecological potential, and evolutionary history, while stimulating the next generation of researchers and the broader scientific community to research these organisms. This specific portion of the Collaborative project involved the University of Michigan, the University of Florida, and the University of Ottawa. This specific team focused on members of the Zygomycetes that cannot be cultured without their hosts, i.e., obligate symbionts. These include fungi that are obligately predatory on microinvertebrates or amoebae, fungi that parasitize other fungi (mycoparasites), fungi that obligately parasitize insects (Entomophthoromycotina), and the Glomeromycotina, which cannot be propagated without their plant hosts. The team focused on developing methods and analysis pipelines for inferring the evolution and ecology of these organisms accessing their genome sequences. The results developed pipelines for creating evolutionary trees of fungi using data from sequencing of the entire pool of RNA of the cell (transcriptomics), sequencing all the DNA from a single cell (single cell genomics), and sequencing the DNA of both the host and parasite (metagenomics). The pieces of these individual studies are being put together to complete the puzzle of the Zygomycete Tree of Life to understand how the organisms have diversified in form and function over evolutionary history.      The project supported the science behind 20  scientific articles published in research journals or books and dozens of research presentations at scientific meetings. Important results include a large collaborative publication that illustrates the promise of using single-cell genomes to more fully understand the Fungal Tree of Life and several analyses of the biology and genomics of Glomeromycotina. There were also a wide range of more specialized taxonomic and phylogenetic analyses that shed light on the evolution of particular groups, including Syncephalis and Piptocephalis which are two diverse genera of obligate mycoparasites, collaborative work to understand the biology of plant-symbiotic Endogonaceae, and the first phylogenomic analysis of Zoopagales.      This project also supported research and training of 4 postdoctoral fellows, 3 graduate students, and 4 undergraduates. The ZyGoLife group held a workshop on the fungi at the Mycological Society of America Annual Meeting in Athens, GA 2017. A companion laboratory guide was developed and will be made freely available as a reference for scientists looking for practical guidelines for working on these fungi. Over the course of the project we also worked to contribute well researched and referenced educational materials for more than 125 species and genera of zygomycetes for the Encyclopedia of Life, an online resource that is freely available on the internet. These EOL ?species pages? were created as part of student education and training projects in fungal biology courses at the University of Florida and several collaborating institutions. These web pages provide an overview on the biology and phylogenetic relationships of zygomycete fungi that can now be used by the public for educational purposes at any time.           Last Modified: 01/24/2020       Submitted by: Timothy James]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
