<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SaTC: STARSS: Collaborative: IPTrust: A Comprehensive Framework for IP Integrity Validation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>178000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandip Kundu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To reduce production cost while meeting time-to-market constraints, semiconductor companies usually design hardware systems with reusable hardware modules, popularly known as Intellectual Property (IP) blocks. Growing reliance on these hardware IPs, often gathered from untrusted third-party vendors, severely affects the security and trustworthiness of the final system. The hardware IPs acquired from external sources may come with deliberate malicious implants, undocumented interfaces working as hidden backdoor, or other integrity issues. Tampered hardware IPs can lead to security and privacy concerns (e.g., when used in handheld devices) as well as life-threatening consequences (e.g., when used in safety-critical systems). It is extremely difficult to verify the integrity and trustworthiness of hardware IPs due to incomplete functional specifications and lack of golden reference models. To address this critical need, in this project, we develop a comprehensive and scalable framework for IP trust analysis and verification. We evaluate IPs of diverse types and forms and develop threat models, taxonomy and instances of IP trust/integrity issues. We investigate an integrative IP trust validation framework that combines the complementary abilities of functional, structural and parametric verification. We employ both statistical as well as judicious directed tests to sensitize rarely triggered malicious changes and observe their effects. The unified validation framework is flexible to detect diverse tampering efforts, scalable to large designs, and eliminates the need for a golden model. A platform for IP trust validation, threat analysis, and trust metrics would provide enabling technology to future designers to implement secure and trusted systems for diverse applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1441667</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prabhat</FirstName>
<LastName>Mishra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Prabhat Mishra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>prabhat@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522946658</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490446</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326116120</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[432 Newell Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8225</Code>
<Text>SaTC Special Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our daily life is intertwined in the fabric of Internet-of-Things (IoT), a fabric in which the number of connected smart computing devices exceeds the human population. Unlike microcontroller based designs in the past, even resource constrained IoT devices nowadays incorporate one or more complex System-on-Chip (SoC) designs. A typical SoC consists of processor, memory, network-on-chip, controllers, converters, input/output devices, etc. SoCs are designed today using hardware Intellectual Property (IP) blocks to reduce cost while meeting aggressive time-to-market constraints. Growing reliance on these pre-verified hardware IPs, often gathered from untrusted third-party vendors, severely affects the security and trustworthiness of SoC computing platforms. An important emerging concern with the hardware IPs acquired from external sources is that they may come with deliberate malicious implants to incorporate undesired functionality (e.g. hardware Trojan), undocumented test/debug interface working as hidden backdoor, or other integrity issues. Recent investigations as well as reported incidences show that such practices make SoCs increasingly vulnerable to trust issues and highlight the impending threat. Therefore, SoC vulnerabilities should be fixed before deployment since it affects the overall system security. Based on Common Vulnerability Exposure (CVE-MITRE) estimates, if hardware-level vulnerabilities are removed, the overall system vulnerability will reduce by 43%.</p> <p>It is extremely difficult to verify integrity and trust of hardware IPs of different types and complexity, due to (a) incomplete functional specifications, and (b) lack of a golden reference model. Even if a reference model is available from an IP vendor, its integrity remains questionable. To address this critical need, in this project, we explored a comprehensive and scalable framework for IP trust validation and verification. Specifically, this project developed automated tools and techniques to perform comprehensive analysis of trust and integrity issues in hardware IPs in order to drastically reduce the overall IP trust validation effort. We have evaluated IPs of diverse types and forms and developed threat models, taxonomy and instances of IP trust and integrity issues as well as benchmarks. We have developed an IP trust validation framework that combines the complementary abilities of simulation based validation, formal verification and side-channel analysis. We employed both statistical as well as directed tests to sensitize arbitrary rarely triggered malicious changes to detect hardware Trojans in a wide variety of IPs. Experimental results demonstrated that the fully automated framework can reduce the overall IP trust validation complexity by several orders of magnitude. Various semiconductor companies have utilized the tools and results from this project on their internal designs. This research has led to two books, eight book chapters, seven journal articles, and fourteen premier international conference publications (including one nomination for the best paper award), as well as several conference tutorials, panels and special sessions on SoC security and IP trust validation.</p> <p>This research project has been the training ground for four Ph.D. students (including one female), one of them is working as a technical lead in VMware and another one has recently joined as a tenure-track Assistant Professor at the University of Florida. This project also supported six minority undergraduate researchers (including one women) through NSF-sponsored Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program. The PI has been successful in involving both graduate and undergraduate students in this research project through introduction of a lecture module on SoC security in several existing courses (embedded systems, computer organization, and computer architecture). Due to the interdisciplinary nature of these courses, this project was able to attract students from various engineering disciplines. The IP trust validation framework developed in this project is publically available, and it has been downloaded by many research groups. Finally, the developed platform of IP trust validation, threat analysis, benchmarks and trust metrics would provide enabling technology to SoC designers to implement secure and trusted SoCs for diverse IoT applications.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2018<br>      Modified by: Prabhat&nbsp;Mishra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our daily life is intertwined in the fabric of Internet-of-Things (IoT), a fabric in which the number of connected smart computing devices exceeds the human population. Unlike microcontroller based designs in the past, even resource constrained IoT devices nowadays incorporate one or more complex System-on-Chip (SoC) designs. A typical SoC consists of processor, memory, network-on-chip, controllers, converters, input/output devices, etc. SoCs are designed today using hardware Intellectual Property (IP) blocks to reduce cost while meeting aggressive time-to-market constraints. Growing reliance on these pre-verified hardware IPs, often gathered from untrusted third-party vendors, severely affects the security and trustworthiness of SoC computing platforms. An important emerging concern with the hardware IPs acquired from external sources is that they may come with deliberate malicious implants to incorporate undesired functionality (e.g. hardware Trojan), undocumented test/debug interface working as hidden backdoor, or other integrity issues. Recent investigations as well as reported incidences show that such practices make SoCs increasingly vulnerable to trust issues and highlight the impending threat. Therefore, SoC vulnerabilities should be fixed before deployment since it affects the overall system security. Based on Common Vulnerability Exposure (CVE-MITRE) estimates, if hardware-level vulnerabilities are removed, the overall system vulnerability will reduce by 43%.  It is extremely difficult to verify integrity and trust of hardware IPs of different types and complexity, due to (a) incomplete functional specifications, and (b) lack of a golden reference model. Even if a reference model is available from an IP vendor, its integrity remains questionable. To address this critical need, in this project, we explored a comprehensive and scalable framework for IP trust validation and verification. Specifically, this project developed automated tools and techniques to perform comprehensive analysis of trust and integrity issues in hardware IPs in order to drastically reduce the overall IP trust validation effort. We have evaluated IPs of diverse types and forms and developed threat models, taxonomy and instances of IP trust and integrity issues as well as benchmarks. We have developed an IP trust validation framework that combines the complementary abilities of simulation based validation, formal verification and side-channel analysis. We employed both statistical as well as directed tests to sensitize arbitrary rarely triggered malicious changes to detect hardware Trojans in a wide variety of IPs. Experimental results demonstrated that the fully automated framework can reduce the overall IP trust validation complexity by several orders of magnitude. Various semiconductor companies have utilized the tools and results from this project on their internal designs. This research has led to two books, eight book chapters, seven journal articles, and fourteen premier international conference publications (including one nomination for the best paper award), as well as several conference tutorials, panels and special sessions on SoC security and IP trust validation.  This research project has been the training ground for four Ph.D. students (including one female), one of them is working as a technical lead in VMware and another one has recently joined as a tenure-track Assistant Professor at the University of Florida. This project also supported six minority undergraduate researchers (including one women) through NSF-sponsored Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program. The PI has been successful in involving both graduate and undergraduate students in this research project through introduction of a lecture module on SoC security in several existing courses (embedded systems, computer organization, and computer architecture). Due to the interdisciplinary nature of these courses, this project was able to attract students from various engineering disciplines. The IP trust validation framework developed in this project is publically available, and it has been downloaded by many research groups. Finally, the developed platform of IP trust validation, threat analysis, benchmarks and trust metrics would provide enabling technology to SoC designers to implement secure and trusted SoCs for diverse IoT applications.       Last Modified: 12/18/2018       Submitted by: Prabhat Mishra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
