<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dimensions US-BIOTA-Sao Paulo: Collaborative Research: Integrating Dimensions of Microbial Biodiversity across Land Use Change in Tropical Forests.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>483077.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>483077</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Tropical forests are the largest reservoirs of biodiversity on Earth and are under great threat due to deforestation. This project addresses the critically important question of how microbial biodiversity responds to and recovers from deforestation. Microorganisms are regarded as drivers of ecosystem processes and have not been characterized as extensively as plants and animals. The US-Brazil research team will focus on the potent green house gas methane and identify the producers and consumers along gradients of land use in the Amazon rainforest. The educational efforts for this project will build relationships between K-12 students in Brazil and US for biological conservation through live video conferences for training of undergraduate students and research mentoring of graduate students and postdoctoral associates. The microbial studies have important conservation and technological implications for forest management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Direct and real time measurements of the methane gas in the soil-atmosphere interface will be combined with a targeted high throughput nucleic acid sequencing of microbes involved in the cycling of methane to assess their genetic, phylogenetic, and functional dimensions in two different regions of the Amazon rainforest. This work will result in the most extensive survey to date of the microbial diversity of any tropical ecosystem, the most comprehensive study of microbial responses to land use change ever documented, and the development of a novel approach for the integration of microbial biodiversity, allowing for accurate prediction of the effects of deforestation on the methane cycle.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1442214</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodrigues</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jorge Rodrigues</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmrodrigues@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5303414355</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000079927</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956168627</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7968</Code>
<Text>Dimensions of Biodiversity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7968</Code>
<Text>Dimensions of Biodiversity</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~483077</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aimed to generate an integrated understanding of how taxonomic, genetic, and functional dimensions of methane-cycling microorganisms respond to forest-to-agriculture conversion in the Amazon rainforest. Measurements of methane emissions from soils under different land uses at two geographically distinct locations were used to identify methane producers (methanogens) and consumers (methanotrophs) and identify community attributes that control the flux of this greenhouse gas in tropical systems. Results from this project revealed that pastures emit high levels of methane, while forests often act as methane sinks. Three microbial community traits were identified as important to the understanding of methane fluxes: abundance, composition, and overall diversity. With forest conversion to pastures, our results showed that the abundance and activity of methanogens was significantly higher in pastures in comparison to primary and secondary forests. Furthermore, results from this project suggested that the conversion of pastures to secondary forests decreased the activity of methanogens, with measurable decreases in methane emissions. These findings are critical to inform land management practices and tropical rainforest conservation to offset gas emissions in the tropics, identified as responsible for the largest variance in global models.</p> <p>During the duration of this project, training and professional development was provided to two American female PhD students, one American male student, five postdoctoral researchers, eight undergraduates. Five Brazilian PhD students, paid with resources from the Brazilian government, were trained in American Universities and interacted with American students. In addition, educational training was provided to 100 graduate students from around the world, including 12 US students, during the international workshop on methane science organized by our team. A total of 59 oral presentations were given to scientists and general public during the duration of this project and approximately 100,000 people per year visited the exhibit on the tropical rainforest biome in the Biophere 2 unit at University of Arizona. A total of 11 scientific publications were reported for this project.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Jorge&nbsp;Rodrigues</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1442214/1442214_10341298_1609267672716_IMG_1630--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1442214/1442214_10341298_1609267672716_IMG_1630--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Amazon River"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1442214/1442214_10341298_1609267672716_IMG_1630--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Amazon River"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Amazon Rainforest during the rainy season</div> <div class="imageCredit">Klaus Nusslein</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jorge&nbsp;Rodrigues</div> <div class="imageTitle">Amazon River</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aimed to generate an integrated understanding of how taxonomic, genetic, and functional dimensions of methane-cycling microorganisms respond to forest-to-agriculture conversion in the Amazon rainforest. Measurements of methane emissions from soils under different land uses at two geographically distinct locations were used to identify methane producers (methanogens) and consumers (methanotrophs) and identify community attributes that control the flux of this greenhouse gas in tropical systems. Results from this project revealed that pastures emit high levels of methane, while forests often act as methane sinks. Three microbial community traits were identified as important to the understanding of methane fluxes: abundance, composition, and overall diversity. With forest conversion to pastures, our results showed that the abundance and activity of methanogens was significantly higher in pastures in comparison to primary and secondary forests. Furthermore, results from this project suggested that the conversion of pastures to secondary forests decreased the activity of methanogens, with measurable decreases in methane emissions. These findings are critical to inform land management practices and tropical rainforest conservation to offset gas emissions in the tropics, identified as responsible for the largest variance in global models.  During the duration of this project, training and professional development was provided to two American female PhD students, one American male student, five postdoctoral researchers, eight undergraduates. Five Brazilian PhD students, paid with resources from the Brazilian government, were trained in American Universities and interacted with American students. In addition, educational training was provided to 100 graduate students from around the world, including 12 US students, during the international workshop on methane science organized by our team. A total of 59 oral presentations were given to scientists and general public during the duration of this project and approximately 100,000 people per year visited the exhibit on the tropical rainforest biome in the Biophere 2 unit at University of Arizona. A total of 11 scientific publications were reported for this project.       Last Modified: 12/29/2020       Submitted by: Jorge Rodrigues]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
