<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EARS: Collaborative Research: Laying the Foundations of Social Network-Aware Cellular Device-to-Device Communications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>227500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>227500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Providing ubiquitous access to the rapidly expanding suite of mobile social applications has strained modern-day wireless networks, motivating the need for new technologies to optimize the usage of the scarce radio resources. Device-to-device (D2D) communications between mobile devices over the reliable and pervasive cellular network infrastructure constitutes one of the most promising technologies for further accelerating the penetration of mobile social services. As compared to conventional D2D over short-range and limited-capacity technologies such as Bluetooth, D2D over cellular provides longer transmission ranges, improved spectrum sharing, higher capacities, guaranteed quality-of-service, and a broader range of applications and services. Owing to its promising potential, D2D is now viewed by both academia and standardization bodies as a cornerstone technology in emerging 5th generation (5G) wireless systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Leveraging cellular D2D for mobile social applications requires addressing a variety of technical challenges that are characterized by a strong interplay between social factors such as content correlation, and wireless features such as network-controlled resource allocation and interference management. This project addresses these challenges by introducing a novel network optimization framework, cognizant of both social and wireless realms, suitable for ensuring the delivery of high-speed, high-quality social networking services over cellular D2D communications. Specifically, new D2D-oriented socio-technological metrics and novel semi-distributed resource allocation and content delivery algorithms will be developed to optimize the quality-of-service of social network-aware D2D systems. In addition, hierarchical resource allocation tools will be introduced to optimize the distribution of social content over D2D while maximizing the spread of data over multiple D2D connections. The results will be evaluated and deployed on two platforms: a large-scale testbed based on open-source Android devices for validating the approach and exploring new social metrics, and a software defined radio platform to analyze the performance of the proposed schemes within a realistic cellular setting.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1443905</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>My</FirstName>
<LastName>Thai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>My T Thai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mythai@cise.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523283000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000391957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~227500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Device-to-device (D2D) communications between mobile devices over the reliable and pervasive cellular network infrastructure constitutes one of the most promising technologies for further accelerating the penetration of mobile social services. As compared to conventional D2D over short-range technologies, D2D over cellular provides longer transmission ranges, improved spectrum sharing, higher capacities, guaranteed quality-of-service, and a broader range of applications and services. Owing to its promising potential, D2D is now viewed by both academia and standardization bodies as a cornerstone technology in emerging 5G wireless systems.</p> <p>Leveraging cellular D2D for mobile social applications requires addressing a variety of technical challenges that are characterized by a strong interplay between social factors such as content correlation, and wireless features such as network-controlled resource allocation and interference management. This project addresses these challenges by introducing a novel network optimization framework, cognizant of both social and wireless realms, suitable for ensuring the delivery of high-speed, high-quality social networking services over cellular D2D communications. Specifically, new D2D-oriented socio-technological metrics and novel semi-distributed resource allocation and content delivery algorithms will be developed to optimize the quality-of-service of social network-aware D2D systems. In addition, hierarchical resource allocation tools will be introduced to optimize the distribution of social content over D2D while maximizing the spread of data over multiple D2D connections.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merits.</strong></p> <p>During the course of this project, several major findings and solutions have been developed and published in 22 journal articles and 15 conferences papers. The transformative contributions of the project at the University of Florida are as follows.</p> <p>1) Social Network Analysis: There are two notable contributions. First, the concept of durable social community, to enhance the way in which multihop D2D communications operate was introduced. &nbsp;This was one of the first efforts towards characterizing such communities while combining both social community detection and wireless cellular networking concepts. Approximation algorithms were developed to detect such community. Second, we investigated how information diffuse in social networks, which helps understand the behavior of content delivery and caching. Several optimization models and approximation were developed.</p> <p>2) Dynamic Resource Allocation:&nbsp; We studied the problem of efficiently reusing resource blocks used in D2D communications, when devices enter or leave the network in an online manner. We developed the first adaptive solution framework to the dynamic resource allocation problem. The solution is taking advantages of the social behaviors of cellular devices as well as taking interference into consideration.</p> <p>3) Efficient Content Delivery for Multicast Users via D2D. We investigated the multicast content delivery in D2D multihop scenario underlaying cellular communication. Our objective was to identify relay devices that incurs minimum BS cost while delivering the content to a set of devices seeking the same content via multihop D2D communication. We modeled this as a stochastic optimization problem and derived algorithms to identify such a set of devices. We showed the consideration of social connection helps achieve faster content delivery.&nbsp;</p> <p>4) Online Caching for D2D Networks of Heterogeneous Users: One method to improve the spectrum efficiency of a cellular network is by proactively caching popular content in the devices themselves and satisfying requests for the files using D2D transmission. However, the storage space available for caching on each device is small, and so consideration must be taken to what devices should cache what content. We developed a content placement algorithm in order to efficiently place a single file where the expected cache hit rate is above a threshold.</p> <p>5) Vulnerability and Security Analysis in D2D: We investigated this via 2 approaches: i) Monitor Placement and ii) Identify a set of critical nodes whose removal will cause the maximum Quality-of-Service degration (QoSD). We developed a new sampling potential cascade technique to detect the malware propagation in order to place&nbsp; monitors. A simulation of bluetooth based malware propagation among mobile devices with real human movement data showed that we only need to monitor a small portion of the network to get high detection rates. For QoSD, we have developed several approximation algorithms. The work also advanced the state-of-the art in continuous optimization domain.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;The project partially supported the 3 PIs and their teams, several of them have obtained their PhD degrees. At the University of Florida, 3 PhD students who have been being supported by this grant have graduated. The research topics and results have been presented at many invited talks and conferences. Several results of this project have been integrated into the teaching curriculum. At the University of Florida, PI Thai introduced a new undergrad/grad course on "Advances in Social Networks", in Fall 2015 that integrates social, optimization, and its applications in wireless networks domain into the class. PI Thai also introduced a new undergrad/grad course on "Internet of Things&rdquo;, in Fall 2016 that integrates social, optimization, and its applications in wireless networks domain focusing next generation devices into the class.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2020<br>      Modified by: My&nbsp;T&nbsp;Thai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Device-to-device (D2D) communications between mobile devices over the reliable and pervasive cellular network infrastructure constitutes one of the most promising technologies for further accelerating the penetration of mobile social services. As compared to conventional D2D over short-range technologies, D2D over cellular provides longer transmission ranges, improved spectrum sharing, higher capacities, guaranteed quality-of-service, and a broader range of applications and services. Owing to its promising potential, D2D is now viewed by both academia and standardization bodies as a cornerstone technology in emerging 5G wireless systems.  Leveraging cellular D2D for mobile social applications requires addressing a variety of technical challenges that are characterized by a strong interplay between social factors such as content correlation, and wireless features such as network-controlled resource allocation and interference management. This project addresses these challenges by introducing a novel network optimization framework, cognizant of both social and wireless realms, suitable for ensuring the delivery of high-speed, high-quality social networking services over cellular D2D communications. Specifically, new D2D-oriented socio-technological metrics and novel semi-distributed resource allocation and content delivery algorithms will be developed to optimize the quality-of-service of social network-aware D2D systems. In addition, hierarchical resource allocation tools will be introduced to optimize the distribution of social content over D2D while maximizing the spread of data over multiple D2D connections.  Intellectual Merits.  During the course of this project, several major findings and solutions have been developed and published in 22 journal articles and 15 conferences papers. The transformative contributions of the project at the University of Florida are as follows.  1) Social Network Analysis: There are two notable contributions. First, the concept of durable social community, to enhance the way in which multihop D2D communications operate was introduced.  This was one of the first efforts towards characterizing such communities while combining both social community detection and wireless cellular networking concepts. Approximation algorithms were developed to detect such community. Second, we investigated how information diffuse in social networks, which helps understand the behavior of content delivery and caching. Several optimization models and approximation were developed.  2) Dynamic Resource Allocation:  We studied the problem of efficiently reusing resource blocks used in D2D communications, when devices enter or leave the network in an online manner. We developed the first adaptive solution framework to the dynamic resource allocation problem. The solution is taking advantages of the social behaviors of cellular devices as well as taking interference into consideration.  3) Efficient Content Delivery for Multicast Users via D2D. We investigated the multicast content delivery in D2D multihop scenario underlaying cellular communication. Our objective was to identify relay devices that incurs minimum BS cost while delivering the content to a set of devices seeking the same content via multihop D2D communication. We modeled this as a stochastic optimization problem and derived algorithms to identify such a set of devices. We showed the consideration of social connection helps achieve faster content delivery.   4) Online Caching for D2D Networks of Heterogeneous Users: One method to improve the spectrum efficiency of a cellular network is by proactively caching popular content in the devices themselves and satisfying requests for the files using D2D transmission. However, the storage space available for caching on each device is small, and so consideration must be taken to what devices should cache what content. We developed a content placement algorithm in order to efficiently place a single file where the expected cache hit rate is above a threshold.  5) Vulnerability and Security Analysis in D2D: We investigated this via 2 approaches: i) Monitor Placement and ii) Identify a set of critical nodes whose removal will cause the maximum Quality-of-Service degration (QoSD). We developed a new sampling potential cascade technique to detect the malware propagation in order to place  monitors. A simulation of bluetooth based malware propagation among mobile devices with real human movement data showed that we only need to monitor a small portion of the network to get high detection rates. For QoSD, we have developed several approximation algorithms. The work also advanced the state-of-the art in continuous optimization domain.  Broader Impact   The project partially supported the 3 PIs and their teams, several of them have obtained their PhD degrees. At the University of Florida, 3 PhD students who have been being supported by this grant have graduated. The research topics and results have been presented at many invited talks and conferences. Several results of this project have been integrated into the teaching curriculum. At the University of Florida, PI Thai introduced a new undergrad/grad course on "Advances in Social Networks", in Fall 2015 that integrates social, optimization, and its applications in wireless networks domain into the class. PI Thai also introduced a new undergrad/grad course on "Internet of Things", in Fall 2016 that integrates social, optimization, and its applications in wireless networks domain focusing next generation devices into the class.             Last Modified: 03/03/2020       Submitted by: My T Thai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
