<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Virtualized Wireless Networks and Their Impact on Capacity Markets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199524.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199524</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project develops a new vision for wireless networks, predicated on the creation of service-driven virtual networks constructed from a pool for resources that belong to a variety of stakeholders. The resources include spectrum, physical infrastructure, and control and management support, and the stakeholders include traditional mobile operators, operators of WiFi access networks, businesses and households that support wireless connectivity through small cell deployment, traffic aggregators (such as Mobile Virtual Network Operators [MVNOs]), and regulators. The resulting architecture separates the consumer-facing service provision from the technologies used to construct the network, enabling the disintermediation of current wireless service provision systems. Moving the point at which network access transactions take place up the value chain (or the protocol stack) means that a greater range of service types can be provided to consumers without requiring large up-front capital investments on the part of the (consumer-facing) service providers. This will have profound impact on both industry and society, affecting the way that these networks are designed and built, spectrum and infrastructure resources are managed, and pricing structures for services provided over the network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project first defines a new architecture that enables the virtualization of a wireless network over a combination of spectrum licensed under different regimes and infrastructure with different ownership. Relying on game theoretic and market models of virtual network construction, new resource management mechanisms are designed to select the appropriate set of resources to build a virtual wireless network with given coverage and capacity requirements. Combinatorial auctions for multiple objects are practical mechanisms for the dynamic allocation and aggregation of resources for such a virtualized wireless network. In analyzing the impact of the proposed architecture on spectrum markets, a key question is whether the incorporation of a virtualized spectrum commodity influences the viability of these markets (as measured by the liquidity outcome), and how this compares to previous scenarios in which the traded commodity was the physical spectrum resource or 'naked spectrum;. Finally, this project explores how markets in virtual wireless capacity would work when implemented in current wireless networks, in the context of LTE-Advanced and expected 5G developments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1443796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Weiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin B Weiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbw@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126247400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000520499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132302</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199524</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>It is obvious that wireless systems have become a critical element in the modern economy.&nbsp; Traditionally, the provision of wireless services has been tightly integrated with the hardware and software of the system provider.&nbsp; This includes cell sites, radio transmitters, system controllers, switches, etc. &nbsp; This tight connection has served to foster a system that is generally dependable and meets user needs.&nbsp; However, as user's needs change, and as these needs become more diverse, this tight connection between infrastructure and service provision can become a liability.</p> <p>Following the innovations in the computer industry, this project explored the<em> virtualization</em> of wireless resources.&nbsp; In a virtualized system, service providers (who are customer facing) effectively lease capability from resource providers (who own and operate the wireless infrastructure).&nbsp; This enables service providers to meet users' changing and diversifying needs in innovative ways. &nbsp;</p> <p>But implementing such a virtualized infrastructure is challenging.&nbsp; How do service providers acquire the resources they need to provide services?&nbsp; How do resource providers operate their infrastructure effectively (essentially subdividing their resources, such as base stations)?&nbsp; These are the essential questions that this project studied.</p> <p>To study this, we proposed an intermediary, a "Virtual Network Builder" that would link the requirements of service providers with the wireless infrastructure of resource providers.&nbsp; We showed that, using the economic theory of matching markets, that virtualized networks using this architecture could be built.&nbsp; At the same time, we modelled resource providers and showed that they could "slice" (subdivide) their resources (such as base stations, controllers, switches) to meet the totality of the demand that their infrastructure was facing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;B&nbsp;Weiss</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ It is obvious that wireless systems have become a critical element in the modern economy.  Traditionally, the provision of wireless services has been tightly integrated with the hardware and software of the system provider.  This includes cell sites, radio transmitters, system controllers, switches, etc.   This tight connection has served to foster a system that is generally dependable and meets user needs.  However, as user's needs change, and as these needs become more diverse, this tight connection between infrastructure and service provision can become a liability.  Following the innovations in the computer industry, this project explored the virtualization of wireless resources.  In a virtualized system, service providers (who are customer facing) effectively lease capability from resource providers (who own and operate the wireless infrastructure).  This enables service providers to meet users' changing and diversifying needs in innovative ways.    But implementing such a virtualized infrastructure is challenging.  How do service providers acquire the resources they need to provide services?  How do resource providers operate their infrastructure effectively (essentially subdividing their resources, such as base stations)?  These are the essential questions that this project studied.  To study this, we proposed an intermediary, a "Virtual Network Builder" that would link the requirements of service providers with the wireless infrastructure of resource providers.  We showed that, using the economic theory of matching markets, that virtualized networks using this architecture could be built.  At the same time, we modelled resource providers and showed that they could "slice" (subdivide) their resources (such as base stations, controllers, switches) to meet the totality of the demand that their infrastructure was facing.       Last Modified: 05/28/2019       Submitted by: Martin B Weiss]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
