<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EARS: Directional Spectrum Sensing and Communications Utilizing Beam- and Frequency-Agile Parasitic Antenna Arrays</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jenshan Lin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract Title: Directional Spectrum Sensing and Communications Utilizing Beam- and Frequency-Agile Parasitic Antenna Arrays&lt;br/&gt;This multidisciplinary research will address some of the major challenges in enabling the next generation of spectrum efficient and energy efficient wireless communication systems for a wide range of applications, including personal communications, emergency-response, and cyber-physical systems (e.g., intelligent transportation systems and the smart-grid), by developing collaboration between two fields of signal processing and communication theory and antenna design.The  principal investigators (PIs) will develop a novel beam- and frequency-agile antenna and new signal processing and communication techniques that take full advantage of the antenna capabilities, in order to enable directional spectrum sensing and communications for portable lightweight terminals and provide significant spectral efficiency gains. This research has multifaceted benefits in advancing the field, and in education and diversity (i) It will make a significant impact on the theory and practice of the evolving cognitive radio networks and technologies, for a variety of applications that benefit society. (ii) It will provide a unique opportunity to bond the two research groups supervised by the PIs and enhance research and education through this partnership. The PIs will train graduate and undergraduate students and will actively engage in the stimulation and development of the field. The undergraduate students will gain experience with research in an interesting area. (iii) It will increase the participation of under-represented students in the  PIs? research groups. The PIs will use the resources available through the UCF Summer mentoring fellowship program, which provides financial support for the minority students who are interested in conducting research with a faculty mentor. (iv) It will integrate research and education through incorporation of the research results into the Electrical and Computer Engineering graduate curriculum. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research thrusts are: (i) Design of a low-cost beam- and frequency-agile antenna, using an Electrically Steerable Parasitic Array Radiator (ESPAR) approach: These ESPAR antenna arrays require minimum number of phase shifters by parasitically coupling antenna elements. Continuous beam (main lobe and null) as well as frequency scanning can be realized simultaneously within the antenna structure. The ESPAR antenna arrays will be used for both directional spectrum sensing and communications. (ii) Model-based signal processing for directional spectrum sensing utilizing the ESPAR antennas: The PIs will develop a signal model for the ESPAR antennas. Based on this signal model, energy and eigenvalue-based detectors will be developed, which do not require any prior information about the signal of primary users (PUs) to be detected.  The energy detector, although simple, requires knowledge of the receiver noise level. On the other hand, the eigenvalue-based detectors do not require this information and hence are insensitive to uncertainties in receiver noise level. Comparing detection performance of eigenvalue-based detectors against that of energy detectors for omnidirectional antennas unveils the improvement in spectrum sensing accuracy provided by the ESPAR antennas.  (iii) Directional communications utilizing the ESPAR antennas: For a system where a pair of secondary users (SUs) wishes to communicate in the presence of primary user( PU) activities, and based on the developed signal model, several constrained communication optimization problems will be formulated, which aim to optimize a physical layer performance metric, subject to interference level constraint, in order to find the best steering angles for SU transmitter and receiver. (iv) Testbed: a low-cost yet flexible test platform will be developed to verify the directional spectrum sensing and communication schemes with the ESPAR antennas. This platform is able to adapt to different frequencies, bandwidths, modulation schemes, and antenna structures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1443942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Azadeh</FirstName>
<LastName>Vosoughi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Azadeh Vosoughi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>azadeh@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078820137</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000325185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xun</FirstName>
<LastName>Gong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xun Gong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xun.gong@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078235762</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000227961</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328162362</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096E</Code>
<Text>High freq comm/sensing circuits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The intellectual merit of the beam- and frequency-agile parasitic antenna arrays is that the design of such antenna arrays facilitates a new class of low-cost antenna arrays for spectrum sensing and sharing applications. Electronically-Steerable Parasitic Array Radiator (ESPAR) antenna is able to achieve beamsteering without using phase shifters or significantly reducing the number of expensive phase shifters. By incorporating frequency reconfigurablity into ESPAR antennas, a second degree of freedom in the frequency domain is added on top of the spatial diversity inherent in ESPAR antennas. Therefore, spectrum utilization can be further enhanced by fully exploiting the diversity in both frequency and spatial domains. In this project, we have developed a novel beam- and frequency-agile antenna as well as new signal processing and communication techniques that take full advantage of the antenna capabilities, in order to enable directional spectrum sensing and communications for portable lightweight terminals and provide significant spectral efficiency gains. The key outcomes of this project follow.</p> <p>1) We have developed such ESPAR antennas, based on microstrip antenna and substrate integrated waveguide (SIW) cavity-backed slot antenna, and showed that the developed antennas realize the aforementioned diversity in both frequency and spatial domains.</p> <p>2) Using a signal model for these ESPAR antennas, and assuming that the spectrum sensing module employs a non-coherent receiver (i.e., a prior knowledge of the primary user signal characteristics is not required), we have developed signal processing algorithms for optimal and near-optimal detection of the activities of primary users, and analyzed the attainable spectrum sensing accuracy of these detection algorithms.</p> <p>3) We have studied the achievable information rate that a secondary user can transmit over wireless fading channels, subject to average transmit and interference power constraints. We have explored how the spectrum sensing inaccuracy and imperfect channel state information (CSI) can affect the achievable information rate. &nbsp;We have obtained the optimal transmit power such that the constrained achievable information rate is maximized. We have also considered how training overhead (in terms of training time and training power) for enabling channel estimation at the receiver can affect the achievable information rate. &nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impact of this research is that beam- and frequency-agile parasitic antenna arrays can significantly enhance the capability of next-generation wireless communication systems, particularly in a crowded spectrum environment. With such ESPAR antennas, radios can efficiently utilize the electromagnetic spectrum by leveraging on the diversity provided in both frequency and spatial domains. Furthermore, this research has broader impacts on the antenna technology as well as advancing the knowledge on the fundamental performance limits of cognitive radio systems that employ such ESPAR antennas (from communication theory, information theory, and statistical signal processing perspectives).</p> <p>We have disseminated our key findings and generated knowledge to research communities of interest (in antenna area as well as signal processing and communication areas), via publishing in highly reputable peer-reviewed journals and refereed international conference proceedings. The antenna design methodology developed for the ESPAR antennas in this project can also be adopted for antenna array designs for other applications, such wireless sensor networks, 5G communications, and satellite communications.</p> <p>The knowledge gained in this research has been incorporated into existing courses at UCF. Two Ph.D. students, who were mentored by Dr. Gong and had worked on this project, have graduated and joined the workforce in U.S. wireless industry. Several undergraduate students have been advised by Dr. Gong to develop a radar for imaging applications. One Ph.D. student, who is mentored by Dr. Vosoughi and has worked on this project, is on his path to earn his Ph.D. degree in December 2020. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Azadeh&nbsp;Vosoughi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit of the beam- and frequency-agile parasitic antenna arrays is that the design of such antenna arrays facilitates a new class of low-cost antenna arrays for spectrum sensing and sharing applications. Electronically-Steerable Parasitic Array Radiator (ESPAR) antenna is able to achieve beamsteering without using phase shifters or significantly reducing the number of expensive phase shifters. By incorporating frequency reconfigurablity into ESPAR antennas, a second degree of freedom in the frequency domain is added on top of the spatial diversity inherent in ESPAR antennas. Therefore, spectrum utilization can be further enhanced by fully exploiting the diversity in both frequency and spatial domains. In this project, we have developed a novel beam- and frequency-agile antenna as well as new signal processing and communication techniques that take full advantage of the antenna capabilities, in order to enable directional spectrum sensing and communications for portable lightweight terminals and provide significant spectral efficiency gains. The key outcomes of this project follow.  1) We have developed such ESPAR antennas, based on microstrip antenna and substrate integrated waveguide (SIW) cavity-backed slot antenna, and showed that the developed antennas realize the aforementioned diversity in both frequency and spatial domains.  2) Using a signal model for these ESPAR antennas, and assuming that the spectrum sensing module employs a non-coherent receiver (i.e., a prior knowledge of the primary user signal characteristics is not required), we have developed signal processing algorithms for optimal and near-optimal detection of the activities of primary users, and analyzed the attainable spectrum sensing accuracy of these detection algorithms.  3) We have studied the achievable information rate that a secondary user can transmit over wireless fading channels, subject to average transmit and interference power constraints. We have explored how the spectrum sensing inaccuracy and imperfect channel state information (CSI) can affect the achievable information rate.  We have obtained the optimal transmit power such that the constrained achievable information rate is maximized. We have also considered how training overhead (in terms of training time and training power) for enabling channel estimation at the receiver can affect the achievable information rate.    The broader impact of this research is that beam- and frequency-agile parasitic antenna arrays can significantly enhance the capability of next-generation wireless communication systems, particularly in a crowded spectrum environment. With such ESPAR antennas, radios can efficiently utilize the electromagnetic spectrum by leveraging on the diversity provided in both frequency and spatial domains. Furthermore, this research has broader impacts on the antenna technology as well as advancing the knowledge on the fundamental performance limits of cognitive radio systems that employ such ESPAR antennas (from communication theory, information theory, and statistical signal processing perspectives).  We have disseminated our key findings and generated knowledge to research communities of interest (in antenna area as well as signal processing and communication areas), via publishing in highly reputable peer-reviewed journals and refereed international conference proceedings. The antenna design methodology developed for the ESPAR antennas in this project can also be adopted for antenna array designs for other applications, such wireless sensor networks, 5G communications, and satellite communications.  The knowledge gained in this research has been incorporated into existing courses at UCF. Two Ph.D. students, who were mentored by Dr. Gong and had worked on this project, have graduated and joined the workforce in U.S. wireless industry. Several undergraduate students have been advised by Dr. Gong to develop a radar for imaging applications. One Ph.D. student, who is mentored by Dr. Vosoughi and has worked on this project, is on his path to earn his Ph.D. degree in December 2020.               Last Modified: 03/29/2020       Submitted by: Azadeh Vosoughi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
