<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Microheater-based Platform for Combustible Gas Sensing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating UC Berkeley?s low power microheater sensor platform to fill the need for low-power combustible gas sensors. Accurate detection of flammable gases is essential for safe operation of many industrial processes, especially in the oil and gas industry. Installing networks of combustible gas monitors in industrial settings can allow for rapid leak detection and increased safety and environmental protection.  The construction and inspection cost associated with installing wired gas monitors in a hazardous facility, such as a refinery, are prohibitive. Battery-powered wireless monitors would eliminate this installation burden, but the high power requirements for current combustible gas sensor technology necessitate a large, expensive, heavy battery or represent a major inconvenience to facility personnel who must replace the battery as often as every week. This project focuses on addressing the need for combustible gas sensors with significantly lower power consumption (at least 100x) than the best commercially available sensor, while maintaining performance parameters such as sensitivity and lifetime.  The proposed ultra-low power combustible gas sensor with competitive sensitivity and lifetime characteristics will enable ubiquitous wireless monitoring of combustible gases in industrial settings, resulting in enhanced safety. Furthermore, in the long-term, the technology may enable embedding gas sensors in smart phones, which will result in increased personal safety. Additional significant impact is on human resource development, in particular in the training of graduate and undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The core technology in this project is a suspended microheater coated with a sensing material that catalyzes hydrocarbon combustion.  These microheater sensors require only a few mW of power to reach operation temperatures of 500 °C.  However, several challenges remain in developing a commercial prototype for combustible gas sensing. These include stable adhesion of the sensing layer to the microheater, stability of materials and sensor response in appropriate atmospheric conditions, and reproducible catalyst deposition. This project addresses these technology gaps as it translates from discovery research toward commercial application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide core training for graduate and undergraduate students who will benefit from interdisciplinary training in surface chemistry, materials science, electrical engineering and market analysis. The students will gain experience not only in research but also in technical presentation through their participation in meetings with industry leaders. This will provide the students with a unique experience in the interconnectivity between research and development and technology and the marketplace.  In addition, the students will be able to take advantage of resources at the Haas School of Business at Berkeley (such as Launch: The Berkeley Start-Up Competition program) as well as the CleanTech Open Accelerator program to gain entrepreneurial/technology translation training.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1444950</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roya</FirstName>
<LastName>Maboudian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roya Maboudian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maboudia@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106437957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000229556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Mickelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Mickelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wmickelson@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106428109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/02/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201462</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Networks of combustible gas monitors installed in industrial settings can allow for rapid leak detection and thus increase personnel safety. Lowering the prohibitive costs associated with installing wired gas monitors in a hazardous facility was identified as a customer priority, and therefore as a business opportunity, by the proposing team. Battery-powered wireless monitors would circumvent this installation burden, if the power requirement of combustible gas sensors could be reduced by a factor of 100 with respect to current technology, while maintaining performance parameters such as sensitivity and lifetime.</p> <p class="Default">This project was able to break through the power consumption barrier by developing a suspended microheater platform, where the micro fabricated heating element is integrated with sensing materials that promote catalytic combustion of the gases to be detected.&nbsp; The combination of microheater and supported catalyst enabled low power combustible gas sensing. The technical breakthrough was made possible by the use of high specific surface area aerogels loaded with catalyst nanoparticles, which afforded an improved response and recovery time for both hydrogen and propane gas (1-2 s). The fast response of the microheater and the catalyst support means that pulsed heating can now be used to lower the power consumption to the single mW range without loss in sensitivity. A newly realized silicon carbide microheater platform allows for more stable sensing performance at operating temperatures of 500 &deg;C or more.</p> <p class="Body">The key outcomes of the research supported by this award, as well as detailed documentation of methods, procedures, and supporting experimental investigations, are described in the doctoral dissertations of two PhD candidates. Both are also co-inventors in a provisional patent filing that resulted from this research. Research results have been disseminated through the publication of several papers in high impact scientific journals, conference&nbsp; presentations, and lectures in academia, industry, and professional meetings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/20/2017<br>      Modified by: Roya&nbsp;Maboudian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Networks of combustible gas monitors installed in industrial settings can allow for rapid leak detection and thus increase personnel safety. Lowering the prohibitive costs associated with installing wired gas monitors in a hazardous facility was identified as a customer priority, and therefore as a business opportunity, by the proposing team. Battery-powered wireless monitors would circumvent this installation burden, if the power requirement of combustible gas sensors could be reduced by a factor of 100 with respect to current technology, while maintaining performance parameters such as sensitivity and lifetime. This project was able to break through the power consumption barrier by developing a suspended microheater platform, where the micro fabricated heating element is integrated with sensing materials that promote catalytic combustion of the gases to be detected.  The combination of microheater and supported catalyst enabled low power combustible gas sensing. The technical breakthrough was made possible by the use of high specific surface area aerogels loaded with catalyst nanoparticles, which afforded an improved response and recovery time for both hydrogen and propane gas (1-2 s). The fast response of the microheater and the catalyst support means that pulsed heating can now be used to lower the power consumption to the single mW range without loss in sensitivity. A newly realized silicon carbide microheater platform allows for more stable sensing performance at operating temperatures of 500 &deg;C or more. The key outcomes of the research supported by this award, as well as detailed documentation of methods, procedures, and supporting experimental investigations, are described in the doctoral dissertations of two PhD candidates. Both are also co-inventors in a provisional patent filing that resulted from this research. Research results have been disseminated through the publication of several papers in high impact scientific journals, conference  presentations, and lectures in academia, industry, and professional meetings.          Last Modified: 03/20/2017       Submitted by: Roya Maboudian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
