<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Miniaturization of Medical Oxygen Concentrators for Portable and Home Medical Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199930.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246355</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on development of a self-contained compact prototype Medical Oxygen Concentrator (MOC) for use in oxygen rehabilitation therapy for patients suffering from Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD), cystic fibrosis and other pulmonary diseases. The market for MOCs producing 1 to 8 liters/min of ~90 % oxygen from compressed ambient air is rapidly growing with an estimated global market in 2017 valued at ~$2 billion. The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that more than 80 million people worldwide have COPD and nearly 3 million deaths per year can be attributed to COPD. A more compact and light-weight MOC design with substantially higher oxygen recovery and longer battery run-time will provide greater mobility to COPD patients for exercise, improved cardiovascular health and quality of life. &lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to meet this critical objective through the development of a fully functional self-contained prototype based on a novel patented Medical Oxygen Concentrator (MOC) design. Our MOC design has the following advantages: (1) it uses a single adsorption column inside a storage tank, as opposed to conventional two-bed rapid pressure swing adsorption processes (RPSA), thereby reducing size; (2) it uses fast cycle times in the range of 3-6 seconds to continuously produce up to 3 liters/min of  ~90% oxygen from compressed air which is  3 times higher than the product delivery rate of commercial portable MOC units; (3) it uses less than one third of the adsorbent inventory for a given product flow rate; (4) it uses lesser number of switching valves and sensors and needs simpler process control for the single adsorption bed design due to the absence of synchronized operation of two or multi-column systems. (5) it provides more flexibility in selection and optimization of the individual step times of the RPSA process; (6) it allows continuous product withdrawal as opposed to pulsed product flow offered by many commercial portable units; (7) it is scalable in size and oxygen flow rates; (8) it can be used as a ?Snap On? device without a dedicated compressor in applications where a compressed air source is available, such as in hospitals (military or civil), cruise ships and airlines.&lt;br/&gt;Graduate and postdoctoral students will be trained on new concepts in technology transfer and business strategies beyond basic research. A master's student from the Technical Entrepreneurship program at Lehigh will benefit from incorporating our study in his/her capstone integrated business design project. Undergraduate Chemical Engineering seniors will conduct experiments that will integrate traditional chemical engineering principles across four years into a single comprehensive project as part of their Opportunities for Student Innovation course.  The project will lead to comprehensive prototype performance data for enabling either a new start-up company or for a licensing agreement with a MOC manufacturer for commercialization.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1444963</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mayuresh</FirstName>
<LastName>Kothare</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mayuresh V Kothare</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mayuresh.kothare@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107586654</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490759</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shivaji</FirstName>
<LastName>Sircar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shivaji Sircar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shs3@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107584469</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808264444</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068570936</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Alumni Building 27]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199930</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~46425</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Accelerating Innovation Research --&nbsp; Technology Translation project was aimed at development of a self-contained&nbsp; compact prototype Medical Oxygen Concentrator (MOC) for use in oxygen rehabilitation therapy for patients suffering from Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disorder (COPD), cystic fibrosis and other pulmonary diseases. The global market for MOCs producing high purity O2 (&gt;90% pure) from compressed ambient air was valued at ~ $2 billion in 2017 and&nbsp;  rapidly growing (~ 6 % /year).&nbsp; The currently preferred technology for a MOC is a cyclic rapid Pressure Swing Adsorption (RPSA) process using a nitrogen-selective LiX zeolite. The dominant research objectives are to lower the adsorbent inventory in the MOC unit in order to produce a compact, light-weight device and raise the O2 recovery of the process in order to<br />lower the air compressor power, thereby extending battery run-time.</p> <p>The<strong> intellectual merit</strong> of this project was the translation of a previous "proof-of-concept" bench-top MOC design to a fully functional self-contained prototype MOC that would move our patented design closer to market commercialization. A fully self-contained "bread-board" prototype has been designed, fabricated and tested. The design incorporates our proprietary single bed RPSA system with a concentric storage tank and integrates a bank of small sized compressors, switching valves, logic controllers, and flow manifolds.&nbsp; The device is capable of producing the target flow rate of 4.8 liters per minute of high purity (92%) oxygen from a compressed air line. The device was also run with the bank of small sized compressors that draw air from the ambient room condition and compress it to deliver to the adsorbent bed. The use of the compressors reduced the product flow rate to about 4 liters per minute at the same purity. The device operation was fully automated with an advanced model-based control algorithm that was implemented in a compact Raspberry Pi hardware platform.</p> <p>The demonstrated prototype was used as the basis to transfer our  technology to a start-up company -- Pharmateck LLC -- which was founded  as an offshoot of the Life Sciences Greenhouse holdings company, with  our oxygen concentration design as the first technology incorporated in  the company as a license.</p> <p>The broader impact of our technology, once commercialized and brought to market, would be greater mobility for COPD patients that would be enabled by our smaller, more compact and lightweight design with a longer single charge battery run time. This enhanced mobility would in turn impact their ability to conduct exercise and improve their cardiovascular health. Our project also resulted in a very broad and techno-economic training and education of two PhD students, one postdoctoral scholar, two undergraduate students and one Technical Entrepreneurship Master's student.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Mayuresh&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kothare</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035450839_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035450839_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="3D Schematic of 5 standard liters per minute  Lehigh Prototype Unit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035450839_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="3D Schematic of 5 standard liters per minute  Lehigh Prototype Unit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic showing proposed prototype oxygen concentrator</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lehigh University</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mayuresh&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kothare</div> <div class="imageTitle">3D Schematic of 5 standard liters per minute  Lehigh Prototype Unit</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035798320_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035798320_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental setup of oxygen concentrator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035798320_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental setup of oxygen concentrator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photograph of the 5 standard liters per minute Lehigh Prototype Experimental Setup (left) and accompanying air compressor assembly (right)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lehigh University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mayuresh&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kothare</div> <div class="imageTitle">Experimental setup of oxygen concentrator</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035972606_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035972606_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Embedded Controller Hardware Schematic:"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544035972606_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Embedded Controller Hardware Schematic:"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The embedded controller communicates with the RPSA device in three ways. Electrical relays impose the cycle step durations via the timing of the solenoid valves. Digital-to-Analog Converters (DAC) are used to transmit setpoints to the digital controllers,</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lehigh University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mayuresh&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kothare</div> <div class="imageTitle">Embedded Controller Hardware Schematic:</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544036143492_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544036143492_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Lab-Scale MOC Device with Embedded Controller"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544036143492_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Lab-Scale MOC Device with Embedded Controller"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The single-bed RPSA device uses a single adsorber column inserted concentrically into a product storage tank. Feed air is supplied from a compressed-air source, and high purity O2 product exits the storage tank.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lehigh University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mayuresh&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kothare</div> <div class="imageTitle">Lab-Scale MOC Device with Embedded Controller</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544036350266_Figure5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544036350266_Figure5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Components of the Embedded Controller"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1444963/1444963_10331847_1544036350266_Figure5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Components of the Embedded Controller"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Raspberry Pi 3 is connected to additional circuitry to operate the RPSA cycle and run the MPC algorithm. A board with electrical relays is used to open and close solenoid valves. Two data acquisition and control (DAQC) boards are used to collect measured data and send set point signals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lehigh University</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mayuresh&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kothare</div> <div class="imageTitle">Components of the Embedded Controller</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Accelerating Innovation Research --  Technology Translation project was aimed at development of a self-contained  compact prototype Medical Oxygen Concentrator (MOC) for use in oxygen rehabilitation therapy for patients suffering from Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disorder (COPD), cystic fibrosis and other pulmonary diseases. The global market for MOCs producing high purity O2 (&gt;90% pure) from compressed ambient air was valued at ~ $2 billion in 2017 and   rapidly growing (~ 6 % /year).  The currently preferred technology for a MOC is a cyclic rapid Pressure Swing Adsorption (RPSA) process using a nitrogen-selective LiX zeolite. The dominant research objectives are to lower the adsorbent inventory in the MOC unit in order to produce a compact, light-weight device and raise the O2 recovery of the process in order to lower the air compressor power, thereby extending battery run-time.  The intellectual merit of this project was the translation of a previous "proof-of-concept" bench-top MOC design to a fully functional self-contained prototype MOC that would move our patented design closer to market commercialization. A fully self-contained "bread-board" prototype has been designed, fabricated and tested. The design incorporates our proprietary single bed RPSA system with a concentric storage tank and integrates a bank of small sized compressors, switching valves, logic controllers, and flow manifolds.  The device is capable of producing the target flow rate of 4.8 liters per minute of high purity (92%) oxygen from a compressed air line. The device was also run with the bank of small sized compressors that draw air from the ambient room condition and compress it to deliver to the adsorbent bed. The use of the compressors reduced the product flow rate to about 4 liters per minute at the same purity. The device operation was fully automated with an advanced model-based control algorithm that was implemented in a compact Raspberry Pi hardware platform.  The demonstrated prototype was used as the basis to transfer our  technology to a start-up company -- Pharmateck LLC -- which was founded  as an offshoot of the Life Sciences Greenhouse holdings company, with  our oxygen concentration design as the first technology incorporated in  the company as a license.  The broader impact of our technology, once commercialized and brought to market, would be greater mobility for COPD patients that would be enabled by our smaller, more compact and lightweight design with a longer single charge battery run time. This enhanced mobility would in turn impact their ability to conduct exercise and improve their cardiovascular health. Our project also resulted in a very broad and techno-economic training and education of two PhD students, one postdoctoral scholar, two undergraduate students and one Technical Entrepreneurship Master's student.       Last Modified: 12/05/2018       Submitted by: Mayuresh V Kothare]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
