<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NuSTEC School on Neutrino Nucleus Scattering Physics at Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, IL, October 18 - 26, 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Shank</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshank@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the major intellectual achievements of the 20th century was the development of the Standard Model (SM) of particle physics. This model succeeded in classifying all of the elementary particles known at the time into a hierarchy of groups having similar quantum properties. The validity of this model to date was recently confirmed by the discovery of the Higgs boson at the Large Hadron Collider at CERN. However, the Standard Model as it currently exists leaves open many questions about the universe, including such fundamental questions as to why the Higgs mass has the value it has and why there is no antimatter in the universe. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the primary areas to search for answers to these and other open questions about the universe, how it came to be and why it is the way it is, is to focus on a study of the properties of neutrinos and to use what we know and can learn about neutrinos as probes of science beyond the Standard Model. Neutrinos are those elementary particles that interact with practically nothing else in the universe. They have no electric charge and were once thought to be massless. Like other elementary particles, they were believed to have an antimatter counterpart, the antineutrino. Moreover, the Standard Model predicted that there were actually three different kinds of neutrinos that were distinguishable through the different interactions that they did undergo whenever there was an interaction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will help fund the first Neutrino Scattering Theory Experiment Collaboration (NuSTEC) neutrino nucleus scattering school. The school will be held at Fermilab from October 18 to 26, 2014. NuSTEC is a collaboration of theorists and experimentalists working on neutrino nucleus scattering physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The aim of the school is to provide the necessary theoretical background on the physics of the electroweak interactions with nucleons and nuclei. The theoretical background is necessary for the preparation of the next generation neutrino physicists. An overarching goal of this school is the better understanding of neutrino&amp;#8722;nucleus interactions for more precise oscillation measurements, based on a complementary approach using experiments, theory and simulations. The target audience consists of graduate students and post-docs in both theoretical and experimental physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The goal of the NuSTEC collaboration is to train the next generation of neutrino physicists. Precise knowledge of neutrino interactions is an absolute necessity for future measurements of the masses and mixing-mediating neutrino oscillations. To enable precision measurements in neutrino physics, the next generation neutrino physics community needs to understand and model in detail the underlying physics of the neutrino weak interaction within a nuclear environment. Thoroughness is required so that we can reliably apply the relevant model calculations across the wide energy ranges and varying nuclei necessary for our precision neutrino investigations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1444969</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Camillo</FirstName>
<LastName>Mariani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Camillo Mariani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>camillo@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402314449</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000626883</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240611039</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[850 West Campus Drv]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1232</Code>
<Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1285</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The first NUSTEC International Training on Neutrino Nucleus Interactions hosted by the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory and Virginia Tech took place at Fermilab National Laboratory, Batavia IL, from October 20th to October 30th, 2014 (actual dates for the lectures were 21-29 October).</p> <p><span style="font-family: Book Antiqua;">The recently formed NuSTEC (Neutrino Theory-Experiment Collaboration) is  organizing this training.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Book Antiqua;">The training program is based on the concept of total immersion in the topic at  hand and relies on experts in the field who are willing to lecture and follow up  by interacting informally with the students. The program included 33 hours of  lectures and 12 hours of recitation in the evenings, encouraging questions and  discussion on all of the day's lectures. The aim of the program is to provide the  necessary theoretical background on the physics of electroweak interactions with  nucleons and nuclei. It should allow the participants to understand recent  developments and to contribute to this field, which has become very important  for the future of neutrino physics. </span></p> <p>As the world's neutrino oscillation experiments ramp up the number of  neutrinos in their beams and build more sensitive detectors, scientists  will be able to collect more and more precise data, reducing   statistical errors. Understanding how neutrinos interact with the nuclei  in the detector material will help further reduce errors and lead to  neutrino oscillation measurements of unprecedented precision.</p> <p>More than 79 students from 12 different countries partecipated in the school. Many of the students educated in this school will continue on to be part of the next generation of neutrino scince.</p> <p>The lectures of the school were digitally recorded and have been permanently archieved at <a title="http://nustec2014.phys.vt.edu/" href="http://nustec2014.phys.vt.edu/" target="_blank">http://nustec2014.phys.vt.edu/</a> and they are freely available.</p> <p><span style="font-family: Book Antiqua;">&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/09/2015<br>      Modified by: Camillo&nbsp;Mariani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1444969/1444969_10312405_1436464185966_nustec-14-0247-01D--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1444969/1444969_10312405_1436464185966_nustec-14-0247-01D--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NUSTEC school group photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1444969/1444969_10312405_1436464185966_nustec-14-0247-01D--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NUSTEC school group photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">At the recent NuSTEC training at Fermilab, graduate students learn all about the subtleties of neutrino-nucleus interactions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fermilab - Reidar Hahn</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Camillo&nbsp;Mariani</div> <div class="imageTitle">NUSTEC school group photo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The first NUSTEC International Training on Neutrino Nucleus Interactions hosted by the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory and Virginia Tech took place at Fermilab National Laboratory, Batavia IL, from October 20th to October 30th, 2014 (actual dates for the lectures were 21-29 October).  The recently formed NuSTEC (Neutrino Theory-Experiment Collaboration) is  organizing this training.  The training program is based on the concept of total immersion in the topic at  hand and relies on experts in the field who are willing to lecture and follow up  by interacting informally with the students. The program included 33 hours of  lectures and 12 hours of recitation in the evenings, encouraging questions and  discussion on all of the day's lectures. The aim of the program is to provide the  necessary theoretical background on the physics of electroweak interactions with  nucleons and nuclei. It should allow the participants to understand recent  developments and to contribute to this field, which has become very important  for the future of neutrino physics.   As the world's neutrino oscillation experiments ramp up the number of  neutrinos in their beams and build more sensitive detectors, scientists  will be able to collect more and more precise data, reducing   statistical errors. Understanding how neutrinos interact with the nuclei  in the detector material will help further reduce errors and lead to  neutrino oscillation measurements of unprecedented precision.  More than 79 students from 12 different countries partecipated in the school. Many of the students educated in this school will continue on to be part of the next generation of neutrino scince.  The lectures of the school were digitally recorded and have been permanently archieved at http://nustec2014.phys.vt.edu/ and they are freely available.          Last Modified: 07/09/2015       Submitted by: Camillo Mariani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
