<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  High Efficient Grid-Tie Inverter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A grid-tie inverter is a critical need to guarantee the integration of residential solar systems with the public utility grid.  Installers and designers of solar systems for residential and commercial buildings are the main potential customers of the proposed grid-tie inverter. The capacity range required for installed photovoltaic (PV) systems ranges from hundreds of watts for typical residential rooftop customers to hundreds of kilowatts for commercial rooftop customers.  Currently, the majority of customers that utilize PV systems face two major challenges: cost and limited surface area available to install the panels. It is expected that the proposed grid-tie inverter, with better efficiency, translates to an installer being able to use fewer solar panels to obtain the same amount of electrical power. Conversely it could be stated that it is possible to generate more power from the same number of solar panels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project transforms a state-of-the-art power electronics technology developed in the PI's laboratory into a commercially viable grid-tie inverter. The compelling value proposition is higher efficiency, reduced semi-conducting components and implementation of active functions.  The proposed grid-tie inverter has a potential impact on ways in which next-generation of grid- tie inverters can be developed. By increasing the efficiency of solar energy conversion through the proposed grid-tie inverters this product will likely impact: (a) security - reduced energy consumption would help decrease demand for foreign sources of fuel, (b) environment - more efficient energy conversion stages will conserve energy and reduce greenhouse gas production, and (c) economy - increased efficiency equates to reduced material and installation costs as well as resale of surplus energy back to the utility grid. An energy conversion unit (grid-tie inverter) able to reduce a fractional amount of loss interfacing solar panels and the utility grid will save millions of dollars in wasted spending across the U.S. every year.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1444834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Euzeli</FirstName>
<LastName>dos Santos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Euzeli C dos Santos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eudossan@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3179196459</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University Purdue Univerity Indianapolis]]></Name>
<CityName>Indianapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>462022915</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[980 Indiana Ave.  RM 2232]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes from the customer discovery through the I-Corp program was instrumental in transforming the laboratory prototype into a minimum viable product (MVP). Such a MVP solves a specific problem faced by the installers of photovoltaic solar systems, i.e., it guarantees installation simplicity, which saves labor time and reduce installation costs. The MVP was designed and built in the power electronics laboratory at Indiana University &ndash; Purdue University Indianapolis and it has the following competitive advantages: 1) easier and faster installation, 2) higher efficiency, and 3) monitoring system with no extra hardware.</p> <p>The project outcomes that address the intellectual merit are associated to the creation of a new solar microinverter device that connects a solar panel to the grid with higher efficiency and a unique triangular shape, as presented in Figure 1. While the higher efficiency allows generation of more electricity by using the same number of solar panels, its unique shape allows the installer an ultra-fast installation reducing critical aspect of a photovoltaic solar system, i.e., the installation time. &nbsp;</p> <p>The initial assumption was that a device with higher efficiency would be well accepted by the photovoltaic solar system installers. However, during the customer discovery process the team realized that this is not a &ldquo;pain&rdquo; for the customers. After 122 interviews it was evident that a device with higher efficiency would be a plus for the customers, but not something that could differentiate this product from other ones in the market. A new value proposition has been considered, i.e., a device that would allow faster installation due to the reduced number of fasteners. The proposed microinverter presents a triangular shape with single screw attachment. A company has been incorporated (Delta Microinverter LLC &ndash; <a href="http://www.dinverter.com/">www.dinverter.com</a>) to commercialize the proposed microinverter.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Euzeli&nbsp;C&nbsp;Dos Santos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1444834/1444834_10310489_1420210674534_20140919_105301--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1444834/1444834_10310489_1420210674534_20140919_105301--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1444834/1444834_10310489_1420210674534_20140919_105301--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Triangular shape of the proposed solar microinverter.</div> <div class="imageCredit">.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Euzeli&nbsp;C&nbsp;Dos Santos</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes from the customer discovery through the I-Corp program was instrumental in transforming the laboratory prototype into a minimum viable product (MVP). Such a MVP solves a specific problem faced by the installers of photovoltaic solar systems, i.e., it guarantees installation simplicity, which saves labor time and reduce installation costs. The MVP was designed and built in the power electronics laboratory at Indiana University &ndash; Purdue University Indianapolis and it has the following competitive advantages: 1) easier and faster installation, 2) higher efficiency, and 3) monitoring system with no extra hardware.  The project outcomes that address the intellectual merit are associated to the creation of a new solar microinverter device that connects a solar panel to the grid with higher efficiency and a unique triangular shape, as presented in Figure 1. While the higher efficiency allows generation of more electricity by using the same number of solar panels, its unique shape allows the installer an ultra-fast installation reducing critical aspect of a photovoltaic solar system, i.e., the installation time.    The initial assumption was that a device with higher efficiency would be well accepted by the photovoltaic solar system installers. However, during the customer discovery process the team realized that this is not a "pain" for the customers. After 122 interviews it was evident that a device with higher efficiency would be a plus for the customers, but not something that could differentiate this product from other ones in the market. A new value proposition has been considered, i.e., a device that would allow faster installation due to the reduced number of fasteners. The proposed microinverter presents a triangular shape with single screw attachment. A company has been incorporated (Delta Microinverter LLC &ndash; www.dinverter.com) to commercialize the proposed microinverter.                   Last Modified: 09/01/2015       Submitted by: Euzeli C Dos Santos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
