<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Amplified Bioelectronic Sensor for Neurotoxic Esterase Inhibitors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199060.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>268943</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating research on nanoscale bioelectronics to fill the need for cost-effective biosensor systems that quickly, sensitively, and accurately measure concentrations of important compounds. The amplified bioelectronic sensor platform being developed is important because it offers an unprecedented combination of performance properties, versatility, and customizability. By varying the architecture and recognition molecules in the sensing interface, a broad range of commercially important biosensor systems could be developed for applications including screening for therapeutic agents, measurement of toxins and pathogens in food and environmental samples, point-of-care testing of biological samples, and real-time, on-site detection of chemical warfare agents for military and homeland-security applications. The project will result in prototype amplified bioelectronic sensors suitable for three types of commercial biosensor systems: portable point-of-care meters, electrochemical multiwell plates, and flow-injection analyzers. This patented bioelectronic sensor platform has the following features: (1) multiple signal-amplification mechanisms, (2) multiple types of biological recognition molecules, (3) compatibility with multiple commercial biosensor systems, and (4) disposable sensing units. These features provide the following advantages: enhanced sensitivity, versatility, user-friendliness, convenience, and cost-effectiveness when compared to the leading competing biosensor technologies in this market space.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gaps as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application. Commercial biosensors are needed to measure organophosphate (OP) compounds that target the human enzyme neuropathy target esterase (NTE) and lead to catastrophic neurological disorders. Such biosensors would need to measure NTE activity rapidly and sensitively. The patented amplified bioelectronic sensor achieves this goal by using a reaction pathway to convert NTE?s esterase activity into an electronic signal and using a redox cycle to amplify the signal. However, technology gaps must be addressed to adapt the bioelectronic sensor interface to widely used commercial biosensor systems and to extend the underlying molecular sensing mechanisms to a wide range of other important compounds. These technology gaps will be addressed by (1) exploiting an enzyme-antibody linkage that translates antibody-antigen binding events into a chemical reaction flux, (2) integrating a redox cycle that converts the chemical reaction flux into an electric current and simultaneously amplifies the current, and (3) incorporating conductive nanomaterials that massively increase the sensor?s signal. In addition, personnel involved in this project, including a Ph.D. student and undergraduates, will receive innovation and technology-translation experiences through participation in virtually all aspects of the research, including entrepreneurial/innovation discussions and activities. The PI will also provide training in entrepreneurship/innovation to students taking the Multidisciplinary Bioprocessing Laboratory (MBL) course he developed with NSF funding. The MBL course incorporates research into education and teaches students from multiple departments to work effectively in multidisciplinary research teams. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project engages Conductive Technologies, Inc., a leader in developing and manufacturing electrochemical devices for sensing commercially important analytes, to support the research effort by providing technical expertise in designing and developing electrochemical platforms as well as providing samples of printed electrodes to demonstrate biosensor performance. The project also engages MSU Technologies, the intellectual-property unit of Michigan State University, to help guide commercialization aspects in this technology translation effort from research discovery toward commercial reality.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1444991</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Worden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert M Worden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>worden@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173539015</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000346492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Satoh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>s</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul s Satoh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>satoh@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173551855</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000327128</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241226</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[428 S. Shaw Lane, Room 2263]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199060</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~57883</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of this project<strong> </strong>was to translate previous NSF-funded research that resulted in a patented enzyme-based electrochemical biosensor technology into market-valued biosensor systems. The original technology provided a rapid and sensitive method to detect dangerous chemical agents that interfere with the human nervous system. The approach involved immobilizing an enzyme from the human nervous system into an electrochemical biosensor. This enzyme?s activity integrated of a chemical reaction pathway that generated an electric current and included a redox-cycling loop that amplified the current. If a neurotoxic chemical agent (e.g., a nerve gas) were introduced, the biosensor?s electrical output signal would drop substantially within a few seconds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, the advantages of the original electrochemical biosensor (high sensitivity and a quantitative electrical output) were combined with the advantages of commercial antibody-based assays (extremely high selectivity) to give a hybrid Enzyme Electrochemical Immunoassay Biosensors (EEIB). Because antibodies are commercially available for a wide range of chemical and biological agents, EEIB could be developed for many commercial applications.&nbsp; In addition, well-established methods for miniaturizing and mass-producing electrochemical biosensors (e.g., glucose biosensors for diabetics) suggest that EEIB could be mass-produced as inexpensive, disposable biosensors that could be used virtually anywhere.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The technical merit of this project included development of new technical approaches to fabricate and optimize EEIB, including methods to integrate antibodies into the electrochemical biosensor reaction pathway. To improve the long-term stability of the EEIB, one of enzymes responsible for the generating the biosensor?s electrical output, tyrosinase, was replaced with a more stable enzyme, horseradish peroxidase (HRP). In addition, to reduce the complexity of the chemical pathway that generates the biosensor?s electrical current, the pathway was reduced from three reactions catalyzed by two enzymes to one reaction catalyzed by one enzyme (HRP).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Methods were developed to bind antibodies for the agent to be detected onto a miniature electrode, and then achieve binding of HRP-labelled secondary antibodies to the electrode in the presence of the agent.&nbsp; We also adapted our EEIB assembly methods to commercially available screen-printed-electrode (SPE) arrays. Using these approaches, we were able to manufacture miniature SPE electrode arrays that combined the advantages of antibody-based detection systems with those of enzyme-based electrochemical biosensors. Using the EEIB, we were able to detect a mouse protein with a lower detection limit of 1 ng/mL in a liquid sample.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The technical merit of the project also included development of two types of mathematical models that were used to predict and optimize the EEIB?s performance. Mechanistic models were developed by deriving and solving a set of differential equations that described the rates of molecular transport processes and chemical reactions responsible for generating the biosensor?s electric current. Statistical models were also used to plan experiments and analyze the resulting data. The program Minitab was used to design a set of experiments to evaluate the effects of four key independent variables (concentrations of two reactants, pH, and electrode voltage) on the dependent variables (biosensor current and signal-to-noise ratio in the presence of the target agent). Minitab?s analysis of the experimental results yielded a statistical model that calculated the strength with which independent variable affected the biosensor?s current and identified the combination of the four independent variables that optimized the current.&nbsp; Results of the mechanistic and statistical models were then compared.&nbsp; The mechanistic models? predictions of how key independent variables influenced the biosensor?s current agreed with predictions of the statistical models. This result is significant, because the validated mechanistic models provide powerful tools for <em>in-silico</em> design of EEIB that exhibit a desired set of operating properties.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project had a broader impact via providing educational opportunities. Two female PhD students in chemical engineering were trained in this project. Also, two female undergraduate students who were trained in this project as Research Experience for Undergraduates participants were admitted into PhD programs at highly-ranked universities. The commercialization focus of this project resulted in its being assigned a team of three graduate students as part of MSU?s Spartan Innovations Fellows Program. These students assessed the project?s commercialization potential. In addition, three biomedical engineering Ph.D. students were assigned to assess health-related commercialization opportunities of EEIB technologies. The project also had a broader impact via intellectual property development. A patent application describing a novel biosensor developed as part of this project is pending.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;M&nbsp;Worden</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this project was to translate previous NSF-funded research that resulted in a patented enzyme-based electrochemical biosensor technology into market-valued biosensor systems. The original technology provided a rapid and sensitive method to detect dangerous chemical agents that interfere with the human nervous system. The approach involved immobilizing an enzyme from the human nervous system into an electrochemical biosensor. This enzyme?s activity integrated of a chemical reaction pathway that generated an electric current and included a redox-cycling loop that amplified the current. If a neurotoxic chemical agent (e.g., a nerve gas) were introduced, the biosensor?s electrical output signal would drop substantially within a few seconds.     In this project, the advantages of the original electrochemical biosensor (high sensitivity and a quantitative electrical output) were combined with the advantages of commercial antibody-based assays (extremely high selectivity) to give a hybrid Enzyme Electrochemical Immunoassay Biosensors (EEIB). Because antibodies are commercially available for a wide range of chemical and biological agents, EEIB could be developed for many commercial applications.  In addition, well-established methods for miniaturizing and mass-producing electrochemical biosensors (e.g., glucose biosensors for diabetics) suggest that EEIB could be mass-produced as inexpensive, disposable biosensors that could be used virtually anywhere.      The technical merit of this project included development of new technical approaches to fabricate and optimize EEIB, including methods to integrate antibodies into the electrochemical biosensor reaction pathway. To improve the long-term stability of the EEIB, one of enzymes responsible for the generating the biosensor?s electrical output, tyrosinase, was replaced with a more stable enzyme, horseradish peroxidase (HRP). In addition, to reduce the complexity of the chemical pathway that generates the biosensor?s electrical current, the pathway was reduced from three reactions catalyzed by two enzymes to one reaction catalyzed by one enzyme (HRP).     Methods were developed to bind antibodies for the agent to be detected onto a miniature electrode, and then achieve binding of HRP-labelled secondary antibodies to the electrode in the presence of the agent.  We also adapted our EEIB assembly methods to commercially available screen-printed-electrode (SPE) arrays. Using these approaches, we were able to manufacture miniature SPE electrode arrays that combined the advantages of antibody-based detection systems with those of enzyme-based electrochemical biosensors. Using the EEIB, we were able to detect a mouse protein with a lower detection limit of 1 ng/mL in a liquid sample.      The technical merit of the project also included development of two types of mathematical models that were used to predict and optimize the EEIB?s performance. Mechanistic models were developed by deriving and solving a set of differential equations that described the rates of molecular transport processes and chemical reactions responsible for generating the biosensor?s electric current. Statistical models were also used to plan experiments and analyze the resulting data. The program Minitab was used to design a set of experiments to evaluate the effects of four key independent variables (concentrations of two reactants, pH, and electrode voltage) on the dependent variables (biosensor current and signal-to-noise ratio in the presence of the target agent). Minitab?s analysis of the experimental results yielded a statistical model that calculated the strength with which independent variable affected the biosensor?s current and identified the combination of the four independent variables that optimized the current.  Results of the mechanistic and statistical models were then compared.  The mechanistic models? predictions of how key independent variables influenced the biosensor?s current agreed with predictions of the statistical models. This result is significant, because the validated mechanistic models provide powerful tools for in-silico design of EEIB that exhibit a desired set of operating properties.         This project had a broader impact via providing educational opportunities. Two female PhD students in chemical engineering were trained in this project. Also, two female undergraduate students who were trained in this project as Research Experience for Undergraduates participants were admitted into PhD programs at highly-ranked universities. The commercialization focus of this project resulted in its being assigned a team of three graduate students as part of MSU?s Spartan Innovations Fellows Program. These students assessed the project?s commercialization potential. In addition, three biomedical engineering Ph.D. students were assigned to assess health-related commercialization opportunities of EEIB technologies. The project also had a broader impact via intellectual property development. A patent application describing a novel biosensor developed as part of this project is pending.        Last Modified: 07/03/2019       Submitted by: Robert M Worden]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
