<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EARS: Enhanced Spectrum Availability and MU-MIMO Coordination for High Spatial-Spectral Efficiency</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>597125.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>597125</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Astounding spectral efficiencies exceeding 40 bits per second per Hertz have already been achieved in multi-user MIMO systems. Unfortunately, the coordination needed to facilitate transmissions in space, frequency, and time can severely limit efficiency. Moreover, many spectral bands are today deemed unavailable even if no active receiver is nearby and hence resources cannot be used at all.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project fuses three integrated thrusts towards achieving high spectral-spatial efficiency (bits per second per Hertz per square meter) with high spectrum availability (permission to transmit in a particular band at a particular location). First, this project enables a new mode of spectrum availability by exploiting smart primary receivers.  The key idea is that a typical primary spectrum transmitter such as a TV broadcaster does not have active receivers in all locations.  This thrust realizes an architecture and algorithms for smart primary receivers to inform a controller of their usage, creating vast new dynamically available spatial-spectral resources. Second, this project overcomes fundamental limits in the coordination that is today required for spectrum access. This thrust considers channel sounding and user-state coordination to be a foundational resource of system design that must itself be allocated. An integrated suite of new methods for coordination limited MU-MIMO protocols is developed. The final thrust provides an implementation and measurement study. This thrust yields the first demonstration of spectrum access enhanced by smart primary users and the first multi-user MIMO diverse spectrum system enhanced by coordination limited protocol mechanisms. The platform targets "at scale" experiments via use of maximally amplified signals and real-word scenarios spanning from tower-to-user to indoor WLAN.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1444056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Knightly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward W Knightly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>knightly@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7135275748</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179561</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lin Zhong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lin.zhong@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034369450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000189041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 Main St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~597125</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project advances the concepts of MU-MIMO by demonstrating the successful operation of our protocol on custom MIMO SDR front-end platforms. Specifically, we explore the regimes in which our opportunistic channel sounding protocol pushes the performance gains of MU-MIMO closer to those predicted by prior theoretical works. Our platform also enabled the first characterization of mobile multi-user channels in UHF bands.</p> <p>The project has resulted in the design and fabrication of a custom MIMO SDR front-end for the WARPv3 SDR platform and a novel framework to enable experiments in the UHF bands. This platform enables the first characterization of mobile multi-user UHF channels, enabling evaluation of opportunistic sounding even in the presence of STA or environmental mobility. The design simplifies high-power UHF-band 8x8 MIMO experiments and improves synchronous clocking over previous SDR testbeds. We obtained experimental radio licenses WH2XJV and WJ9XFF to operate our experimental equipment on UHF channels in Houston, TX and performed a series of indoor and outdoor measurement campaigns in various mobility scenarios to analyze MU-MIMO beamforming capacity with respect to CSIT overhead.</p> <p>The project has also produced a multiuser UHF MU-MIMO, the first system to achieve UHF band full-rank uplink multi-user capacity in a fully distributed and scalable manner without a control channel. The project&rsquo;s multiuser, multi-antenna transmission scheme is for UHF, a portion of the radio spectrum that is traditionally reserved for television broadcasts. Based on over-the-air experiments in a range of indoor and outdoor operating environments, the team found that UHF-band multiuser MIMO compared favorably and produced high spectral efficiency as well as low-overhead wireless access.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Edward&nbsp;W&nbsp;Knightly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project advances the concepts of MU-MIMO by demonstrating the successful operation of our protocol on custom MIMO SDR front-end platforms. Specifically, we explore the regimes in which our opportunistic channel sounding protocol pushes the performance gains of MU-MIMO closer to those predicted by prior theoretical works. Our platform also enabled the first characterization of mobile multi-user channels in UHF bands.  The project has resulted in the design and fabrication of a custom MIMO SDR front-end for the WARPv3 SDR platform and a novel framework to enable experiments in the UHF bands. This platform enables the first characterization of mobile multi-user UHF channels, enabling evaluation of opportunistic sounding even in the presence of STA or environmental mobility. The design simplifies high-power UHF-band 8x8 MIMO experiments and improves synchronous clocking over previous SDR testbeds. We obtained experimental radio licenses WH2XJV and WJ9XFF to operate our experimental equipment on UHF channels in Houston, TX and performed a series of indoor and outdoor measurement campaigns in various mobility scenarios to analyze MU-MIMO beamforming capacity with respect to CSIT overhead.  The project has also produced a multiuser UHF MU-MIMO, the first system to achieve UHF band full-rank uplink multi-user capacity in a fully distributed and scalable manner without a control channel. The project?s multiuser, multi-antenna transmission scheme is for UHF, a portion of the radio spectrum that is traditionally reserved for television broadcasts. Based on over-the-air experiments in a range of indoor and outdoor operating environments, the team found that UHF-band multiuser MIMO compared favorably and produced high spectral efficiency as well as low-overhead wireless access.       Last Modified: 09/29/2017       Submitted by: Edward W Knightly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
