<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Proposal for Organizing the 21st GENI Engineering Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports hosting the four day 21th edition of the GENI Engineering conference, including organizing and hosting the demo session, to be held October 20 to 23, 2014 at the Indiana University (IU) in Bloomington, Indiana.   The Global Environment for Network Innovations (GENI) is a virtual instrument that is rapidly emerging in prototype form across the United States. GENI is an instrument designed to address three issues: &lt;br/&gt;1) Science Issues: We cannot currently understand or predict the behavior of complex,large-scale networks. &lt;br/&gt;2) Society Issues: We increasingly rely on the Internet but are unsure we can trust its security, privacy or resilience. &lt;br/&gt;3) Innovation Issues: Pre-GENI substantial barriers existed to at-scale experimentation with new architectures, services, and technologies. &lt;br/&gt;GENI addresses these issues via scale (from federation) and support for two kinds of experiments: 1) controlled and repeatable experiments, which will greatly help improve our scientific understanding of complex, large-scale networks; and 2) in-the- wild trials of experimental services that ride atop or connect to today's Internet and that engage large numbers of human participants.  The GEC meeting and Demo sessions provide graduate students with both an opportunity to demonstrate and explain their work to the GENI community prior to formal publication. It is a key part of helping new graduate students understand what is being done with GENI and who amongst their peers at other institutions might be valuable resources. It also supports outreach to new community members, including the emerging US Ignite community. GENI is already being used as an instrument for research. This project supports the development and use of the research instrument.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The four-day conference will be held at the Indiana Memorial Union (IMU) Biddle Hotel and Conference Center at the heart of the Bloomington campus. The demo night event will be held at the Cyberinfrastructure Building (CIB), located in IU's growing tech park at the edge of campus. Event planning and logistical support for the event will be coordinated by the IT Communications Office's events team, which has extensive experience in conference planning and access to executive and internal technical support. The IT Communications Office is part of University Information Technology Services (UITS), which maintains a modern IT environment throughout the university in support of research, teaching, outreach, and lifelong learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1445643</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon-Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Herron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon-Paul Herron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpherron@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128560419</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474082761</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2709 East 10th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023F</Code>
<Text>GENI PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~49999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">GENI GEC 21 Project Outcome Report</span></strong></p> <p><em>Prepared by the host Indiana University Global Research NOC</em>&nbsp;</p> <p>Indiana University (IU) hosted the 21st GENI Engineering Conference (GEC 21) from October 20 to 23, 2014 bringing together users, developers, and operators of GENI (Global Environment for Network Innovations).&nbsp; The four-day conference helped further GENI&rsquo;s mission by promoting innovations in network science, security, services and applications.</p> <p>GEC 21&rsquo;s agenda covered a diverse number of topics and activities.&nbsp; These included:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>For those new to GENI, they were provided with a detailed overview of the project and introductions to GENI network architecture and OpenFlow, which enables researchers to run experimental protocols to determine the path of network packets through the network of switches. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>Updates on current engineering activities with GENI racks and resources at campuses, regional and national/international networks.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>A presentation and live demonstration of the GENI Meta Operations Center, which is provided locally by the Indiana University Global Research Network Operations Center (GlobalNOC).</li> </ul> <ul> <li>A tutorial on the GENI desktop, which showed how to configure and schedule active measurements and how to view them.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>How to use the LabWiki tool to plan, prepare and execute experiments in GENI testbeds</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Tutorials and presentations on future internet architectures such as XIA, ChoiceNet, MobilityFirst, and NDN.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>An exciting evening demo session at the Indiana University Cyberinfrastructure Building with over 30 demonstrations on infrastructure and measurement, experiments and education, intelligent Software Defined Networking (SDN) traffic aggregation, federation and international projects, and wireless.</li> </ul> <p>In summary, GEC 21 achieved its goal of allowing participants to engage in range of activities designed to increase their understanding and expertise on obtaining and connecting compute resources, utilizing customer software and operating systems, controlling how network switches handle experimental traffic flows, and running their own network protocols.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2015<br>      Modified by: Jon-Paul&nbsp;Herron</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ GENI GEC 21 Project Outcome Report  Prepared by the host Indiana University Global Research NOC   Indiana University (IU) hosted the 21st GENI Engineering Conference (GEC 21) from October 20 to 23, 2014 bringing together users, developers, and operators of GENI (Global Environment for Network Innovations).  The four-day conference helped further GENIÆs mission by promoting innovations in network science, security, services and applications.  GEC 21Æs agenda covered a diverse number of topics and activities.  These included:   For those new to GENI, they were provided with a detailed overview of the project and introductions to GENI network architecture and OpenFlow, which enables researchers to run experimental protocols to determine the path of network packets through the network of switches.    Updates on current engineering activities with GENI racks and resources at campuses, regional and national/international networks.   A presentation and live demonstration of the GENI Meta Operations Center, which is provided locally by the Indiana University Global Research Network Operations Center (GlobalNOC).   A tutorial on the GENI desktop, which showed how to configure and schedule active measurements and how to view them.   How to use the LabWiki tool to plan, prepare and execute experiments in GENI testbeds   Tutorials and presentations on future internet architectures such as XIA, ChoiceNet, MobilityFirst, and NDN.   An exciting evening demo session at the Indiana University Cyberinfrastructure Building with over 30 demonstrations on infrastructure and measurement, experiments and education, intelligent Software Defined Networking (SDN) traffic aggregation, federation and international projects, and wireless.   In summary, GEC 21 achieved its goal of allowing participants to engage in range of activities designed to increase their understanding and expertise on obtaining and connecting compute resources, utilizing customer software and operating systems, controlling how network switches handle experimental traffic flows, and running their own network protocols.       Last Modified: 08/24/2015       Submitted by: Jon-Paul Herron]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
