<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A DataViz Hackathon for Polar CyberInfrastructure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mstiegli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924354</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This workshop will focus on the bridging of the cyberinfrastructure/data visualization and polar communities and it is scheduled to be held in New York City at the Parsons New School for Design in November 2014. Improving the use and the value of existing data sets over the polar regions is crucial to promote science and support new discoveries. Ultimately, collaborations between data visualization experts and polar scientists will foster the understanding of the variability of the polar regions at different timescales, with implicit benefit for the society. &lt;br/&gt;The participants will be motivated by several public Polar datasets that will be acquired and made available before the starting date of the workshop. One of the expected outcomes is to produce high impact and novel prototypes and data visualizations that will be made available under open source licenses. Releasing the prototypes will allow the NSF to make longer-term investments in technologies and visualizations that can be adopted by the community. The workshop will also increase cross agency collaboration between NSF, NASA, NOAA and other Arctic/Polar related agencies.&lt;br/&gt;The organizing committee is composed by both cyberinfrastructure and polar experts, including participation from academia, industry, the federally funded research and development centers, and from the broader open source community. The workshop will: (1) recommend several sets of open source software for data and metadata processing; scientific workflow management; data curation; and data dissemination; (2) identify some relevant Polar data visualization techniques and assess the needs and challenges of visualizing Polar datasets; (3) package, deliver, and make available the outcomes of the workshop via a public website; and (4) provide input to the NSF Polar CyberInfrastructure program officer through a final report.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1445624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Mattmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chris A Mattmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mattmann@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8183548810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5407</Code>
<Text>Polar Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~49997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 5"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>H</span><span>ACKATHON BACKGOUND<br /> </span><span>Science data sets concerning the Polar regions are currently underutilized relative to their potential value - </span></p> <p><span>these data relate to U.S. and international maritime, oil and natural resources, and climate oriented concerns. It is exceedingly di</span><span>ffi</span><span>cult to ask concise and scienti</span><span>fi</span><span>c questions of this information since doing so involves a combination of high powered data processing; information retrieval, big data, and data visualization tech- nologies to be orchestrated together and combined for many diverse end users. Improving the use and&nbsp;value of existing polar region data sets is crucial to understanding the polar regions variability over di</span><span>ff</span><span>erent timescales, with consequent associated bene</span><span>fi</span><span>ts for society. One of the critical </span><span>fi</span><span>rst steps towards realising such improvements involves fostering e</span><span>ff</span><span>ective collaborations, communications and meetings between those community experts in data visualization; big data processing, information retrieval, and polar scientists. </span></p> <p><span>The U.S. National Science Foundation &ldquo;DataViz Hackathon for Polar CyberInfrastructure&rdquo; was designed to both bridge the cyberinfrastructure data visualization and polar science communities through informal collaboration,and to notably improve the use and value of polar region data sets through the adaptation of visualization tools for polar data.&nbsp;</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 5"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>H</span><span>ACKATHON IMPLEMENTATION<br /> </span><span>Forty polar scientists, data engineers, and design scholars, from a diverse set of institutions (see </span><span>fi</span><span>gure 1) gathered in New York in November for 2 days. Recognising the need for design expertise in visualisation problems it was hosted at The Parsons Institute for Information Mapping, personnel from here provided invaluable input from a third community not traditionally engaged by either polar science or cyber-infrastructure. Following introductory remarks and goalsetting by both the polar and cyberinfrastructure communities, lightning talks by session leaders served to guide participants into self forming hack sub- groups.Following a pattern of discuss-hack-review-repeat, over the course of 4 half-day hack sessions in total, these groups practically tackled the issues and goals set forth. These sessions resulted in 42 commits to a communal github account created for the event.&nbsp;</span></p> </div> </div> </div> <div class="page" title="Page 6"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>H</span><span>ACKATHON CONCLUSIONS AND RECCOMMENDATIONS<br /> </span><span>Overwhelmingly participants indicated they would be likely attend another similar event, valuing most highly the trans-disciplinary interactions and networking opportunities, and most commonly lamenting the limited time in which to accomplish ambitious goals. Based on this feedback, and the practical outcomes achieved (code commits,skill and knowledge transfers, and new collaborations) it is recommended other similar event be held, particularly for this conjunction of domains. </span></p> <p><span>Given the combined relative novelty of hosting a transdisciplinary, unconference, the organising committee learnt many practical lessons which should be of use to future event organisers. </span></p> <p><span>Based on the transdisciplinary nature of the event, it is recommend that a greater e</span><span>ff</span><span>ort be made, prior to the event or in introductions, to educate all participants as regards communicating with members of other domains and explain...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    HACKATHON BACKGOUND  Science data sets concerning the Polar regions are currently underutilized relative to their potential value -   these data relate to U.S. and international maritime, oil and natural resources, and climate oriented concerns. It is exceedingly difficult to ask concise and scientific questions of this information since doing so involves a combination of high powered data processing; information retrieval, big data, and data visualization tech- nologies to be orchestrated together and combined for many diverse end users. Improving the use and value of existing polar region data sets is crucial to understanding the polar regions variability over different timescales, with consequent associated benefits for society. One of the critical first steps towards realising such improvements involves fostering effective collaborations, communications and meetings between those community experts in data visualization; big data processing, information retrieval, and polar scientists.   The U.S. National Science Foundation "DataViz Hackathon for Polar CyberInfrastructure" was designed to both bridge the cyberinfrastructure data visualization and polar science communities through informal collaboration,and to notably improve the use and value of polar region data sets through the adaptation of visualization tools for polar data.      HACKATHON IMPLEMENTATION  Forty polar scientists, data engineers, and design scholars, from a diverse set of institutions (see figure 1) gathered in New York in November for 2 days. Recognising the need for design expertise in visualisation problems it was hosted at The Parsons Institute for Information Mapping, personnel from here provided invaluable input from a third community not traditionally engaged by either polar science or cyber-infrastructure. Following introductory remarks and goalsetting by both the polar and cyberinfrastructure communities, lightning talks by session leaders served to guide participants into self forming hack sub- groups.Following a pattern of discuss-hack-review-repeat, over the course of 4 half-day hack sessions in total, these groups practically tackled the issues and goals set forth. These sessions resulted in 42 commits to a communal github account created for the event.         HACKATHON CONCLUSIONS AND RECCOMMENDATIONS  Overwhelmingly participants indicated they would be likely attend another similar event, valuing most highly the trans-disciplinary interactions and networking opportunities, and most commonly lamenting the limited time in which to accomplish ambitious goals. Based on this feedback, and the practical outcomes achieved (code commits,skill and knowledge transfers, and new collaborations) it is recommended other similar event be held, particularly for this conjunction of domains.   Given the combined relative novelty of hosting a transdisciplinary, unconference, the organising committee learnt many practical lessons which should be of use to future event organisers.   Based on the transdisciplinary nature of the event, it is recommend that a greater effort be made, prior to the event or in introductions, to educate all participants as regards communicating with members of other domains and explaining some of the points of likely misunderstanding. For instance the science and engineering community here would have benefited from an overview of the nature of the design process, while the design and visualisation community would have found an explanation of the need for precision in science data helpful. In both cases such explanations would have reduced the time spent on unnecessary discussions.   In regards to the "unconference" nature of a hackathon, the use of a public hosting forums such as Github was highly successful in helping facilitate organisation prior to, during, and post the event, and it is therefore recommended. Participants also requested that future events be, longer (3 days at least), have more narrowly focused session goals, ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
