<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Understanding Climate Processes with Causal Discovery and Graphs of Information Flow in the Coupled Atmosphere-Land-Ocean System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>283062.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299062</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to develop graphical models of causal discovery and apply them to topics the field of climate dynamics.  In these models lagged correlations are used to identify pathways of causal influence among components of a coupled system, and the model is constructed by representing each component as one node of a directed graph.  Edges between node are assigned values representing the extent to which one component is predictable given prior knowledge of another.  A key issue in causal discovery is accounting for indirect effects, in which component A influences component B which in turn influences component C, as opposed to the case in which component A directly influences component C.  In graphical terms the distinction is whether or not an edge exists between A and C, or whether A's connection to C is only through B. This evaluation is done through a statistical calculation of conditional probabilities.   Previous work by the PIs applied causal discovery to identify relationships among four well-known teleconnection patterns, the Western Pacific and Eastern Pacific Oscillations (WPO and EPO), the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO), and the Pacific/North America (PNA) pattern.  In this case the method shows that the EPO can affect the NAO 18 days later, while the NAO can influence the PNA pattern three to six days later. Although the application to atmospheric science is novel, the method has been used successfully in other disciplines including economics, systems engineering, and bioinformatics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Work under the project will further develop the modeling technique, with a goal of increasing computational speed by a factor of 100 through improvements in parallelization and localization of memory access.  Visualization tools will also be developed to display results.  In addition to these development efforts, the PIs will apply the technique to address three topics in climate dynamics: the onset dynamics of the Asian summer monsoon, the subseasonal variation of the Northern Hemisphere annual mode (NAM), and changes in the characteristics of information flow in global warming simulations.  Work on monsoon onset will focus on three questions: What are the critical processes responsible for the establishment of the cross-equatorial flow? How important is the mechanical and thermal forcing associated with the Tibetan Plateau for the onset compared to local air-sea interaction in the Bay of Bengal and South China Sea? Is the onset a direct manifestation of atmospheric instability?  For subseasonal NAM variability, the research goal is to investigate the relative importance of tropospheric dynamics, stratosphere-troposphere coupling, and troposphere-surface coupling in determining the phase transition of the NAM.  The work on global warming is based on a preliminary analysis of one simulation in which information flows in the Northern midlatitudes become weaker as the climate warms, suggesting a reduction in atmospheric predictability in the tropics and mid-latitudes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The work has broader impacts through the introduction of a methodology developed in one scientific discipline (economics) into another (climate dynamics).  The PIs will promote the adoption of the modeling technique by making their algorithms and software available to the community of climate dynamics researchers through a web portal.  They will also offer tutorials at scientific conferences including the annual meetings of the American Meteorological Society and the American Geophysical Union.  Tutorial materials will also be made available online and through published papers.  In addition, the project will support and train a graduate students and a postdoctoral fellow, thereby providing for the future workforce in this research area.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1445978</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Imme</FirstName>
<LastName>Ebert-Uphoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Imme R Ebert-Uphoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>iebert@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9702373119</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652880</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805214593</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 W. Lake St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~299062</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p>This project focused on applying methods from causal discovery, i.e. methods to identify potential cause-effect relationships from data, to a variety of climate science applications.&nbsp; Firstly, the aim was to use causal discovery to construct and interpret spatial graphs of information flow in the Earth's coupled atmosphere-land-ocean system. This research was performed in collaboration with Yi Deng at Georgia Tech (Award #1445956).&nbsp; Secondly, we also applied causal discovery to several low-dimensional problems in climate science, discovered strategies for successful collaboration between climate scientists and data scientists, and identified the most promising avenues for future research combining the areas of climate science and machine learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit </strong></p> <p>Through the research in this project we advanced knowledge and understanding in both climate science and data science in several areas.&nbsp; Below we provide several <em>examples</em>, listed in order <em>from specific insights to general insights</em>:</p> <p>1) The spatially distributed maps of information flow provided new insights into climate processes, including the following trends in the projected future climate: a significant poleward drift of midlatitude storm tracks, diminishing of major tropical interaction pathways, and generally a more chaotic atmosphere in the future.&nbsp; We also studied atmospheric scale-interaction processes by applying causal discovery in spectral space (using spherical harmonics) and identified the key interactions between Regimes I, II and III.&nbsp; Furthermore, we identified pathways of information flow related to the South Asian monsoon onset.</p> <p>2) We used causal discovery to study the links between the arctic and midlatitude jet-stream.&nbsp; The study revealed positive feedback loops between arctic temperature and jet speed, as well as between arctic temperature and jet latitude.</p> <p>3) We gained important insights on how to best apply causal discovery methods to a variety of different climate applications and will disseminate the lessons learned in a summary paper, thus making it easier for other climate scientists to apply these methods without having to fall into the same pitfalls. &nbsp;Examples include how to deal with phase-amplitude variables which tend to be highly non-Gaussian, with changing regimes, and with spatial auto-correlation.</p> <p>4) We determined the key characteristics of earth science applications that make the use of standard machine learning methods very challenging and identified the most promising machine learning approaches to address those challenges and move the field forward. &nbsp;Our findings are summarized in a journal paper.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong></p> <p>The broader impacts of this project include:</p> <p><strong>1) Effects of climate change</strong></p> <p>Through our research we have provided additional understanding of the anticipated consequences of climate change, and while these insights are still relatively abstract, we hope to have contributed in a small way to the understanding of this critical societal topic.</p> <p><strong>2) Diversity &nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Three of the four participants supported by this grant are female, namely PI Ebert-Uphoff, doctoral student Savini Samarasinghe, and one of the two REU students involved in this project, thus bolstering the career of 3 female scientists.</p> <p><strong>3) Workforce development and STEM education</strong></p> <p>We realized that there is a huge discrepancy between the current training of graduate students in geoscience and the data analysis skills they need to be successful in their current and future research.&nbsp; We reviewed the literature and solicited the insights of many colleagues on best techniques to fill these gaps in existing graduate programs.&nbsp; The results were presented at the 2018 AGU Fall meeting and a longer version submitted as a journal paper.</p> <p><strong>4) Accelerating future progress at the intersection of Climate Science and Machine learning</strong></p> <p>Over the 4-year period of this award PI Ebert-Uphoff has worked vigorously on bringing researchers from the fields of earth science and machine learning closer together through numerous strategic activities partly supported by this grant (e.g., funding the PI?s travel to such events).&nbsp; She served as co-convener on numerous sessions at AGU Fall meetings: in 2015 a session on <em>Climate Diagnosis and Modeling in the Era of Climate Informatics</em>, and in 2018 she helped convene a research session on <em>AI applications in the geosciences</em>, a panel session on <em>Future directions for AI in the geosciences</em> (see figure), a session on <em>Educating the Next Generation of Scientists: Interdisciplinary Education Bridging Geoscience and Data Science</em>, and a full-day workshop on <em>Emerging Data Science and Machine Learning Opportunities in the Weather and Climate Sciences.</em> Furthermore, she served as a driving force on the organizing committee of the climate Informatics workshop series every year of the project, an annual 2-day event.</p> <p><strong>5) Strategies for collaboration</strong></p> <p>We also gained many insights into what it takes to create successful, deep, interdisciplinary collaborations between earth scientists and data scientists.&nbsp; We provide a structured approach for such collaborations in an EOS magazine article, entitled <em>Three Steps to Successful Collaboration with Data Scientists</em>, which guides novices in this area through this collaboration process (see also three accompanying figures).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Imme&nbsp;R&nbsp;Ebert-Uphoff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554062762292_Collaboration_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554062762292_Collaboration_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Phase 1 of collaborative process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554062762292_Collaboration_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Phase 1 of collaborative process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phase 1 of the collaborative process between an earth scientist and a data scientist consists of defining the problem and approach - an iterative process involving both Peter and Andrea.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Imme Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Imme&nbsp;R&nbsp;Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Phase 1 of collaborative process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554063895895_Collaboration_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554063895895_Collaboration_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Phase 2 of the collaborative process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554063895895_Collaboration_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Phase 2 of the collaborative process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phase 2 of the collaborative process between an earth scientist and a data scientist - the researchers conduct many experiments on the data, but again need to work closely together to obtain meaningful results.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Imme Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Imme&nbsp;R&nbsp;Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Phase 2 of the collaborative process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554063982983_Collaboration_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554063982983_Collaboration_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Phase 3 of the collaborative process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554063982983_Collaboration_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Phase 3 of the collaborative process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phase 3 of the collaborative process between an earth scientist and a data scientist - the researchers evaluate the results, translate them back into earth science language and discuss in depth what the results imply for earth sciences.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Imme Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Imme&nbsp;R&nbsp;Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Phase 3 of the collaborative process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554064350292_AGU_panel_slide_version--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554064350292_AGU_panel_slide_version--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Panel Session at 2018 AGU Fall Meeting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1445978/1445978_10345767_1554064350292_AGU_panel_slide_version--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Panel Session at 2018 AGU Fall Meeting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Panel session at the 2018 AGU Fall meeting on Augmenting Advances in the Next Century: Why AI and Knowledge-Centered Research in Geosciences Is Important Now and How It Will Change the Next Century.  Four of the eight panelists (left) and the large audience (right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Imme Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Imme&nbsp;R&nbsp;Ebert-Uphoff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Panel Session at 2018 AGU Fall Meeting</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  This project focused on applying methods from causal discovery, i.e. methods to identify potential cause-effect relationships from data, to a variety of climate science applications.  Firstly, the aim was to use causal discovery to construct and interpret spatial graphs of information flow in the Earth's coupled atmosphere-land-ocean system. This research was performed in collaboration with Yi Deng at Georgia Tech (Award #1445956).  Secondly, we also applied causal discovery to several low-dimensional problems in climate science, discovered strategies for successful collaboration between climate scientists and data scientists, and identified the most promising avenues for future research combining the areas of climate science and machine learning.     Intellectual Merit   Through the research in this project we advanced knowledge and understanding in both climate science and data science in several areas.  Below we provide several examples, listed in order from specific insights to general insights:  1) The spatially distributed maps of information flow provided new insights into climate processes, including the following trends in the projected future climate: a significant poleward drift of midlatitude storm tracks, diminishing of major tropical interaction pathways, and generally a more chaotic atmosphere in the future.  We also studied atmospheric scale-interaction processes by applying causal discovery in spectral space (using spherical harmonics) and identified the key interactions between Regimes I, II and III.  Furthermore, we identified pathways of information flow related to the South Asian monsoon onset.  2) We used causal discovery to study the links between the arctic and midlatitude jet-stream.  The study revealed positive feedback loops between arctic temperature and jet speed, as well as between arctic temperature and jet latitude.  3) We gained important insights on how to best apply causal discovery methods to a variety of different climate applications and will disseminate the lessons learned in a summary paper, thus making it easier for other climate scientists to apply these methods without having to fall into the same pitfalls.  Examples include how to deal with phase-amplitude variables which tend to be highly non-Gaussian, with changing regimes, and with spatial auto-correlation.  4) We determined the key characteristics of earth science applications that make the use of standard machine learning methods very challenging and identified the most promising machine learning approaches to address those challenges and move the field forward.  Our findings are summarized in a journal paper.     Broader impacts  The broader impacts of this project include:  1) Effects of climate change  Through our research we have provided additional understanding of the anticipated consequences of climate change, and while these insights are still relatively abstract, we hope to have contributed in a small way to the understanding of this critical societal topic.  2) Diversity    Three of the four participants supported by this grant are female, namely PI Ebert-Uphoff, doctoral student Savini Samarasinghe, and one of the two REU students involved in this project, thus bolstering the career of 3 female scientists.  3) Workforce development and STEM education  We realized that there is a huge discrepancy between the current training of graduate students in geoscience and the data analysis skills they need to be successful in their current and future research.  We reviewed the literature and solicited the insights of many colleagues on best techniques to fill these gaps in existing graduate programs.  The results were presented at the 2018 AGU Fall meeting and a longer version submitted as a journal paper.  4) Accelerating future progress at the intersection of Climate Science and Machine learning  Over the 4-year period of this award PI Ebert-Uphoff has worked vigorously on bringing researchers from the fields of earth science and machine learning closer together through numerous strategic activities partly supported by this grant (e.g., funding the PI?s travel to such events).  She served as co-convener on numerous sessions at AGU Fall meetings: in 2015 a session on Climate Diagnosis and Modeling in the Era of Climate Informatics, and in 2018 she helped convene a research session on AI applications in the geosciences, a panel session on Future directions for AI in the geosciences (see figure), a session on Educating the Next Generation of Scientists: Interdisciplinary Education Bridging Geoscience and Data Science, and a full-day workshop on Emerging Data Science and Machine Learning Opportunities in the Weather and Climate Sciences. Furthermore, she served as a driving force on the organizing committee of the climate Informatics workshop series every year of the project, an annual 2-day event.  5) Strategies for collaboration  We also gained many insights into what it takes to create successful, deep, interdisciplinary collaborations between earth scientists and data scientists.  We provide a structured approach for such collaborations in an EOS magazine article, entitled Three Steps to Successful Collaboration with Data Scientists, which guides novices in this area through this collaboration process (see also three accompanying figures).          Last Modified: 03/31/2019       Submitted by: Imme R Ebert-Uphoff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
