<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Design and Execution of a Design Laboratory (Learning Lab) for STEM Projects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299215.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299215</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca A. Kruse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Networked Improvement Communities (NICs) are a structure for redefining the relationship between education research and development and practice so as to more effectively address real problems in order to produce knowledge that can meaningfully contribute to improvement. NICs are scientific learning communities distinguished by essential characteristics: they are focused on a well-specified common aim, guided by a deep understanding of the problem and a shared working theory of how to improve it. NICs are committed to the rigor of improvement science and are coordinated to accelerate the development, testing and refinement of interventions. NICs also diffuse their knowledge to the field more rapidly and work to integrate their findings into varied educational contexts. This project provides an opportunity to learn how best to implement NIC principles so as to realize their potential to support STEM initiatives. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A NIC Design Learning Laboratory is a series of learning sessions in which participants are convened together and are interspersed between action periods in their local contexts leading to the formation networks. At each learning session, significant knowledge about the developmental stage of NIC design and initiation is introduced. During the action periods, teams follow through on ideas introduced and plans established. Subsequent learning sessions offer design teams the opportunity for coaching on particular problems that may arise and to encounter the ideas and work to be addressed in the next developmental stage. Participants learn the ideas of NIC conceptualization and initiation by working on launching their own networks, with the training and guidance relevant to each step in NIC development provided by Carnegie and colleagues in the Learning Lab. The focus for the learning sessions includes technical skill and leadership development and forming learning community networks related to STEM goals.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;At the end of the Learning Laboratory the following will be produced: 1) a NIC Design Learning Laboratory for STEM Projects that would support up to five project teams as they plan, initiate and launch NICs; 2) an Assessors Guide to document the essential elements of NICs and their expression in programmatic thinking; 3) A Design and Operational Plan and timeline for each of the participating teams guiding the establishment of their NIC as would constitute the centerpiece for their plans and possible proposal for seeking support; 4) A final report drawing upon the Developmental Evaluation and External Review.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1445853</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>LeMahieu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul G LeMahieu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lemahieu@carnegiefoundation.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6505665110</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000651546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943058703</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6505665110</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>51 Vista Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>067831891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE FOUNDATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF TEACHING, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943058703</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~299215</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h2><em>Five out of six teams launched or will soon launch their NICs </em></h2> <p>Four months after the completion of the Learning Lab, five of the six participating teams had launched their NICs or had concrete plans to launch their NICs (e.g., a convening marking the official launch scheduled).</p> <ul> <li><strong>EdLeaders21</strong> officially launched their STEM NIC in October 2015 with four school districts working together to establish interdisciplinary STEM learning in 100 sixth grade classrooms by 2018. </li> <li>The<strong> American Institutes for Research</strong> launched their NIC in partnership with the Nellie Mae Education Foundation in summer 2015 aimed at increasing the number of students who engage in meaningful mathematics learning through student centered teaching in Algebra I.</li> <li>The <strong>Knowles Science Teaching Foundation (KSTF)</strong> launched Project ASCENT in July 2015 aiming to increase the number of students that are successful in advanced STEM classes in partnering high schools.</li> <li>The <strong>Clinical Experiences Research Action Cluster (RAC)</strong> is a NIC operating within a larger NIC (the Mathematics Teacher Education Partnership sponsored by the Association of Public and Land-grant Universities) aiming to increase the capacity of teacher candidates to use NCTM&rsquo;s eight mathematics teaching practices at least once a week during full time student teaching.</li> <li><strong>California State University East Bay</strong> will launch the Next Gen TARSC NIC in June 2016 aimed at improving the preparation of pre-service teachers to practice high quality three-dimensional science teaching. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The sixth team, representing <strong>Partners for Student Success</strong> has a strong commitment to launch their NIC, but was still trying to raise the necessary funding to support NIC operation. Partners for Student Success aims to improve the first attempt passage of students in Algebra I classes in their partnering districts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to support the launch of five out of six participating networks, a key accomplishment of the Learning Lab was that deep and timely learning experience provided. Overall, interviewees across teams were quite enthusiastic about the learning and development opportunities provided through the Learning Lab. Comments representing various teams included:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s probably the single most valuable activity of this kind I&rsquo;ve been involved in for at least a couple of reasons. One, having to do with focus, very well focused, or asking us to be well focused. Then, a very specific approach that they are conveying to us about how to address the problem. So it [participating in the learning lab] was very important in my mind.&rdquo;</li> <li>&ldquo;The nuts and bolts, the balance of presentations and time with our team, grappling with new materials, it was good. It was really solid.&rdquo;</li> <li>&ldquo;[Without the Learning Lab] there is no way we would be where we are today.&rdquo;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <h2><em>Iterative refinement of working theories of improvement and aligned measures</em></h2> <p>All six teams pointed to a principle benefit of their participation in Learning Lab: the iterative refinement of their working theory of improvement, represented as a driver diagram, and the identification of aligned measures to track progress toward their aim. For example, the AIR team noted that they were on version 5.0 of their driver diagram due to their work in the Learning Lab and they had recently vetted the theory of improvement with practitioners. Several teams appreciated the support they got from the Learning Lab to revise and focus their aim statement. For example the Clinical Experiences RAC team reported, &ldquo;changing our aim to something that we think is more manageable and measurable.&rdquo;</p> ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Five out of six teams launched or will soon launch their NICs   Four months after the completion of the Learning Lab, five of the six participating teams had launched their NICs or had concrete plans to launch their NICs (e.g., a convening marking the official launch scheduled).  EdLeaders21 officially launched their STEM NIC in October 2015 with four school districts working together to establish interdisciplinary STEM learning in 100 sixth grade classrooms by 2018.  The American Institutes for Research launched their NIC in partnership with the Nellie Mae Education Foundation in summer 2015 aimed at increasing the number of students who engage in meaningful mathematics learning through student centered teaching in Algebra I. The Knowles Science Teaching Foundation (KSTF) launched Project ASCENT in July 2015 aiming to increase the number of students that are successful in advanced STEM classes in partnering high schools. The Clinical Experiences Research Action Cluster (RAC) is a NIC operating within a larger NIC (the Mathematics Teacher Education Partnership sponsored by the Association of Public and Land-grant Universities) aiming to increase the capacity of teacher candidates to use NCTMÆs eight mathematics teaching practices at least once a week during full time student teaching. California State University East Bay will launch the Next Gen TARSC NIC in June 2016 aimed at improving the preparation of pre-service teachers to practice high quality three-dimensional science teaching.       The sixth team, representing Partners for Student Success has a strong commitment to launch their NIC, but was still trying to raise the necessary funding to support NIC operation. Partners for Student Success aims to improve the first attempt passage of students in Algebra I classes in their partnering districts.     In addition to support the launch of five out of six participating networks, a key accomplishment of the Learning Lab was that deep and timely learning experience provided. Overall, interviewees across teams were quite enthusiastic about the learning and development opportunities provided through the Learning Lab. Comments representing various teams included:     "ItÆs probably the single most valuable activity of this kind IÆve been involved in for at least a couple of reasons. One, having to do with focus, very well focused, or asking us to be well focused. Then, a very specific approach that they are conveying to us about how to address the problem. So it [participating in the learning lab] was very important in my mind." "The nuts and bolts, the balance of presentations and time with our team, grappling with new materials, it was good. It was really solid." "[Without the Learning Lab] there is no way we would be where we are today."     Iterative refinement of working theories of improvement and aligned measures  All six teams pointed to a principle benefit of their participation in Learning Lab: the iterative refinement of their working theory of improvement, represented as a driver diagram, and the identification of aligned measures to track progress toward their aim. For example, the AIR team noted that they were on version 5.0 of their driver diagram due to their work in the Learning Lab and they had recently vetted the theory of improvement with practitioners. Several teams appreciated the support they got from the Learning Lab to revise and focus their aim statement. For example the Clinical Experiences RAC team reported, "changing our aim to something that we think is more manageable and measurable." Emerging PLC / network of improvement coaches  A final significant accomplishment of the Learning Lab was the development of an emerging professional learning community for improvement coaches. Responding to a collective feeling that they had more to learn about coaching network members to engage in improvement science methods, some of the teamsÆ improvement coaches decided to establish a monthly meeting time where the...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
