<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Mexico conference in representation theory and noncommutative algebra</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49940.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49940</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant will fund participation of U.S.-based researchers in the US-Mexico Conferences on Representation Theory, Categorification, and Non-Commutative Algebra that will take place at Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico in  Mexico City, January 15-18, 2015 and the University of Southern California, Los Angeles, January 14-17, 2016. Representation theory is a major branch of mathematics that studies symmetries of of physical theories and of mathematical objects. Often the main objects in representation theory are only the shadow of richer structures that are recovered through deeper study. Non-commutative algebra is another major, related branch of algebra that studies deformations of commutative objects found in quantum theories, representation theory, and geometry. The foci of the conferences will be on recent advances at the interface of representation theory and non-commutative algebra; on fostering an environment for the establishment of international collaborations between the US and Mexico in this research areas; and on exposing graduate students, post-docs, and young faculty in both countries to current developments in the field. The conference series has an international component and is co-funded by the International Science and Engineering Section.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will organize one four-day conference each academic year that will alternate between the US and Mexico. The main scientific topics of the conference series will be algebraic, geometric and homological methods in representation theory, categorification, and non-commutative algebra. The talks will cover some of the most recent trends including: cluster algebras, quantum groups, monoidal and additive categorifications, Calabi-Yau algebras and categories, and non-commutative projective algebraic geometry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1446398</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Milen</FirstName>
<LastName>Yakimov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Milen T Yakimov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yakimov@math.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255781566</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487061</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Lauda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Lauda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lauda@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6462410921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511103</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900892532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3620 S. Vermont Ave., KAP 108]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5922</Code>
<Text>MEXICO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~49940</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes related to Intellectual Merit: </strong>The grant supported two US-Mexico Conferences in Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra. The first one was held in UNAM, Mexico City,&nbsp; January 15-17, 2016 and the second in the University  of Southern California May 30th - June 3rd, 2016. The conferences had approximately 50 and 90 registered participants, as well as many drop in participants  from the Maexico City and LA area.</p> <p>Both conferences featured talks by a number of leading researchers, who reported their latest research results on a wide range of topics in the areas of  in Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra. The plenary lectures highlighted future directions and current trends in  these rapidly developing areas. The speakers also discussed important open problems in the areas which stimulated a great deal of research after the conferences. The ample discussion time facilitated in depth  collaboration and the exchange of ideas. Many research collaborations were formed after the conferences. The junior  researchers had ample opportunities for personal discussions  with the presenters from whom they learned a detailed picture of the latest research results in the reas.<strong><br /></strong></p> <p><strong>Outcomes related to Broader Impacts: </strong>The conference series fosters an environment for the establishment of international collaboration<br />between the US and Mexico in the fields of Noncommutative Algebra and<br />Representation Theory. An annual conference series in Algebra between the US and Mexico has been discussed since the 70's, but it has never been realized. This NSF grant supported the first step in the attempt of the PI to organize a permanent US-Mexico conference series  in Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra that will run every year.</p> <p><br />The PIs made a great effort in attracting many female and minority mathematicians to the conference series. As a result, 25% of the speakers at the USC conference were women. Furthermore, the PIs made a focused effort on junior participants via a dedicated poster  session which provided a unique opportunity for graduate students and postdocs  to present their findings and gain valuable feedback from conference  participants. In addition, many graduate students and postdocs were invited to give talks (a total of 12 for both conferences).&nbsp; <strong><br /></strong></p> <p><strong>Summary of Outcomes: </strong>The conference establishes a permanent environment for US-Mexico collaborations in the areas of Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra. It brings together researchers with diverse  approaches based on categorical, algebraic, geometric and combinatorial techniques. It exposing graduate students, post-docs, and young faculty to cutting edge research in the areas. The conference series also presents unique opportunities for recruiting female and minority  graduate students to the areas of representation theory and  noncommutative algebra, and attracting female and minority researchers in these  areas to the US.<strong><br /></strong></p> <p>Both the Mexico and US participants were extremely  enthusiastic  about the prospects of an annual series of conferences on  these topics  that would alternate between the two countries.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/19/2017<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;Lauda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559419815_img_6467--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559419815_img_6467--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2016 Conference Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559419815_img_6467--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2016 Conference Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group photo</div> <div class="imageCredit">USC Math department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Milen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Yakimov</div> <div class="imageTitle">2016 Conference Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559477090_img_6461--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559477090_img_6461--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poster Presenters"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559477090_img_6461--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poster Presenters"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference organizers with poster presenters</div> <div class="imageCredit">USC Math department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;Lauda</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poster Presenters</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559531494_2016-05-31-14-59-25--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559531494_2016-05-31-14-59-25--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poster session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559531494_2016-05-31-14-59-25--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poster session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference participants attending the poster session.</div> <div class="imageCredit">USC Math department</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;Lauda</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poster session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559668082_img_6409--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559668082_img_6409--rgov-800width.jpg" title="conference room"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1483559668082_img_6409--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="conference room"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Lecture room</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aaron Lauda</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;Lauda</div> <div class="imageTitle">conference room</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1484857711321_Mexico-Conf-Photo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1484857711321_Mexico-Conf-Photo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2015 Conforence Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1446398/1446398_10344939_1484857711321_Mexico-Conf-Photo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2015 Conforence Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mexico Conference Photo</div> <div class="imageCredit">UNAM</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Milen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Yakimov</div> <div class="imageTitle">2015 Conforence Photo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes related to Intellectual Merit: The grant supported two US-Mexico Conferences in Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra. The first one was held in UNAM, Mexico City,  January 15-17, 2016 and the second in the University  of Southern California May 30th - June 3rd, 2016. The conferences had approximately 50 and 90 registered participants, as well as many drop in participants  from the Maexico City and LA area.  Both conferences featured talks by a number of leading researchers, who reported their latest research results on a wide range of topics in the areas of  in Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra. The plenary lectures highlighted future directions and current trends in  these rapidly developing areas. The speakers also discussed important open problems in the areas which stimulated a great deal of research after the conferences. The ample discussion time facilitated in depth  collaboration and the exchange of ideas. Many research collaborations were formed after the conferences. The junior  researchers had ample opportunities for personal discussions  with the presenters from whom they learned a detailed picture of the latest research results in the reas.   Outcomes related to Broader Impacts: The conference series fosters an environment for the establishment of international collaboration between the US and Mexico in the fields of Noncommutative Algebra and Representation Theory. An annual conference series in Algebra between the US and Mexico has been discussed since the 70's, but it has never been realized. This NSF grant supported the first step in the attempt of the PI to organize a permanent US-Mexico conference series  in Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra that will run every year.   The PIs made a great effort in attracting many female and minority mathematicians to the conference series. As a result, 25% of the speakers at the USC conference were women. Furthermore, the PIs made a focused effort on junior participants via a dedicated poster  session which provided a unique opportunity for graduate students and postdocs  to present their findings and gain valuable feedback from conference  participants. In addition, many graduate students and postdocs were invited to give talks (a total of 12 for both conferences).     Summary of Outcomes: The conference establishes a permanent environment for US-Mexico collaborations in the areas of Representation Theory and Non-Commutative Algebra. It brings together researchers with diverse  approaches based on categorical, algebraic, geometric and combinatorial techniques. It exposing graduate students, post-docs, and young faculty to cutting edge research in the areas. The conference series also presents unique opportunities for recruiting female and minority  graduate students to the areas of representation theory and  noncommutative algebra, and attracting female and minority researchers in these  areas to the US.   Both the Mexico and US participants were extremely  enthusiastic  about the prospects of an annual series of conferences on  these topics  that would alternate between the two countries.       Last Modified: 01/19/2017       Submitted by: Aaron Lauda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
