<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: TTP Option: Synergy: Traffic Signal Control with Connected and Autonomous Vehicles in the Traffic Stream</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1280428.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1296428</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent progress in autonomous and connected vehicle technologies coupled with Federal and State initiatives to facilitate their widespread use provide significant opportunities in enhancing mobility and safety for highway transportation. This project develops signalized intersection control strategies and other enabling sensor mechanisms for jointly optimizing vehicle trajectories and signal control by taking advantage of existing advanced technologies (connected vehicles and vehicle to infrastructure communications, sensors, autonomous vehicle technologies, etc.)  Traffic signal control is a critical component of the existing transportation infrastructure and it has a significant impact on transportation system efficiency, as well as energy consumption and environmental impacts. In addition to advanced vehicle technologies, the strategies developed consider the presence of conventional vehicles in the traffic stream to facilitate transition to these new strategies in a mixed vehicle environment. The project also develops and uses simulation tools to evaluate these strategies as well as to provide tools that can be used in practice to consider the impacts of automated and connected vehicles in arterial networks. The project involves two industry partners (ISS and Econolite) to help facilitate new product development in anticipation of increased market penetration of connected and autonomous vehicles.  The approach will be tested through simulation at University of Florida, through field tests at the Turner Fairbank Highway Research Center (TFHRC) and through the control algorithms that also will be deployed and tested in the field.  The project will support multiple graduate students and will support creation of on-line classes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is at the intersection of several different disciplines (optimization, sensors, automated vehicles, transportation engineering) required to produce a real-time engineered system that depends on the seamless integration of several components: sensor functionality, connected and autonomous vehicle information communication, signal control optimization strategy, missing and erroneous information, etc.  The project develops and implements optimization processes and strategies considering a seamless fusion of multiple data sources, as well as a mixed vehicle stream (autonomous, connected, and conventional vehicles) under real-world conditions of uncertain and missing data. Since trajectories for connected and conventional vehicles cannot be optimized or guaranteed, the project examines the impacts of the presence of automated vehicles on the following vehicles in a queue.  The project also integrates advanced sensing technology needed to control a mixed vehicle stream, as well as address malfunctioning communications in connected and autonomous vehicles.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1446813</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjay</FirstName>
<LastName>Ranka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjay Ranka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sanjayranka@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3525140743</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000622772</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
<LastName>Crane</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carl D Crane</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carl.crane@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523929461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000186526</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lily-Ageliki</FirstName>
<LastName>Elefteriadou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lily-Ageliki Elefteriadou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elefter@ce.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523929537</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000671335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326116550</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O423</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O424</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8237</Code>
<Text>CISE Interagency Agreements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1280428</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A multidisciplinary team of researchers from academia and industry has developed and tested a series of tools for jointly optimizing signal control and vehicle movement to improve mobility by exploiting capabilities of connected and autonomous vehicles. Connected vehicles are those that can communicate with surrounding vehicles and infrastructure using wireless communication.&nbsp; Autonomous vehicles have the ability to operate without a human driver using a variety of sensors such as GPS, LiDAR, Radar, and smart cameras, as well as terrain information.&nbsp; The system was successfully implemented and tested in simulation and in the field, and it was shown that it has the potential to improve travel times by as much as 70%, depending on market penetration of autonomous and connected vehicles. &nbsp;</p> <p>The first tool, Real-time Intersection Optimizer (RIO) is an algorithm that optimizes Signal Phase and Timing (SigPT) and vehicle trajectories. RIO receives real-time positioning of Connected Vehicles (CNV) or Connected Autonomous Vehicles (CAV), determines SigPT in order to better serve the current demand in the intersection, and sends back optimized trajectories such that vehicles depart from the stop bar at the saturation rate and at the maximum possible speed. RIO can handle the presence of pedestrians either through LiDAR detection, or through the use of the pedestrian button. RIO sends trajectory instructions to all vehicles.&nbsp; CAVs are able to implement them directly without driver intervention. &nbsp;CNVs receive trajectory information through a phone app developed for this project. The app provides drivers with a recommended speed that matches the optimized trajectory. It also shows a time countdown of when the driver is expected to cross the stop-bar according to the optimized trajectory.</p> <p>The second tool, Sensible, is a real-time multi-sensor fusion software framework, which &nbsp;assembles information from several sensors and fuses it to provide vehicle arrival information to RIO. Sensible supports inputs from commercial traffic sensors such as the Econolite Autoscope, Smartmicro radar, and Cohda DSRC for V2X. It contains sensor drivers and tracking algorithms for each sensor type, as well as fusion algorithms for combining all inputs into a single information stream. This information is provided to RIO, which optimizes signal control based on vehicle arrival information. The research team also developed sensor drivers and detection algorithms for LiDAR-based pedestrian detection near the intersection area.</p> <p>The research team has tested the system in simulation (through our own custom simulation as well as with the commercially available microsimulator VISSIM) and in the field. &nbsp;We conducted a series of tests at the closed-course testing facility of the Florida Department of Transportation (FDOT) to test all hardware and software components of our algorithms (RIO and Sensible) and to evaluate the system?s performance with a variety of combinations of vehicle and pedestrian demand and prepare for field testing. &nbsp;The research team worked with the City of Gainesville to install sensors at the intersection of Gale Lemerand and Stadium Rd. on the UF campus, in order to conduct further testing. The intersection has video, radar and connectivity for vehicles able to receive information from the infrastructure. A video clip posted on our website (<a href="http://avian.essie.ufl.edu/gallery/sensor-fusion-demonstration/">http://avian.essie.ufl.edu/gallery/sensor-fusion-demonstration/</a> ) shows the recommended trajectories sent to vehicles as well as the actual trajectories followed by vehicles. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Lily-Ageliki&nbsp;Elefteriadou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A multidisciplinary team of researchers from academia and industry has developed and tested a series of tools for jointly optimizing signal control and vehicle movement to improve mobility by exploiting capabilities of connected and autonomous vehicles. Connected vehicles are those that can communicate with surrounding vehicles and infrastructure using wireless communication.  Autonomous vehicles have the ability to operate without a human driver using a variety of sensors such as GPS, LiDAR, Radar, and smart cameras, as well as terrain information.  The system was successfully implemented and tested in simulation and in the field, and it was shown that it has the potential to improve travel times by as much as 70%, depending on market penetration of autonomous and connected vehicles.    The first tool, Real-time Intersection Optimizer (RIO) is an algorithm that optimizes Signal Phase and Timing (SigPT) and vehicle trajectories. RIO receives real-time positioning of Connected Vehicles (CNV) or Connected Autonomous Vehicles (CAV), determines SigPT in order to better serve the current demand in the intersection, and sends back optimized trajectories such that vehicles depart from the stop bar at the saturation rate and at the maximum possible speed. RIO can handle the presence of pedestrians either through LiDAR detection, or through the use of the pedestrian button. RIO sends trajectory instructions to all vehicles.  CAVs are able to implement them directly without driver intervention.  CNVs receive trajectory information through a phone app developed for this project. The app provides drivers with a recommended speed that matches the optimized trajectory. It also shows a time countdown of when the driver is expected to cross the stop-bar according to the optimized trajectory.  The second tool, Sensible, is a real-time multi-sensor fusion software framework, which  assembles information from several sensors and fuses it to provide vehicle arrival information to RIO. Sensible supports inputs from commercial traffic sensors such as the Econolite Autoscope, Smartmicro radar, and Cohda DSRC for V2X. It contains sensor drivers and tracking algorithms for each sensor type, as well as fusion algorithms for combining all inputs into a single information stream. This information is provided to RIO, which optimizes signal control based on vehicle arrival information. The research team also developed sensor drivers and detection algorithms for LiDAR-based pedestrian detection near the intersection area.  The research team has tested the system in simulation (through our own custom simulation as well as with the commercially available microsimulator VISSIM) and in the field.  We conducted a series of tests at the closed-course testing facility of the Florida Department of Transportation (FDOT) to test all hardware and software components of our algorithms (RIO and Sensible) and to evaluate the system?s performance with a variety of combinations of vehicle and pedestrian demand and prepare for field testing.  The research team worked with the City of Gainesville to install sensors at the intersection of Gale Lemerand and Stadium Rd. on the UF campus, in order to conduct further testing. The intersection has video, radar and connectivity for vehicles able to receive information from the infrastructure. A video clip posted on our website (http://avian.essie.ufl.edu/gallery/sensor-fusion-demonstration/ ) shows the recommended trajectories sent to vehicles as well as the actual trajectories followed by vehicles.            Last Modified: 06/29/2021       Submitted by: Lily-Ageliki Elefteriadou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
