<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Synergy: Collaborative Research: Control of Vehicular Traffic Flow via Low Density Autonomous Vehicles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239971.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239971</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the next few decades, autonomous vehicles will become an integral part of the traffic flow on highways. However, they will constitute only a small fraction of all vehicles on the road. This research develops technologies to employ autonomous vehicles already in the stream to improve traffic flow of human-controlled vehicles. The goal is to mitigate undesirable jamming, traffic waves, and to ultimately reduce the fuel consumption. Contemporary control of traffic flow, such as ramp metering and variable speed limits, is largely limited to local and highly aggregate approaches. This research represents a step towards global control of traffic using a few autonomous vehicles, and it provides the mathematical, computational, and engineering structure to address and employ these new connections. Even if autonomous vehicles can provide only a small percentage reduction in fuel consumption, this will have a tremendous economic and environmental impact due to the heavy dependence of the transportation system on non-renewable fuels. The project is highly collaborative and interdisciplinary, involving personnel from different disciplines in engineering and mathematics. It includes the training of PhD students and a postdoctoral researcher, and outreach activities to disseminate traffic research to the broader public.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project develops new models, computational methods, software tools, and engineering solutions to employ autonomous vehicles to detect and mitigate traffic events that adversely affect fuel consumption and congestion. The approach is to combine the data measured by autonomous vehicles in the traffic flow, as well as other traffic data, with appropriate macroscopic traffic models to detect and predict congestion trends and events. Based on this information, the loop is closed by carefully following prescribed velocity controllers that are demonstrated to reduce congestion. These controllers require detection and response times that are beyond the limit of a human's ability. The choice of the best control strategy is determined via optimization approaches applied to the multiscale traffic model and suitable fuel consumption estimation. The communication between the autonomous vehicles, combined with the computational and control tasks on each individual vehicle, require a cyber-physical approach to the problem. This research considers new types of traffic models (micro-macro models, network approaches for higher-order models), new control algorithms for traffic flow regulation, and new sensing and control paradigms that are enabled by a small number of controllable systems available in a flow.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1446715</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benedetto</FirstName>
<LastName>Piccoli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benedetto Piccoli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>piccoli@camden.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8562256356</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546074</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University Camden</Name>
<CityName>Camden</CityName>
<ZipCode>081021400</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8562252949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>311 N. 5th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Room 351]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>625216556</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University Camden]]></Name>
<CityName>Camden</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>081021519</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[311 N 5th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8235</Code>
<Text>CPS-Synergy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~239971</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The CPS collaborative project focused on the design of control algorithms to dissipate traffic waves using a small number of Autonomous Vehicles, briefly AVs.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the near future a limited number of AVs will be immersed in bulk traffic. The project showed that, before a completely automated traffic will be available, a careful control of the AVs will allow to dissipate traffic waves, which are responsible for increased fuel consumption and emissions as well as safety issues. Such waves arise naturally in traffic, because of specific triggers (lane changing, merging etc,) but also sue to endogenous instabilities caused by human driving.</p> <p>The RUC group, in collaboration with other project partners (UIUC, U. Arizona and Tempe) developed models for AVs in bulk traffic and designed a number of control algorithms to dampen traffic waves. Different approaches were explored, including fully automated control algorithms, open-loop with external inputs and human-actuated. Such algorithms correspond to the situation of AVs, vehicles connected to other vehicles or intelligent infrastructures, which can share non-local data about traffic.</p> <p>The control algorithms were verified in silico and in a experiments performed in Illinois and Arizona, showing the effectivness of the project approach. In particular, during the experiments with up to 40% decrease in the grand total fuel consumption (AV and human-driven traffic) and up to 99% decrease in breaking events.</p> <p>The project paved the way to a successull use of AVs in the near future of traffic for the public benefit.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Benedetto&nbsp;Piccoli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1446715/1446715_10339124_1518190232850__MG_0177-2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1446715/1446715_10339124_1518190232850__MG_0177-2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Arizona AV experiments"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1446715/1446715_10339124_1518190232850__MG_0177-2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Arizona AV experiments"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image of experiments performed in Tucson Arizona with one AV and 20 human-driven vehicles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dan Work</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Benedetto&nbsp;Piccoli</div> <div class="imageTitle">Arizona AV experiments</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The CPS collaborative project focused on the design of control algorithms to dissipate traffic waves using a small number of Autonomous Vehicles, briefly AVs.   In the near future a limited number of AVs will be immersed in bulk traffic. The project showed that, before a completely automated traffic will be available, a careful control of the AVs will allow to dissipate traffic waves, which are responsible for increased fuel consumption and emissions as well as safety issues. Such waves arise naturally in traffic, because of specific triggers (lane changing, merging etc,) but also sue to endogenous instabilities caused by human driving.  The RUC group, in collaboration with other project partners (UIUC, U. Arizona and Tempe) developed models for AVs in bulk traffic and designed a number of control algorithms to dampen traffic waves. Different approaches were explored, including fully automated control algorithms, open-loop with external inputs and human-actuated. Such algorithms correspond to the situation of AVs, vehicles connected to other vehicles or intelligent infrastructures, which can share non-local data about traffic.  The control algorithms were verified in silico and in a experiments performed in Illinois and Arizona, showing the effectivness of the project approach. In particular, during the experiments with up to 40% decrease in the grand total fuel consumption (AV and human-driven traffic) and up to 99% decrease in breaking events.  The project paved the way to a successull use of AVs in the near future of traffic for the public benefit.       Last Modified: 02/09/2018       Submitted by: Benedetto Piccoli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
