<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An Exploration of Multi Decadal, Continental-Scale Evapotranspiration Inferred from Weather Data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>333635.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>333635</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030109</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Holly Barnard</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An Exploration of Multi Decadal, Continental-Scale Evapotranspiration&lt;br/&gt;Inferred from Weather Data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Land surface evapotranspiration (ET) is the transformation of water in soils, plants and lakes into atmospheric water vapor.  It is a significant part of the regional water balance with direct influence on streamflow and groundwater recharge.  ET is also a significant part of the atmospheric water balance with direct influence on humidity and rainfall.  Because of the energy required to vaporize water, the ET process also influences land and air temperature.  Despite its relevance to water resources and climate, ET is notoriously difficult to measure, especially at regional scales.  This proposal develops and applies a newly discovered method for estimating ET from readily available weather data, based on daily patterns of relative humidity.  With this method, the proposal addresses these questions: &lt;br/&gt;* What is the seasonal and geographic variability of ET over the U.S?  &lt;br/&gt;* What are the seasonal and geographic roles of forcing (temperature, humidity, wind and precipitation) and surface properties (soil, vegetation, topography) in these space-time patterns?  &lt;br/&gt;* What trends have occurred in ET over the last 50 years, and what is responsible for those trends (for instance, wind, moisture availability, radiation, temperature)?&lt;br/&gt;* How do these seasonal, geographical, and decadal variabilities (including trends) compare with state-of-the art climate models; and &lt;br/&gt;* How do the interactions between the land surface, the lower atmosphere, and cloud formation influence relative humidity?  &lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this work include development and demonstration of a practical means for water resource managers to estimate ET, better understanding of geographic water resource availability and new observational constraints on climate models.  In addition, the work will involve a graduate and undergraduate student, as well as a high school senior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Progress in understanding surface and atmospheric controls on ET, feedbacks between the surface and atmosphere, and decadal time scale variations in ET, require reliable estimates of ET.  Direct, continuous measurements, however, are recent (approximately one decade old), and spatially limited (a few hundreds of flux stations, each measuring approximately one square kilometer of land area).  Because of this, hydroclimatological research on ET has been either limited in space and time or has relied on model output. The proposed work overcomes these limitations and addresses critical questions related to the space-time variations of ET over decadal time scales (including trends), the drivers of these variations, and the ability of current climate models to capture these variations. Typically estimating ET requires either measurement of soil water status and surface temperature, or temporally integrated modeling of the water and energy balance. For broad use, the former requires remotely sensed observations, and the latter requires calibration of numerous soil hydraulic and vegetation parameters, leading to highly model-formulation dependent results. The method developed here provides ET estimation without site-specific calibration.   The parsimony of required forcing and surface data allows for broad geographic and temporal (e.g., prior to the satellite era) application, and yields results that are significantly less model dependent.  The intellectual merit of the proposed research is in addressing a vital questions of hydrologic sciences - determination of the terrestrial evaporation component of the water balance at hourly to decadal time scales over continental scales.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1446798</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guido</FirstName>
<LastName>Salvucci</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guido D Salvucci</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gdsalvuc@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173538344</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091399</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[685 Commonwealth Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~333635</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goals of this project were to develop a methodology for measuring the evaporation component of the water cycle using readily available weather station data, and to then apply the newly developed method to answer a set of questions.&nbsp; The method is called ETRHEQ (Evapotranspiration from Relative Humidity at Equilibrium).&nbsp; Current methods for directly measuring evaporation (called eddy covariance instruments) are prohibitively expensive and thus can not be applied to large land areas. The questions addressed were:&nbsp; 1) What is the seasonal and geographic variability of evapotranspiration (ET) over the U.S.;&nbsp; 2) What are the seasonal and geographic roles of forcing (weather and precipitation) and surface conductance (aerodynamic and vegetation/soil) in these space-time patterns ?&nbsp; 3) What trends have occurred in&nbsp; ET over the last 50 years, and what is responsible for them (wind, moisture availability, radiation, temperature) ?; 4) How do these seasonal, geographical, and decadal variabilities (including trends) compare with state-of-the art CMIP5 Global Climate model simulations and 5) What interactions between the land surface and atmosphere are responsible for the equilibration of relative humidity between the surface (soils and vegetation) and atmosphere.</span></p> <p><span><strong><em>Outcomes</em></strong>: <strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> We significantly extended testing of the key method for estimating evaporation that was proposed in the research.&nbsp; The original proposal was based on testing our methodology at five field sites with direct measurements of evapotranspiration&nbsp; (Ameriflux sites).&nbsp; We have now tested the methodology at more than 60 Ameriflux sites, and have found the method to be extremely robust and to apply to essentially all land cover and climatic conditions occurring in the U.S (except within approximately ten miles of the coast, where sea breezes negatively influence our results). We found that the methodology could be simplified by defining the relative humidity equilibrium between only the surface laminar boundary layer (e.g., for vegetation,&nbsp; the surface of leaves, just outside the stomata) and the measurement height (typically two meters).&nbsp; Previously, equilibrium was defined by evaluating the variability of vertical profiles throughout the lower atmosphere.&nbsp; The new method is simpler and more robust.&nbsp; In addition, we compared the seasonal and geographical patterns of our estimates with water balance estimates based on streamflow measurements by the United States Geological Survey, and with benchmark statistical and land surface model estimates.&nbsp; We also assessed the ability of the ETRHEQ method to capture inter-annual variability, since a major goal was to look at decadal trends. We found that the method can explain about half the variance (correlation coefficients of around 0.7) in monthly anomalies in the summer.</span><span>&nbsp; </span><span>We compiled weather station data (&gt;300 stations) and ran careful data quality checks on the key measurements required to estimate ET using our proposed method.&nbsp; We applied the ETRHEQ methodology and found statistically significant trends (decreasing ET), with strong spatial structure, across the U.S.&nbsp; These trends are consistent with some other estimates (e.g. by the ECMWF ERA-interim reanalysis), but differ from other estimates (e.g. the NASA NLDAS land surface model estimates)..&nbsp; Through spatial and temporal regression analysis we demonstrated that the strong declining trends we see in ET over the past 15 years are likely due to more frequent stomatal closure in response to a well documented continental scale decline in humidity, as well as to increasing carbon dioxide content of the boundary layer.&nbsp;&nbsp; We also derived a method to use ancillary soil moisture data from the NASA SMAP satellite to partition the ETRHEQ evapotranspiration estimates into components due to direct soil evaporation and due to transpiration from vegetation. &nbsp; The partitioning compared favorably to photosynthesis estimates based on satellite measured solar induced fluorescence.</span></p> <p><span><strong><em>Outcomes</em></strong>: <strong>Broader Impacts:&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></span></p> <p><span>Broader impacts of this work include further development and demonstration of a <em>practical and robust</em> means for water resource managers to estimate evaporation, better understanding of geographic water resource availability and possible trends therein, and new observational constraints on Climate Models.&nbsp; In conjunction with existing hydrologic and climatic records, such continental-scale, long-term <em>ET</em> estimates provide insights and empirical constraints on climate model projected accelerations of the hydrologic cycle.</span><span>&nbsp; </span><span>This grant, to date, has supported one graduate student (A. Rigden) and one undergraduate research assistant (Michael Woo) and has led to 3 publications related to the spatial and temporal dynamics (including trends and drivers) of evapotranspiration over the continental United States, and to 5 other publications related to <em>ET</em> processes, and 14 conference and seminar contributions.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Guido&nbsp;D&nbsp;Salvucci</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this project were to develop a methodology for measuring the evaporation component of the water cycle using readily available weather station data, and to then apply the newly developed method to answer a set of questions.  The method is called ETRHEQ (Evapotranspiration from Relative Humidity at Equilibrium).  Current methods for directly measuring evaporation (called eddy covariance instruments) are prohibitively expensive and thus can not be applied to large land areas. The questions addressed were:  1) What is the seasonal and geographic variability of evapotranspiration (ET) over the U.S.;  2) What are the seasonal and geographic roles of forcing (weather and precipitation) and surface conductance (aerodynamic and vegetation/soil) in these space-time patterns ?  3) What trends have occurred in  ET over the last 50 years, and what is responsible for them (wind, moisture availability, radiation, temperature) ?; 4) How do these seasonal, geographical, and decadal variabilities (including trends) compare with state-of-the art CMIP5 Global Climate model simulations and 5) What interactions between the land surface and atmosphere are responsible for the equilibration of relative humidity between the surface (soils and vegetation) and atmosphere.  Outcomes: Intellectual Merit: We significantly extended testing of the key method for estimating evaporation that was proposed in the research.  The original proposal was based on testing our methodology at five field sites with direct measurements of evapotranspiration  (Ameriflux sites).  We have now tested the methodology at more than 60 Ameriflux sites, and have found the method to be extremely robust and to apply to essentially all land cover and climatic conditions occurring in the U.S (except within approximately ten miles of the coast, where sea breezes negatively influence our results). We found that the methodology could be simplified by defining the relative humidity equilibrium between only the surface laminar boundary layer (e.g., for vegetation,  the surface of leaves, just outside the stomata) and the measurement height (typically two meters).  Previously, equilibrium was defined by evaluating the variability of vertical profiles throughout the lower atmosphere.  The new method is simpler and more robust.  In addition, we compared the seasonal and geographical patterns of our estimates with water balance estimates based on streamflow measurements by the United States Geological Survey, and with benchmark statistical and land surface model estimates.  We also assessed the ability of the ETRHEQ method to capture inter-annual variability, since a major goal was to look at decadal trends. We found that the method can explain about half the variance (correlation coefficients of around 0.7) in monthly anomalies in the summer.  We compiled weather station data (&gt;300 stations) and ran careful data quality checks on the key measurements required to estimate ET using our proposed method.  We applied the ETRHEQ methodology and found statistically significant trends (decreasing ET), with strong spatial structure, across the U.S.  These trends are consistent with some other estimates (e.g. by the ECMWF ERA-interim reanalysis), but differ from other estimates (e.g. the NASA NLDAS land surface model estimates)..  Through spatial and temporal regression analysis we demonstrated that the strong declining trends we see in ET over the past 15 years are likely due to more frequent stomatal closure in response to a well documented continental scale decline in humidity, as well as to increasing carbon dioxide content of the boundary layer.   We also derived a method to use ancillary soil moisture data from the NASA SMAP satellite to partition the ETRHEQ evapotranspiration estimates into components due to direct soil evaporation and due to transpiration from vegetation.   The partitioning compared favorably to photosynthesis estimates based on satellite measured solar induced fluorescence.  Outcomes: Broader Impacts:    Broader impacts of this work include further development and demonstration of a practical and robust means for water resource managers to estimate evaporation, better understanding of geographic water resource availability and possible trends therein, and new observational constraints on Climate Models.  In conjunction with existing hydrologic and climatic records, such continental-scale, long-term ET estimates provide insights and empirical constraints on climate model projected accelerations of the hydrologic cycle.  This grant, to date, has supported one graduate student (A. Rigden) and one undergraduate research assistant (Michael Woo) and has led to 3 publications related to the spatial and temporal dynamics (including trends and drivers) of evapotranspiration over the continental United States, and to 5 other publications related to ET processes, and 14 conference and seminar contributions.          Last Modified: 05/31/2019       Submitted by: Guido D Salvucci]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
