<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>P2C2: Collaborative Research: Quantitative Reconstruction of Past Drought Patterns in Western North America Using Lakes, Stable Isotopes, and Modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>262125.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>262125</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan G Wynn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwynn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924725</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative grant will help address current shortcomings of the data we have on Western droughts during the last 6,000 years. Currently most data on droughts has been derived from tree-ring records, but we have realized that although tree-ring data give excellent annual resolution, trees tend to record only summer weather while they are actually growing the ring, and winter weather is under-represented because ring growth is slow or stopped during this season. Given the importance of winter precipitation for much of the West, this gap in data has made accurate modeling difficult, and this grant will attempt to address that by sampling lake sediments, which 'record' the weather throughout the year in their bottom sediments, although at less than annual resolution. This work will result in a new map of droughts throughout the study period that will incorporate previous lake and tree-ring records from a region spanning from British Columbia in the Northwest to New Mexico in the Southeast.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grant will produce six new lacustrine sediment records (two from British Columbia, two from Alberta and two from New Mexico) that would extend 6000 years through the middle Holocene and conduct sedimentological analyses on core transects from closed-basin lakes to constrain water-level changes as a physical means of confirming the magnitude of hydrologic change inferred from the stable isotope measurements. The Penn State group will use paleodrought data produced previous efforts in Washington and British Columbia, as well as data from published research to improve intermediate complexity Earth system model (EMIC) data assimilation exercises, while the Pitt and UMN-D groups will produce new lake-level and stable isotope data from sites in the Pacific northwest and the desert southwest that have already been identified and in several cases cored. The team would combine analyses of open-basin isotope records and leaf wax deuterium measurements with the closed-basin and algal biomarker records to produce reconstructions of drought variability that are not influenced by changes in the isotopic composition of precipitation. The team has quantitatively interpreted the lake sediment oxygen isotope and lake level records using hydrologic and isotope mass balance models, and will synthesize the resulting data to produce a gridded, paleodrought network. These reconstructions would be used to investigate hypotheses regarding contrasting, North-South drought patterns in the Pacific Northwest and the desert Southwest during the Medieval Climate Anomaly, the Little Ice Age and middle Holocene.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will support two graduate students in the field and laboratory, as well as some undergraduate research activities, and the results will be published in peer-reviewed journals, presented at professional conferences and public meetings. The collected cores will be available for further sampling by other researchers, and the results will be made publicly accessible and available in a NOAA database.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1447048</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Byron</FirstName>
<LastName>Steinman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Byron A Steinman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bsteinma@d.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7242163707</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000591077</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota Duluth</Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<ZipCode>558123011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2187267582</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1049 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071508873</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota Duluth]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>558122496</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1577</Code>
<Text>GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~76801</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~99569</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~85755</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project was to produce Holocene length records of hydroclimate (e.g. drought) in western North America using oxygen isotope analysis of lake sediment and to use these records to provide insight into ocean-atmosphere circulation responses to changes in Earth&rsquo;s orbit and other external forcing factors. A complimentary objective of this project was to synthesize these data with climate model simulation results in order to better understand internal variability affecting ENSO dynamics and hydroclimate teleconnections. The scientific knowledge obtained through this research has the potential to inform water management strategies by 1) providing a perspective that extends much farther back in time than historical observations and 2) revealing links between internal variability processes in the Pacific basin and climate in North America.</p> <p>The main finding of this research is that there appears to have been a gradual shift in broad-scale atmospheric circulation patterns across North America around 4,000 years ago likely in response to changes in the nature and spatial expression of the El Nino Southern Oscillation. The lake sediment based paleodata produced herein support this idea and are consistent with the findings of prior research (e.g. Liu et al. 2014 &ndash; reference below).</p> <p>This award supported Principal Investigator Steinman while he was employed as an Assistant Professor and was integral in the successful promotion of PI Steinman to tenured Associate Professor. This award also provided support for four Masters (MS) students, of whom three have completed their degrees (with one expected to finish in 2021). Of these four students, three are from groups underrepresented in the sciences.</p> <p>The research conducted as part of this award resulted in the following products at the University of Minnesota Duluth (UMD) (in collaboration with the University of Pittsburgh and the Pennsylvania State University):</p> <p>1 &ndash; the development of four Holocene length oxygen isotope records from lakes located in the Pacific Northwest. Three of these records were developed by MS students at UMD. These data either have been (or upon publication will be) made publicly available through the NOAA NCEI paleoclimate database. https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/data-access/paleoclimatology-data</p> <p>2 &ndash; a hydrologic and isotope mass balance model that can be used to quantitatively interpret lake sediment-based oxygen isotope records in order to produce estimates of past precipitation variability. The development of the model was the basis of a UMD graduate student&rsquo;s MS thesis.</p> <p>3 &ndash; over ten peer reviewed manuscripts, with several more in various stages of development. A selection appears below.</p> <p>4 &ndash; numerous abstracts (with associated oral and/or poster presentations) published as part of regional, national, and international science meetings attended by PI Steinman and his graduate students.</p> <p><em>2019, Steinman, B.A., D.B. Nelson, M.B. Abbott, N.D. Stansell, M.S. Finkenbinder, and B.P. Finney. Lake sediment records of Holocene hydroclimate and impacts of the Mount Mazama eruption, north-central Washington, USA. Quaternary Science Reviews 204: 17&ndash;36.</em></p> <p>2017, Cheung, A.H., M.E. Mann, B.A. Steinman, L.M. Frankcombe, M.H. England, and S.K. Miller. Reply to Comment on &lsquo;Comparison of Low Frequency Internal Climate Variability in CMIP5 Models and Observations&rsquo;. Journal of Climate 30: 9773&ndash;9782.</p> <p>2017, Cheung, A.H., M.E. Mann, B.A. Steinman, L.M. Frankcombe, M.H. England, and S.K. Miller. Comparison of Low Frequency Internal Climate Variability in CMIP5 Models and Observations. Journal of Climate 30: 4763&ndash;4776.</p> <p><em>2016</em>, Steinman, B.A., D.P. Pompeani, M.B. Abbott, J.D. Ortiz, N.D. Stansell, L. Mihindukalasooriya, A.L. Hillman, and M.S. Finkenbinder. Oxygen isotope records of Holocene climate variability in the Pacific Northwest. <em>Quaternary Science Reviews </em>142: 40-60.</p> <p class="Normal1"><em>2016</em>, Anderson, L., M. Berkelhammer, J. Barron, B.A. Steinman, B.P. Finney, and M.B. Abbott. North American Rocky Mountain hydroclimate recorded in lake oxygen isotopes:&nbsp; Holocene patterns and variability at multi-decadal to millennial time scales. <em>Global and Planetary Change </em>137: 131&ndash;148.</p> <p><em>2015</em>, Steinman<sup>*</sup>, B.A., L.M. Frankcombe<sup>*</sup>, M.E. Mann, S.K. Miller, and M.H. England. Response to Comment on &ldquo;Atlantic and Pacific multidecadal oscillations and Northern Hemisphere temperatures&rdquo;. <em>Science</em> 350: 1326-c. <sup>*</sup>Co-first authors.</p> <p><em>2015</em>, Frankcombe, L.M., M.H. England, M.E. Mann, and B.A. Steinman. Separating Internal Variability from the Externally Forced Climate Response. <em>Journal of Climate</em> 28: 8184&ndash;8202.</p> <p><em>2015</em>, Steinman, B.A.,&nbsp; M.E. Mann, and S.K. Miller. Atlantic and Pacific multidecadal oscillations and northern hemisphere temperatures. <em>Science </em>347: 988&ndash;991.</p> <p>Liu, Z., Yoshimura, K., Bowen, G.J., Buenning, N.H., Risi, C., Welker, J.M., Yuan, F., 2014. Paired oxygen isotope records reveal modern North American atmospheric dynamics during the Holocene. Nat. Commun. 5, 3701. http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncomms4701.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/06/2021<br>      Modified by: Byron&nbsp;A&nbsp;Steinman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1447048/1447048_10350652_1617753543624_WiemerAGU2019--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1447048/1447048_10350652_1617753543624_WiemerAGU2019--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Wiemer et al. 2020 AGU poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1447048/1447048_10350652_1617753543624_WiemerAGU2019--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Wiemer et al. 2020 AGU poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Poster presentation of graduate student Ali Wiemer at AGU 2019 Fall Meeting.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Wiemer and Byron Steinman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Byron&nbsp;A&nbsp;Steinman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Wiemer et al. 2020 AGU poster</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project was to produce Holocene length records of hydroclimate (e.g. drought) in western North America using oxygen isotope analysis of lake sediment and to use these records to provide insight into ocean-atmosphere circulation responses to changes in Earth’s orbit and other external forcing factors. A complimentary objective of this project was to synthesize these data with climate model simulation results in order to better understand internal variability affecting ENSO dynamics and hydroclimate teleconnections. The scientific knowledge obtained through this research has the potential to inform water management strategies by 1) providing a perspective that extends much farther back in time than historical observations and 2) revealing links between internal variability processes in the Pacific basin and climate in North America.  The main finding of this research is that there appears to have been a gradual shift in broad-scale atmospheric circulation patterns across North America around 4,000 years ago likely in response to changes in the nature and spatial expression of the El Nino Southern Oscillation. The lake sediment based paleodata produced herein support this idea and are consistent with the findings of prior research (e.g. Liu et al. 2014 &ndash; reference below).  This award supported Principal Investigator Steinman while he was employed as an Assistant Professor and was integral in the successful promotion of PI Steinman to tenured Associate Professor. This award also provided support for four Masters (MS) students, of whom three have completed their degrees (with one expected to finish in 2021). Of these four students, three are from groups underrepresented in the sciences.  The research conducted as part of this award resulted in the following products at the University of Minnesota Duluth (UMD) (in collaboration with the University of Pittsburgh and the Pennsylvania State University):  1 &ndash; the development of four Holocene length oxygen isotope records from lakes located in the Pacific Northwest. Three of these records were developed by MS students at UMD. These data either have been (or upon publication will be) made publicly available through the NOAA NCEI paleoclimate database. https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/data-access/paleoclimatology-data  2 &ndash; a hydrologic and isotope mass balance model that can be used to quantitatively interpret lake sediment-based oxygen isotope records in order to produce estimates of past precipitation variability. The development of the model was the basis of a UMD graduate student’s MS thesis.  3 &ndash; over ten peer reviewed manuscripts, with several more in various stages of development. A selection appears below.  4 &ndash; numerous abstracts (with associated oral and/or poster presentations) published as part of regional, national, and international science meetings attended by PI Steinman and his graduate students.  2019, Steinman, B.A., D.B. Nelson, M.B. Abbott, N.D. Stansell, M.S. Finkenbinder, and B.P. Finney. Lake sediment records of Holocene hydroclimate and impacts of the Mount Mazama eruption, north-central Washington, USA. Quaternary Science Reviews 204: 17&ndash;36.  2017, Cheung, A.H., M.E. Mann, B.A. Steinman, L.M. Frankcombe, M.H. England, and S.K. Miller. Reply to Comment on ‘Comparison of Low Frequency Internal Climate Variability in CMIP5 Models and Observations’. Journal of Climate 30: 9773&ndash;9782.  2017, Cheung, A.H., M.E. Mann, B.A. Steinman, L.M. Frankcombe, M.H. England, and S.K. Miller. Comparison of Low Frequency Internal Climate Variability in CMIP5 Models and Observations. Journal of Climate 30: 4763&ndash;4776.  2016, Steinman, B.A., D.P. Pompeani, M.B. Abbott, J.D. Ortiz, N.D. Stansell, L. Mihindukalasooriya, A.L. Hillman, and M.S. Finkenbinder. Oxygen isotope records of Holocene climate variability in the Pacific Northwest. Quaternary Science Reviews 142: 40-60. 2016, Anderson, L., M. Berkelhammer, J. Barron, B.A. Steinman, B.P. Finney, and M.B. Abbott. North American Rocky Mountain hydroclimate recorded in lake oxygen isotopes:  Holocene patterns and variability at multi-decadal to millennial time scales. Global and Planetary Change 137: 131&ndash;148.  2015, Steinman*, B.A., L.M. Frankcombe*, M.E. Mann, S.K. Miller, and M.H. England. Response to Comment on "Atlantic and Pacific multidecadal oscillations and Northern Hemisphere temperatures". Science 350: 1326-c. *Co-first authors.  2015, Frankcombe, L.M., M.H. England, M.E. Mann, and B.A. Steinman. Separating Internal Variability from the Externally Forced Climate Response. Journal of Climate 28: 8184&ndash;8202.  2015, Steinman, B.A.,  M.E. Mann, and S.K. Miller. Atlantic and Pacific multidecadal oscillations and northern hemisphere temperatures. Science 347: 988&ndash;991.  Liu, Z., Yoshimura, K., Bowen, G.J., Buenning, N.H., Risi, C., Welker, J.M., Yuan, F., 2014. Paired oxygen isotope records reveal modern North American atmospheric dynamics during the Holocene. Nat. Commun. 5, 3701. http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncomms4701.          Last Modified: 04/06/2021       Submitted by: Byron A Steinman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
