<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BIGDATA: F: DKM: Spectral Analysis and Control of Evolving Large Scale Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>During the last decade, the study of complex networks has diffused through many branches of science. How do we characterize the connectivity structure of the Internet, the power grid, or the human brain? Are there universal principles underlying the structure of these diverse systems? The availability of massive databases and reliable tools for data analysis provide a powerful framework to explore these structural questions. Furthermore, as the structure of most real-world networks is inherently evolving, an understanding of the dynamical complexity of networks is needed to provide a realistic description of such networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop efficient algorithms to analyze structural properties of large-scale networks. The PIs will also explore the connection between local structural properties and global spectral graph properties of relevance, such as the spectral radius of the adjacency matrix or the spectral gap of the Laplacian. The analysis will be extended to time-evolving networks and dynamic models of network evolution will be developed. Three scientific objectives of this proposal are:  (1) designing algorithms to efficiently estimate local and global structural  properties of large-scale networks, (2) relating  local structural properties of a graph with its global spectral properties, using tools from spectral graph theory and convex optimization, and  (3) developing predictive models of network evolution, as well as control strategies to drive the evolution of the network structure towards desirable spectral properties. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Networks are ubiquitous (the Internet, the web, biological, and social networks to name a few), and are continually evolving. Thus, developing efficient tools for understanding the evolution of structural and spectral properties of networks is of great relevance to many scientific disciplines. The project will support and train one PhD student, as well as involve undergraduate students in research at the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For further information see the project web site at:  &lt;http://sites.google.com/site/victormpreciado/research-projects/nsf_bigdata_2014&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1447470</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjeev</FirstName>
<LastName>Khanna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjeev Khanna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sanjeev@cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158980375</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjeev</FirstName>
<LastName>Khanna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjeev Khanna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sanjeev@cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158980375</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/16/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>VICTOR</FirstName>
<LastName>PRECIADO</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>VICTOR M PRECIADO</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>preciado@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158987293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630510</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>VICTOR</FirstName>
<LastName>PRECIADO</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>VICTOR M PRECIADO</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>preciado@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158987293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630510</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/16/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of the University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3451 Walnut Street P-221 FB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CCF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-0432e2b1-0f1f-ac7d-3826-8fae0a09d902"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Spectral graph methods have become a fundamental tool in the analysis of large complex networks, and related disciplines, with a broad range of applications across computer science. The eigenvalue spectrum of a graph is closely connected to the dynamical behavior of dynamical processes taking place over them, such as viral spreading processes, synchronization of oscillators, or distributed algorithms.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In this project, we have exploited this connection to find efficient techniques to contain viral epidemic outbreaks using a finite number of resources. These resources can be, for example, the fabrication and distribution of vaccines, traffic control actions, or even disease-awareness campaigns. Each one of these actions have an associated cost and, using tools from convex optimization, we have proposed a new technique for finding the optimal distribution of resources by solving a spectral graph design problem. Moreover, we have developed fast algorithms for solving the problem of finding the minimum number of nodes that need to be driven by an external input so that the resulting system can be steered towards any desired state. In particular, we showed that this problem is equivalent to the classical maximum bipartite matching problem. Furthermore, we have developed a new methodology to analyze the tradeoff between the number of nodes that are needed to actuate in order to drive the dynamics of a system towards a desired state in a given timeframe. Finally, we have also developed sublinear algorithms for estimating many well-studied graph parameters, as well as established formal barriers to obtaining better performance guarantees. &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Further impact of this research project stems from an educational agenda integrated into the Networked and Social Systems (NETS) program at the University of Pennsylvania. Given the importance of spectral methods in network analysis, the research undertaken in the context of this project is of inherent interest to NETS students. At the level of K-12 education, PI Preciado has lectured in a course in the Engineering Summer Academy at Penn (ESAP). ESAP provides high-school students with the opportunity to experience college-level coursework on Network Science and Engineering during an intense three-week program. PI Khanna has engaged high-school students by giving lectures on the broad theme of algorithmic thinking. The PIs hope that these efforts have contributed towards getting high-school students excited about STEM undergraduate education. The project has also supported mentoring of PhD students as well as supported short-term projects for undergraduate students at Penn to give them exposure to graduate-level research tasks.</span></p> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Victor&nbsp;M&nbsp;Preciado</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Spectral graph methods have become a fundamental tool in the analysis of large complex networks, and related disciplines, with a broad range of applications across computer science. The eigenvalue spectrum of a graph is closely connected to the dynamical behavior of dynamical processes taking place over them, such as viral spreading processes, synchronization of oscillators, or distributed algorithms. In this project, we have exploited this connection to find efficient techniques to contain viral epidemic outbreaks using a finite number of resources. These resources can be, for example, the fabrication and distribution of vaccines, traffic control actions, or even disease-awareness campaigns. Each one of these actions have an associated cost and, using tools from convex optimization, we have proposed a new technique for finding the optimal distribution of resources by solving a spectral graph design problem. Moreover, we have developed fast algorithms for solving the problem of finding the minimum number of nodes that need to be driven by an external input so that the resulting system can be steered towards any desired state. In particular, we showed that this problem is equivalent to the classical maximum bipartite matching problem. Furthermore, we have developed a new methodology to analyze the tradeoff between the number of nodes that are needed to actuate in order to drive the dynamics of a system towards a desired state in a given timeframe. Finally, we have also developed sublinear algorithms for estimating many well-studied graph parameters, as well as established formal barriers to obtaining better performance guarantees.    Further impact of this research project stems from an educational agenda integrated into the Networked and Social Systems (NETS) program at the University of Pennsylvania. Given the importance of spectral methods in network analysis, the research undertaken in the context of this project is of inherent interest to NETS students. At the level of K-12 education, PI Preciado has lectured in a course in the Engineering Summer Academy at Penn (ESAP). ESAP provides high-school students with the opportunity to experience college-level coursework on Network Science and Engineering during an intense three-week program. PI Khanna has engaged high-school students by giving lectures on the broad theme of algorithmic thinking. The PIs hope that these efforts have contributed towards getting high-school students excited about STEM undergraduate education. The project has also supported mentoring of PhD students as well as supported short-term projects for undergraduate students at Penn to give them exposure to graduate-level research tasks.        Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Victor M Preciado]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
