<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2015 AMS Summer Institute in Algebraic Geometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>248620.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>248620</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The American Mathematical Society Summer Research Institute in Algebraic Geometry will be held July 13-31, 2015 on the campus of the University of Utah in Salt Lake City. Since the 1960s, the US algebraic geometry community has organized decennial meetings under the auspices of the American Mathematical Society. These extended summer conferences summarized progress in the field and pointed to future developments. The resulting proceedings volumes have been valuable references for generations of algebraic geometers. As the field has grown, these meetings help different communities within algebraic geometry keep in contact and current on the broader trends in the field. This award supports travel and local expenses for approximately 200 of the anticipated 600 participants in the 2015 summer research institute.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The last decade has seen major advances in arithmetic geometry, birational geometry, derived algebraic geometry, derived categories of coherent sheaves, enumerative geometry, geometric representation theory, Hodge theory, Kaehler-Einstein metrics and stability, and p-adic geometry. The institute will offer morning plenary talks by top experts summarizing recent progress, and afternoon parallel seminars with more detailed discussion of relevant techniques. The institute will support participation by many young researchers, as their exposure to the breadth of modern algebraic geometry will set the research agenda for the coming decades. More details about the institute can found at the following two websites:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.ams.org/meetings/amsconf/summerinst-2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/2015summerinstitute/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1447423</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>T. Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>T. Christine Stevens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tcs@ams.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4014554130</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000191112</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
<LastName>Maycock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ellen J Maycock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ejm@ams.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4014554101</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244079</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/02/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brendan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hassett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brendan E Hassett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Brendan_Hassett@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018637961</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tommaso</FirstName>
<LastName>de Fernex</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tommaso de Fernex</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>defernex@math.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015816851</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000299015</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Mathematical Society</Name>
<CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>029042294</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4014554150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007870827</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN MATHEMATICAL SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007870827</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Mathematical Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029042213</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Charles Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~248620</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The American Mathematical Society (AMS) has organized Summer Research Institutes in Algebraic Geometry for many years: Boulder (1954), Woods Hole (1964), Arcata (1974), Bowdoin (1985), Santa Cruz (1995), and Seattle (2005). Many of the leading results of the field were presented at these meetings. And the associated proceedings volumes have become indispensible references for generations of researchers. &nbsp;</p> <p>The 2015 AMS Summer Research Institute in Algebraic Geometry was held at the University of Utah, and organized in collaboration with the Clay Mathematics Institute (CMI). The National Science Foundation (NSF) provided the majority of financial support, with additional contributions by the National Security Agency, the Simons Foundation, and the European Mathematical Society.</p> <p>The 2015 Summer Research Institute is perhaps the largest and broadest meeting ever held in algebraic geometry. There were 742 participants from 28 countries, the majority being graduate students and recent PhD's. About 357 individuals received travel and housing support from NSF - almost 3/4 were students and recent graduates. The scientific program ran for three weeks and included 16 plenary lecturers, 144 invited lectures, 72 contributed talks, and 64 poster presentations. These touched on most branches of the field: algebraic cycles, arithmetic fundamental groups, analytic techniques, birational geometry, commutative algebra, connections with topology and homotopy theory, derived categories, enumerative geometry, geometric representation theory, Hodge theory, moduli theory, p-adic techniques, rational points, and tropical geometry.</p> <p>What distinguishes the AMS Summer Research Institute from typical conferences and workshops? First, it offers experts in different specialties the opportunity to interact with each other. Some leading algebraic geometers only cross paths every ten years at the Summer Research Institutes. Second, it is the unique forum where students and postdocs can view the full panorama of algebraic geometry. Thus it offers an important check on centrifugal forces in algebraic geometry and reinforces the fundamental unity of the subject.</p> <p>With the support of CMI, 170 invited lectures were live-streamed, recorded, and archived online. We expect these will be a valuable resource for years to come -- some videos have already been accessed hundreds of times. The organizers are preparing a two-volume set of contributions growing out of lectures given at the meeting. This will include over 40 manuscripts on the full range of topics covered at the Summer Research Institute and will be published jointly by AMS and CMI.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2017<br>      Modified by: T. Christine&nbsp;Stevens</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The American Mathematical Society (AMS) has organized Summer Research Institutes in Algebraic Geometry for many years: Boulder (1954), Woods Hole (1964), Arcata (1974), Bowdoin (1985), Santa Cruz (1995), and Seattle (2005). Many of the leading results of the field were presented at these meetings. And the associated proceedings volumes have become indispensible references for generations of researchers.    The 2015 AMS Summer Research Institute in Algebraic Geometry was held at the University of Utah, and organized in collaboration with the Clay Mathematics Institute (CMI). The National Science Foundation (NSF) provided the majority of financial support, with additional contributions by the National Security Agency, the Simons Foundation, and the European Mathematical Society.  The 2015 Summer Research Institute is perhaps the largest and broadest meeting ever held in algebraic geometry. There were 742 participants from 28 countries, the majority being graduate students and recent PhD's. About 357 individuals received travel and housing support from NSF - almost 3/4 were students and recent graduates. The scientific program ran for three weeks and included 16 plenary lecturers, 144 invited lectures, 72 contributed talks, and 64 poster presentations. These touched on most branches of the field: algebraic cycles, arithmetic fundamental groups, analytic techniques, birational geometry, commutative algebra, connections with topology and homotopy theory, derived categories, enumerative geometry, geometric representation theory, Hodge theory, moduli theory, p-adic techniques, rational points, and tropical geometry.  What distinguishes the AMS Summer Research Institute from typical conferences and workshops? First, it offers experts in different specialties the opportunity to interact with each other. Some leading algebraic geometers only cross paths every ten years at the Summer Research Institutes. Second, it is the unique forum where students and postdocs can view the full panorama of algebraic geometry. Thus it offers an important check on centrifugal forces in algebraic geometry and reinforces the fundamental unity of the subject.  With the support of CMI, 170 invited lectures were live-streamed, recorded, and archived online. We expect these will be a valuable resource for years to come -- some videos have already been accessed hundreds of times. The organizers are preparing a two-volume set of contributions growing out of lectures given at the meeting. This will include over 40 manuscripts on the full range of topics covered at the Summer Research Institute and will be published jointly by AMS and CMI.              Last Modified: 03/31/2017       Submitted by: T. Christine Stevens]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
