<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Data Privacy for Smart Meter Data: A Scenario-Based Study</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>266101.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>266101</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Smart electric meters comprise one key technology element in an overall strategy to modernize the nation's energy infrastructure. Smart meters capture data on household energy usage at frequent intervals and transmit those data to utility companies, who use the data to automate meter reading and billing, detect and respond to outages, and manage grid operations. Data collected over time can be used to forecast demand, understand customer behavior and develop new service and pricing plans.  In the long run, these data can drive forecasting and control models that allow utilities to respond rapidly to fluctuations in power demand with compensatory load control strategies. This capability can reduce the magnitude of peak demand, thereby reducing both infrastructure costs and the consumption of fossil fuels that power peak generation facilities. Despite these advantages, smart meter data also appear to create powerful customer privacy concerns that may inhibit the adoption of smart meter technology by utilities. To address privacy concerns pertaining to the smart meter data, this project proposes three studies: Study 1 uses public data on electricity usage to develop a set of privacy scenarios that will be tested in focus groups to explore consumer privacy concerns. Study 2 involves a quasi-experiment to assess key dimensions of the scenarios and help identify which scenario has the highest level of acceptability to consumers. Study 3 involves one-on-one discussions with utility company representatives to develop a toolbox of communication methods and content that balance consumers' privacy concerns with the goals and constraints of utilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current theoretical model of privacy and technology, based on an information boundary framework, posits that consumers' willingness to share private information is rooted in the nature of the relationship with the party with whom the information is shared. Although a number of researchers have applied this information boundary framework to intra-organizational situations, the framework has not been tested in the context of smart meter data privacy. In the proposed sequence of three studies, this project gathers data from informants with the intention of understanding whether the information boundary framework is applicable to examining the relationships between consumers and regulated monopolies. The proposed project provides insights into public attitudes and concerns, as well as industry practices and policies regarding privacy of smart meter data. Through direct interaction with utility companies, as well as dissemination at industry conferences, in trade journals and through the media, the researchers will share their findings with practitioners, regulators and others who can create solutions that give customers confidence about the protection of their data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1447589</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Stanton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey M Stanton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmstanto@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154432879</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Dedrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Dedrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdedrick@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154432807</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000609573</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[School of Information Studies]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441190</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[324 Hinds Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~266101</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual merit</span></p> <p>The objective of this project was to identify consumers&rsquo; perceptions of privacy concerns raised by the deployment of smart electric meters. Specifically, the study asked:</p> <ul> <li>How do consumers perceive      privacy risks when presented with information about the nature of smart      meter data collection and use?</li> <li>How do utility companies      currently protect data privacy and how well do their policies and      practices correspond to the privacy concerns of consumers? </li> </ul> <p>Our theoretical model of privacy and technology, based on an information boundary framework, posited that consumers&rsquo; willingness to share private information is rooted in individuals&rsquo; beliefs about the nature of their relationship with the message audience (institutional, aggregate, or individual), the expected uses of revealed information, and the expected benefits of revealing information.&rdquo;<em> </em></p> <p>Although a number of researchers have applied this information boundary framework to intra-organizational situations (such as employee monitoring), the framework has not yet been tested in the context of consumer privacy. In this project, we elicited consumer privacy attitudes through focus groups and an online survey, and gathered data on utility privacy policies through interviews and by collecting privacy statements from utility web sites.</p> <p>Eight focus groups were conducted in four cities. Participants reviewed scenarios that illustrated potential privacy issues and shared their reactions.&nbsp; Based on coding and analyzing the text and video of the focus groups, we identified four common themes that emerged with regard to customers' attitudes toward smart meter data privacy:</p> <p>-&nbsp; perceived benefit of having access to smart meter data</p> <p>-&nbsp; perceived control over the use and sharing of data by the utility</p> <p>- &nbsp;perceived risks associated with loss of privacy</p> <p>- &nbsp;value of privacy, or how much an individual generally cares about privacy</p> <p>These findings generally accorded with existing privacy literature, but the appearance of perceived benefit in consumer&rsquo;s thinking about privacy was novel. &nbsp;Cluster analysis of these themes revealed that three of them (perceived control, perceived risk (reverse coded) and value of privacy) tended to move in the same direction, while perceived benefit was negatively related to those. In other words, people who saw more benefit from access to the data expressed fewer concerns about possible risk and lack of control, and didn't value privacy as much in general. There were also differences for certain demographic variables, including age and education, with older and less highly educated participants fitting in the cluster that saw less benefit, felt less control, and perceived greater risk.</p> <p>The online survey used a 2x2 experimental manipulation, with participants seeing one of two utility bills and one of two advertisements for energy efficient appliances with questions related to the four themes from the focus groups, as well as demographic information.&nbsp; The goal of the experiment was to examine the impacts of utilities&rsquo; ostensive purpose of data collection, as well as the way that the utility had shared information with the advertiser. We hypothesized that perceived risk would increase when information sharing between companies was more salient and that perceived benefit would increase based upon how actionable the energy use information was.&nbsp; These survey data require further analysis.</p> <p>Interviews with utility representatives showed that they treated privacy primarily with respect to legal requirements, while mainly neglecting the customer concerns that were identified in focus groups. The language in utility privacy policies likewise was "legalistic" in many cases, and sometimes used vague terms or phrases giving the utility flexibility in how they collect, use and share customer data. We conclude that there is a disconnect between consumers&rsquo; privacy concerns and the privacy policies of utilities.</p> <p>Analysis of these research data continues and results will be submitted as a conference paper and a journal article. The audience for this work includes scholars working in the areas of privacy, technology adoption and public policy, as well as managers of utility firms.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader impacts</span></p> <p>Partial results of this research were presented at a major utility industry conference, the 2016 Grid of the Future Symposium in Philadelphia.&nbsp; The results also have been considered at a roundtable discussion with utility company representatives in Washington D.C. in 2016.&nbsp; We plan to continue to share the results with the utility industry, regulators, consulting firms and other industry experts involved in privacy issues and policies. We believe our work will have broader impacts in encouraging the adoption of privacy policies that are responsive to the concerns of consumers, and in improving communication between utilities and consumers about privacy issues.</p> <p>The project supported one recent Ph.D. graduate and one Ph.D. student from Syracuse University&rsquo;s School of Information Studies.&nbsp; The project also supported two master&rsquo;s students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;Dedrick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit  The objective of this project was to identify consumers? perceptions of privacy concerns raised by the deployment of smart electric meters. Specifically, the study asked:  How do consumers perceive      privacy risks when presented with information about the nature of smart      meter data collection and use? How do utility companies      currently protect data privacy and how well do their policies and      practices correspond to the privacy concerns of consumers?    Our theoretical model of privacy and technology, based on an information boundary framework, posited that consumers? willingness to share private information is rooted in individuals? beliefs about the nature of their relationship with the message audience (institutional, aggregate, or individual), the expected uses of revealed information, and the expected benefits of revealing information."   Although a number of researchers have applied this information boundary framework to intra-organizational situations (such as employee monitoring), the framework has not yet been tested in the context of consumer privacy. In this project, we elicited consumer privacy attitudes through focus groups and an online survey, and gathered data on utility privacy policies through interviews and by collecting privacy statements from utility web sites.  Eight focus groups were conducted in four cities. Participants reviewed scenarios that illustrated potential privacy issues and shared their reactions.  Based on coding and analyzing the text and video of the focus groups, we identified four common themes that emerged with regard to customers' attitudes toward smart meter data privacy:  -  perceived benefit of having access to smart meter data  -  perceived control over the use and sharing of data by the utility  -  perceived risks associated with loss of privacy  -  value of privacy, or how much an individual generally cares about privacy  These findings generally accorded with existing privacy literature, but the appearance of perceived benefit in consumer?s thinking about privacy was novel.  Cluster analysis of these themes revealed that three of them (perceived control, perceived risk (reverse coded) and value of privacy) tended to move in the same direction, while perceived benefit was negatively related to those. In other words, people who saw more benefit from access to the data expressed fewer concerns about possible risk and lack of control, and didn't value privacy as much in general. There were also differences for certain demographic variables, including age and education, with older and less highly educated participants fitting in the cluster that saw less benefit, felt less control, and perceived greater risk.  The online survey used a 2x2 experimental manipulation, with participants seeing one of two utility bills and one of two advertisements for energy efficient appliances with questions related to the four themes from the focus groups, as well as demographic information.  The goal of the experiment was to examine the impacts of utilities? ostensive purpose of data collection, as well as the way that the utility had shared information with the advertiser. We hypothesized that perceived risk would increase when information sharing between companies was more salient and that perceived benefit would increase based upon how actionable the energy use information was.  These survey data require further analysis.  Interviews with utility representatives showed that they treated privacy primarily with respect to legal requirements, while mainly neglecting the customer concerns that were identified in focus groups. The language in utility privacy policies likewise was "legalistic" in many cases, and sometimes used vague terms or phrases giving the utility flexibility in how they collect, use and share customer data. We conclude that there is a disconnect between consumers? privacy concerns and the privacy policies of utilities.  Analysis of these research data continues and results will be submitted as a conference paper and a journal article. The audience for this work includes scholars working in the areas of privacy, technology adoption and public policy, as well as managers of utility firms.  Broader impacts  Partial results of this research were presented at a major utility industry conference, the 2016 Grid of the Future Symposium in Philadelphia.  The results also have been considered at a roundtable discussion with utility company representatives in Washington D.C. in 2016.  We plan to continue to share the results with the utility industry, regulators, consulting firms and other industry experts involved in privacy issues and policies. We believe our work will have broader impacts in encouraging the adoption of privacy policies that are responsive to the concerns of consumers, and in improving communication between utilities and consumers about privacy issues.  The project supported one recent Ph.D. graduate and one Ph.D. student from Syracuse University?s School of Information Studies.  The project also supported two master?s students.          Last Modified: 11/08/2017       Submitted by: Jason Dedrick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
