<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Undergraduate Biology Education Research:  Investigation and Implementation Conference, July 12-17, 2015 at Bates College in Maine</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award has been made to support a Gordon Research Conference on Undergraduate Biology Education Research.  This Conference will take place from July 12-17, 2015 at Bates College in Maine. Undergraduate science education is of critical interest to science education researchers, campus leaders, scientists, politicians, and the nation's technology industry. Among recommendations for reform are calls for increasing the diversity and numbers of students who graduate with STEM, increasing the scale at which evidence-based teaching and learning approaches are used, and increasing the abilities of students to conduct science that is becoming more interdisciplinary in nature. There is now a solid base of research that supports making significant changes to undergraduate programs such as focusing on major concepts and the application of knowledge, using more evidence-based teaching strategies, aligning learning assessment with course outcomes and teaching strategies, providing more research experiences for undergraduate students, and aligning outcomes and pedagogy across high school, community college and four-year institution programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will bring together scholars from communities that rarely interact (biology researchers, biology instructors, science education researchers, faculty development specialists, and leaders of scientific societies) but who are working in overlapping arenas to advance our understanding of what it takes to more systemically change undergraduate biology programs and to synthesize new directions for future research. While the conference will focus on the community engaged in biology instruction, investigators from other disciplines who can contribute to the discussion will also be invited. Key issues to be addressed include: cutting edge instructional and assessment techniques, elucidating the common challenges across biology that impede systemic change in biology programs, identifying the levers for change, describing mechanisms and strategies known for measuring and monitoring change over the long term, and determining the impacts of systemic change on student learning and persistence with a focus on underrepresented minorities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is now a confluence of emerging research and reports, rising up from campuses and spurred by national projects such as Vision and Change, PULSE, and the NSF-funded Research Coordination Networks in Undergraduate Biology Education. This creates an opportunity for participants at this Gordon Research Conference to address issues on the horizon that represent new challenges, strategies, and technologies that have the potential to hasten the rate of change in undergraduate STEM education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1448927</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
<LastName>Uno</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gordon E Uno</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>guno@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4053256281</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000415707</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Elrod</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Elrod</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slelrod@iusb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5745204220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7972</Code>
<Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br />The Gordon Research Conference on Undergraduate Biology Education Research was held at Bates College in Lewiston, Maine from July 12-17, 2015. &nbsp;The Conference was well-attended with 192 participants (attendees list attached). The attendees represented the spectrum of endeavor in this field coming from academia, industry, and government laboratories,<br />both U.S. and foreign scientists, senior researchers, young investigators, and<br />students. Of the 192 attendees, 169 voluntarily responded to a general inquiry regarding ethnicity which appears on our registration forms. Of the 169 respondents, 14% were Minorities &ndash; 4% Hispanic, 5% Asian and 5% African American. Approximately 71% of the participants at the 2015 meeting were women.</p> <p><br />In designing the formal speakers program, emphasis was placed on current unpublished research and discussion of the future target areas in this field. There was a conscious effort to stimulate lively discussion about the key issues in the field today. Time for formal presentations was limited in the interest of group discussions. In order that more scientists could communicate their most recent results, poster presentation time was scheduled. Attached is a copy of the formal schedule and speaker program and the poster program. In addition to these formal interactions, "free time" was scheduled to allow informal discussions. Such discussions are fostering new collaborations and joint efforts in the field.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/10/2015<br>      Modified by: Gordon&nbsp;E&nbsp;Uno</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Gordon Research Conference on Undergraduate Biology Education Research was held at Bates College in Lewiston, Maine from July 12-17, 2015.  The Conference was well-attended with 192 participants (attendees list attached). The attendees represented the spectrum of endeavor in this field coming from academia, industry, and government laboratories, both U.S. and foreign scientists, senior researchers, young investigators, and students. Of the 192 attendees, 169 voluntarily responded to a general inquiry regarding ethnicity which appears on our registration forms. Of the 169 respondents, 14% were Minorities &ndash; 4% Hispanic, 5% Asian and 5% African American. Approximately 71% of the participants at the 2015 meeting were women.   In designing the formal speakers program, emphasis was placed on current unpublished research and discussion of the future target areas in this field. There was a conscious effort to stimulate lively discussion about the key issues in the field today. Time for formal presentations was limited in the interest of group discussions. In order that more scientists could communicate their most recent results, poster presentation time was scheduled. Attached is a copy of the formal schedule and speaker program and the poster program. In addition to these formal interactions, "free time" was scheduled to allow informal discussions. Such discussions are fostering new collaborations and joint efforts in the field.       Last Modified: 09/10/2015       Submitted by: Gordon E Uno]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
