<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development of a Dual Energy Micro-focused X-ray Excitation Beam for Chemical Analysis and Materials Characterization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149880.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149880</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will focus on the development of a system for generating microfocus x-ray excitation beams for X-ray fluorescence (micro-XRF) analysis applications. The resulting instrument will create dual-energy x-rays with high flux in a narrow energy band.  Micro-XRF is a powerful, non-destructive, and widely used technique for the determination of elemental composition and elemental mapping, which relies on the measurement of characteristic fluorescent x-rays generated when atoms are excited by x-rays, electrons or other ionizing particles.  This method is used in a broad range of applications including mining, semiconductor, forensics, materials research, and even biological research.  The project will enable development of Micro-XRF systems with substantially improved elemental detection sensitivity over a large range of atomic numbers (Z) and with higher spatial resolution. The proposed product is expected to significantly impact more than half of the current $900 million x-ray fluorescence market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the development of a coaxial dual mirror system which will focus two x-ray beams of different energies onto the sample at high spatial resolution and high flux, enabling a substantial improvement in spatial resolution and enhancing the compositional spot analysis and mapping capabilities of micro X-ray fluorescence analysis (micro-XRF) applications. The proposed project will result in three major advantages for users of micro-XRF: 1) high analytical sensitivity to both low- and high-atomic number elements by the utilization of two x-ray energy ranges, 2) high x-ray flux due to improved optical design, and 3) a longer working distance which will add flexibility and ease integration of the new device into existing equipment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1448727</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenbing</FirstName>
<LastName>Yun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenbing Yun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wyun801@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9259471469</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000672026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Sigray</Name>
<CityName>Concord</CityName>
<ZipCode>945205348</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9259471469</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5750 Imhoff Drive Ste I</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079183051</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SIGRAY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sigray]]></Name>
<CityName>Walnut Creek</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>945951800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~149880</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sigray has completed its Phase I SBIR project aimed toward development of a microfocus dual energy x-ray excitation beam for micro X-ray fluorescence (micro-XRF) analysis to enable high throughput and high resolution (~5 &micro;m) chemical analysis of a broad range of elements. This excitation beam system is enabled by an innovative x-ray focusing optic comprised of two concentric Wolter mirror lens that collect characteristic x-ray of two substantially separated energies from a bright microfocus source and focus them down onto the same sample spot. In particular, our Phase I goal was to address the most difficult technical challenge of the proposed project by developing a system capable of producing prototypes of the outermost low energy x-ray mirror lens, which requires a large slope that is non-trivial to produce.</p> <p>Sigray successfully developed a proprietary x-ray mirror shaping system, which was used to fabricate 10 prototypes with slopes meeting and exceeding the requirements proposed in Phase I (verified by an optical characterization procedure developed during Phase I). Additionally, the team developed a robust in-house ray tracing program for analysis and simulation of the x-ray mirror lens parameters. While not a deliverable of Phase I, the team piloted a successful research and development project on coating the inner surface of the mirrors, which has the potential to even further improve the performance of the optic and increase its flux.</p> <p class="vert-spacing">The proposed x-ray Wolter optic will enable XRF chemical analysis with substantially higher spatial resolution, higher detection sensitivity and accuracy, of elements over a large atomic numbers and has significant potential to influence the approximately $1B/year global XRF market. This unique capability will enable scientists and engineers with powerful new analysis capabilities in their research and development, or even in-line monitoring applications. For example, the recent advances in manmade materials and products (e.g. electronics, pharmaceuticals) demand increasing information at smaller length scales and at smaller concentrations to make continued improvements. Furthermore, in industries such as natural resources extraction, conventional &ldquo;easy&rdquo; sandstone reservoirs have largely been depleted, leaving complex carbonate and shale reservoirs, which require new analysis techniques that provide high resolution and high sensitivity to determine reservoir mineralogical characteristics and thus optimal extraction processes (a vast majority of the natural resources are left trapped underground &ndash; and in a more difficult to extract state &ndash;due to sub-optimal extraction). Societal benefits also include improving criminal investigations by increasing the accuracy of forensics tests, which typically rely on SEM-EDS for analysis of samples such as gunshot residue but are well-known to have accuracy issues when encountering non-uniform particles and elements at &lt;1% weight.</p> <p class="vert-spacing">Additionally, the x-ray mirror lens prototypes developed have potential to provide substantial cost savings for synchrotron facilities which currently upgrade to micro-scale capabilities by using x-ray optics such as Kirkpatrick-Baez mirrors, which results in the construction of long (and therefore expensive) beamlines. This development will allow for dramatically more compact, less expensive beamlines to upgrade synchrotron facility capabilities, thus removing cost barriers and providing access to research analysis capabilities at critically needed at microscopic dimensions (as such existing beamlines are often oversubscribed), including micro-small angle x-ray scattering (micro-SAXS), micro-x-ray diffraction, and micro x-ray fluorescence for synchrotron users.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Wenbing&nbsp;...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sigray has completed its Phase I SBIR project aimed toward development of a microfocus dual energy x-ray excitation beam for micro X-ray fluorescence (micro-XRF) analysis to enable high throughput and high resolution (~5 &micro;m) chemical analysis of a broad range of elements. This excitation beam system is enabled by an innovative x-ray focusing optic comprised of two concentric Wolter mirror lens that collect characteristic x-ray of two substantially separated energies from a bright microfocus source and focus them down onto the same sample spot. In particular, our Phase I goal was to address the most difficult technical challenge of the proposed project by developing a system capable of producing prototypes of the outermost low energy x-ray mirror lens, which requires a large slope that is non-trivial to produce.  Sigray successfully developed a proprietary x-ray mirror shaping system, which was used to fabricate 10 prototypes with slopes meeting and exceeding the requirements proposed in Phase I (verified by an optical characterization procedure developed during Phase I). Additionally, the team developed a robust in-house ray tracing program for analysis and simulation of the x-ray mirror lens parameters. While not a deliverable of Phase I, the team piloted a successful research and development project on coating the inner surface of the mirrors, which has the potential to even further improve the performance of the optic and increase its flux. The proposed x-ray Wolter optic will enable XRF chemical analysis with substantially higher spatial resolution, higher detection sensitivity and accuracy, of elements over a large atomic numbers and has significant potential to influence the approximately $1B/year global XRF market. This unique capability will enable scientists and engineers with powerful new analysis capabilities in their research and development, or even in-line monitoring applications. For example, the recent advances in manmade materials and products (e.g. electronics, pharmaceuticals) demand increasing information at smaller length scales and at smaller concentrations to make continued improvements. Furthermore, in industries such as natural resources extraction, conventional "easy" sandstone reservoirs have largely been depleted, leaving complex carbonate and shale reservoirs, which require new analysis techniques that provide high resolution and high sensitivity to determine reservoir mineralogical characteristics and thus optimal extraction processes (a vast majority of the natural resources are left trapped underground &ndash; and in a more difficult to extract state &ndash;due to sub-optimal extraction). Societal benefits also include improving criminal investigations by increasing the accuracy of forensics tests, which typically rely on SEM-EDS for analysis of samples such as gunshot residue but are well-known to have accuracy issues when encountering non-uniform particles and elements at &lt;1% weight. Additionally, the x-ray mirror lens prototypes developed have potential to provide substantial cost savings for synchrotron facilities which currently upgrade to micro-scale capabilities by using x-ray optics such as Kirkpatrick-Baez mirrors, which results in the construction of long (and therefore expensive) beamlines. This development will allow for dramatically more compact, less expensive beamlines to upgrade synchrotron facility capabilities, thus removing cost barriers and providing access to research analysis capabilities at critically needed at microscopic dimensions (as such existing beamlines are often oversubscribed), including micro-small angle x-ray scattering (micro-SAXS), micro-x-ray diffraction, and micro x-ray fluorescence for synchrotron users.            Last Modified: 07/01/2015       Submitted by: Wenbing Yun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
