<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Cost-effective production of biopolymers for eco-friendly erosion control and soil revegetation with synthetic microbial consortia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader  impact/commercial  potential  of this Small Business  Technology  Transfer Phase I project will be the development of a new biological route, based on microbial co- cultures,   for   efficient   production   of   an   environmentally friendly (eco-friendly)   mixture   of   biopolymers   for revegetation and erosion control applications, with a $375 million potential market. Tackifying polymers (adhesive-like materials) are widely used to stabilize loose soils/mulches  and  promote  revegetation  via  aggregation  and  water  retention.  This project will focus on producing an eco-friendly biopolymer mixture of microbial polyamino acids and polysaccharides that has improved properties compared to conventional tackifiers, providing superior adhesion and water retention. Despite promising potential and market demand for more effective bio-based tackifiers, these microbial  biopolymers  have  never  been  investigated  for  use  in  this  application,  as current   fermentation   methods   for  producing   them   are  not  economical.   The   key innovation in this project entails engineering microbial co-cultures to produce relatively expensive  biopolymer  precursors  in-situ  from  beet  molasses,  an  inexpensive  and renewable   feedstock,   resulting   in   dramatic   cost   reductions.   Beyond   biopolymer production, the proposed approach of engineering co-cultures for in-situ precursor production  (ISPP)  is potentially  transferrable  to many  other  bioprocesses,  and  could offer  more  efficient,  cost-effective  routes  for  producing  other  bio-based  fuels  and chemicals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this Phase I research project are to i) implement, experimentally characterize, and model co-culture prototypes to demonstrate technoeconomic feasibility of biopolymer production with this approach, and ii) validate the performance of these biopolymers  in  revegetation  and  erosion  control  applications.  Completion  of  these objectives  will  demonstrate  proof-of-concept,  and  represent  important  technical milestones   towards   commercializing   this   technology.   The   proposed   approach   of engineering synthetic microbial consortia represents a distinct shift from the conventional paradigm   of   utilizing   single-species   monocultures   for   bioprocessing   and   offers substantial potential cost-savings through in-situ precursor production and process consolidation. Despite these potential benefits, synthetic microbial consortia for bioprocessing have not been explored in a commercial context due to the level of high technical risk entailed. Building on prior NSF-funded academic research in engineering consortia  for  cellulosic  biofuel  production,  this  project  will  implement  microbial  co- cultures  capable  of  producing  polyamino  acids  /  polysaccharides  through  ISPP  and perform a preliminary investigation of the interplay between ecological interactions, environmental  conditions,  and  key  performance  metrics  (such  as  titer,  yield,  and biopolymer  composition).  This  project  will  also  investigate  the  novel  application  of polyamino acids / polysaccharides as bio-tackifiers for revegetation and erosion control, enabled by the potential cost-savings of the proposed co-culture.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1448990</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoxia</FirstName>
<LastName>Lin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoxia Lin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ninalin@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346478026</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000202533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Minty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy J Minty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jeremy.minty@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2489530594</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000670230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ecovia Renewables Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481039002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2489530594</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>600 South Wagner Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 15]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079363071</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ECOVIA RENEWABLES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092136</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2300 Hayward Street, 3235 HH Dow]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview and Project Background.</strong> The primary goal of this STTR Phase I project was to demonstrate the feasibility an innovative bioprocess for efficient production of polyglutamic acid (PGA). PGA is a non-toxic, renewable, and biodegradable polymer that can potentially serve as a bio-based, eco-friendly replacement for conventional polyacrylates (PAC) and polyacrylamides (PAM), which are major petroleum derived industrial commodity chemicals. However, current methods for producing PGA are not economical, and despite promising potential, commercial application of PGA has been minimal. Inspired by the sophisticated metabolic capabilities of natural microbial communities, this project aimed to engineer a microbial co-culture process to cost-effectively produce PGA via<em> in-situ </em>precursor production (ISPP) from low-cost raw materials. The key innovation of this approach is that costly PGA precursors are produced <em>in-situ </em>(instead of being purchased)<em>, </em>which substantially reduces PGA production costs and enables PGA applications that were not previously economical.</p> <p>Furthermore, this project also focused on developing PGA-based materials for commercial applications and validating key performance characteristics. Initially, the project focused on developing PGA based tackifiers for revegetation and erosion control. However, Ecovia identified a more technically and commercially promising opportunity to develop cross-linked PGA superabsorbent polymers (SAP) for absorbent hygiene product (AHP) applications, and the project scope and goals were revised accordingly. Superabsorbent polymers (typically based on PAC/PAM or starch-graft polymers) are materials that can absorb several hundred times their weight in liquid, and are widely used in the absorbent cores of hygiene products, with disposable diapers representing approximately 80% of the global SAP market of $6B. Increasing consumer preferences for sustainable personal care products have driven the development of eco-friendly and natural labeled AHP brands, particularly diapers, and these products are currently experiencing strong growth. Ecovia has pursued a promising pivot opportunity to develop PGA-based superabsorbent polymers (SAPs), offering improved performance/cost over incumbent bio-based SAPs, for application in eco-branded diapers and other AHPs. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes Summary. </strong>The team at the University of Michigan and Ecovia Renewables have successful developed a proof-of-concept ISPP prototype process for producing hygiene-grade PGA superabsorbent polymers from crude waste glycerol, an abundant and low-cost by-product of biodiesel production. Through detailed process modeling and economic analysis, the team estimates that the novel production process developed under this grant can reduce the cost of PGA production up to 96% compared to conventional methods. Thus, with further process development, PGA production can likely be cost-competitive with conventional polyacrylamides and polyacrylates. In addition to developing a process prototype, Ecovia has also completed a panel of hygiene industry-standard absorbency tests for prototype PGA SAP material, and has provided samples to prospective customers/partners in the absorbent hygiene products industry for internal evaluation; results from these studies suggest that the prototype PGA SAP material already has competitive performance with incumbent biobased SAPs, and with further optimizations can like meet or exceed the performance characteristics of gold-standard polyacrylates and polyacrylamides.</p> <p>The outcomes of this project have numerous potential environmental, societal, and scientific impacts. Globally, over 2 million metric tons of polyacrylate/polyacrylamide superabsorbent polymers are produced each year from non-renewable fossil feedstocks, 98% of which are used in absorbent hygiene products that are ultimately landfilled. This project developed a renewable, eco-friendly, biodegradable PGA based SAP for hygiene applications that can potentially be highly cost and performance competitive with conventional superabsorbents, facilitating increased commercialization of biodegradable absorbent hygiene products and associated services like diaper composting facilties. Diversion of absorbent hygiene products from landfills can offer significant environmental benefits in developed markets (such as EU and USA). In the longer term, these types of products could offer even more substantial environmental benefits in developing markets struggling with waste management issues (such as India and China), especially as incomes and disposable diaper usage increase. Successful commercialization of this technology at mass market scale will provide a new demand for biobased/agricultural feedstocks (such as waste glycerol) and create numerous "green" jobs through the development of biorefineries to produce PGA SAPs, which will likely be located in rural areas close to feedstock supplies.</p> <p>In addition to potential environmental/societal impacts, this project also advances the current scientific state-of-the-art in industrial bioprocessing. Engineering synthetic microbial consortia / sequential cultures represents a distinct break from the conventional paradigm of utilizing single-species monocultures for bioprocessing and offers significant cost-savings through <em>in-situ</em> precursor production (ISPP) and process consolidation. While this project focused specifically on producing PGA, this new bioprocessing paradigm could offer more efficient, cost-effective routes for producing other biobased fuels and chemicals.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Jeremy&nbsp;J&nbsp;Minty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview and Project Background. The primary goal of this STTR Phase I project was to demonstrate the feasibility an innovative bioprocess for efficient production of polyglutamic acid (PGA). PGA is a non-toxic, renewable, and biodegradable polymer that can potentially serve as a bio-based, eco-friendly replacement for conventional polyacrylates (PAC) and polyacrylamides (PAM), which are major petroleum derived industrial commodity chemicals. However, current methods for producing PGA are not economical, and despite promising potential, commercial application of PGA has been minimal. Inspired by the sophisticated metabolic capabilities of natural microbial communities, this project aimed to engineer a microbial co-culture process to cost-effectively produce PGA via in-situ precursor production (ISPP) from low-cost raw materials. The key innovation of this approach is that costly PGA precursors are produced in-situ (instead of being purchased), which substantially reduces PGA production costs and enables PGA applications that were not previously economical.  Furthermore, this project also focused on developing PGA-based materials for commercial applications and validating key performance characteristics. Initially, the project focused on developing PGA based tackifiers for revegetation and erosion control. However, Ecovia identified a more technically and commercially promising opportunity to develop cross-linked PGA superabsorbent polymers (SAP) for absorbent hygiene product (AHP) applications, and the project scope and goals were revised accordingly. Superabsorbent polymers (typically based on PAC/PAM or starch-graft polymers) are materials that can absorb several hundred times their weight in liquid, and are widely used in the absorbent cores of hygiene products, with disposable diapers representing approximately 80% of the global SAP market of $6B. Increasing consumer preferences for sustainable personal care products have driven the development of eco-friendly and natural labeled AHP brands, particularly diapers, and these products are currently experiencing strong growth. Ecovia has pursued a promising pivot opportunity to develop PGA-based superabsorbent polymers (SAPs), offering improved performance/cost over incumbent bio-based SAPs, for application in eco-branded diapers and other AHPs.    Project Outcomes Summary. The team at the University of Michigan and Ecovia Renewables have successful developed a proof-of-concept ISPP prototype process for producing hygiene-grade PGA superabsorbent polymers from crude waste glycerol, an abundant and low-cost by-product of biodiesel production. Through detailed process modeling and economic analysis, the team estimates that the novel production process developed under this grant can reduce the cost of PGA production up to 96% compared to conventional methods. Thus, with further process development, PGA production can likely be cost-competitive with conventional polyacrylamides and polyacrylates. In addition to developing a process prototype, Ecovia has also completed a panel of hygiene industry-standard absorbency tests for prototype PGA SAP material, and has provided samples to prospective customers/partners in the absorbent hygiene products industry for internal evaluation; results from these studies suggest that the prototype PGA SAP material already has competitive performance with incumbent biobased SAPs, and with further optimizations can like meet or exceed the performance characteristics of gold-standard polyacrylates and polyacrylamides.  The outcomes of this project have numerous potential environmental, societal, and scientific impacts. Globally, over 2 million metric tons of polyacrylate/polyacrylamide superabsorbent polymers are produced each year from non-renewable fossil feedstocks, 98% of which are used in absorbent hygiene products that are ultimately landfilled. This project developed a renewable, eco-friendly, biodegradable PGA based SAP for hygiene applications that can potentially be highly cost and performance competitive with conventional superabsorbents, facilitating increased commercialization of biodegradable absorbent hygiene products and associated services like diaper composting facilties. Diversion of absorbent hygiene products from landfills can offer significant environmental benefits in developed markets (such as EU and USA). In the longer term, these types of products could offer even more substantial environmental benefits in developing markets struggling with waste management issues (such as India and China), especially as incomes and disposable diaper usage increase. Successful commercialization of this technology at mass market scale will provide a new demand for biobased/agricultural feedstocks (such as waste glycerol) and create numerous "green" jobs through the development of biorefineries to produce PGA SAPs, which will likely be located in rural areas close to feedstock supplies.  In addition to potential environmental/societal impacts, this project also advances the current scientific state-of-the-art in industrial bioprocessing. Engineering synthetic microbial consortia / sequential cultures represents a distinct break from the conventional paradigm of utilizing single-species monocultures for bioprocessing and offers significant cost-savings through in-situ precursor production (ISPP) and process consolidation. While this project focused specifically on producing PGA, this new bioprocessing paradigm could offer more efficient, cost-effective routes for producing other biobased fuels and chemicals.             Last Modified: 09/30/2016       Submitted by: Jeremy J Minty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
