<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Foundations of Social and Ethical Responsibility Among Undergraduate Engineering Students: Comparing Across Time, Institutions, and Interventions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>160000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>160000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Parker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recognizing the critical roles played by technical professionals in serving the public and addressing grand&lt;br/&gt;challenges, many formal courses and programs have been created to promote professional responsibility&lt;br/&gt;and ethical integrity among engineering graduates. Other interventions (e.g., service learning programs)&lt;br/&gt;have been developed to more broadly challenge engineering and technology students to see themselves as&lt;br/&gt;engaged citizens and community members. Yet there has been a lack of research on foundational&lt;br/&gt;understandings of social and ethical responsibility among such students, including how these&lt;br/&gt;understandings change over time and through participation in specific types of learning experiences.&lt;br/&gt;Additional empirical evidence is needed to guide ongoing efforts to cultivate enhanced social and ethical&lt;br/&gt;responsibility among future engineers, including by identifying and promoting specific interventions that&lt;br/&gt;have the biggest positive impacts on students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed study responds to these gaps in the existing scholarship by asking the following research&lt;br/&gt;questions: 1) What do engineering students perceive as responsible (and irresponsible) professional&lt;br/&gt;conduct, and what do they perceive as socially just (and unjust) technical practices?, and 2) How do&lt;br/&gt;foundational measures and understandings of social and ethical responsibility change during a four-year&lt;br/&gt;engineering degree program, both in general and in relation to specific kinds of learning experiences? To&lt;br/&gt;investigate these questions, a longitudinal mixed-method study design will collect and analyze&lt;br/&gt;quantitative and qualitative data from undergraduate engineering students at four universities. To improve&lt;br/&gt;transferability of results, these schools will represent a variety of institution types. Each collaborating&lt;br/&gt;school also has large numbers of students in programs of interest, e.g., service-learning and intensified&lt;br/&gt;ethics instruction. Further, the study will give priority to investigating differences in perceptions and&lt;br/&gt;experiences among underrepresented student populations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1449490</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jameson</FirstName>
<LastName>Wetmore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jameson M Wetmore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jameson.wetmore@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807270750</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000295884</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/30/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Seager</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas P Seager</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Thomas.Seager@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807270531</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208067</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Jordan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn S Jordan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Shawn.S.Jordan@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807271405</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000587336</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/30/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7491</Code>
<Text>ETHICS EDU FOR SCI &amp; ENG PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7787</Code>
<Text>EESE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span class="author-15498584 font-color-000000 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato,;"><span class="author-15498584 font-color-000000 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;">Professional engineering ethics education typically encourages engineering students to model virtuous behavior consistent with ethical "whistleblowing."&nbsp; In the traditional model, students are encouraged to make commitments to risk their own personal or professional advancement </span><span class="author-15498584 font-color-222222 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;">in the interest of protecting public health, safety, and welfare.&nbsp; </span><span class="author-15498584 font-color-000000 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;">However, in the context of engineering practice, ethical communications can only be as effective as they are persuasive.&nbsp; Even expert engineers face obstacles to effecting ethical outcomes that may result in a failure to avoid ethical catastrophes, </span><span class="author-15498584 font-color-000000 font-color-222222 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;">despite ethically responsible messaging</span><span class="author-15498584 font-color-000000 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;">.&nbsp; At Arizona State University, this project developed a new module of engineering ethics education that may develop enhanced ethical deliberation skills in engineering students.&nbsp; While students are introduced to the Fundamental Canons of Engineering Ethics, including their obligations to the public, to clients, and to the profession. They are subsequently expected to apply their understanding of the Canon to an analysis of the actions of </span><span class="author-15498584" style="font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; color: #222222;">William LeMessurier</span><span class="author-15498584 font-color-222222 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;"> in the the retrofit of structural connections in the Citicorp Tower in Manhattan.&nbsp; Critical to the activity is their participation in a deliberative jury that is assigned the task of determining the extent to which LeMessurier conformed to the Canon.&nbsp; </span><span class="author-15498584 font-color-000000 font-size-medium" style="color: #222222; font-family: Lato, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px;">By anticipating and refuting counter arguments in their analysis, students are called upon to develop greater power of ethical persuasion that may prepare them to be more effective ethical actors within their professional organizations.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;P&nbsp;Seager</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Professional engineering ethics education typically encourages engineering students to model virtuous behavior consistent with ethical "whistleblowing."  In the traditional model, students are encouraged to make commitments to risk their own personal or professional advancement in the interest of protecting public health, safety, and welfare.  However, in the context of engineering practice, ethical communications can only be as effective as they are persuasive.  Even expert engineers face obstacles to effecting ethical outcomes that may result in a failure to avoid ethical catastrophes, despite ethically responsible messaging.  At Arizona State University, this project developed a new module of engineering ethics education that may develop enhanced ethical deliberation skills in engineering students.  While students are introduced to the Fundamental Canons of Engineering Ethics, including their obligations to the public, to clients, and to the profession. They are subsequently expected to apply their understanding of the Canon to an analysis of the actions of William LeMessurier in the the retrofit of structural connections in the Citicorp Tower in Manhattan.  Critical to the activity is their participation in a deliberative jury that is assigned the task of determining the extent to which LeMessurier conformed to the Canon.  By anticipating and refuting counter arguments in their analysis, students are called upon to develop greater power of ethical persuasion that may prepare them to be more effective ethical actors within their professional organizations.       Last Modified: 10/04/2020       Submitted by: Thomas P Seager]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
