<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Monolithic 3D Integration of Resistive Random Access Memory (ReRAM): A Technological Exploration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>258000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the rapid growth of big data, next generation non-volatile memory technologies are needed to enable a large capacity and fast bandwidth. The resistive random access memory (ReRAM) technology is one of the emerging candidates beyond the scaling limit of today's FLASH technology. The research and development of the ReRAM technology will benefit nearly every digital device available today from consumer electronics to enterprise electronics. It may also spawn new applications involving the computation on the exascale of data, e.g. data mining, machine learning, and bio-informatics etc. thus benefitting the semiconductor industry at large. Student summer internships are planned with the industrial partners, which will be invaluable for broadening the knowledge and skills of the students. The tools and techniques developed in this research will be used in the newly developed seminar course on memory design at ASU. The PI will make simulator tools available for use by other educators, researchers, and industry practitioners. Dissemination of research findings will also be carried out through conference tutorials, panel discussions, and workshops. A concerted effort will be made to involve underrepresented groups and undergraduate students in this research, and also to promote the K-12 students to major in science and engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal aims to tackle the fundamental technological challenges for the monolithic 3D integration of ReRAM. Although the ReRAM technology shows very attractive characteristics at single cell level, at the array level its lower integration density limits its economical competiveness over the mainstream NAND FLASH technology. The project examines the use of monolithic 3D integration of ReRAM as a promising approach for enabling ultra-high density cross-point memory architecture. The proposed research activities focus on the device-level engineering with the design targets from the circuit-level array modeling, aiming at enabling the large-scale integration of 3D ReRAM technology. Array macro model that can assess integration density, cost per bit, read/write margin, access latency, and power/energy consumption will be developed and calibrated by SPICE simulation. Device prototypes for 3D ReRAM will be fabricated and optimized towards the desired targets given by the array macro model. All device engineering activities will leverage the existing knowledge of the electrode/oxide interface engineering and oxide/oxide interface engineering and further contribute to new understandings of relevant issues.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1449653</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shimeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Yu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shimeng Yu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shimeng.yu@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048942571</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project the PI and the research team has investigated the fundamental technological challenges of the monolithic 3D integration of the resistive random access memory (RRAM) in the future computer systems. The research activities ranged from the device-level, the array-level up to the system-level. The research outcome at the device-level included a developed NbO2 based selector device with strong I-V nonlinearity to minimize the sneak path in the 3D cross-point architecture, and a RRAM compact model that is written in Verilog-A format. The research outcome at the array-level included a methodology to simulate the write/read margin of a 3D cross-point array in SPICE, and a semi-analytical model to speed up the simulation for Mb-level sub-array. The research outcome at the system-level included a methodology to evaluate the design trade-offs between the performance, energy-efficiency and reliability of the 3D RRAM based memory system. &nbsp;</p> <p>The research outcomes of this project have been disseminated to the research community and the industry through journal and conference publications, invited talks and seminars. In particular, the PI advocated the web-based release of the research tools and models. The ASU RRAM model was released online with more than 400 downloads by the end of project and is now widely used in the community today. ASU Memory Trend has been released online as well. This material summarized the recent progress of the emerging non-volatile memory prototype chips.</p> <p>This research resulted in about 20 journal and conference papers, published in the premier journals in this field including IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices, IEEE Electron Devices Letters, and IEEE Transactions on VLSI Systems, etc.</p> <p>This project has supported or partially supported one postdoc researcher and two PhD students and the REU supplement fund trained 3 undergraduate researchers, and 2 of them completed the BS honor&rsquo;s thesis.</p> <p>This project also has broader impact than the initial scope, and has inspired new applications of the RRAM technology and 3D cross-point array towards implementing the neural network on-chip and functioning as hardware security primitives.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Shimeng&nbsp;Yu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619459849_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619459849_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fabricated crossbar array"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619459849_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fabricated crossbar array"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">12*12 crossbar array with HfO2 RRAM fabricated at ASU NanoFab</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shimeng Yu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shimeng&nbsp;Yu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fabricated crossbar array</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619512838_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619512838_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ASU RRAM Model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619512838_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ASU RRAM Model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ASU RRAM compact model that has been fitted with HfO2 RRAM data</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shimeng Yu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shimeng&nbsp;Yu</div> <div class="imageTitle">ASU RRAM Model</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619570069_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619570069_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="3D RRAM array"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1449653/1449653_10338189_1508619570069_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="3D RRAM array"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of 3D RRAM cross-point array with vertical pillar architecture</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shimeng Yu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shimeng&nbsp;Yu</div> <div class="imageTitle">3D RRAM array</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project the PI and the research team has investigated the fundamental technological challenges of the monolithic 3D integration of the resistive random access memory (RRAM) in the future computer systems. The research activities ranged from the device-level, the array-level up to the system-level. The research outcome at the device-level included a developed NbO2 based selector device with strong I-V nonlinearity to minimize the sneak path in the 3D cross-point architecture, and a RRAM compact model that is written in Verilog-A format. The research outcome at the array-level included a methodology to simulate the write/read margin of a 3D cross-point array in SPICE, and a semi-analytical model to speed up the simulation for Mb-level sub-array. The research outcome at the system-level included a methodology to evaluate the design trade-offs between the performance, energy-efficiency and reliability of the 3D RRAM based memory system.    The research outcomes of this project have been disseminated to the research community and the industry through journal and conference publications, invited talks and seminars. In particular, the PI advocated the web-based release of the research tools and models. The ASU RRAM model was released online with more than 400 downloads by the end of project and is now widely used in the community today. ASU Memory Trend has been released online as well. This material summarized the recent progress of the emerging non-volatile memory prototype chips.  This research resulted in about 20 journal and conference papers, published in the premier journals in this field including IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices, IEEE Electron Devices Letters, and IEEE Transactions on VLSI Systems, etc.  This project has supported or partially supported one postdoc researcher and two PhD students and the REU supplement fund trained 3 undergraduate researchers, and 2 of them completed the BS honor?s thesis.  This project also has broader impact than the initial scope, and has inspired new applications of the RRAM technology and 3D cross-point array towards implementing the neural network on-chip and functioning as hardware security primitives.           Last Modified: 10/21/2017       Submitted by: Shimeng Yu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
