<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Community Organization In Capital Cities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17338.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17338</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cities are at the center of political, economic, religious and social life. A key way to understand how they function is through the investigation of their social and spatial organization, seen in the way neighborhoods, districts and ethnic groups form and interact. Compact and highly centralized cities function in different ways when compared to garden cities with more dispersed layouts. Cities that are capitals of large states provide unique information on political organization and the nature of rulership since they are home to a society's leaders and central institutions. A capital city may be dominated by a centralized single governing institution, or may contain several, suggesting a more segmented form of rulership. Archaeology is particularly well suited to study social relations in capital cities as it can trace long term trajectories of city formation and change and their relationship with political power and statecraft. Under the supervision of Dr. Elizabeth Arkush, the doctoral candidate Gabriela Cervantes will study the social organization of the Sican capital city in Peru, with emphasis on urban organization and interaction, domestic economies and subsistence practices, economic differentiation and power relations and statecraft. This project will provide training to US and Peruvian students from various universities in contemporary archeological techniques. The information obtained, which will provide the basis for Cervantes' dissertation, will also be presented in a public talk in the Sican National Museum in Peru for the local community; detailed data will be made available through the Center for Comparative Archaeology of the University of Pittsburgh webpage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researcher will examine how urban patterns and city life involve social relations, economy and power. The Sican state in Peru was one of the most developed societies in metallurgy technology and long distance trade in the Americas. The research will involve a program of full coverage survey, systematic surface collection and mapping of the city. The data obtained will be used to address the residential nature of the capital, its size, density and urban layout and the socioeconomic differentiation and economic occupation of its residents. The research will expand current views of urban variability and neighborhood formation and compact versus dispersed settlements in cities. Further, the research will investigate how power is structured and practiced, and use this information to refine and compare current constructs of statecraft and sociopolitical trajectories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1449610</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Arkush</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Arkush</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arkush@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349895730</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriela</FirstName>
<LastName>Cervantes Quequezana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriela Cervantes Quequezana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gac29@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126247400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000672823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152600001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~17338</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cities are at the center of political, economic, religious and social life. Cities that are capitals of states provide exceptional information on political organization and the nature of rulership since they are home to a society&rsquo;s leaders and central institutions. Archaeology is particularly well suited to study social relations in capital cities as it can trace long term trajectories of city formation, change and their relationship with political power and statecraft.</p> <p>The main objective of this research is to investigate the socioeconomic organization and urban layout of the capital of the Pre-hispanic Sican state (AD 800-1375) located in the north coast of Per&uacute;.</p> <p>&nbsp;In order to accomplish this objective, the research developed two main phases.</p> <p>&nbsp;The first phase of research involved a six-month (July-December) program of full coverage survey combined with intensive surface collection of archaeological materials and mapping of the city including the Sican Precinct or &ldquo;Sican Core&rdquo; and its surroundings or &ldquo;Greater Sican&rdquo;. A total area of 50km2 located within the Bosque de Poma Historical Sanctuary in the Lambayeque region of the north coast of Peru was studied. The second phase involved an eight-month (January-August) program of analysis of archaeological materials recovered that took place at the Sican National Museum laboratory facilities (Ferre&ntilde;afe, Per&uacute;).</p> <p>The results of the research indicate that the Sican capital had a dispersed urban pattern with several nuclei, similar to those found in garden cities like Mayan cities or those found in Southeast Asia, but very rare for the Andes. Based on residential architecture and household assemblages, the Sican society shows a highly stratified social organization with noticeable differences between elites and commoners. Economic activities at the capital varied broadly including craft production of ceramics, lithic and metal tools and adornments. Agriculture took place within the city in the areas between houses or house groups. Sican&rsquo;s urban layout, social organization and political centralization differs markedly from typical compact urban centers in the Andes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2016<br>      Modified by: Gabriela&nbsp;Cervantes Quequezana</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cities are at the center of political, economic, religious and social life. Cities that are capitals of states provide exceptional information on political organization and the nature of rulership since they are home to a societyÆs leaders and central institutions. Archaeology is particularly well suited to study social relations in capital cities as it can trace long term trajectories of city formation, change and their relationship with political power and statecraft.  The main objective of this research is to investigate the socioeconomic organization and urban layout of the capital of the Pre-hispanic Sican state (AD 800-1375) located in the north coast of Per&uacute;.   In order to accomplish this objective, the research developed two main phases.   The first phase of research involved a six-month (July-December) program of full coverage survey combined with intensive surface collection of archaeological materials and mapping of the city including the Sican Precinct or "Sican Core" and its surroundings or "Greater Sican". A total area of 50km2 located within the Bosque de Poma Historical Sanctuary in the Lambayeque region of the north coast of Peru was studied. The second phase involved an eight-month (January-August) program of analysis of archaeological materials recovered that took place at the Sican National Museum laboratory facilities (Ferre&ntilde;afe, Per&uacute;).  The results of the research indicate that the Sican capital had a dispersed urban pattern with several nuclei, similar to those found in garden cities like Mayan cities or those found in Southeast Asia, but very rare for the Andes. Based on residential architecture and household assemblages, the Sican society shows a highly stratified social organization with noticeable differences between elites and commoners. Economic activities at the capital varied broadly including craft production of ceramics, lithic and metal tools and adornments. Agriculture took place within the city in the areas between houses or house groups. SicanÆs urban layout, social organization and political centralization differs markedly from typical compact urban centers in the Andes.          Last Modified: 03/06/2016       Submitted by: Gabriela Cervantes Quequezana]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
