<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Some topics in time-frequency analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/13/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>67099.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>67099</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lie and his collaborators will investigate a number of problems  that  lie  at the interface of time-frequency analysis and other areas of mathematics such as additive combinatorics, geometric measure theory, incidence geometry and partial differential equations.  The main objectives for the time-frequency analysis-themed problems in this project are (a), to develop a satisfactory generalized wave packet  theory  and (b),  to develop the proper environment for the time - frequency analysis in higher dimensions. One step in the first direction was taken by the PI in his Ph.D. thesis, where he introduced a new perspective on the generalized wave packet theory which later proved beneficial in proving  the boundedness of the Polynomial Carleson operator in dimension one.  Some of these techniques appear to be  applicable to the study of the boundedness  of the maximal Schrodinger operator in dimension one.  The PI and his collaborators will investigate several  other problems,  including: boundedness of the Bilinear Hilbert transform along curves;  boundedness of the higher dimensional version of the Polynomial Carleson operator; pointwise convergence of the solution to the free Schrodinger equation in higher dimensions; convergence of the subsequences of  sequences of partial Fourier sums. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This mathematics research project investigates various problems in harmonic analysis, which is an area of mathematics that has important applications to problems that arise in other sciences, such as pattern recognition in computer graphics; electrical charges distribution in physics; wave propagation in seismology. The techniques to be employed will bridge several areas of mathematics, including partial differential equations, incidence geometry, and additive combinatorics. The resulting synergies will enrich the arsenal of analytical tools and available techniques; these will be presented in graduate seminars designed with the specific purpose to attract  students and young researchers to this dynamic area of mathematics and its applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1449514</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Lie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor D Lie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vlie@math.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941901</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600983</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~67099</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project <strong>focused on various connections between the area of Harmonic Analysis (the core of this project) and other mathematical areas such as additive combinatorics, incidence geometry and PDE.</strong></p> <p>The concrete outcomes/products of our project (see the list below) split in three components: publications appeared during the time covered by this award (3 papers), submitted articles that are currently under the review process&nbsp; (one paper),&nbsp; preprints and work in progress ( 4 preprints).&nbsp; At this we should add&nbsp; three other components of the PI&rsquo;s activity: 1) delivered invited talks at several international conferences, seminars and colloquiums ( 15 talks) &nbsp;2) &nbsp;co-organized an AIM workshop on topics in Harmonic Analysis and 3) offered guidance for three undergraduate junior &nbsp;thesis, &nbsp;five reading courses for three undergraduates and was coordinating the Putnam preparation of &nbsp;Purdue University team.</p> <p>INTELECTUAL MERIT: &nbsp;This proposal developed new connections between areas such as time-frequency analysis,&nbsp; additive geometry, incidence geometry and PDE. The PI made important contributions in several of the proposed topics &nbsp;- see below the detailed list of the outcomes for this project. Also the PI extended his interests in the area of fluid dynamics where he gained more expertise &nbsp;by working with more senior collaborators. &nbsp;Overall, this project presented a diverse array of problems both in terms of directions of research and in terms of difficulty.</p> <p>BROADER IMPACT:&nbsp; The PI contributed to the human scientific resources by individual teaching, advising junior theses, delivering reading courses. In Spring 2015, the PI co-organized the AIM workshop: ``Carleson Theorems and Multilinear operators" interacting with a consistent number of participants at the level of graduate students and postdoctoral&nbsp; fellows.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The fluid dynamic component in this project is directly connected with physics and more generally with the real world. The results of PI&rsquo; s research were presented at conferences and various seminars. They were/will also be made available through publications/journals and posted on electronic libraries such as Arxiv.</p> <p>Below we present the research outcome of this project:</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;A) Publications,&nbsp; submitted</p> <p>1) &nbsp;The pointwise convergence of the Fourier Series (I); On a conjecture of Konyagin, submitted</p> <p>2) &nbsp;(with C. Fefferman and A. Ionescu) On the absence of "splash" singularities in the case of two-fluid interfaces, to appear&nbsp; Duke J. Math.</p> <p>3) &nbsp;The boundedness of the Bilinear Hilbert Transform along ``non-flat'' smooth curves, Amer. J. Math., 137(2), pp. 313-364, 2015</p> <p>4) On the boundedness of the {C}arleson operator near $L^1$, Rev. Mat. Iber...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project focused on various connections between the area of Harmonic Analysis (the core of this project) and other mathematical areas such as additive combinatorics, incidence geometry and PDE.  The concrete outcomes/products of our project (see the list below) split in three components: publications appeared during the time covered by this award (3 papers), submitted articles that are currently under the review process  (one paper),  preprints and work in progress ( 4 preprints).  At this we should add  three other components of the PIÆs activity: 1) delivered invited talks at several international conferences, seminars and colloquiums ( 15 talks)  2)  co-organized an AIM workshop on topics in Harmonic Analysis and 3) offered guidance for three undergraduate junior  thesis,  five reading courses for three undergraduates and was coordinating the Putnam preparation of  Purdue University team.  INTELECTUAL MERIT:  This proposal developed new connections between areas such as time-frequency analysis,  additive geometry, incidence geometry and PDE. The PI made important contributions in several of the proposed topics  - see below the detailed list of the outcomes for this project. Also the PI extended his interests in the area of fluid dynamics where he gained more expertise  by working with more senior collaborators.  Overall, this project presented a diverse array of problems both in terms of directions of research and in terms of difficulty.  BROADER IMPACT:  The PI contributed to the human scientific resources by individual teaching, advising junior theses, delivering reading courses. In Spring 2015, the PI co-organized the AIM workshop: ``Carleson Theorems and Multilinear operators" interacting with a consistent number of participants at the level of graduate students and postdoctoral  fellows.                                                                                                                                                                              The fluid dynamic component in this project is directly connected with physics and more generally with the real world. The results of PIÆ s research were presented at conferences and various seminars. They were/will also be made available through publications/journals and posted on electronic libraries such as Arxiv.  Below we present the research outcome of this project:           A) Publications,  submitted  1)  The pointwise convergence of the Fourier Series (I); On a conjecture of Konyagin, submitted  2)  (with C. Fefferman and A. Ionescu) On the absence of "splash" singularities in the case of two-fluid interfaces, to appear  Duke J. Math.  3)  The boundedness of the Bilinear Hilbert Transform along ``non-flat'' smooth curves, Amer. J. Math., 137(2), pp. 313-364, 2015  4) On the boundedness of the {C}arleson operator near $L^1$, Rev. Mat. Iberoam., 29(4),1239-1262, 2013.         B) Preprints, work in progress  1) (with M. Bateman) Extremal con?guration for Kakeya Problem in 2D,  to be submitted  2) (with A. Ionescu)  On a 3D Euler-Maxwell model with vorticity, to be submitted  3) The boundedness of the Bilinear Hilbert Transform along ``non-flat'' smooth curves; $L^p-$case,  to be submitted  4) (with C. Fefferman and A. Israel) Understanding the limiting 2D water-waves splash scenario, in preparation             Last Modified: 10/09/2015       Submitted by: Victor D Lie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
