<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRNC: AMI: Collaborative Research: Software-Defined and Privacy-Preserving Network Measurement Instrument and Services for Understanding Data-Driven Science Discovery</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1254935.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1254935</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Data intensive science discovery at a global scale has imposed new requirements on the speed and management of international research and education networks. At the connection points of these international networks, it is critical to measure the network data flows to understand network traffic patterns, identify network anomalies and provide insights to network control and planning. However, the ever-increasing network speed, the massive amount of network flows and the changing measurement objectives have made the flow-level measurement on very high-speed networks extremely challenging. The Advanced Measurement Instrument and Services (AMIS) project leverages many-core, programmable network processors to prototype and deploy an advanced measurement instrument to enable services for accurate network monitoring and in-depth traffic analysis. The instrument supports flow-granularity measurement at line rate up to 100Gbps and software application programming interfaces to examine selected flows, with no impact to the performance of user traffic. With scalable hardware and an open source software stack, the measurement services equip network operators with effective tools to quantify flow-level network performance and study network flows through privacy-preserving computational analytics. This project is built on a consortium of academia, industrial partners, network operators and international alliances, who bring unique expertise and resources to achieve the objectives of high performance, programmable flow-granularity network measurement.  The outcomes from this project will significantly benefit data driven science discovery, such as astronomy and space weather studies, and will promote broadened participation of underrepresented groups (such as Hispanic and female students) through the involvement of multiple universities, including an EPSCoR university and a Hispanic Serving Institution.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1450996</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yan</FirstName>
<LastName>Luo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yan Luo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Yan_Luo@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789342592</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Lowell</Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<ZipCode>018543692</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9789344170</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[600 Suffolk Street - Suite 212]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>956072490</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Lowell]]></Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018542827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7369</Code>
<Text>International Res Ret Connect</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7369</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL RES NET CONNECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1254935</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default"><span>IRNC AMIS project aims to design a high-performance software defined measurement instrument and associated services to monitor, measure and analyze the network traffic on international research network connections, at flow-granularity, in a programmable and privacy-preserving way. This is a collaboration among teams from University of Massachusetts Lowell (UML), University of Massachusetts Boston (UMB), University of Kentucky (UKY) and University of Texas at El Paso (UTEP). Each team has contributed to one of the four components of the AMIS framework: UML developed the measurement instrument and programmable framework, UMB researched with privacy preserving schemes, UTEP designed visualization and analytics tools, and UKY implemented plugin management framework to connect these essential software components.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="Default"><span>At UMass Lowell, the key outcomes from the project include (1) the novel hardware and software platform of network flow measurement capable of up to 100Gbps line rate; (2) a programmable framework of distributed measurement with multiple measurement instrument; (3) A new network measurement query language called Equery supporting event based measurement tasks; (4) testbeds deployed at four locations in US, and one international site (at La Serena, Chile); and (5) demonstrations of live system at national and international computing/networking conference. The deliverable of this projects have been disseminated through journal/conference publications, demonstrations, website and open source programs.</span></p> <p class="Default"><span>The project has provided many opportunities for training the students and postdocs on state of art technology and real-world challenges. The project enriched the participants' knowledge in networking and software systems, cultivated their verbal and written communication skills, and taught them the importance of critical thinking and innovation. The research activities significantly improved their problem-solving skills and the skills to derive observations through experimentation. The participants were also given opportunities to present the findings to technical and non-technical audience, interact with their peers and experts, which are essential experiences for future scientists and engineers.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/13/2020<br>      Modified by: Yan&nbsp;Luo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[IRNC AMIS project aims to design a high-performance software defined measurement instrument and associated services to monitor, measure and analyze the network traffic on international research network connections, at flow-granularity, in a programmable and privacy-preserving way. This is a collaboration among teams from University of Massachusetts Lowell (UML), University of Massachusetts Boston (UMB), University of Kentucky (UKY) and University of Texas at El Paso (UTEP). Each team has contributed to one of the four components of the AMIS framework: UML developed the measurement instrument and programmable framework, UMB researched with privacy preserving schemes, UTEP designed visualization and analytics tools, and UKY implemented plugin management framework to connect these essential software components.   At UMass Lowell, the key outcomes from the project include (1) the novel hardware and software platform of network flow measurement capable of up to 100Gbps line rate; (2) a programmable framework of distributed measurement with multiple measurement instrument; (3) A new network measurement query language called Equery supporting event based measurement tasks; (4) testbeds deployed at four locations in US, and one international site (at La Serena, Chile); and (5) demonstrations of live system at national and international computing/networking conference. The deliverable of this projects have been disseminated through journal/conference publications, demonstrations, website and open source programs. The project has provided many opportunities for training the students and postdocs on state of art technology and real-world challenges. The project enriched the participants' knowledge in networking and software systems, cultivated their verbal and written communication skills, and taught them the importance of critical thinking and innovation. The research activities significantly improved their problem-solving skills and the skills to derive observations through experimentation. The participants were also given opportunities to present the findings to technical and non-technical audience, interact with their peers and experts, which are essential experiences for future scientists and engineers.          Last Modified: 07/13/2020       Submitted by: Yan Luo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
