<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Linking Crow Roosting Behavior with Nitrogen Biogeochemistry in Urban Ecosystems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The earth has become urbanized at an accelerating rate, with more than half of its population now living in cities. Human land use and resource consumption have profound impacts on the natural patterns and processes at the city, region, and global scales.  But while humans are clearly the dominant drivers of urban ecosystems, animals living in cities can also play important roles. For example, movement of chemicals from human food sources into otherwise isolated urban forests by animals can produce unique chemical hot spots with multiple potential consequences. Even so, very few studies have linked the movement of chemicals with the behavior and dynamics of urban wildlife populations. This project will explore the links between the nesting behavior of American crows and the movement of nitrogen to create hotspots in the many small to medium sized cities in central New York. Under-represented minority students from local areas will be recruited for the project, which will also involve citizen scientists and lead to increased public awareness of human-nature connections. The project will also provide a base of science to local city managers and county soil and water conservation managers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central hypothesis of this project is that when urbanized American crow populations forage on human-subsidized food sources and roost in high densities in urban forest patches, they create high ? and sometimes episodic - nitrogen availability. That changes the pattern of nitrogen cycling in the forest fragments, affects critical ecosystem processes of denitrification and nitrogen leaching, and causes localized water and air pollution. This study poses two main questions. First, what is the distribution of crow roosts and its association with cities and towns? Second, what are the biogeochemical consequences of concentrated N input from crow roosts? The study will investigate a novel linkage between crow behavior, including foraging, roosting and defecating, and the formation of biogeochemical hot spots. It will compare and contrast nitrogen transformations and transfers between the hot spots and urban sites without concentrated bird activities. It will examine the patterns and mechanisms regulating different pathways of N loss (leaching vs. denitrification) and various potential end forms of nitrogen gas and dissolved losses in urban hot spots receiving pulsed, concentrated N input. Finally, it will advance urban ecological research by integrating population and ecosystem level studies beyond the usual foci of humans and trees. The project will examine fundamental aspects of how animal species affect ecosystem function in the novel context of a spatially heterogeneous urban landscape (driven by human land use decisions) and supplemental energy and material (driven by human food consumption).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1450383</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Clark</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne B Clark</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aclark@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077776228</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000236636</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weixing</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weixing Zhu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wxzhu@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077773218</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093635</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 6000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090189965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Binghamton]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~149600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The earth has become rapidly urbanized, with more than 50% of the world population now living in cities. Human populations and activities have profound impacts on urban ecosystems and ecosystem processes such as nitrogen (N) cycling. In addition to humans, wildlife species increasingly make cities their home and become part of the urban ecosystem. Much less known, however, are the impacts of resident wildlife on urban N biogeochemistry. Here, we studied a novel linkage between the roosting behavior of American crow (<em>Corvus brachyrhynchos</em>) and crow-mediated input of N, the emergence of biogeochemical hot spots and hot moments, and the alteration of N biogeochemistry in urban ecosystems.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Our study showed that crows can roost in high density, thousands or tens of thousands, in America cities and towns. Winter migration of the birds and their nightly roosts, created concentrated inputs of N from crow faces (hot spots) that have dramatically altered N biogeochemistry. In one roost site in Auburn, NY, over 40,000 crows roosted together each night over the winter from December to March. We sampled soils in spring, summer, and fall to understand the temporal changes of N biogeochemistry (hot moments). Our study focused in particular the pathways of N loss. The microbial process of denitrification converts soil nitrate to N<sub>2</sub>, a benign nitrogen gas making up 78% of the atmosphere. However, it also releases nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O), a potent greenhouse gas 200 times stronger than carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>). In addition, N<sub>2</sub>O damages ozone layer in the stratosphere that protects the earth from harmful UV radiation from the sun. Our data showed concentrated N input from crow roosts created fluxes of N<sub>2</sub>O and N<sub>2</sub> 1800 and 30 times of the respective N fluxes from the non-roost sites, while soil ammonium and nitrate concentrations were 31-47 times of those at the non-roost sites. This biogeochemistry hot spots of N remained active in summer even though rates were significantly lower than in spring right after the crows left for spring breeding areas. Our study sheds light on linkages between animal behaviors and ecosystem processes in cities, which may be particularly important in small to medium-sized cities. This study has high societal interest, and can benefit society by exciting participation from citizen scientists, establishing scientific basis for wildlife and pollution management, and enhancing environmental education through K-12 schools to colleges.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Weixing&nbsp;Zhu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The earth has become rapidly urbanized, with more than 50% of the world population now living in cities. Human populations and activities have profound impacts on urban ecosystems and ecosystem processes such as nitrogen (N) cycling. In addition to humans, wildlife species increasingly make cities their home and become part of the urban ecosystem. Much less known, however, are the impacts of resident wildlife on urban N biogeochemistry. Here, we studied a novel linkage between the roosting behavior of American crow (Corvus brachyrhynchos) and crow-mediated input of N, the emergence of biogeochemical hot spots and hot moments, and the alteration of N biogeochemistry in urban ecosystems.                  Our study showed that crows can roost in high density, thousands or tens of thousands, in America cities and towns. Winter migration of the birds and their nightly roosts, created concentrated inputs of N from crow faces (hot spots) that have dramatically altered N biogeochemistry. In one roost site in Auburn, NY, over 40,000 crows roosted together each night over the winter from December to March. We sampled soils in spring, summer, and fall to understand the temporal changes of N biogeochemistry (hot moments). Our study focused in particular the pathways of N loss. The microbial process of denitrification converts soil nitrate to N2, a benign nitrogen gas making up 78% of the atmosphere. However, it also releases nitrous oxide (N2O), a potent greenhouse gas 200 times stronger than carbon dioxide (CO2). In addition, N2O damages ozone layer in the stratosphere that protects the earth from harmful UV radiation from the sun. Our data showed concentrated N input from crow roosts created fluxes of N2O and N2 1800 and 30 times of the respective N fluxes from the non-roost sites, while soil ammonium and nitrate concentrations were 31-47 times of those at the non-roost sites. This biogeochemistry hot spots of N remained active in summer even though rates were significantly lower than in spring right after the crows left for spring breeding areas. Our study sheds light on linkages between animal behaviors and ecosystem processes in cities, which may be particularly important in small to medium-sized cities. This study has high societal interest, and can benefit society by exciting participation from citizen scientists, establishing scientific basis for wildlife and pollution management, and enhancing environmental education through K-12 schools to colleges.          Last Modified: 10/30/2017       Submitted by: Weixing Zhu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
