<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Age-Targeted Automated Cueing Against Cyber Social Engineering Attacks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>245497.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>261497</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Online social engineering attacks have been often used for cybercrime activities. These attacks are low cost and complicate attack attribution. Pure technical defense solutions cannot counter them, which rely on human gullibility. Humans often engage in short-cut decision-making, which can lead to errors. Another expectation is that users should be able to understand complex security tips, which do not consider user demographics. User age has been overlooked in understanding these attacks and user behavior related to them. This project investigates the influence of user age on the type and the effectiveness of social engineering attacks through user studies involving young and older adults. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this research, participants are first monitored in their homes while using the Internet and receiving age-targeted malicious e-mails. Then, in a lab session involving benign and malicious Internet activities, the experimental group receives age-targeted cues about the attacks. Participants' visual attention is monitored with eye tracking technology. The results of these studies allow the development of a browser extension to cue users in an age-targeted fashion about risky situations online. This project represents a paradigm change: age-targeted security information reaches users at the time they need it, and not the other way around.  This research will lead to widespread benefits on Internet safety for end-users, especially to the population of older adults, who will likely be a target of the next generation of social engineering attacks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1450624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniela</FirstName>
<LastName>Oliveira</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniela A Oliveira</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniela@ece.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523928671</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000582084</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natalie</FirstName>
<LastName>Ebner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Natalie Ebner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>natalie.ebner@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2036910371</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673966</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[216 Larsen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8225</Code>
<Text>SaTC Special Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~245497</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-9e3dc17c-5a65-9905-ed80-e4f8f8ac0ada"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project investigated the influence of user age on the type and the effectiveness of social engineering attacks by email (spear phishing and spam) through user studies involving young and older adults. The outcomes of the user studies &nbsp;have the potential to inform the development of interventional tools to warn Internet users about deception in emails. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For spam, we found, using manual content coding on a large set of emails that young and older internet users had forwarded to us from their spam folders, that all principles of influence and life domains are already currently represented in today&rsquo;s &nbsp;spam emails. Our analysis further showed that reciprocation was the most frequently used principle of influence, finances the most prevalent incentivizing life domain, and leisure and independence the most popular contextual life domains in today&rsquo;s spam. We also found that older adults were more likely to receive spam emails related to health and independence, while young adults were more likely to receive spam emails related to leisure and occupation. We found no difference in young and older adults&rsquo; spam emails regarding the use of specific principles of influence, however, and no effect for gender.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These findings support &nbsp;the existence of a level of targeting in today&rsquo;s spam campaigns by the use of particular principles of influence and life domains, and even specific tailoring of age demographics. This novel knowledge is crucial for the development of the next generation of spam mitigation solutions, in particular with regard to content analysis based on machine learning.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For phishing, we showed that Internet users were highly susceptible to such attacks, as 43% of the participants clicked on at least one phishing email during the 21-day study period in which participants received, unbeknownst to them, simulated phishing emails. We found that older women were the most susceptible to phishing attacks and that the principles of influence scarcity and authority were the most effective for all age groups. However, while young users were most susceptible to scarcity, older adults were most susceptible to reciprocation. All users were most susceptible to emails pertaining to the legal life domain. Unexpectedly, we observed that &nbsp;the financial domain was not very effective. It is possible that educational efforts in everyday life outside of our study raise awareness about scams involving money, knowledge that our participants may have transferred into the study. Also, use of the life domain of health in the emails, even though health becomes increasingly important with advanced &nbsp;age, was not particularly effective in older adults. It is possible that older adults frequently hear from friends and family anecdotes about medication offers via email (e.g., weight loss pills and Viagra), which may have contributed to the low appeal of this domain in our study. Interestingly, we found a discrepancy, especially among older users, between actual behavioral susceptibility to spear phishing emails and participants&rsquo; self-reported susceptibility awareness (assessed at the end of the study). This low susceptibility awareness &nbsp;may make older users particularly at-risk for phishing.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Today&rsquo;s security training and warning, for phishing come as one size fits all solutions. However, our research shows that one size does not fit all. Rather, security solutions for Internet users should be tailored to the specifics of user demographics. Further, training, warning, and security education for Internet users attempt to accomplish too much, and are not effective because people follow mental shortcuts, forget, and habituate to warnings. Based on our findings, we advocate targeted security interventions (e.g., training and warnings), with a focus on the most relevant vulnerabilities of a given population of Internet users. For example, our research showed that, for phishing, young users were most susceptible to scarcity, while older users were most susceptible to reciprocation. We believe that an age-tailored training and prevention approach will increase the effectiveness of security measures because such approach would impose less requirements on people and would match their specific vulnerabilities. In our study we compared young and older adults. However, teenagers and middle-age adults might show specific vulnerabilities, which need to be identified in future lifespan research. Further, personal background, such as education level, profession, or culture/country might also influence user susceptibility to phishing. Our study was the first to point out differential susceptibility patterns by user demographic and suggests the need for targeted security warnings, training and education. We hope that our findings will spur future investigation pertaining to a variety of demographics.</span></p> <p><br /><span>Broader Impacts:</span><span> This interdisciplinary study involved principal investigators, and more than ten students from various levels in their careers (undergraduate, Masters, and PhD students) from Computer Engineering and Psychology. This project also produced three academic papers and several high-profile talks (in academic, industry, and government contexts) and posters. It also contributed to the cybersecurity awareness of the more than 200 participants who participants across our &nbsp;two user studies.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Daniela&nbsp;A&nbsp;Oliveira</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1450624/1450624_10339036_1513345618151_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1450624/1450624_10339036_1513345618151_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF SaTC PI Meeting Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1450624/1450624_10339036_1513345618151_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF SaTC PI Meeting Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Poster about our project at the 2017 NSF SaTC PI Meeting</div> <div class="imageCredit">our entire research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniela&nbsp;A&nbsp;Oliveira</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF SaTC PI Meeting Poster</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This project investigated the influence of user age on the type and the effectiveness of social engineering attacks by email (spear phishing and spam) through user studies involving young and older adults. The outcomes of the user studies  have the potential to inform the development of interventional tools to warn Internet users about deception in emails.     For spam, we found, using manual content coding on a large set of emails that young and older internet users had forwarded to us from their spam folders, that all principles of influence and life domains are already currently represented in today?s  spam emails. Our analysis further showed that reciprocation was the most frequently used principle of influence, finances the most prevalent incentivizing life domain, and leisure and independence the most popular contextual life domains in today?s spam. We also found that older adults were more likely to receive spam emails related to health and independence, while young adults were more likely to receive spam emails related to leisure and occupation. We found no difference in young and older adults? spam emails regarding the use of specific principles of influence, however, and no effect for gender.    These findings support  the existence of a level of targeting in today?s spam campaigns by the use of particular principles of influence and life domains, and even specific tailoring of age demographics. This novel knowledge is crucial for the development of the next generation of spam mitigation solutions, in particular with regard to content analysis based on machine learning.    For phishing, we showed that Internet users were highly susceptible to such attacks, as 43% of the participants clicked on at least one phishing email during the 21-day study period in which participants received, unbeknownst to them, simulated phishing emails. We found that older women were the most susceptible to phishing attacks and that the principles of influence scarcity and authority were the most effective for all age groups. However, while young users were most susceptible to scarcity, older adults were most susceptible to reciprocation. All users were most susceptible to emails pertaining to the legal life domain. Unexpectedly, we observed that  the financial domain was not very effective. It is possible that educational efforts in everyday life outside of our study raise awareness about scams involving money, knowledge that our participants may have transferred into the study. Also, use of the life domain of health in the emails, even though health becomes increasingly important with advanced  age, was not particularly effective in older adults. It is possible that older adults frequently hear from friends and family anecdotes about medication offers via email (e.g., weight loss pills and Viagra), which may have contributed to the low appeal of this domain in our study. Interestingly, we found a discrepancy, especially among older users, between actual behavioral susceptibility to spear phishing emails and participants? self-reported susceptibility awareness (assessed at the end of the study). This low susceptibility awareness  may make older users particularly at-risk for phishing.    Today?s security training and warning, for phishing come as one size fits all solutions. However, our research shows that one size does not fit all. Rather, security solutions for Internet users should be tailored to the specifics of user demographics. Further, training, warning, and security education for Internet users attempt to accomplish too much, and are not effective because people follow mental shortcuts, forget, and habituate to warnings. Based on our findings, we advocate targeted security interventions (e.g., training and warnings), with a focus on the most relevant vulnerabilities of a given population of Internet users. For example, our research showed that, for phishing, young users were most susceptible to scarcity, while older users were most susceptible to reciprocation. We believe that an age-tailored training and prevention approach will increase the effectiveness of security measures because such approach would impose less requirements on people and would match their specific vulnerabilities. In our study we compared young and older adults. However, teenagers and middle-age adults might show specific vulnerabilities, which need to be identified in future lifespan research. Further, personal background, such as education level, profession, or culture/country might also influence user susceptibility to phishing. Our study was the first to point out differential susceptibility patterns by user demographic and suggests the need for targeted security warnings, training and education. We hope that our findings will spur future investigation pertaining to a variety of demographics.   Broader Impacts: This interdisciplinary study involved principal investigators, and more than ten students from various levels in their careers (undergraduate, Masters, and PhD students) from Computer Engineering and Psychology. This project also produced three academic papers and several high-profile talks (in academic, industry, and government contexts) and posters. It also contributed to the cybersecurity awareness of the more than 200 participants who participants across our  two user studies.          Last Modified: 12/15/2017       Submitted by: Daniela A Oliveira]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
