<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: BRAIN EAGER: Stretchable graphene transistors for high signal, high channel count neural recording</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Sanford</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is jointly made by two programs the Instrument Development for Biological Research program (IDBR) and Emerging Frontiers (EF) in the Directorate of Biological Sciences (BIO).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A key roadblock to expanding our knowledge of the brain is that existing tools to probe its function are simply not up to the enormity of the task. Techniques for recording neural signals allow at most signals from tens or hundreds of neurons to be recorded, when thousands or even millions are needed. To address this challenge, improved types of sensors are required that record neural activity with greater signal quality and are more suited to parallel recording than current approaches. This collaborative project will develop a new type of sensor based on flexible graphene transistors. Graphene is an atomically thin sheet of carbon atoms that exhibits desirable physical, chemical, and electrical properties for interfacing with biological systems. However, the use of graphene transistors for single neuron sensing is largely unexplored. Open questions include the nature of the contact between the neuron and the graphene, the ultimate strength of electrical signals, and the long-term biocompatibility of graphene-based electrodes in the brain. Our proposed work will address these fundamental questions. If successful, this project will ultimately lead to societal benefits such as better neural prosthetics and new treatments for neurological disorders. Training opportunities at the interface of nano- and neuroscience, a key area of need for America?s technological future, will be available for graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Graphene can be nanofabricated into arrays of conformable, stretchable transistors using techniques borrowed from the Japanese paper art of kirigami. Prior work of this research team has shown that unlike traditional electronic devices, such graphene transistors are both extremely flexible and can stretch by &gt; 100% without degrading their electrical properties. The current project will investigate the electrical and mechanical interactions between kirigami graphene and individual neurons. Graphene will be cut into different patterns to optimize the mechanical contact between graphene and single neurons. Wrapping of graphene on the neuron will be maximized and the graphene will be used to measure voltage spikes produced by individual neurons, both in vitro and in vivo. With optimized conformal contact between graphene and neurons it will be possible to measure a large fraction of the intracellular potential (~ 70 mV). The semiconducting properties of graphene will also be used to amplify the bioelectronic signals to robust levels to facilitate multiplexed detection of thousands of neuron signals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1450967</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
<LastName>Minot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ethan D Minot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>minote@physics.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417379671</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973316507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ideal brain-activity sensor would have the following features: no damage to the brain, measure the activity of individual neurons, report measurements with a large signal-to-noise ratio. Existing neuron sensors are far from reaching this ideal. Measurements are made by inserting sharp, stiff needles into the brain. Scar tissue quickly develops around these needles. Signals are picked up by small metal pads on the needle. Signals are often lost in the background noise. The technology has changed very little over the past 50 years.</p> <p>In this project we investigated a promising new approach to neurosensing that is enabled by flexible, stretchable electronic materials. We showed that a sheet of graphene, one atom in thickness, and tens of microns in length/width, can wrap around a living cell like a blanket. We characterized the electronic performance of this flexible, stretchable sensor. We determined the fundamental noise limits and the transduction performance in biological environments.</p> <p>Our exploratory experiments concluded that flexible, stretchable graphene-based biosensors are a promising new technology. Compared to existing technology, the sensor can be placed closer to the neuron without causing damage. This feature will improve signal strength. The transduction sensitivity and background noise is similar to existing technology, but the graphene-based sensor amplifies the signal at the neuron location, rather than outside the brain. Thus, the graphene device is an all-in-one microelectrode plus amplifier. This feature will facilitate greater parallelization of neuron sensing devices.</p> <p>During the project, three graduate students were trained in an interdisciplinary, collaborative environment. The students developed expertise in state-of-the-art &nbsp;neuroscience technology, 2-d material growth, electrical and optical measurements, and biological sample preparation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Ethan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Minot</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ideal brain-activity sensor would have the following features: no damage to the brain, measure the activity of individual neurons, report measurements with a large signal-to-noise ratio. Existing neuron sensors are far from reaching this ideal. Measurements are made by inserting sharp, stiff needles into the brain. Scar tissue quickly develops around these needles. Signals are picked up by small metal pads on the needle. Signals are often lost in the background noise. The technology has changed very little over the past 50 years.  In this project we investigated a promising new approach to neurosensing that is enabled by flexible, stretchable electronic materials. We showed that a sheet of graphene, one atom in thickness, and tens of microns in length/width, can wrap around a living cell like a blanket. We characterized the electronic performance of this flexible, stretchable sensor. We determined the fundamental noise limits and the transduction performance in biological environments.  Our exploratory experiments concluded that flexible, stretchable graphene-based biosensors are a promising new technology. Compared to existing technology, the sensor can be placed closer to the neuron without causing damage. This feature will improve signal strength. The transduction sensitivity and background noise is similar to existing technology, but the graphene-based sensor amplifies the signal at the neuron location, rather than outside the brain. Thus, the graphene device is an all-in-one microelectrode plus amplifier. This feature will facilitate greater parallelization of neuron sensing devices.  During the project, three graduate students were trained in an interdisciplinary, collaborative environment. The students developed expertise in state-of-the-art  neuroscience technology, 2-d material growth, electrical and optical measurements, and biological sample preparation.          Last Modified: 10/31/2016       Submitted by: Ethan D Minot]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
