<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BRAIN EAGER:   Wireless Measurement of Neuronal Currents Using Spin-Torque Nano-Oscillators</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is jointly made by two programs the Instrument Development for Biological Research program (IDBR) and Emerging Frontiers (EF) in the Directorate of Biological Sciences (BIO).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The brain is a complex network of interconnected circuits that exchange signals in the form of action potentials.  These action potentials hold the key to understanding cognition and complex thought.  Currently available non-invasive methods for probing neuronal activity cannot achieve sufficient spatial or temporal resolution to observe individual action potentials from single neurons or small clusters, which is a major limitation.   This principal investigator proposes to study a novel approach for non-invasive measurements that will be able to read out individual action potentials across the entire brain.  This project will take advantage of recent advances in spintronic devices to create injectable nano-reporters that will detect weak electrical signals in the brain and convert them to microwave signals that can be detected wirelessly outside the body.  The detection device to be used is the spin-torque nano-oscillator (STNO), which converts electrical signals into microwave field oscillations that can be detected wirelessly.  This approach could ultimately lead to the first non-invasive technology capable of measuring activations of individual neurons and small-scale neuronal networks in live primates and humans. This capability would have a major impact on our understanding of the inner workings of the brain and cognition.  It could also have important clinical applications, particularly in the areas of neurological disorders and brain machine interfaces. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ability to monitor neuronal activity at the cellular level non-invasively is crucial for attaining a better understanding of cognition, as well as many clinical applications. Currently, all non-invasive methods for monitoring brain activity cannot simultaneously achieve the spatial and temporal resolution required to sense individual action potentials from a single neuron. This project is a novel approach for non-invasive measurements that will be able to read out individual action potentials across the whole brain from single neurons.  To achieve the transduction of electrical activity to microwaves, a nano-sized device called a spin-torque nano-oscillator (STNO) will be used that converts steady electrical signals into microwave frequency magnetic field oscillations that can be detected wirelessly.  The STNO responds in microseconds to electric signals, and thus can be directly used to measure individual neuronal action potentials.  In addition, the STNO is a nano-scale device and can report on the firing and location of a single neuron.  This project represents the first application to neurobiology of the exciting and rapidly evolving field of spintronics.  A test system will be developed that includes a neuron simulator (a tunable circuit that simulates the voltages and impedance of a single neuron) and a high sensitivity microwave receiver to demonstrate the ability of these devices to report that activation state of a neuron wirelessly.  this project also involves the design, fabrication, and test optimization of STNO devices for neurobiological applications.  The ultimate and specific goal of this EAGER project is to perform a proof-of-concept demonstration of the proposed apparatus on a live squid axon.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1450921</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Shapiro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Shapiro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>benshap@eng.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014054191</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000259767</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edo</FirstName>
<LastName>Waks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edo Waks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>edowaks@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014055022</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000321331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This program developped a new method to sense and control brain activity wirelessly using spintronics.&nbsp; Spintronic devices have novel properties such as the ability to convert small biological signals to microwave field oscillations and vice versa.&nbsp; This approach provides a way to both sense and control brain activity.&nbsp; Through this program, we demonstated wireless sensing of small currents using spintronics. Using various animal models, we were also able to transduce single action potentials to microwave signals, and to control the firing rate of single neurong using microwaves.&nbsp; These combined capabilities provide a promising groundwork for devloping noveling neurosensors that can report and control the firing of single neurons in the same device.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merits: The field of spintronics provides unique ways to interconvert microwave signals and DC currents.&nbsp; Nevertheless, the application of these devices to neuro-science remains largely unexplored.&nbsp; We showed that by exploiting spin transfer torque, such devices can act as microwave transducers for biological signals.&nbsp; These results show the broad applicability of spintronics to neurosensing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impact: Our results would generate a new area of research in the field of spintronics in the area of neuroscience.&nbsp; This program developed the concepts and measurement capabilities that will serve as the foundation for this new field. The results could have broad application in the field of biological sensing, neuro-science, spintronics, energy harvesting, and low power electronics. The program trained one PhD student and one postdoctoral fellow.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/05/2017<br>      Modified by: Edo&nbsp;Waks</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This program developped a new method to sense and control brain activity wirelessly using spintronics.  Spintronic devices have novel properties such as the ability to convert small biological signals to microwave field oscillations and vice versa.  This approach provides a way to both sense and control brain activity.  Through this program, we demonstated wireless sensing of small currents using spintronics. Using various animal models, we were also able to transduce single action potentials to microwave signals, and to control the firing rate of single neurong using microwaves.  These combined capabilities provide a promising groundwork for devloping noveling neurosensors that can report and control the firing of single neurons in the same device.     Intellectual merits: The field of spintronics provides unique ways to interconvert microwave signals and DC currents.  Nevertheless, the application of these devices to neuro-science remains largely unexplored.  We showed that by exploiting spin transfer torque, such devices can act as microwave transducers for biological signals.  These results show the broad applicability of spintronics to neurosensing.     Broader impact: Our results would generate a new area of research in the field of spintronics in the area of neuroscience.  This program developed the concepts and measurement capabilities that will serve as the foundation for this new field. The results could have broad application in the field of biological sensing, neuro-science, spintronics, energy harvesting, and low power electronics. The program trained one PhD student and one postdoctoral fellow.         Last Modified: 12/05/2017       Submitted by: Edo Waks]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
