<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2014 NSF Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation (EFRI) Workshop: Interdisciplinarity and Innovation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Garie Fordyce</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent reports from the National Academies speak to the weakening of U.S. competitiveness and the need for a diverse workforce to drive innovation. Federally funded university research is a proven driver of innovation, and minorities and women remain an insufficiently tapped talent source. This workshop, targeted towards women and underrepresented minority engineering faculty, will be conducted at NSF on August 21-22, 2014.  It will provide participants with opportunities for professional development and a chance to gain a better understanding of how to identify, conduct and fund transformative research carried out by interdisciplinary teams. In doing so, the workshop addresses strategic goals of the National Science Foundation and critical needs of the nation related to our global competiveness and an improved national economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Building upon past professional development models employed in previous workshops led by the PI and incorporating programming that addresses interdisciplinarity and research innovation, this EFRI funded workshop is uniquely positioned for success. Faculty participants will gain a better understanding of interdisciplinarity and what constitutes cutting-edge transformative research, how to bring a team together to define an important research problem/challenge and develop a strategy to address it, how to lead interdisciplinary teams and manage large complex projects, and how to network and exploit opportunities. The workshop format will consist of a series of informational and interactive sessions over a 1 ½ day period. It is organized to specifically address professional development, leadership and innovation along with project management in support of transformative research. Participants will be recruited from institutions across the country with a special emphasis on minority serving institutions and presenters will be drawn from the academy of engineers, federal agencies, senior faculty and administrators, NSF program officers, and successful EFRI awardees.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1450726</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gilda</FirstName>
<LastName>Barabino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gilda Barabino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Gbarabino@olin.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505435</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Convent Avenue at 138th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2014 NSF Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation (EFRI) Workshop, Interdisciplinarity and Innovation: Strategies for Effective Team Research was held at the National Science Foundation, August 21-22, 2014. It was organized by Dr. Gilda Barabino, Dean of the Grove School of Engineering at The City College of New York and Executive Director of the National Institute for Faculty Equity. The workshop was unique in its first time offering of tailored and integrated training on innovation, interdisciplinarity and professional leadership to women and underrepresented minority faculty, a largely untapped pool of talent to lead interdisciplinary team research. Participants were drawn from U.S. four-year institutions and represented the spectrum of engineering disciplines. 32 women and underrepresented faculty participated in a series of informational and interactive sessions over a 2 day period. Three organizational sections comprised the workshop: 1) day 1 was devoted to sessions designed to: provide a framework for understanding interdisciplinarity and diversity and for understanding social networks and team science, introduce funding opportunities, provide examples of models of success, and address leadership challenges, 2) a portion of day 2 was devoted to interactions with NSF and NIH program directors and 3) a portion of day 2 was devoted to interactive discussions on challenges and strategies related to effectively leading team research. The 2014 NSF EFRI Workshop represented a new and strategically designed effort to broaden participation from underrepresented groups and diverse institutions in frontiers of fundamental engineering research. It provided a mechanism for participants to enhance their professional development and to gain a better understanding of how to identify, conduct, fund and lead transformative research carried out by interdisciplinary teams. In doing so, the workshop contributes to strategic goals of the National Science Foundation and addresses critical needs of the nation related to enhanced global competiveness and an improved national economy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2015<br>      Modified by: Gilda&nbsp;A&nbsp;Barabino</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2014 NSF Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation (EFRI) Workshop, Interdisciplinarity and Innovation: Strategies for Effective Team Research was held at the National Science Foundation, August 21-22, 2014. It was organized by Dr. Gilda Barabino, Dean of the Grove School of Engineering at The City College of New York and Executive Director of the National Institute for Faculty Equity. The workshop was unique in its first time offering of tailored and integrated training on innovation, interdisciplinarity and professional leadership to women and underrepresented minority faculty, a largely untapped pool of talent to lead interdisciplinary team research. Participants were drawn from U.S. four-year institutions and represented the spectrum of engineering disciplines. 32 women and underrepresented faculty participated in a series of informational and interactive sessions over a 2 day period. Three organizational sections comprised the workshop: 1) day 1 was devoted to sessions designed to: provide a framework for understanding interdisciplinarity and diversity and for understanding social networks and team science, introduce funding opportunities, provide examples of models of success, and address leadership challenges, 2) a portion of day 2 was devoted to interactions with NSF and NIH program directors and 3) a portion of day 2 was devoted to interactive discussions on challenges and strategies related to effectively leading team research. The 2014 NSF EFRI Workshop represented a new and strategically designed effort to broaden participation from underrepresented groups and diverse institutions in frontiers of fundamental engineering research. It provided a mechanism for participants to enhance their professional development and to gain a better understanding of how to identify, conduct, fund and lead transformative research carried out by interdisciplinary teams. In doing so, the workshop contributes to strategic goals of the National Science Foundation and addresses critical needs of the nation related to enhanced global competiveness and an improved national economy.          Last Modified: 12/27/2015       Submitted by: Gilda A Barabino]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
