<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Small Data Research Infrastructure: Workshop Proposal</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>97068.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>97068</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Nilsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wnilsen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922568</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Small Data Research Infrastructure: Workshop Proposal&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is for a workshop series to assess the research needs and opportunities in small data research. Small data refers to the collection of digital traces that individuals generate implicitly and explicitly during their everyday lives. As the use of big data analytics has exploded, a growing community of computer and information science researchers has started to focus on the capture, processing, governance, and use of these small data streams. The research challenges raised by small data cut across the computer science community and include: 1) Personal data mining and modeling: parsing and fusion of diverse and noisy data streams to create informative, descriptive, and predictive models of individuals and their behaviors; 2) Data Privacy and sharing: constructs, architecture, and policies, for protecting and sharing raw and derived personal data streams; and 3) User-centered applications and human-computer interaction: design methods and tools to create meaningful and engaging experiences for individuals. In order to make progress across these three research thrusts, at a scale and pace that matches the potential for impact to individuals and society, this project aims to run a series of workshops to convene the technical community. The output of the workshop series will include the articulation of a small data research agenda, and a plan for a shared community research infrastructure to support real world experiments with real participants and their small data streams. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project brings together expertise from across computer and information sciences and engineering for a series of workshops to develop a research agenda and community infrastructure for small data research. To develop and evaluate realistic systems using "small data" requires user involvement and an end-to-end system test bed involving data streams controlled by various companies and further, that such a test bed should be a shared community infrastructure, since no single research group can afford to build it. The infrastructure development at the center of the proposed workshops has the potential to change how investigators do research, which broadly impacts the research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1451448</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Estrin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah L Estrin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>destrin@cs.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9176754954</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100111121</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Eighth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~97068</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In order to develop the sdX concept and build community we held a series of 4 workshops. The first three were small workshops held in September 2014 (the first was hybrid in person virtual, the second two all virtual), and a final larger workshop (June 2015) in person.</p> <p>Comments from the September workshops were incorporated to a description of sdX and resulted in a letter of support for the CRI submission (Submitted in October).</p> <p>In preparation for the larger workshop the description of sdX was made available on line for editing and comments. The document can be found here:</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">https://docs.google.com/document/d/1da7xOQSDatc1WajBpIjOLapfr92aujWDd5_N1wAZtTA/edit</span></p> <p>Extensive work was done by the workshop organizers to create a working agenda that would meaningfully engage community members in both the framing and planning of sdX.</p> <p>All participants were required to review the document and comment in advance of the meeting. A selection of key comments are summarized below in the &ldquo;Pre June workshop Feedback Summary.</p> <p>The workshop series resulted in a community articulation of:</p> <ul> <li>The major opportunities and needs for building a small data infrastructure for research</li> <li>The major challenges in building such an infrastructure, and how to address them</li> <li>Proposed starting points for developing the sdX infrastructure and research community</li> </ul> <p>Following are key findings of the workshop engagement</p> <p><strong>Problems sdX will solve to enable more rapid experimentation with small data</strong></p> <p>1. Data ingesters/device drivers with well-defined metadata, data schema, APIs</p> <p>2. User on boarding, secure login / identity management, role management</p> <p>3. Provenance tracking (for measures/feature calculation in addition to data)</p> <p>4. Revision tracking of most components (code, etc.)</p> <p>5. Smoothing consent and privacy processes, IRB relationships</p> <p>6. Async data-flow style processing environment for small data, which can drive online (e.g., real time user feedback applications) as well as post facto research and analysis.</p> <p>7. Alarms/notifications for user participation interaction</p> <p>8. Interfacing with individual services&rsquo; terms of use</p> <p>9. Participant recruitment for small data studies</p> <p>10. Allowing researchers to compare strategies and build common toolkits (even if we can&rsquo;t reuse data, we can reuse plug ins/models!)</p> <p>11. Tools for data management: normalizing data, aligning disparate data on a temporal dimension, etc.</p> <p>12. Understand user recurrent behavior or preference; similar to Yahoo or Google</p> <p>Now&rsquo;s news recommendation.</p> <p>13. Run tool chain on line locally (N=1, on a mobile device or in a private cloudlet) as well as for large groups in batch &hellip; (from Jim/James group)</p> <p>14. providing a canonical representation for data, as motivating/enabling the tool chain (transport format + schema)</p> <p>15. Do for small data experimentation what device drivers did for operating systems</p> <p>16. Robust audit logging tools (what modules accessed a particular participant&rsquo;s data)</p> <p>17. Meta data generation tools (characterize the completeness/lossiness/likelihood of a data stream)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>sdX Services that many researchers would find useful</strong></p> <ul> <li>One click IRB language </li> <li>Usable privacy management for end users</li> <li>Standardized data access for data sources such as Wearables, Corporate email, &hellip;</li> <li>Common demographic information and format for all study participants and the ability to contact other studies&rsquo; users to request reuse</li> <li>Commons/Registry for descriptions of ALL primary and derived data to make it easier to share and reuse data or the modules run to create processed dat...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In order to develop the sdX concept and build community we held a series of 4 workshops. The first three were small workshops held in September 2014 (the first was hybrid in person virtual, the second two all virtual), and a final larger workshop (June 2015) in person.  Comments from the September workshops were incorporated to a description of sdX and resulted in a letter of support for the CRI submission (Submitted in October).  In preparation for the larger workshop the description of sdX was made available on line for editing and comments. The document can be found here:  https://docs.google.com/document/d/1da7xOQSDatc1WajBpIjOLapfr92aujWDd5_N1wAZtTA/edit  Extensive work was done by the workshop organizers to create a working agenda that would meaningfully engage community members in both the framing and planning of sdX.  All participants were required to review the document and comment in advance of the meeting. A selection of key comments are summarized below in the "Pre June workshop Feedback Summary.  The workshop series resulted in a community articulation of:  The major opportunities and needs for building a small data infrastructure for research The major challenges in building such an infrastructure, and how to address them Proposed starting points for developing the sdX infrastructure and research community   Following are key findings of the workshop engagement  Problems sdX will solve to enable more rapid experimentation with small data  1. Data ingesters/device drivers with well-defined metadata, data schema, APIs  2. User on boarding, secure login / identity management, role management  3. Provenance tracking (for measures/feature calculation in addition to data)  4. Revision tracking of most components (code, etc.)  5. Smoothing consent and privacy processes, IRB relationships  6. Async data-flow style processing environment for small data, which can drive online (e.g., real time user feedback applications) as well as post facto research and analysis.  7. Alarms/notifications for user participation interaction  8. Interfacing with individual servicesÆ terms of use  9. Participant recruitment for small data studies  10. Allowing researchers to compare strategies and build common toolkits (even if we canÆt reuse data, we can reuse plug ins/models!)  11. Tools for data management: normalizing data, aligning disparate data on a temporal dimension, etc.  12. Understand user recurrent behavior or preference; similar to Yahoo or Google  NowÆs news recommendation.  13. Run tool chain on line locally (N=1, on a mobile device or in a private cloudlet) as well as for large groups in batch &hellip; (from Jim/James group)  14. providing a canonical representation for data, as motivating/enabling the tool chain (transport format + schema)  15. Do for small data experimentation what device drivers did for operating systems  16. Robust audit logging tools (what modules accessed a particular participantÆs data)  17. Meta data generation tools (characterize the completeness/lossiness/likelihood of a data stream)     sdX Services that many researchers would find useful  One click IRB language  Usable privacy management for end users Standardized data access for data sources such as Wearables, Corporate email, &hellip; Common demographic information and format for all study participants and the ability to contact other studiesÆ users to request reuse Commons/Registry for descriptions of ALL primary and derived data to make it easier to share and reuse data or the modules run to create processed data if permitted by participants and researcher Micropayments to study participants Pool of potential study participants for generic population testing? Specific populations will be recruited by the specific researchers. Feature engineering for data scientists (understanding what kind of data/time granularity/etc. tends to be the most useful in models) APIs/hooks for common platforms (Android/iOS/Windows/OSX) Easily build experiments, s...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
