<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Creating and Sustaining Dialogs on Conceptual Change in Engineering Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47550.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>52260</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amedinab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While there is much discussion on what needs to be changed in engineering education and how those changes should take place, there is no current venue for sustaining a meaningful dialog on change and archiving these discussions for the benefit of the entire engineering community. The proposed workshops will help to advance knowledge and understanding about the purposes of engineering education and begin a well-informed and lasting dialog on possible ways to reconceptualize engineering education for the benefit of all participants.  Sustained and informed dialog is needed to created change in the face of the major disruptions taking place in higher education and the workplace. To sustain the needed on-going dialog, these workshops are framed around the organizational structure of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE).  A major goal of this effort is to ensure broad and diverse participation.   The leaders of three ASEE divisions will coordinate the workshop. The workshops and significant dissemination effort will broadly impact society by creating a scholarly and sustainable dialog between multiple stakeholders in engineering education. The workshops are intended to open up a new venue for dialog that captures a broader range of voices. The project plan includes participation of the needed diverse elements of the larger engineering education system. The plan provides resources for long-term, sustainable dissemination anticipated to be in the form of a self-sustaining dialog and discussion journal.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1451713</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheville</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan Cheville</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alan.cheville@bucknell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5705773460</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000237269</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bucknell University</Name>
<CityName>LEWISBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>178372111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5705773510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Dent Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003030335</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BUCKNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003030335</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bucknell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lewisburg</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>178372111</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Dent Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~47550</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~4710</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Tens of thousands of Americans receive engineering degrees each year.&nbsp; An engineering education is an ordinary means to great and extraordinary ends.&nbsp; Engineers are employed across the economy and contribute culturally, civically, technologically, and economically to society.&nbsp; The benefits of an engineering education&mdash;which accrue both to individuals and the United States&mdash;are, however, not evenly distributed across the population; some groups are under-represented.&nbsp;</p> <p>Through a series of workshops this project explored ways to support individuals' ability to reconceptualize engineering education with the central goal of broadening the impact of engineering education.&nbsp; Reconceptualization implies significant change, and such change&mdash;as compared to step-by-step iterative approaches&mdash;is difficult to achieve and requires dialog from a wide range of stakeholders.&nbsp; Since an engineering education serves multiple purposes for multiple stakeholders, this workshop project sought to engage a wide range of individuals to have and support continuing dialogs about what changes will be needed in engineering education as well as how such changes will be developed and supported.&nbsp; A key goal was to bring in broad range of voices to better ensure changes will be equitable.</p> <p>A series of workshops, which engaged a wide and diverse range of individuals, was held over the project lifetime and resulted in several concrete outcomes.&nbsp; One of these outcomes was a report to the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Board of Directors recommending ways to increase the range of publications to better support needed dialogs.&nbsp; ASEE is the premiere society for supporting and advancing engineering education both in the US and internationally.</p> <p>A second concrete outcome is the creation of an on-line, open access, open review, dialog journal named <em>Murmurations:&nbsp; Emergence, Equity, and Education</em>.&nbsp; Since the journal is on-line and open access it is accessible by anyone without charge.&nbsp; The journal has adopted an open review policy in which the peer review process is visible to readers, i.e. names of reviewers are known, rather than a blind review policy.&nbsp; Both the final, edited work as well as initial drafts and reviewer comments are visible to readers. &nbsp;The goal of open review is to make the processes of publication and peer review visible.&nbsp; Making reviews processes visible is intended to illustrate how peer review occurs and thus encourage submissions from individuals and groups that typically do not have access to academic publishing venues and get alternative views of engineering education systems.&nbsp; To create more equitable systems of education the perspectives of groups that are not typically included need to be sought and expressed.&nbsp; The dialog format of the journal is supported by making the dialogs between authors and reviewers visible as well as encouraging responses to articles and organizing articles through dialog threads.&nbsp; The journal has published one issue to date and is soliciting materials for a second issue.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2018<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cheville</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Tens of thousands of Americans receive engineering degrees each year.  An engineering education is an ordinary means to great and extraordinary ends.  Engineers are employed across the economy and contribute culturally, civically, technologically, and economically to society.  The benefits of an engineering education&mdash;which accrue both to individuals and the United States&mdash;are, however, not evenly distributed across the population; some groups are under-represented.   Through a series of workshops this project explored ways to support individuals' ability to reconceptualize engineering education with the central goal of broadening the impact of engineering education.  Reconceptualization implies significant change, and such change&mdash;as compared to step-by-step iterative approaches&mdash;is difficult to achieve and requires dialog from a wide range of stakeholders.  Since an engineering education serves multiple purposes for multiple stakeholders, this workshop project sought to engage a wide range of individuals to have and support continuing dialogs about what changes will be needed in engineering education as well as how such changes will be developed and supported.  A key goal was to bring in broad range of voices to better ensure changes will be equitable.  A series of workshops, which engaged a wide and diverse range of individuals, was held over the project lifetime and resulted in several concrete outcomes.  One of these outcomes was a report to the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Board of Directors recommending ways to increase the range of publications to better support needed dialogs.  ASEE is the premiere society for supporting and advancing engineering education both in the US and internationally.  A second concrete outcome is the creation of an on-line, open access, open review, dialog journal named Murmurations:  Emergence, Equity, and Education.  Since the journal is on-line and open access it is accessible by anyone without charge.  The journal has adopted an open review policy in which the peer review process is visible to readers, i.e. names of reviewers are known, rather than a blind review policy.  Both the final, edited work as well as initial drafts and reviewer comments are visible to readers.  The goal of open review is to make the processes of publication and peer review visible.  Making reviews processes visible is intended to illustrate how peer review occurs and thus encourage submissions from individuals and groups that typically do not have access to academic publishing venues and get alternative views of engineering education systems.  To create more equitable systems of education the perspectives of groups that are not typically included need to be sought and expressed.  The dialog format of the journal is supported by making the dialogs between authors and reviewers visible as well as encouraging responses to articles and organizing articles through dialog threads.  The journal has published one issue to date and is soliciting materials for a second issue.       Last Modified: 12/19/2018       Submitted by: Richard A Cheville]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
