<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Is Anthropocene sedimentation in valley bottoms a geologically significant event?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>172118.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>172118</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Yuretich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ryuretic@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924744</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical description of the project's broader significance and importance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent research in geomorphology, the study of Earth's surface and the processes that shape it, has found that human modification of land in the northeastern U.S. over the past few centuries has resulted in large volumes of sediment being eroded from hillsides and deposited in valleys along rivers and streams. Prior research has suggested that this sediment transfer is the most important modification of Earth's landscape in tens of thousands of years. This project will evaluate the significance of these deposits on a regional scale by carefully measuring them in representative field locations and then using newly available high-resolution topographic data to extrapolate the findings to whole watersheds and regions. Knowledge of how human activities have contributed to landscape change is a prerequisite for informed land-management and restoration decisions. To ensure broad communication of project findings, the researchers will interact with policy makers, planners, government agencies, and non-profit organizations interested in stream and wetland conservation. This project also will include strong opportunities for student research, since the collaborating institutions are heavily invested in undergraduate education as a priority.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description of the project &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent global sedimentation studies demonstrate that rates of erosion due to human activities exceed the amount of sediment delivered to the oceans by rivers. At the same time, field-based studies at the channel to watershed scale have found large quantities of sediment stored in valley bottoms during the past few centuries. This project will bridge the gap between global and watershed-based approaches by quantifying the amount of Anthropocene (recent, human related) sediment stored in valley bottoms of the northeastern United States, and then comparing this amount to published volumes and timescales of (1) erosion from the landscape, and (2) deposition in reservoirs, lakes, and estuaries along the Atlantic margin. The research will use high-resolution topographic data to map the extent and thickness of this fill over large spatial areas (1,000-10,000 square km), and will test these methods using fieldwork (mapping, coring, geophysical data collection, sediment sampling and dating) in key watersheds. A central goal is to evaluate the extent to which sediment storage in the unglaciated mid-Atlantic region applies in the glaciated, less-studied New England region, where upland soils are thin, sediment sources are generally localized to glacial deposits, and large natural lakes and wetlands provide terrestrial accommodation space. The results of the project will help resolve the discrepancy between erosion and deposition rates at small spatial (watershed) and temporal (decadal to centennial) scales versus the rates that occur globally and over geological time.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1451562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noah</FirstName>
<LastName>Snyder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noah P Snyder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>noah.snyder@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175520839</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000125562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~172118</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-82613ca1-0541-d44b-ff39-c22887c69856"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Recent research in geomorphology, the study of Earth&rsquo;s surface and the processes that shape it, has found that human modification of land in the northeastern U.S. over the past few centuries has resulted in storage of sediment eroded from hillsides in valley bottoms. Using large-scale global sediment budgets, previous researchers have suggested that this storage is the most important modification of Earth&rsquo;s landscape in tens of thousands of years. This project investigated whether these deposits are geologically significant on the regional scale by carefully mapping them in the field and then using newly available high-resolution topographic datasets to scale up the findings. We conducted field analysis of sediment exposures, radiocarbon dating, and computer-based analysis using newly available high-resolution laser topographic data in 3 watersheds in New England and 5 watersheds in the Mid Atlantic region. We focused on estimates of the volume of sediment storage in each watershed by mapping historic terraces.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We estimate that legacy sediment storage ranges from 0.02 to 3.7 cm of soil erosion in the New England watersheds, and from 0.7 to 2.3 cm in the Mid Atlantic watersheds. This likely represents 10% or less of soil erosion that resulted from land clearing for agriculture. However, much eroded sediment is not stored behind dams (due to incomplete trapping and intentional flushing by dam operators) or floodplains and is deposited elsewhere (e.g, lakes and intact reservoirs, estuaries, the ocean). There is a correlation between milldam density and legacy sediment storage, which likely reflects a combination of more intensive land clearing and opportunities for storage in millponds. No significant correlations exist between legacy sediment storage and relief or drainage area. Results from the Sheepscot River, Maine and Charles River, Massachusetts suggest that legacy sediment storage is a lesser factor in formerly glaciated watersheds. The watersheds are in coastal settings, with numerous natural lakes and only localized thick glacial deposits. The upland South River, Massachusetts is exceptional in the context of New England in terms of both available sediment supply and anthropogenic sediment storage. </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our findings comparing New England with the Mid Atlantic region underscore the importance for restoration efforts to take regional context into account when evaluating the importance of legacy sediment. To ensure broad communication of project findings, the researchers make presentations to and lead workshops for policy makers, planners, government agencies, and non-profit organizations interested in stream and wetland conservation, and will continue to do so beyond the period of this award. </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project resulted in three M.S. theses and six undergraduate theses. All of these students presented their research at regional and/or international scientific conferences. Each of the M.S. students have submitted or are currently preparing manuscripts for the peer-reviewed literature. So far, the project has resulted in one published paper, one manuscript in review, six manuscripts in preparation, and 17 conference presentations.</span></p> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Noah&nbsp;P&nbsp;Snyder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Recent research in geomorphology, the study of Earth?s surface and the processes that shape it, has found that human modification of land in the northeastern U.S. over the past few centuries has resulted in storage of sediment eroded from hillsides in valley bottoms. Using large-scale global sediment budgets, previous researchers have suggested that this storage is the most important modification of Earth?s landscape in tens of thousands of years. This project investigated whether these deposits are geologically significant on the regional scale by carefully mapping them in the field and then using newly available high-resolution topographic datasets to scale up the findings. We conducted field analysis of sediment exposures, radiocarbon dating, and computer-based analysis using newly available high-resolution laser topographic data in 3 watersheds in New England and 5 watersheds in the Mid Atlantic region. We focused on estimates of the volume of sediment storage in each watershed by mapping historic terraces. We estimate that legacy sediment storage ranges from 0.02 to 3.7 cm of soil erosion in the New England watersheds, and from 0.7 to 2.3 cm in the Mid Atlantic watersheds. This likely represents 10% or less of soil erosion that resulted from land clearing for agriculture. However, much eroded sediment is not stored behind dams (due to incomplete trapping and intentional flushing by dam operators) or floodplains and is deposited elsewhere (e.g, lakes and intact reservoirs, estuaries, the ocean). There is a correlation between milldam density and legacy sediment storage, which likely reflects a combination of more intensive land clearing and opportunities for storage in millponds. No significant correlations exist between legacy sediment storage and relief or drainage area. Results from the Sheepscot River, Maine and Charles River, Massachusetts suggest that legacy sediment storage is a lesser factor in formerly glaciated watersheds. The watersheds are in coastal settings, with numerous natural lakes and only localized thick glacial deposits. The upland South River, Massachusetts is exceptional in the context of New England in terms of both available sediment supply and anthropogenic sediment storage.  Our findings comparing New England with the Mid Atlantic region underscore the importance for restoration efforts to take regional context into account when evaluating the importance of legacy sediment. To ensure broad communication of project findings, the researchers make presentations to and lead workshops for policy makers, planners, government agencies, and non-profit organizations interested in stream and wetland conservation, and will continue to do so beyond the period of this award.  The project resulted in three M.S. theses and six undergraduate theses. All of these students presented their research at regional and/or international scientific conferences. Each of the M.S. students have submitted or are currently preparing manuscripts for the peer-reviewed literature. So far, the project has resulted in one published paper, one manuscript in review, six manuscripts in preparation, and 17 conference presentations.        Last Modified: 06/15/2018       Submitted by: Noah P Snyder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
