<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>JST-NSF-DFG Workshop on Future Power System Architectures and Control Paradigms, Arlington VA, April 22-24, 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>65000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>65000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This workshop will bring together leading international researchers from Germany, Japan and the United States to discuss how to address the rapidly changing demands being placed on the power grid. The recent deployment and integration of more renewable energy sources to the electric power grid coupled with the shutting down of nuclear units in some countries or switching over from coal to natural gas is placing unprecedented stresses on the power grids around the world. This workshop will investigate new system architectures and control paradigms to address these challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An electricity supply less reliant on fossil fuels is central to any meaningful approach to a sustainable energy future. Encouragingly, renewable generation has grown rapidly in recent years. The US will have 65 GW of installed wind capacity by the end of 2014 with anticipated continued rapid growth for several years. Solar PV costs have dropped dramatically. Internationally for reasons of safety, national security and environmental concern, we see similar trends as well as the shutting down of nuclear generation. These changes all place new demands on the existing power transmission infrastructure. Germany and Japan have some of the most aggressive plans for moving to a low carbon future. This workshop with the support of the Japan Science and Technology (JST) Agency and the German Research Foundation (DFG) will bring together researchers and educators in electric energy and sustainability from across the globe to discuss relevant issues to these changes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A primary goal of the workshop is to learn about research activities in power and energy from the different countries and to discuss ways to leverage the on-going efforts and develop collaborations. Specifically, we wish to take advantage of the progressive changes in electricity sources occurring in Germany, Japan and the US and learn from these developments. Topics for discussion include renewable energy generation, the smart grid, demand response, energy storage, HVDC and supergrids, distributed controls, microgrids and various new control paradigms. The workshop will examine control, communication, computational science, environmental, energy, power systems and social aspects of electric energy and sustainability. A report will be generated discussing accomplishments of workshop along with action items.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1451473</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Tomsovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin L Tomsovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tomsovic@tennessee.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~65000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Introduction</strong></p> <p>This workshop brought together leading international researchers from Germany, Japan, Norway and the United States to discuss how to address the rapidly changing demands being placed on the power grid.&nbsp; The recent deployment and integration of more renewable energy sources to the electric power grid coupled with the shutting down of nuclear units in some countries or switching over from coal to natural gas is placing unprecedented stresses on the power grids around the world. The workshop had discussions and presentations on new system architectures and control paradigms to address these challenges.</p> <p>This workshop was a follow up to two recent NSF workshops related to power system developments: the <strong>Joint JST-NSF-DFG Workshop</strong><br /> <strong>Distributed Energy Management Systems, Honolulu, Hawai&rsquo;i, January 2014 and the </strong><strong>NSF Power and Energy Education Workshop</strong>, Arlington, VA, July 2014.</p> <p>Presentations were given from leading international researchers in multiple research areas including: control, communication, computational science, economics, environmental, energy, power systems and social sciences. These presentations along with the agenda can be found at</p> <p>http://curent.utk.edu/research/conferences/jst-nsf-dfg-workshop/</p> <p><strong></strong>The workshop series has continued with a meeting in May 2016 entitled <strong>DFG-JST-RCN-NSF Workshop on Energy Management Systems in Heidelberg</strong>. Importantly, a number of collaborative research projects have begun based on these meetings.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts </strong></p> <p>A primary goal of the workshop is to learn about research activities in power and energy from the different countries and to discuss ways to leverage the on-going efforts and develop collaborations. Specifically, we want to take advantage of the progressive changes in electricity sources occurring in Germany, Japan and the US and learn from these developments. The<br />workshop examined control, communication, computational science, environmental, energy, power systems and social aspects of electric energy and sustainability.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tomsovic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Introduction  This workshop brought together leading international researchers from Germany, Japan, Norway and the United States to discuss how to address the rapidly changing demands being placed on the power grid.  The recent deployment and integration of more renewable energy sources to the electric power grid coupled with the shutting down of nuclear units in some countries or switching over from coal to natural gas is placing unprecedented stresses on the power grids around the world. The workshop had discussions and presentations on new system architectures and control paradigms to address these challenges.  This workshop was a follow up to two recent NSF workshops related to power system developments: the Joint JST-NSF-DFG Workshop  Distributed Energy Management Systems, Honolulu, Hawai?i, January 2014 and the NSF Power and Energy Education Workshop, Arlington, VA, July 2014.  Presentations were given from leading international researchers in multiple research areas including: control, communication, computational science, economics, environmental, energy, power systems and social sciences. These presentations along with the agenda can be found at  http://curent.utk.edu/research/conferences/jst-nsf-dfg-workshop/  The workshop series has continued with a meeting in May 2016 entitled DFG-JST-RCN-NSF Workshop on Energy Management Systems in Heidelberg. Importantly, a number of collaborative research projects have begun based on these meetings.  Broader Impacts   A primary goal of the workshop is to learn about research activities in power and energy from the different countries and to discuss ways to leverage the on-going efforts and develop collaborations. Specifically, we want to take advantage of the progressive changes in electricity sources occurring in Germany, Japan and the US and learn from these developments. The workshop examined control, communication, computational science, environmental, energy, power systems and social aspects of electric energy and sustainability.       Last Modified: 09/01/2016       Submitted by: Kevin L Tomsovic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
