<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2014 Internet Measurement Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darleen Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 14th ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), sponsored by ACM SIGCOMM and ACM SIGMETRICS, in cooperation with USENIX, will be held in Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, November 5-7, 2014. This award provides funds to assist approximately 12-14 graduate students from US institutions to attend this conference. IMC is the primary venue for presenting new research results on collecting and analyzing measurements of the Internet. Attending conferences such as IMC is of paramount importance for graduate students pursuing research in the field. Authors have the opportunity to present their work and all attendees have a chance to interact with many others performing leading-edge research in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award serves to widen the audience attending the Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), raising the level of interaction and the potential for new collaboration, new investigations, and higher quality research. Given the rising cost of international travel, the grant will enable students (who otherwise do not have sufficient funds) to attend the conference in Canada. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project, by enabling students to attend who might not otherwise be able, will increase the dissemination of the conference's research results to a larger and more diverse audience. It also integrates research and education of graduate students by allowing students to observe high-quality presentations and interact with senior researchers in the field. By giving preference in grant awards to women and minority students, it is hoped the participation among these underrepresented groups will be widened. Furthermore, by advertising to a wide range of colleges and universities, participants from a more diverse set of institutions should be able to attend and benefit from the conference.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1452228</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Allman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Allman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mallman@icir.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4402351792</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000279986</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>International Computer Science Institute</Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<ZipCode>947041345</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106662900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2150 Shattuck Ave, Suite 1100</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>187909478</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INTERNATIONAL COMPUTER SCIENCE INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[International Computer Science Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947041159</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1947 Center Street, Suite 600]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 14th ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC),sponsored by ACM SIGCOMM and co-sponsored by USENIX, was held in Vancouver, BC, Canada, November 5-7, 2014. This project helped fund15 graduate students from US institutions to attend this conference. &nbsp;IMC is the primary venue for presenting new research results on collecting and analyzing measurements of the Internet. Attending conferences such as IMC is of paramount importance for graduate students pursuing research in the field. Authors have the opportunity to present their work and all attendees have a chance to interact with many others performing leading-edge research in the field.</p> <p><br />This travel grant, by enabling students to attend who might not otherwise be able, has increased the dissemination of the conference's research results to a larger and more diverse audience. It also integrated research and education of graduate students by allowing students to observe high-quality presentations and interact with senior researchers in the field. By giving preference in grant awards to women and minority students (two awardees are female), we helped widen the participation among these underrepresented groups. Furthermore, by advertising to a wide range of colleges and universities, participants from a more diverse set of institutions should be able to attend and benefit from the conference.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Allman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 14th ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC),sponsored by ACM SIGCOMM and co-sponsored by USENIX, was held in Vancouver, BC, Canada, November 5-7, 2014. This project helped fund15 graduate students from US institutions to attend this conference.  IMC is the primary venue for presenting new research results on collecting and analyzing measurements of the Internet. Attending conferences such as IMC is of paramount importance for graduate students pursuing research in the field. Authors have the opportunity to present their work and all attendees have a chance to interact with many others performing leading-edge research in the field.   This travel grant, by enabling students to attend who might not otherwise be able, has increased the dissemination of the conference's research results to a larger and more diverse audience. It also integrated research and education of graduate students by allowing students to observe high-quality presentations and interact with senior researchers in the field. By giving preference in grant awards to women and minority students (two awardees are female), we helped widen the participation among these underrepresented groups. Furthermore, by advertising to a wide range of colleges and universities, participants from a more diverse set of institutions should be able to attend and benefit from the conference.       Last Modified: 02/03/2016       Submitted by: Mark Allman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
