<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: CHS: Collaborative Research: Analyzing Elder Care to Guide the Design of Caregiver Robots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38825.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim Glinert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eglinert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One approach to expanding the availability of elder care and reducing elder care costs is to increase the number of elders who can live independently in their own homes which is referred to as "aging in place". This is an attractive option because elders prefer to live independently and report better health and quality of life when they do, and because aging in place can reduce the increasing costs of elder health care. However, aging in place still requires caregivers, and caregivers are in short supply. One approach to expanding the availability of caregivers for elders who are aging in place is to develop robots that can serve as caregivers in these homes. Research already suggests that many elders are open to this possibility, especially if it allows them to retain their independence. Furthermore, many elders report that for many tasks they would actually prefer to be helped by a robot rather than another human. As is the case for human caregivers, robot caregivers will be enmeshed in a larger complex social network and technical system beyond just the caregivers and the person who is being cared for. This larger context will need to be understood in order for robotic caregivers to successfully deliver the care that is needed, such as to know who to contact and with what information if the person that they are assisting is not following his or her usual patterns of behavior. This project will explore and describe how caregiving robots should function by analyzing the current form of caregiving in elders' homes, by creating a detailed account of current elder care practices, and by translating this account into design recommendations for caregiving robots.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The analysis will begin by describing the complex socio-technical context of current and future caregiving systems, specifically in terms of the work function and the work domain of the human or robot caregiver. Work function will be described independently of who or what will perform those functions. Work domain will be analyzed using a variety of techniques such as Abstraction-Decomposition Spaces (ADSs) and Contextual Activity Diagrams (ConADs). ADSs will map the relationships between a home's overall objectives and physical resources at several different levels of abstraction, such as by mapping the objective of providing a safe physical environment to different resources that are available to assist with transfers. ConADs will relate different work functions to different work situations, such as by relating the administration of medications to the appropriate time of day and location in the home. Based on these analyses of work function and work domain, the project will draft, refine, and validate formal descriptions of design requirements for caregiving robots.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1452422</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Cherry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Cherry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barbara.cherry@ttuhsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8067432961</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000573156</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University Health Science Center</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794306271</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067434565</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3601 4th Street, MS 6271</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>609980727</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY HEALTH SCIENCES CENTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University Health Science Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794153398</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3601 4th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~38825</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Elders generally prefer to live independently, i.e., age in place, and report better health and quality of life when they do so. To age in place, elders often depend on caregivers. Unfortunately, caregivers are in short supply. To address that shortfall, one option is to develop caregiver robots.</p> <p>To best design caregiver robots, one would need a detailed account of the caregiving that takes place in elders&rsquo; homes. Unfortunately, such a detailed account of caregiving did not exist. Accordingly, we sought to develop one.</p> <p>To do so, the research team completed 4 steps: 1) analyzing existing caregiving documentation, 2) observing caregiving and interviewing caregivers, 3) drafting and/or refining our aging in place system description, and 4) validating our system description. Steps 2 and 3 were iterative. Our research revealed a number of important findings.</p> <p>&nbsp;For example, we discovered that the aging in place system exhibited all nine main characteristics of socio-technical systems, which are comprised of the many workers, technologies, and environments that interact to produce work, in this case, caregiving. Workers in such systems coordinate, have diverse backgrounds (e.g., helpful neighbors and elders&rsquo; physicians will likely have different backgrounds), may not be collocated (e.g., caregivers may have to coordinate with medical personnel who are not present in the elder&rsquo;s home), and interact with technologies that automate work (e.g., a device that measures blood pressure). Information in such systems is imperfect (e.g., unclear communication during shift changes), and frequently filters through technology (e.g., measuring temperature via an ear thermometer). Work in such systems changes over time (e.g., as elders&rsquo; needs change), involves unexpected events (e.g., a fall), and has serious consequences if not done correctly. Accordingly, we concluded that caregiver robots should be conceptualized as workers in aging in place socio-technical systems rather than as consumer products. How one conceptualizes caregiver robots has important implications for how one goes about designing them. Specifically, if one conceptualized caregiver robots as consumer products, then one would design them so as to align with consumer&rsquo;s preferences (i.e., design them to look and act in ways that potential users preferred). Instead, if one conceptualized caregiver robots as workers in aging in place socio-technical systems, then one would design them so as to have the knowledge, skills, and abilities necessary to meet elders&rsquo; caregiving needs, independent of potential users&rsquo; preferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;Furthermore, our research made clear that caregiving for those who age in place is a complex and nuanced activity, which cannot be pursued in a one-size-fits-all way; rather, caregivers performed different sets of actions to accomplish the same goal depending on the current state of the system, which has been referred to as context-conditioned variability. Furthermore, the quality of care would have suffered greatly had caregivers not exhibited context-conditioned variability. Accordingly, in order to develop caregiver robots that provide high quality care, we must understand the context-conditioned variability that occurs during caregiving and design caregiver robots that can exhibit such variability appropriately. Toward that end, we described 21 contextual factors that influenced caregivers&rsquo; meal preparation decisions, as well as how those factors interacted with one another. Furthermore, we identified concrete implications of those factors for the design of caregiver robots that will prepare meals.</p> <p>&nbsp;Finally, our research revealed that caregiver robots would need to perform certain tasks that had not been previously detailed. For example, during data collection, a caregiver was observed supervising an elder&rsquo;s walk around his apartment complex. The elder enjoyed these supervised walks, but they were very infrequent because the caregiver usually had too many other caregiving duties to perform. Accordingly, the elder sometimes took short unsupervised walks, which was very dangerous because he was functionally blind and did not use a cane or guide dog. In response, we investigated how a caregiver robot could supervise the elder&rsquo;s walks. In particular, we argued that the caregiver robot must understand the elder&rsquo;s field of safe travel, which is determined by the elder&rsquo;s action capabilities relative to the environment in which the walks would take place (i.e., affordances). Furthermore, we aimed to leverage what is known about a person&rsquo;s abilities to perceive another person&rsquo;s action capabilities in order to inform the design of caregiver robots that perceive elder&rsquo;s action capabilities, and thus the elder&rsquo;s field of safe travel. We also developed means by which caregiver robots could computationally represent and reason with incomplete knowledge about the elder&rsquo;s field of safe travel.</p> <p>&nbsp;In sum, our research addressed fundamental human-robot collaboration research challenges.&nbsp; The products of this research will facilitate caregiver robot development, the development of other technologies that are designed to support elders who age in place (e.g., smart home technologies), efforts to improve human caregivers&rsquo; activities, as well as research efforts to better understand the aging process.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Barbara&nbsp;Cherry</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Elders generally prefer to live independently, i.e., age in place, and report better health and quality of life when they do so. To age in place, elders often depend on caregivers. Unfortunately, caregivers are in short supply. To address that shortfall, one option is to develop caregiver robots.  To best design caregiver robots, one would need a detailed account of the caregiving that takes place in elders? homes. Unfortunately, such a detailed account of caregiving did not exist. Accordingly, we sought to develop one.  To do so, the research team completed 4 steps: 1) analyzing existing caregiving documentation, 2) observing caregiving and interviewing caregivers, 3) drafting and/or refining our aging in place system description, and 4) validating our system description. Steps 2 and 3 were iterative. Our research revealed a number of important findings.   For example, we discovered that the aging in place system exhibited all nine main characteristics of socio-technical systems, which are comprised of the many workers, technologies, and environments that interact to produce work, in this case, caregiving. Workers in such systems coordinate, have diverse backgrounds (e.g., helpful neighbors and elders? physicians will likely have different backgrounds), may not be collocated (e.g., caregivers may have to coordinate with medical personnel who are not present in the elder?s home), and interact with technologies that automate work (e.g., a device that measures blood pressure). Information in such systems is imperfect (e.g., unclear communication during shift changes), and frequently filters through technology (e.g., measuring temperature via an ear thermometer). Work in such systems changes over time (e.g., as elders? needs change), involves unexpected events (e.g., a fall), and has serious consequences if not done correctly. Accordingly, we concluded that caregiver robots should be conceptualized as workers in aging in place socio-technical systems rather than as consumer products. How one conceptualizes caregiver robots has important implications for how one goes about designing them. Specifically, if one conceptualized caregiver robots as consumer products, then one would design them so as to align with consumer?s preferences (i.e., design them to look and act in ways that potential users preferred). Instead, if one conceptualized caregiver robots as workers in aging in place socio-technical systems, then one would design them so as to have the knowledge, skills, and abilities necessary to meet elders? caregiving needs, independent of potential users? preferences.   Furthermore, our research made clear that caregiving for those who age in place is a complex and nuanced activity, which cannot be pursued in a one-size-fits-all way; rather, caregivers performed different sets of actions to accomplish the same goal depending on the current state of the system, which has been referred to as context-conditioned variability. Furthermore, the quality of care would have suffered greatly had caregivers not exhibited context-conditioned variability. Accordingly, in order to develop caregiver robots that provide high quality care, we must understand the context-conditioned variability that occurs during caregiving and design caregiver robots that can exhibit such variability appropriately. Toward that end, we described 21 contextual factors that influenced caregivers? meal preparation decisions, as well as how those factors interacted with one another. Furthermore, we identified concrete implications of those factors for the design of caregiver robots that will prepare meals.   Finally, our research revealed that caregiver robots would need to perform certain tasks that had not been previously detailed. For example, during data collection, a caregiver was observed supervising an elder?s walk around his apartment complex. The elder enjoyed these supervised walks, but they were very infrequent because the caregiver usually had too many other caregiving duties to perform. Accordingly, the elder sometimes took short unsupervised walks, which was very dangerous because he was functionally blind and did not use a cane or guide dog. In response, we investigated how a caregiver robot could supervise the elder?s walks. In particular, we argued that the caregiver robot must understand the elder?s field of safe travel, which is determined by the elder?s action capabilities relative to the environment in which the walks would take place (i.e., affordances). Furthermore, we aimed to leverage what is known about a person?s abilities to perceive another person?s action capabilities in order to inform the design of caregiver robots that perceive elder?s action capabilities, and thus the elder?s field of safe travel. We also developed means by which caregiver robots could computationally represent and reason with incomplete knowledge about the elder?s field of safe travel.   In sum, our research addressed fundamental human-robot collaboration research challenges.  The products of this research will facilitate caregiver robot development, the development of other technologies that are designed to support elders who age in place (e.g., smart home technologies), efforts to improve human caregivers? activities, as well as research efforts to better understand the aging process.            Last Modified: 12/01/2017       Submitted by: Barbara Cherry]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
