<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Biogeochemical arsenic cycling in a Paleoarchean ocean basin</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>87000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Luciana Astiz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lastiz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924705</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Kimberly D. Myers has been awarded an NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship to investigate evidence for arsenic cycling in 3.2 billion-year-old Fig Tree Group sediments within the Barberton Greenstone Belt, South Africa. Microorganisms control arsenic redox reactions in modern near surface environments. Arsenic (As) metabolism also may have played an important role in Archean microbial ecosystems; however, current models of microbial arsenic cycling in the Archean are poorly constrained by observations in the sedimentary record. Arsenopyrite (FeAsS) was discovered within hematite-rich sediments deposited in a shallow marine setting. Preliminary analyses demonstrated that the As in FeAsS was introduced as As(III) or As(V) during or shortly after these iron rich sediments were deposited, then later reduced, indicating a complex arsenic redox cycle in the Fig Tree basin that may have involved microbial activity. This research will generate results of significant interest to several earth- and life-science research themes. It will improve our understanding of arsenic behavior in Archean surface environments and may uncover evidence for the earliest microbially driven arsenic cycle on Earth, a subject of interest to many environmental and evolutionary microbiologists. This work will also contribute to our understanding of arsenic mobility in modern reducing sediments, and could inform remediation efforts for arsenic-contaminated aquifers that negatively impact the health of millions of people worldwide. In conjunction with Texas A&amp;M University Libraries, Dr. Myers will also be participating in a nation-wide effort to provide open-access learning materials to university students as a low cost alternative to traditional textbook resources. She will compose a chapter for an open-access introductory Geology textbook comparing the Earth's geochemical cycles before and after the Great Oxidation Event. The text will include online learning modules following the story of this NSF-funded research project from design to execution to motivate young geoscientists, especially women, and reinforce the role of creativity in scientific achievement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Myers will perform her research in conjunction with the Department of Geology and Geophysics at Texas A&amp;M University and the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, Columbia University. She will conduct fieldwork in South Africa to further characterize As-containing jasper deposits. Rock samples will be examined using arsenic K-edge absorption spectroscopy, and &amp;#956;-XRF. A multi-faceted experimental and analytical approach will be used to understand how As was introduced, retained, and preserved in the Fig Tree Group sediments. The mechanisms for As introduction and retention in Fe-oxy-hydroxide and silica rich amorphous solids will be examined experimentally, with a specific focus on impact of the oxidation state of As, and the effect of microorganisms on the adsorption and retention of As(III) and As(V) to sediments under anaerobic conditions. The precipitation of arsenopyrite will then be examined in these Fe- and silica-rich solids both abiotically in the presence of sulfide, and in the presence of a consortium of As-, Fe-, and S-reducing microorganisms. Experimental material will be examined using SEM-EDS, Raman spectroscopy, and arsenic K-edge absorption spectroscopy, to obtain a robust model for the (bio)geochemical behavior of arsenic in the Archean Fig Tree depositional basin.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1452347</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Myers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly D Myers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6073398572</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Myers                   Kimberly       D</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787233125</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Geology & Geophysics]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433115</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>Postdoctoral Fellowships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~87000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~87000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="normal">This fellowship project investigated arsenic (As) enrichments discovered in Paleoarchean (3.26-billion-years-old) cherts, specifically to determine whether As oxidation and reduction (biogeochemical cycling) by microorganisms contributed to their origin and preservation. The discovery of As in sediments of this age was of significant importance: we currently have a poor record of redox-sensitive elements such as As, which are mobile under the reducing conditions on the early Earth's surface. Arsenic cycling is dominated by microorganisms in modern anaerobic environments and proposed to play a critical role in microbial ecosystems on the early Earth, before the evolution of oxygenic photosynthesis. This study was the first to confirm that As was utilized by microorganisms in environments older than 3.0 Ga. This work also provides the first (and most ancient) direct evidence for As(III)-driven photosynthesis in 3.26 Ga environments, and showed that As photosynthesis provided energy and carbon to support diverse microorganisms cycling iron (Fe), As, and sulfur (S) in ancient Fig Tree lagoons.</p> <p>Fieldwork and sample collection were conducted at a 3.26-billion-year-old outcrop in the Barberton Greenstone Belt, South Africa, where the distribution of As was recorded at the environment-scale using X-ray fluorescence (Fig. 1). Significant As and Fe co-enrichments through the outcrop demonstrate a primary, geochemical link between these elements at the time of deposition (Fig. 1b). Compelling evidence for microbial As cycling was discovered in conglomerates, which contain pebbles with well-preserved sediments that eroded from diverse, heterogeneous, local environments (Fig. 2a). Laboratory analyses of conglomerate pebbles supported outcrop-scale evidence for early As and Fe co-deposition (Fig. 1b) and further demonstrated that As and Fe were deposited in oxidized associations (Fe(III)-oxides with As(V)). The signatures preserved in the sediments provided a record of early environmental signals unaffected by late stages of alteration (Fig. 2b).</p> <p>Fine-scale analyses of As distribution, mineralogy, and oxidation states in deposits provided direct evidence that As was cycled by microorganisms. Arsenic(V), which was previously unconfirmed in ancient environments, was measured in the most well-preserved deposits, and was deposited in direct association with primary organic carbon in carbonaceous grains that resemble cells (Fig. 3a), showing strong evidence that As was oxidized by As(III)-driven photosynthesis. These deposits also show that rapid preservation in evaporating seawater was essential to preserve As enrichments, and that rapid, early reduction was also critical for preserving the As signals (Fig. 3b). Systematic analyses of Fe and As in pebbles revealed two primary modes of As preservation resulting from early post-depositional conditions, and the microbial pathways and conditions that formed each mode of Fe-As association (Fig. 4). First, greater As was preserved in the most rapidly reduced sediments, which also preserved As(V) in stark disequilibrium with surrounding phases (Fig. 4, left panel). In contrast, sediments that were not reduced rapidly preserved more Fe(III)-oxides (Fig. 4, right panel), during which As was mobilized and lost from sediments during microbial sulfidization, producing distinctly different Fe-As-S associations that strongly resemble those occurring under similar conditions in modern environments.</p> <p class="normal"><strong>Intellectual merit and Broader Impacts:</strong> This work generated results of significant interest to Earth and Life science research themes. Foremost, it provided the first definitive record for the existence of a high-potential oxidant (As(V)) by 3.26 Ga. This discovery provides an important benchmark, informing the capacity of early environments to support life, long-standing models of Earth surface evolution, and novel techniques for Archean geobiology research. For example, the shallow water conglomerate pebbles studied here represent an expansive set of previously unknown environments that will continue to inform studies about early life and early processes for decades to come. The approach used here, which combined micro-to-environment scale techniques across outcrop (environment) and pebble (microenvironment) scales allowed the development of robust, environment-scale models for element cycling. These models are capable of distinguishing primary, biological, and late-diagenetic signals in a way that has never been achieved previously, and the implementation of this approach will help inform future early Earth investigations, and potentially studies of As and S-rich worlds like Mars.</p> <p>In addition to informing Archean life, the Fe and As geochemical processes recorded in these cherts strongly resemble modern those that occur in As-contaminated environments in southeast Asia. Groundwater As contamination is the largest global health crisis on Earth. Results from this work have already been used to improve models for linked As and Fe behavior in As contaminated groundwaters in Dr. Myers&rsquo; work on As behavior in Bangladesh riverbank aquifers. In additional to traditional journal publication and scholarly presentations, the outcomes of this project are being incorporated into forthcoming, collaborative Open Access learning exercises for high school and university level classrooms, and are serving as a model for Open Access educational resource development for the educational community at large.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Kimberly&nbsp;D&nbsp;Myers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506638001450_Fig2-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506638001450_Fig2-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 2. Diverse environments in Fig Tree conglomerate pebbles record evidence of early, in-place As preservation before erosion"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506638001450_Fig2-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 2. Diverse environments in Fig Tree conglomerate pebbles record evidence of early, in-place As preservation before erosion"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 2 (a) Fig Tree conglomerates contain heterogeneous pebbles at local scales (circled areas). (b) Micro-X-ray fluorescence maps of conglomerate surfaces demonstrate early arsenic (As) preservation before pebble erosion. Late conglomerate alteration mobilized barium (Ba), but did not mobilize As.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly D. Myers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;D&nbsp;Myers</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 2. Diverse environments in Fig Tree conglomerate pebbles record evidence of early, in-place As preservation before erosion</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506635698594_Fig3-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506635698594_Fig3-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 3. Arsenic(V) measured with primary organic carbon in intact, unaltered grains demonstrates photosynthetic As-oxidation and rapid, incomplete reduction in evaporative lagoons"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506635698594_Fig3-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 3. Arsenic(V) measured with primary organic carbon in intact, unaltered grains demonstrates photosynthetic As-oxidation and rapid, incomplete reduction in evaporative lagoons"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 3 (a) Arsenic(V) measured in intact grains shows its co-production with organic carbon via As(III)-photosynthesis. (b) Micro-scale Fe, As, and S distributions show As was preserved in the earliest stages of sedimentation (ie. evaporative fluid-escape cracks) preserving early biological signals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly D. Myers</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;D&nbsp;Myers</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 3. Arsenic(V) measured with primary organic carbon in intact, unaltered grains demonstrates photosynthetic As-oxidation and rapid, incomplete reduction in evaporative lagoons</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506636129560_Fig4-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506636129560_Fig4-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 4. Early sediment conditions promoted two major biogeochemical pathways for As preservation in 3.26 Ga shallow-water environments"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506636129560_Fig4-NSFoutcomesKDM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 4. Early sediment conditions promoted two major biogeochemical pathways for As preservation in 3.26 Ga shallow-water environments"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 4. Two pathways of early reduction, preserved in distinct Fe-As-S microstructures, resulted from micro-scale conditions in early Fe(III) and As(V) deposits. Evaporation drove rapid reduction, producing high-As (left) associations. Alternatively, slow reduction led to low-As (right) associations</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly D. Myers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;D&nbsp;Myers</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 4. Early sediment conditions promoted two major biogeochemical pathways for As preservation in 3.26 Ga shallow-water environments</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506635112955_Fig1-NSFoutcomes-KDM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506635112955_Fig1-NSFoutcomes-KDM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1. Arsenic was deposited with iron in 3.26 Ga environments of the Barberton Greenstone Belt"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1452347/1452347_10366728_1506635112955_Fig1-NSFoutcomes-KDM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1. Arsenic was deposited with iron in 3.26 Ga environments of the Barberton Greenstone Belt"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig.1. (a) Outcrop of bedded, late Onverwacht-aged cherts, overlain by Fig Tree-aged delta (3.26 Ga). (b) Elemental analysis shows co-occurrence of arsenic (As) and iron (Fe) in these environments, especially in shallow-water conglomerate pebbles. Background As levels (red dash) seen in barite (Ba).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly D. Myers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;D&nbsp;Myers</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1. Arsenic was deposited with iron in 3.26 Ga environments of the Barberton Greenstone Belt</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This fellowship project investigated arsenic (As) enrichments discovered in Paleoarchean (3.26-billion-years-old) cherts, specifically to determine whether As oxidation and reduction (biogeochemical cycling) by microorganisms contributed to their origin and preservation. The discovery of As in sediments of this age was of significant importance: we currently have a poor record of redox-sensitive elements such as As, which are mobile under the reducing conditions on the early Earth's surface. Arsenic cycling is dominated by microorganisms in modern anaerobic environments and proposed to play a critical role in microbial ecosystems on the early Earth, before the evolution of oxygenic photosynthesis. This study was the first to confirm that As was utilized by microorganisms in environments older than 3.0 Ga. This work also provides the first (and most ancient) direct evidence for As(III)-driven photosynthesis in 3.26 Ga environments, and showed that As photosynthesis provided energy and carbon to support diverse microorganisms cycling iron (Fe), As, and sulfur (S) in ancient Fig Tree lagoons.  Fieldwork and sample collection were conducted at a 3.26-billion-year-old outcrop in the Barberton Greenstone Belt, South Africa, where the distribution of As was recorded at the environment-scale using X-ray fluorescence (Fig. 1). Significant As and Fe co-enrichments through the outcrop demonstrate a primary, geochemical link between these elements at the time of deposition (Fig. 1b). Compelling evidence for microbial As cycling was discovered in conglomerates, which contain pebbles with well-preserved sediments that eroded from diverse, heterogeneous, local environments (Fig. 2a). Laboratory analyses of conglomerate pebbles supported outcrop-scale evidence for early As and Fe co-deposition (Fig. 1b) and further demonstrated that As and Fe were deposited in oxidized associations (Fe(III)-oxides with As(V)). The signatures preserved in the sediments provided a record of early environmental signals unaffected by late stages of alteration (Fig. 2b).  Fine-scale analyses of As distribution, mineralogy, and oxidation states in deposits provided direct evidence that As was cycled by microorganisms. Arsenic(V), which was previously unconfirmed in ancient environments, was measured in the most well-preserved deposits, and was deposited in direct association with primary organic carbon in carbonaceous grains that resemble cells (Fig. 3a), showing strong evidence that As was oxidized by As(III)-driven photosynthesis. These deposits also show that rapid preservation in evaporating seawater was essential to preserve As enrichments, and that rapid, early reduction was also critical for preserving the As signals (Fig. 3b). Systematic analyses of Fe and As in pebbles revealed two primary modes of As preservation resulting from early post-depositional conditions, and the microbial pathways and conditions that formed each mode of Fe-As association (Fig. 4). First, greater As was preserved in the most rapidly reduced sediments, which also preserved As(V) in stark disequilibrium with surrounding phases (Fig. 4, left panel). In contrast, sediments that were not reduced rapidly preserved more Fe(III)-oxides (Fig. 4, right panel), during which As was mobilized and lost from sediments during microbial sulfidization, producing distinctly different Fe-As-S associations that strongly resemble those occurring under similar conditions in modern environments. Intellectual merit and Broader Impacts: This work generated results of significant interest to Earth and Life science research themes. Foremost, it provided the first definitive record for the existence of a high-potential oxidant (As(V)) by 3.26 Ga. This discovery provides an important benchmark, informing the capacity of early environments to support life, long-standing models of Earth surface evolution, and novel techniques for Archean geobiology research. For example, the shallow water conglomerate pebbles studied here represent an expansive set of previously unknown environments that will continue to inform studies about early life and early processes for decades to come. The approach used here, which combined micro-to-environment scale techniques across outcrop (environment) and pebble (microenvironment) scales allowed the development of robust, environment-scale models for element cycling. These models are capable of distinguishing primary, biological, and late-diagenetic signals in a way that has never been achieved previously, and the implementation of this approach will help inform future early Earth investigations, and potentially studies of As and S-rich worlds like Mars.  In addition to informing Archean life, the Fe and As geochemical processes recorded in these cherts strongly resemble modern those that occur in As-contaminated environments in southeast Asia. Groundwater As contamination is the largest global health crisis on Earth. Results from this work have already been used to improve models for linked As and Fe behavior in As contaminated groundwaters in Dr. Myers? work on As behavior in Bangladesh riverbank aquifers. In additional to traditional journal publication and scholarly presentations, the outcomes of this project are being incorporated into forthcoming, collaborative Open Access learning exercises for high school and university level classrooms, and are serving as a model for Open Access educational resource development for the educational community at large.       Last Modified: 09/28/2017       Submitted by: Kimberly D Myers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
