<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:  Modeling systemic risk: Finding precursors of emerging financial crises</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>57721.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>57721</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Seung-Hyun Hong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In our modern world, the critical infrastructure systems like electric power, water supply telecommunications and banking and finance that affect all areas of daily life are usually interdependent. Even though systemic risk is not unique to markets and financial institutions, the far-reaching consequences from the failure of a financial institution are in general much more significant than the impact of the demise of a non-financial institution. The failure of individual companies within a particular industry will not propagate throughout the corporate system, but the failure of a one large bank can bring the economy to the brink of disaster. This proposal will use tolls from economics, physics, computer science and statistics to build a model that will monitor financial systems and develop an early warning system for impending financial crises. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to use concepts from complexity science and interdependent network theory to create a signaling mechanism for potential financial crisis cascades based on the complex interdependencies of different economic and financial networks. The research will demonstrate short-range and long-range correlations in interacting networks and identify and describe the dependencies of different financial networks as a complex system. It will model the cascading effect of a crisis using dependency links that connect the failure of one network node to the failure of another network node. The proposal will combine information from bank analysis, investor sentiments, sovereign debt and regulatory frameworks to create monitoring system and a potential early warning for the global financial system.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1452061</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>H. Eugene</FirstName>
<LastName>Stanley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>H. Eugene Stanley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hes@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173532617</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000203870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Irena</FirstName>
<LastName>Vodenska</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Irena Vodenska</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vodenska@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173580005</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673979</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~57721</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Summary Intellectual Merit: Since the beginning of the EAGER award, we analyzed the network structure of lagged correlations among daily financial news sentiments and returns of financial market indices of 40 countries from 2002 to 2012. Using a spectral method, we decomposed the network into bipartite sub-structures, and showed that these sub-structures are relevant to the performance of prediction models, bridging concepts from network theory and time series analysis. Our results suggest that, at the daily level, endogenous influences among financial markets overwhelm exogenous influences of news outlets, and that changes in financial news sentiments respond to market movements more substantially than they drive them (Curme et al., 2015). This work has been published at the International Journal of Theoretical and Applied Finance. A second paper, &ldquo;Multiple Tipping Points and Optimal Repairing in Interacting Networks&rdquo; under review in Nature Communications, proposes a model to study the collective behavior of coupled interacting systems and investigates the fundamental processes of failure, damage spread, and recovery. We find a very rich phase diagram that becomes increasingly more complex as the number of interacting networks increases (Majdandzic et al., 2015).</p> <p>Summary Broader Impacts: We attempted to answer questions such as whether our models can be generalized and applied universally to more than one system, and whether the novel methodologies that we have developed could be useful to teams of interdisciplinary researchers to develop more sophisticated methods for measuring the fragility of interconnected systems. Interdisciplinary research in modeling and visualizing financial distress propagation through interdependent economic networks could be useful for policy makers and regulators. The economic dynamics tools developed could provide novel approaches for computing of important economic indicators of systemic risk and for building an infrastructure for systemic risk management.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2015<br>      Modified by: Irena&nbsp;Vodenska</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1452061/1452061_10339622_1450107732919_Fig-2NSF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1452061/1452061_10339622_1450107732919_Fig-2NSF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bank-Asset Bipartite Network: Japanese Banking System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1452061/1452061_10339622_1450107732919_Fig-2NSF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bank-Asset Bipartite Network: Japanese Banking System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Bipartite network of banks and assets. Crimson and light green circles show banks and assets,respectively, with diameters proportional to the bank and asset sizes based on FY 1994 data. The width of links is proportional to the size of the banks' holding of corresponding assets.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sakamoto, Y. & Vodenska, I., Systemic risk and structural change in bipartite bank network: new perspective on Japanese banking crisis of the 1990s., Journal of Complex Networks, 2015 (under review)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Irena&nbsp;Vodenska</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bank-Asset Bipartite Network: Japanese Banking System</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary Intellectual Merit: Since the beginning of the EAGER award, we analyzed the network structure of lagged correlations among daily financial news sentiments and returns of financial market indices of 40 countries from 2002 to 2012. Using a spectral method, we decomposed the network into bipartite sub-structures, and showed that these sub-structures are relevant to the performance of prediction models, bridging concepts from network theory and time series analysis. Our results suggest that, at the daily level, endogenous influences among financial markets overwhelm exogenous influences of news outlets, and that changes in financial news sentiments respond to market movements more substantially than they drive them (Curme et al., 2015). This work has been published at the International Journal of Theoretical and Applied Finance. A second paper, "Multiple Tipping Points and Optimal Repairing in Interacting Networks" under review in Nature Communications, proposes a model to study the collective behavior of coupled interacting systems and investigates the fundamental processes of failure, damage spread, and recovery. We find a very rich phase diagram that becomes increasingly more complex as the number of interacting networks increases (Majdandzic et al., 2015).  Summary Broader Impacts: We attempted to answer questions such as whether our models can be generalized and applied universally to more than one system, and whether the novel methodologies that we have developed could be useful to teams of interdisciplinary researchers to develop more sophisticated methods for measuring the fragility of interconnected systems. Interdisciplinary research in modeling and visualizing financial distress propagation through interdependent economic networks could be useful for policy makers and regulators. The economic dynamics tools developed could provide novel approaches for computing of important economic indicators of systemic risk and for building an infrastructure for systemic risk management.        Last Modified: 12/14/2015       Submitted by: Irena Vodenska]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
