<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Network Protocol Stack for Galvanic Coupled Intra-body Sensors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299953.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299953</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Implanted sensors will enable the next generation of healthcare by in-situ testing of abnormal physiological conditions, personalized medicine and proactive drug delivery. These functions require energy efficient communication of data between implants through the body tissues, which is difficult to achieve via radio frequency (RF) waves owing to their high attenuation within the body. The project involves the design of a network protocol stack using weak electrical currents as the underlying communication mechanism, instead of conventional RF waves to connect the implants. This paradigm results in energy savings of two orders of magnitude compared to RF. This research will help in realizing diverse applications arising out from a network of connected implants that benefit athletes, military personnel, and other at-risk populations. The ability to proactively report physiological changes within the body will increase longevity of human life. The project incorporates outreach components targeting K-12 students, design of computer-simulation based projects, and demonstrations at public venues like science museums.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research planned in the course of this project is the first effort to systematically devise networking protocols based on galvanic coupling of electric signals. It has the following goals: (i) explore the impact of the transmission frequency and power on signal reflection and refraction at the tissue boundaries for multicast communication, (ii) design of interference-free medium access schemes that take into account heat generated at the crossings of the signal paths for all simultaneously active transceiver pairs, for both CSMA and TDMA-based approaches, (iii) research new strategies and conduct performance analysis for optimal placement of on-skin relay nodes for retrieving the sensor data from locations in the body that minimize the data gathering latency while being constrained by feasible on-body locations, and (iv) the first simulator and testbed for galvanic coupled communication using ns-3, and will also propose ways to charge the implanted sensors through contact-less magnetically coupled coils.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1453384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaushik</FirstName>
<LastName>Chowdhury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaushik R Chowdhury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krc@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173735304</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000541186</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299953</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Implanted sensors will enable the next generation of healthcare through in-situ testing of abnormal physiological conditions, personalized medicine, continuous health monitoring and proactive drug delivery. This requires energy efficient communication of data between implants through the body tissues, which is difficult to achieve in conventional radio frequency waves owing to their high attenuation within the body. The project aimed to use galvanically coupled weak electrical currents, instead of over the air RF waves, to connect the implants, which results in energy savings of two orders of magnitude within tissues. Building on our efforts on modeling the intra-body channel, the project developed a network protocol stack that incorporates transmitter parameters selection, medium access control, multicast transmissions, end to end data delivery through relays and latency calculations.<span>&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span><span><span>We started by developing the channel models of the way galvanic signals propagate in the human body to study how our communication systems should be designed to achieve the most efficient communication for various applications of intra-body networks. We developed analytical models that involve (i) a suite of expressions for modeling the resulting communication channel for weak electrical signals in a three dimensional tissue structure, (ii) validating and verifying this electrical-equivalent tissue model, (iii) obtaining the influence of different network and hardware parameters such as transmission frequency and electrode placements. Another important aspect of an efficient intra-body communication system is the efficient placement of implanted sensors. Utilizing measurement-driven tissue channel models, we developed a strategy for optimal placement of data collection points/relays in order to form an energy-efficient topology.<span>&nbsp;</span></span><br /></span></span></p> <p><span><span><span>To verify tissue safety, we analyzed the thermal distribution within tissues. We also investigated the sensitivity of the spatio-temporal temperature profile in association with the normal and extreme rates of blood perfusion. Our results confirmed that tissue heating can remain well below safe limit of 1&#9702;C. In our effort to create an efficient, safe intra-body network, we looked into utilizing beamforming for efficient intra-body transmissions. We devised a method that allows multiple intra-body implants to communicate individual sensed data to each other through CDMA code assignments, but delegates the computational burden of decoding only to the on-body surface relays.<span>&nbsp;</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span><span><span>Finally, we investigated other techniques such as Radio Frequency, Ultrasound, Galvanic, Magnetic Resonance and Capacitive coupling for intra-body communication. After thorough analysis and comparison we concluded that coupling methods are preferable to RF-methods for communication in the body due to a combination of high safety factors, low power and attenuation levels. We concluded the project by developing applications that may be benefit from galvanic coupling, as it provides a significant trade off between data rate, power, attenuation, low interference and system design, as opposed to other peer technologies. While we developed a prototype for transmitting securely body generated passwords for continuous authentication, other possible uses of our research lie in implantable continuous blood glucose management system, wireless energy harvesting for implanted sensor networks, wireless neural stimulation and numerous others.</span></span></span></p> <p>The project resulted in two PhD students graduating, both from under-represented minority groups. It also resulted in several journal and conference publications, collaborations with medical professionals, public demonstrations of the technology, and annual outreach events for K-12 students.</p> <p><span><span><span><br /></span></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Kaushik&nbsp;R&nbsp;Chowdhury</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086582845_GCIBC_report_fig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086582845_GCIBC_report_fig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Galvanic coupling and breakdown of an implanted sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086582845_GCIBC_report_fig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Galvanic coupling and breakdown of an implanted sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(Left) Propagation pathway of galvanic signals, and (Right) the role and functions of an implanted sensor</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kaushik Chowdhury</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kaushik&nbsp;R&nbsp;Chowdhury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Galvanic coupling and breakdown of an implanted sensor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086404593_testbed--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086404593_testbed--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tissue heating and safety"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086404593_testbed--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tissue heating and safety"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Skin phantom (7 ? 7 ? 0.3 ? cm cube ) coupled with 2 sources. We use the alligator clips (40 mm) as the exciting and ground electrodes. Simulated spatial thermal profile (&#9702; C ) after 5e4 secs (top right). The temperature rise is linear with almost the same slope in the phantom (bottom right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">IEE ICC Conf</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kaushik&nbsp;R&nbsp;Chowdhury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tissue heating and safety</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086250766_Concept-IBC-arm--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086250766_Concept-IBC-arm--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Concept of galvanic coupling"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1453384/1453384_10337937_1554086250766_Concept-IBC-arm--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Concept of galvanic coupling"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Galvanic coupling setup on skin surface with multiple tissue layers (a) Top view (b) Lateral view. Majority of the induced current passes through the return path of transmitter and a minor part through the body.</div> <div class="imageCredit">IEEE Trans on Biomed Circuits and Sys</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kaushik&nbsp;R&nbsp;Chowdhury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Concept of galvanic coupling</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Implanted sensors will enable the next generation of healthcare through in-situ testing of abnormal physiological conditions, personalized medicine, continuous health monitoring and proactive drug delivery. This requires energy efficient communication of data between implants through the body tissues, which is difficult to achieve in conventional radio frequency waves owing to their high attenuation within the body. The project aimed to use galvanically coupled weak electrical currents, instead of over the air RF waves, to connect the implants, which results in energy savings of two orders of magnitude within tissues. Building on our efforts on modeling the intra-body channel, the project developed a network protocol stack that incorporates transmitter parameters selection, medium access control, multicast transmissions, end to end data delivery through relays and latency calculations.   We started by developing the channel models of the way galvanic signals propagate in the human body to study how our communication systems should be designed to achieve the most efficient communication for various applications of intra-body networks. We developed analytical models that involve (i) a suite of expressions for modeling the resulting communication channel for weak electrical signals in a three dimensional tissue structure, (ii) validating and verifying this electrical-equivalent tissue model, (iii) obtaining the influence of different network and hardware parameters such as transmission frequency and electrode placements. Another important aspect of an efficient intra-body communication system is the efficient placement of implanted sensors. Utilizing measurement-driven tissue channel models, we developed a strategy for optimal placement of data collection points/relays in order to form an energy-efficient topology.    To verify tissue safety, we analyzed the thermal distribution within tissues. We also investigated the sensitivity of the spatio-temporal temperature profile in association with the normal and extreme rates of blood perfusion. Our results confirmed that tissue heating can remain well below safe limit of 1&#9702;C. In our effort to create an efficient, safe intra-body network, we looked into utilizing beamforming for efficient intra-body transmissions. We devised a method that allows multiple intra-body implants to communicate individual sensed data to each other through CDMA code assignments, but delegates the computational burden of decoding only to the on-body surface relays.   Finally, we investigated other techniques such as Radio Frequency, Ultrasound, Galvanic, Magnetic Resonance and Capacitive coupling for intra-body communication. After thorough analysis and comparison we concluded that coupling methods are preferable to RF-methods for communication in the body due to a combination of high safety factors, low power and attenuation levels. We concluded the project by developing applications that may be benefit from galvanic coupling, as it provides a significant trade off between data rate, power, attenuation, low interference and system design, as opposed to other peer technologies. While we developed a prototype for transmitting securely body generated passwords for continuous authentication, other possible uses of our research lie in implantable continuous blood glucose management system, wireless energy harvesting for implanted sensor networks, wireless neural stimulation and numerous others.  The project resulted in two PhD students graduating, both from under-represented minority groups. It also resulted in several journal and conference publications, collaborations with medical professionals, public demonstrations of the technology, and annual outreach events for K-12 students.          Last Modified: 03/31/2019       Submitted by: Kaushik R Chowdhury]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
