<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Differentiating mechanisms of ecological divergence in sympatric microbial populations using an integrated population genomics approach</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>810512.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>810512</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A centerpiece of evolutionary ecology research is to understand how new adaptations arise and spread in populations leading to speciation.  The adaptation of microbes is important to understand, because microbes are: a) the primary drivers of global biogeochemical cycles, b) the means of production for many applications in biotechnology, and c) the causes of most infectious diseases. Microbes are frequently moved around by the action of animals, plants, wind and water, and may be deposited in unfavorable habitats. As a consequence, microbes adapt to new environments through to a combination of fast mutation rates and acquisition of new genes directly from their environment. There is a pressing need to better understand these processes by which microbes generate and maintain adaptive genetic variation, because such information is needed to forecast the responses of microbial species to rapid changes in land management or climate. This project studies how adaptive genetic variation permits a common bacteria important in biotechnology and the food supply, Escherichia coli, to survive after deposition in unfavorable habitats. Data on this process can tell us about how adaptive variation in populations contributes to the formation of new species. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is designed to use the process of passive dispersal to diverse habitats as a natural experiment in order to differentiate between three models of ecological divergence in microbial populations. Studies of the landscape level structure in microbial populations will be complemented with genome-wide association studies. These experiments will link genomic polymorphisms to variation in phenotype, gene expression regulation, and source environment characteristics.  These analyses will be coupled with laboratory challenges to quantify the adaptive value of genomic polymorphisms. Machine learning analytical techniques will be used to determine which of three models of ecological divergence best explains the data. An education program will teach undergraduate students about the ecological processes contributing to microevolution and speciation in microbes. The program will combine an agent-based model and data from experiments to teach students to interpret genomic adaptations in light of ecological processes acting on microbes in natural environments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1453397</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Bergholz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Bergholz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.bergholz@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7012318045</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648592</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1735 Research Park Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>803882299</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>803882299</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Dakota State University Fargo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7968</Code>
<Text>Dimensions of Biodiversity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~147598</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~188557</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~223165</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~251192</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project focused on research about the ecological and evolutionary processes that permit microbes, including pathogens, to adapt to new environments and that may generate and maintain the tremendous amounts of natural genetic biodiversity observed in microbial species.&nbsp; For example, the species <em>E. coli </em>(the subject of this project) comprises commensal and pathogenic strains of the intestinal tract of warm-blooded animals.&nbsp; It has been observed in soil, plant-surfaces and waterways where it is used as an indicator of fecal pollution of the water and food supply.&nbsp; Like most microbial species, <em>E. coli </em>contains seemingly unfathomable genomic diversity, each genome from an individual <em>E. coli</em> cell contains approx. 5,000 genes, but the collective species pan-genome (i.e. all genes in all <em>E. coli</em>) is thought to contain 10 to 20-times as many types of genes.&nbsp; The meaning of much of that genomic biodiversity is unknown, and much of it may confer adaptations to environments outside the host.</p> <p>The work on this project combined genome-wide association studies, transcriptomics, machine learning techniques, and biogeographic analyses on <em>E. coli </em>that were cultured from surface soil in an agricultural landscape.&nbsp; It included analysis of the genetic variation associated with soil environments and with complex phenotypes important for clinical and biotechnological use of <em>E. coli</em>, like biofilms, signaling, and resistance against antimicrobials.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project tested hypotheses about the geographic distribution and adaptation of <em>E. coli </em>in soil.&nbsp; We collected comprehensive landscape-scale data on the genomes of a microbial population living in, and adapting to, conditions in soil.&nbsp;&nbsp; The project generated an ecological database comprising more than 3,300 new isolates of <em>E. coli </em>from 1,430 surface soil samples and whole genome sequences from 944 <em>E. coli</em> to add an important comparison set to the already extensive collection of <em>E. coli </em>from human and animal hosts.&nbsp; The work on this project generated fourteen new genome-wide association data sets for important microbial traits, and it generated eight new datasets of gene-by-environment interactions for each of three major subspecies (phylogroups) of <em>E. coli</em>.&nbsp; During this work, the project provided the primary research training experiences for nine graduate students and fourteen undergraduate researchers.</p> <p>Although three major phylogroups of <em>E. coli </em>appear to have similar ecology in the host intestinal environment, they displayed dramatically different ecology outside the host with differing persistence in, spread through, and adaptation to the soil environments that they encountered.&nbsp; We concluded one phylogroup, phylogroup D, is displaying clear evidence of adaptation to soil environments that are the result of natural selection on alleles in the core set of <em>E. coli </em>gene families as well as gene transfer in the accessory gene families.&nbsp; Many of those genetic changes occurred in combination across laboratory phenotypes and soil environments, providing further evidence that this type of <em>E. coli </em>is acting as a different ecological species<em> </em>when outside the host.&nbsp; In contrast, two other phylogroups showed little evidence of long-term adaptation to various surface soil environments.&nbsp; As a result, we concluded that much of the genomic biodiversity in <em>E. coli </em>is important for adaptation when <em>E. coli </em>leave the intestinal environment and that different phylogroups within the species responded to the soil environment very differently.</p> <p>The results have relevance for clinical practices, as extraintestinal <em>E. coli</em>, especially community-acquired and hospital-acquired urinary tract infections, contribute greatly to the incidence of antimicrobial resistant infections in clinical settings.&nbsp; Those pathogens rely on new gene families and adaptations to survive and grow outside intestine: on surfaces, skin, catheters, in urine, and in urinary tract tissues.&nbsp; The results showing that at least one major phylogroup of <em>E. coli </em>lives in surface soil also weakens the status of <em>E. coli </em>in water as an indicator of fecal pollution, even in temperate regions (where this study was conducted) because many <em>E. coli </em>in recreational water may have originated from soil entering the water during storms, rather than in host intestines.</p> <p>The project also contributed to the training of more than sixty undergraduate students who participated in semester-long course-based research experiences to make their own discoveries about adaptation of microbial traits and genome sequencing as part of the integration of research and teaching in this CAREER award.&nbsp; The teaching program included new efforts at developing contiguous research experiences across three courses.&nbsp; Students initially encountered the course-based research experiences in a second year, full-semester, lab course that used authentic, student-conceived research to teach fundamental knowledge and methods about microbial evolution.&nbsp; Upper division courses in microbial genomics and microbial ecology taught methods of genome sequence research and analysis and interpretation of computational models of microbial evolution.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Bergholz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project focused on research about the ecological and evolutionary processes that permit microbes, including pathogens, to adapt to new environments and that may generate and maintain the tremendous amounts of natural genetic biodiversity observed in microbial species.  For example, the species E. coli (the subject of this project) comprises commensal and pathogenic strains of the intestinal tract of warm-blooded animals.  It has been observed in soil, plant-surfaces and waterways where it is used as an indicator of fecal pollution of the water and food supply.  Like most microbial species, E. coli contains seemingly unfathomable genomic diversity, each genome from an individual E. coli cell contains approx. 5,000 genes, but the collective species pan-genome (i.e. all genes in all E. coli) is thought to contain 10 to 20-times as many types of genes.  The meaning of much of that genomic biodiversity is unknown, and much of it may confer adaptations to environments outside the host.  The work on this project combined genome-wide association studies, transcriptomics, machine learning techniques, and biogeographic analyses on E. coli that were cultured from surface soil in an agricultural landscape.  It included analysis of the genetic variation associated with soil environments and with complex phenotypes important for clinical and biotechnological use of E. coli, like biofilms, signaling, and resistance against antimicrobials.   The project tested hypotheses about the geographic distribution and adaptation of E. coli in soil.  We collected comprehensive landscape-scale data on the genomes of a microbial population living in, and adapting to, conditions in soil.   The project generated an ecological database comprising more than 3,300 new isolates of E. coli from 1,430 surface soil samples and whole genome sequences from 944 E. coli to add an important comparison set to the already extensive collection of E. coli from human and animal hosts.  The work on this project generated fourteen new genome-wide association data sets for important microbial traits, and it generated eight new datasets of gene-by-environment interactions for each of three major subspecies (phylogroups) of E. coli.  During this work, the project provided the primary research training experiences for nine graduate students and fourteen undergraduate researchers.  Although three major phylogroups of E. coli appear to have similar ecology in the host intestinal environment, they displayed dramatically different ecology outside the host with differing persistence in, spread through, and adaptation to the soil environments that they encountered.  We concluded one phylogroup, phylogroup D, is displaying clear evidence of adaptation to soil environments that are the result of natural selection on alleles in the core set of E. coli gene families as well as gene transfer in the accessory gene families.  Many of those genetic changes occurred in combination across laboratory phenotypes and soil environments, providing further evidence that this type of E. coli is acting as a different ecological species when outside the host.  In contrast, two other phylogroups showed little evidence of long-term adaptation to various surface soil environments.  As a result, we concluded that much of the genomic biodiversity in E. coli is important for adaptation when E. coli leave the intestinal environment and that different phylogroups within the species responded to the soil environment very differently.  The results have relevance for clinical practices, as extraintestinal E. coli, especially community-acquired and hospital-acquired urinary tract infections, contribute greatly to the incidence of antimicrobial resistant infections in clinical settings.  Those pathogens rely on new gene families and adaptations to survive and grow outside intestine: on surfaces, skin, catheters, in urine, and in urinary tract tissues.  The results showing that at least one major phylogroup of E. coli lives in surface soil also weakens the status of E. coli in water as an indicator of fecal pollution, even in temperate regions (where this study was conducted) because many E. coli in recreational water may have originated from soil entering the water during storms, rather than in host intestines.  The project also contributed to the training of more than sixty undergraduate students who participated in semester-long course-based research experiences to make their own discoveries about adaptation of microbial traits and genome sequencing as part of the integration of research and teaching in this CAREER award.  The teaching program included new efforts at developing contiguous research experiences across three courses.  Students initially encountered the course-based research experiences in a second year, full-semester, lab course that used authentic, student-conceived research to teach fundamental knowledge and methods about microbial evolution.  Upper division courses in microbial genomics and microbial ecology taught methods of genome sequence research and analysis and interpretation of computational models of microbial evolution.           Last Modified: 01/11/2021       Submitted by: Peter Bergholz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
