<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Modeling Polymer Electrolyte Microstructure: How Polymer Architecture Controls Ion Conduction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>475000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>475000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award supports theoretical and computational studies of polymeric materials for potential applications as non-flammable polymer electrolytes in a new generation of safe, lightweight batteries. The goal of this project is to develop and use innovative computational and theoretical tools to model ionic conductance in block copolymer based materials. In diblock copolymers, chains of the two different chemical types are connected together, forming a long chain molecule with different chemical composition on each end. If the two blocks are different, they phase separate (like oil and water) forming nanometer scale structures. Of special interest for future applications are diblock copolymers with added salts in which one block forms soft and the other forms hard domains. The softer domains conduct lithium ions (serving the purpose of the battery electrolyte), while the harder domains prevent the growth of lithium dendrites which can short-circuit the battery. The PI's group will focus on understanding how polymer structure controls final materials properties.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education and outreach part of this project builds on development of an interactive simulation setup with a 3D display and force-feedback joystick to communicate to students across the age groups and to the general public what polymers are and how their structure impacts material properties. The PI and members of her group will participate in the "Translating Engineering Research to K-8" (TEK8) program through the College of Engineering at OSU and use the existing infrastructure of Ohio State's STEAM Factory and Women in Engineering program to increase interest of underrepresented groups in science and engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award supports research and educational activities with a focus on development of innovative computational tools for modeling ionic conductance in block copolymer based materials. The goal is to use theoretical techniques and computer modeling to elucidate the underlying physics behind the structure and conductance of polymeric materials and to guide future synthesis efforts. The experimental systems that inspire this research are nonflammable battery electrolytes that are inherently safer and could increase battery energy density while preventing lithium dendrite growth. &lt;br/&gt;The approach is designed to overcome difficulties associated with the multiple time and length scales of the problem due to complex polymer morphology, effects of packing of finite size ions and polymeric units, and the long-range electrostatic interactions between charged species. The theoretical approach will be based on the fluid density functional theory and simulation techniques will include molecular dynamics simulations of the coarse-grained models. To bridge multiple time and length scales the strategy will be to obtain the equilibrium polymer morphology from density functional calculations and to use this structure as a starting point for coarse-grained simulations. This approach will be applied to model material properties of diblock copolymers and tapered copolymers, in which a region with a gradient in monomer composition is added between two pure blocks. The goal of this approach is to efficiently sample parameter space and to show how the materials properties depend on polymer architecture, polymer morphology, and ion concentration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education and outreach part of this project builds on development of an interactive simulation setup with a 3D display and force-feedback joystick to communicate to students across the age groups and to the general public what polymers are and how their structure impacts material properties. The PI and members of her group will participate in the "Translating Engineering Research to K-8" (TEK8) program through the College of Engineering at OSU and use the existing infrastructure of Ohio State's STEAM Factory and Women in Engineering program to increase interest of underrepresented groups in science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1454343</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa M Hall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hall.1004@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6146881017</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000645250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Polymers are large molecules composed of many smaller units bonded together into long chains. When two different types of chemical units (monomers A and B) are incorporated in the same chain in a blocky fashion (a sequence such as AAAABBBB), the resulting material can locally separate into microscopic A-rich and B-rich regions. Thus, microphase separating copolymers with added salt (ions) are of interest as battery electrolytes, among other applications, because one microphase can solvate and transport the ions, while the other provides mechanical strength or other desired properties. In designing improved materials, there are many variables to consider such as fraction of A, chain length, chemical properties of A and B, and how each phase interacts with ions (related to its dielectric strength). <br /><br />To understand how these variables work together to set the structure and ion transport properties of the materials, this work used coarse-grained modeling in which the A and B units and ions are represented as spheres. This is efficient and allows focus on the main properties of the material such as dielectric strength rather than on atomistic detail, though it is important that the coarse-grained model includes enough detail to capture appropriate experimental trends. Initial work showed, for short chain polymers without ions, that we can reproduce the proper phase diagram of specialty sequence copolymers as predicted by theoretical work (see figure), that we can use theory to initialize simulations for faster equilibration, and the impacts of sequential dispersity/blockiness. Further work showed details of chain alignment, diffusion/conduction in various structures (including showing the tortuosity of the double gyroid structure as shown in the figure), and the impact of having a ring architecture. The main intellectual merit of this project was the development and use of models with a strong and relatively long-ranged interaction potential to describe how ions are solvated by high dielectric strength polymer units. This model reproduced appropriate experimental trends in ion diffusion and conductivity with ion concentration. By applying the updated ion solvation model to a range of systems with different ion sizes and dielectric strengths, this work provided some insights into what is most relevant to the design of future materials with improved ion conductivity (see figure). Details were described in 11 peer-reviewed publications.<br /><br />One broader impact of this award was the career development of the researchers; this award partially supported the PI, one postdoctoral scholar, five graduate students, and eight undergraduates. These researchers have participated in several outreach initiatives impacting the public. Specifically, an interactive simulation demonstration about polymer chains, along with real polymer samples, was presented to K-12 students and the general public (see figure; approximately 2 presentations per year). Three of the undergraduates (along with two K-12 teachers who also participated in summer research experiences in the PI's group) were also part of a semester-long program demonstrating engineering concepts to a 6th grade after school program for underserved students. Additionally, the PI developed and twice taught a Molecular Dynamics course for undergraduate and graduate students. The scripts created as part of this project are also publicly available.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hall</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188390049_careerimage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188390049_careerimage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outreach materials"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188390049_careerimage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outreach materials"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Interactive simulation setup and physical manipulatives representing polymers used in outreach to K-12 groups and the public.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lisa Hall</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hall</div> <div class="imageTitle">Outreach materials</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188185484_Career2016highlightFig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188185484_Career2016highlightFig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Phase diagram of block copolymers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188185484_Career2016highlightFig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Phase diagram of block copolymers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phase diagram of block copolymers (blue lines) with a linear gradient region between A and B blocks (gradient is 30% of chain length) and grey lines for typical diblocks. Images of cylinder, gyroid, and perforated lamellae.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Y. Seo, J. R. Brown, and L. M. Hall, Macromolecules 48, 4974 (2015).</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hall</div> <div class="imageTitle">Phase diagram of block copolymers</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188314891_Career2018HighlightFig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188314891_Career2018HighlightFig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Diffusion constants of penetrants in copolymers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628188314891_Career2018HighlightFig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Diffusion constants of penetrants in copolymers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Normalized diffusion constant (inverse of tortuosity) of various structures shown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. H. Shen, J. R. Brown, and L. M. Hall, ACS Macro Letters 7, 1092 (2018).</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hall</div> <div class="imageTitle">Diffusion constants of penetrants in copolymers</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628187753319_CareerReport3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628187753319_CareerReport3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Transference number versus conductivity for salt-doped polymers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1454343/1454343_10350251_1628187753319_CareerReport3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Transference number versus conductivity for salt-doped polymers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Cation transference number as a function of total conductivity for a variety of salt-doped polymer systems with different anion/cation size ratios as labeled. Dielectric strength increases in the direction shown. Similar size ions can allow for higher cation conductivity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. H. Shen and L. M. Hall, Macromolecules 53, 10086 (2020).</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hall</div> <div class="imageTitle">Transference number versus conductivity for salt-doped polymers</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Polymers are large molecules composed of many smaller units bonded together into long chains. When two different types of chemical units (monomers A and B) are incorporated in the same chain in a blocky fashion (a sequence such as AAAABBBB), the resulting material can locally separate into microscopic A-rich and B-rich regions. Thus, microphase separating copolymers with added salt (ions) are of interest as battery electrolytes, among other applications, because one microphase can solvate and transport the ions, while the other provides mechanical strength or other desired properties. In designing improved materials, there are many variables to consider such as fraction of A, chain length, chemical properties of A and B, and how each phase interacts with ions (related to its dielectric strength).   To understand how these variables work together to set the structure and ion transport properties of the materials, this work used coarse-grained modeling in which the A and B units and ions are represented as spheres. This is efficient and allows focus on the main properties of the material such as dielectric strength rather than on atomistic detail, though it is important that the coarse-grained model includes enough detail to capture appropriate experimental trends. Initial work showed, for short chain polymers without ions, that we can reproduce the proper phase diagram of specialty sequence copolymers as predicted by theoretical work (see figure), that we can use theory to initialize simulations for faster equilibration, and the impacts of sequential dispersity/blockiness. Further work showed details of chain alignment, diffusion/conduction in various structures (including showing the tortuosity of the double gyroid structure as shown in the figure), and the impact of having a ring architecture. The main intellectual merit of this project was the development and use of models with a strong and relatively long-ranged interaction potential to describe how ions are solvated by high dielectric strength polymer units. This model reproduced appropriate experimental trends in ion diffusion and conductivity with ion concentration. By applying the updated ion solvation model to a range of systems with different ion sizes and dielectric strengths, this work provided some insights into what is most relevant to the design of future materials with improved ion conductivity (see figure). Details were described in 11 peer-reviewed publications.  One broader impact of this award was the career development of the researchers; this award partially supported the PI, one postdoctoral scholar, five graduate students, and eight undergraduates. These researchers have participated in several outreach initiatives impacting the public. Specifically, an interactive simulation demonstration about polymer chains, along with real polymer samples, was presented to K-12 students and the general public (see figure; approximately 2 presentations per year). Three of the undergraduates (along with two K-12 teachers who also participated in summer research experiences in the PI's group) were also part of a semester-long program demonstrating engineering concepts to a 6th grade after school program for underserved students. Additionally, the PI developed and twice taught a Molecular Dynamics course for undergraduate and graduate students. The scripts created as part of this project are also publicly available.       Last Modified: 08/05/2021       Submitted by: Lisa M Hall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
