<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: In- and Out-of-Equilibrium Behavior of Colloidal Clusters with Broken Symmetries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>548413.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>548413</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wolbrich@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924842</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Colloidal dispersions play an important role in materials processing for industries ranging from electronics to pharmaceuticals. When colloidal particles are organized into arrays and other structures, the resulting materials can exhibit optical and electrical properties that are not found in natural materials. Therefore, colloids serve as building blocks for fabricating advanced functional materials. This project will develop new approaches to make clusters of colloidal particles with well-controlled compositions and geometries, which will expand the range of materials that can be fabricated.  The project will investigate how external fields can be used to manipulate the assembly of particles into clusters and ultimately into large ensembles.  Results from the project will provide fundamental knowledge that scientists and engineers can use to develop materials and devices, such as new sensors or new coatings with controlled optical properties.  In addition, the project team will develop a summer research program in colloidal science targeted to high school students in the Denver area and especially to students from underrepresented groups.  A multi-disciplinary course titled "Engineering of Soft Materials" will be developed to engage undergraduate students in colloidal science and train them for careers in the materials industry.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;New approaches will be developed to make clusters of colloids with well-controlled broken symmetries. A microfluidic device that integrates both electric (for assembly) and optical fields (for structural cross-linking) will be used to fabricate monodisperse higher order colloidal clusters with addressable compositions and geometries. The asymmetric properties of colloidal clusters will be systematically studied within the context of particle propulsion, which constitutes a significant step toward understanding the transport properties of active colloids. A virtually patterned electrode will be used to generate micro-gradients in electric field and direct particles into periodic structures with addressable symmetry at both cluster and lattice levels. The coupled optical effects between neighboring clusters and the feasibility for making functional coatings will also be explored. The overall goal of the project is to understand how the broken-symmetry in colloidal clusters affects their in- and out-of-equilibrium behavior from the level of an individual particle to a large ensemble.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1454095</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ning</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ning Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ningwu@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3032733702</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000578320</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE COLORADO SCHOOL OF MINES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado School of Mines]]></Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 Illinois St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~548413</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this project is to develop new approaches to fabricate clusters of colloids with broken symmetries in geometry, configuration, and composition. These asymmetric properties will then be exploited to study two representative out-of- and in-equilibrium behavior of colloidal clusters, which are fundamentally different from conventional colloids.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>First, the assembly of colloidal molecules from a binary mixture of polystyrene spheres was investigated under an alternating current electric field. The rich family of assembled oligomers typically consists of a large sphere surrounded by a few smaller petal particles, driven by the dipolar attraction between large and small particles. The number of satellite particles increased with the increasing size ratio of the constituent particles. For a given size ratio, it decreased with the increasing frequency of the applied field. These trends have also been correctly captured by computing the electric energy of different oligomers based on induced dipolar and double-layer interactions. This method provided a robust way to produce a family of colloidal molecules with well-defined geometry and high yield.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to microspheres, the propulsion and assembly of colloidal clusters made of asymmetric dimers were also studied. It was demonstrated that incorporating Stern-layer conductivity resolved the puzzle that the electrohydrodynamic (EHD) flow surrounding a particle with moderate zeta potentials can be extensile. Asymmetric EHD motors made from polystyrene and silica particles exhibited behaviors consistent with the model predictions. In the high-frequency regime, a new phenomenon was discovered. All-dielectric asymmetric particles can propel along the substrate. In particular, polystyrene-silica dimers propelled with the polystyrene lobe forward at an elevated height above the electrode. With the help of nanoparticle tracers, strong and contractile hydrodynamic flow surrounding both lobes was observed. Since the frequency regime for active motion is very close to the inverse of the time scale for ions migrating in and out of the double layer, it is hypothesized that the hydrodynamic flow is originated from the electro-osmosis of induced charges within the double layer near the electrode can potentially be the mechanism. This new propulsion mechanism greatly expands the material library for designing active motors for both fundamental and practical studies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A better understanding of the EHD flow surrounding colloidal dimers was further utilized to assemble them into colloidal clusters with chirality, which have potential use as sensors to detect molecules or metamaterials with exotic optical properties. Applying electric fields can assemble dielectric dumbbell-shaped particles coated with a thin magnetic layer into chiral clusters with an equal right- and left-handedness population. However, with the superposition of an additional rotating magnetic field, the chirality of the clusters changed according to the rotating direction of the magnetic field. By controlling the direction of the magnetic field, the cluster chirality can be reversibly switched. This finding provides a convenient route to produce chiral colloidal clusters with single-handedness.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond small colloidal clusters, flexible magnetic colloidal chains were also fabricated. They are inspired by microscale swimmers that utilize long filaments or slender bodies for propulsion since one-dimensional chains are the simplest structure that can be bent, twisted, braided, or folded into a wide range of geometrically or topologically complex morphologies. As the result of their reconfigurability, the long colloidal chains can switch propulsion mode from free-swimming to surface-enabled translation, enabling navigation through complex 3D environments such as channels that mimic arteries, veins, and capillaries. The demonstrated shape change and adaptability are ubiquitous in natural systems and are necessary for microbot navigation in complex environments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project supported one master student and one postdoctoral fellow. It also partially supported three Ph. D. students. In addition, we have mentored two REU students in the summers and three undergraduate students at Colorado School of Mines. Seven peer-reviewed papers have been published. Three additional manuscripts are under preparation. More than twenty talks were given based on the work performed in this project. Research findings in this work have been incorporated into a book coedited by the PI, &ldquo;Anisotropic Particle Assemblies&rdquo; (Elsevier, 2018), and a graduate-level course entitled &ldquo;Engineering of Soft Materials.&rdquo; The PI and his graduate students also prepared learning modules on colloids, surfactants, and emulsions and presented them to participants in the Summer Camp for Kids with Dyslexia and Summer Workshop on Energy Education for STEM high school Teachers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Ning&nbsp;Wu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project is to develop new approaches to fabricate clusters of colloids with broken symmetries in geometry, configuration, and composition. These asymmetric properties will then be exploited to study two representative out-of- and in-equilibrium behavior of colloidal clusters, which are fundamentally different from conventional colloids.     First, the assembly of colloidal molecules from a binary mixture of polystyrene spheres was investigated under an alternating current electric field. The rich family of assembled oligomers typically consists of a large sphere surrounded by a few smaller petal particles, driven by the dipolar attraction between large and small particles. The number of satellite particles increased with the increasing size ratio of the constituent particles. For a given size ratio, it decreased with the increasing frequency of the applied field. These trends have also been correctly captured by computing the electric energy of different oligomers based on induced dipolar and double-layer interactions. This method provided a robust way to produce a family of colloidal molecules with well-defined geometry and high yield.     In addition to microspheres, the propulsion and assembly of colloidal clusters made of asymmetric dimers were also studied. It was demonstrated that incorporating Stern-layer conductivity resolved the puzzle that the electrohydrodynamic (EHD) flow surrounding a particle with moderate zeta potentials can be extensile. Asymmetric EHD motors made from polystyrene and silica particles exhibited behaviors consistent with the model predictions. In the high-frequency regime, a new phenomenon was discovered. All-dielectric asymmetric particles can propel along the substrate. In particular, polystyrene-silica dimers propelled with the polystyrene lobe forward at an elevated height above the electrode. With the help of nanoparticle tracers, strong and contractile hydrodynamic flow surrounding both lobes was observed. Since the frequency regime for active motion is very close to the inverse of the time scale for ions migrating in and out of the double layer, it is hypothesized that the hydrodynamic flow is originated from the electro-osmosis of induced charges within the double layer near the electrode can potentially be the mechanism. This new propulsion mechanism greatly expands the material library for designing active motors for both fundamental and practical studies.     A better understanding of the EHD flow surrounding colloidal dimers was further utilized to assemble them into colloidal clusters with chirality, which have potential use as sensors to detect molecules or metamaterials with exotic optical properties. Applying electric fields can assemble dielectric dumbbell-shaped particles coated with a thin magnetic layer into chiral clusters with an equal right- and left-handedness population. However, with the superposition of an additional rotating magnetic field, the chirality of the clusters changed according to the rotating direction of the magnetic field. By controlling the direction of the magnetic field, the cluster chirality can be reversibly switched. This finding provides a convenient route to produce chiral colloidal clusters with single-handedness.      Beyond small colloidal clusters, flexible magnetic colloidal chains were also fabricated. They are inspired by microscale swimmers that utilize long filaments or slender bodies for propulsion since one-dimensional chains are the simplest structure that can be bent, twisted, braided, or folded into a wide range of geometrically or topologically complex morphologies. As the result of their reconfigurability, the long colloidal chains can switch propulsion mode from free-swimming to surface-enabled translation, enabling navigation through complex 3D environments such as channels that mimic arteries, veins, and capillaries. The demonstrated shape change and adaptability are ubiquitous in natural systems and are necessary for microbot navigation in complex environments.     This project supported one master student and one postdoctoral fellow. It also partially supported three Ph. D. students. In addition, we have mentored two REU students in the summers and three undergraduate students at Colorado School of Mines. Seven peer-reviewed papers have been published. Three additional manuscripts are under preparation. More than twenty talks were given based on the work performed in this project. Research findings in this work have been incorporated into a book coedited by the PI, "Anisotropic Particle Assemblies" (Elsevier, 2018), and a graduate-level course entitled "Engineering of Soft Materials." The PI and his graduate students also prepared learning modules on colloids, surfactants, and emulsions and presented them to participants in the Summer Camp for Kids with Dyslexia and Summer Workshop on Energy Education for STEM high school Teachers.       Last Modified: 08/16/2021       Submitted by: Ning Wu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
