<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Genomics of Speciation and Diversification in Primates</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17892.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17892</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Questions about how and why new species form are central to evolutionary biology because speciation is the primary process responsible for our planet's amazing variety of plants and animals, including our own species. This project explores the genomic causes and consequences of speciation in the macaque (genus Macaca).  During the past 5 million years, this genus of monkeys has diversified rapidly and radiated into at least 22 species occupying a wide range of environments and habitats across northern Africa, Europe, and Asia.  Given the wealth of data already available on biological, morphological, and ecological variation among macaques, the genomic data generated by this study will allow detailed analysis of the links among genomic change, biological change, natural selection and speciation in primates. Further, the diversification of Macaca resembles, and was roughly contemporary with, that of the hominins, and therefore serves as a comparative model for human evolution. Findings from this project will also inform primate conservation efforts and medical models of human health and disease, and the investigators are highly invested in student training and public scientific outreach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this 18-month project, the entire coding region of the genome will be sequenced (exome sequencing) for species across the macaque genus. The data will allow identification of genomic 'islands' that show relatively high divergence among species and determine whether a few large or many small islands drive genomic isolation. Examination of sequence changes and variation in the copy number of protein-coding regions of the genome will address the extent to which natural selection has shaped this radiation. The project will be able to address links between micro- and macroevolutionary processes, place this primate adaptive radiation within a spatial and environmental context, and generate new hypotheses about speciation in other clades such as hominins. The scientific and societal impact of this project is amplified through extensive training and outreach efforts, as well as sharing of data relevant to biomedical research and conservation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1455818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Watts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David P Watts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.watts@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034329597</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000214802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Webster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy H Webster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>timothy.h.webster@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8012131549</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065112503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~17892</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Project Summary</em></p> <p>In this project, we undertook the first genus-wide genomic study of the macaques, a group of Old World monkeys that is&nbsp;behaviorally, morphologically, and ecologically diverse, geographically widespread, and evolutionarily highly successful. &nbsp;We generated genome-scale data for 70 individuals from eight species to explore patterns of genomic divergence across the macaque radiation.&nbsp; We found that macaques simultaneously exhibit high levels of both variation and constraint in genome evolution.&nbsp; Despite evidence for different demographic and evolutionary histories among taxa, the landscapes of variation in the number of copies of specific genes, genomic diversity, and genomic divergence were very similar among species.&nbsp; These results show that relatively small genomic changes can drive substantial differences in behavior, morphology, and ecology.&nbsp; Moreover, this study highlights the fact that a primate adaptive radiation can occur without major changes in genomic architecture or to the landscape of genomic diversity and divergence.</p> <p>We first characterized copy number variation &ndash; gains and losses of genomic material &ndash; within and among macaque populations. &nbsp;The extent to which species shared duplications and deletions reflected their evolutionary relationships.&nbsp; Duplications were more common than deletions and more likely to be shared, but both types of copy number variation were strongly associated with certain genomic features.&nbsp; Genes in copy number variable regions were enriched for a host of biological functions, including activity of the gene that codes for alpha-amylase, a digestive enzyme.&nbsp; In particular, species that are often found in and around human settlements exhibit more copies of the gene <em>AMY2B</em>, which codes for pancreatic amylase.&nbsp; This change is very similar to that observed in dogs after domestication, and this finding suggests that convergent genomic evolution has occurred in macaques and dogs, driven by the availability of starch-rich foods in human settlements, that allows then to benefit from the availability of these foods.</p> <p>We next investigated patterns of diversity across macaque genomes and found a threefold range of variation in genetic diversity among taxa. &nbsp;This amount of variation is higher than that observed in great ape species, especially when comparing estimates in the same genomic regions. Relatively low diversity estimates for <em>Macaca nigra</em>, <em>M. silenus</em>, and <em>M. thibetana</em> closely matched their threatened and endangered conservation statuses in the wild and highlighted these species as at priorities for conservation efforts.&nbsp; The fact that these taxa harbor more genetic diversity than the great apes suggests that substantial genetic diversity is still available and this should inform conservation decisions. In all species of macaque, the ratio of diversity on the X chromosome to that of the autosomes fell well below expected values.&nbsp; Several evolutionary and demographic forces can cause this, and we found strong evidence that several have acted during macaque evolution. &nbsp;These include male mutation bias (higher probabilities of mutations on Y chromosomes than on other chromosomes),, more diversity-reducing selection on the X chromosome, and changes in population size.</p> <p>Finally, we examined the landscape of genomic divergence across a speciation continuum of six taxa.&nbsp; All comparisons exhibited a pattern of many, small islands and peaks of diversity scattered across the genome separated by strecthes with low diversity.&nbsp; In all cases, however, the X chromosome exhibited significantly less divergence than the autosomes overall, but significantly greater divergence when only considering variant sites.&nbsp; This pattern is consistent with more efficient selection on the X chromosome than autosomes and may be the result of either ancestral or recurrent selective sweeps on the X chromosome.&nbsp; We identified many genes falling in islands of divergence, including several islands exhibiting evidence of balancing selection in all species analyzed.&nbsp; One of the potential targets of balancing selection is <em>TAS2R38</em>, a bitter taste receptor gene under independent balancing selection in humans and chimpanzees.&nbsp; Overall, these patterns suggest more constraint than diversity in genomic divergence across the macaque exome.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts</em></p> <ul> <li>This project enabled the co-PI to develop skills and experience in next-generation sequencing, genome assembly, genomic analysis, and programming that he has been able to use to mentor bioinformatics trainees.&nbsp; Moreover, he also trained undergraduates in molecular laboratory methods and participated in community outreach science education projects sponsored by the host institution (Yale University)..</li> <li>Analyses of genetic diversity highlighted three species as conservation priorities.</li> <li>The genomic dataset consisting of 70 macaque individuals from eight species will be made publicly available upon publication and serve as a resource for biomedical research, conservation efforts, and futher study in evolutionary biology.</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;P&nbsp;Watts</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Summary  In this project, we undertook the first genus-wide genomic study of the macaques, a group of Old World monkeys that is behaviorally, morphologically, and ecologically diverse, geographically widespread, and evolutionarily highly successful.  We generated genome-scale data for 70 individuals from eight species to explore patterns of genomic divergence across the macaque radiation.  We found that macaques simultaneously exhibit high levels of both variation and constraint in genome evolution.  Despite evidence for different demographic and evolutionary histories among taxa, the landscapes of variation in the number of copies of specific genes, genomic diversity, and genomic divergence were very similar among species.  These results show that relatively small genomic changes can drive substantial differences in behavior, morphology, and ecology.  Moreover, this study highlights the fact that a primate adaptive radiation can occur without major changes in genomic architecture or to the landscape of genomic diversity and divergence.  We first characterized copy number variation &ndash; gains and losses of genomic material &ndash; within and among macaque populations.  The extent to which species shared duplications and deletions reflected their evolutionary relationships.  Duplications were more common than deletions and more likely to be shared, but both types of copy number variation were strongly associated with certain genomic features.  Genes in copy number variable regions were enriched for a host of biological functions, including activity of the gene that codes for alpha-amylase, a digestive enzyme.  In particular, species that are often found in and around human settlements exhibit more copies of the gene AMY2B, which codes for pancreatic amylase.  This change is very similar to that observed in dogs after domestication, and this finding suggests that convergent genomic evolution has occurred in macaques and dogs, driven by the availability of starch-rich foods in human settlements, that allows then to benefit from the availability of these foods.  We next investigated patterns of diversity across macaque genomes and found a threefold range of variation in genetic diversity among taxa.  This amount of variation is higher than that observed in great ape species, especially when comparing estimates in the same genomic regions. Relatively low diversity estimates for Macaca nigra, M. silenus, and M. thibetana closely matched their threatened and endangered conservation statuses in the wild and highlighted these species as at priorities for conservation efforts.  The fact that these taxa harbor more genetic diversity than the great apes suggests that substantial genetic diversity is still available and this should inform conservation decisions. In all species of macaque, the ratio of diversity on the X chromosome to that of the autosomes fell well below expected values.  Several evolutionary and demographic forces can cause this, and we found strong evidence that several have acted during macaque evolution.  These include male mutation bias (higher probabilities of mutations on Y chromosomes than on other chromosomes),, more diversity-reducing selection on the X chromosome, and changes in population size.  Finally, we examined the landscape of genomic divergence across a speciation continuum of six taxa.  All comparisons exhibited a pattern of many, small islands and peaks of diversity scattered across the genome separated by strecthes with low diversity.  In all cases, however, the X chromosome exhibited significantly less divergence than the autosomes overall, but significantly greater divergence when only considering variant sites.  This pattern is consistent with more efficient selection on the X chromosome than autosomes and may be the result of either ancestral or recurrent selective sweeps on the X chromosome.  We identified many genes falling in islands of divergence, including several islands exhibiting evidence of balancing selection in all species analyzed.  One of the potential targets of balancing selection is TAS2R38, a bitter taste receptor gene under independent balancing selection in humans and chimpanzees.  Overall, these patterns suggest more constraint than diversity in genomic divergence across the macaque exome.  Broader Impacts  This project enabled the co-PI to develop skills and experience in next-generation sequencing, genome assembly, genomic analysis, and programming that he has been able to use to mentor bioinformatics trainees.  Moreover, he also trained undergraduates in molecular laboratory methods and participated in community outreach science education projects sponsored by the host institution (Yale University).. Analyses of genetic diversity highlighted three species as conservation priorities. The genomic dataset consisting of 70 macaque individuals from eight species will be made publicly available upon publication and serve as a resource for biomedical research, conservation efforts, and futher study in evolutionary biology.        Last Modified: 09/29/2016       Submitted by: David P Watts]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
