<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Nanomaterials for Thermal Management of Power Electronics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>High power electronics is playing a vital role in rapid advancements in energy generation, storage and transmission, hybrid automobile vehicles, defense, and aerospace technologies. Wide bandgap semiconductor (WBGS) devices are the leading contenders for high power electronics, but they operate at high current densities requiring the rapid dissemination of heat. Current strategies for thermal management of power electronics have limited efficacy due to their reliance on bulky, multicomponent heat extraction strategies via multiple interfaces with high thermal interface resistances. Therefore, there is a critical need for a simplified commercial thermal management technology which will enable direct extraction of heat from operating power electronics devices. The lack of such a technology limits the operating conditions, reliability, and efficiency of WBGS power electronic systems. This team proposes to address this technological gap by commercializing a novel thermal management strategy based on nanocrystalline diamond (NCD), which is an excellent thermal conductor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rationale behind the proposed technology is that: NCD possess high thermal conductivity and electrical resistivity making it well-suited for thermal management of WBGS power electronics, extraction of heat directly from a device (as opposed to heat extraction through a substrate) will result in significant enhancements in efficiency, and higher heat extraction efficiency leads to longer operating lifetimes, enables higher device density, and reduced operating costs. The preliminary research consisting of experimental and simulation studies has demonstrated proof-of-principle for the proposed technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1455067</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raj</FirstName>
<LastName>Singh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raj Singh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rajns@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9185948650</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 WHITEHURST HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The key driving force in our effort to commercialize our research on a novel strategy for thermal management of high power electronics is the fact that it plays vital role in rapid advancements in energy generation, storage and transmission, hybrid automobile vehicles, defense, and aerospace technologies. We participated in the NSF I-Corps program in order to identify if our technology is suitable for commercialization, and ascertain customer interest and market size. The I-Corps program was invaluable in helping us achieve our goals. In particular, we developed a realistic business model canvas and learned techniques for conducting an effective customer discovery process. Through our efforts we found that there is a strong demand for thermal management of power devices in spacecraft and military applications. However, the capital investment requirements for our technology are high requiring several million dollars in investment and will need at least 5-8 years to transition into the market. Given the nature of our technology, we found that there are only a few major players in the industry, and the barriers to entry are high. In spite of these challenges, we believe that this technology has strong demand in aerospace, energy and defense sectors. Therefore, we are considering potential avenues for commercializing our technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through the NSF I-Corps program we not only developed skills and hands-on experiences which are indispensable to help us assess our current technology for commercialization, but will also help us evaluate future technologies for commercial potential. Furthermore, given the global market place and extremely stiff competition for markets and resources, rapid commercialization of technology will play an increasingly important role in future R&amp;D. Therefore, the skills and techniques we have learned and developed through the I-Corps program will have a very important impact on the way we conduct research in near and distant future. Also, the NSF I-Corps program helps academic faculty, staff, and students develop skills which are required to successfully commercialize technology in the modern marketplace. Since the techniques and resources deployed involve some of the top business schools and faculty in the world, the knowledge, understanding, and skills developed will have a broad impact beyond engineering per se. In our particular case, we have developed the skills and techniques required to successfully interact with the business world. It has not only has enriched our understanding, but there is also the broader and unquantifiable impact of disseminating our knowledge to students, staff, and faculty in our own institution and beyond.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/17/2015<br>      Modified by: Raj&nbsp;Singh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The key driving force in our effort to commercialize our research on a novel strategy for thermal management of high power electronics is the fact that it plays vital role in rapid advancements in energy generation, storage and transmission, hybrid automobile vehicles, defense, and aerospace technologies. We participated in the NSF I-Corps program in order to identify if our technology is suitable for commercialization, and ascertain customer interest and market size. The I-Corps program was invaluable in helping us achieve our goals. In particular, we developed a realistic business model canvas and learned techniques for conducting an effective customer discovery process. Through our efforts we found that there is a strong demand for thermal management of power devices in spacecraft and military applications. However, the capital investment requirements for our technology are high requiring several million dollars in investment and will need at least 5-8 years to transition into the market. Given the nature of our technology, we found that there are only a few major players in the industry, and the barriers to entry are high. In spite of these challenges, we believe that this technology has strong demand in aerospace, energy and defense sectors. Therefore, we are considering potential avenues for commercializing our technology.     Through the NSF I-Corps program we not only developed skills and hands-on experiences which are indispensable to help us assess our current technology for commercialization, but will also help us evaluate future technologies for commercial potential. Furthermore, given the global market place and extremely stiff competition for markets and resources, rapid commercialization of technology will play an increasingly important role in future R&amp;D. Therefore, the skills and techniques we have learned and developed through the I-Corps program will have a very important impact on the way we conduct research in near and distant future. Also, the NSF I-Corps program helps academic faculty, staff, and students develop skills which are required to successfully commercialize technology in the modern marketplace. Since the techniques and resources deployed involve some of the top business schools and faculty in the world, the knowledge, understanding, and skills developed will have a broad impact beyond engineering per se. In our particular case, we have developed the skills and techniques required to successfully interact with the business world. It has not only has enriched our understanding, but there is also the broader and unquantifiable impact of disseminating our knowledge to students, staff, and faculty in our own institution and beyond.          Last Modified: 05/17/2015       Submitted by: Raj Singh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
