<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Improved Skeletal Age-at-Death Estimation and Its Impact on Archaeological Analyses</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>23950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>23950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Age-at-death estimates from skeletal remains are essential for archaeological studies of human longevity, mortality patterns, population growth, disease experience and mortuary practices, as well as medicolegal identifications of missing persons, crime victims, migrant border deaths, and war-crime victims. Despite over a century of development, the accuracy (estimated and actual age correspondence) and precision (age interval length) of adult age estimates produced by existing methods are insufficient to reach these ends. That means much current understanding of the age-structure of past populations, long-term population trends, pathogen load and its effect on human hosts, and human longevity may be seriously flawed by age-estimation error. In response to this pressing theoretical and practical need, an international research team that includes Dr. George Milner and his doctoral student Sara Getz (Penn State University) are developing a method to produce more accurate, precise, and unbiased skeletal age estimates for the entire adult lifespan, building on their earlier statistical procedure (Transition Analysis, TA). This ongoing work will significantly reduce age-estimation error, describe and quantify skeletal variation, and refine statistical methods. It involves a fundamental shift from assessing only a few skeletal characteristics with simple statistics to analyzing traits throughout the skeleton using sophisticated statistical methods to extract the most information possible from age-related changes in bones. This project will validate the newly expanded TA method on a large number of modern known-age European skeletons, and then apply the procedure to two large medieval and early modern samples as a proof of concept for archaeological applications. At the conclusion of the project, revised TA will be disseminated as a free, downloadable, and easy-to-use program and illustrated scoring manual. Data will be maintained and made available for other researchers' use. The project PI and Co-PI will train students (undergraduate and graduate) and professionals through peer-reviewed publications, professional meeting presentations, and invited lectures and workshops.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Validation on numerous known-age European skeletons will demonstrate the increased accuracy and precision of revised TA. This focused study is the first step in expanding the research team?s method to a wide range of geographically diverse populations. After validation, two urban cemetery samples from the Danish city of Horsens - Ole Worms Gade (1100 -1500 CE) and Monastery Church (1500 -1800 CE) - will be used to investigate the potential implications of improved age estimates for our understanding of important social and demographic trends over time, such as changes in migration and adult life expectancy. This application will demonstrate how better skeletal data can bridge the gap between archaeological and historical sources. In particular, it will provide information about the characteristics of past populations that cannot be obtained through historical documents or from skeletons where ages were estimated using standard methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1455810</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Milner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George R Milner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ost@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651268</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000240200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Getz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara M Getz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smg5036@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651372</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642868</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8819</Code>
<Text>Forensic Science</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~23950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Long-term trends in life expectancy, disease, and population growth for most of the human past are best studied using skeletons. Accurate age-at-death estimates are critical to such work. Good estimates can be produced for infants, children, and adolescents, but even after a century of research they are not possible for most of adulthood. Standard methods rely heavily on just a few parts of the skeleton, notably the joints of the skull and pelvis that go through numerous changes throughout life. This NSF-funded doctoral work, in contrast, shows that more accurate age estimates are possible using many different features throughout the skeleton. The skeletal characteristics individually provide little age information, but in combination they greatly improve age-at-death estimates.</p> <p>This project consisted of three phases, with Phases 2 and 3 funded by NSF. In Phase 1, more than 200 trait variations were evaluated and 40 skeletal features that provide information about adult age were identified. Reference data were collected from over 1,000 individuals from four well-documented North American skeletal collections. In Phase 2, funded by NSF, a revised version of an existing statistical method known as Transition Analysis (TA) was developed in collaboration with an international research team. The new TA method produces individualized age estimates based on the unique mix of traits present in a particular skeleton. This method, along with several commonly used methods, were first applied to modern skeletons from Athens, Greece, to test how the method performed on individuals similar to those used to develop the procedure. Next, the same methods were applied to individuals from St. Bride's Crypt who lived several hundred years ago in London, England. That tested whether the new procedure performed well on Europeans who had much different diets, activity levels, and disease exposure. In Phase 3, also funded by NSF, the same procedures from Phase 2 were applied to two archaeological samples from the Danish city of Horsens&mdash;Ole Worms Gade (1100-1536 CE) and Monastery Church (1536-1856 CE). That phase of the research assessed whether demographic changes could be detected between the late Middle Ages and Early Modern period in northern Europe using standard methods and new TA.</p> <p>When compared to three widely used standard age-estimation methods, the new TA procedure yields estimates that more closely approximate the known ages of individuals in the modern Athens and historical St. Bride&rsquo;s samples. Standard methods produce distributions of estimated ages that differ greatly from the distributions of known ages in the Greek and English samples. In fact, standard methods produce estimated age distributions that are unique to each method. In other words, the age estimates, individually and collectively, have more to do with the method being used than with reality. Published studies based on standard methods, therefore, report age distributions that do not reflect the true mortality characteristics of the populations of interest.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Turning to the Danish archaeological samples, the mortality distributions produced using the new TA procedure show potentially important changes over time. More young adults died in the late Middle Ages (Ole Worms Gade), and more people died at older ages during the Early Modern period (Klosterkirke). These results are consistent with what would be expected based on historical documents, but now we have a procedure that allows knowledge of population characteristics to be expanded beyond sparse historical documentation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Although the new TA method needs additional work before it is widely used, pairing the TA statistical approach with a large number of new age-related skeletal features has been a success. More realistic approximations of age can be produced than ever before, even when using the incomplete skeletons that are typical of archaeological and forensic contexts. The first archaeological application of the new TA procedure provides an exciting glimpse of differences in mortality in the city of Horsens between the late Middle Ages and Early Modern period. Such changes could not be detected with standard age-estimation procedures. This dissertation, in conjunction with a larger ongoing international research effort using a similar approach and a more geographically diverse reference sample, provides every indication that new TA will become the gold standard for adult age estimation in both paleodemographic studies and medicolegal investigations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/17/2017<br>      Modified by: Sara&nbsp;M&nbsp;Getz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Long-term trends in life expectancy, disease, and population growth for most of the human past are best studied using skeletons. Accurate age-at-death estimates are critical to such work. Good estimates can be produced for infants, children, and adolescents, but even after a century of research they are not possible for most of adulthood. Standard methods rely heavily on just a few parts of the skeleton, notably the joints of the skull and pelvis that go through numerous changes throughout life. This NSF-funded doctoral work, in contrast, shows that more accurate age estimates are possible using many different features throughout the skeleton. The skeletal characteristics individually provide little age information, but in combination they greatly improve age-at-death estimates.  This project consisted of three phases, with Phases 2 and 3 funded by NSF. In Phase 1, more than 200 trait variations were evaluated and 40 skeletal features that provide information about adult age were identified. Reference data were collected from over 1,000 individuals from four well-documented North American skeletal collections. In Phase 2, funded by NSF, a revised version of an existing statistical method known as Transition Analysis (TA) was developed in collaboration with an international research team. The new TA method produces individualized age estimates based on the unique mix of traits present in a particular skeleton. This method, along with several commonly used methods, were first applied to modern skeletons from Athens, Greece, to test how the method performed on individuals similar to those used to develop the procedure. Next, the same methods were applied to individuals from St. Bride's Crypt who lived several hundred years ago in London, England. That tested whether the new procedure performed well on Europeans who had much different diets, activity levels, and disease exposure. In Phase 3, also funded by NSF, the same procedures from Phase 2 were applied to two archaeological samples from the Danish city of Horsens&mdash;Ole Worms Gade (1100-1536 CE) and Monastery Church (1536-1856 CE). That phase of the research assessed whether demographic changes could be detected between the late Middle Ages and Early Modern period in northern Europe using standard methods and new TA.  When compared to three widely used standard age-estimation methods, the new TA procedure yields estimates that more closely approximate the known ages of individuals in the modern Athens and historical St. Bride?s samples. Standard methods produce distributions of estimated ages that differ greatly from the distributions of known ages in the Greek and English samples. In fact, standard methods produce estimated age distributions that are unique to each method. In other words, the age estimates, individually and collectively, have more to do with the method being used than with reality. Published studies based on standard methods, therefore, report age distributions that do not reflect the true mortality characteristics of the populations of interest.     Turning to the Danish archaeological samples, the mortality distributions produced using the new TA procedure show potentially important changes over time. More young adults died in the late Middle Ages (Ole Worms Gade), and more people died at older ages during the Early Modern period (Klosterkirke). These results are consistent with what would be expected based on historical documents, but now we have a procedure that allows knowledge of population characteristics to be expanded beyond sparse historical documentation.   Although the new TA method needs additional work before it is widely used, pairing the TA statistical approach with a large number of new age-related skeletal features has been a success. More realistic approximations of age can be produced than ever before, even when using the incomplete skeletons that are typical of archaeological and forensic contexts. The first archaeological application of the new TA procedure provides an exciting glimpse of differences in mortality in the city of Horsens between the late Middle Ages and Early Modern period. Such changes could not be detected with standard age-estimation procedures. This dissertation, in conjunction with a larger ongoing international research effort using a similar approach and a more geographically diverse reference sample, provides every indication that new TA will become the gold standard for adult age estimation in both paleodemographic studies and medicolegal investigations.          Last Modified: 03/17/2017       Submitted by: Sara M Getz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
