<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Observationally-Constrained Estimates of Effective Radiative Forcing from Aerosol Radiation Interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>178322.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>178322</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The solar heating of the Earth is affected by aerosols emitted from human activites including agriculture (for instance the burning of crop residue after the harvest), power generation (including both sulfate aerosol which reflects solar radiation and black carbon aerosol that absorbs it), and transportation. The radiative effects of these anthropogenic aerosols are hard to quantify, and their climatic effect is among the largest uncertainties in projections of future climate change. The goal of this project is to develop observationally-based estimates of the radiative forcing due to anthropogenic aerosols using the best available satellite and surface-based datasets. More specifically, the research seeks to produce estimates of the effective radiative forcing from aerosol-radiation interactions (ERFari), which includes both the radiative effects of the aerosols and the changes in radiative forcing due to changes in clouds brought about by aerosol radiative heating. For example, the heating due to absorption of solar radiation by black carbon aerosols (soot) can lead to the "burn off" of clouds, resulting in more sunlight reaching the ground. Data used to determine aerosol amounts, vertical profiles, and radiative parameters comes from several satellite missions ( (MODIS, the CALIPSO/CALIOP lidar, MISR, CERES) and from the ground-based AERONET network. The aerosol amounts and properties are used in combination with a radiative transfer model (MACR) to determine the aerosol radiative forcing. The radiative forcing is then used as an input to global climate models, from which estimates of the further impact of aerosols on cloud radiative forcing are determined. Model-derived estimates of the cloud radiative properties are then compared to further satellite cloud observations. A key assumption of the project is that fine-mode aerosols can be used as a proxy for anthropogenic aerosols, provided that known natural sources of fine-mode aerosol (dust, marine sulfate, sea salt) can be factored out. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The work has broader impacts due to the potential importance of anthropogenic aerosol as a regional and global climate forcing. Work to reduce the large uncertainty in this climate forcing could lead to better projections of future climate change and its impacts on human activities. In addition, the project would support a graduate student and provide a research opportunity for an undergraduate student at an ethnically diverse university. One of the PIs also performs outreach to local K-12 students through a local nonprofit organization.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1455759</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chul Eddy</FirstName>
<LastName>Chung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chul Eddy Chung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eddy.chung@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7756747145</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675308</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nevada System of Higher Education, Desert Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7756737300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2215 Raggio Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>134599174</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nevada Desert Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~178322</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Aerosols directly affect climate through absorption and scattering of solar radiation.&nbsp; This climatic effect is normally quantified as &ldquo;aerosol direct radiative forcing&rdquo;.&nbsp; In the 5<sup>th</sup> IPCC report, aerosol direct radiative forcing was estimated to be &minus;0.35&plusmn;0.5 W m<sup>&minus;2</sup>, which means that aerosols were estimated to cool the earth surface and the troposphere by about 0.35 W m<sup>&minus;2</sup>.&nbsp; The uncertainty in the estimated forcing, i.e., &minus;0.85 ~ +0.15 W m<sup>&minus;2</sup>, is large, because the estimate depended greatly on aerosol simulations.&nbsp; Global aerosol simulations are subject to large uncertainties in emissions, transport, gas-to-aerosol conversion, aerosol aging, aerosol mixing state, and wet and dry deposition, and so different aerosol simulations yield quite different aerosol direct forcing estimates.&nbsp; Attempts have been made to constrain global aerosol simulations by observations to reduce the uncertainty in estimated forcing.&nbsp; &nbsp;The #1 goal of the project was to significantly increase the use of observations in constraining aerosol simulations, so that the estimated forcing would be more accurate (i.e., less biased) and subject to a smaller uncertainty size.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We integrated a comprehensive suite of satellite and ground-based observations to</p> <p>constrain total AOD, its fine-mode fraction, the vertical distribution of aerosols and clouds, and the co-location of clouds and overlying aerosols.&nbsp; Compared to previous semi-empirical studies of having constrained aerosol simulations by observations, we have made much greater constraining.&nbsp; We found that fine-mode forcing is &minus;0.46 Wm<sup>-2</sup> (&minus;0.54 ~ &minus;0.39 Wm<sup>-2</sup>).&nbsp; Fine-mode aerosols include sea salt and dust aerosols.&nbsp; Global direct aerosol radiative forcing was estimated to be less negative than &minus;0.35 Wm<sup>-2</sup>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the integration of satellite and ground-based observations, we also looked into the relationship between cloud and above-cloud aerosol amount.&nbsp; The CALIPSO data showed that aerosol amount above low cloud tends to be smaller than in nearby clear sky during the daytime and the opposite is true during the nighttime.<strong>&nbsp; </strong>In particular, over oceanic regions with wide-spread low cloud, such as the tropical southeastern Atlantic Ocean and northeastern Pacific Ocean, the daytime aerosol amount above low cloud is often 40% smaller than in surrounding clear skies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also further analyzed aerosol solar absorption data.&nbsp; Ambient organic aerosols have been assumed to have little-to-no absorption in the red and near-infrared spectral regions of solar radiation.&nbsp; In our project, we demonstrated that ambient atmospheric data from commonly-used 7-wavelength aethalometers contain evidence of abundant near-infrared light absorption by organic aerosols.&nbsp; This evidence comes from the absorption &Aring;ngstr&ouml;m exponent over the wavelength region of 880-950 nm that often exceeds values explainable by fresh or coated black carbon, or mineral dust.&nbsp; This evidence is not an artefact from instrument random errors or biases, either.&nbsp; A good explanation for these large 880/950 nm absorption &Aring;ngstr&ouml;m exponent values in the aethalometer data is near-infrared light absorption by tar balls.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Chul Eddy&nbsp;Chung</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1455759/1455759_10368055_1528840595841_fine_mode--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1455759/1455759_10368055_1528840595841_fine_mode--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fine-mode aerosols"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1455759/1455759_10368055_1528840595841_fine_mode--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fine-mode aerosols"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A) 2001-2010 mean 550 nm fine-mode AOD (fAOD) obtained by integrating MODIS, MISR, and AERONET data.  B) 2001-2010 mean direct fine-mode aerosol radiative effect at TOA in units of Wm-2; this estimate includes natural fine-mode particles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Chung</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chul Eddy&nbsp;Chung</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fine-mode aerosols</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Aerosols directly affect climate through absorption and scattering of solar radiation.  This climatic effect is normally quantified as "aerosol direct radiative forcing".  In the 5th IPCC report, aerosol direct radiative forcing was estimated to be &minus;0.35&plusmn;0.5 W m&minus;2, which means that aerosols were estimated to cool the earth surface and the troposphere by about 0.35 W m&minus;2.  The uncertainty in the estimated forcing, i.e., &minus;0.85 ~ +0.15 W m&minus;2, is large, because the estimate depended greatly on aerosol simulations.  Global aerosol simulations are subject to large uncertainties in emissions, transport, gas-to-aerosol conversion, aerosol aging, aerosol mixing state, and wet and dry deposition, and so different aerosol simulations yield quite different aerosol direct forcing estimates.  Attempts have been made to constrain global aerosol simulations by observations to reduce the uncertainty in estimated forcing.   The #1 goal of the project was to significantly increase the use of observations in constraining aerosol simulations, so that the estimated forcing would be more accurate (i.e., less biased) and subject to a smaller uncertainty size.     We integrated a comprehensive suite of satellite and ground-based observations to  constrain total AOD, its fine-mode fraction, the vertical distribution of aerosols and clouds, and the co-location of clouds and overlying aerosols.  Compared to previous semi-empirical studies of having constrained aerosol simulations by observations, we have made much greater constraining.  We found that fine-mode forcing is &minus;0.46 Wm-2 (&minus;0.54 ~ &minus;0.39 Wm-2).  Fine-mode aerosols include sea salt and dust aerosols.  Global direct aerosol radiative forcing was estimated to be less negative than &minus;0.35 Wm-2.     During the integration of satellite and ground-based observations, we also looked into the relationship between cloud and above-cloud aerosol amount.  The CALIPSO data showed that aerosol amount above low cloud tends to be smaller than in nearby clear sky during the daytime and the opposite is true during the nighttime.  In particular, over oceanic regions with wide-spread low cloud, such as the tropical southeastern Atlantic Ocean and northeastern Pacific Ocean, the daytime aerosol amount above low cloud is often 40% smaller than in surrounding clear skies.     We also further analyzed aerosol solar absorption data.  Ambient organic aerosols have been assumed to have little-to-no absorption in the red and near-infrared spectral regions of solar radiation.  In our project, we demonstrated that ambient atmospheric data from commonly-used 7-wavelength aethalometers contain evidence of abundant near-infrared light absorption by organic aerosols.  This evidence comes from the absorption &Aring;ngstr&ouml;m exponent over the wavelength region of 880-950 nm that often exceeds values explainable by fresh or coated black carbon, or mineral dust.  This evidence is not an artefact from instrument random errors or biases, either.  A good explanation for these large 880/950 nm absorption &Aring;ngstr&ouml;m exponent values in the aethalometer data is near-infrared light absorption by tar balls.       Last Modified: 06/12/2018       Submitted by: Chul Eddy Chung]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
