<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Integrative Approaches to Plant Cell Wall Digestion by Non holometabolous Insects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>230354.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>230354</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Dickson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdickson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927380</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Plant cell walls contain lignocellulosic compounds that are difficult to degrade, such as xylan, cellulose, hemicellulose, and pectin. However, insect herbivores are capable of degrading these compounds and using the simpler compounds derived from the degradation processes for energy. While early work assumed that the source of the catalyst enzymes involved in the biochemical breakdown of lignocellulosic compounds (i.e., plant cell wall degradation enzymes, PCWDE) in insects was gut-resident symbiotic bacteria, recent work has shown that PCWDE produced by the cells of the insect gut are more important than previously realized. The goal of this research is to examine the diversity of PCWDE in two major lower insect lineages using a combination of functional genomics and biochemical tests. This basic research will improve understanding about the physiological mechanisms of insect digestion and may yield novel insights about insect control methods, biofuel industry improvements, and other industrial applications. This work will provide the opportunity for undergraduate, high school and graduate students to gain experience in cutting edge functional genomics, and insect physiology and biochemistry. Museum exhibits will be produced to educate the public about the importance of wood feeding insects. These exhibits will be presented at the University of California David Bohart Museum of Entomology and several other science museums across California and Tennessee. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Preliminary work revealed that Phasmids (walking sticks) and Thysanurans (silverfish and firebrats) have strikingly high numbers of PCWDE, that these genes show compartment specific expression within the gut, and are effective at degrading plant cell wall compounds. This project will identify the full complement of PCWDE present in the focal species (6 Phasmids and 3 Thysanurans) and compare the activity and expression levels of them in the digestive systems of these insects. Using heterologous expression, the researchers will characterize the activity of the most active enzymes in these systems. The researchers will also analyze how patterns of gene expression correlate with the physical attributes of the gut, which vary greatly between the two focal insect orders. The ultimate goal is to describe the variation in physiological compartmentalization of the digestive system and determine how it works synergistically with a diversity of differentially-expressed enzymes to maximize digestion of lignocellulosic compounds. Findings from this research will be published in peer-reviewed journals, and presented at regional and national scientific meetings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456662</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>Jurat-Fuentes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan Luis Jurat-Fuentes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jurat@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659745931</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261397</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Institute of Agriculture</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379964506</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659747357</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2621 Morgan Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[225 Morgan Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>133891015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Institute of Agriculture]]></Name>
<CityName>KNoxville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379964506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2621 Morgan Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~73677</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~77367</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~79310</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project allowed the PI to characterize digestion of cellulose from plants in primitive insects (firebrat and silverfish) as a poorly characterized biological model for highly effective digestion of plant-derived materials. The PhD student was trained and supervised by the PI in the use of diverse techniques (histology, genomics, proteomics?) to identify the anterior portion of the digestive tube as the main region responsible for degradation of cellulose in firebrats and silverfish. This observation provides a drastic contrast to alternative primitive insect models such as termites and roaches in which cellulose degradation locates to the posterior region of the gut and is driven by microbes. Moreover, the production of enzymes (proteins) digesting cellulose is independent of diet, but highly dependent on the gut region, suggesting a highly specialized process akin to a biorefinery in these insects, where long cellulose chains are first processed to shorter chains in the anterior gut and then these products are fully degraded to glucose in the middle and posterior gut regions. Importantly, data from the project supports that the enzymes driving this degradation are mostly made by the insect and not by microbes, in striking contrast with roaches and termites. These results identify silverfish and firebrats as a biological biorefinery model from which useful enzymes may be identified to optimize degradation of plant materials for livestock diet improvement or for production of ethanol biofuel from plant biomass.</p> <p>The project has provided training in diverse techniques to a female graduate (PhD) student that worked full time in the completion of the objectives proposed in the project. The teaching/outreach skills of this graduate student were promoted through participation in the educational outreach component of the project, training of visiting scientists, and presentations of project information in seminars. The project allowed the PI to develop a high throughput transcriptome-based approach in his laboratory to identify plant cell wall degrading enzymes with potential industrial application in lignocellulosic biofuel production. Through the project, the PI and PhD student established a collaboration with the National Institute for Biotechnology and Genetic Engineering (Pakistan) focused on developing enzymes to improve fiber digestion in livestock. The project also provided an opportunity for the PI to deliver a workshop on some of the methods developed from the project at the Universidade Federal do Amazonas (UFAM) in Brazil, which has been continued with a visiting PhD student from Brazil performing research on cellulase genes in aquatic insects. Results from the project have been presented in scientific congresses and have been recognized with awards by the Entomological Society of America and the Tennessee Entomological Society, and are presented in peer-reviewed publications.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2018<br>      Modified by: Juan Luis&nbsp;L&nbsp;Jurat-Fuentes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1456662/1456662_10361596_1545612447397_Firebratonpaper--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1456662/1456662_10361596_1545612447397_Firebratonpaper--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Firebrat feeding on paper"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1456662/1456662_10361596_1545612447397_Firebratonpaper--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Firebrat feeding on paper"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Firebrats are primitive insects that feed on diverse substrates, including paper.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juan Jurat-Fuentes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juan Luis&nbsp;L&nbsp;Jurat-Fuentes</div> <div class="imageTitle">Firebrat feeding on paper</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1456662/1456662_10361596_1545612724236_Firebratgut--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1456662/1456662_10361596_1545612724236_Firebratgut--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Digestive system in firebrat"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1456662/1456662_10361596_1545612724236_Firebratgut--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Digestive system in firebrat"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Structure of the digestive system in firebrat. The crop in the foregut is the main region of digestion of cellulose.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ratnasri Mallipeddi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juan Luis&nbsp;L&nbsp;Jurat-Fuentes</div> <div class="imageTitle">Digestive system in firebrat</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project allowed the PI to characterize digestion of cellulose from plants in primitive insects (firebrat and silverfish) as a poorly characterized biological model for highly effective digestion of plant-derived materials. The PhD student was trained and supervised by the PI in the use of diverse techniques (histology, genomics, proteomics?) to identify the anterior portion of the digestive tube as the main region responsible for degradation of cellulose in firebrats and silverfish. This observation provides a drastic contrast to alternative primitive insect models such as termites and roaches in which cellulose degradation locates to the posterior region of the gut and is driven by microbes. Moreover, the production of enzymes (proteins) digesting cellulose is independent of diet, but highly dependent on the gut region, suggesting a highly specialized process akin to a biorefinery in these insects, where long cellulose chains are first processed to shorter chains in the anterior gut and then these products are fully degraded to glucose in the middle and posterior gut regions. Importantly, data from the project supports that the enzymes driving this degradation are mostly made by the insect and not by microbes, in striking contrast with roaches and termites. These results identify silverfish and firebrats as a biological biorefinery model from which useful enzymes may be identified to optimize degradation of plant materials for livestock diet improvement or for production of ethanol biofuel from plant biomass.  The project has provided training in diverse techniques to a female graduate (PhD) student that worked full time in the completion of the objectives proposed in the project. The teaching/outreach skills of this graduate student were promoted through participation in the educational outreach component of the project, training of visiting scientists, and presentations of project information in seminars. The project allowed the PI to develop a high throughput transcriptome-based approach in his laboratory to identify plant cell wall degrading enzymes with potential industrial application in lignocellulosic biofuel production. Through the project, the PI and PhD student established a collaboration with the National Institute for Biotechnology and Genetic Engineering (Pakistan) focused on developing enzymes to improve fiber digestion in livestock. The project also provided an opportunity for the PI to deliver a workshop on some of the methods developed from the project at the Universidade Federal do Amazonas (UFAM) in Brazil, which has been continued with a visiting PhD student from Brazil performing research on cellulase genes in aquatic insects. Results from the project have been presented in scientific congresses and have been recognized with awards by the Entomological Society of America and the Tennessee Entomological Society, and are presented in peer-reviewed publications.       Last Modified: 12/23/2018       Submitted by: Juan Luis L Jurat-Fuentes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
