<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Novel Selective Autophagy Pathway in Plant Immune Responses to Necrotrophic Pathogens</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>550000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Mishkind</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmishkin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928413</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Necrotrophic pathogens are an important group of plant pathogenic fungi and bacteria notorious for their aggressiveness and broad host range. They actively kill plant cells to extract nutrients from dead tissue. Control of crop diseases caused by necrotrophic pathogens often relies on pesticide application because resistance to necrotrophic pathogens is usually controlled by multiple genes, making it difficult to breed for resistance. Presently, knowledge about, and understanding of the underlying molecular mechanisms for resistance to this type of pathogen is very limited.  It is known to involve a process called autophagy in which specific cytoplasmic constituents are degraded, which in turn somehow prevents the invading necrotroph from inducing cell death. This project aims to elucidate the mechanism by which autophagy protects plants from necrotrophic pathogens.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At the focus of this project is a novel selective autophagy pathway mediated by the plant-specific ATI3 autophagy receptor, which is recruited to autophagosomes through interaction with ATG8. Genetic analyses suggest ATI3 plays a critical role in plant resistance to necrotrophs. ATI3 also interacts with UBAC2a and UBAC2b, homologs of a conserved ubiquitin-binding component of endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-associated degradation (ERAD).  This project will test whether the ATI3 selective autophagy pathway plays an important role in plant immunity to necrotrophs by targeting deleterious ER constituents, thereby protecting against pathogen-induced, ER stress-mediated cell death.  Specific objectives are to (1) confirm the critical role of ATI3 and UBAC2 in plant disease resistance through comprehensive genetic analysis; 2) determine whether the ATI3/UBAC2-mediated selective autophagy protects plant cells against pathogen-induced ER stress; and 3) analyze the role of the ER stress sensor IRE1 and the physical ATI3-UBAC2 interaction in the regulation of the ATI3 selective autophagy pathway. The goal of the project is the discovery of distinct pathways of selective autophagy associated with plant responses to specific plant biotic and abiotic stresses. Detailed knowledge on the role of autophagy in plant immune systems will lead to development of novel strategies for creating disease resistant crops. Autophagy and ERAD are also involved in many diseases in humans including cancers and, therefore, the knowledge from the project will have implications beyond the plant world. This project will provide a strong interdisciplinary training environment for graduate students. Some aspects of project will be incorporated into programs for training undergraduate students with hands-on experience in molecular biology techniques and for creative teaching in classrooms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456300</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhixiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhixiang Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Zhixiang@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654944657</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000173311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072054</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[915 W. State Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>047Y</Code>
<Text>Plant-Biotic Interactions</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~180749</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~183280</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~185971</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A major threat to plants including crop production is the diseases caused by microbial pathogens.&nbsp; Great progress has been made in our understanding of plant immune system against biotrophic pathogens, which colonize and obtain nutrients from living host cells.&nbsp; Necrotrophic pathogens actively kill host cells prior to or during colonization and extract nutrients from dead host cells.&nbsp; Despite many devastating plant diseases caused by necrotrophic pathogens, relatively little is known about the genetic and molecular basis of plant immune system against this important group of plant pathogens.&nbsp; In 2011, we and Dr. Thorsten Nurnberger&rsquo;s group in Germany first independently reported that autophagy plays a critical role in plant resistance to broad host-range necrotrophic pathogens.&nbsp; Autophagy is an evolutionarily conserved process by which cytoplasmic constituents including proteins and organelles are delivered to lysosomes or vacuoles for degradation.&nbsp; Autophagy plays a critical role in plant resistance to necrotrophic pathogens mostly likely by promoting host cell survival during the infection by necrotrophic pathogens.&nbsp; However, the molecular basis of the pro-survival activity of autophagy in plant disease resistance was unclear.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project investigated a family of three closely related proteins (ATI1 to ATI3) that physically interact with key autophagy proteins.&nbsp; This project revealed that like autophagy, the ATI proteins play an important role in plant resistance to necrotrophic pathogens.&nbsp; Furthermore, the three ATI3 proteins interact with two conserved proteins called UBAC2 located in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER).&nbsp; Importantly, genetic analysis also revealed that the ER-localized UBAC2 proteins are also required for plant resistance to necrotrophic pathogens.&nbsp; ER is a subcellular organelle where a large number of proteins are synthesized, folded and transported to other subcellular compartments.&nbsp; Under stress conditions, misfolded and potentially toxic proteins can accumulate in the ER, leading to ER stress and cell death.&nbsp; This project further revealed that ATI3 protein mediate a novel selective autophagy pathway that promotes plant immunity against necrotrophic pathogens by targeting deleterious ER cargo during pathogen-induced ER stress, thereby antagonizing ER stress-triggered cell death to promote host cell survival.&nbsp; The findings of this aspect of the project were reported in the premier journal Autophagy.</p> <p>This project also found a broad role of the ER-localized UBAC2 proteins in plant immune system against biotrophic pathogens as well.&nbsp; This role of UBAC2 is mediated through its role in pathogen-induced accumulation of callose, a cell wall component known to be in plant defense against microbial pathogens.&nbsp; Further studies showed that UBAC2 proteins coordinate with another ER-localized protein called PICC and play a critical role in the accumulation of the PMR4 callose synthase responsible for pathogen-induced callose synthesis.&nbsp; Through the analysis of the UBAC2, the project has discovered that the ER bodies found only in the Breaaicles are probably evolved from a novel type of ER-derived structures widely present in all plants.&nbsp; The ER bodies in the Brassicales are involved in plant responses to biotic stresses through participation in the metabolism of glucosinolates, which are also present only in Brassicles.&nbsp; Discovery of a similar type of ER vesicles in other plants will open the door to the studies of the broad roles of these ER structures in plants.&nbsp; These findings were published in the journals Plant Cell and Plant Physiology.</p> <p>In addition, the project has provided scientific and professional training to both graduate and undergraduate.&nbsp; The knowledge from the research part of the project was disseminated to the scientific community through publications, seminars, and talks at national and international meetings. The PI also gave talks to high school teachers and student from Indiana on the topics of plant immune system.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2019<br>      Modified by: Zhixiang&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A major threat to plants including crop production is the diseases caused by microbial pathogens.  Great progress has been made in our understanding of plant immune system against biotrophic pathogens, which colonize and obtain nutrients from living host cells.  Necrotrophic pathogens actively kill host cells prior to or during colonization and extract nutrients from dead host cells.  Despite many devastating plant diseases caused by necrotrophic pathogens, relatively little is known about the genetic and molecular basis of plant immune system against this important group of plant pathogens.  In 2011, we and Dr. Thorsten Nurnberger?s group in Germany first independently reported that autophagy plays a critical role in plant resistance to broad host-range necrotrophic pathogens.  Autophagy is an evolutionarily conserved process by which cytoplasmic constituents including proteins and organelles are delivered to lysosomes or vacuoles for degradation.  Autophagy plays a critical role in plant resistance to necrotrophic pathogens mostly likely by promoting host cell survival during the infection by necrotrophic pathogens.  However, the molecular basis of the pro-survival activity of autophagy in plant disease resistance was unclear.   This project investigated a family of three closely related proteins (ATI1 to ATI3) that physically interact with key autophagy proteins.  This project revealed that like autophagy, the ATI proteins play an important role in plant resistance to necrotrophic pathogens.  Furthermore, the three ATI3 proteins interact with two conserved proteins called UBAC2 located in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER).  Importantly, genetic analysis also revealed that the ER-localized UBAC2 proteins are also required for plant resistance to necrotrophic pathogens.  ER is a subcellular organelle where a large number of proteins are synthesized, folded and transported to other subcellular compartments.  Under stress conditions, misfolded and potentially toxic proteins can accumulate in the ER, leading to ER stress and cell death.  This project further revealed that ATI3 protein mediate a novel selective autophagy pathway that promotes plant immunity against necrotrophic pathogens by targeting deleterious ER cargo during pathogen-induced ER stress, thereby antagonizing ER stress-triggered cell death to promote host cell survival.  The findings of this aspect of the project were reported in the premier journal Autophagy.  This project also found a broad role of the ER-localized UBAC2 proteins in plant immune system against biotrophic pathogens as well.  This role of UBAC2 is mediated through its role in pathogen-induced accumulation of callose, a cell wall component known to be in plant defense against microbial pathogens.  Further studies showed that UBAC2 proteins coordinate with another ER-localized protein called PICC and play a critical role in the accumulation of the PMR4 callose synthase responsible for pathogen-induced callose synthesis.  Through the analysis of the UBAC2, the project has discovered that the ER bodies found only in the Breaaicles are probably evolved from a novel type of ER-derived structures widely present in all plants.  The ER bodies in the Brassicales are involved in plant responses to biotic stresses through participation in the metabolism of glucosinolates, which are also present only in Brassicles.  Discovery of a similar type of ER vesicles in other plants will open the door to the studies of the broad roles of these ER structures in plants.  These findings were published in the journals Plant Cell and Plant Physiology.  In addition, the project has provided scientific and professional training to both graduate and undergraduate.  The knowledge from the research part of the project was disseminated to the scientific community through publications, seminars, and talks at national and international meetings. The PI also gave talks to high school teachers and student from Indiana on the topics of plant immune system.          Last Modified: 10/16/2019       Submitted by: Zhixiang Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
