<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The neural basis of online error correction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>510000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sridhar Raghavachari</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sraghava@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924845</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A central question in neuroscience is how the brain detects and corrects errors in behavior. This type of error correction is essential for the learning and performance of complex tasks such as speaking and using tools, and deficits of error correction resulting from neurological diseases can have devastating effects on the ability of an individual to interact with the world. This research will examine the mechanisms by which the brain corrects errors in vocal behavior. By building mathematical models of how the brain detects and eliminates errors in performance and by directly recording the electrical activity of individual brain cells, these studies will provide novel insights into this key aspect of brain function. Additionally, the investigators will develop course materials based on their research to be used to enhance science education in underserved communities in the Atlanta area. The benefit to society of this work is therefore twofold: it will reveal previously unknown mechanisms of brain function and will improve the general public's understanding of neurobiology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed experiments combine a range of experimental approaches to test a simple model of how the brain rapidly corrects errors in behavior. The central hypothesis is that the brain is able to rapidly correct errors in vocal behavior because brain cells that control the vocal output are affected by the sensory (auditory) feedback arising from vocal output. By collecting electrical recordings of single brain cells during both vocal behavior and auditory stimulation, experiments in Aim 1 will compare the sensory tuning (the tuning for the pitch of a recently-heard syllable) and motor tuning (effect on the pitch of vocal output) of neurons that control behavior. Studies in Aim 2 will use lesions and reversible inactivations to selectively eliminate auditory input to premotor neurons, thereby facilitating tests of the hypothesis that such sensory inputs are required for rapid online error correction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456912</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Sober</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel Sober</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>samuel.j.sober@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4157223276</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000610073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1599-001-1BA]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMORY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303224218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1510 Clifton Rd. NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7713</Code>
<Text>Activation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~510000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our scientific research supported by this award has both enhanced our knowledge of brain function and provided educational and scientific outreach to our local community. Our research studies have sought to understand how the brain learns from its mistakes. Specifically, our work has combined careful studies of behavior, advanced mathematical methods, and neurobiological data to understand how the nervous system implements learning. Put another way, our mathematical studies have provided a detailed account of WHAT the brain is doing when it learns, and biological data have yielded insight into HOW the brain executes these computations.&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, our broader impacts projects (developing neuroscience course materials for local middle school students) had a positive impact on the public's understanding of neuroscience and result in improved methods to measure students' learning of scientific ideas. This component of our work sought to improve public understanding of science by involving members of historically under-represented groups with research and educational experiences. By working with students and teachers in Atlanta-area middle schools (which include a high proportion of students from groups that have historically been under-represented in STEM fields)&nbsp;our work has improved both students? and teachers? access to cutting-edge scientific ideas, potentially improving students? future participation/retention in technical fields. Finally, in addition to our school outreach, by involving undergraduate researchers in our work we taught budding young scientists research skills that will serve them well in their future careers.</p> <p>Beyond these immediate scientific and outreach accomplishments, in the future our studies might enhance clinical approaches to restoring function following nervous system injury or disease. Because our neurobiological studies have revealed a previously unknown method by which the nervous system controls motor output, our work might be extended to improve the design of theraputic devices that could be used to record brain activity from a paralyzed patient and control a prosthetic device.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;Sober</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our scientific research supported by this award has both enhanced our knowledge of brain function and provided educational and scientific outreach to our local community. Our research studies have sought to understand how the brain learns from its mistakes. Specifically, our work has combined careful studies of behavior, advanced mathematical methods, and neurobiological data to understand how the nervous system implements learning. Put another way, our mathematical studies have provided a detailed account of WHAT the brain is doing when it learns, and biological data have yielded insight into HOW the brain executes these computations.   Additionally, our broader impacts projects (developing neuroscience course materials for local middle school students) had a positive impact on the public's understanding of neuroscience and result in improved methods to measure students' learning of scientific ideas. This component of our work sought to improve public understanding of science by involving members of historically under-represented groups with research and educational experiences. By working with students and teachers in Atlanta-area middle schools (which include a high proportion of students from groups that have historically been under-represented in STEM fields) our work has improved both students? and teachers? access to cutting-edge scientific ideas, potentially improving students? future participation/retention in technical fields. Finally, in addition to our school outreach, by involving undergraduate researchers in our work we taught budding young scientists research skills that will serve them well in their future careers.  Beyond these immediate scientific and outreach accomplishments, in the future our studies might enhance clinical approaches to restoring function following nervous system injury or disease. Because our neurobiological studies have revealed a previously unknown method by which the nervous system controls motor output, our work might be extended to improve the design of theraputic devices that could be used to record brain activity from a paralyzed patient and control a prosthetic device.           Last Modified: 07/29/2019       Submitted by: Samuel Sober]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
