<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Values and Policy in Interdisciplinary Environmental Science: A Dialogue-based Framework for Ethics Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>76670.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>76670</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wenda K. Bauchspies</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbauchsp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925034</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A collaborative team of investigators from Michigan State University and the University of Idaho is working with instructors and students in interdisciplinary environmental science programs (IESPs) to conduct systematic, critical analysis of ethical concepts in the context of interdisciplinary environmental science. IESPs have multiplied in post-secondary and graduate curricula in response to pressing environmental problems. Ethical considerations are of immense importance in addressing environmental topics, because they often involve value judgments and the ethical issues involved are complex, multi-faceted, and high-stakes. Yet, ethics education materials for graduate IESP courses have not kept pace. This education and research project is developing an approach to graduate ethics education in IESPs that can better prepare the next generation of environmental scientists to solve complex problems. Materials development is being guided by two pedagogical commitments: (a) a constructivist paradigm that recognizes the social and collaborative nature of learning; and (b) a commitment to problem-driven models of education. A structured, yet flexible, framework is being created to enable development of course modules that can subsequently be adopted for use in classroom dialogue, building on results of work previously funded by NSF (the Toolbox Project - NSF award #0823058). The framework consists of materials for instructors and students that help them identify contexts in their IESP where ethical dilemmas generated by value judgments are likely to occur. The framework has two dimensions, corresponding to "content" and "method". The "content" concerns value judgments that relate to (a) the conduct of interdisciplinary scientific research, and (b) the impact of interdisciplinary environmental science on societal needs and policies. The "method" engages students, as teams or groups, in critical, conceptual analysis of value and policy aspects of their own practice as scientists and engineers. Students in courses using these modules will participate actively in identifying and assessing values-related challenges that are at the intersection of multiple environmental perspectives and at the intersection of science with policy. In addition to developing this framework, the project team is conducting a rigorous evaluation of its effectiveness for facilitating better consideration of ethical issues in IESP courses. Dissemination of the framework broadly through presentations and publications will strengthen interdisciplinary undergraduate and graduate education and will also provide professional development opportunities, ethics training, and mentoring for graduate research assistants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456085</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Troy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Troy E Hall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>troy.hall@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417371306</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536303</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318583</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[321 Richardson Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7787</Code>
<Text>EESE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7491</Code>
<Text>ETHICS EDU FOR SCI &amp; ENG PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~76670</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>a. Project outcomes or findings. </em></p> <p>Our work was accomplished through a pair of collaborative research awards from the NSF. Our goal was to understand challenges that interdisciplinary environmental science graduate programs face when incorporating &ldquo;sociopolitical&rdquo; issues into their curricula and to develop and assess state-of-the-art learning modules.</p> <p>Our team &ndash; located at Oregon State University &ndash; conducted initial research through an email survey of 480 instructors and administrators from 81 interdisciplinary environmental education programs across the United States. The study asked respondents about the need for &ldquo;social ethics&rdquo; topics in their graduate programs, as well as challenges they face when incorporating such topics. Respondents overwhelmingly agreed that their programs should help prepare students to think about how people&rsquo;s values (their own and those of the public) should be addressed when applying science to environmental policy and management. Respondents identified several challenges, including lack of expertise and materials within their programs; they indicated that the most effective way to incorporate such material would be through modules or activities within existing courses that engage students in active learning and dialogue. (This work was published in <em>Science and Engineering Ethics</em> in 2016).</p> <p>The second team &ndash; located at Michigan State University &ndash; developed curricular materials to help graduate students enrolled in interdisciplinary environmental science programs think and reason about selected social/ethical issues involved in research on environmental problems. Specifically, the curriculum focused on four themes: a) risk (what values are at stake in any particular issue? whose values should take priority in deciding what to study, how to study it, and how to make decisions?); b) expertise (who should be involved in providing credible knowledge about the nature of a problem and/or its solution? What is the appropriate role for scientists in making decisions about social/environmental problems?); c) sociopolitical constraints (how do political realities affect what is studied, how research is conducted, and what is done with research findings?); and d) impacts to non-human entities (how should impacts to other species or ecosystems be considered in research related to environmental problems and making decisions about how to address them?). The curriculum is designed so students read about and discuss the four themes, and it culminates in an in-class discussion (guided by a set of discussion prompts).</p> <p>The curricular materials are packaged into an &ldquo;instructor toolkit&rdquo; and a &ldquo;student&rdquo; toolkit, both of which are publicly available on a website hosted at Michigan State University. The instructor toolkit includes the following:</p> <ul> <li>A letter to instructors describing the toolkit and providing suggestions for its use within existing courses;</li> <li>An overview of the four themes;</li> <li>A set of Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs);</li> <li>A 6-hour lesson plan and a 3-hour lesson plan;</li> <li>A set of articles describing case examples related to the four themes, as well as guidance for selecting locally relevant case examples;</li> <li>Instruction for developing discussion prompts and conducting the group dialogue; and</li> <li>Suggested assessment activities for evaluating student accomplishment of learning outcomes;</li> </ul> <p>Finally, the two teams worked together to evaluate the effectiveness of our curricular materials. Instructors from five diverse graduate programs were recruited to participate in the study. We conducted semi-structured interviews with students at the beginning and end of the term (asking how they would approach various issues related to expertise, risk and sociopolitical constraints in the context of a particular environmental problem they might research). In the first year, the curriculum was not implemented, and the students served as a control group. In the second year, the curriculum was implemented between the initial and end-of-term interviews. This work is currently in review at a scientific journal (see &ldquo;c&rdquo; below). The approach and materials used in the research (the interview questions we asked and the rubric we developed to assess and score students&rsquo; responses) are available from the Oregon State University research team.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>b. Other products. </em></p> <p>As noted above, the curricular materials and research instruments are available from the principal investigators, Drs. Michael O&rsquo;Rourke (Michigan State University) and Troy Hall (Oregon State University).</p> <p><em>c. Anticipated publication of project results.</em></p> <p>This project currently has a manuscript in review at a refereed scientific journal, titled &ldquo;Evaluating a Dialogue-Based Approach to Teaching Values and Policy in Graduate Transdisciplinary Environmental Science Programs.&rdquo; This paper describes research in which we assessed how graduate students reason about issues associated with the involvement of the public and other stakeholders in research to address complex environmental problems; we evaluated reasoning before and after students in five classes engaged with our curriculum. The study demonstrates that the curricular materials and activities improve graduate students&rsquo; understanding of and ability to articulate the appropriate roles for different stakeholders in different phases of research.</p> <p>The MSU team is continuing work on its component of the project, and they anticipate additional publications within the next year. Those will be described in the MSU Project Outcomes Report.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2017<br>      Modified by: Troy&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hall</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ a. Project outcomes or findings.   Our work was accomplished through a pair of collaborative research awards from the NSF. Our goal was to understand challenges that interdisciplinary environmental science graduate programs face when incorporating "sociopolitical" issues into their curricula and to develop and assess state-of-the-art learning modules.  Our team &ndash; located at Oregon State University &ndash; conducted initial research through an email survey of 480 instructors and administrators from 81 interdisciplinary environmental education programs across the United States. The study asked respondents about the need for "social ethics" topics in their graduate programs, as well as challenges they face when incorporating such topics. Respondents overwhelmingly agreed that their programs should help prepare students to think about how people?s values (their own and those of the public) should be addressed when applying science to environmental policy and management. Respondents identified several challenges, including lack of expertise and materials within their programs; they indicated that the most effective way to incorporate such material would be through modules or activities within existing courses that engage students in active learning and dialogue. (This work was published in Science and Engineering Ethics in 2016).  The second team &ndash; located at Michigan State University &ndash; developed curricular materials to help graduate students enrolled in interdisciplinary environmental science programs think and reason about selected social/ethical issues involved in research on environmental problems. Specifically, the curriculum focused on four themes: a) risk (what values are at stake in any particular issue? whose values should take priority in deciding what to study, how to study it, and how to make decisions?); b) expertise (who should be involved in providing credible knowledge about the nature of a problem and/or its solution? What is the appropriate role for scientists in making decisions about social/environmental problems?); c) sociopolitical constraints (how do political realities affect what is studied, how research is conducted, and what is done with research findings?); and d) impacts to non-human entities (how should impacts to other species or ecosystems be considered in research related to environmental problems and making decisions about how to address them?). The curriculum is designed so students read about and discuss the four themes, and it culminates in an in-class discussion (guided by a set of discussion prompts).  The curricular materials are packaged into an "instructor toolkit" and a "student" toolkit, both of which are publicly available on a website hosted at Michigan State University. The instructor toolkit includes the following:  A letter to instructors describing the toolkit and providing suggestions for its use within existing courses; An overview of the four themes; A set of Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs); A 6-hour lesson plan and a 3-hour lesson plan; A set of articles describing case examples related to the four themes, as well as guidance for selecting locally relevant case examples; Instruction for developing discussion prompts and conducting the group dialogue; and Suggested assessment activities for evaluating student accomplishment of learning outcomes;   Finally, the two teams worked together to evaluate the effectiveness of our curricular materials. Instructors from five diverse graduate programs were recruited to participate in the study. We conducted semi-structured interviews with students at the beginning and end of the term (asking how they would approach various issues related to expertise, risk and sociopolitical constraints in the context of a particular environmental problem they might research). In the first year, the curriculum was not implemented, and the students served as a control group. In the second year, the curriculum was implemented between the initial and end-of-term interviews. This work is currently in review at a scientific journal (see "c" below). The approach and materials used in the research (the interview questions we asked and the rubric we developed to assess and score students? responses) are available from the Oregon State University research team.     b. Other products.   As noted above, the curricular materials and research instruments are available from the principal investigators, Drs. Michael O?Rourke (Michigan State University) and Troy Hall (Oregon State University).  c. Anticipated publication of project results.  This project currently has a manuscript in review at a refereed scientific journal, titled "Evaluating a Dialogue-Based Approach to Teaching Values and Policy in Graduate Transdisciplinary Environmental Science Programs." This paper describes research in which we assessed how graduate students reason about issues associated with the involvement of the public and other stakeholders in research to address complex environmental problems; we evaluated reasoning before and after students in five classes engaged with our curriculum. The study demonstrates that the curricular materials and activities improve graduate students? understanding of and ability to articulate the appropriate roles for different stakeholders in different phases of research.  The MSU team is continuing work on its component of the project, and they anticipate additional publications within the next year. Those will be described in the MSU Project Outcomes Report.       Last Modified: 12/09/2017       Submitted by: Troy E Hall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
