<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Fast Switching Electrochromic Window</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1036661</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to improve light/heat control into the automobile and enhance user comfort by replacing existing automotive glass with dynamic automotive glass.  Economic and environmental benefits of using dynamic windows in automobiles include increase of miles per gallon by reducing air conditioning load with enhance light/heat management.  Replacing standard automotive sunroof glass with dynamic sunroof glass will increase fuel efficiency by 3 miles per gallon during summer time.  If all the glass in an automobile is replaced with dynamic glass then the impact will be much larger, resulting in decrease in oil consumption by several millions of barrels per day.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will utilize scalable solution processed techniques to create unique fast switching electrochromic layers. Current dynamic window technologies have not reached their market potential due to their high cost.  Due to technological limitations, current dynamic window products can only be used for sunroof applications as a result there are not being used for side windows, rear glass or windshield.  New class of electrochromic windows based on innovative materials and device designs that achieve fast switching, high contrast and low production costs will enable wide spread adoption of smart windows in a broad range of automobiles. The novel electrochromic layers developed during Phase I research will be improved further and scaled up to commercially significant size prototypes. New smart windows will cost 3-4x lower compared to current smart window products on the market or in advanced development stage.  These novel electrochromic devices will be thoroughly characterized and their long term reliability established by the end of Phase II research. At the end of Phase II prototypes of fast switching electrochromic automotive glazing will be built that are suitable for installation in a car for sunroof and/or side window.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456092</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Damoder</FirstName>
<LastName>Reddy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Damoder Reddy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>damoder.reddy@argilinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4088584808</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620611</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ARGIL, INC.</Name>
<CityName>Los Gatos</CityName>
<ZipCode>950321910</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4088584808</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>16457 West Mozart Ave.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078459650</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARGIL, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ARGIL, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>San Jose</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>951381400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5941 Optical Court]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>168E</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR/ERC Collab (SECO)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~888567</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~148094</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">This Small Business Innovation Research Phase-II project developed ?Fast Switching Electrochromic Window for Automotive Applications? by dynamically optimizing light transmission and heat gain through automotive glazing.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman;"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">:</span>&nbsp; Argil utilized scalable solution processed techniques to create unique fast switching electrochromic layers. The novel electrochromic layers developed during Phase I research were improved further and scaled up the process during Phase II&nbsp; to make commercially significant size prototypes. These devices were thoroughly characterized and their long term reliability established. At the end of Phase II Argil built prototypes of fast switching electrochromic automotive glazing installed in a car for sunroof and side window.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman;"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-size: small;">Broader/Commercial Impact:</span></span></strong><span style="font-size: small;"> Automotive applications represent a prime opportunity to improve light/heat control into the automobile and enhance user comfort by replacing existing automotive glass with dynamic automotive glass.&nbsp; Economic and environmental benefits of using dynamic windows in automotives are clear:&nbsp; increase miles per gallon by reducing air conditioning load with enhance light/heat management: increasing fuel efficiency by 3 miles per gallon will decrease oil consumption by one million barrels of oil per day.&nbsp; It is estimated that replacing standard automotive sunroof glass with dynamic sunroof glass will increase fuel efficiency by 3 miles per gallon during summer time.&nbsp; If all the glass in an automobile is replaced with dynamic glass then the impact will be much larger resulting in decrease in oil consumption by several millions of barrels per day.&nbsp; Still, current dynamic window technologies have not reached their market potential due to their high cost (~$100/ft</span><sup><span style="font-size: x-small;">2</span></sup><span style="font-size: small;">).&nbsp; Due to the technological limitation current dynamic window products can only be used for sunroof applications as a result there are not being used for side windows or windshield.&nbsp; Argil electrochromic windows are based innovative materials and device designs that achieve fast switching and high contrast while reducing production costs compared to alternate dynamic window technologies available today.&nbsp; Wide scale adoption of this unique technology will not only enhance market penetration for dynamic windows but establish a new benchmark for performance and cost.&nbsp;</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Damoder&nbsp;Reddy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research Phase-II project developed ?Fast Switching Electrochromic Window for Automotive Applications? by dynamically optimizing light transmission and heat gain through automotive glazing.   Intellectual Merit:  Argil utilized scalable solution processed techniques to create unique fast switching electrochromic layers. The novel electrochromic layers developed during Phase I research were improved further and scaled up the process during Phase II  to make commercially significant size prototypes. These devices were thoroughly characterized and their long term reliability established. At the end of Phase II Argil built prototypes of fast switching electrochromic automotive glazing installed in a car for sunroof and side window.   Broader/Commercial Impact: Automotive applications represent a prime opportunity to improve light/heat control into the automobile and enhance user comfort by replacing existing automotive glass with dynamic automotive glass.  Economic and environmental benefits of using dynamic windows in automotives are clear:  increase miles per gallon by reducing air conditioning load with enhance light/heat management: increasing fuel efficiency by 3 miles per gallon will decrease oil consumption by one million barrels of oil per day.  It is estimated that replacing standard automotive sunroof glass with dynamic sunroof glass will increase fuel efficiency by 3 miles per gallon during summer time.  If all the glass in an automobile is replaced with dynamic glass then the impact will be much larger resulting in decrease in oil consumption by several millions of barrels per day.  Still, current dynamic window technologies have not reached their market potential due to their high cost (~$100/ft2).  Due to the technological limitation current dynamic window products can only be used for sunroof applications as a result there are not being used for side windows or windshield.  Argil electrochromic windows are based innovative materials and device designs that achieve fast switching and high contrast while reducing production costs compared to alternate dynamic window technologies available today.  Wide scale adoption of this unique technology will not only enhance market penetration for dynamic windows but establish a new benchmark for performance and cost.        Last Modified: 11/09/2018       Submitted by: Damoder Reddy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
