<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Ultra-softening polymers from engineered thiol-based resins for additive manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>730198</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is making tough, 3D printed parts that can be directly manufactured through additive processes commercially available. Additive manufacturing has potential to revolutionize the way parts are produced by streamlining product design, production, and validation, which allows for low production costs and accelerated lead times. The penetration of additive technology into industrial processes has been greatly slowed by the current inability to 3D print parts of any stiffness with materials properties on par with traditionally manufactured parts. Particularly, 3D printed materials tend to tear or fracture more readily between successive printed layers. At Adaptive 3D Technologies, we have developed resins that produce tough, robust parts that are tougher than many current 3D printed products in the x, y and z planes by achieving covalent crosslinking across printed layers. These materials and processing techniques will help drive additive manufacturing into large volume, yet customizable, market sectors to increase efficiency and productivity across industries.  The printed parts resulting from our printable materials will further U.S. manufacturing by lowering production costs, increasing product performance and reshoring advanced manufacturing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is focused on understanding interface chemistry and adhesion phenomena in a special class of low-viscosity, thiol-ene resins to produce a range of mechanically tough materials that are 3D printable via stereolithography (SLA). A significant problem with current SLA approaches is that successive printed layers do not adhere sufficiently together, leading to large reductions in toughness as measured by the stress-strain response in soft, viscoelastic and stiff materials. Our Phase II research explores the tradeoffs between molecular architecture, reactivity, resin viscosity, and key printing parameters to develop improved materials to enable tougher printed parts than industry standards along multiple axes of deformation at similar printing speeds and feature sizes well below 100 microns. We have developed a portfolio of 3D printable materials with room temperature Young's moduli near 2 MPa, 20 MPa, 200 MPa or 2 GPa.  Soft and viscoelastic materials have strain capacities well above 100% in all print directions, including when measured perpendicular to print layer interfaces. We expect to further our polymers' thermomechanical properties through the proposed Phase II SBIR effort by incorporating proper additives into our systems to control color, shelf life, aesthetics, mechanical properties and compatibility with various jetting techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456407</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cary</FirstName>
<LastName>Baur</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cary Baur</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cary@memoryplastics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8643147346</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/08/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lund</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin R Lund</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>benjamin@adaptive3dtechnologies.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728837125</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701450</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Adaptive 3D Technologies LLC</Name>
<CityName>Dallas</CityName>
<ZipCode>752528004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728837156</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>17217 Waterview Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 1.202]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079393561</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADAPTIVE 3D TECHNOLOGIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Adaptive 3D Technologies LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Dallas</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>752528004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17217 Waterview Pkwy, STE 1.202]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~730198</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;">Adaptive3D enables ultra-soft, high-elongation,</p> <p style="text-align: center;">rubber-like materials for additive manufacturing</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Additive manufacturing, the high-throughput, high-volume industrially relevant cousin to 3D printing, has captured the imagination of companies large and small with promises to change how the world processes materials. A technique for rapid prototyping today, 3D printing has led to innovative fabrication models where limited numbers of custom parts are produced <em>just-in-time</em> and sometimes at the <em>point-of-use</em>. These paradigms have massive implications for global distribution channels and global manufacturing if cost, throughput and materials properties issues can be overcome. Further, the ability of 3D printing to perform free-form fabrication means that printed parts can be personalized to specific users, allowing mass customization of once-generic products. This potential has inspired ideas of a so-called <em>factory of the future model </em>where individualized parts are produced on demand for specific customers. In the Gartner hype cycle and life cycle of technologies, specific products in additive manufacturing race toward the <em>pinnacle of inflated expectations</em> and are about to plunge into the <em>trough of disillusionment</em> until fundamental issues of cost, throughput and properties at scale can be addressed for each specific material, for each specific product, for each specific end customer.</p> <p><strong>3D printed materials are not the same as traditional polymers and rubbers.</strong> These differences range from changes in molecular weight for thermoplastics and elastomers to completely new chemical formulations available and necessary to rapidly process thermosets. The lack of sufficient materials&rsquo; properties (specifically toughness and strain capacity), continues to limit the adoption of additive manufacturing and threatens to stifle healthy and robust market projections in this space.</p> <p>At Adaptive3D we seek to ultimately compete with injection molding and mass thermoplastic processing through the commercialization of novel chemistries: specifically those involving sulfur-based thiol reactions. During the course of our NSF Phase II SBIR entitled, <em>Ultra-softening Polymers from Engineered Thiol-based Resins for Additive Manufacturing</em> we began to explore the use of thiols in 3D printed polymeric systems and are now pleased to report on some of our findings which have already translated into two launched commercial products and several more projected in late 2018 and 2019.</p> <p>Thiols have been known for many years to act as effective chain transfer agents in radical systems, enabling excellent control of molecular weight and polymer network morphology. Due to the pioneering work of Hoyle and Bowman in the early 2000&rsquo;s, thiol-ene chemistry has enjoyed a Renaissance in the halls of academia and received skeptical, but renewed curiosity from the industrial community. Traditionally, thiols suffer from a number of drawbacks: thiol-ene formulations often have limited shelf-life; most thiols have an unpleasant odor that is repulsive to those handling them (nature&rsquo;s foremost example being the skunk); and finally, thiol-based chemicals are often expensive, making it commercially infeasible to incorporate them into formulations at high loading levels.</p> <p>Despite these drawbacks, thiol-ene chemistries offer unique properties with the potential to solve a number of challenges in 3D printing today and additive manufacturing tomorrow. Ultra-low cure stress and resistance to oxygen make thiol-ene chemistries ideal choices for polymers that can take advantage of long lifetimes of propagating radicals, improved printed part isotropy and enhanced control of the macromolecular structure of the polymer.</p> <p>Over the course of our grant we explored thiol-ene, thiol-ene/acrylate and thiol-acrylate systems. The resulting materials, initially designed as shape memory polymers, exhibited excellent mechanical toughness (&gt; 20MJ/m<sup>3</sup> at 150% elongation) or ultra-softness (Shore A 16 at 250% elongation). Initially, commercialization was hindered by the residual smell of thiols in the cured parts. We next explored decreasing the amount of thiol in our formulations and switched our focus from stoichiometric or near stoichiometric thiol-enes and thiol-ene/acrylate systems to thiol-acrylate systems, utilizing the thiols as low volume chain transfer agents, rather than stoichiometric reagents. In the past, shelf-life and pot-life issue had limited this approach in one pot resin systems.</p> <p>In Adaptive3D&rsquo;s thiol-acrylate systems, we were able to reduce the thiol smell to imperceptible levels while retaining the excellent aforementioned thermomechanical properties. We settled on an intriguing materials properties space for commercializing our first rubber-like resin formulation, Tough<strong>Rubber</strong> 30.<strong>450</strong>&mdash;Shore A of 90, a toughness of 30 MJ/m<sup>3</sup> and an elongation at break of 450%&mdash;making our 385 nm curable energy-damping photo-resin the world&rsquo;s stretchiest, tough photopolymer for additive manufacturing.&nbsp; &nbsp;In late 2018, we anticipate launching Tough<strong>Rubber</strong> 3.<strong>450, </strong>a silicon-like rubber exhibiting a softness of 20 (Shore A), a failure toughness of 3 MJ/m<sup>3</sup> and an elongation at break of 450%.</p> <p>Adaptive3D works with global market leaders in materials, apparel, automotive, oil and gas, medical, audio, industrial and manufacturing sectors to provide resins to help companies move from 3D printing prototypes to additively manufacturing products and components at large volumes and high throughputs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2018<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;R&nbsp;Lund</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Adaptive3D enables ultra-soft, high-elongation, rubber-like materials for additive manufacturing     Additive manufacturing, the high-throughput, high-volume industrially relevant cousin to 3D printing, has captured the imagination of companies large and small with promises to change how the world processes materials. A technique for rapid prototyping today, 3D printing has led to innovative fabrication models where limited numbers of custom parts are produced just-in-time and sometimes at the point-of-use. These paradigms have massive implications for global distribution channels and global manufacturing if cost, throughput and materials properties issues can be overcome. Further, the ability of 3D printing to perform free-form fabrication means that printed parts can be personalized to specific users, allowing mass customization of once-generic products. This potential has inspired ideas of a so-called factory of the future model where individualized parts are produced on demand for specific customers. In the Gartner hype cycle and life cycle of technologies, specific products in additive manufacturing race toward the pinnacle of inflated expectations and are about to plunge into the trough of disillusionment until fundamental issues of cost, throughput and properties at scale can be addressed for each specific material, for each specific product, for each specific end customer.  3D printed materials are not the same as traditional polymers and rubbers. These differences range from changes in molecular weight for thermoplastics and elastomers to completely new chemical formulations available and necessary to rapidly process thermosets. The lack of sufficient materials? properties (specifically toughness and strain capacity), continues to limit the adoption of additive manufacturing and threatens to stifle healthy and robust market projections in this space.  At Adaptive3D we seek to ultimately compete with injection molding and mass thermoplastic processing through the commercialization of novel chemistries: specifically those involving sulfur-based thiol reactions. During the course of our NSF Phase II SBIR entitled, Ultra-softening Polymers from Engineered Thiol-based Resins for Additive Manufacturing we began to explore the use of thiols in 3D printed polymeric systems and are now pleased to report on some of our findings which have already translated into two launched commercial products and several more projected in late 2018 and 2019.  Thiols have been known for many years to act as effective chain transfer agents in radical systems, enabling excellent control of molecular weight and polymer network morphology. Due to the pioneering work of Hoyle and Bowman in the early 2000?s, thiol-ene chemistry has enjoyed a Renaissance in the halls of academia and received skeptical, but renewed curiosity from the industrial community. Traditionally, thiols suffer from a number of drawbacks: thiol-ene formulations often have limited shelf-life; most thiols have an unpleasant odor that is repulsive to those handling them (nature?s foremost example being the skunk); and finally, thiol-based chemicals are often expensive, making it commercially infeasible to incorporate them into formulations at high loading levels.  Despite these drawbacks, thiol-ene chemistries offer unique properties with the potential to solve a number of challenges in 3D printing today and additive manufacturing tomorrow. Ultra-low cure stress and resistance to oxygen make thiol-ene chemistries ideal choices for polymers that can take advantage of long lifetimes of propagating radicals, improved printed part isotropy and enhanced control of the macromolecular structure of the polymer.  Over the course of our grant we explored thiol-ene, thiol-ene/acrylate and thiol-acrylate systems. The resulting materials, initially designed as shape memory polymers, exhibited excellent mechanical toughness (&gt; 20MJ/m3 at 150% elongation) or ultra-softness (Shore A 16 at 250% elongation). Initially, commercialization was hindered by the residual smell of thiols in the cured parts. We next explored decreasing the amount of thiol in our formulations and switched our focus from stoichiometric or near stoichiometric thiol-enes and thiol-ene/acrylate systems to thiol-acrylate systems, utilizing the thiols as low volume chain transfer agents, rather than stoichiometric reagents. In the past, shelf-life and pot-life issue had limited this approach in one pot resin systems.  In Adaptive3D?s thiol-acrylate systems, we were able to reduce the thiol smell to imperceptible levels while retaining the excellent aforementioned thermomechanical properties. We settled on an intriguing materials properties space for commercializing our first rubber-like resin formulation, ToughRubber 30.450&mdash;Shore A of 90, a toughness of 30 MJ/m3 and an elongation at break of 450%&mdash;making our 385 nm curable energy-damping photo-resin the world?s stretchiest, tough photopolymer for additive manufacturing.   In late 2018, we anticipate launching ToughRubber 3.450, a silicon-like rubber exhibiting a softness of 20 (Shore A), a failure toughness of 3 MJ/m3 and an elongation at break of 450%.  Adaptive3D works with global market leaders in materials, apparel, automotive, oil and gas, medical, audio, industrial and manufacturing sectors to provide resins to help companies move from 3D printing prototypes to additively manufacturing products and components at large volumes and high throughputs.                   Last Modified: 08/22/2018       Submitted by: Benjamin R Lund]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
