<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The role of the FEI Pathway in Regulating Cell Wall Synthesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>719999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>841776</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gschoenk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925076</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical summary:&lt;br/&gt;Plant cell walls are diverse and highly dynamic structures that respond to developmental and environmental cues. They are a primary source of building materials, paper, biofuels, cotton, and many other useful products and also plays a crucial role in the growth and development of plants. Despite their importance both from a practical and fundamental point of view, the signaling pathways regulating the function and assembly of plant cell walls are just beginning to be understood. This project seeks to gain fundamental knowledge regarding how plants regulate the synthesis of their cell walls, which should ultimately help improve the diverse products derived from them and will provide insight into basic aspects of plant growth and development. In addition to providing interdisciplinary training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, this project will work with programs designed to increase the representation of minorities in the sciences and with several outreach programs designed to increase the public understanding of plant science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description of the Project:&lt;br/&gt;Previous studies identified a pair of transmembrane protein kinases, called FEI1 and FEI2, that play a role in regulating the biosynthesis of cellulose, which is a critical component of the plant cell wall and acts as the primary load-bearing element. These kinases define a novel signaling pathway that includes a non-canonical role for 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC), a molecule previously thought to act only as a precursor in the biosynthesis of the phytohormone ethylene. A series of experiments to further characterize the FEI signaling pathway and its role in regulating cell wall function will be pursued. The mechanism by which the FEI pathway regulates cellulose biosynthesis will be explored (Aim 1). The signaling role of ACC and other potential ACC-derivatives in regulating wall synthesis will be examined (Aim 2). Other components involved in this FEI pathway will be identified and characterized, including SHOU4, a protein that appears to act in the FEI pathway and which is likely associated with the cytoskeleton (Aim 3). These studies will answer fundamental questions regarding how this pathway regulates the production of cellulose and how it interacts with other elements to regulate cell wall synthesis. Further, the FEIs are belong to a group of kinases call the receptor-like kinase, which are one of the largest families of genes in plants; the function of only a handful of RLKs are known, and thus these findings will shed light on a poorly understood class of plant signaling elements. Finally, these studies should help elucidate a role for ACC in plant signaling and may uncover important roles for a novel signaling compound in plants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1456658</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Kieber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph J Kieber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkieber@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199624455</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000203015</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275993280</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8288</Code>
<Text>BM Gates Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1141</Code>
<Text>PHYSIOLOG &amp; STRUCTURAL SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>40XX</Code>
<Name>NSF TRUST FUND</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>048960</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~179999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~301777</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Plant cell walls are a primary source of building materials, paper, biofuels, cotton, and many other useful products. The cell wall also plays a crucial role in the growth and development of plants as it provides structural support, defines the size and shape of cells and hence of plant form, and provides a barrier to infection by pathogens. Thus determining how plants regulate the synthesis of their cell walls is important both for improving diverse products derived from them and for understanding basic aspects of plant growth and development and their response to the environment. The goal of this study was to characterize a signaling pathway involved in regulating the function and assembly of cell walls. Previous studies from our laboratory identified a pair of transmembrane protein kinases, called FEI1 and FEI2, that play a role in regulating the biosynthesis of cellulose, which is a critical component of the plant cell wall and which acts as the primary load-bearing element. These kinases define a novel signaling pathway controlling cell wall synthesis.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; One major focus of the studies supported by this award was to understand the role of a new element in the FEI pathway called SHOU4. Disruption of <em>SHOU4</em> completely reverses the cellulose-deficient phenotype of the <em>fei</em> mutants. Our studies indicated that SHOU4 plays a key role in regulating how much cellulose plants make. Through a variety of approaches, we found that SHOU4 acts by controlling how much of the enzyme that makes cellulose, called CESA, is sent to the surface of the cell where cellulose is made. SHOU4 was found to interact directly with CESA at the cell surface, which, combined with other data, suggests that when SHOU4 interacts with CESA, it generates a signal to reduce further delivery of CESA, thus acting to feedback inhibit cellulose production. We hypothesize that SHOU4 acts as a key integrator of multiple inputs regulating cell wall function to increase or decrease cellulose synthesis as needed. We also identified the genes corresponding to a number of additional SHOU loci that will form the foundation for further insight into the pathways regulating cellulose synthesis.</p> <p>A second focus of our studies has been to understand the role that 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC), a molecule previously thought to act only as a precursor in the biosynthesis of the phytohormone ethylene, plays in the FEI pathway. We identified a number of genes that are involved in the ACC signaling pathway using a mutant screen in an <em>ein2</em> background (to eliminate confounding effects of ethylene). We named these mutants <span style="text-decoration: underline;">AC</span>C <span style="text-decoration: underline;">re</span>sistant (<em>acre</em>). Intriguingly, many of these mutants had phenotypes strikingly similar to our <em>shou4</em> mutants, suggesting that blocking ACC perception leads to increased cellulose levels. These results are consistent with our previous work, which together suggest that ACC, in addition to serving as the precursor for ethylene biosynthesis, plays a role a key role in modulating cellulose biosynthesis. Cloning these <em>ACRE</em> genes should provide insight into how plant cells perceive this novel signaling molecule and contribute to our understanding of the pathways regulating cell wall synthesis.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition to the insight gained regarding the fundamental question of how plants regulate the synthesis of cell walls, these studies will also provide avenues for improving cell wall feedstock into a variety of products, such as biofuels. As part of this project, we also co-organized a week-long science camp for middle school children, named SciVentures, which helped expose middle school students to the science being done in our lab. We hosted campers in our laboratory, showed them the facilities and equipment, and explained what scientific questions are being currently studied. The students left with a better appreciation of the importance of research in general and plant science in particular.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kieber</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Plant cell walls are a primary source of building materials, paper, biofuels, cotton, and many other useful products. The cell wall also plays a crucial role in the growth and development of plants as it provides structural support, defines the size and shape of cells and hence of plant form, and provides a barrier to infection by pathogens. Thus determining how plants regulate the synthesis of their cell walls is important both for improving diverse products derived from them and for understanding basic aspects of plant growth and development and their response to the environment. The goal of this study was to characterize a signaling pathway involved in regulating the function and assembly of cell walls. Previous studies from our laboratory identified a pair of transmembrane protein kinases, called FEI1 and FEI2, that play a role in regulating the biosynthesis of cellulose, which is a critical component of the plant cell wall and which acts as the primary load-bearing element. These kinases define a novel signaling pathway controlling cell wall synthesis.      One major focus of the studies supported by this award was to understand the role of a new element in the FEI pathway called SHOU4. Disruption of SHOU4 completely reverses the cellulose-deficient phenotype of the fei mutants. Our studies indicated that SHOU4 plays a key role in regulating how much cellulose plants make. Through a variety of approaches, we found that SHOU4 acts by controlling how much of the enzyme that makes cellulose, called CESA, is sent to the surface of the cell where cellulose is made. SHOU4 was found to interact directly with CESA at the cell surface, which, combined with other data, suggests that when SHOU4 interacts with CESA, it generates a signal to reduce further delivery of CESA, thus acting to feedback inhibit cellulose production. We hypothesize that SHOU4 acts as a key integrator of multiple inputs regulating cell wall function to increase or decrease cellulose synthesis as needed. We also identified the genes corresponding to a number of additional SHOU loci that will form the foundation for further insight into the pathways regulating cellulose synthesis.  A second focus of our studies has been to understand the role that 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC), a molecule previously thought to act only as a precursor in the biosynthesis of the phytohormone ethylene, plays in the FEI pathway. We identified a number of genes that are involved in the ACC signaling pathway using a mutant screen in an ein2 background (to eliminate confounding effects of ethylene). We named these mutants ACC resistant (acre). Intriguingly, many of these mutants had phenotypes strikingly similar to our shou4 mutants, suggesting that blocking ACC perception leads to increased cellulose levels. These results are consistent with our previous work, which together suggest that ACC, in addition to serving as the precursor for ethylene biosynthesis, plays a role a key role in modulating cellulose biosynthesis. Cloning these ACRE genes should provide insight into how plant cells perceive this novel signaling molecule and contribute to our understanding of the pathways regulating cell wall synthesis.          In addition to the insight gained regarding the fundamental question of how plants regulate the synthesis of cell walls, these studies will also provide avenues for improving cell wall feedstock into a variety of products, such as biofuels. As part of this project, we also co-organized a week-long science camp for middle school children, named SciVentures, which helped expose middle school students to the science being done in our lab. We hosted campers in our laboratory, showed them the facilities and equipment, and explained what scientific questions are being currently studied. The students left with a better appreciation of the importance of research in general and plant science in particular.       Last Modified: 04/08/2019       Submitted by: Joseph J Kieber]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
