<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Linking Causes of Variation in the Amphibian Skin Microbiome with Consequences for Disease Risk</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>306075.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>306075</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamta Rawat</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mrawat@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927265</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Animals have communities of microbes (bacteria, viruses, fungi) living in and on their bodies. These microbial communities are referred to as symbiotic microbial communities, or the microbiome. Symbiotic microbial communities are increasingly recognized as important players in the health of humans and animals. Symbiotic microbes may be important to animal (host) health by affecting host response to disease-causing organisms (pathogens). This project aims to understand how the microbiome affects disease resistance while studying chytridiomycosis, a devastating disease of amphibians (frogs, toads and salamanders) caused by the pathogen Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis (abbreviated Bd). Bd is a fungus that infects the skin of amphibians and can cause potentially-lethal chytridiomycosis. The Sierra Nevada yellow-legged frog (Rana sierrae) is in danger of extinction and Bd is one of the most serious threats to this frog. Bd has caused massive die-offs of entire populations of R. sierrae. However, certain populations of R. sierrae appear to be somewhat resistant to lethal chytridiomycosis. Understanding why these resistant populations are able to survive despite Bd infection may be critical for efforts to conserve the species. It is possible that the skin microbiome contributes to disease resistance, however definitive evidence is lacking. This project will address three core questions: (1) To what extent does the R. sierrae skin microbiome contribute to disease resistance? (2) Does microbiome composition (i.e., the microbial species that make up the microbiome) affect the stability of the microbiome when frogs become infected with Bd? This may be important to understanding continued functionality of the microbiome when the host is threatened by infectious diseases. (3) How do host and environmental differences affect microbiome assembly? In other words, what are the forces that lead to differences in the microbiome of different frogs or populations, or within an individual frog at different times? This may reveal underlying causes that shape functional variation attributed to the microbiome, such as differences in disease resistance. In summary, this work will advance understanding of how host and environment determine microbiome composition and how this in turn may shape microbiome function and stability. Understanding of these processes is relevant to strategies for protecting threatened amphibians. More broadly, understanding how the R. sierrae microbiome interacts with Bd can provide insights into microbiome-pathogen interactions and management of infectious disease in other animals and humans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Symbiotic microbial communities are increasingly recognized as important players in the development and health of multicellular organisms. Several studies have found that disease caused by pathogenic microbes is associated with changes in the composition of the microbiome of the host compared with the microflora of healthy individuals, but it has often been difficult to determine cause and effect: the observed correlation may indicate that particular microbiome assemblages confer disease resistance, or that pathogen infection disrupts and alters the microbiome.  This project aims to understand the role of the amphibian skin-associated bacterial community (skin microbiome) in mediating resistance to the fungal pathogen Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis. The project will test if microbiome differences exist between disease-resistant and -susceptible hosts, suggestive of a protective role in nature.  Importantly, this work will further clarify the causal relationship between pathogen and microbiome by testing if experimental alteration of the microbiome leads to changes in disease resistance, or if instead pathogen infection alters the microbiome. This study also aims to understand what determines the phylogenetic and functional composition of the microbiome, a question that is fundamental to understanding the root of microbiome-associated differences in disease resistance.  Field surveys will be used to quantify the degree to which host genetic variation and environmental factors are associated with the phylogenetic and functional composition of the skin microbiome sampled from wild frogs, while experimental manipulations will clearly show cause and effect in these relationships.  Mathematical models will be developed to identify ecological mechanisms that potentially drive variation in microbial community composition.  Finally, predictive models of microbial community dynamics under conditions of disturbance (such as pathogen infection) will be developed, integrating community assembly and disease resistance concepts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457265</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roland</FirstName>
<LastName>Knapp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roland A Knapp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>knapp@lifesci.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7606470034</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Briggs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheryl J Briggs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>briggs@lifesci.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058932199</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332450</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marine Science Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931066150</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Bldg 520, MC 6150]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~306075</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Animals are inhabited by microbes such as bacteria, microbial fungi, and viruses, which together are referred to as the microbiome. Microbiomes can affect the health, development, and even behavior of the animals that they inhabit (the host). Research on the human microbiome has made great strides in understanding microbiome structure, control, and function, but a great deal is still unknown. Far less is known about the microbiomes of animals, and filling these knowledge gaps may provide valuable information for a range of applications such as veterinary medicine, animal husbandry, fermentation biotechnology, and the conservation of threatened species. This project focused on the interaction between the frog skin microbiome and a deadly disease of amphibians: chytridiomycosis. Chytridiomycosis is caused by a fungal pathogen (<em>Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</em>&nbsp;&ndash; abbreviated Bd) and has caused declines and even extinctions of hundreds of amphibian species. Some studies have shown that the microbiome of amphibians may provide protection against chytridiomycosis. However, attempts to control chytridiomycosis outbreaks using probiotics have had variable success, indicating a need to better understand the amphibian microbiome. This project had three overarching scientific goals: (1) identify the factors that determine which bacterial species make up the amphibian microbiome (microbiome composition); (2) test if the microbiome can help prevent Bd infection and disease; (3) understand the effect of Bd infection on microbiome composition and stability. This project used field studies, laboratory experiments, and mathematical models to understand the composition and function of the skin-associated microbiome of amphibians.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Objective 1: what determines microbiome composition? This project showed that the microbiome is controlled in part by the host. Different frog populations harbor different sets of bacteria, and these differences partially persist even when frogs are housed under identical laboratory conditions. The environment also affects the microbiome, and in some cases may override subtle differences between frogs: when frogs of similar genetic backgrounds are moved to new environments, they develop distinct microbiomes. Finally, mathematical models showed that microbiome composition may be partially explained by a combination of natural selection for certain bacterial species, as well as random processes. These findings suggest that it should be possible to manipulate the microbiome through environmental parameters, but that some degree of microbiome composition is controlled by the host or by ecological processes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Objectives 2 and 3: Does the microbiome protect frogs from disease, or does pathogen infection change the microbiome? This work showed that disease-resistant and disease-susceptible frog populations have different microbiomes. Laboratory studies from this project showed that differences in the microbiomes between frogs did not lead to differences in disease resistance. Together, these results show that pathogen infection altered the microbiome, and that the natural microbiome did not prevent infection, at least under the conditions of this study and without prebiotic or probiotic treatments. The work also showed that the microbiome has low resilience to disturbance by the pathogen &ndash; in other words, the microbiome was not stable when faced with pathogen infection. This means that the pathogen can change the composition of the microbiome, and clearing frogs of infection (e.g., through the use of antifungal drugs) does not lead to the microbiome recovering its original state. This finding indicates that pathogen infection may lead to long-term changes to the microbiome, which may affect the success of efforts to conserve these endangered frogs. Importantly, data from this project suggest negative effects of microbiome shifts: greater microbiome shifts were associated with weight loss by the frogs, and the functional genes found in the microbiome changed due to Bd infection. Further research to determine causal connections and understand how these genes affect host health will be very important.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project contributed to STEM training and education, conservation biology, and broad understanding of microbiome-disease interactions. The project trained four undergraduate students and one graduate student in field biology, disease ecology, and the use of cutting-edge next generation sequencing technologies in microbiome science. All of the student trainees are women. The project also trained one postdoctoral fellow in advanced mathematical modeling of microbial communities. The project provided valuable information for the conservation of amphibians, which are declining at alarming rates. Chytridiomycosis is one of the greatest threats to amphibians, and deeper understanding of the disease is critical to stem species declines. Finally, aspects of this project exploring infectious disease interactions with the microbiome would be difficult to reproduce for human diseases due to ethical or logistical barriers, and some of the findings of this study may indirectly inform understanding of the human microbiome in relation to infectious disease. To date, this project has yielded two public datasets and four publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Cheryl&nbsp;J&nbsp;Briggs</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Animals are inhabited by microbes such as bacteria, microbial fungi, and viruses, which together are referred to as the microbiome. Microbiomes can affect the health, development, and even behavior of the animals that they inhabit (the host). Research on the human microbiome has made great strides in understanding microbiome structure, control, and function, but a great deal is still unknown. Far less is known about the microbiomes of animals, and filling these knowledge gaps may provide valuable information for a range of applications such as veterinary medicine, animal husbandry, fermentation biotechnology, and the conservation of threatened species. This project focused on the interaction between the frog skin microbiome and a deadly disease of amphibians: chytridiomycosis. Chytridiomycosis is caused by a fungal pathogen (Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis &ndash; abbreviated Bd) and has caused declines and even extinctions of hundreds of amphibian species. Some studies have shown that the microbiome of amphibians may provide protection against chytridiomycosis. However, attempts to control chytridiomycosis outbreaks using probiotics have had variable success, indicating a need to better understand the amphibian microbiome. This project had three overarching scientific goals: (1) identify the factors that determine which bacterial species make up the amphibian microbiome (microbiome composition); (2) test if the microbiome can help prevent Bd infection and disease; (3) understand the effect of Bd infection on microbiome composition and stability. This project used field studies, laboratory experiments, and mathematical models to understand the composition and function of the skin-associated microbiome of amphibians.      Objective 1: what determines microbiome composition? This project showed that the microbiome is controlled in part by the host. Different frog populations harbor different sets of bacteria, and these differences partially persist even when frogs are housed under identical laboratory conditions. The environment also affects the microbiome, and in some cases may override subtle differences between frogs: when frogs of similar genetic backgrounds are moved to new environments, they develop distinct microbiomes. Finally, mathematical models showed that microbiome composition may be partially explained by a combination of natural selection for certain bacterial species, as well as random processes. These findings suggest that it should be possible to manipulate the microbiome through environmental parameters, but that some degree of microbiome composition is controlled by the host or by ecological processes.      Objectives 2 and 3: Does the microbiome protect frogs from disease, or does pathogen infection change the microbiome? This work showed that disease-resistant and disease-susceptible frog populations have different microbiomes. Laboratory studies from this project showed that differences in the microbiomes between frogs did not lead to differences in disease resistance. Together, these results show that pathogen infection altered the microbiome, and that the natural microbiome did not prevent infection, at least under the conditions of this study and without prebiotic or probiotic treatments. The work also showed that the microbiome has low resilience to disturbance by the pathogen &ndash; in other words, the microbiome was not stable when faced with pathogen infection. This means that the pathogen can change the composition of the microbiome, and clearing frogs of infection (e.g., through the use of antifungal drugs) does not lead to the microbiome recovering its original state. This finding indicates that pathogen infection may lead to long-term changes to the microbiome, which may affect the success of efforts to conserve these endangered frogs. Importantly, data from this project suggest negative effects of microbiome shifts: greater microbiome shifts were associated with weight loss by the frogs, and the functional genes found in the microbiome changed due to Bd infection. Further research to determine causal connections and understand how these genes affect host health will be very important.       This project contributed to STEM training and education, conservation biology, and broad understanding of microbiome-disease interactions. The project trained four undergraduate students and one graduate student in field biology, disease ecology, and the use of cutting-edge next generation sequencing technologies in microbiome science. All of the student trainees are women. The project also trained one postdoctoral fellow in advanced mathematical modeling of microbial communities. The project provided valuable information for the conservation of amphibians, which are declining at alarming rates. Chytridiomycosis is one of the greatest threats to amphibians, and deeper understanding of the disease is critical to stem species declines. Finally, aspects of this project exploring infectious disease interactions with the microbiome would be difficult to reproduce for human diseases due to ethical or logistical barriers, and some of the findings of this study may indirectly inform understanding of the human microbiome in relation to infectious disease. To date, this project has yielded two public datasets and four publications.          Last Modified: 11/27/2020       Submitted by: Cheryl J Briggs]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
