<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Phylogeny and diversification of the orb weaving spiders (Araneae)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>489857.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>489857</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will chronicle the evolution and diversification of the orb-weaving spiders to resolve a long-standing problem in animal evolution, that is, the origin and genealogical relationships of the main groups of orb-weavers. Ubiquitous, diverse, and exclusively predatory, spiders are one the most diverse and fascinating animal groups and the dominant arthropod predators in most terrestrial ecosystems. Orb-weavers are remarkable not only because of the high number of species described so far, but also because of the extraordinary architectural diversity of their foraging webs, ranging from highly geometric snare designs, often regarded as a pinnacle of animal engineering, to sheet and irregular cob webs. Understanding web evolution and diversification requires an empirically robust hypothesis about the underlying genealogical patterns - the spider tree of life. Traditional anatomical and genetic methods have not yet produced a compelling answer to this problem, and thus our understanding of the evolution of this group is far from satisfactory. The researchers of this project will use new methods to gather genetic data to answer this long-standing question. The results of this research will be of interest to many biologists working on any comparative aspects of orb-weavers because it will provide the genomic resources and the fundamental comparative basis for studies on a broad diversity of topics (silk biology, sexual selection, venom evolution, etc.). This project will serve as a training platform for postdoctoral, graduate and undergraduate researchers. In addition, the project will produce a public exhibit at the Harvard Museum of Natural History that will explore the evolution and biology of orb-weaving spiders.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A team of three investigators, experts in arachnid systematics and with a long and productive history of research collaboration, will generate novel data through the sequencing of 120 transcriptomes and target capture approaches using modern DNA sequencing techniques for phylogenetic inference for a taxonomic sample of orbicularians that would include representatives of all 21 known families of orb-weavers and a diverse array of outgroups. These genomic data will be used to infer the family-level phylogenetic relationships of orb-weaving spiders using a diversity of analytical techniques. The PIs will also analyze a morphological matrix of 85 selected orbicularians largely based on extensive data already at hand. This project will use the results of the phylogenetic analyses to carry out comparative analyses of orb-weaver diversification and of web architecture evolution.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457539</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gonzalo</FirstName>
<LastName>Giribet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gonzalo Giribet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ggiribet@g.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174951473</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000174557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[26 Oxford Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6133</Code>
<Text>GoLife</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY SURVEYS &amp; INVENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~197732</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~292125</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A synergistic approach was used to study spider evolution through phylogenomics, comparative transcriptomics and lineage diversification analyses. The team, composed of the two PIs, up to three postdoctoral trainees, three doctoral trainees and two foreign collaborators in Norway and Spain obtained a large number of spiders and generated more than 150 transcriptomes using Illumina sequencing technologies. These data were analyzed in conjunction with legacy data and information about web architecture to investigate the origins and evolution of spider webs. The transcriptomic data were leveraged to investigate functional novelties that putatively drove spider diversification. The work completed has been published in major specialized and general journals<sup>1-4&nbsp;</sup>and some of our work has been featured in the popular press, including major newspapers around the US and abroad.&nbsp;</p> <p>The research conducted in this award needed fresh spider specimens for genomic and transcriptomic work, requiring field work in New Zealand, Australia, Costa Rica, Trinidad &amp; Tobago, Chile, Spain and the USA. All specimens and genetic materials are deposited in the Invertebrate Zoology collections of the Museum of Comparative Zoology, and the genetic data are publicly available through NCBI.</p> <p>In collaboration with the Harvard Museum of Natural History we produced an exhibit to disseminate our research to the general public, which opened on October 21st, 2107 (&ldquo;Orb-Weavers: Web Masters of the Spider World&rdquo;). Some of the exhibit materials, including photographs, videos and interviews, are available on line (<a href="https://hmnh.harvard.edu/orb-weavers-web-masters-spider-world">https://hmnh.harvard.edu/orb-weavers-web-masters-spider-world</a>).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>References:</strong></p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">1&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Dimitrov, D.<em>et al.</em>Rounding up the usual suspects: a standard target-gene approach for resolving the interfamilial phylogenetic relationships of ecribellate orb-weaving spiders with a new family-rank classification (Araneae, Araneoidea).&nbsp;<em>Cladistics</em><strong>33</strong>, 221-250, doi:10.1111/cla.12165 (2017).</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">2&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Huang, D.<em>et al.</em>Origin of spiders and their spinning organs illuminated by mid-Cretaceous amber fossils.&nbsp;<em>Nat. Ecol. Evo.</em><strong>2</strong>, 623-627, doi:10.1038/s41559-018-0475-9 (2018).</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">3&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Fern&aacute;ndez, R.<em>et al.</em>Phylogenomics, diversification dynamics and comparative transcriptomics across the Spider Tree of Life.&nbsp;<em>Curr. Biol.</em>(in press).</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">4&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Kallal, R. J., Fern&aacute;ndez, R., Giribet, G. &amp; Hormiga, G. A phylotranscriptomic backbone of the orb-weaving spider family Araneidae (Arachnida, Araneae) supported by multiple methodological approaches.&nbsp;<em>Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.</em>(in press).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Gonzalo&nbsp;Giribet</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A synergistic approach was used to study spider evolution through phylogenomics, comparative transcriptomics and lineage diversification analyses. The team, composed of the two PIs, up to three postdoctoral trainees, three doctoral trainees and two foreign collaborators in Norway and Spain obtained a large number of spiders and generated more than 150 transcriptomes using Illumina sequencing technologies. These data were analyzed in conjunction with legacy data and information about web architecture to investigate the origins and evolution of spider webs. The transcriptomic data were leveraged to investigate functional novelties that putatively drove spider diversification. The work completed has been published in major specialized and general journals1-4 and some of our work has been featured in the popular press, including major newspapers around the US and abroad.   The research conducted in this award needed fresh spider specimens for genomic and transcriptomic work, requiring field work in New Zealand, Australia, Costa Rica, Trinidad &amp; Tobago, Chile, Spain and the USA. All specimens and genetic materials are deposited in the Invertebrate Zoology collections of the Museum of Comparative Zoology, and the genetic data are publicly available through NCBI.  In collaboration with the Harvard Museum of Natural History we produced an exhibit to disseminate our research to the general public, which opened on October 21st, 2107 ("Orb-Weavers: Web Masters of the Spider World"). Some of the exhibit materials, including photographs, videos and interviews, are available on line (https://hmnh.harvard.edu/orb-weavers-web-masters-spider-world).     References: 1                Dimitrov, D.et al.Rounding up the usual suspects: a standard target-gene approach for resolving the interfamilial phylogenetic relationships of ecribellate orb-weaving spiders with a new family-rank classification (Araneae, Araneoidea). Cladistics33, 221-250, doi:10.1111/cla.12165 (2017). 2                Huang, D.et al.Origin of spiders and their spinning organs illuminated by mid-Cretaceous amber fossils. Nat. Ecol. Evo.2, 623-627, doi:10.1038/s41559-018-0475-9 (2018). 3                Fern&aacute;ndez, R.et al.Phylogenomics, diversification dynamics and comparative transcriptomics across the Spider Tree of Life. Curr. Biol.(in press). 4                Kallal, R. J., Fern&aacute;ndez, R., Giribet, G. &amp; Hormiga, G. A phylotranscriptomic backbone of the orb-weaving spider family Araneidae (Arachnida, Araneae) supported by multiple methodological approaches. Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.(in press).             Last Modified: 04/06/2018       Submitted by: Gonzalo Giribet]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
