<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GENSIPS 2014: Workshop on Genomic Signal Processing and Statistics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computational systems biology is a multi-disciplinary research area that combines biology, computer science, engineering and statistics. The goal of this research area is to develop and apply computational methods for analyzing of complex biological phenomena. The 2014 IEEE Workshop on Genomic Signal Processing and Statistics (GENSIPS) aims to bring together expertise in biology, computer science, signal processing, engineering and statistics, and provide a forum to discuss challenges confronting the research community. GENSIPS'14 teamed up with the 2014 IEEE Global Conference on Signal and Information Processing (GlobalSIP'14), a flagship conference in IEEE Signal Processing Society that brings together 13 symposia and 2 workshops. GENSIPS is one of the two workshops, and is synergistic to symposiums on algorithms, big data and machine learning. Such a partnership is anticipated to foster collaborations and interdisciplinary research ideas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The theme of GENSIPS-14 is going to be centered around computational systems biology and signal processing. One major goal is to provide a forum for addressing research problems at the forefront of this area, including next-generation sequencing, integration of multi-modality genomics data, modeling of regulatory and signaling networks, single-cell analysis, metagenomics, and several other topics in this fast growing field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The partnership with GlobalSIP-14 attracts participations from the signal processing society. To enable signal processing researcher to jump-start in computational systems biology, GENSIPS-14 offers three tutorials on drug effect prediction, single-cell analysis, and imaging informatics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Another important mission of GENSIPS-14 is to promote the participation of graduate students and post-doctoral researchers (especially women and minority), and foster education and development of the next-generation scientists in computational systems biology. GENSIPS-14 will provide travel awards to encourage graduate students to participate. Specifically, 20-30% of the awards will be allocated to encourage women and minority students to participate and submit papers to GENSIPS-14.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457664</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dongmei</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dongmei Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maywang@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043852954</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yufei</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yufei Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Yufei.Huang@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2103479320</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506552</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peng</FirstName>
<LastName>Qiu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peng Qiu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peng.qiu@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043851656</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000634648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Computational systems biology is a highly multi-disciplinary research area that aims to develop and use mathematical and statistical tools for systematic analysis of complex biological phenomena. In contrast to the reductionist approach of traditional experiment-centric biomedical research, systems biology uses a holistic approach and relies on iterations between biological experiments and computational modeling. &nbsp;To address research challenges and foster student education in this interdisciplinary area, the IEEE Workshop on Genomic Signal Processing and Statistics 2014 (GENSIPS&rsquo;14) aims to bridge and stimulate synergistic activities in biology, computer science, engineering and statistics. The research focus for GENSIPS&rsquo;14 included: next-generation sequencing, multi-modality omics data integration, regulatory and signaling networks modeling, imaging and genomics, single-cell analysis, etc. To increase participation and collaboration, GENSIPS'14 teamed up with GlobalSIP'14, a flagship conference of IEEE Signal Processing Society that brought together 13 symposia and 2 workshops. Such a partnership enabled GENSIPS'14 to attract more participation in the signal processing community. Another goal of GENSIPS&rsquo;14 was to promote participation of graduate students and post-doctoral researchers, especial woman and minority students, and foster student education on systems biology<strong>. </strong>This grant was awarded to support GENSIPS&rsquo;14.&nbsp; The award was used to provide travel awards to 14 students to supplement their travel expenses to attend GENSIPS&rsquo;14. Among the awardees, 3 were women students. This National Science Foundation award has made significant impact on the student attendance and help foster student research and education. Papers in GENSIPS&rsquo;14 were published in the GlobalSIP'14 conference proceedings, and selected papers were invited to submit to IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics and EURASIP Journal on Bioinformatics and Systems Biology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2015<br>      Modified by: Peng&nbsp;Qiu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Computational systems biology is a highly multi-disciplinary research area that aims to develop and use mathematical and statistical tools for systematic analysis of complex biological phenomena. In contrast to the reductionist approach of traditional experiment-centric biomedical research, systems biology uses a holistic approach and relies on iterations between biological experiments and computational modeling.  To address research challenges and foster student education in this interdisciplinary area, the IEEE Workshop on Genomic Signal Processing and Statistics 2014 (GENSIPSÆ14) aims to bridge and stimulate synergistic activities in biology, computer science, engineering and statistics. The research focus for GENSIPSÆ14 included: next-generation sequencing, multi-modality omics data integration, regulatory and signaling networks modeling, imaging and genomics, single-cell analysis, etc. To increase participation and collaboration, GENSIPS'14 teamed up with GlobalSIP'14, a flagship conference of IEEE Signal Processing Society that brought together 13 symposia and 2 workshops. Such a partnership enabled GENSIPS'14 to attract more participation in the signal processing community. Another goal of GENSIPSÆ14 was to promote participation of graduate students and post-doctoral researchers, especial woman and minority students, and foster student education on systems biology. This grant was awarded to support GENSIPSÆ14.  The award was used to provide travel awards to 14 students to supplement their travel expenses to attend GENSIPSÆ14. Among the awardees, 3 were women students. This National Science Foundation award has made significant impact on the student attendance and help foster student research and education. Papers in GENSIPSÆ14 were published in the GlobalSIP'14 conference proceedings, and selected papers were invited to submit to IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics and EURASIP Journal on Bioinformatics and Systems Biology.          Last Modified: 12/18/2015       Submitted by: Peng Qiu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
