<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using replicated empirical networks to understand drivers of ecosystem structure and stability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>508751.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>547149</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Science still does not understand the basic drivers of ecosystem structure (e.g., complexity) or how an ecosystem's structure affects its ability to resist disturbance. Understanding these relationships is necessary for predicting the response of ecosystems to many kinds of disruption (e.g. species extinction, invasion, habitat loss). This conceptual shortcoming thus prevents the efficient use of scarce conservation resources by limiting our ability to identify and conserve systems most sensitive to human disturbance. By comparing ecosystem structure across a series of islands that vary in ecosystem size and productivity - this project will examine the extent to which these basic properties drive ecosystem structure and how that structure determines ecosystem stability. This work should lead to broad management insight on the importance of environmental characteristics in determining the impact of species removals and invasions. This project will train multiple graduate students, undergraduates, and a postdoctoral researcher, with a focus on underrepresented groups. Furthermore, through partnerships with the university Kids in Nature program, the researchers will also engage grade school children, and train elementary school teachers in ecology and invasive species. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ecological complexity makes it difficult to identify general patterns in nature, such as community stability. To understand what drives stability, one could measure changes in systems over time across environmental gradients. Another approach has been to consider how system structure affects community stability. However, it is unlikely that structure and environmental gradients are independent, because environmental factors might alter system structure as well as their stability. To understand how ecosystem size and productivity influences ecosystem stability, 23 high-resolution food-webs from a series of Pacific islets that vary independently in size and productivity will be assembled and compared. A suite of mathematical modeling approaches will then create predictions for how variation in food-web structure affects food-web stability. These model-generated predictions of stability will then be tested against observed changes in food-web structure before and after the removal of a common omnivore, the rat (Rattus rattus). These results can then be used to evaluate the relative importance of ecosystem size, productivity, and food-web structure, in predicting system stability. Cumulatively, these efforts will help identify not only how environmental characteristics structure communities but also the extent to which they drive system-level responses to perturbation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457371</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lafferty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin D Lafferty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lafferty@lifesci.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058938778</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472722</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hillary</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hillary S Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hillary.young@lifesci.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058934681</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000657133</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marine Science Institute]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931066150</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~508751</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20392</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~10096</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~7910</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Earth?s life generating systems are undergoing big, fast changes. Scientists are trying to figure out how to predict what is going to happen to these systems as they change. This is challenging because of the complexity of living systems. Complex systems are characterized by synergy - when you put two or more parts together the resulting product often has properties none of the parts possessed. Oxygen and Hydrogen are a good analogy. Both are gasses but combine them through combustion and you get liquid water. Living systems are like water, in that it?s hard to predict how they will behave from just a list of ingredients. The tools that we use to figure out how simple mechanistic systems work don?t do well when systems are complex, so we have to create new tools. Networks are one of the most promising tools being developed to understand complex ecological systems. A network contains a list of the ingredients (in this case, the organisms) and their interactions with each other. Networks are useful because they provide lots of ways to measure whole systems, which is necessary for predicting their stability in the face of change.</p> <p>What makes systems stable is an open question in ecology. It is a critical question because stable systems are more likely to keep providing services in the face of changes like nutrient pollution and habitat destruction. Even stable systems, when pushed too far, can collapse, losing species and halting the provision of services; however stable systems are more resilient to these forms of changes. Ecologists use food-web networks to understand when systems might collapse and potentially how to fix them. Food webs function like ecological maps by tracing the flow energy through systems along a network of who-eats-who. Using these maps, ecologists have identified structures that appear to be important for stability. However, we still do not know what creates these important structures, where they are likely to be found, or if they really matter for stability. For example, a system?s context, such as its size (large lake vs small lake), temperature (tropical vs arctic) and habitat type (e.g. mountain top vs. ocean bottom) are all likely to drive differences in structure, but we don?t have enough studies to understand these relationships. Taken together, this limits our ability to use our most promising predictive tool effectively. This project addressed these shortcomings in our understanding by linking context to network structure and network structure to stability.</p> <p>We have assembled food webs for tropical forests on 16 islands at Palmyra Atoll. Palmyra Atoll is a remote and uninhabited National Wildlife Refuge about 1000 miles south of Hawaii. The atoll is made up of several different sized islands (from backyard-sized to big enough to hold a mile-long runway) that also have different nutrient levels available to plants. Building food webs for different islands allows us to determine how their size (a stand-in for habitat loss) and productivity (a stand-in for nutrient pollution) affect network structure. Next, we have been exploring how network structures affect stability, by examining how the different islands have responded to the successful removal of rats (a proxy for species loss). Finally, we are testing how good our models are at predicting the behavior of complex systems by comparing their results for the effects of rat removals to our empirical observations.</p> <p>The networks we have assembled are the most detailed ecological maps ever made for anywhere on Earth. To assemble them we have figured out not only what species are present, but how many individuals of each species are on each island. This is challenging but is allowing us to test almost a wide range of models to understand which best predict stability in real systems. To get this level of detail for each island we conducted a lot of sampling in a lot of places. We used over a dozen different sampling methods at over 435 sites, conducted more than 2km of transects with 1 cm resolution for understory plants, fogging the canopies of 112 individual trees for arthropods and identifying more than 300,000 individual arthropods comprising more than 350 species. Over the course of the project we have documented species extinctions (Asian Tiger Mosquito), species invasions (Yellow-faced Bee) and discovered 20 species that are new to science. Our progress was delayed by COVID-19 but we are adapting and continuing to publish our results.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016081437_IMG_5393--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016081437_IMG_5393--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Canopy Fogging"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016081437_IMG_5393--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Canopy Fogging"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Postdoctoral researcher fogging the canopy of a Coconut Palm with an insecticide fog. The Teflon coated cones below will collect insects that fall from the canopy. We fogged 112 individual trees at Palmyra to adequately capture their insect communities.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ana Miller-ter Kuile</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</div> <div class="imageTitle">Canopy Fogging</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016294410_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016294410_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Understanding network changes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016294410_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Understanding network changes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The impact of rats (red node) on the small but highly connected network from Palmyra Atoll. Red lines indicate the species that the rats feed on. Plants are at the bottom and predators are at the top. Removing rats from islands provided an opportunity to understand how networks respond to change.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. McLaughlin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</div> <div class="imageTitle">Understanding network changes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016387425_G0030235--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016387425_G0030235--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Assembling the network"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016387425_G0030235--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Assembling the network"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF REUs and a graduate students collecting soil cores for microbial analysis and sampling the understory and of a native forest at Palmyra Atoll.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. McLaughlin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</div> <div class="imageTitle">Assembling the network</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016517724_IMG_5365--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016517724_IMG_5365--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Berlese funnels"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016517724_IMG_5365--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Berlese funnels"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Some of the 120 Berlese funnels used to extract arthropods from vegetation and soil samples.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ana Miller-ter Kuile</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</div> <div class="imageTitle">Berlese funnels</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016595577_IMG_5407--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016595577_IMG_5407--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Branch Clipping"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604016595577_IMG_5407--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Branch Clipping"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prof. Rodolfo Dirzo (Stanford University) sampling a Cocos Palm frond with a pole saw.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ana Miller-ter Kuile</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</div> <div class="imageTitle">Branch Clipping</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604017405792_ScreenShot2020-10-24at8.42.59PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604017405792_ScreenShot2020-10-24at8.42.59PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="New Species at Palmyra"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1457371/1457371_10362011_1604017405792_ScreenShot2020-10-24at8.42.59PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="New Species at Palmyra"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Undescribed species at Palmyra. All scale bars are 1 mm. (A) a common cricket, (B) nymph, male and female thrips, (C) a picture-wing fly, (D) a cream-colored cockroach, (E) a striped springtail, (F) a barklouse, (G) a common isopod.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. McLaughlin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hillary&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</div> <div class="imageTitle">New Species at Palmyra</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Earth?s life generating systems are undergoing big, fast changes. Scientists are trying to figure out how to predict what is going to happen to these systems as they change. This is challenging because of the complexity of living systems. Complex systems are characterized by synergy - when you put two or more parts together the resulting product often has properties none of the parts possessed. Oxygen and Hydrogen are a good analogy. Both are gasses but combine them through combustion and you get liquid water. Living systems are like water, in that it?s hard to predict how they will behave from just a list of ingredients. The tools that we use to figure out how simple mechanistic systems work don?t do well when systems are complex, so we have to create new tools. Networks are one of the most promising tools being developed to understand complex ecological systems. A network contains a list of the ingredients (in this case, the organisms) and their interactions with each other. Networks are useful because they provide lots of ways to measure whole systems, which is necessary for predicting their stability in the face of change.  What makes systems stable is an open question in ecology. It is a critical question because stable systems are more likely to keep providing services in the face of changes like nutrient pollution and habitat destruction. Even stable systems, when pushed too far, can collapse, losing species and halting the provision of services; however stable systems are more resilient to these forms of changes. Ecologists use food-web networks to understand when systems might collapse and potentially how to fix them. Food webs function like ecological maps by tracing the flow energy through systems along a network of who-eats-who. Using these maps, ecologists have identified structures that appear to be important for stability. However, we still do not know what creates these important structures, where they are likely to be found, or if they really matter for stability. For example, a system?s context, such as its size (large lake vs small lake), temperature (tropical vs arctic) and habitat type (e.g. mountain top vs. ocean bottom) are all likely to drive differences in structure, but we don?t have enough studies to understand these relationships. Taken together, this limits our ability to use our most promising predictive tool effectively. This project addressed these shortcomings in our understanding by linking context to network structure and network structure to stability.  We have assembled food webs for tropical forests on 16 islands at Palmyra Atoll. Palmyra Atoll is a remote and uninhabited National Wildlife Refuge about 1000 miles south of Hawaii. The atoll is made up of several different sized islands (from backyard-sized to big enough to hold a mile-long runway) that also have different nutrient levels available to plants. Building food webs for different islands allows us to determine how their size (a stand-in for habitat loss) and productivity (a stand-in for nutrient pollution) affect network structure. Next, we have been exploring how network structures affect stability, by examining how the different islands have responded to the successful removal of rats (a proxy for species loss). Finally, we are testing how good our models are at predicting the behavior of complex systems by comparing their results for the effects of rat removals to our empirical observations.  The networks we have assembled are the most detailed ecological maps ever made for anywhere on Earth. To assemble them we have figured out not only what species are present, but how many individuals of each species are on each island. This is challenging but is allowing us to test almost a wide range of models to understand which best predict stability in real systems. To get this level of detail for each island we conducted a lot of sampling in a lot of places. We used over a dozen different sampling methods at over 435 sites, conducted more than 2km of transects with 1 cm resolution for understory plants, fogging the canopies of 112 individual trees for arthropods and identifying more than 300,000 individual arthropods comprising more than 350 species. Over the course of the project we have documented species extinctions (Asian Tiger Mosquito), species invasions (Yellow-faced Bee) and discovered 20 species that are new to science. Our progress was delayed by COVID-19 but we are adapting and continuing to publish our results.       Last Modified: 10/29/2020       Submitted by: Hillary S Young]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
