<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WiFiUS: Collaborative Research: Future Small-Cell Networks Using Reconfigurable Antennas</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90161.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90161</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The future proliferation of wireless systems and services is dependent on the design of flexible radio architectures that can adapt to the rapidly changing wireless environment. Since usable spectrum is limited, and modulation and coding techniques are approaching their Shannon capacity limitation, improving capacity through increased spectrum reuse and interference mitigation has become a high priority in future cellular networks. Industry leaders have focused on a multi-tiered heterogeneous network structure, where small-cell (e.g., pico-cell, femto-cell) base stations are deployed to meet capacity demand. Among the technical challenges making full-scale deployment of small-cell base stations possible, interference management still looms the largest. This project focuses on providing wireless systems with the available hardware and algorithmic tools to make intelligent decisions about antenna configuration for small-cell base stations to mitigate interference and improve network capacity and coexistence in a heterogeneous network environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is composed of three main research thrusts: i.) Algorithm and System Design; ii.) Antenna and Transceiver Design; and iii.) Testbed Implementation. The first focus is on the mathematical modeling and overall system design of small-cell networks making use of reconfigurable antennas. A vital component of this overall system design is the development of efficient and effective analytical tools and algorithms for downlink transmission, focusing on directional network design, algorithms for directionality selection, and base station user association. The second thrust includes the development of practical reconfigurable antennas and transceiver processing techniques for small-cell base stations. The project team is adapting reconfigurable metamaterial and alford loop antenna designs to provide new, compact reconfigurable antenna architectures with both beam steering and variable beam width capabilities. Using these new antenna technologies this research enhances direction of arrival and digital pre-distortion techniques for enhanced small-cell uplink and downlink. The cornerstone of this research is the design of a fully implemented, programmable across-the-stack SDR platform with integrated reconfigurable antennas. This project makes use of open-source technologies and will result in the deployment of a fully functional cellular backbone system, consisting of both macro-cell and small-cell base stations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project leverages collaboration between Drexel University and WPI, along with a strong international collaboration with the University of Oulu, VTT Technical Research Centre and Tampere University of Technology. This ongoing collaboration with Finnish institutions continues to provide novel international research experiences for undergraduate and graduate students as well as pilot testing for dissemination of the developed testbed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Wyglinski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Wyglinski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alexw@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5088315061</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000089529</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041508581</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WORCESTER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041508581</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Worcester Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Worcester</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016092280</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Institute Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8229</Code>
<Text>WiFiUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~90161</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The future of wireless systems and services is dependent on the design of flexible radio architectures that can adapt to the rapidly changing wireless environment.&nbsp; To enable the evolution of these systems, the wireless sector has focused on a multi-tiered heterogeneous network structure such that small-cell (e.g., pico-cell, femto-cell) base stations can meet capacity demand.&nbsp; To resolve technological challenges associated with this structure, enhancements to direction of arrival (DoA) and new digital pre-distorion techniques for enhanced small-cell uplink and downlink need to be devised.<br />Furthermore, to assess the viability of these solutions, real world experimentation via fully implemented, programmable across-the-stack SDR platform with integrated reconfigurable antennas are needed. This project leveraged models, algorithms, and design insights in order to develop practical transceiver signal processing algorithms for direction of arrival (DoA) estimation-enhanced uplink and digital pre-distortion-enhanced downlink to minimize interference seen by other users in the network. Furthermore, international US-Finnish joint development and demonstration of the technology created during this project was conducted using a software defined radio (SDR) implementation.&nbsp; Specifically, the international research team from the US and Finland worked together and focused on the implementation of direction finding algorithms using SDR hardware in order to provide a realistic and representative scenario for the localization and tracking of real-world targets, especially in indoor environments.&nbsp; Replacing commonly used Cramer-Rao bounds for estimation, which often ignores real-world effects such as antenna placement, non-ideal antenna elements, receiver phase misalignment, and antenna coupling, the joint US/Finnish research team first focused on a baseline implementation using traditional phased array processing techniques in order to provide representative DoA performance metrics, followed by an alternative DoA estimation approach.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Wyglinski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320342370_pegboard_array_ant--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320342370_pegboard_array_ant--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hardware SDR Testbed"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320342370_pegboard_array_ant--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hardware SDR Testbed"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Pegboard array setup with single transmitting USRP-N210 with two receiving arrays each connected to a USRP-X310. A second pegboard is bolted to the original to provide additional azimuth angles to test over.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Travis Collins</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;Wyglinski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hardware SDR Testbed</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320419830_music_flowgraph--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320419830_music_flowgraph--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MUSIC GNU Radio Flowgraph"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320419830_music_flowgraph--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MUSIC GNU Radio Flowgraph"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GNURadio flowgraph of MUSIC algorithm with attached SDR hardware with four receive chains. The "Phase Correct" block provides correction across the daughterboards, and the additional QT blocks are for visualization.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Travis Collins</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;Wyglinski</div> <div class="imageTitle">MUSIC GNU Radio Flowgraph</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320478903_OFDM_Receiver-crop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320478903_OFDM_Receiver-crop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="OFDM Receiver"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1457310/1457310_10350451_1514320478903_OFDM_Receiver-crop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="OFDM Receiver"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">OFDM SIMO receiver structure for the GNURadio implementation. Four chains are used for signal reception and recovery, with only a single chain generating estimates across all remaining chains to maintain coherence between those chains.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Travis Collins</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;Wyglinski</div> <div class="imageTitle">OFDM Receiver</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The future of wireless systems and services is dependent on the design of flexible radio architectures that can adapt to the rapidly changing wireless environment.  To enable the evolution of these systems, the wireless sector has focused on a multi-tiered heterogeneous network structure such that small-cell (e.g., pico-cell, femto-cell) base stations can meet capacity demand.  To resolve technological challenges associated with this structure, enhancements to direction of arrival (DoA) and new digital pre-distorion techniques for enhanced small-cell uplink and downlink need to be devised. Furthermore, to assess the viability of these solutions, real world experimentation via fully implemented, programmable across-the-stack SDR platform with integrated reconfigurable antennas are needed. This project leveraged models, algorithms, and design insights in order to develop practical transceiver signal processing algorithms for direction of arrival (DoA) estimation-enhanced uplink and digital pre-distortion-enhanced downlink to minimize interference seen by other users in the network. Furthermore, international US-Finnish joint development and demonstration of the technology created during this project was conducted using a software defined radio (SDR) implementation.  Specifically, the international research team from the US and Finland worked together and focused on the implementation of direction finding algorithms using SDR hardware in order to provide a realistic and representative scenario for the localization and tracking of real-world targets, especially in indoor environments.  Replacing commonly used Cramer-Rao bounds for estimation, which often ignores real-world effects such as antenna placement, non-ideal antenna elements, receiver phase misalignment, and antenna coupling, the joint US/Finnish research team first focused on a baseline implementation using traditional phased array processing techniques in order to provide representative DoA performance metrics, followed by an alternative DoA estimation approach.       Last Modified: 12/26/2017       Submitted by: Alexander Wyglinski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
