<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Impact of selection pressure for social behavior on canid brain evolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>532390.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>532390</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edda Thiels</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ethiels@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928167</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate features of neural system organization that can be linked to altered social behavior, including reduced or increased aggression.  Two species of canids, experimentally domesticated silver foxes (Vulpes vulpes) and domestic dogs (Canis familiaris), have been selectively bred by humans for altered social behavior.  These behavioral changes occurred alongside a restricted set of genetic changes, creating an unparalleled opportunity to link the evolution of behavioral characteristics (phenotypes) to neural phenotypes.  Recent technological advancements enable detailed, non-invasive studies of brain anatomy at relatively low cost.  This project will take advantage of these innovations to create high-resolution three-dimensional (3D) brain maps using structural magnetic resonance imaging, diffusion tensor imaging, and digitized histology.  Expected products of this research include: (1) identification of features of neural organization that are linked to reduced or increased sociality or aggression, expected to be generalizable to other species, (2) the production of online fox and dog brain atlases that will be publicly available as a research tool for the general scientific community, (3) training opportunities for young scientists, and (4) outreach efforts using blog and social media posts for the general public.   Because dogs are a "common denominator" across various cultures, this research has a unique opportunity to be personally relevant and compelling to people from all walks of society, and to enhance public appreciation for science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Both experimentally-domesticated foxes and domestic dogs are distinguished from their wild forebears by altered social approach-avoidance behavior.  Previous research in rodents and primates, and the researchers' own preliminary data, allow for the formation of well-grounded hypotheses about neural adaptations that result from selection pressure on social approach-avoidance behavior.  Specifically, this project will investigate limbic and fronto-limbic systems governing social behavior and response selection.  In order to identify features of neural system organization associated with altered social behavior, whole-brain white and gray matter organization will be compared (a) between various breeds of domestic dogs, each tested for social approach-avoidance/aggression behavior, and (b) between strains of foxes bred for social avoidance behavior, which react aggressively to social contact, versus foxes bred for social approach behavior, which are tame and friendly like dogs, versus wild type foxes.  Whole-brain MRI and DTI images will be collected using 3.0 and 9.4 Tesla MRI scanners.  Histology images will be digitally scanned and aligned to MRI images.  Analyses will include voxel-based morphometry, tract-based spatial statistics, probabilistic tractography, and k-means connectivity-based parcellation.  The research will advance knowledge about how evolution modified brain organization in response to selection for social approach and avoidance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457291</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Preuss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd M Preuss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tpreuss@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4047128159</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000207564</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Sakai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharleen T Sakai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sakai@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173538889</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000443313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Hecht</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erin Hecht</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>erin_hecht@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173848642</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000510736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Gutman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Gutman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dgutman@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4047272503</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000603230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
<LastName>Kent</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marc Kent</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mkent1@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065425939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675467</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1599-001-1BA]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMORY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303294208</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[954 Gatewood Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~532390</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the major challenges of modern neuroscience is understanding how brain organization gives rise to behavior.&nbsp; This research examined this question using two &ldquo;natural experiments&rdquo; where differences in brain anatomy can be tied to specific, known differences in behavior.&nbsp; One of these is domestic dogs (<em>Canis familiaris</em>), where different breeds have been selectively bred by humans for different behaviors, like hunting, herding, and guarding.&nbsp; The other is experimentally domesticated silver foxes (<em>Vulpes vulpes</em>).&nbsp; One strain of foxes has been selectively bred for tameness; they seek out human contact, lick, whine, bark, wag their tails, and can be kept as pets.&nbsp; This parallels the evolution of dogs from wolves.&nbsp; Other strains of foxes have been bred for avoidance of human contact (the opposite of tameness), or are kept on the farm and bred without selection for any particular behavior.&nbsp; In order to investigate differences in brain organization related to differences in behavior between dog breeds and fox strains, this research used neuroimaging, behavior tests, histology, and microscopy.&nbsp; Results from this research to date have found that different breeds of dogs do indeed show differences in brain organization which cannot be wholly explained by differences in body size or head shape, but do appear to be related to breed-specialized behavior like hunting, herding, and companionship.&nbsp; Further, preliminary results in foxes indicate that selection on social behavior (tameness) has produced differences in the anatomy and connectivity of limbic-prefrontal circuits.&nbsp; The phylogenetic approach taken here, in contrast to typical within-species lesion and pharmacological studies, is able inform not only our understanding of which structures are involved in different behaviors, but also our understanding of how evolution modifies those structures in response to specific pressures.&nbsp; Additionally, a number of undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral researchers benefited from scientific training during participation in this research.&nbsp; Results have been disseminated both to the scientific community, in the form of journal articles and conference presentations, and to the general public, in the form of press releases, media interviews, and online web articles.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit.&nbsp; </strong>The proposed research has advanced knowledge about how evolution modified brain organization in response to selection for different, specific behaviors. Our approach uniquely evaluates brain-behavior relationships in 2 carnivore species not typically studied.&nbsp; The research team was ideally qualified for this work, with expertise in mammalian and canid neuroanatomy, histology, neuroimaging, and bioinformatics.&nbsp; Unique resources were utilized, including a 9.4 Tesla MRI scanner able to collect images with spatial resolution several hundred-fold better than typical human scans (100-300 cubic microns, on the order of a cortical column); a parallel supercomputing cluster for data analysis and web hosting; fixed brains of behaviorally characterized selectively-bred foxes; and an unusually high-resolution veterinary research scanner for collecting <em>in vivo</em> dog MRI images.&nbsp; Furthermore, this approach enabled the detailed study of brains in an unprecedentedly large number of behaviorally characterized individuals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Erin&nbsp;Hecht</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the major challenges of modern neuroscience is understanding how brain organization gives rise to behavior.  This research examined this question using two "natural experiments" where differences in brain anatomy can be tied to specific, known differences in behavior.  One of these is domestic dogs (Canis familiaris), where different breeds have been selectively bred by humans for different behaviors, like hunting, herding, and guarding.  The other is experimentally domesticated silver foxes (Vulpes vulpes).  One strain of foxes has been selectively bred for tameness; they seek out human contact, lick, whine, bark, wag their tails, and can be kept as pets.  This parallels the evolution of dogs from wolves.  Other strains of foxes have been bred for avoidance of human contact (the opposite of tameness), or are kept on the farm and bred without selection for any particular behavior.  In order to investigate differences in brain organization related to differences in behavior between dog breeds and fox strains, this research used neuroimaging, behavior tests, histology, and microscopy.  Results from this research to date have found that different breeds of dogs do indeed show differences in brain organization which cannot be wholly explained by differences in body size or head shape, but do appear to be related to breed-specialized behavior like hunting, herding, and companionship.  Further, preliminary results in foxes indicate that selection on social behavior (tameness) has produced differences in the anatomy and connectivity of limbic-prefrontal circuits.  The phylogenetic approach taken here, in contrast to typical within-species lesion and pharmacological studies, is able inform not only our understanding of which structures are involved in different behaviors, but also our understanding of how evolution modifies those structures in response to specific pressures.  Additionally, a number of undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral researchers benefited from scientific training during participation in this research.  Results have been disseminated both to the scientific community, in the form of journal articles and conference presentations, and to the general public, in the form of press releases, media interviews, and online web articles.     Intellectual Merit.  The proposed research has advanced knowledge about how evolution modified brain organization in response to selection for different, specific behaviors. Our approach uniquely evaluates brain-behavior relationships in 2 carnivore species not typically studied.  The research team was ideally qualified for this work, with expertise in mammalian and canid neuroanatomy, histology, neuroimaging, and bioinformatics.  Unique resources were utilized, including a 9.4 Tesla MRI scanner able to collect images with spatial resolution several hundred-fold better than typical human scans (100-300 cubic microns, on the order of a cortical column); a parallel supercomputing cluster for data analysis and web hosting; fixed brains of behaviorally characterized selectively-bred foxes; and an unusually high-resolution veterinary research scanner for collecting in vivo dog MRI images.  Furthermore, this approach enabled the detailed study of brains in an unprecedentedly large number of behaviorally characterized individuals.          Last Modified: 11/03/2019       Submitted by: Erin Hecht]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
