<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The role of habitat transitions in parallel marine fish radiations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397896.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>436784</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fish diversity spans high-performance swimmers such as tunas, barracudas, and swordfish that spend their entire life cruising the open ocean in search of food (pelagic species) to sluggish, sedentary forms such as flounders or seahorses that live buried in the bottom or attached to vegetation (benthic species). Much variation in body form and habit can be explained by adaptation to the habitats where these fishes live. But the effects of ecological habitat on processes leading to diversification over evolutionary time remain poorly explored. This project will focus on two groups of closely related species that harbor a huge diversity of benthic and pelagic forms (about 2000 species) to disentangle the effects of habitat transitions on rates of speciation and extinction. Understanding the factors that promote diversification in form and habit is important for the long-term conservation of marine biodiversity. Innovative image data analysis necessary to synthesize morphological variation among these fishes also will be applied to develop a fish species identification app for smartphones (FishSnap) that will be freely available to the public, expandable in the future to include all fishes. Educational opportunities will be available for undergraduate and graduate students and outreach activities in partnership with the National Museum of Natural History in Washington DC will result in a new public exhibit on fish biodiversity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent studies in fish phylogenetics are resolving long-lasting uncertainties about the relationships among the most species-rich marine fish groups, and opening up unprecedented opportunities to infer mechanisms that explain their extraordinary diversity. This project takes advantage of newly discovered affinities among fishes that revealed two independent clades with benthic and pelagic forms to investigate connections between genomic and morphological features in relation to their ecological habitat. The researchers will collect and compare a genome-scale DNA sequence data set of protein-coding genes to infer a phylogenetic tree for about 800 species of these two groups. This tree will be time-calibrated on the basis of carefully selected fossil data to provide a dated evolutionary framework for comparative studies. The project will also assemble a large phenotypic (digital image) dataset of curated specimens for morphometric analysis. Using state-of-the art comparative methodologies, this project will shed light on the effect of habitat shifts along the benthic-pelagic axis on the rate of morphological and lineage diversification. The integration of well-resolved molecular phylogenies, the fossil record, trait and ecological data, and comparative methodologies will provide new insights to understand the causes of marine biodiversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1457426</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guillermo</FirstName>
<LastName>Orti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guillermo Orti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>guilleorti@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029947065</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000169174</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200521000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2023 G Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>075Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Maria 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~397896</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~38888</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merit: </strong>This project had two major goals, (i) inference of taxonomically-dense phylogenies using genome-wide data for several clades of percomorph fishes that include some of the best-known fishes, such as tunas, flounders, billfishes, jacks, silversides, and snappers, as well as charismatic ones, such as sea horses, and trumpetfishes, (ii) use of the newly-generated phylogenetic trees to map organismal traits and ecological data layers using state-of-the art comparative methodologies to study how habitat shifts (benthic to pelagic, marine to freshwater), geological events,&nbsp; and biogeography have shaped morphological diversity and biodiversity in these groups.</p> <p>Outcomes of the first objective include newly inferred phylogenomic trees (based on 900-1,100 genes) for <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Lutjanidae</span> (snappers and fusiliers; 110 out of 136 species; Fig. 1), <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Pelagiaria</span> (tunas, mackerels, stromateoids, and allies; 150 out of 284 species; Fig. 2), <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Syngnatharia</span> (trumpetfishes, goatfishes, dragonets, flying gurnards, seahorses, pipefishes, and allies; 169 out of 320 species; Fig. 3), <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Carangaria</span> (flatfishes, jacks, barracudas, billfishes and allies; ~700 out of 1,100 species; work in progress, but see Fig. 4 for a preliminary analysis using ~20 genes), and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">South American silversides</span> (<em>Odontesthes</em>; 14 out of 19 species; Fig. 5).</p> <p>For the second aim, we examined evolutionary transitions along the benthic-pelagic axis (bottom dwellers versus open-water swimmers) in two of these clades: Lutjanidae and Carangaria. With Lutjanidae, we studied cases of convergent evolution along this ecological axis. Deep-bodied&nbsp;forms tend to occur in benthic habitats, while pelagic&nbsp;species typically have streamlined body plans.&nbsp;Body shape is a strong predictor of habitat occupation in fishes, which changes rapidly at micro-evolutionary scales&nbsp;in well-studied freshwater systems such as sticklebacks and cichlids. The recurrent evolution&nbsp;of this pattern across distantly related groups suggests that limited sets of high-fitness&nbsp;solutions exist due to environmental constraints. We rigorously tested these observations showing that similar constraints&nbsp;operate at deeper evolutionary scales in lutjanids, a clade of primarily benthic&nbsp;fish dwellers that&nbsp;repeatedly transitioned into midwater habitats in all major&nbsp;oceans throughout its 45-million-year history. Our results&nbsp;show independent incursions into the water column by ancestral benthic&nbsp;lineages in all major oceanic basins. These evolutionary transitions are persistently&nbsp;associated with convergent phenotypes, where&nbsp;deep-bodied benthic forms with&nbsp;truncate caudal fins repeatedly evolve into slender midwater species with furcate caudal fins.&nbsp;Lineage diversification and transition dynamics vary asymmetrically&nbsp;between&nbsp;habitats, with benthic lineages diversifying faster and&nbsp;colonizing midwater habitats more often than the reverse (Fig. 1, center plot).&nbsp;Convergent ecological and functional phenotypes along the&nbsp;benthic-pelagic axis&nbsp;are pervasive among different lineages and across vastly different&nbsp;evolutionary scales, achieving predictable high-fitness solutions for similar&nbsp;environmental challenges, ultimately demonstrating strong determinism&nbsp;in fish body-shape evolution.</p> <p>Carangaria comprises a disparate array of benthic and pelagic species (<em>ca.</em> 1100), including some of the most astonishing fish forms such as  flatfishes, billfishes, remoras, barracudas, and archerfishes (Fig. 4). Our goal was to assess how the Cretaceous-Paleogene mass exctinction (KP-G) affected the evolutionary dynamics in the group. Ecological opportunity arising in the aftermath of mass extinction is thought to provide ideal conditions for the onset of evolutionary radiations. We estimated a fossil-calibrated multi-locus time tree that includes all major lineages in this group and used a set of phylogenetic comparative approaches to investigate how rates of lineage diversification, multivariate morphological evolution, and habitat transitions vary throughout the history of the clade. Analyses of lineage diversification show time-heterogeneous rates of lineage diversification in carangarians, with highest rates reached during the Paleocene. Likewise, a remarkable proportion of Carangaria?s morphological variation originated early in the history of the group and in tandem with a marked incidence of habitat shifts (Fig. 4). Taken together, these results suggest that all major lineages and body plans in Carangaria originated in an early burst shortly after the K-Pg mass extinction, which ultimately allowed the occupation of newly released niches along the benthic-pelagic habitat axis.</p> <p>Marine-to-freshwater habitat transitions were studied in South American silverside fishes (genus <em>Odontesthes</em>, Atherinopsidae), a radiation of 19 marine and freshwater species. A robust phylogenetic framework (Fig. 5) showed that this group originally diversified in the Pacific but independently colonized the Atlantic three times, producing three separate marine-to-freshwater transitions. Comparative transcriptomics revealed inter-specific differences mapping to genes with a diversity of functions, suggesting that multiple abiotic and biotic factors in marine and freshwater habitats are driving genomic differences between these species.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts:</strong> Molecular markers and bioinformatics pipelines developed by this project are already being used in the scientific community to resolve phylogenies of many other groups of fishes, advancing fish systematics broadly. Human resource development (undergraduate and graduate student training, supervision of postdoctoral fellows) and establishment of international collaborations in the framework of the project also produced significant broader impacts. Co-PI Betancur and his collaborators developed an annual Latin American Macroevolution Workshop, which was offered in Puerto Rico (2016), Argentina (2017), and Mexico (2018).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/06/2021<br>      Modified by: Guillermo&nbsp;Orti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721112686_Fig1_Lutjanidae--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721112686_Fig1_Lutjanidae--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721112686_Fig1_Lutjanidae--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phylogenomics of Lutjanidae (snappers and fussiliers)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rincon Sandoval et al. 2020 (doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2006511117)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Guillermo&nbsp;Orti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721254277_Fig2_Pela--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721254277_Fig2_Pela--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721254277_Fig2_Pela--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phylogenomics of Pelagiaria (tunas, mackerels, stromateids, and allies)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Arcila et al. 2021 (doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syab018)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Guillermo&nbsp;Orti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721402060_Fig3_Syngna--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721402060_Fig3_Syngna--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721402060_Fig3_Syngna--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phylogenomics of Syngnatharia (seahorses, pipefishes, trumpetfishes, goatfishes, dragonets, and allies)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Santaquiteria et al 2021 (accepted MS in Syst Biol)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Guillermo&nbsp;Orti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721690998_Fig4_Carang--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721690998_Fig4_Carang--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721690998_Fig4_Carang--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phylogenomics of Carangaria (jacks, barracudas, flatfishes, billfishes, and allies)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ribeiro et al. (2018; dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2018.2010)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Guillermo&nbsp;Orti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721912180_Fig5-silversides--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721912180_Fig5-silversides--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1457426/1457426_10362067_1617721912180_Fig5-silversides--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Biogeography, marine to freshwater habitat transitions, and hybridization in South American silversides (genus Odontesthes)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hughes et al. 2020 (DOI:10.1111/mec.15350)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Guillermo&nbsp;Orti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit: This project had two major goals, (i) inference of taxonomically-dense phylogenies using genome-wide data for several clades of percomorph fishes that include some of the best-known fishes, such as tunas, flounders, billfishes, jacks, silversides, and snappers, as well as charismatic ones, such as sea horses, and trumpetfishes, (ii) use of the newly-generated phylogenetic trees to map organismal traits and ecological data layers using state-of-the art comparative methodologies to study how habitat shifts (benthic to pelagic, marine to freshwater), geological events,  and biogeography have shaped morphological diversity and biodiversity in these groups.  Outcomes of the first objective include newly inferred phylogenomic trees (based on 900-1,100 genes) for Lutjanidae (snappers and fusiliers; 110 out of 136 species; Fig. 1), Pelagiaria (tunas, mackerels, stromateoids, and allies; 150 out of 284 species; Fig. 2), Syngnatharia (trumpetfishes, goatfishes, dragonets, flying gurnards, seahorses, pipefishes, and allies; 169 out of 320 species; Fig. 3), Carangaria (flatfishes, jacks, barracudas, billfishes and allies; ~700 out of 1,100 species; work in progress, but see Fig. 4 for a preliminary analysis using ~20 genes), and South American silversides (Odontesthes; 14 out of 19 species; Fig. 5).  For the second aim, we examined evolutionary transitions along the benthic-pelagic axis (bottom dwellers versus open-water swimmers) in two of these clades: Lutjanidae and Carangaria. With Lutjanidae, we studied cases of convergent evolution along this ecological axis. Deep-bodied forms tend to occur in benthic habitats, while pelagic species typically have streamlined body plans. Body shape is a strong predictor of habitat occupation in fishes, which changes rapidly at micro-evolutionary scales in well-studied freshwater systems such as sticklebacks and cichlids. The recurrent evolution of this pattern across distantly related groups suggests that limited sets of high-fitness solutions exist due to environmental constraints. We rigorously tested these observations showing that similar constraints operate at deeper evolutionary scales in lutjanids, a clade of primarily benthic fish dwellers that repeatedly transitioned into midwater habitats in all major oceans throughout its 45-million-year history. Our results show independent incursions into the water column by ancestral benthic lineages in all major oceanic basins. These evolutionary transitions are persistently associated with convergent phenotypes, where deep-bodied benthic forms with truncate caudal fins repeatedly evolve into slender midwater species with furcate caudal fins. Lineage diversification and transition dynamics vary asymmetrically between habitats, with benthic lineages diversifying faster and colonizing midwater habitats more often than the reverse (Fig. 1, center plot). Convergent ecological and functional phenotypes along the benthic-pelagic axis are pervasive among different lineages and across vastly different evolutionary scales, achieving predictable high-fitness solutions for similar environmental challenges, ultimately demonstrating strong determinism in fish body-shape evolution.  Carangaria comprises a disparate array of benthic and pelagic species (ca. 1100), including some of the most astonishing fish forms such as  flatfishes, billfishes, remoras, barracudas, and archerfishes (Fig. 4). Our goal was to assess how the Cretaceous-Paleogene mass exctinction (KP-G) affected the evolutionary dynamics in the group. Ecological opportunity arising in the aftermath of mass extinction is thought to provide ideal conditions for the onset of evolutionary radiations. We estimated a fossil-calibrated multi-locus time tree that includes all major lineages in this group and used a set of phylogenetic comparative approaches to investigate how rates of lineage diversification, multivariate morphological evolution, and habitat transitions vary throughout the history of the clade. Analyses of lineage diversification show time-heterogeneous rates of lineage diversification in carangarians, with highest rates reached during the Paleocene. Likewise, a remarkable proportion of Carangaria?s morphological variation originated early in the history of the group and in tandem with a marked incidence of habitat shifts (Fig. 4). Taken together, these results suggest that all major lineages and body plans in Carangaria originated in an early burst shortly after the K-Pg mass extinction, which ultimately allowed the occupation of newly released niches along the benthic-pelagic habitat axis.  Marine-to-freshwater habitat transitions were studied in South American silverside fishes (genus Odontesthes, Atherinopsidae), a radiation of 19 marine and freshwater species. A robust phylogenetic framework (Fig. 5) showed that this group originally diversified in the Pacific but independently colonized the Atlantic three times, producing three separate marine-to-freshwater transitions. Comparative transcriptomics revealed inter-specific differences mapping to genes with a diversity of functions, suggesting that multiple abiotic and biotic factors in marine and freshwater habitats are driving genomic differences between these species.  Broader impacts: Molecular markers and bioinformatics pipelines developed by this project are already being used in the scientific community to resolve phylogenies of many other groups of fishes, advancing fish systematics broadly. Human resource development (undergraduate and graduate student training, supervision of postdoctoral fellows) and establishment of international collaborations in the framework of the project also produced significant broader impacts. Co-PI Betancur and his collaborators developed an annual Latin American Macroevolution Workshop, which was offered in Puerto Rico (2016), Argentina (2017), and Mexico (2018).          Last Modified: 04/06/2021       Submitted by: Guillermo Orti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
