<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarship Program for Master's Degree Seeking Students in Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>610180.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>610180</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Jackman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjackman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924816</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Binghamton University will create a scholarship program that will encourage capable, domestic, and financially challenged students to successfully complete a master's (MS) degree in electrical, computer, or mechanical engineering.  MS students will also develop leadership skills, entrepreneurial ability, and teamwork through course work, seminars, and internships in industry.  The program allows Binghamton University to offer scholarships to directly address a current need in high-technology industries for American citizens with advanced degrees in engineering.  Scholarships for academically strong engineering students, who may not otherwise be able to afford study for advanced engineering degrees, will provide the future technological leadership needed by national, regional, and local high-technology industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Departments of Electrical and Computer Engineering and Mechanical Engineering at Binghamton University will recruit three cohorts of nine students each. The program of study for the recipients will closely follow the recommendations in the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) reports for educating the engineer of 2020. Specifically, the program will be dedicated to fostering the MS degree as a professional engineering degree.  As advocated by the NAE in Engineer 2020, the development of advanced technical expertise will be combined with leadership skills, entrepreneurial thinking, and teamwork.  These educational goals will be achieved through courses and seminars taken in common by the students.  Internships opportunities with high-technology industries will be emphasized. The S-STEM scholars will participate in monthly seminars with fellow students, faculty members, and industry partners. The seminars will be used as a vehicle to guide students in their academic and professional development.  The program aligns with an institution-wide initiative at Binghamton University highlighting combining master's degrees with internships.  The S-STEM scholars will benefit from Binghamton University's departments of Electrical and Computer Engineering and Mechanical Engineering history of active interdisciplinary collaboration and engagement with industry.  The experience of the program as developed through evaluation and assessment will add to the body of knowledge about best practices for need and merit-based scholarship programs in engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1458739</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zahorian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Zahorian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zahorian@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000148547</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Pitarresi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James M Pitarresi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmp@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077774037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000186534</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Summerville</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas H Summerville</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dsummer@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077772942</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000183187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Carpenter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Carpenter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carpentera1@wit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6179894716</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637323</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/14/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 6000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090189965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Binghamton]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~610180</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main activity of this project was to provide financial support and enrichment activities to a group of computer engineering, electrical engineering, and mechanical engineering students to help them successfully complete a master&rsquo;s degree program in their respective disciplines.&nbsp;&nbsp; During the course of this project, a total of 59 students were supported, primarily in the master&rsquo;s year of a 4+1 integrated BS/MS program.&nbsp;&nbsp; A few of the students were also supported in their senior year.&nbsp;&nbsp; Of these 59 students, 17 majored in computer engineering, 25 majored in electrical engineering, and 17 majored in mechanical engineering.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 45 of the students awarded scholarships completed a STEM master&rsquo;s degree, 6 completed STEM BS degrees, and the remaining 8 students left the S-STEM program for a variety of reasons. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Of the 59 supported students, 47 were male students, 9 were female students, and 3 declined to indicate. &nbsp;&nbsp;Of the 59 students race was reported as 34 White, 6 Black or African-American, 3 American Indian or Alaska Native, 8 Asian, 1 Hawaiian or Pacific Islander, 8 declined to indicate race or ethnicity, and 14 indicated Hispanic or Latino ethnicity.&nbsp; Note that some students reported two race categories and some reported one race and one ethnicity.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>There were five cohorts of students, with one cohort beginning each year of the program.&nbsp;&nbsp; The majority of the students were enrolled in the program for only one year, but there were also several who participated in the program for two years.&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition to scholarship funding, enrichment activities were held for the students.&nbsp;&nbsp; These activities included field trips, and meetings for the students approximately once per month.&nbsp; In the meetings several types of activities were held, such as talks by guest speakers, and visits from prior graduates of the program.&nbsp;&nbsp; Students were also encouraged, and partially financially supported, to attend national student professional meetings of interest to stem students.&nbsp; Several students attended a National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE) meeting and several students attended a Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE) meeting.&nbsp;&nbsp; After returning to campus, the students who had gone to those meetings gave short presentations to the remainder of the S-STEM group.&nbsp;&nbsp; It was quite clear that the majority of the students attending these meetings were quite energized by events at the meeting and many of them received job offers on the spot at the meetings.</p> <p>Multiple surveys were conducted each year of the program.&nbsp;&nbsp; The students reported that the financial aid received from NSF, and the focus on entrepreneurship and coop experiences in the S-STEM program, benefited them greatly.&nbsp; The majority of the students did take advantage of company co-op opportunities one or more summers during their college career. The majority of the students reported they had job offers in stem fields, even before graduation.&nbsp;</p> <p>A more comprehensive survey was also done in the final spring of the program using data reported by the students on LinkedIn.&nbsp;&nbsp; Based on this self-reported data as of the year 2020 most of the students are working in STEM fields.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Typical careers the students reported were computer engineer, electrical engineer, mechanical engineer, software engineer, robotics engineer, and several more specific engineering fields. &nbsp;Despite the focus on entrepreneurship in the program, to date none of the students are full-time entrepreneurs.&nbsp;&nbsp; However, three of them have started small companies as secondary activities.&nbsp;&nbsp; It was anticipated that the vast majority of the students upon graduation would at least work for company for a few years before considering launching start-up companies. &nbsp;&nbsp;Of course the long term careers of these graduates remains to be seen.&nbsp;&nbsp; It is clear that the majority of these domestic graduates have a good start in a stem engineering position at a major United States company.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;Zahorian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main activity of this project was to provide financial support and enrichment activities to a group of computer engineering, electrical engineering, and mechanical engineering students to help them successfully complete a master’s degree program in their respective disciplines.   During the course of this project, a total of 59 students were supported, primarily in the master’s year of a 4+1 integrated BS/MS program.   A few of the students were also supported in their senior year.   Of these 59 students, 17 majored in computer engineering, 25 majored in electrical engineering, and 17 majored in mechanical engineering.    45 of the students awarded scholarships completed a STEM master’s degree, 6 completed STEM BS degrees, and the remaining 8 students left the S-STEM program for a variety of reasons.     Of the 59 supported students, 47 were male students, 9 were female students, and 3 declined to indicate.   Of the 59 students race was reported as 34 White, 6 Black or African-American, 3 American Indian or Alaska Native, 8 Asian, 1 Hawaiian or Pacific Islander, 8 declined to indicate race or ethnicity, and 14 indicated Hispanic or Latino ethnicity.  Note that some students reported two race categories and some reported one race and one ethnicity.         There were five cohorts of students, with one cohort beginning each year of the program.   The majority of the students were enrolled in the program for only one year, but there were also several who participated in the program for two years.   In addition to scholarship funding, enrichment activities were held for the students.   These activities included field trips, and meetings for the students approximately once per month.  In the meetings several types of activities were held, such as talks by guest speakers, and visits from prior graduates of the program.   Students were also encouraged, and partially financially supported, to attend national student professional meetings of interest to stem students.  Several students attended a National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE) meeting and several students attended a Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE) meeting.   After returning to campus, the students who had gone to those meetings gave short presentations to the remainder of the S-STEM group.   It was quite clear that the majority of the students attending these meetings were quite energized by events at the meeting and many of them received job offers on the spot at the meetings.  Multiple surveys were conducted each year of the program.   The students reported that the financial aid received from NSF, and the focus on entrepreneurship and coop experiences in the S-STEM program, benefited them greatly.  The majority of the students did take advantage of company co-op opportunities one or more summers during their college career. The majority of the students reported they had job offers in stem fields, even before graduation.   A more comprehensive survey was also done in the final spring of the program using data reported by the students on LinkedIn.   Based on this self-reported data as of the year 2020 most of the students are working in STEM fields.    Typical careers the students reported were computer engineer, electrical engineer, mechanical engineer, software engineer, robotics engineer, and several more specific engineering fields.  Despite the focus on entrepreneurship in the program, to date none of the students are full-time entrepreneurs.   However, three of them have started small companies as secondary activities.   It was anticipated that the vast majority of the students upon graduation would at least work for company for a few years before considering launching start-up companies.   Of course the long term careers of these graduates remains to be seen.   It is clear that the majority of these domestic graduates have a good start in a stem engineering position at a major United States company.                Last Modified: 09/04/2020       Submitted by: Stephen Zahorian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
