<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Planktonic Sources of Chromophoric Dissolved Organic Matter in Seawater</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>231109.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>231109</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henrietta Edmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hedmonds@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927427</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Chromophoric dissolved organic matter (CDOM) is a small but important fraction of the marine carbon pool that interacts with solar radiation and thus affects many photochemical and biological processes in the ocean. Despite its importance, the chemical basis for the formation of oceanic CDOM remains unclear. CDOM may be formed from two possible sources: 1) heterotrophic bacterial transformations of primary productivity (plankton-derived), or 2) terrestrially-derived. This project will examine the role of phytoplankton as a source of CDOM in the ocean by utilizing a powerful, new technique to measure particulate organic matter absorbance and fluorescence, discrete chemical measurements of probable precursors to planktonic CDOM, and enzymatic assays. Results of this research will provide new insights into the origin and production of planktonic CDOM and its transformation by heterotrophic bacteria. This research on CDOM will be shared broadly through a module at a North Carolina Aquarium, and streaming live feeds of shipboard activities to elementary school classrooms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Terrestrial and oceanic dissolved organic matter (DOM) differ in their chemical composition. Laboratory and open-ocean observations suggest that bacterial transformation of phytoplankton DOM produces humic-like CDOM signals that are visually similar to those in terrestrial CDOM. However, prior studies of oceanic CDOM using absorbance and fluorescence fit an electronic interaction (EI) model of intramolecular charge transfer (CT) reactions between donor and acceptor molecules common to partially-oxidized terrestrial molecules found in humic substances. This project will test the hypothesis that phytoplankton and bacteria provide a source of donors and acceptors that are microbially-transformed and linked, enabling CT contacts between them and creating oceanic CDOM. To address this, researchers will systematically study phytoplankton growth, including marine snow formation. A new technique for measuring base-extracted POM (BEPOM) absorbance and fluorescence will be used to incorporate planktonic CDOM results into the EI model, and supplemented with measurements of its probable chemical precursors. These experiments will improve understanding of how the production of CDOM in the ocean is linked to the optics and chemistry of planktonic CDOM formation. Determining the time course and extent of phytoplankton POM and DOM transformation by heterotrophic bacteria during the same phytoplankton growth experiments will provide an in-depth understanding as to how bacterial transformation of marine snow-associated planktonic organic matter drives CDOM production throughout the ocean.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1459294</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bianchi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas S Bianchi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tbianchi@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523926138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000187707</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112120</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1389</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~231109</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The origin and mechanisms driving the formation of fluorescent dissolved organic matter (FDOM) in the open ocean remain unclear.&nbsp; One hypothesis is that oceanic FDOM, derives from heterotrophic bacterial transformation of primary productivity (Nelson and Siegel 2013, and references therein), while a second interpretation is that the FDOM appears terrestrial because its optical properties arise from intramolecular electronic interactions of charge transfer between electron-rich donors and electron-poor acceptors in molecules such as lignin that are more abundant in terrestrial DOM (formulated as the EI model) (Del Vecchio and Blough 2004; Andrew et al. 2013). Here, we investigated the transformations in oceanic FDOM/FPOM using a biomarker approach in a controlled growth and degradation experiment.</p> <p>In this experiment, a natural assemblage of phytoplankton was collected off the coast of North Carolina and incubated within roller bottles containing 0.2 &micro;m-filtered North Atlantic surface water amended with f/2 nutrients.&nbsp; Samples were collected at the beginning (day 0), during exponential growth (day 13), stationary (day 20), and dark degradation (day 62) phases of the phytoplankton incubation. Amino acids of the DOM and POM were measured in conjunction with enzyme assays and bacterial counts to track shifts in OM composition as FDOM and FPOM formed and was then transformed throughout the experiment.</p> <p>In the FDOM, a strong protein-like peak dominated during the initial and mid-exponential phases of the phytoplankton and increased in &lsquo;humic-like&rsquo; peaks during the stationary and degradation phases (Fig. 1). The POM and DOM were significantly altered as the incubation experiment progressed, and they remained distinct from each other with regards to amino acid and fluorescent composition (Fig. 2). The aromatic amino acids were significantly correlated to both protein-like peaks B and T (Fig. 3).&nbsp; Tryptophan was significantly correlated for the POM only (Fig. 4).&nbsp; This could be due to dissolved tryptophan remaining near the limit-of-detection, or the presence of other indole-containing compounds. Particulate serine and threonine increased in relative abundance throughout the incubation and was significantly correlated to all humic-like FDOM peaks (Fig.5).&nbsp; We hypothesize that the degradation of POM is driving many of the changes in DOM fluorescence.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Bianchi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125251660_Fig.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125251660_Fig.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125251660_Fig.1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Excitation-emission spectra during the initial, mid-exponential, stationary, and degradation phases of the incubation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">none required</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Bianchi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125358405_Fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125358405_Fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125358405_Fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. a) Mean and 95% CI of DOC and POC for the entire incubation, b) Mean and 95% CI of percentage of OC that is in the form of amino acids for the entire incubation, and c) PCA of the amino acid composition (mol %) and relative fluorescent intensities for DOM and POM.</div> <div class="imageCredit">none required</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Bianchi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125437623_Fig.3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125437623_Fig.3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125437623_Fig.3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3.  Biplots of Protein-like Peak B fluorescence vs. a) dissolved aromatic amino acids, b) particulate aromatic amino acids, c) total dissolved amino acids, and d) total particulate amino acids. Particulates are plotted vs. BEPOM fluorescent peaks and dissolved constituents are plotted against</div> <div class="imageCredit">none required</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Bianchi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125508583_Fig.4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125508583_Fig.4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125508583_Fig.4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4.  Biplots of Protein-like Peak T fluorescence vs. a) dissolved tryptophan, b) particulate tryptophan, c) dissolved aromatic amino acids, and d) particulate aromatic amino acids. Particulates are plotted vs. BEPOM fluorescent peaks and dissolved constituents are plotted against FDOM peaks.</div> <div class="imageCredit">none required</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Bianchi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125577683_Fig.5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125577683_Fig.5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1459294/1459294_10351454_1523125577683_Fig.5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5.  Biplots of a) particulate amino acid concentration vs. aminopeptidase activity, b) aminopeptidase activity vs. humic-like BEPOM, c) particulate serine + threonine (mole %) vs. humic-like DOM, and d) particulate serine + threonine (mole %) vs. the DOM humification index.</div> <div class="imageCredit">none required</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;S&nbsp;Bianchi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 5</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The origin and mechanisms driving the formation of fluorescent dissolved organic matter (FDOM) in the open ocean remain unclear.  One hypothesis is that oceanic FDOM, derives from heterotrophic bacterial transformation of primary productivity (Nelson and Siegel 2013, and references therein), while a second interpretation is that the FDOM appears terrestrial because its optical properties arise from intramolecular electronic interactions of charge transfer between electron-rich donors and electron-poor acceptors in molecules such as lignin that are more abundant in terrestrial DOM (formulated as the EI model) (Del Vecchio and Blough 2004; Andrew et al. 2013). Here, we investigated the transformations in oceanic FDOM/FPOM using a biomarker approach in a controlled growth and degradation experiment.  In this experiment, a natural assemblage of phytoplankton was collected off the coast of North Carolina and incubated within roller bottles containing 0.2 &micro;m-filtered North Atlantic surface water amended with f/2 nutrients.  Samples were collected at the beginning (day 0), during exponential growth (day 13), stationary (day 20), and dark degradation (day 62) phases of the phytoplankton incubation. Amino acids of the DOM and POM were measured in conjunction with enzyme assays and bacterial counts to track shifts in OM composition as FDOM and FPOM formed and was then transformed throughout the experiment.  In the FDOM, a strong protein-like peak dominated during the initial and mid-exponential phases of the phytoplankton and increased in ?humic-like? peaks during the stationary and degradation phases (Fig. 1). The POM and DOM were significantly altered as the incubation experiment progressed, and they remained distinct from each other with regards to amino acid and fluorescent composition (Fig. 2). The aromatic amino acids were significantly correlated to both protein-like peaks B and T (Fig. 3).  Tryptophan was significantly correlated for the POM only (Fig. 4).  This could be due to dissolved tryptophan remaining near the limit-of-detection, or the presence of other indole-containing compounds. Particulate serine and threonine increased in relative abundance throughout the incubation and was significantly correlated to all humic-like FDOM peaks (Fig.5).  We hypothesize that the degradation of POM is driving many of the changes in DOM fluorescence.          Last Modified: 04/07/2018       Submitted by: Thomas S Bianchi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
