<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Social and Spatio-Temporal Patterns of Arsenic Exposure and Effects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15763.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15763</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Antoinette WinklerPrins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>anwinkle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927266</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project examines the changing geographies of exposure to arsenic-contaminated drinking water and the resulting human health effects of respiratory disease and impaired lung function. Utilizing a political ecology of disease framework and spatial statistical methods, the objective of the project is to investigate the social, economic, political and environmental factors that lead to and perpetuate exposure to arsenic and its resulting health effects. The research findings are expected to advance knowledge within health and medical geography by expanding understanding about how multiple factors intersect to both create and mitigate risk of toxic exposures over space and time. This advancement of knowledge will have important important implications for policy evaluation and the planning of future mitigation strategies by highlighting priority locations and groups at risk. Although this research focuses on Bangladesh, its findings will be broadly applicable to many areas of the world reporting arsenic poisoning from contaminated groundwater including Chile, Taiwan, and parts of the United States. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Arsenic occurs naturally in the sediments of Bangladesh, though with high spatial variability due to changes in local geology. At the same time, household and individual exposure to that arsenic varies due to social, economic, and political factors that influence both access to wells and the likelihood that a well taps a contaminated aquifer. Therefore, understanding the relationship between arsenic exposure and human health demands an understanding of human-environment interactions and how they vary across spatial and temporal scales. Situated in this context, this research is guided by three main questions: (1) How does arsenic exposure in rural Bangladesh vary spatially, temporally, and with social/demographic factors? (2) What factors influence a household's behavior to access an uncontaminated water source? (3) What are the consequences of chronic arsenic exposure for lung function and respiratory disease? The research will contribute a new methodological approach to the study of arsenic and health that combines a Bayesian cluster detection model with spatial regression techniques. Together these techniques will highlight risk factors and areas of persistent arsenic exposure and the role of arsenic exposure in lung disease. In addition to novel results, the theoretical framing of this study will provide an example for incorporating geographic theory on human-environment interactions and political ecology into health studies, improving future research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1459184</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jane</FirstName>
<LastName>Menken</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jane A Menken</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>menken@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034928148</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222171</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elisabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Root</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elisabeth D Root</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>root.145@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142921882</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elisabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Root</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elisabeth D Root</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>root.145@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142921882</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/19/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Warren</FirstName>
<LastName>Jochem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Warren C Jochem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>warren.jochem@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034922631</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090572</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine St,, Rm 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9187</Code>
<Text>TOXIC SUBSTANCES/SOLID &amp; HAZARDOUS WASTE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~15763</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Bangladesh has a long history of exposure to high levels of inorganic arsenic in its drinking water as an unintended consequence of development programs that installed new wells. Arsenic occurs naturally in the sediments of this region, though with high spatial variability due to changes in geology. At the same time, human exposure to that arsenic varies due to social, economic, and political factors that influence both access to wells and mitigation projects, and the likelihood that a well taps a contaminated aquifer. Arsenic has no distinguishing color, odor, or taste so as many as 77 million people were exposed for decades until contamination was discovered in the 1990s. Since that time millions of dollars have been spent by the government and international aid organizations on testing water sources and encouraging households to adopt arsenic-safe sources.</p> <p>This study takes a geographic approach to examine the patterns of arsenic exposure, how exposure has shifted since contamination was realized, and the subsequent impacts of exposure on respiratory health in the area of Matlab, Bangladesh. The analyses draw on new longitudinal survey data linked to 30 years of spatially-referenced health and demographic surveillance records and apply a combination of spatial statistical methods. The results show that since arsenic contamination was realized, exposure has declined dramatically overall. Yet within the overall trend for Matlab there are local areas that remain at increased risk for exposure, likely due to geologic variation. Furthermore a social gradient in exposure has recently emerged as poorer households are far more likely to be exposed to arsenic. The decline in exposure has not yielded health benefits for respiratory health. Higher lifetime exposures to arsenic are associated with reductions in FEV1 and FVC (measures of lung strength and lung capacity, respectively) in both adults and children.</p> <p>In the past, the health effects of arsenic exposure have been primarily studied by scholars in epidemiology or environmental health using a biomedical view. In contrast, this project was designed to contribute to scholarly debates in health and medical geography. Toward this goal, it explored the mechanisms by which social, economic, and political contexts shape how people experience the physical environment and how they behave when faced with environmental changes. This theoretical framing questions the naturalness of exposure. Instead, exposure is seen to act as an intermediate factor linking social determinants to more proximate biological differences and individual characteristics affecting human health. Methodologically this work demonstrated the importance of using quantitative spatial statistical methods in the study of exposures and health impacts. It applied several advanced techniques including Generalized Additive Models (GAM) in a form of point-pattern and cluster analysis, as well as Bayesian estimation techniques for spatial discrete choice models.</p> <p>The findings of this project have important implications for understanding future health burdens in Bangladesh and planning arsenic mitigation projects. The results highlight the geographic areas and populations which are most vulnerable and are experience health disparities. The recent decrease in arsenic exposure overall is positive, yet more mitigation work which addresses the root causes of vulnerability is needed as even low-levels of exposure are found to have detrimental health consequences and these will likely continue in the future. While this work has focused on Bangladesh, it also has application to other areas of the world including Chile, Taiwan, and parts of the U.S. which all experience arsenic poisoning from contaminated groundwater.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/22/2016<br>      Modified by: Jane&nbsp;A&nbsp;Menken</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Bangladesh has a long history of exposure to high levels of inorganic arsenic in its drinking water as an unintended consequence of development programs that installed new wells. Arsenic occurs naturally in the sediments of this region, though with high spatial variability due to changes in geology. At the same time, human exposure to that arsenic varies due to social, economic, and political factors that influence both access to wells and mitigation projects, and the likelihood that a well taps a contaminated aquifer. Arsenic has no distinguishing color, odor, or taste so as many as 77 million people were exposed for decades until contamination was discovered in the 1990s. Since that time millions of dollars have been spent by the government and international aid organizations on testing water sources and encouraging households to adopt arsenic-safe sources.  This study takes a geographic approach to examine the patterns of arsenic exposure, how exposure has shifted since contamination was realized, and the subsequent impacts of exposure on respiratory health in the area of Matlab, Bangladesh. The analyses draw on new longitudinal survey data linked to 30 years of spatially-referenced health and demographic surveillance records and apply a combination of spatial statistical methods. The results show that since arsenic contamination was realized, exposure has declined dramatically overall. Yet within the overall trend for Matlab there are local areas that remain at increased risk for exposure, likely due to geologic variation. Furthermore a social gradient in exposure has recently emerged as poorer households are far more likely to be exposed to arsenic. The decline in exposure has not yielded health benefits for respiratory health. Higher lifetime exposures to arsenic are associated with reductions in FEV1 and FVC (measures of lung strength and lung capacity, respectively) in both adults and children.  In the past, the health effects of arsenic exposure have been primarily studied by scholars in epidemiology or environmental health using a biomedical view. In contrast, this project was designed to contribute to scholarly debates in health and medical geography. Toward this goal, it explored the mechanisms by which social, economic, and political contexts shape how people experience the physical environment and how they behave when faced with environmental changes. This theoretical framing questions the naturalness of exposure. Instead, exposure is seen to act as an intermediate factor linking social determinants to more proximate biological differences and individual characteristics affecting human health. Methodologically this work demonstrated the importance of using quantitative spatial statistical methods in the study of exposures and health impacts. It applied several advanced techniques including Generalized Additive Models (GAM) in a form of point-pattern and cluster analysis, as well as Bayesian estimation techniques for spatial discrete choice models.  The findings of this project have important implications for understanding future health burdens in Bangladesh and planning arsenic mitigation projects. The results highlight the geographic areas and populations which are most vulnerable and are experience health disparities. The recent decrease in arsenic exposure overall is positive, yet more mitigation work which addresses the root causes of vulnerability is needed as even low-levels of exposure are found to have detrimental health consequences and these will likely continue in the future. While this work has focused on Bangladesh, it also has application to other areas of the world including Chile, Taiwan, and parts of the U.S. which all experience arsenic poisoning from contaminated groundwater.       Last Modified: 10/22/2016       Submitted by: Jane A Menken]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
