<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site at UW Bothell</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>246941.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246941</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nakannan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The REU site at UW Bothell will bring nine undergraduate students per summer to the University of Washington Bothell for a memorable research experience that will encourage and prepare them to pursue graduate education and research-oriented careers. Working closely with three faculty members on projects in knot theory, tiling theory, optimization, and biomedical analysis that are carefully chosen to be both accessible and significant, students will see firsthand that mathematical research can be both fun and interesting. The research experience will be complemented by professional development presentations, organized outings, and social activities. The investigators believe that this program will have a greater effect by recruiting students from underrepresented groups and from universities where research opportunities are limited; in particular, American Indians, women, and first generation college students from non-Ph.D. granting universities will be targeted.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each summer, the REU site will host three research groups consisting of three students and one faculty member. The research focus of the three groups will be from among the following four topics: Knot theory; interesting questions concerning lattice knots, in the standard cubic lattice as well as other lattices, such as the face-centered cubic lattice or the simple hexagonal lattice, will be pursued, including questions involving the minimal sized sphere that can contain a nontrivial knot (the sphere number of a lattice). Tiling theory; the problem of finding all convex pentagons that admit tilings of the plane is a long-standing unsolved problem. Students will develop an algorithm to search for pentagons that admit i-block transitive tilings of the plane, which could lead to the discovery of new convex pentagonal tiles that admit tilings of the plane. Optimization; Students will work to improve numerical optimization algorithms, including two variants of the modified spectral subgradient method. This project will also help develop students' scientific computing skills using MATLAB. Biomedical analysis; Students will develop methods for analyzing data from ultrasound devices used to detect abnormalities in brain tissue, including development of two-dimensional cross-correlation techniques to track ultrasound induced shear-wave propagation (whose speed is proportional to the shear modulus of tissue), development and testing of first principle models of that propagation as a function of material properties, and comparison of direct measures of brain-tissue stiffness.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1460699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Casey</FirstName>
<LastName>Mann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Casey Mann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cemann@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065434043</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>McLoud-Mann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer McLoud-Mann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>JMcLoud@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065434043</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington Bothell]]></Name>
<CityName>Bothell</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>980118246</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box 358538; 18115 Campus Way NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~246941</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This report summarizes the major goals and outcomes regarding the NSF criteria of Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts for the NSF REU site at the University of Washington Bothell during summers 2015, 2016, and 2017. PIs Dr. Jennifer McLoud-Mann and Dr. Casey Mann both mentored 3 groups of students. Another PI (Dr. Milagros Loreto) mentored 3 groups of students and<br />two senior personnel (Dr. Thomas Humphries and Dr. Pietro Paparella) mentored 1 group of students each. We are proud to describe the successes of this REU site.</p> <p>Broader Impacts. One of main goals of our REU site was to increase participation in mathematical research and graduate training by underrepresented groups &ndash; minorities, especially American Indians,<br />women, and first-generation college students. In particular, we wanted at least 66.6% of our participants to be from one of these groups. The table below contains participant demographics showing that we exceeded our goal by selecting 93% of our participants from the underrepresented groups mentioned<br />above. Something that the table does not show but it true is that we made offers to every American Indian applicant; some of them chose to accept another REU's offer but we were happy they would have the opportunity to participate in undergraduate research.</p> <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="630"> <tbody> <tr> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>REU</p> <p>Participants</p> </td> <td width="97" valign="top"> <p>AfroAM, AmInd, Hisp, HawPac</p> </td> <td width="107" valign="top"> <p>Female</p> </td> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>First-gen</p> </td> <td width="116" valign="top"> <p>Underrepresented</p> <p>Total</p> </td> <td width="106" valign="top"> <p>Institution not granting Ph.D.</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>2015</p> </td> <td width="97" valign="top"> <p>2/9</p> </td> <td width="107" valign="top"> <p>5/9</p> </td> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>3/9</p> </td> <td width="116" valign="top"> <p>7/9</p> </td> <td width="106" valign="top"> <p>8/9</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>2016</p> </td> <td width="97" valign="top"> <p>4/9</p> </td> <td width="107" valign="top"> <p>4/9</p> </td> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>4/9</p> </td> <td width="116" valign="top"> <p>9/9</p> </td> <td width="106" valign="top"> <p>8/9</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>2017</p> </td> <td width="97" valign="top"> <p>2/10</p> </td> <td width="107" valign="top"> <p>7/10</p> </td> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>3/10</p> </td> <td width="116" valign="top"> <p>10/10</p> </td> <td width="106" valign="top"> <p>7/10</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>Total</p> </td> <td width="97" valign="top"> <p>8/28 or 29%</p> </td> <td width="107" valign="top"> <p>16/28 or 57%</p> </td> <td width="102" valign="top"> <p>10/28 or 36%</p> </td> <td width="116" valign="top"> <p>26/28 or 93%</p> </td> <td width="106" valign="top"> <p>23/28 or 82%</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit. Another major goal of the program was to increase the number of undergraduates choosing to pursue graduate degrees in mathematics. Of the 15 students that have completed their Bachelor&rsquo;s degrees in mathematics, 11 of them are pursuing graduate degrees. We wanted at least 50% of our participants to pursue graduate degrees within two years of completing their undergraduate programs; from those completing their programs we have 73% in graduate programs at Wesleyan University, University of Texas Arlington, Texas A&amp;M University, University of Tennessee Knoxville, University of Virginia, Montana State University, The University of Utah, Boise State University, and North Carolina A&amp;T State University.</p> <p>The other two goals of the program were to increase students&rsquo; mathematical communication skills and to disseminate research results to the mathematical community. We have been achieving these goals in a variety of ways. All students participate in writing research results in Latex, creating slides/posters with Latex, and presenting their research results using both slides and posters. All REU groups have presented their research results at the Joint Mathematics Meeting's Undergraduate Poster Session; two groups were awarded as Outstanding Poster Presentations in their area of specialization. There have been many additional regional and local presentations; a recent award was given for a poster at a regional SIAM conference. Some students appear as co-authors on peer-reviewed publications (three peer-reviewed journal articles appeared or accepted, two more under review) and more articles are in preparation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;Mcloud-Mann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This report summarizes the major goals and outcomes regarding the NSF criteria of Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts for the NSF REU site at the University of Washington Bothell during summers 2015, 2016, and 2017. PIs Dr. Jennifer McLoud-Mann and Dr. Casey Mann both mentored 3 groups of students. Another PI (Dr. Milagros Loreto) mentored 3 groups of students and two senior personnel (Dr. Thomas Humphries and Dr. Pietro Paparella) mentored 1 group of students each. We are proud to describe the successes of this REU site.  Broader Impacts. One of main goals of our REU site was to increase participation in mathematical research and graduate training by underrepresented groups &ndash; minorities, especially American Indians, women, and first-generation college students. In particular, we wanted at least 66.6% of our participants to be from one of these groups. The table below contains participant demographics showing that we exceeded our goal by selecting 93% of our participants from the underrepresented groups mentioned above. Something that the table does not show but it true is that we made offers to every American Indian applicant; some of them chose to accept another REU's offer but we were happy they would have the opportunity to participate in undergraduate research.      REU  Participants    AfroAM, AmInd, Hisp, HawPac    Female    First-gen    Underrepresented  Total    Institution not granting Ph.D.      2015    2/9    5/9    3/9    7/9    8/9      2016    4/9    4/9    4/9    9/9    8/9      2017    2/10    7/10    3/10    10/10    7/10      Total    8/28 or 29%    16/28 or 57%    10/28 or 36%    26/28 or 93%    23/28 or 82%         Intellectual Merit. Another major goal of the program was to increase the number of undergraduates choosing to pursue graduate degrees in mathematics. Of the 15 students that have completed their Bachelor?s degrees in mathematics, 11 of them are pursuing graduate degrees. We wanted at least 50% of our participants to pursue graduate degrees within two years of completing their undergraduate programs; from those completing their programs we have 73% in graduate programs at Wesleyan University, University of Texas Arlington, Texas A&amp;M University, University of Tennessee Knoxville, University of Virginia, Montana State University, The University of Utah, Boise State University, and North Carolina A&amp;T State University.  The other two goals of the program were to increase students? mathematical communication skills and to disseminate research results to the mathematical community. We have been achieving these goals in a variety of ways. All students participate in writing research results in Latex, creating slides/posters with Latex, and presenting their research results using both slides and posters. All REU groups have presented their research results at the Joint Mathematics Meeting's Undergraduate Poster Session; two groups were awarded as Outstanding Poster Presentations in their area of specialization. There have been many additional regional and local presentations; a recent award was given for a poster at a regional SIAM conference. Some students appear as co-authors on peer-reviewed publications (three peer-reviewed journal articles appeared or accepted, two more under review) and more articles are in preparation.          Last Modified: 03/21/2018       Submitted by: Jennifer Mcloud-Mann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
