<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Research and Training Experience for Undergraduates in the Area of Secure Cloud Computing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harriet Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Missouri University of Science and Technology.  Each summer a cohort of undergraduate students will work with faculty in small groups to design, implement, and evaluate research projects involving secure cloud computing, an emerging research area that is current and important to our national interests. The research projects involve security, trust, and privacy in cloud computing.  The use of secure cloud technology offers an effective means for establishing secure cyberinfrastructures to develop a wide variety of applications that are used by citizens and that support our technology-based society.   Thus the students and researchers have the opportunity to explore problems that are important and timely and relevant to all our citizens.  This project builds human capacity in computing and communications research and knowledge. The program will provide experiences to undergraduate students that may influence their choices about further education and future careers and continue to give them confidence to pursue these choices and thus increase the size and diversity of the scientific workforce. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The site will focus on recruiting females and students from groups under-represented in computing fields as well as students from 2 and 4 year institutions.   The students will participate in professional development activities that make them more aware of graduate school and professional aspects of a computing career. The students will be able to use the state-of-the-art facilities available at the university and interact with faculty mentors to conduct challenging and timely research on emerging technologies fundamental to developing trustworthy systems for the future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1460697</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjay</FirstName>
<LastName>Madria</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>k</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjay k Madria</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>madrias@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5733644856</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000289664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Jiang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Jiang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wjiang@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5738829122</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000525250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[202 Centennial Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804883767</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006326904</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Missouri University of Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This REU site, at the Missouri University of Science and Technology, on&nbsp;Research and Training Experience for Undergraduates in the Area of Secure Cloud Computing trained 30+ undergraduate students from many different universities for 10+ weeks during three summers, and some continued to work during the regular academic year as well. Students worked on several research projects in a group of 2 to 3 students. They all were given necessary training through classroom lectures as well as lab exercises to train them before starting their research projects. Their projects were in the area of secure cloud computing, secure document comparison and analysis, risk analysis in sensor cloud, and privacy preserving trajectory management in cloud.&nbsp; These students helped not only design algorithms, but also written code and performed experiments. They also presented their findings each week by means of oral presentations, and also produced written technical reports.&nbsp; Some of them could publish (and presented) research papers jointly with faculty and graduate students in national and international conferences, and one of them received an award for the best student poster in a mid-west security workshop organized yearly.&nbsp;</p> <p>The students&rsquo; body was consisting of underrepresented students, women and others from many different institutions across the nation with some students came as far as&nbsp;Puerto Rico.&nbsp; These students ranged from the sopomore year to seniors, and many of these students had no access to security research infrastructure and cloud lab facilities. Based on the survey before the training, about 70% of participants did not have rich opportunities to talk to faculty/scientists about careers in science and engineering, and at least 60% of participants didn&rsquo;t have many opportunities to make science &ldquo;come to life&rdquo;.&nbsp;This research grant not only allowed them to understand cybersecurity issues, but also got the training to address some of them which otherwise was not possible&nbsp; to get in their institutions.&nbsp; The overall program effectiveness and participants' satisfaction were consistently high over the three year period.</p> <p>These undergraduate students worked not only with graduate faculty but also collaborated with PhD and MS students for their summer research. They were mentored also for graduate studies, and some of them did join graduate programs or have taken up jobs in industry or federal labs.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Sanjay&nbsp;K&nbsp;Madria</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This REU site, at the Missouri University of Science and Technology, on Research and Training Experience for Undergraduates in the Area of Secure Cloud Computing trained 30+ undergraduate students from many different universities for 10+ weeks during three summers, and some continued to work during the regular academic year as well. Students worked on several research projects in a group of 2 to 3 students. They all were given necessary training through classroom lectures as well as lab exercises to train them before starting their research projects. Their projects were in the area of secure cloud computing, secure document comparison and analysis, risk analysis in sensor cloud, and privacy preserving trajectory management in cloud.  These students helped not only design algorithms, but also written code and performed experiments. They also presented their findings each week by means of oral presentations, and also produced written technical reports.  Some of them could publish (and presented) research papers jointly with faculty and graduate students in national and international conferences, and one of them received an award for the best student poster in a mid-west security workshop organized yearly.   The students? body was consisting of underrepresented students, women and others from many different institutions across the nation with some students came as far as Puerto Rico.  These students ranged from the sopomore year to seniors, and many of these students had no access to security research infrastructure and cloud lab facilities. Based on the survey before the training, about 70% of participants did not have rich opportunities to talk to faculty/scientists about careers in science and engineering, and at least 60% of participants didn?t have many opportunities to make science "come to life". This research grant not only allowed them to understand cybersecurity issues, but also got the training to address some of them which otherwise was not possible  to get in their institutions.  The overall program effectiveness and participants' satisfaction were consistently high over the three year period.  These undergraduate students worked not only with graduate faculty but also collaborated with PhD and MS students for their summer research. They were mentored also for graduate studies, and some of them did join graduate programs or have taken up jobs in industry or federal labs.               Last Modified: 05/30/2019       Submitted by: Sanjay K Madria]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
