<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: SHINE: Data-constrained Simulations of Coronal Mass Ejection Initiation and Propagation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>58956.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>58956</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carrie E. Black</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cblack@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922426</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project addresses coronal mass ejections (CMEs) which are violent expulsions of plasma from the Sun that contribute to space weather. It is vital to understand how these eruptions happen and how they propagate towards Earth in order to accurately predict their behavior. The current fleet of solar and space observatories provides unprecedented temporal and spatial coverage of the surface magnetic field, extreme ultraviolet (EUV) and X-ray coronal structures. In this study, data-constrained simulations of CME initiation and propagation will be performed starting from realistic initial conditions for the magnetic field and plasma of an active region that contains a flux rope on the verge of eruption. These simulations will provide a unique opportunity to investigate the processes behind the eruption and early development of CMEs. &lt;br/&gt;The project has the following science objectives: 1) Develop models of CME initiation that are highly constrained by observations in order to study the early development phases of CMEs; 2) Constrain CME properties near the Sun (kinetics, morphology, shock and compression region parameters) based on the flux rope properties and the ambient coronal field, and 3) Reproduce the observed three-part and two-front structure of CMEs and their in situ properties using data-constrained magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations. &lt;br/&gt;Data-constrained non-linear force-free field (NLFFF) models of observed erupting active regions will be used as initial conditions to the Space Weather Modeling Framework (SWMF) global MHD code. The initial conditions on the active region and flux rope plasma will also be constrained by data using recently developed analysis techniques. These tools will be used to propagate more realistic CMEs to 1AU. The properties of the simulated CMEs (direction, velocity, acceleration, morphology, and shock-driving capability) will be compared with all available observations (coronal EUV and X-ray, white-light and in situ data).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1460179</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noe</FirstName>
<LastName>Lugaz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noe Lugaz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nlugaz@guero.sr.unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7342742441</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000077972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>111089470</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY SYSTEM OF NEW HAMPSHIRE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001765866</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Hampshire]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1523</Code>
<Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1323</Code>
<Text>SOLAR INFLUENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~18176</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~18674</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~22106</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In collaboration with researchers from Harvard Center for Astrophysics and from George Mason University, we studied solar eruptions focusing on how isolated events occur at the Sun and propagate between the Sun and the Earth. Through the entire collaborative project, we focused on a new and more physical way of initiating these events into global simulations, which advances both our understanding of these eruptions but also our capabilities to forecast their properties and arrival at Earth.In addition, we focused on the morphology of these eruptions when they impact a spacecraft and the different ways in which they can impact technology both in space, and on Earth but also how they may affect other planets in our solar system and in exoplanetary systems. We worked on determining how the size of these eruptions grows as they propagate and how it impacts their properties.</p> <p>Associated with this work, the UNH PI worked with 3 undergraduate students, one of which wrote his undergraduate final thesis on work associated with the effects of these solar eruptions on Earth's magnetic field. A graduate student at UNH also performs part of his PhD research on the data-analysis of the propagation of solar eruptions. Results from this award have been published in peer-reviewed publications and presented at conferences. The PI organized multiple sessions on the theme of solar eruptions/coronal mass ejections at the main conferences in the US (AGU and SHINE), and served as the SHINE workshop coordinator during the duration of this award.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Noe&nbsp;Lugaz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In collaboration with researchers from Harvard Center for Astrophysics and from George Mason University, we studied solar eruptions focusing on how isolated events occur at the Sun and propagate between the Sun and the Earth. Through the entire collaborative project, we focused on a new and more physical way of initiating these events into global simulations, which advances both our understanding of these eruptions but also our capabilities to forecast their properties and arrival at Earth.In addition, we focused on the morphology of these eruptions when they impact a spacecraft and the different ways in which they can impact technology both in space, and on Earth but also how they may affect other planets in our solar system and in exoplanetary systems. We worked on determining how the size of these eruptions grows as they propagate and how it impacts their properties.  Associated with this work, the UNH PI worked with 3 undergraduate students, one of which wrote his undergraduate final thesis on work associated with the effects of these solar eruptions on Earth's magnetic field. A graduate student at UNH also performs part of his PhD research on the data-analysis of the propagation of solar eruptions. Results from this award have been published in peer-reviewed publications and presented at conferences. The PI organized multiple sessions on the theme of solar eruptions/coronal mass ejections at the main conferences in the US (AGU and SHINE), and served as the SHINE workshop coordinator during the duration of this award.       Last Modified: 10/04/2019       Submitted by: Noe Lugaz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
