<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Career and Technical Education as a Foundation to Support Postsecondary Transitions in STEM for Students with Disabilities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>151300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>151300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The "Career and Technical Education as a Foundation to Support Postsecondary Transitions in STEM for Students with Disabilities" award is a Broadening Participation Research project designed to investigate non-traditional and less formal educational pathways, specifically career and technical education (CTE) experiences, for high school students with disabilities pursuing postsecondary STEM degrees and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team will examine three forms of CTE in high school, specifically those identified by the 2006 Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act, considered critical in supporting the school-to-postsecondary transition of students moving toward STEM college majors and, ultimately, STEM careers: (1) STEM course-taking, (2) school-based employment programs, and (3) labor force participation. STEM course-taking includes both traditional and applied STEM courses that impart quantitative concepts, logic, and problem solving skills to students in a structured classroom setting. School-based employment experiences include activities organized and sponsored by schools that promote career development, such as cooperative education, internships, and career mentoring. Labor force participation includes paid work done for an employer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are five specific research questions.&lt;br/&gt;1. What CTE experiences are provided to students with disabilities during high school?&lt;br/&gt;2. Do CTE experiences in high school improve the odds of students with disabilities transitioning into a STEM field of study in college? If so, which experiences are most beneficial?&lt;br/&gt;3. Conditional on having attended college, do CTE experiences in high school improve the odds of students with disabilities transitioning into a STEM profession after college? If so, which experiences are most beneficial?&lt;br/&gt;4. Do answers to the preceding four questions differ by specific disability classification of the individual student?&lt;br/&gt;5. Are these results generalizable to multiple nationally-representative datasets?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address these research questions, the research will conduct secondary data analyses of two existing national datasets: the NCES Education Longitudinal Study of 2002 (ELS) and the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth 1997 (NLSY97).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will be evaluated by an independent evaluator, Dr. Vi-Nhuan Le, and will include formative and summative assessments.  Results are expected to advance the field's knowledge about the future CTE experiences of students with disabilities pursuing STEM at the postsecondary level.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1460043</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gottfried</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Gottfried</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mgottfr2@upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3233878039</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000578766</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931069490</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1545</Code>
<Text>RES IN DISABILITIES ED</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1545</Code>
<Text>RES IN DISABILITIES ED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~151300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This study explored&nbsp;non-traditional, less formalized pathways to the pursuit of and persistence in STEM for students with disabilities U.S. In more detail, this study explored different aspects of career and technical education (CTE) that students with disabilities experience in high school, and the extent to which CTE helps promote transition towards post-secondary opportunities and subsequent careers in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM).<em> </em>We assessed three forms of CTE in high school prescribed by the 2006 Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act (i.e. &ldquo;Perkins IV&rdquo;) as critical in supporting the school-to-postsecondary transition of those moving toward STEM college majors and, ultimately, STEM careers: (1) STEM course-taking, (2) school-based employment programs, and (3) labor force participation. STEM course-taking included both traditional and applied STEM courses that impart quantitative concepts, logic, and problem solving skills to students in a structured classroom setting. School-based employment experiences included activities organized and sponsored by schools that promote career development, such as cooperative education, internships, and career mentoring. Labor force participation included paid work done for an employer. Using two nationally representative samples of youth, with sizeable subsamples of students with a range of disabilities, this study examined whether and how these three forms of CTE prepared these students for STEM fields of study in college and for post-college careers in STEM or with STEM applications.</p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">This study was important because prior to our research, there were no national estimates on the types, timing, and prevalence of CTE taken by students with disabilities. This study was the first to document the landscape of these experiences for students with disabilities using nationally representative data. Additionally, this study was the first to jointly evaluate the efficacy of all three CTE categories mentioned above. Although a number of national studies have examined the importance of traditional, formal STEM schooling experiences (i.e., curriculum in the general education classroom) for college and post-college labor market outcomes, none have looked at whether CTE can be successful in preparing and motivating students with disabilities to pursue and persist in STEM fields as they transition from high school to college and beyond.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">In terms of policy, schools face the difficult task of balancing the competing demands of providing students with disabilities the applied skills and knowledge to thrive in college and the adult labor force while at the same time ensuring they meet the high standards of academic competenc that are required for college. With limited resources, education policy makers must make informed choices regarding how to best structure their curriculum to meet the needs of a diverse student population. This project provides new information on CTE experiences and the role they play in advancing students with disabilities toward college majors in STEM and careers in STEM fields. To date, a number of reform initiatives have been enacted to reduce the dramatic underrepresentation of students with disabilities in STEM fields at the postsecondary level and in post-college careers. The results from this study can help policy makers and practitioners by providing an empirical basis on which to make decisions regarding the efficacy of STEM preparation and exposure on which these reform initiatives are premised.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Cambria; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2015<br>      Modified by: Michael&...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This study explored non-traditional, less formalized pathways to the pursuit of and persistence in STEM for students with disabilities U.S. In more detail, this study explored different aspects of career and technical education (CTE) that students with disabilities experience in high school, and the extent to which CTE helps promote transition towards post-secondary opportunities and subsequent careers in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). We assessed three forms of CTE in high school prescribed by the 2006 Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act (i.e. "Perkins IV") as critical in supporting the school-to-postsecondary transition of those moving toward STEM college majors and, ultimately, STEM careers: (1) STEM course-taking, (2) school-based employment programs, and (3) labor force participation. STEM course-taking included both traditional and applied STEM courses that impart quantitative concepts, logic, and problem solving skills to students in a structured classroom setting. School-based employment experiences included activities organized and sponsored by schools that promote career development, such as cooperative education, internships, and career mentoring. Labor force participation included paid work done for an employer. Using two nationally representative samples of youth, with sizeable subsamples of students with a range of disabilities, this study examined whether and how these three forms of CTE prepared these students for STEM fields of study in college and for post-college careers in STEM or with STEM applications.  This study was important because prior to our research, there were no national estimates on the types, timing, and prevalence of CTE taken by students with disabilities. This study was the first to document the landscape of these experiences for students with disabilities using nationally representative data. Additionally, this study was the first to jointly evaluate the efficacy of all three CTE categories mentioned above. Although a number of national studies have examined the importance of traditional, formal STEM schooling experiences (i.e., curriculum in the general education classroom) for college and post-college labor market outcomes, none have looked at whether CTE can be successful in preparing and motivating students with disabilities to pursue and persist in STEM fields as they transition from high school to college and beyond.  In terms of policy, schools face the difficult task of balancing the competing demands of providing students with disabilities the applied skills and knowledge to thrive in college and the adult labor force while at the same time ensuring they meet the high standards of academic competenc that are required for college. With limited resources, education policy makers must make informed choices regarding how to best structure their curriculum to meet the needs of a diverse student population. This project provides new information on CTE experiences and the role they play in advancing students with disabilities toward college majors in STEM and careers in STEM fields. To date, a number of reform initiatives have been enacted to reduce the dramatic underrepresentation of students with disabilities in STEM fields at the postsecondary level and in post-college careers. The results from this study can help policy makers and practitioners by providing an empirical basis on which to make decisions regarding the efficacy of STEM preparation and exposure on which these reform initiatives are premised.                    Last Modified: 11/23/2015       Submitted by: Michael Gottfried]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
