<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MAGIC MT - Uplift of the Appalachians</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>266015.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>266015</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dennis Geist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dgeist@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924361</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The eastern edge of the North American continent is located far from currently active boundaries of tectonic plates, and is thus often considered relatively "quiet" in plate tectonic terms.  However, the eastern margin of North America has experienced a long and rich plate tectonic history, most recently being involved in the break-up of North America and Europe and the formation of the Atlantic Ocean.  That break-up involved multiple important geologic processes, including magmatism, stretching of the continent, and uplift that is responsible for the formation of the Appalachian Mountains.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although most of this activity finished long ago, there is evidence to suggest the Appalachians are even now being partially supported by flow of the mantle beneath the mountains. We are using electric and magnetic fields of the earth recorded at the surface to image the structure of the continent and the properties of the underlying convecting mantle, in order to better understand the processes that control modern day topography and those involved in continental break-up, or rifting. The project partly supports the education of a PhD student as well as training of highly skilled technical staff, and the experiment uses equipment manufactured by Cape Abilities, a non-profit company on Cape Cod that finds work for people with disabilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We are carrying out fieldwork to collect magnetotelluric (MT) data in a profile of about 28 stations across the Appalachians, from Ohio to Virginia.  The MT method measures naturally occurring electric and magnetic fields at the surface of the earth, and uses this information to image structure to depths of several hundred km below the surface. The method measures the ability of the earth to conduct electrical current, a property that is sensitive to temperature as well as to the presence of fluids such as water or magma. We can construct a cross sectional image of the deep structure along the entire length of the profile.  The survey is coincident with an ongoing seismic experiment, and we are working with the principal investigators of that project to carry out a coordinated joint interpretation of results constraining lithospheric thickness, hydration state of the mantle, and the presence of any partial melt associated with mantle upwelling.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1460257</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert L Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>revans@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082892673</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000095233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082892623</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 Wood Hole Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Fenno House, MS#39]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Woods Hole Road, MS# 22]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~161729</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~104286</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant funded collection and analysis of geophysical Magnetotelluric (MT) data across a portion of the Appalachian mountains, from Virginia into Ohio. The region was chosen as it presents the opportunity to test the hypothesis that active flow deep within the Earth is responsible for pushing up the mountains.</p> <p>Magnetotellurics (MT) is a geophysical technique used to image deep into the Earth. The method measures naturally occurring electric and magnetic fields at the Earth&rsquo;s surface, generated by the interaction of the Earth&rsquo;s magnetic field and the charged particles of the solar wind. These charged particles create electric currents in the ionosphere which, in turn, induce current flow within the Earth. The pattern of current flow beneath Earth&rsquo;s surface is dependent on the electrical conductivity structure, a physical property sensitive to temperature, composition and particularly the presence of fluids. In particular, MT can be used to understand variations in the structure of the continental lithosphere, the outermost rigid plate that drifts slowly over the deeper convecting asthenosphere. These variations in thickness and the presence or absence of molten regions in the asthenosphere are key to our understanding of the evolution of the region.</p> <p>MT data were collected along a line roughly coincident with the MAGIC seismic experiment (Figure 1). &nbsp;Thick (&gt;100km) lithosphere, cold dry material that is a poor conductor of electrical current, is seen at each end of the profile. But the lithosphere beneath the mountains in markedly thinner. We see evidence for a small amount of molten material (melt) below this thinned region and infer that the melt has eroded away the base of what was presumably a much thicker lithosphere in the past. Interestingly, the region of thinnest lithosphere sits just to the west of a region where there was a volcanic eruption some 50 million years ago.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2018<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Evans</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1460257/1460257_10359577_1537885314130_Outcomes_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1460257/1460257_10359577_1537885314130_Outcomes_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="A map of the Survey area"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1460257/1460257_10359577_1537885314130_Outcomes_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="A map of the Survey area"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A map showing the locations of MT and seismic stations deployed in the MAGIC survey as well as surrounding Earthscope Transportable Array sites. The MT stations are plotted as ellipses which document the complexity of structure beneath the site (red, thin ellipses means more complex structure)</div> <div class="imageCredit">R Evans</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Evans</div> <div class="imageTitle">A map of the Survey area</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1460257/1460257_10359577_1537885393398_Outcomes_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1460257/1460257_10359577_1537885393398_Outcomes_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cartoon of Structure"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1460257/1460257_10359577_1537885393398_Outcomes_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cartoon of Structure"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A cartoon illustrating the important features beneath the MAGIC survey line.</div> <div class="imageCredit">R. Evans</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Evans</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cartoon of Structure</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant funded collection and analysis of geophysical Magnetotelluric (MT) data across a portion of the Appalachian mountains, from Virginia into Ohio. The region was chosen as it presents the opportunity to test the hypothesis that active flow deep within the Earth is responsible for pushing up the mountains.  Magnetotellurics (MT) is a geophysical technique used to image deep into the Earth. The method measures naturally occurring electric and magnetic fields at the Earth?s surface, generated by the interaction of the Earth?s magnetic field and the charged particles of the solar wind. These charged particles create electric currents in the ionosphere which, in turn, induce current flow within the Earth. The pattern of current flow beneath Earth?s surface is dependent on the electrical conductivity structure, a physical property sensitive to temperature, composition and particularly the presence of fluids. In particular, MT can be used to understand variations in the structure of the continental lithosphere, the outermost rigid plate that drifts slowly over the deeper convecting asthenosphere. These variations in thickness and the presence or absence of molten regions in the asthenosphere are key to our understanding of the evolution of the region.  MT data were collected along a line roughly coincident with the MAGIC seismic experiment (Figure 1).  Thick (&gt;100km) lithosphere, cold dry material that is a poor conductor of electrical current, is seen at each end of the profile. But the lithosphere beneath the mountains in markedly thinner. We see evidence for a small amount of molten material (melt) below this thinned region and infer that the melt has eroded away the base of what was presumably a much thicker lithosphere in the past. Interestingly, the region of thinnest lithosphere sits just to the west of a region where there was a volcanic eruption some 50 million years ago.       Last Modified: 09/25/2018       Submitted by: Robert L Evans]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
