<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site:  Research in Optics (RIO) at the University of Arizona</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>BROADER SIGNIFICANCE OF THE PROJECT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research in Optics (RiO) is a Research Experience for Undergraduate (REU) program at the College of Optical Sciences, The University of Arizona supported by the Division of Engineering Education and Centers at the National Science Foundation.  Optics involves the study of light and the year 2015 has been recognized as the International Year of Light. The goal for the three years of support is to educate and conduct research with ten undergraduates per year in the field of optics. The field is a burgeoning area of industry and consumer product development, academic research, and energy generation. In the commercial sector, optical products are integral to everyday lives through smartphone displays, LEDs for lighting, and imaging systems used in the medical field. In the energy sector, optical concentrators are being used in solar power facilities to improve the efficiency of electricity generation.  In the academic sector, researchers and students are developing novel technologies, exploring the fundamental limits of the world, and developing the telescopes imaging distant stars and their planets. These topics and others are the areas of research for the undergraduates selected for the RiO program.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of RiO is to develop an interest in optics within the student participants and encourage them to pursue graduate studies in a STEM field.  A metric of 50% female and 60% minority representation has been set for this program.  The participants additionally will have workshops in introductory optics, ethics training, presentation skills, and lab and laser safety and at the end of each summer will hone their presentation skills through both oral and poster events. Thus, RiO will educate future researchers and engineers in this recognized and important field for the United States in the 21st century. The participants will serve as role models for future generations by encouraging others to pursue STEM research, especially in optics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PROJECT DESCRIPTION:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;RiO participants will engage in experimental, theoretical, and modeling research over the breadth of the optics field, including optical engineering, imaging systems, photonics, and optical physics.  A project on bio-inspired optical design based on models of animal eyes has the potential to improve upon the designs of lens systems currently in use. Research on a better understanding of the optical properties of semiconductors can lead to a multitude of benefits including improved lasers and future optical technologies. Research on improved internal building illumination using daylighting means less dependency on fossil fuel electricity generation. Development of a platform independent toolbox for quantum control and measurement can lead to improved quantum information security and cryptography along with error correction. A project in the optical detection and classification of special nuclear material can determine if the matter is benign or threatening. Specific research will develop endoscopes with both forward and backward optics that can see tumors that are hidden from view for solely front-viewing systems. Research on the effect of mid-spatial frequency optical surface error will allow control of such during the manufacture of multi-meter telescope mirrors, such as the Giant Magellan Telescope. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These and other projects will expand our knowledge in and use of optics to solve challenges and develop new technology.  The student participants will also have workshops in introductory optics, ethics training, presentation and writing skills, and lab and laser safety.  Thus, the student participants will not only be conducting research at the forefront of optics, but they will be trained to succeed as researchers if they pursue graduate studies or enter the workforce after graduation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1460723</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Koshel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard J Koshel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkoshel@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206216357</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000677276</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210158</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[888 N Euclid]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>EWFD-Eng Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research in Optics (RiO) was a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) funded by the Engineering Directorate of the NSF.&nbsp;&nbsp;RiO brought undergraduates from all around the county to the College of Optical Sciences, University of Arizona to conduct novel research in the burgeoning field of optics.&nbsp;&nbsp;Optics plays a leading role in the fourth industrial revolution, which is seen as the integration of technology, especially for connectivity, communication, and computing.&nbsp;&nbsp;Examples of optics playing an important role include fiber optics (the backbone of the internet), smartphones (through their displays, cameras, and sensors), optical lithography (used to make the ever smaller integrated circuits and photonics within computer chips), security (sensors and detectors along with image-processing technology), and augmented-reality devices (employing light to provide additional information on top of real-world scenes).&nbsp;&nbsp;To highlight the increasing importance of light and optics, the National Photonics Initiative was started in 2012, the United Nations designated 2015 as the Year of Light, the American Institute for Manufacturing Integrated Photonics (AIM Photonics) started in late 2015, and 2018 marks the start of the National Quantum Initiative.&nbsp;&nbsp;In order to assist these programs, the nation needs an educated workforce in the area of optics specifically, and Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) in general.&nbsp;&nbsp;This objective is especially challenging in light of a limited number of programs providing full undergraduate and/or graduate education in optics.&nbsp;&nbsp;Thus, the primary goal of RiO was to educate the REU participants in the field of optics and encourage them to pursue graduate studies and careers in optics or associated STEM fields.&nbsp;&nbsp;Additionally, this provides an avenue to encourage women and underrepresented minorities to pursue this rapidly developing field.&nbsp;&nbsp;By the conclusion of the program, 34 undergraduates from 16 states and 27 institutions of higher learning were alumni of the program.&nbsp;&nbsp;The number of RiO women and underrepresented minorities were 12 and 10, respectively.&nbsp;The second goal of the RiO program was to introduce the participants to novel research in the field of optics, which spans from the applied to the fundamental.&nbsp;&nbsp;This breadth is typically denoted as vertical integration rather than horizontal integration.&nbsp;&nbsp;For example in horizontal integration, one has physics in the fundamental area with subfields including thermal, condensed matter, atomic-molecular-optical, and so forth. Respectively, in the applied arena one can consider electrical engineering, which includes subfields such as power systems, digital, computers, and optics.&nbsp;A given horizontally integrated field spans only fundamental science or engineering, respectively.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Counter to this, in vertical integration, such as in the field of optics, students gain extensive knowledge from the backing science to applied technology.&nbsp;&nbsp;For example, in optics the students understand by the end of their undergraduate studies the three interpretations of light, which is imperative: geometrical (ray-like), physical (wave-like), and quantum (wave-particle duality).&nbsp;&nbsp;To illustrate the need for such consider that lens systems employ geometrical optics in order to effectively design the many lens elements within the bulk lens, physical optics to characterize the limits of image formation within this lens, and quantum optics to explain how the detector interacts with the photons that are imaged upon it.&nbsp;&nbsp;Finally, the lens is employed within an application area, such as biomedical optics (e.g., imaging tissue through an endoscope), lithography (e.g., the stepper lenses that create modern integrated circuits), and remote sensing (e.g., lenses on space-based weather satellites).&nbsp;&nbsp;In conclusion, optics, while its own field, is also used extensively within other STEM fields.&nbsp;&nbsp;The RiO students performed novel research in a multitude of topics: freeform (i.e., optics lacking rotational symmetry) optical design, fabrication and metrology, endoscope design (i.e., biomedical optics), visualization of optics and their inherent aberrations, lidar for autonomous vehicles, quantum control and information, modeling of semiconductors, polarization imaging in both the UV and visible, imaging from highly diffuse reflections, UV microscope design, and novel methods to mount and hold optics (i.e., optomechanics).&nbsp;&nbsp;The REU participants also studied for and took the Graduate Record Examination (GRE), were trained in practical optics workshops, received training in laser and chemical safety, toured a number of research facilities, and took part in discussion sessions about graduate school and careers in optics.&nbsp;&nbsp;These professional development opportunities provided a more in-depth understanding of optics / STEM careers.&nbsp;&nbsp;To date 75% of the RiO alumni have started graduate studies or indicated that they will pursue such upon completion of their undergraduate degrees.&nbsp;Finally, based on the knowledge obtained from the NSF-funded site, the RiO program will be standalone starting in the summer of 2020.&nbsp;&nbsp;Thus, RiO will continue into the future without site-level funding from government agencies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/02/2019<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Koshel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190285314_RiO-Logo-Color-LightBGs-TransBG-300dpi--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190285314_RiO-Logo-Color-LightBGs-TransBG-300dpi--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Logo for the Research in Optics (RiO) program"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190285314_RiO-Logo-Color-LightBGs-TransBG-300dpi--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Logo for the Research in Optics (RiO) program"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Logo for the Research in Optics (RiO) program</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ayala, Koshel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Koshel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Logo for the Research in Optics (RiO) program</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190697466_REU-15-3b--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190697466_REU-15-3b--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2015 RiO cohort celebrating completion of the program"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190697466_REU-15-3b--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2015 RiO cohort celebrating completion of the program"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2015 RiO cohort celebrating completion of the program</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hunt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Koshel</div> <div class="imageTitle">2015 RiO cohort celebrating completion of the program</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190838620_AberrationGenerator--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190838620_AberrationGenerator--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Aberration Generator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554190838620_AberrationGenerator--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Aberration Generator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The aberration generator shows how "light rays" propagate through a lens, showing both the monochromatic and chromatic aberrations of the system</div> <div class="imageCredit">Summitt, Jafari, Takashima</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Koshel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Aberration Generator</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554191040760_Freeform_Painting--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554191040760_Freeform_Painting--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Freeform illumination of painting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554191040760_Freeform_Painting--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Freeform illumination of painting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Geometry of an optical system for uniform illumination of a painting using freeform optics at highly oblique angles</div> <div class="imageCredit">Williams, Ulanch, King, Uthoff, Ruiz Diaz, Steidle, Koshel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Koshel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Freeform illumination of painting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554191339089_Polarization--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554191339089_Polarization--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Flower polarization images"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1460723/1460723_10348013_1554191339089_Polarization--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Flower polarization images"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Six sub images showing the polarization characteristics of a flower, including the Stokes vector (s0 through s3), degree of linear polarization (DoLP), and angle of linear polarization (AoLP).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marin, Ding, Pau</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Koshel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Flower polarization images</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research in Optics (RiO) was a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) funded by the Engineering Directorate of the NSF.  RiO brought undergraduates from all around the county to the College of Optical Sciences, University of Arizona to conduct novel research in the burgeoning field of optics.  Optics plays a leading role in the fourth industrial revolution, which is seen as the integration of technology, especially for connectivity, communication, and computing.  Examples of optics playing an important role include fiber optics (the backbone of the internet), smartphones (through their displays, cameras, and sensors), optical lithography (used to make the ever smaller integrated circuits and photonics within computer chips), security (sensors and detectors along with image-processing technology), and augmented-reality devices (employing light to provide additional information on top of real-world scenes).  To highlight the increasing importance of light and optics, the National Photonics Initiative was started in 2012, the United Nations designated 2015 as the Year of Light, the American Institute for Manufacturing Integrated Photonics (AIM Photonics) started in late 2015, and 2018 marks the start of the National Quantum Initiative.  In order to assist these programs, the nation needs an educated workforce in the area of optics specifically, and Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) in general.  This objective is especially challenging in light of a limited number of programs providing full undergraduate and/or graduate education in optics.  Thus, the primary goal of RiO was to educate the REU participants in the field of optics and encourage them to pursue graduate studies and careers in optics or associated STEM fields.  Additionally, this provides an avenue to encourage women and underrepresented minorities to pursue this rapidly developing field.  By the conclusion of the program, 34 undergraduates from 16 states and 27 institutions of higher learning were alumni of the program.  The number of RiO women and underrepresented minorities were 12 and 10, respectively. The second goal of the RiO program was to introduce the participants to novel research in the field of optics, which spans from the applied to the fundamental.  This breadth is typically denoted as vertical integration rather than horizontal integration.  For example in horizontal integration, one has physics in the fundamental area with subfields including thermal, condensed matter, atomic-molecular-optical, and so forth. Respectively, in the applied arena one can consider electrical engineering, which includes subfields such as power systems, digital, computers, and optics. A given horizontally integrated field spans only fundamental science or engineering, respectively.   Counter to this, in vertical integration, such as in the field of optics, students gain extensive knowledge from the backing science to applied technology.  For example, in optics the students understand by the end of their undergraduate studies the three interpretations of light, which is imperative: geometrical (ray-like), physical (wave-like), and quantum (wave-particle duality).  To illustrate the need for such consider that lens systems employ geometrical optics in order to effectively design the many lens elements within the bulk lens, physical optics to characterize the limits of image formation within this lens, and quantum optics to explain how the detector interacts with the photons that are imaged upon it.  Finally, the lens is employed within an application area, such as biomedical optics (e.g., imaging tissue through an endoscope), lithography (e.g., the stepper lenses that create modern integrated circuits), and remote sensing (e.g., lenses on space-based weather satellites).  In conclusion, optics, while its own field, is also used extensively within other STEM fields.  The RiO students performed novel research in a multitude of topics: freeform (i.e., optics lacking rotational symmetry) optical design, fabrication and metrology, endoscope design (i.e., biomedical optics), visualization of optics and their inherent aberrations, lidar for autonomous vehicles, quantum control and information, modeling of semiconductors, polarization imaging in both the UV and visible, imaging from highly diffuse reflections, UV microscope design, and novel methods to mount and hold optics (i.e., optomechanics).  The REU participants also studied for and took the Graduate Record Examination (GRE), were trained in practical optics workshops, received training in laser and chemical safety, toured a number of research facilities, and took part in discussion sessions about graduate school and careers in optics.  These professional development opportunities provided a more in-depth understanding of optics / STEM careers.  To date 75% of the RiO alumni have started graduate studies or indicated that they will pursue such upon completion of their undergraduate degrees. Finally, based on the knowledge obtained from the NSF-funded site, the RiO program will be standalone starting in the summer of 2020.  Thus, RiO will continue into the future without site-level funding from government agencies.          Last Modified: 04/02/2019       Submitted by: Richard J Koshel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
