<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Integrated Nanomanufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360757.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>410757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>BROADER SIGNIFICANCE OF THE PROJECT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanomanufacturing research is an emerging interdisciplinary area at the intersection of nanotechnology and fabrication. Nanotechnology seeks to develop and synthesize systems that manipulate, measure or control physical processes at the nanoscale, while integrated nanomanufacturing incorporates nanofabrication and materials research. The Boston University (BU) REU Site in Integrated Nanomanufacturing will bring ten undergraduate students from universities and two-year colleges to engage in summer research in more than 30 potential interdisciplinary labs in Nanotechnology, Electrical and Computer, Biomedical, Materials Science, and/or Mechanical Engineering at the Boston University Charles River campus. The REU Site will offer an interdisciplinary and transformative experience to students from varying engineering disciplines that reflect the diversity of the BU mentors in Integrated Nanomanufacturing. The program's target is to recruit at least 50% of the 10 participants from underrepresented minorities and at least 50% female participants. Training female and underrepresented minorities from universities that have limited STEM research capabilities for graduate studies will provide the largest impact to diversifying future role models in nanotechnology. Participants will be immersed in research while simultaneously gaining an education in the proper techniques for research via mentored training from faculty and graduate students with clear learning goals agreed upon at the start of the program. The REU site program will be organized into various training sessions, hands-on cleanroom activities, scientific research in appointed laboratories and seminars for undergraduate research students. The Boston University NSF REU Site in Integrated Nanomanufacturing will provide a program with the aim of educating a diverse group of the next generation of engineers in nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PROJECT DESCRIPTION:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants will be mentored and coached through a unique problem-based research experience, from basic skills building to open-ended discovery, with a focus on developing research independence. Through the mentored training, participants will also engage in a training program of nanotechnology content, skills development, and career preparation with a focus on interdisciplinary engineering topics. Participants will also be immersed in a positive research culture in the mentor's laboratories and through the research mentoring training program that favorably shapes the mentee's and mentor's awareness, confidence and understanding of research, graduate school and other STEM career choices. Students will participate in mentored discovery, engineering of new devices, and fabrication at the nanoscale level to explore optical and integrated nanoscale systems, while developing critical skills, awareness and confidence necessary to advance along their career pathways in academics and research. Through this site, students will gain the opportunity to share their work with the research community at BU through presentations and to also submit to national conferences or co-author publications based on their research. Three thematic research areas will serve as the foundation for this REU Site: 1) Materials synthesis and characterization, 2) Combination photonic and electronic nanostructures, and 3) Integration of nanosystems that generate, sense, and manipulate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will emphasize the participation of underrepresented minority students, including novices (first and second year undergraduates) to establish primarily racial and ethnic, but also institutional, technical, and experiential diversity among the participants and to seed greater diversity in the national graduate student applicant pool. Recruiting will utilize strong existing relationships BU has with historically Black colleges and Universities (HBCU's) and Hispanic serving institutions (HSI's). Recruiting for this NSF REU site will also be concentrated on two-year colleges as well as four-year colleges that lack graduate research in STEM. As part of the REU site goals, a minimum of 50% of ten participants will be from colleges where graduate research opportunities in STEM are unavailable with a minimum of 50% underrepresented minorities and 50% female participants to be recruited. Undergraduate students who are veterans of the U.S. Armed Services will also be encouraged to apply.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF REU site Integrated Nanomanufacturing has been funded by the National Science Foundation Division of Engineering Education and Centers (EEC).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xin Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xinz@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173582702</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000096200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Helen</FirstName>
<LastName>Fawcett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Helen Fawcett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hfawcett@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8577531719</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022150001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8 Saint Mary's Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1359</Code>
<Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>EWFD-Eng Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~360757</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>Three thematic research areas served as the foundation for this REU Site in Integrated Nanomanufacturing: 1) materials synthesis and characterization, 2) combination photonic and electronic nanostructures, and 3) integration of nanosystems that generate, sense, and manipulate. Students participated in mentored discovery, engineering of new devices, and fabrication at the nanoscale level to explore optical and integrated nanoscale systems, while developing the critical skills, awareness and confidence necessary to advance along their career pathways in academics and research. Through this site students had the opportunity to share their work with the research community at BU through presentations, to submit to national conferences, and co-author publications based on their research. Through group projects with a planned/staged outcome, students learned about nanotechnology fabrication processes that will be useful in their laboratory research. In the mentor labs, students conducted research that was not staged and was part of the research being conducted by the group; their research outcomes directly impacted or assisted the lab in exploring new areas. Students became independent researchers and about four weeks into the program, became mentors for their teacher counterparts that arrive on campus as part of the complementary NSF RET Site in Integrated Nanomanufacturing. The teachers contributed the scientific method of inquiry to the team and the students contributed knowledge and training, creating a cohesive research teams that learned from each other as they completed their summer research efforts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>The broader impact aim of the program was to educate members of the next generation of engineers in nanotechnology. Through collaboration and commitment from the Smart Lighting ERC, the Photonics Center, the NSF I/UCRC CBSS, and a pipeline of Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCU) and Hispanic Serving Institutions (HSI) partners, this site gained a strong, diverse pool of candidates. The participant demographics included 65% female and 76% underrepresented minorities in engineering. 45% of the participants in the program were considered novice students (first- and second-year undergraduates from two and four-year institutions). 44% of the participants in the REU program had no graduate STEM engineering research at their institutions. Those with limited STEM engineering graduate research programs at their institution (one or fewer of the four engineering majors available) was 55%. The goals of the program included at least 50% minority in engineering and 50% female participants, and at least 50% participation from institutions with limited STEM graduate research programs. In addition to our established relationships with HCBUs and HSIs, through the recruitment process we developed new and lasting relationships with additional partner institutions. Recruitment of undergraduates without a graduate research program at their home institution and students from 2-year colleges had the greatest impact on the future generation of engineers. From our senior population (19 participants), about 63% have pursued graduate degrees and 37% pursued jobs in industry. Students continue engagement with the faculty, PI and co-PI long after their summer research has passed. They often check in or respond to our inquires and help us to recruit more students by telling them about the program and encouraging them to apply to our program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Using anonymous evaluation, students reported statistically valid gains in their self-reported understanding of how research is conducted; 80% of those surveyed identified that participation in the REU program clarified their attitudes toward pursuing a career in science and 80% noted that participation was a clear indicator of their desire to pursue a graduate degree. 90% of those surveyed reported overwhelmingly that the experience enabled them to determine that they would like to pursue a career that included research. 45% of our participants had never participated in summer research and 50% had never participated in academic year research at their institution. 95% of the students indicated that participation in the REU helped develop research skills identified this as important to their career goals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Xin&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066571879_MG_5641--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066571879_MG_5641--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF REU and RET INM participants share a nanoparticles fabrication lab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066571879_MG_5641--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF REU and RET INM participants share a nanoparticles fabrication lab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF REU and INM participants work together in a chemistry teaching lab, where they create nanoparticles. As part of this session, they will work on characterizing the particles they created to learn imaging and characterization techniques commonly used in nanotechnology applications</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ben Bonadies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;Fawcett</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF REU and RET INM participants share a nanoparticles fabrication lab</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066857179_2016REUonstairs--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066857179_2016REUonstairs--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF REU INM - summer 2016 cohort"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066857179_2016REUonstairs--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF REU INM - summer 2016 cohort"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PI (Xin Zhang, far left) and Co-PI (Helen Fawcett, far right) on stairs at Boston University Photonics Center with summer 2016 NSF REU INM cohort.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Vanessa Quintero</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;Fawcett</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF REU INM - summer 2016 cohort</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616260316_REU17-icecreamtruck--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616260316_REU17-icecreamtruck--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF REU INM - summer 2017 cohort"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616260316_REU17-icecreamtruck--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF REU INM - summer 2017 cohort"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The NSF REU INM summer 2017 cohort enjoys a cool summer break from the lab with the PI, Xin Zhang, lower left and Co-PI, Helen Fawcett, upper right at the Boston University Photonics Center annual ice cream truck social.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ben Bonadies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;Fawcett</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF REU INM - summer 2017 cohort</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616455370_REU15--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616455370_REU15--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF REU INM - summer 2015 cohort"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616455370_REU15--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF REU INM - summer 2015 cohort"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF REU INM summer 2015 cohort spends several sessions in the Boston University Optoelectronic Facility Cleanroom. As part of the introduction day, the participants learn how to gown up, receive a tour of the cleanroom and prepare for the next week's photolithography session.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emily Biehl</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;Fawcett</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF REU INM - summer 2015 cohort</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616989780_REUincleanroom--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616989780_REUincleanroom--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF REU INM participant in the cleanroom"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562616989780_REUincleanroom--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF REU INM participant in the cleanroom"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF REU INM participant works alongside her faculty and graduate student mentor as she operates the CHA evaporation system to complete her research work.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Helen Fawcett</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;Fawcett</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF REU INM participant in the cleanroom</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066392125_REUINM2018--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066392125_REUINM2018--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF REU INM - summer 2018 cohort"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1461152/1461152_10346808_1562066392125_REUINM2018--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF REU INM - summer 2018 cohort"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The PI and co-PI (Xin Zhang and Helen Fawcett, far left) with no cost extension and supplemental NSF REU INM students from summer 2018 cohort</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lilia Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;Fawcett</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF REU INM - summer 2018 cohort</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  Three thematic research areas served as the foundation for this REU Site in Integrated Nanomanufacturing: 1) materials synthesis and characterization, 2) combination photonic and electronic nanostructures, and 3) integration of nanosystems that generate, sense, and manipulate. Students participated in mentored discovery, engineering of new devices, and fabrication at the nanoscale level to explore optical and integrated nanoscale systems, while developing the critical skills, awareness and confidence necessary to advance along their career pathways in academics and research. Through this site students had the opportunity to share their work with the research community at BU through presentations, to submit to national conferences, and co-author publications based on their research. Through group projects with a planned/staged outcome, students learned about nanotechnology fabrication processes that will be useful in their laboratory research. In the mentor labs, students conducted research that was not staged and was part of the research being conducted by the group; their research outcomes directly impacted or assisted the lab in exploring new areas. Students became independent researchers and about four weeks into the program, became mentors for their teacher counterparts that arrive on campus as part of the complementary NSF RET Site in Integrated Nanomanufacturing. The teachers contributed the scientific method of inquiry to the team and the students contributed knowledge and training, creating a cohesive research teams that learned from each other as they completed their summer research efforts.     Broader Impacts:  The broader impact aim of the program was to educate members of the next generation of engineers in nanotechnology. Through collaboration and commitment from the Smart Lighting ERC, the Photonics Center, the NSF I/UCRC CBSS, and a pipeline of Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCU) and Hispanic Serving Institutions (HSI) partners, this site gained a strong, diverse pool of candidates. The participant demographics included 65% female and 76% underrepresented minorities in engineering. 45% of the participants in the program were considered novice students (first- and second-year undergraduates from two and four-year institutions). 44% of the participants in the REU program had no graduate STEM engineering research at their institutions. Those with limited STEM engineering graduate research programs at their institution (one or fewer of the four engineering majors available) was 55%. The goals of the program included at least 50% minority in engineering and 50% female participants, and at least 50% participation from institutions with limited STEM graduate research programs. In addition to our established relationships with HCBUs and HSIs, through the recruitment process we developed new and lasting relationships with additional partner institutions. Recruitment of undergraduates without a graduate research program at their home institution and students from 2-year colleges had the greatest impact on the future generation of engineers. From our senior population (19 participants), about 63% have pursued graduate degrees and 37% pursued jobs in industry. Students continue engagement with the faculty, PI and co-PI long after their summer research has passed. They often check in or respond to our inquires and help us to recruit more students by telling them about the program and encouraging them to apply to our program.     Using anonymous evaluation, students reported statistically valid gains in their self-reported understanding of how research is conducted; 80% of those surveyed identified that participation in the REU program clarified their attitudes toward pursuing a career in science and 80% noted that participation was a clear indicator of their desire to pursue a graduate degree. 90% of those surveyed reported overwhelmingly that the experience enabled them to determine that they would like to pursue a career that included research. 45% of our participants had never participated in summer research and 50% had never participated in academic year research at their institution. 95% of the students indicated that participation in the REU helped develop research skills identified this as important to their career goals.          Last Modified: 07/09/2019       Submitted by: Xin Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
