<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nanoscale Sintering Understanding</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300682.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>336682</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alewis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sintering is an important materials consolidation and densification strategy. It is used to make components with complex shapes, in near net-shapes, and with relatively simple equipment. Also, different compositions and structures can be flexibly tailored using sintering. However, sintering is also a complex process. With the progress of nanoparticle-based materials, many conventional sintering theories cannot predict new sintering behaviors; relying on existing sintering knowledge to guide nanoparticle-based material processing has led to numerous failures and contradictory results. This award supports fundamental research to build our understanding of the sintering process, to test the scalability of sintering equations from nanometers up, and to quantify the function of pores in nanostructure evolution and shrinkage. Successful nano-sintering represents exciting possibilities in improved structural, electrical, optical, and other functional properties and unprecedented nanostructures. The application areas are numerous, including energy storage/conversion, nanophotonic devices, microfluidic devices, catalysts, microreactor devices, and optical components. This program also includes extensive outreach activities (such as HBCU, local schools, camps) to increase the participation of underrepresented groups in engineering, especially in the area of nanomaterials.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This award supports research to build direct and quantitative sintering shrinkage-nanostructure evolution correlations, test the scalability of sintering equations from nanoscale and up, and quantify the function of pores in nanostructure evolution and shrinkage. There are three key components to this research. The first is to demonstrate that below a critical density, shrinkage extrapolation from grain neck size is dependent on coarsening-induced grain-reconfiguration; microstructure scalability is only valid for homogenous microstructures. The second is to show that above the critical density, pore size, distribution, and shape are critical factors for decoupling grain boundary diffusion from grain boundary migration and 3D microstructure reconstruction is a unique technique to provide such quantitative data. The third component is to illustrate that sintering of particle packing in unusual configurations is dependent on the balance between packing structures and diffusion mechanisms. The research will provide the much needed linkage between nanoparticle arrangement, microstructural evolution, and shrinkage by using small features that can track individual to multiple nanoparticles and reconstructing 3D nanostructures. The sintering knowledge gained will provide not only effective solutions to nanoparticle-based sintering but also never-before conduits for net-shape sintering, novel nanostructures, and a vast array of complex material design capabilities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461516</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathy</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathy Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>klu@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402313225</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000285204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[445 Old Turner Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>088E</Code>
<Text>THERMALLY DRIVEN PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~310682</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sintering is an important material consolidation and densification strategy. It can make components with complex shapes, in near net-shapes, and with much simpler equipment. Also, different composition arrangements and porous microstructures can be flexibly tailored. However, sintering is also a complex process. With the progress of nanoparticle-based materials, many conventional sintering theories cannot predict new sintering behaviors.</p> <p>During this project, we have developed an efficient approach of making micron and sub-micron features: centrifuge-aided micromolding, followed by comprehensive sintering studies. In-depth theories were developed and extensive calculations were carried out to provide fundamental understanding of suspension-based micron- and submicron-sized feature formation process. We also advanced the understanding of the sintering behaviors of micron-sized ZnO features and provided predictive ability for the micron- and submicron-sized feature sintering process.</p> <p>With the use of a focused ion beam and an electron beam, slice-by-slice imaging was conducted to obtain the microstructures of the sintered samples. Amira software was used to align at least a hundred images in the depth direction of the sample and obtain quantiative microstrucrual data. Thus, 3D microstrcutre reconstruction was achieved for the isothermal sintered micron-sized ridges and rods. We further explained the new relationships between the relative density and grain sizes of the sintered ridges. We also investigated pore shape evolution. These were all new sintering knowledge that was not available before.</p> <p>Taking the advantages of the small size features that we created, we were able to study the atmosphere effects on small component sintering. The evolution of ZnO ridges was explored based on ridge size, line edge roughness, grain size, apparent shrinkage, and relative density. It provided a new comprehensive viewpoint on the feature shape evolution process, different from the traditional understanding of bulk samples.</p> <p>Focusing on ZnO and ZrO<sub>2</sub>, the effects of material species on the evolution of the micron-sized ridge features during sintering were explored based on the ridge morphology, fidelity, grain size, relative density, and linear shrinkage. The sintering behaviors and mechanisms of ZnO and ZrO<sub>2</sub> in bulk and micron-sized features were studied with consideration of the coupling effect from densification and grain growth.</p> <p>Additionally, the sintering behaviors and mechanisms of micron-sized ZnO rod features were studied. Relative density, shrinkage, grain size, and rod circularity were measured, and the difference in the sintering behaviors between the rods and the bulk was revealed by a new factor based on the theoretical modeling and Voronoi diagram simulation. The destruction effects derived from the feature sintering were investigated. Sintering behavior, feature evolution, and roughening were explored. Prediction of feature destruction was proposed with respect to sintering time and relative density.</p> <p>These studies helped to build direct and quantitative sintering shrinkage-nanostructure evolution correlations, test the scalability of sintering equations at nanoscale, and quantify the function of pores in nanostructure evolution and shrinkage. With such knowledge, components and devices made by sintering will have improved structural, electrical, optical, and other functional properties. The application areas are numerous, including energy storage/conversion, nanophotonic devices, microfluidic devices, catalysts, microreactor devices, and optical components.</p> <p>Through this project, we have supported multiple graduate students (including a female PhD student) and undergraduate students (including 4 female students and one Africa American male student). We also conducted extensive outreach activities to HBCU, summer camps, and science museum to increase the enrollment of females and minorities in engineering. In addition, we have been an active participant of on-campus communities to encourage and retain female engineering students, such as Women&rsquo;s Preview Weekend and Hypatia. These efforts will not only improve female and minority students&rsquo; understanding and knowledge base about nanomaterials but more importantly will show them the career potentials in engineering.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Kathy&nbsp;Lu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863788929_Fig.3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863788929_Fig.3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="3D reconstructed features"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863788929_Fig.3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="3D reconstructed features"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">3D reconstruction of different features in micron-sized ridges.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Ning, K. Lu, H. Ju, ?Sintering behaviors of micron-sized features based on 3D reconstruction" Acta Materialia, submitted</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathy&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">3D reconstructed features</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863676002_Fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863676002_Fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Centrifugal molding effect"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863676002_Fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Centrifugal molding effect"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Centrifugal molding parameters that affect the pattern quality</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Ning, K. Lu, ?Fundamental understanding of centrifugal micromolding for high fidelity patterns,? Journal of the European Ceramic Society</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathy&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Centrifugal molding effect</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864039340_Fig.4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864039340_Fig.4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Atmosphere effect"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864039340_Fig.4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Atmosphere effect"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sintering atmosphere effect on  features of different material types</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Ning, H. Ju, K. Lu, ?Effects of ceramic types on evolution of micron-sized features during sintering,? Journal of the American Ceramic Society, accepted</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathy&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Atmosphere effect</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864200637_Fig.5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864200637_Fig.5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Microstructure evolution"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864200637_Fig.5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Microstructure evolution"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Microstructure evolution simulated by Voronoi diagram</div> <div class="imageCredit">H. Ju, K. Ning, K. Lu, ?Sintering Behaviors of Micron-Sized Ceramic Rod Feature,? Acta Materialia, 144 (1) 534-542, 2018</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathy&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Microstructure evolution</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864339521_Fig.6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864339521_Fig.6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Feature destruction"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527864339521_Fig.6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Feature destruction"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Micron-sized feature roughening and destruction and theoretical prediction</div> <div class="imageCredit">H. Ju, K. Ning, K. Lu, ?Roughening and Destructive Effect of Sintering on Micron-Sized ZnO Features,? Acta Materialia, 141, 352-359, 2017.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathy&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Feature destruction</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863536802_Fig.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863536802_Fig.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Centrifugal molding"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1461516/1461516_10353901_1527863536802_Fig.1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Centrifugal molding"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Illustration of our centrifuge-aided patterning process.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Ning, K. Lu, ?Fundamental understanding of centrifugal micromolding for high fidelity patterns,? Journal of the European Ceramic Society</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kathy&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Centrifugal molding</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sintering is an important material consolidation and densification strategy. It can make components with complex shapes, in near net-shapes, and with much simpler equipment. Also, different composition arrangements and porous microstructures can be flexibly tailored. However, sintering is also a complex process. With the progress of nanoparticle-based materials, many conventional sintering theories cannot predict new sintering behaviors.  During this project, we have developed an efficient approach of making micron and sub-micron features: centrifuge-aided micromolding, followed by comprehensive sintering studies. In-depth theories were developed and extensive calculations were carried out to provide fundamental understanding of suspension-based micron- and submicron-sized feature formation process. We also advanced the understanding of the sintering behaviors of micron-sized ZnO features and provided predictive ability for the micron- and submicron-sized feature sintering process.  With the use of a focused ion beam and an electron beam, slice-by-slice imaging was conducted to obtain the microstructures of the sintered samples. Amira software was used to align at least a hundred images in the depth direction of the sample and obtain quantiative microstrucrual data. Thus, 3D microstrcutre reconstruction was achieved for the isothermal sintered micron-sized ridges and rods. We further explained the new relationships between the relative density and grain sizes of the sintered ridges. We also investigated pore shape evolution. These were all new sintering knowledge that was not available before.  Taking the advantages of the small size features that we created, we were able to study the atmosphere effects on small component sintering. The evolution of ZnO ridges was explored based on ridge size, line edge roughness, grain size, apparent shrinkage, and relative density. It provided a new comprehensive viewpoint on the feature shape evolution process, different from the traditional understanding of bulk samples.  Focusing on ZnO and ZrO2, the effects of material species on the evolution of the micron-sized ridge features during sintering were explored based on the ridge morphology, fidelity, grain size, relative density, and linear shrinkage. The sintering behaviors and mechanisms of ZnO and ZrO2 in bulk and micron-sized features were studied with consideration of the coupling effect from densification and grain growth.  Additionally, the sintering behaviors and mechanisms of micron-sized ZnO rod features were studied. Relative density, shrinkage, grain size, and rod circularity were measured, and the difference in the sintering behaviors between the rods and the bulk was revealed by a new factor based on the theoretical modeling and Voronoi diagram simulation. The destruction effects derived from the feature sintering were investigated. Sintering behavior, feature evolution, and roughening were explored. Prediction of feature destruction was proposed with respect to sintering time and relative density.  These studies helped to build direct and quantitative sintering shrinkage-nanostructure evolution correlations, test the scalability of sintering equations at nanoscale, and quantify the function of pores in nanostructure evolution and shrinkage. With such knowledge, components and devices made by sintering will have improved structural, electrical, optical, and other functional properties. The application areas are numerous, including energy storage/conversion, nanophotonic devices, microfluidic devices, catalysts, microreactor devices, and optical components.  Through this project, we have supported multiple graduate students (including a female PhD student) and undergraduate students (including 4 female students and one Africa American male student). We also conducted extensive outreach activities to HBCU, summer camps, and science museum to increase the enrollment of females and minorities in engineering. In addition, we have been an active participant of on-campus communities to encourage and retain female engineering students, such as Women?s Preview Weekend and Hypatia. These efforts will not only improve female and minority students? understanding and knowledge base about nanomaterials but more importantly will show them the career potentials in engineering.          Last Modified: 06/01/2018       Submitted by: Kathy Lu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
