<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Accelerator Physics and Synchrotron Radiation Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>404625.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404625</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the continuation of the Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site in physics at Cornell University.   The students will work on a range of projects that advance the Laboratory's scientific mission, further their education and training, and heighten their interest in pursuing careers in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines.  Although the research scope of this REU program is focused on understanding the fundamental physics of beams and accelerators and the uses of the radiation they produce, the techniques and technologies utilized are applicable to a much wider range of scientific careers. Each student is asked to participate in one of the outreach programs at the Laboratory, teaching them to communicate the scientific ideas with the general public and exposing them to the outreach prospects at their home institutions, through the Student Physical Society (SPS) chapters and other outlets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Cornell Laboratory has an international reputation for research, with a unique constellation of programs including accelerator physics, synchrotron radiation research, and microwave superconductivity. The student participants have full access to the resources of the Laboratory and University, and will work closely with Laboratory experienced researchers. The students will participate in joint activities that include lectures of wide topics in the accelerator physics and X-ray science; take part with a bigger body of REU groups on campus in fun-talks and hands-on activities that introduce various frontiers of physics research; and attend events addressing the social and ethical issues in scientific research and conduct. These joint activities provide an excellent environment for networking of the future scientists.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461111</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georg</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffstaetter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georg H Hoffstaetter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gh77@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555197</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000322135</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bazarov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan V Bazarov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ib38@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072542781</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~129591</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~134855</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~140179</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This report serves as a brief summary, prepared specifically for the public, of the nature and outcomes of this NSF-funded project and is in addition to the final project report.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Accelerated particle beams have a wide range of applications from the basic sciences to the production of computer chips with yet higher information density and to truck- or ship-penetrating investigation systems for border security. Nuclear physics and elementary particle physics has relied on accelerators for decades and many Nobel prizes have only become possible with these instruments. X-ray science uses focused x-rays, usually from accelerators, to investigate materials, from hair fractures in airplane wings to the atomic structure of viruses, of proteins, or of pharmaceuticals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This REU program at Cornell's laboratory for accelerator based sciences and education (CLASSE) has provided research opportunities for 54 undergraduate students form all across the US, nearly 50% of which came from underrepresented groups. Research topics were in the field of X-ray science, analyzing a large variety of materials (medical, biological, chemical, and mechanical, and more), in the field of Accelerator Physics that enables the particle accelerators producing the X-rays, and including accelerators that enable elementary particle physics, and in the field of Superconducting Radio-Frequency structures, which are the integral parts in many accelerators that supply energy to particle beams.</p> <p>Each student worked for 10 weeks supervised by a practicing scientist in the environment of a vibrant research laboratory on a forefront research project that often lead to publication in a scientific journal or to presentation in a scientific conference. Student were exposed to all major projects of the laboratory by introductory talks, and learned about good research practices, laboratory safety, and ethical standards in the sciences. Additionally, each student participated in outreach activities for the general public, making science results accessible to non-scientists. Fun presentations and group events made this summer a valuable experience for all involved.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Georg&nbsp;H&nbsp;Hoffstaetter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This report serves as a brief summary, prepared specifically for the public, of the nature and outcomes of this NSF-funded project and is in addition to the final project report.     Accelerated particle beams have a wide range of applications from the basic sciences to the production of computer chips with yet higher information density and to truck- or ship-penetrating investigation systems for border security. Nuclear physics and elementary particle physics has relied on accelerators for decades and many Nobel prizes have only become possible with these instruments. X-ray science uses focused x-rays, usually from accelerators, to investigate materials, from hair fractures in airplane wings to the atomic structure of viruses, of proteins, or of pharmaceuticals.     This REU program at Cornell's laboratory for accelerator based sciences and education (CLASSE) has provided research opportunities for 54 undergraduate students form all across the US, nearly 50% of which came from underrepresented groups. Research topics were in the field of X-ray science, analyzing a large variety of materials (medical, biological, chemical, and mechanical, and more), in the field of Accelerator Physics that enables the particle accelerators producing the X-rays, and including accelerators that enable elementary particle physics, and in the field of Superconducting Radio-Frequency structures, which are the integral parts in many accelerators that supply energy to particle beams.  Each student worked for 10 weeks supervised by a practicing scientist in the environment of a vibrant research laboratory on a forefront research project that often lead to publication in a scientific journal or to presentation in a scientific conference. Student were exposed to all major projects of the laboratory by introductory talks, and learned about good research practices, laboratory safety, and ethical standards in the sciences. Additionally, each student participated in outreach activities for the general public, making science results accessible to non-scientists. Fun presentations and group events made this summer a valuable experience for all involved.       Last Modified: 06/07/2019       Submitted by: Georg H Hoffstaetter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
