<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chemical Reactions at Surfaces GRC/GRS - From Model Studies to Complex Real World Systems, February 7-8, 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis (CAT) program in the Division of Chemistry supports this project which provides funds for the attendance and research presentations of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers from U.S. universities at the Chemical Reactions at Surfaces Gordon Research Seminar to be held on February 7-8, 2015 at the Ventura Beach Marriott in Ventura Beach, CA. Knowledge about chemical reactions at surfaces underpins important technologies such as catalysis and economically important industries that utilize catalysis.  The Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) will involve seminars, poster presentations and discussion on this topic broadly, and the subsequent Gordon Research Conference (GRC) that the students and postdocs will be able to attend will focus specifically on topics of theory and computation of reactions at surfaces, environmental chemistry, fundamental mechanistic studies, catalysis, new materials for surface chemistry, and surface layer chemistry.  Historically, Gordon Research Seminars and Conferences are a forum for scientists to present and discuss pre-publication results and data.  The discussion serves to shape the future of the field and to provide an opportunity for scientists of all career stages and expertise to interact in formal and informal settings.  Thus, the GRS/GRC provides a means to create scientific networks and to develop human resources needed to further science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461831</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Gellman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew J Gellman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ag4b@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122683848</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000442815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>West Kinsgton</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028920001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Gordon Research Conference on CHEMICAL REACTIONS AT SURFACES was held at the<br />Ventura Beach Marriott, Ventura, California, January 8-13th, 2015. The<br />Conference was well-attended with 142 participants (attendees list attached).<br />The attendees represented the spectrum of endeavor in this field coming from academia,<br />industry, and government laboratories, both U.S. and foreign scientists, senior<br />researchers, young investigators, and students. Of the 142 attendees, 48<br />voluntarily responded to a general inquiry regarding ethnicity which appears on<br />our registration forms. Of the 48 respondents, 19% were Minorities &ndash; 4%<br />Hispanic, 15% Asian and 0% African American. Approximately &nbsp;29% of the participants at the 2015 meeting<br />were women.</p> <p><br />The Gordon Research Seminar on CHEMICAL REACTIONS AT SURFACES was held at the Ventura&nbsp; Beach Marriott, Ventura, California, January 7-8<sup>th</sup>,<br />2015. The Conference was well-attended with 52 participants (attendees list<br />attached). The attendees represented the spectrum of endeavor in this field<br />coming from academia, industry, and government laboratories, both U.S.<br />and foreign scientists, senior researchers, young investigators, and students.<br />Of the 52 attendees, 14 voluntarily responded to a general inquiry regarding<br />ethnicity which appears on our registration forms. Of the 14 respondents, 14%<br />were Minorities &ndash; 0% Hispanic, 14% Asian and 0% African American.<br />Approximately&nbsp; 39% of the participants at<br />the 2015 meeting were women.</p> <p><br />In designing the<br />formal speakers program, emphasis was placed on current unpublished research<br />and discussion of the future target areas in this field. There was a conscious<br />effort to stimulate lively discussion about the key issues in the field today.<br />Time for formal presentations was limited in the interest of group discussions.<br />In order that more scientists could communicate their most recent results,<br />poster presentation time was scheduled. Attached is a copy of the formal<br />schedule and speaker program and the poster program. In addition to these<br />formal interactions, "free time" was scheduled to allow informal<br />discussions. Such discussions are fostering new collaborations and joint<br />efforts in the field.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/03/2015<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;J&nbsp;Gellman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Gordon Research Conference on CHEMICAL REACTIONS AT SURFACES was held at the Ventura Beach Marriott, Ventura, California, January 8-13th, 2015. The Conference was well-attended with 142 participants (attendees list attached). The attendees represented the spectrum of endeavor in this field coming from academia, industry, and government laboratories, both U.S. and foreign scientists, senior researchers, young investigators, and students. Of the 142 attendees, 48 voluntarily responded to a general inquiry regarding ethnicity which appears on our registration forms. Of the 48 respondents, 19% were Minorities &ndash; 4% Hispanic, 15% Asian and 0% African American. Approximately  29% of the participants at the 2015 meeting were women.   The Gordon Research Seminar on CHEMICAL REACTIONS AT SURFACES was held at the Ventura  Beach Marriott, Ventura, California, January 7-8th, 2015. The Conference was well-attended with 52 participants (attendees list attached). The attendees represented the spectrum of endeavor in this field coming from academia, industry, and government laboratories, both U.S. and foreign scientists, senior researchers, young investigators, and students. Of the 52 attendees, 14 voluntarily responded to a general inquiry regarding ethnicity which appears on our registration forms. Of the 14 respondents, 14% were Minorities &ndash; 0% Hispanic, 14% Asian and 0% African American. Approximately  39% of the participants at the 2015 meeting were women.   In designing the formal speakers program, emphasis was placed on current unpublished research and discussion of the future target areas in this field. There was a conscious effort to stimulate lively discussion about the key issues in the field today. Time for formal presentations was limited in the interest of group discussions. In order that more scientists could communicate their most recent results, poster presentation time was scheduled. Attached is a copy of the formal schedule and speaker program and the poster program. In addition to these formal interactions, "free time" was scheduled to allow informal discussions. Such discussions are fostering new collaborations and joint efforts in the field.       Last Modified: 06/03/2015       Submitted by: Andrew J Gellman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
