<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Creating Woodlands: Integrating Land-Use Practices and New Savanna Models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249634.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249634</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Scott Freundschuh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sfreunds@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927076</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will focus on determining the mechanisms through which everyday land-management practices create conditions conducive to the establishment and growth of highly valued trees in savannah environments.  The project also will seek to improve capabilities for predicting how shifts in management practices will impact future environments.  Savannas long have posed a conundrum for scientists, with uncertainty remaining regarding how trees and grasses coexist in the same parkland landscapes and what factors prevent one vegetation form from dominating the other.  This project will address fundamental questions of savanna science pertaining to competition between grasses and trees at different life-cycle phases in a mesic savanna.  It will integrate new theories of disequilibrium ecology and human land-use practices to determine the long-term impacts of human actions on tree establishment and growth in parklands, and it will provide valuable historical data about how parklands form over time.  The project will enhance understanding of how savanna parklands are created through human-environment interactions, thereby providing critical information for foresters and land managers seeking to improve parkland management and to reverse trends that have seen the parklands decline.  The project will inform the development of models of carbon sequestration, and it will provide information to improve economic livelihoods for those who rely on savannah environments, especially the products of highly valued trees, for their well-being.  The project also will help assess the use of unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs, often known as drones) as an inexpensive means for gathering data at local scales in the study area and in other parts of the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Explaining the mechanisms that determine the ratio of trees to grasses within landscapes has long been of interest to geographers, ecologists, and others interested in the basic functioning and distribution of the Earth's ecosystems. Recent scientific developments have increased the importance of this task, because in mesic areas that receive intermediate amounts of rainfall, both forests and savannas persist, which indicates that savanna is a different stated from a tropical forest.  These alternative states cover vast areas, including large parts of Africa as well as parts of the Americas. Tree cover now is thought to be largely determined by fire and other disturbance regimes, including human land management.  This project will consist of a focused case study of the role of human practices in determining disturbance regimes in savannas where people set nearly all fires and are responsible for rotational agriculture and animal grazing.  The investigators will work in the western African nation of Mali.  The investigators will test hypotheses that manipulation of woody environments has been both conscious and unconscious in savanna and that it has been a factor in the selection of specific valued tree species, such as shea trees (Vitellaria paradoxa), which yield a fruit that consists of a nutritious pulp and an oil-rich seed from which shea butter can be processed.  The investigators will pursue three interconnected sets of activities. They will conduct field experiments to test the hypothesis that specific human practices differentially affect specific tree species at different times in the lives of the trees.  They will analyze a natural experiment, combining field and remote sensing methods to test the hypothesis that disturbance history determines current vegetation cover more so than biophysical conditions, and they will conduct ethnographic research to learn how people occupying savannas understand human-plant interactions and dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461345</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher T Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Christopher.lee@csulb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3109755764</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000456303</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/24/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Laris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Laris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Paul.laris@csulb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5629852357</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000441281</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Winslow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Winslow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Scott.Winslow@csulb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5629854305</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000746949</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State University-Long Beach Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Long Beach</CityName>
<ZipCode>908154670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5629858051</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6300 State Univ. Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[St. 332]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006199129</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY, LONG BEACH RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006199129</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Long Beach]]></Name>
<CityName>Long Beach</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>908400004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1250 Bellflower Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9186</Code>
<Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9278</Code>
<Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~249634</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to address basic questions pertaining to the science of savanna ecology and biogeography by answering fundamental questions about the forces that shape the ratio of trees to grasses in savanna landscapes. In recent decades, new savanna ecological theory has emerged built on the concept that forces determining tree cover depend upon the annual rainfall regime. In savannas with higher rainfall, so-called mesic savannas, disturbances such as frequent fires reduce tree growth rates and trap trees in a juvenile stage preventing them from reaching adulthood. According to this model, trees only escape the firetrap during rare events such as abnormal rainfall or a lack of fire for several years. Semi-arid savannas, with lower rainfall, operate under a different model. In these arid lands, limited access to water restricts tree cover. Understanding the forces that determine tree cover in savannas is critical for both sustaining livelihoods, because the ratio of tree to grasses determines the resources available for human use such as animal fodder or forest products as well as for carbon sequestration in mesic savannas, which can theoretically support a denser tree layer.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Our study challenged the underlying notion that disturbance intensity alone governs tree growth and escape rates in mesic savannas. We designed a field test to determine whether grasses compete strongly with juvenile trees (less than two meters tall) to reduce tree growth rates. Our field test examined the effects of four different grass reduction treatments on tree growth rates: (i) herbicide, (ii) grass clipping, (iii) grazing, and (iv) traditional hoeing. Our study found that two years of grass removal resulted in a statistically significant increase in juvenile tree growth varying from 147 to 205% depending on the treatment. Grass treatments of hoeing, clipping and herbicide resulted in fewer tree deaths than the control, while grazing caused an increase in deaths. To test the ecological significance of the increase in tree growth rates, our study included a fire experiment to determine how fires set at different times during the long dry season--early, middle and late affect tree growth and death. We found that both early and late fires resulted in increased tree growth rates over the control, although late fires resulted in more tree deaths. Surprisingly, we found that growth rates on trees subjected to mid-season burning did not differ from the control.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A critical outcome of the study is that the increase in tree growth by reducing grass competition for two years is enough to allow trees to escape the firetrap (trees grow enough to reach a height of three meters sufficient to escape top-kill from fire). In practice, this means that savannas treated by hoeing, grass mowing or herbicides for just two years become significantly more wooded. Trees are long living and mature trees shade out grasses, as such, once juvenile trees escape, they theoretically transform the savanna for decades because mature trees are fire resistant. Such savanna transformation would have implications for carbon sequestration in tree biomass as well as increase the amount of tree products available to local communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Our research also set out determine which tree species would benefit the most from the different grass treatments. We studied the sprouting and growth rates of ten trees that are important for human livelihoods, such as the Shea nut tree (<em>Vittellaria paradoxa</em>), which provides a valued oil nut, or the <em>Pterocarpus erynaceus</em> known for its high valued wood. The goal of this latter study was to determine ways to facilitate the establishment and growth of valued tree species. In many African savannas, native tree species are not planted, rather they populate landscapes over time through a process of agro-parkland development. Our study of valued tree species will have important uses for communities seeking to restore degraded parklands, which are known to be highly productive agroforests.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In summary, our study advances scientific theory by synthesizing two competing savanna ecological models, demonstrating that competition between grasses and small trees must be accounted for in mesic savanna models. Our results have important implications for managing mesic savannas. We find that short-term grass removal treatments can be used to facilitate tree growth rates ultimately increasing the tree/grass ratio in a savanna. Strategic use of grass treatments could potentially increase the numbers of highly valued trees in a landscape. Finally, it is important to note that we are not recommending a policy of large-scale grass treatments to enhance carbon sequestration. We caution against any such plans especially given the long history of coercive efforts in many savanna countries to restrict fire and increase forest cover. Whether a local community prefers a more wooded savanna should remain a local decision, one that we hope our work can inform.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/04/2021<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;Laris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389311127_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389311127_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389311127_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Numerous trees sprouting on a hoe treated plot in Tabou, Mali (2019)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Laris</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Laris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389173629_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389173629_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389173629_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Average height growth rate by grass disturbance and dead trees in study plots for Tabou and Faradiele, Mali (2016-2018)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lilian Yang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Laris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389236486_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389236486_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612389236486_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Number of tree deaths and average height growth rate by fire disturbance in study plots for Tabou and Faradiele, Mali (2016-2018)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lilian Yang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Laris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612451259416_treescorch--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612451259416_treescorch--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1461345/1461345_10355926_1612451259416_treescorch--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Height and State  of Scorched Trees by Fire Season in a Burned Savanna Landscape (Sonjankoro, Mali)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Laris</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Laris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to address basic questions pertaining to the science of savanna ecology and biogeography by answering fundamental questions about the forces that shape the ratio of trees to grasses in savanna landscapes. In recent decades, new savanna ecological theory has emerged built on the concept that forces determining tree cover depend upon the annual rainfall regime. In savannas with higher rainfall, so-called mesic savannas, disturbances such as frequent fires reduce tree growth rates and trap trees in a juvenile stage preventing them from reaching adulthood. According to this model, trees only escape the firetrap during rare events such as abnormal rainfall or a lack of fire for several years. Semi-arid savannas, with lower rainfall, operate under a different model. In these arid lands, limited access to water restricts tree cover. Understanding the forces that determine tree cover in savannas is critical for both sustaining livelihoods, because the ratio of tree to grasses determines the resources available for human use such as animal fodder or forest products as well as for carbon sequestration in mesic savannas, which can theoretically support a denser tree layer.              Our study challenged the underlying notion that disturbance intensity alone governs tree growth and escape rates in mesic savannas. We designed a field test to determine whether grasses compete strongly with juvenile trees (less than two meters tall) to reduce tree growth rates. Our field test examined the effects of four different grass reduction treatments on tree growth rates: (i) herbicide, (ii) grass clipping, (iii) grazing, and (iv) traditional hoeing. Our study found that two years of grass removal resulted in a statistically significant increase in juvenile tree growth varying from 147 to 205% depending on the treatment. Grass treatments of hoeing, clipping and herbicide resulted in fewer tree deaths than the control, while grazing caused an increase in deaths. To test the ecological significance of the increase in tree growth rates, our study included a fire experiment to determine how fires set at different times during the long dry season--early, middle and late affect tree growth and death. We found that both early and late fires resulted in increased tree growth rates over the control, although late fires resulted in more tree deaths. Surprisingly, we found that growth rates on trees subjected to mid-season burning did not differ from the control.              A critical outcome of the study is that the increase in tree growth by reducing grass competition for two years is enough to allow trees to escape the firetrap (trees grow enough to reach a height of three meters sufficient to escape top-kill from fire). In practice, this means that savannas treated by hoeing, grass mowing or herbicides for just two years become significantly more wooded. Trees are long living and mature trees shade out grasses, as such, once juvenile trees escape, they theoretically transform the savanna for decades because mature trees are fire resistant. Such savanna transformation would have implications for carbon sequestration in tree biomass as well as increase the amount of tree products available to local communities.              Our research also set out determine which tree species would benefit the most from the different grass treatments. We studied the sprouting and growth rates of ten trees that are important for human livelihoods, such as the Shea nut tree (Vittellaria paradoxa), which provides a valued oil nut, or the Pterocarpus erynaceus known for its high valued wood. The goal of this latter study was to determine ways to facilitate the establishment and growth of valued tree species. In many African savannas, native tree species are not planted, rather they populate landscapes over time through a process of agro-parkland development. Our study of valued tree species will have important uses for communities seeking to restore degraded parklands, which are known to be highly productive agroforests.            In summary, our study advances scientific theory by synthesizing two competing savanna ecological models, demonstrating that competition between grasses and small trees must be accounted for in mesic savanna models. Our results have important implications for managing mesic savannas. We find that short-term grass removal treatments can be used to facilitate tree growth rates ultimately increasing the tree/grass ratio in a savanna. Strategic use of grass treatments could potentially increase the numbers of highly valued trees in a landscape. Finally, it is important to note that we are not recommending a policy of large-scale grass treatments to enhance carbon sequestration. We caution against any such plans especially given the long history of coercive efforts in many savanna countries to restrict fire and increase forest cover. Whether a local community prefers a more wooded savanna should remain a local decision, one that we hope our work can inform.        Last Modified: 02/04/2021       Submitted by: Paul Laris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
