<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU QUEST (Research Experience for Undergraduates in QUantitative Environmental Science and Technology)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>264287.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>264287</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sally O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This REU Site award to Grand Valley State University, located in Muskegon, Michigan, will support the training of 10 students for 10 weeks during the summers of 2015-2017. The program emphasizes two themes: understanding freshwater systems and their catchments, and applying quantitative methods in research. Its main components are individual student-oriented research projects, faculty mentoring, peer interactions, development of communication skills, and development of quantitative skills. Students also will receive training in the ethics of science and responsible conduct of research, use of library resources, career planning, and resume writing. Research areas include lake and stream metabolism, carbon and nutrient biogeochemistry, transformative/comparative immunology of freshwater organisms, molecular ecology, fish population dynamics, harmful algal blooms, environmental chemistry, remote sensing, watershed analysis, and more. Research equipment available to students includes, for example, a monitoring buoy on Muskegon Lake, flow cytometer, gene sequencer, analytical instruments for environmental chemistry, and indoor mesocosm facility. The summer program concludes with a research symposium where students present their findings. Program success will be evaluated using both the BIO REU common assessment tool and an external evaluator. The program is open to all bright, adequately prepared undergraduates throughout the nation, with extra emphasis on recruiting from groups underrepresented in the biological sciences. Student applications are completed online at the website listed below and include evidence of adequate academic preparation, an essay, and a faculty letter of recommendation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is anticipated that over the 3-year period of the grant, a total of 30 students primarily from schools with limited research opportunities, will be trained in the program. Students will learn how research is conducted, and many will present the results of their work at scientific conferences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A common web-based assessment tool used by all REU programs funded by the Division of Biological Infrastructure (Directorate for Biological Sciences) will be used to determine the effectiveness of the training program. Students are required to be tracked after the program and must respond to an automatic email sent via the NSF reporting system. More information is available by visiting www.gvsu.edu/wri/mcnair/reuquest or by contacting the PI (Dr. James McNair at mcnairja@gvsu.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Kevin Strychar at strychak@gvsu.edu).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461249</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>McNair</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James McNair</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcnairja@gvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163313987</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000395869</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Strychar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin B Strychar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>strychak@gvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163318796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Grand Valley State University</Name>
<CityName>Allendale</CityName>
<ZipCode>494019401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6163316840</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 Campus Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059692996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GRAND VALLEY STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059692996</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Grand Valley State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Muskegon</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>494411678</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[740 W Shoreline Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~264287</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="western" style="margin-bottom: 0in; line-height: 100%;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">Over its 3-year duration, the REU-QUEST program trained a combined total of 30 student participants for 10 weeks each summer during the summers of 2015, 2016, and 2017. The program was open to all qualified students, but our recruitment process especially targeted students from ethnic and racial groups currently underrepresented in the biological sciences. Of the 30 student participants trained over 3 years, 27% identified as Hispanic or Latino/a, 23% as Native American or Alaska Native, 20% as African American, 13% as Asian, and 3% as Pacific Islander (many students identified as more than one ethnic or racial group); 73% were female.</span></span></p> <p class="western" style="margin-bottom: 0in; line-height: 100%;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp; The program emphasized two major research themes: understanding freshwater systems and their catchments, and applying quantitative methods in research. The main components of training included one-on-one meetings of students with their faculty mentors to select and design research projects, conducting the research projects, a weekly class on quantitative methods, a weekly journal club, weekly training in professional ethics and responsible conduct of research, training in how to prepare a curriculum vitae, training in how to apply to graduate school, training in how to prepare oral and poster research presentations, and hands-on experience in giving an oral presentation at a scientific meeting.</span></span></p> <p class="western" style="margin-bottom: 0in; line-height: 100%;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Presentation and publication outcomes of the REU-QUEST program to date include (1) 30 oral presentations by student participants at the REU-QUEST Research Symposium, which was held at the end of each summer program, (2) 2 oral presentations and three poster presentations at regional scientific meetings, (3) 1 poster presentation at an international scientific meeting, (4) 1 publication in a mainstream peer-reviewed scientific journal, and (5) 2 manuscripts submitted to mainstream peer-reviewed scientific journals that are currently under review. All of these presentations and publications have one or more of our REU-QUEST student participants as either the lead author or a co-author.</span></span></p> <p class="western" style="margin-bottom: 0in; line-height: 100%;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Of the 20 student participants who have shared information about their current educational or career status since completing the REU-QUEST program, 6 are still undergraduates, 3 are currently in PhD programs in areas related to their REU-QUEST research projects (1 of these is Hispanic or Latino, 1 is Asian), 5 are currently in Master's degree programs in areas related to their REU-QUEST research projects (1 of these is Hispanic/Latina and 1 is Native American), 1 (a Native Hawaiian student) received his Bachelor's degree in Spring 2018 and is currently applying to graduate programs in the biological sciences, and<span style="font-style: normal;"> </span><span style="font-style: normal;">5</span><span style="font-style: normal;"> received </span><span style="font-style: normal;">their Bachelor&rsquo;s</span><span style="font-style: normal;"> degree in Fall 2017 or Spring 2018 and </span><span style="font-style: normal;">currently </span><span style="font-style: normal;">plan to work for </span><span style="font-style: normal;">one or two</span><span style="font-style: normal;"> years in order to clarify their main area of interest before applying to graduate school.</span><span style="font-style: normal;">&nbsp;</span></span></span></p> <p class="western" style="margin-bottom: 0in; line-height: 100%;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We are proud to have contributed to the training of these 30 student participants and to have succeeded in cultivating an interest among many of them in pursuing graduate degrees in the biological sciences, environmental engineering, or related disciplines. We are especially proud of the mentoring roles we have played for our students from various ethnic and racial groups that currently are underrepresented in the biological sciences. We hope and believe that increasing the participation of these groups in the sciences will help to gradually narrow the intellectual and socioeconomic gaps between different segments of our society and thus help to pave the way toward a society in which all talented students perceive the door to a career in the sciences as being open to them.</span></span></p> <p class="western" style="margin-bottom: 0in; line-height: 100%;">&nbsp;</p> <!-- p { margin-bottom: 0.1in; line-height: 120%; }p.western { font-family: "Arial", sans-serif; } --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/17/2018<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Mcnair</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Over its 3-year duration, the REU-QUEST program trained a combined total of 30 student participants for 10 weeks each summer during the summers of 2015, 2016, and 2017. The program was open to all qualified students, but our recruitment process especially targeted students from ethnic and racial groups currently underrepresented in the biological sciences. Of the 30 student participants trained over 3 years, 27% identified as Hispanic or Latino/a, 23% as Native American or Alaska Native, 20% as African American, 13% as Asian, and 3% as Pacific Islander (many students identified as more than one ethnic or racial group); 73% were female.      The program emphasized two major research themes: understanding freshwater systems and their catchments, and applying quantitative methods in research. The main components of training included one-on-one meetings of students with their faculty mentors to select and design research projects, conducting the research projects, a weekly class on quantitative methods, a weekly journal club, weekly training in professional ethics and responsible conduct of research, training in how to prepare a curriculum vitae, training in how to apply to graduate school, training in how to prepare oral and poster research presentations, and hands-on experience in giving an oral presentation at a scientific meeting.      Presentation and publication outcomes of the REU-QUEST program to date include (1) 30 oral presentations by student participants at the REU-QUEST Research Symposium, which was held at the end of each summer program, (2) 2 oral presentations and three poster presentations at regional scientific meetings, (3) 1 poster presentation at an international scientific meeting, (4) 1 publication in a mainstream peer-reviewed scientific journal, and (5) 2 manuscripts submitted to mainstream peer-reviewed scientific journals that are currently under review. All of these presentations and publications have one or more of our REU-QUEST student participants as either the lead author or a co-author.      Of the 20 student participants who have shared information about their current educational or career status since completing the REU-QUEST program, 6 are still undergraduates, 3 are currently in PhD programs in areas related to their REU-QUEST research projects (1 of these is Hispanic or Latino, 1 is Asian), 5 are currently in Master's degree programs in areas related to their REU-QUEST research projects (1 of these is Hispanic/Latina and 1 is Native American), 1 (a Native Hawaiian student) received his Bachelor's degree in Spring 2018 and is currently applying to graduate programs in the biological sciences, and 5 received their Bachelor?s degree in Fall 2017 or Spring 2018 and currently plan to work for one or two years in order to clarify their main area of interest before applying to graduate school.       We are proud to have contributed to the training of these 30 student participants and to have succeeded in cultivating an interest among many of them in pursuing graduate degrees in the biological sciences, environmental engineering, or related disciplines. We are especially proud of the mentoring roles we have played for our students from various ethnic and racial groups that currently are underrepresented in the biological sciences. We hope and believe that increasing the participation of these groups in the sciences will help to gradually narrow the intellectual and socioeconomic gaps between different segments of our society and thus help to pave the way toward a society in which all talented students perceive the door to a career in the sciences as being open to them.          Last Modified: 07/17/2018       Submitted by: James Mcnair]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
