<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Seminar on Stochastic Processes 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference Seminar on Stochastic Processes (SSP) 2015 will be held at the University of Delaware in Newark DE on April 1-4, 2015. The conference will provide a platform for the dissemination of the most recent significant progress in research in the theory of stochastic processes, and to enable participants to discuss their work in an informal atmosphere. In addition to talks by invited speakers on key recent themes in stochastic process research and their important connections to other parts of mathematics and the sciences, there will be opportunities for new researchers to present their research, and for the discussion of open problems, as well as a tutorial on major recent developments in probability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stochastic processes are basic building blocks of the way that randomness exhibits itself in the real world, and are used to model a wide range of physical, biological, ecological, and financial phenomena. The Seminar on Stochastic Processes is a fixture in probability, and many of the most prominent probabilists make a habit of attending it every year. The morning invited presentations provide a platform for the latest developments in the field. Moreover, the informal format of the afternoon sessions gives graduate students and young researchers a unique opportunity to expose themselves to the most recent research trends by engaging in high level open discussions, and by offering the opportunity to present their own research to leaders in their field. The synergy made possible by this original formula is very rarely found in more traditional meetings. Financial support to attend the conference will preferentially be given to graduate students, postdocs, women, and minorities, as well as to junior faculty who may not otherwise be able to attend the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More details are available at the conference website &lt;br/&gt;http://www.mathsci.udel.edu/events/conferences/ssp/Pages/default.aspx</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1461446</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Petr</FirstName>
<LastName>Plechac</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Petr Plechac</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plechac@math.udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028310637</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000415921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mokshay</FirstName>
<LastName>Madiman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mokshay Madiman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>madiman@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028311865</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nayantara</FirstName>
<LastName>Bhatnagar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nayantara Bhatnagar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>banerjee.naya@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2674038413</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The Seminars on Stochastic Processes (SSP) have been held annually since 1981 and have become the most important regular conference series for probabilists in North America. The project supported SSP 2015, held at the University of Delaware. It brought together a diverse group of accomplished researchers and young investigators in probability and stochastic processes, providing a platform for the dissemination of the most recent significant progress in research (through 5 invited talks, a tutorial, and a poster session), and enabling participants to discuss their work with others. There were also other activities intended especially for new and young researchers&mdash; a special session to celebrate the mathematical contributions of Professor Wenbo V. Li (1963--2013), and a panel discussion that included career advice and research success strategies from a range of panelists. About 70 registered participants attended SSP 2015, including 37 junior researchers, who benefited from the invited talks, publicizing their own work through brief talks and posters, the panel discussion, and social interaction.&nbsp;</span><br /><br /><span>The project funds that remained after SSP 2015 were used towards a Workshop on Probabilistic and Information-Theoretic Inequalities held at the University of Delaware during April 22-23, 2017. The workshop featured talks by top experts in this field coming from different areas including information theory, geometric functional analysis, and probability theory, and led to many of the participants being exposed to perspectives from the other areas for the first time. The workshop had about 40 attendees, around half of whom were graduate students and postdocs. The invited talks gave them both an opportunity to learn about the latest developments in probabilistic inequalities and also to establish contact with leaders working in this area.&nbsp;</span><br /><br /><span>Both SSP 2015 and the 2017 workshop featured an Open Problems session, where a number of researchers presented a range of intriguing open problems to stimulate future research. They also each featured a banquet and social activities to give participants the opportunity to mingle and get to know one another. The selection of speakers for both events was diverse in terms of both gender and ethnicity. Travel and lodging for almost all participants at both events was supported by the project funds.&nbsp;</span><br /><br /><span>In summary, the project fulfilled its intellectual merit mandate through the dissemination of the latest research developments in stochastic processes and probabilistic inequalities, and its broader impact mandate through human resource development, especially the opportunities it afforded to junior researchers.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Mokshay&nbsp;Madiman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Seminars on Stochastic Processes (SSP) have been held annually since 1981 and have become the most important regular conference series for probabilists in North America. The project supported SSP 2015, held at the University of Delaware. It brought together a diverse group of accomplished researchers and young investigators in probability and stochastic processes, providing a platform for the dissemination of the most recent significant progress in research (through 5 invited talks, a tutorial, and a poster session), and enabling participants to discuss their work with others. There were also other activities intended especially for new and young researchers&mdash; a special session to celebrate the mathematical contributions of Professor Wenbo V. Li (1963--2013), and a panel discussion that included career advice and research success strategies from a range of panelists. About 70 registered participants attended SSP 2015, including 37 junior researchers, who benefited from the invited talks, publicizing their own work through brief talks and posters, the panel discussion, and social interaction.   The project funds that remained after SSP 2015 were used towards a Workshop on Probabilistic and Information-Theoretic Inequalities held at the University of Delaware during April 22-23, 2017. The workshop featured talks by top experts in this field coming from different areas including information theory, geometric functional analysis, and probability theory, and led to many of the participants being exposed to perspectives from the other areas for the first time. The workshop had about 40 attendees, around half of whom were graduate students and postdocs. The invited talks gave them both an opportunity to learn about the latest developments in probabilistic inequalities and also to establish contact with leaders working in this area.   Both SSP 2015 and the 2017 workshop featured an Open Problems session, where a number of researchers presented a range of intriguing open problems to stimulate future research. They also each featured a banquet and social activities to give participants the opportunity to mingle and get to know one another. The selection of speakers for both events was diverse in terms of both gender and ethnicity. Travel and lodging for almost all participants at both events was supported by the project funds.   In summary, the project fulfilled its intellectual merit mandate through the dissemination of the latest research developments in stochastic processes and probabilistic inequalities, and its broader impact mandate through human resource development, especially the opportunities it afforded to junior researchers.       Last Modified: 11/01/2017       Submitted by: Mokshay Madiman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
