<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mechanics of Dynamic Discontinuities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>280172.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>295862</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Siddiq Qidwai</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sqidwai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922211</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As flexible objects move, they often develop discontinuities in their shapes. Discontinuities of interest are features such as sharp folds, contacts with obstacles and guides, or tears. This work seeks to understand the mechanics and dynamics of these discontinuities and investigates how they move, and how they affect the motion of the flexible object as a whole. Fundamental engineering science outcomes may eventually be applied to many different technology domains. Thin, flexible structures like strings, cables, sheets, and plates are important components of many engineered systems, including, among other things, energy harvesting technologies, sensors, marine and aerospace structures. Manufacturing technologies such as transfer printing and textile processing also involve the dynamical behavior of thin, flexible structures and their contact discontinuities. Mechanical metamaterials and morphing devices rely on the manipulation and response of thin plates or strips linked by hinges or other sharp features. The project will also provide opportunities for outreach and education on topics in mechanics, through demonstration of exciting phenomena insightful to the general public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The dynamical behavior of discontinuities is a fundamental topic in analytical mechanics. The work will apply a new unifying variational framework for non-material discontinuities in materials and structures, including kinks and folds, moving contacts and impacts, and peeling and tearing fronts. The approach is new in that it treats all of these objects as time-dependent boundaries. The work is organized around three projects, each representing a different class of discontinuity: 1) Pickup, impact, and peeling of cables and tapes, 2) Propagating folds in membranes, plates, and shells, and 3) Cracking, tearing, and cutting of sheets. The work will generate novel theoretical results on momentum and energy balances in these systems, and analytical solutions for motions of discontinuities. Tabletop experiments with chains will provide experimental data on discontinuous dynamic contacts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1462501</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hanna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Hanna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhanna@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7757846406</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652358</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1630</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~280172</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~15690</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project dealt with discontinuities -- locations in a structure where the shape, velocity, or forces applied to the body change very rapidly.&nbsp; For example, the place where a piece of adhesive tape is being peeled off of a surface, or the place where a piece of paper is being fed out of a guiding channel in a printer, are discontinuities.&nbsp; Discontinuities appear in many places, including industrial applications involving the processing of textiles or other materials in string or sheet form, or the manufacture of certain electronic devices.&nbsp;</p> <p>The work performed in this study helped us understand how to relate forces and energy losses at these discontinuities.&nbsp; Often these relationships are counterintuitive and not easy to predict.&nbsp; Sometimes unexpected phenomena occur, such as the tendency of a flexible object to speed up, rather than slow down, when undergoing impact with an obstacle.&nbsp; Other effects can be harnessed in strategies for the motion of soft robotic appendages or other objects along surfaces or through narrow channels.&nbsp; Our work produced a general theoretical framework that can be applied to many types of systems with discontinuities.</p> <p>In the course of this work, a Ph.D. student was trained, who is continuing in academia towards becoming a professor.&nbsp; Additionally, several undergraduate students gained research experience, before either joining the aerospace industry or continuing academic studies in graduate school.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2019<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Hanna</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project dealt with discontinuities -- locations in a structure where the shape, velocity, or forces applied to the body change very rapidly.  For example, the place where a piece of adhesive tape is being peeled off of a surface, or the place where a piece of paper is being fed out of a guiding channel in a printer, are discontinuities.  Discontinuities appear in many places, including industrial applications involving the processing of textiles or other materials in string or sheet form, or the manufacture of certain electronic devices.   The work performed in this study helped us understand how to relate forces and energy losses at these discontinuities.  Often these relationships are counterintuitive and not easy to predict.  Sometimes unexpected phenomena occur, such as the tendency of a flexible object to speed up, rather than slow down, when undergoing impact with an obstacle.  Other effects can be harnessed in strategies for the motion of soft robotic appendages or other objects along surfaces or through narrow channels.  Our work produced a general theoretical framework that can be applied to many types of systems with discontinuities.  In the course of this work, a Ph.D. student was trained, who is continuing in academia towards becoming a professor.  Additionally, several undergraduate students gained research experience, before either joining the aerospace industry or continuing academic studies in graduate school.       Last Modified: 10/24/2019       Submitted by: James Hanna]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
