<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Mathematical-Experimental Strategy to Discern the Molecular Basis of "Successful Mucus"</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>959999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>959999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In human airways, the mucus barrier is the front line of defense whereas the immune system is secondary.  "Successful mucus" efficiently traps invasive cargo (pathogens and particulates) and continuously clears mucus and cargo from the airways to the larynx where it is swallowed to the gut and chemically disarmed before penetration of the mucus barrier, preventing exposure to cells or the blood stream.  Many diseases and pathologies are now associated with "unsuccessful mucus," from genetic diseases like cystic fibrosis to acquired conditions such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).  Mucus has become the miner's canary of lung health.  The experimental-mathematical projects outlined in this research present a strategy to replace quality-of-life metrics of lung disorders with rigorous, robust scientific metrics that integrate novel experimental technique with the mathematics of data analytics, model selection, and predictive computation.  These advances promise a new standard for mucus biology, with the potential to transform clinical practice from patient symptoms to preemptive monitoring and assessment of mucus transport properties, to identification of likely sources of success and failure, and to test impact and duration of therapeutics.  The education and training of undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral scholars in the integration of knowledge and techniques from biology, biophysics, applied mathematics, statistics, and medicine contributes to the enrichment of all disciplines and fields, and furthermore to the future generation of researchers and practitioners in academia and the public and private sector. &lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;Mucus in every organ has a baseline composition (a spectrum of mucin macromolecules, proteins, electrolytes, and water) that is reproducible in cell cultures, and then a host of "living-induced" molecular species (pathogens and by-products, immune response agents, DNA from dead cells, and substances from environmental and lifestyle factors).  This molecular composition conveys to healthy mucus the ability to impede the diffusion of species from nanometer to micron size, and the ability to be activated (thereby cleared) down to pico-Newton forces of single cilia.  All particles tracked via microscopy in mucus diffuse "non-normally" and the statistics of their diffusion varies with particle size and surface chemistry; all rheology data point to nonlinear viscoelastic behavior that differs depending on the frequency, lengthscale, and stress level of the propulsion mechanisms in the lung.  This striking capacity of successful mucus to respond simultaneously yet differently to the diversity of insults and to its clearance by cilia and air drag has confounded the science of mucus biology.  Consequently, there has been no assessment standard of transport properties for mucus, no conclusive test for successful mucus, no understanding of what molecular species or tandem species determine mucus success or failure in either transport property, and no rigorous basis to test potential remedies to reinstate healthy transport properties.  In this project, experimental techniques will be explored to decompose mucus with respect to its molecular basis, with top-down deconstruction of clinical mucus into baseline and living-induced components, and bottom-up reconstruction from a sterile cell culture baseline superimposed with controlled living-induced components.  Mathematical techniques will be developed to assess diffusive and viscoelastic properties of physiological relevance over this entire mucus sample space, including strategies to resolve open mathematical questions about anomalous diffusion and nonlinear viscoelasticity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1462992</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M. Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Forest</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>M. Gregory Forest</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>forest@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199629606</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000361580</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David B Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dbhill@med.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199663411</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 Airport Drive, Suite 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8047</Code>
<Text>NIGMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4075</Code>
<Text>NSF/NIGMS Initiative-Mathematical Bio</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~639998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~320001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this project has been to employ various  microscale experiments integrated with mathematical modeling to assess  the biophysical structure and properties of human lung mucus <em>and</em> the transport behavior of passive and active species within mucus  hydrogels. Through the course of the project, the mathematical advances  have been extended to other biological hydrogels and experiments of  them, including cervicovaginal and intestinal mucus, the cytoplasm  inside living cells, and the structure and dynamics of chromosomal DNA  inside the nucleus of living cells.&nbsp; The project has also produced a  technological advance in removing the bottleneck in the conversion of  huge video files from microscopy experiments to analyzable data of all  tracked particles and species with a convolutional neural network that  automates the file conversion. The project has led to novel diagnostic  and predictive capabilities for translational applications to human lung  health and disease, to virology and bacteriology, and to DNA damage and  repair. The new data diagnostic and simulation tools provide the  ability to: &nbsp;discern between healthy and unhealthy lung or other organ  barrier mucus, and normal versus damaged chromosomal DNA in living  cells; to detect from a mucus sample its likelihood of statistical  similarity with respect to disease progression; to detect from  experimental data of fluorescent DNA domains how the genome is producing  gene-gene associations through the transient binding-unbinding of small  molecule proteins to specific domains on chromosomes; and, to detect  the ability of antibodies or engineered small molecules to immobilize  viruses, bacteria, and sperm.&nbsp; The predictive tools center upon the  ability to mechanistically model the motion of diverse passive and  active &ldquo;particles&rdquo; (pathogens, antibodies, nanoparticulates, bacteria,  sperm, passive or active microbeads) with sufficient accuracy that we  can reconstruct experimental data and predict beyond experimental  limitations. &nbsp;The translational applications include collaborations in  clinical trials for lung disease (cystic fibrosis, COPD) as well as  teaming with other experimentalists to provide modeling expertise on  studies of dispersed particles, pathogens, or sperm in mucus, and  related mechanistic modeling of other biological gels such as  chromosomal DNA inside the nucleus of living cells.&nbsp; Many experimental  challenges require new mathematical theory and tools, including:&nbsp; use of  experimental data to construct mechanistic models; use of experimental  data to select among candidate mechanistic models for the particles,  pathogens, or DNA domains that are being imaged and tracked; and,  statistical methods to disentangle the underlying stochastic  fluctuations of tracked particles from experimental effects such as  deterministic drift and camera error.&nbsp; In the course of analyzing  particle tracking data, we have overcome the major bottleneck between  experiments and data analysis, the conversion of 3D and 4D video files  to analyzable data, by developing a convolutional neural net that  automates this conversion.&nbsp; The tools developed in this project are  thereby propagating out to diverse applications beyond human lung mucus  that were not envisioned at the start of the project.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has generated significant findings that have been  published in a wide range of journals, including high profile ones such  as PNAS, Nature Communications, Science Translational Medicine, and  Nucleic Acids Research. &nbsp;With respect to intellectual merit, the  mathematical team has made a fundamental contribution by applying  stochastic homogenization theory to identify optimal transient binding  interactions of small molecule crosslinking molecules or proteins in  biopolymer gels that produce wildly diverse outcomes:&nbsp; immobilize  pathogens, particulates or sperm in mucus, endow and sustain the  structure and rheology of mucus gels, and establish gene cluster  organization on sufficient timescales to perform critical gene  functions.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Several graduate and undergraduate students and postdoctoral scholars  have been supported by the project, with all of them advancing in their  respective career development goals.&nbsp; Partial support has been provided  to:&nbsp; postdocs Jay Newby (now Assistant Professor at U. Alberta),  Matthew Markovetz (now funded through a fellowship award from the Cystic  Fibrosis Foundation), Feifei Xu (now a data scientist at Google, Inc.)  and Xuezheng Cao (now Assistant Professor at Xiamen University);  graduate students Caitlin Hult and Tim Wessler (both currently postdocs  at U. Michigan), Ian Seim, Ben Walker, Jordan Brown, Neall Caughman, and  Andrew Ford (each progressing toward the PhD); and undergrads Matthew  Christy (now a data analyst at Draft Kings), David Cavender (graduating  Spring 2020, applying to graduate school), and Keshav Patel (graduated  with honors, first year graduate student at University of Utah).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2019<br>      Modified by: M. Gregory&nbsp;Forest</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project has been to employ various  microscale experiments integrated with mathematical modeling to assess  the biophysical structure and properties of human lung mucus and the transport behavior of passive and active species within mucus  hydrogels. Through the course of the project, the mathematical advances  have been extended to other biological hydrogels and experiments of  them, including cervicovaginal and intestinal mucus, the cytoplasm  inside living cells, and the structure and dynamics of chromosomal DNA  inside the nucleus of living cells.  The project has also produced a  technological advance in removing the bottleneck in the conversion of  huge video files from microscopy experiments to analyzable data of all  tracked particles and species with a convolutional neural network that  automates the file conversion. The project has led to novel diagnostic  and predictive capabilities for translational applications to human lung  health and disease, to virology and bacteriology, and to DNA damage and  repair. The new data diagnostic and simulation tools provide the  ability to:  discern between healthy and unhealthy lung or other organ  barrier mucus, and normal versus damaged chromosomal DNA in living  cells; to detect from a mucus sample its likelihood of statistical  similarity with respect to disease progression; to detect from  experimental data of fluorescent DNA domains how the genome is producing  gene-gene associations through the transient binding-unbinding of small  molecule proteins to specific domains on chromosomes; and, to detect  the ability of antibodies or engineered small molecules to immobilize  viruses, bacteria, and sperm.  The predictive tools center upon the  ability to mechanistically model the motion of diverse passive and  active "particles" (pathogens, antibodies, nanoparticulates, bacteria,  sperm, passive or active microbeads) with sufficient accuracy that we  can reconstruct experimental data and predict beyond experimental  limitations.  The translational applications include collaborations in  clinical trials for lung disease (cystic fibrosis, COPD) as well as  teaming with other experimentalists to provide modeling expertise on  studies of dispersed particles, pathogens, or sperm in mucus, and  related mechanistic modeling of other biological gels such as  chromosomal DNA inside the nucleus of living cells.  Many experimental  challenges require new mathematical theory and tools, including:  use of  experimental data to construct mechanistic models; use of experimental  data to select among candidate mechanistic models for the particles,  pathogens, or DNA domains that are being imaged and tracked; and,  statistical methods to disentangle the underlying stochastic  fluctuations of tracked particles from experimental effects such as  deterministic drift and camera error.  In the course of analyzing  particle tracking data, we have overcome the major bottleneck between  experiments and data analysis, the conversion of 3D and 4D video files  to analyzable data, by developing a convolutional neural net that  automates this conversion.  The tools developed in this project are  thereby propagating out to diverse applications beyond human lung mucus  that were not envisioned at the start of the project.   The project has generated significant findings that have been  published in a wide range of journals, including high profile ones such  as PNAS, Nature Communications, Science Translational Medicine, and  Nucleic Acids Research.  With respect to intellectual merit, the  mathematical team has made a fundamental contribution by applying  stochastic homogenization theory to identify optimal transient binding  interactions of small molecule crosslinking molecules or proteins in  biopolymer gels that produce wildly diverse outcomes:  immobilize  pathogens, particulates or sperm in mucus, endow and sustain the  structure and rheology of mucus gels, and establish gene cluster  organization on sufficient timescales to perform critical gene  functions.       Several graduate and undergraduate students and postdoctoral scholars  have been supported by the project, with all of them advancing in their  respective career development goals.  Partial support has been provided  to:  postdocs Jay Newby (now Assistant Professor at U. Alberta),  Matthew Markovetz (now funded through a fellowship award from the Cystic  Fibrosis Foundation), Feifei Xu (now a data scientist at Google, Inc.)  and Xuezheng Cao (now Assistant Professor at Xiamen University);  graduate students Caitlin Hult and Tim Wessler (both currently postdocs  at U. Michigan), Ian Seim, Ben Walker, Jordan Brown, Neall Caughman, and  Andrew Ford (each progressing toward the PhD); and undergrads Matthew  Christy (now a data analyst at Draft Kings), David Cavender (graduating  Spring 2020, applying to graduate school), and Keshav Patel (graduated  with honors, first year graduate student at University of Utah).       Last Modified: 12/23/2019       Submitted by: M. Gregory Forest]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
