<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Development of a bioengineered organic matrix for enhanced bone regeneration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>lydia mcclure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Currently, synthetic bone substitutes are poorly designed materials that do not effectively induce new bone formation. Use of these products increases risk of delayed bone healing. Bone matrix proteins (BMPs) stimulate new bone formation, but are expensive and are known to cause adverse effects in patients, as documented recently by the FDA. The team has developed a cost-effective, organic biomaterial for enhanced bone mineralization and orthopedic regeneration. Through the use of an innovative, materials design approach employing the aforementioned bone proteins, this project aims at commercializing a new class of hybrid organic matrices that can significantly enhance the growth of new bone tissue.  The development of the bone substitute seeks to shift paradigms in orthopedic regenerative medicine. The success of this work will usher in a new class of bioengineered matrices that safely induce new bone formation and prevent occurrence of non-unions. An increased efficacy in bone grafting procedures will directly translate to lowered hospitals costs and better patient outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-collagenous proteins (NCPs) osteocalcin (OC) and osteopontin (OPN) are building blocks of bone, and are released by cells into the extracellular environment during the mineralization process, where they are incorporated into the matrix due to their affinity for bone mineral. OC and OPN are considered powerful regulators of bone matrix quality, strongly influencing mechanical integrity of bone. NCPs function as link proteins connecting the collagen and mineral phases of bone matrix together, and as regulators of bone mineral properties.  The self-healing potential of NCPs due, to their interactions with both, the mineral and collagen phases in bone matrix, makes them ideal candidates to explore in the field of orthopedic regeneration. By providing the body with these building blocks of bone, the team seeks to achieve enhanced mineralization and accelerated bone regeneration.  The team is fabricating and characterizing collagen-based matrices containing NCPs that now need to be characterized and tested for efficacy through in vitro and in vivo studies.  Preliminary conversations with clinicians and angel investors, have led the team to believe that a successful test of efficacy will be a significant milestone in the commercialization of its innovation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1462613</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deepak</FirstName>
<LastName>Vashishth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deepak Vashishth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vashid@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182764050</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF I-Corps project explored the commercial feasibility of novel bone scaffolds (considered an implantable medical device by the FDA), for use in orthopedic regenerative medicine. We began the process by meeting with and talking to stakeholders in the orthopedic devices space. In due process, we also went to a major medical devices conference where we spoke to potential strategic partners and investors. We conducted over 90 interviews with clinicians, medical device industry people, hospital administration and reimbursement professionals to evaluate the position of our product within the orthopedic biomaterials market. We learned that the market ecosystem in this segment of medical devices is quite complex with multiple stakeholders involved in the decision-making process. However, in talks with clinicians, we learned that an opportunity lies in the development of such products for high-risk aging patients in whom fractures, or bone defects, do not heal rapidly. Currently there are not many orthopedic regenerative products that specifically target high-risk aging populations.</p> <p>Having learnt what we did during the customer discovery process, we proceeded to develop and test our minimum viable product (MVP) for application to the high-risk aging patients segment. Firstly, we developed our MVP, blocks of protein-ceramic based material as shown in Fig. 1. Once the MVP was developed, we perfomed a pilot small animal study to preliminarily evaluate the safety and efficacy of our MVP. This was done by creating bone defects animal femur and tibia bones, that would not spontaneously heal, and fill them with the MVP to observe healing response. We saw that our MVP integrated well with the host bone and bone formation could be seen in the defect site as early as 6 weeks. As an effort to commercialize our efforts, we have protected our intellectual property by filing provisional applications and a PCT application (for international patent filing) through Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. Successful commercialization of such a product will be of great benefit to aging patients at high risk of orthopedic non-healing, and improve their surgical outcomes and quality of life.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Deepak&nbsp;Vashishth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1462613/1462613_10343191_1469447282300_scaffolds--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1462613/1462613_10343191_1469447282300_scaffolds--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1462613/1462613_10343191_1469447282300_scaffolds--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image of the minimum viable product (a bone scaffold) developed and tested during this I-Corps project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Atharva Poundarik</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deepak&nbsp;Vashishth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF I-Corps project explored the commercial feasibility of novel bone scaffolds (considered an implantable medical device by the FDA), for use in orthopedic regenerative medicine. We began the process by meeting with and talking to stakeholders in the orthopedic devices space. In due process, we also went to a major medical devices conference where we spoke to potential strategic partners and investors. We conducted over 90 interviews with clinicians, medical device industry people, hospital administration and reimbursement professionals to evaluate the position of our product within the orthopedic biomaterials market. We learned that the market ecosystem in this segment of medical devices is quite complex with multiple stakeholders involved in the decision-making process. However, in talks with clinicians, we learned that an opportunity lies in the development of such products for high-risk aging patients in whom fractures, or bone defects, do not heal rapidly. Currently there are not many orthopedic regenerative products that specifically target high-risk aging populations.  Having learnt what we did during the customer discovery process, we proceeded to develop and test our minimum viable product (MVP) for application to the high-risk aging patients segment. Firstly, we developed our MVP, blocks of protein-ceramic based material as shown in Fig. 1. Once the MVP was developed, we perfomed a pilot small animal study to preliminarily evaluate the safety and efficacy of our MVP. This was done by creating bone defects animal femur and tibia bones, that would not spontaneously heal, and fill them with the MVP to observe healing response. We saw that our MVP integrated well with the host bone and bone formation could be seen in the defect site as early as 6 weeks. As an effort to commercialize our efforts, we have protected our intellectual property by filing provisional applications and a PCT application (for international patent filing) through Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. Successful commercialization of such a product will be of great benefit to aging patients at high risk of orthopedic non-healing, and improve their surgical outcomes and quality of life.       Last Modified: 07/29/2016       Submitted by: Deepak Vashishth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
