<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Design and Exploration of High-Temperature Steels for Electric Power Generation Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>336367.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>336367</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alewis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Increasing the efficiency of electric power generation helps reducing fuel consumption and carbon dioxide emission. About 80 percent of the electricity in the U.S. is generated with steam turbines whose efficiency is limited by their maximum operating temperature. This award supports fundamental research to develop economically viable steels that can be used at substantially higher temperatures than those used in steam generators today, in order to increase their energy conversion efficiencies. Benefits for the U.S. economy and society will be multidimensional: in addition to potential savings in fuel cost and reduced emissions in power generation afforded by these new alloys, this research will advance the knowledge base for designing improved high-temperature alloys by deepening the understanding of how processing and the resulting microstructure bring about the improved properties of a newly designed material.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research aims to develop the intellectual basis for designing high-temperature resistant steels that can be used in high-efficiency ultra-supercritical steam generators for electric power plants at temperatures above 650C (1200F). This involves a novel combination of several strategies in steel design: utilizing a fine dispersion of semi-coherent mono-carbide or carbo-nitride  precipitates, additions of molybdenum or tungsten for solid solution strengthening, and optimizing the carbon concentration to suppress formation of precipitate phases detrimental to creep strength. The underlying scientific concepts include minimizing interfacial energies and diffusion to reduce the rate of coarsening, and semi-coherent interfaces between precipitates and the matrix to create obstacles for impinging dislocations for improved high-temperature strength. In pursuing these design principles, computational thermodynamics, precipitation modeling, micro- and nanostructural characterization by optical, transmission-electron and atom-probe microscopies, and evaluation of high-temperature mechanical properties will contribute to a multidimensional understanding of the processes governing the high-temperature creep strength, ultimately leading to the development of new alloys with improved properties.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1462850</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Morris</FirstName>
<LastName>Fine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Morris E Fine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>m-fine412@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474914322</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000385720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yip-Wah</FirstName>
<LastName>Chung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yip-Wah Chung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ywchung@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913112</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000456848</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Semyon</FirstName>
<LastName>Vaynman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Semyon Vaynman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>svaynman@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474914475</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306262</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dieter</FirstName>
<LastName>Isheim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dieter Isheim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>isheim@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913575</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306364</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080893</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2220 Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~336367</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Raising the operating temperature of steam generators increases thermal efficiency and lowers CO<sub>2</sub> emissions of fossil-fueled plants. The highest possible operating temperature is, however, limited by the long-term corrosion and creep resistance of the materials used, generally martensitic or ferritic steels. Precipitate coarsening and transformations during long-term high-temperature service result in loss of creep strength and eventually component failure. We developed a concept for novel economically viable steels with improved creep resistance, drawing on fundamental principles of precipitation strengthening and thermodynamic stability, with a new combination of several alloy design strategies: (i) utilizing a fine dispersion of semi-coherent carbide or carbonitride precipitates, (ii) additions of molybdenum or tungsten for solid solution strengthening, and (iii) optimizing the carbon concentration to eliminate formation of precipitate phases detrimental to creep strength. The underlying scientific concepts include (iv) minimizing precipitate interfacial energies, and (v) diffusion coefficients, to reduce the rate of precipitate coarsening, and (vi) semi-coherency of the interfaces between precipitates and the matrix to create obstacles for impinging dislocations for improved high-temperature strength. The new steels are strengthened exclusively by metal-carbide or -carbonitride precipitates while excluding the precipitation of M23C6, Laves phase and Z-phase, which are associated with microstructural degradation. Our comprehensive and iterative design approach combines computational thermodynamics, multi-scale microstructural characterization, and mechanical testing at high temperatures.</p> <p>We designed three generations of ferritic creep-resistant steels. NUNb03 is designed to form 0.35 vol.% NbC; NUV12 and NUV12H 0.35 and 0.76 vol.% V-rich MX, respectively. The MX precipitates form by aging in the intended service temperature range, and remain almost constant in size afterwards. The precipitate composition and their slow coarsening are consistent with thermodynamic and kinetic modeling. The threshold stresses for creep deformation at 700 <sup>o</sup>C are 37+/-2, 42+/-2 and 45+/-1 MPa for NUNB03, NUV12 and NUV12H respectively. These values are comparable or slightly higher than the ones for the standard martensitic steel P91, 35+/-4 MPa, but are achieved with a much lower volume fraction of precipitates, and smaller quantities of expensive alloying additions. We demonstrate that MX precipitates can provide effective creep strengthening in spite of their relatively low volume fraction. Tailoring morphology, interfacial coherency and volume fraction of the precipitates has the potential to further enhance the creep performance.</p> <p>Austenitic steels possess intrinsically higher creep strength due to the lower diffusivity in the closed-packed fcc lattice, compared to bcc, but have higher concentrations of alloying additions and thus are significantly more expensive. A series of 9-12% Cr austenitic creep-resistant steels was designed computationally with ~1 vol.% MX-type thermodynamically stable precipitates. Unlike MX in current austenitic creep-resistant steels, which are mainly micro-scale primary precipitates, the MX precipitates in the newly designed steels can be completely dissolved with a solution treatment around 1250 <sup>o</sup>C and re-precipitated as fine secondary precipitates. Meanwhile, the comparatively simple microstructure, in comparison to the complex structure of steels with M23C6, Z-, sigma- or other phases, is more predictable and reliable in practical applications. This new class of creep-resistant steels is a promising candidate to explore further in the future.</p> <p><em>Intellectual merit</em>: We developed the intellectual basis for designing high-temperature steels that can be used in ultra-supercritical steam generators for electric power plants above 650&deg;C. We utilize a novel combination of several strategies in steel design based on a fine dispersion of semi-coherent metal-carbide or -carbonitride precipitates, additions of molybdenum or tungsten for solid solution strengthening, and optimizing the carbon concentration to suppress formation of precipitate phases detrimental to creep strength. The underlying scientific concepts include minimizing interfacial energies and diffusion to reduce the rate of coarsening, while maintaining semi-coherent interfaces between precipitates and the matrix to create drag on impinging dislocations for improved high-temperature strength. We designed the new steels employing computational thermodynamics, precipitation modeling, micro- an nanoscale characterization of the microstructure and precipitates, and determination of high-temperature mechanical properties through creep experiments.</p> <p><em>Broader Impact</em>: We developed high-temperature resistant steels suitable for high-efficiency electric power generation.&nbsp; Since 80% of electric energy is generated <em>via </em>steam turbines, higher temperature operations afforded by these steels will increase energy conversion efficiency, resulting in lower fuel consumption and reduced CO<sub>2</sub> emission. The potential societal impact cannot be overstated. Throughout the project period, students underwent multi-dimensional training, including physical metallurgy, computational modeling, state-of-the art micro- and nanostructural characterization tools, and experimental mechanical and creep testing. Our research resulted in two PhD theses and degrees, one patent, three publications in peer-reviewd journals and several conference presentations. We generated example materials for classroom teaching, including topics such as computational thermodynamics, precipitation-strengthened alloys, and sustainability, and a case study for a materials design class. Because the motivation for the proposed research can be easily appreciated by the general public, it provides an easy focal point for outreach to K-12 students and their teachers during their visits and programs organized through our MRSEC and university partnership programs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/10/2020<br>      Modified by: Dieter&nbsp;Isheim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Raising the operating temperature of steam generators increases thermal efficiency and lowers CO2 emissions of fossil-fueled plants. The highest possible operating temperature is, however, limited by the long-term corrosion and creep resistance of the materials used, generally martensitic or ferritic steels. Precipitate coarsening and transformations during long-term high-temperature service result in loss of creep strength and eventually component failure. We developed a concept for novel economically viable steels with improved creep resistance, drawing on fundamental principles of precipitation strengthening and thermodynamic stability, with a new combination of several alloy design strategies: (i) utilizing a fine dispersion of semi-coherent carbide or carbonitride precipitates, (ii) additions of molybdenum or tungsten for solid solution strengthening, and (iii) optimizing the carbon concentration to eliminate formation of precipitate phases detrimental to creep strength. The underlying scientific concepts include (iv) minimizing precipitate interfacial energies, and (v) diffusion coefficients, to reduce the rate of precipitate coarsening, and (vi) semi-coherency of the interfaces between precipitates and the matrix to create obstacles for impinging dislocations for improved high-temperature strength. The new steels are strengthened exclusively by metal-carbide or -carbonitride precipitates while excluding the precipitation of M23C6, Laves phase and Z-phase, which are associated with microstructural degradation. Our comprehensive and iterative design approach combines computational thermodynamics, multi-scale microstructural characterization, and mechanical testing at high temperatures.  We designed three generations of ferritic creep-resistant steels. NUNb03 is designed to form 0.35 vol.% NbC; NUV12 and NUV12H 0.35 and 0.76 vol.% V-rich MX, respectively. The MX precipitates form by aging in the intended service temperature range, and remain almost constant in size afterwards. The precipitate composition and their slow coarsening are consistent with thermodynamic and kinetic modeling. The threshold stresses for creep deformation at 700 oC are 37+/-2, 42+/-2 and 45+/-1 MPa for NUNB03, NUV12 and NUV12H respectively. These values are comparable or slightly higher than the ones for the standard martensitic steel P91, 35+/-4 MPa, but are achieved with a much lower volume fraction of precipitates, and smaller quantities of expensive alloying additions. We demonstrate that MX precipitates can provide effective creep strengthening in spite of their relatively low volume fraction. Tailoring morphology, interfacial coherency and volume fraction of the precipitates has the potential to further enhance the creep performance.  Austenitic steels possess intrinsically higher creep strength due to the lower diffusivity in the closed-packed fcc lattice, compared to bcc, but have higher concentrations of alloying additions and thus are significantly more expensive. A series of 9-12% Cr austenitic creep-resistant steels was designed computationally with ~1 vol.% MX-type thermodynamically stable precipitates. Unlike MX in current austenitic creep-resistant steels, which are mainly micro-scale primary precipitates, the MX precipitates in the newly designed steels can be completely dissolved with a solution treatment around 1250 oC and re-precipitated as fine secondary precipitates. Meanwhile, the comparatively simple microstructure, in comparison to the complex structure of steels with M23C6, Z-, sigma- or other phases, is more predictable and reliable in practical applications. This new class of creep-resistant steels is a promising candidate to explore further in the future.  Intellectual merit: We developed the intellectual basis for designing high-temperature steels that can be used in ultra-supercritical steam generators for electric power plants above 650&deg;C. We utilize a novel combination of several strategies in steel design based on a fine dispersion of semi-coherent metal-carbide or -carbonitride precipitates, additions of molybdenum or tungsten for solid solution strengthening, and optimizing the carbon concentration to suppress formation of precipitate phases detrimental to creep strength. The underlying scientific concepts include minimizing interfacial energies and diffusion to reduce the rate of coarsening, while maintaining semi-coherent interfaces between precipitates and the matrix to create drag on impinging dislocations for improved high-temperature strength. We designed the new steels employing computational thermodynamics, precipitation modeling, micro- an nanoscale characterization of the microstructure and precipitates, and determination of high-temperature mechanical properties through creep experiments.  Broader Impact: We developed high-temperature resistant steels suitable for high-efficiency electric power generation.  Since 80% of electric energy is generated via steam turbines, higher temperature operations afforded by these steels will increase energy conversion efficiency, resulting in lower fuel consumption and reduced CO2 emission. The potential societal impact cannot be overstated. Throughout the project period, students underwent multi-dimensional training, including physical metallurgy, computational modeling, state-of-the art micro- and nanostructural characterization tools, and experimental mechanical and creep testing. Our research resulted in two PhD theses and degrees, one patent, three publications in peer-reviewd journals and several conference presentations. We generated example materials for classroom teaching, including topics such as computational thermodynamics, precipitation-strengthened alloys, and sustainability, and a case study for a materials design class. Because the motivation for the proposed research can be easily appreciated by the general public, it provides an easy focal point for outreach to K-12 students and their teachers during their visits and programs organized through our MRSEC and university partnership programs.       Last Modified: 05/10/2020       Submitted by: Dieter Isheim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
