<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER-DynamicData: Dynamic Data-Driven Avionics Systems for Flight Decision Support in Emergency Conditions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>akbar sayeed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dynamic Data Driven Avionics Systems (DDDAS) have the potential to endow aircraft with the ability to dynamically use sensor data to detect failure conditions and accurately simulate flight plans in order to support pilot decisions in emergency scenarios.  PI Varela will investigate how to dynamically detect data errors and equipment failures by matching measured data to pre-computed error signatures and damage performance profiles.  Once a failure type is detected, redundant data will be used to correct for instrument errors when possible and to increase the fidelity of an onboard self flight simulator.  This research will enable virtual failure enhanced flight simulations to predict the outcome of different flight plans before they are executed.  DDDAS will thus support better-informed decision making for pilots in emergency conditions and it will also be applicable to autonomous unmanned air and space vehicles.  Furthermore, new mathematical techniques and associated software for data streaming analytics will likely be applicable to other domains, including health monitoring and spacesuit technologies.  The PI intends to make all developed programming technology, run-time middleware, and flight data available to the community in open-source form.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will investigate methodologies and develop new techniques in several fundamental research directions as they pertain to the proposed DDDAS model:  (1) This project will enhance dataflow concurrent programming to make it fault-cognizant and fault-tolerant. In particular, this work will extend the unbound and bound states of dataflow variables with a new dataflow variable state: correlated uncertainly bound.  This enhancement will allow software developers to explicitly model distributed redundant data streams to be able to recognize and tolerate failures with quantified uncertainty.  The project will also study the impact of this enhancement on the heterogeneity and asynchrony tolerance already afforded by the dataflow concurrent programming model.  (2) This project will investigate extensions to logic programming to support stochastic reasoning.  In particular, the PI will create language extensions to standard Horn clause-based knowledge bases to incorporate probabilities.  Additional extensions will specifically support spatial and temporal data streams.  Furthermore, the PI will create incremental reasoning algorithms to be able to recompute queries efficiently as applications dynamically receive new data.  (3) Finally, this project will investigate cloud-based techniques for scalable data analytics.  The PI will explore the use of hybrid (private and public) clouds for online (real-time) data analytics as well as for offline data storage and processing.  Elasticity and scalability of data streaming, storage, and processing techniques on hybrid clouds will enable multi-criteria optimization.  Policies will include optimizing for analytics performance, aircraft-to-cloud communication, and/or cost.  &amp;#8232;The DDDAS model will be applied to flight decision support systems in emergency conditions.  Specific activities will include: i) creating multi-fidelity models and incremental algorithms that will allow DDDAS to inject data from aircraft sensors dynamically, ii) formalizing the notion of aircraft damage/failure profiles, and iii) evaluating the new mathematical and computational techniques with actual flight accident data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1462342</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Varela</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlos A Varela</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cvarela@cs.rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182766912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314767</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8th St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O395</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5384</Code>
<Text>DATA AND DATA SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of the project was to research fundamental dynamic data-driven application systems (DDDAS) techniques to enable development of safer flight systems to support pilots in emergency conditions: (i) We created error signatures as a method to detect and correct errors in redundant data streams, in particular, those coming from aircraft sensors.&nbsp; (ii) We also studied the application of machine learning techniques to understand normal and abnormal aircraft operational modes.&nbsp; (iii) We investigated workload and performance prediction models to enable effective virtual machine scheduling for real-time data stream analytics in the cloud.&nbsp; (iv) We are looking at dynamic data-driven flight trajectory generation to help pilots in loss of thrust emergencies. Throughout the project,&nbsp;we are also developing programming technology to enable high-level declarative specification of potential failure modes inferrable from data and corrective action.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition, we are studying real-world commercial aviation accidents data to validate our fundamental research results.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>(i) We have shown our DDDAS approach to be able to detect and correct for the air speed failure in the Air France Flight 447 (AF447) that crashed in the Atlantic Ocean in June 2009. Airspeed sensor failure of the AF447 flight is successfully detected and corrected after 5 seconds from beginning of the failure. Overall error mode detection accuracy reaches 96.31%. We have also applied our mathematical techniques and software to analyzing the Tuninter 1153 accident in August 2005. The underweight condition due to the installation of an incorrect fuel sensor is successfully detected with 100% accuracy during the cruise phase of flight. We have studied the relationship between error signatures (a concept we created) and error residuals (a more traditional concept studied in the Fault Detection, Identification and Reconfiguration community). The results of this study have been published as a feature article in IEEE Aerospace &amp; Electronic Systems Magazine (AESM) and featured in the back cover in April 2017.</p> <p>(ii) We have studied how to integrate methods for machine learning from data into our PILOTS software. In particular, we are looking at polynomial regression to learn model parameters, and at Bayesian classification methods to learn normal and failure modes.&nbsp; We have created a dynamic Bayesian classification algorithm to recognize new (untrained for) modes of operation, and when statistically significant, extend the classes of failures observed from data dynamically.&nbsp; The results of this study have been published in Cluster Computing journal's Special Issue on Dynamic Data-Driven Application Systems (DDDAS) in October 2017.</p> <p>(iii) We are also studying cloud computing techniques to enable scalable data analytics. In particular, we are looking at application-agnostic models for performance prediction of virtual computing environments, to enable accurate virtual machine resource allocation according to multi-objective policies including: time-to-solution, cost, and solution accuracy.&nbsp; We identified maximum sustainable throughput (MST) as a key metric for resource allocation.&nbsp; MST is a function of the number of virtual machines associated to a data streaming analytics task.&nbsp; We developed techniques to measure MST, and to predict it by creating a performance model from low-scale measurements and to use it during scalable cloud-based data analytics.&nbsp; The results of this study have been published in ACM/IEEE Cloud, Cluster, and Grid Computing (CCGrid 2017) conference in May 2017.</p> <p>(iv) We are studying DDDAS methods to help pilots in loss of thrust emergencies, such as the Hudson River ditching incident of US Airways 1549 in January 2009.&nbsp; Loss of thrust emergencies-e.g., induced by bird/drone strikes or fuel exhaustion-create the need for dynamic data-driven flight trajectory planning to advise pilots or control UAVs.&nbsp; We developed an initial damaged aircraft model that can use sensor data to update the aircraft's gliding performance characteristics taking into account dynamics such as partial power and icing conditions and be able to generate plausible trajectories in sub-second time.&nbsp; Our damaged aircraft model is parameterized on a baseline glide ratio for a clean aircraft configuration assuming best gliding airspeed on straight flight. The model predicts purely geometric criteria for flight trajectory generation, namely, glide ratio and turn radius for different bank angles and drag configurations. Given actual aircraft performance data, we dynamically infer the baseline glide ratio to update the damaged aircraft model. We further introduce a trajectory utility function to rank trajectories for safety. In the Hudson River case study, a baseline glide ratio of 17.25:1 enabled us to generate trajectories up to 28 seconds after the birds strike, whereas, a 19:1 baseline glide ratio enabled us to generate trajectories up to 36 seconds after the birds strike.&nbsp; The results of this study have been presented at the Second International Conference on InfoSymbiotics / DDDAS (Dynamic Data Driven Applications Systems) held at MIT, Cambridge, Massachusetts in August, 2017.&nbsp; We have published a preliminary arXiv technical report and have submitted an article to IEEE Transactions on Aerospace and Electronic Systems currently under review.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Carlos&nbsp;A&nbsp;Varela</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of the project was to research fundamental dynamic data-driven application systems (DDDAS) techniques to enable development of safer flight systems to support pilots in emergency conditions: (i) We created error signatures as a method to detect and correct errors in redundant data streams, in particular, those coming from aircraft sensors.  (ii) We also studied the application of machine learning techniques to understand normal and abnormal aircraft operational modes.  (iii) We investigated workload and performance prediction models to enable effective virtual machine scheduling for real-time data stream analytics in the cloud.  (iv) We are looking at dynamic data-driven flight trajectory generation to help pilots in loss of thrust emergencies. Throughout the project, we are also developing programming technology to enable high-level declarative specification of potential failure modes inferrable from data and corrective action.  In addition, we are studying real-world commercial aviation accidents data to validate our fundamental research results.    (i) We have shown our DDDAS approach to be able to detect and correct for the air speed failure in the Air France Flight 447 (AF447) that crashed in the Atlantic Ocean in June 2009. Airspeed sensor failure of the AF447 flight is successfully detected and corrected after 5 seconds from beginning of the failure. Overall error mode detection accuracy reaches 96.31%. We have also applied our mathematical techniques and software to analyzing the Tuninter 1153 accident in August 2005. The underweight condition due to the installation of an incorrect fuel sensor is successfully detected with 100% accuracy during the cruise phase of flight. We have studied the relationship between error signatures (a concept we created) and error residuals (a more traditional concept studied in the Fault Detection, Identification and Reconfiguration community). The results of this study have been published as a feature article in IEEE Aerospace &amp; Electronic Systems Magazine (AESM) and featured in the back cover in April 2017.  (ii) We have studied how to integrate methods for machine learning from data into our PILOTS software. In particular, we are looking at polynomial regression to learn model parameters, and at Bayesian classification methods to learn normal and failure modes.  We have created a dynamic Bayesian classification algorithm to recognize new (untrained for) modes of operation, and when statistically significant, extend the classes of failures observed from data dynamically.  The results of this study have been published in Cluster Computing journal's Special Issue on Dynamic Data-Driven Application Systems (DDDAS) in October 2017.  (iii) We are also studying cloud computing techniques to enable scalable data analytics. In particular, we are looking at application-agnostic models for performance prediction of virtual computing environments, to enable accurate virtual machine resource allocation according to multi-objective policies including: time-to-solution, cost, and solution accuracy.  We identified maximum sustainable throughput (MST) as a key metric for resource allocation.  MST is a function of the number of virtual machines associated to a data streaming analytics task.  We developed techniques to measure MST, and to predict it by creating a performance model from low-scale measurements and to use it during scalable cloud-based data analytics.  The results of this study have been published in ACM/IEEE Cloud, Cluster, and Grid Computing (CCGrid 2017) conference in May 2017.  (iv) We are studying DDDAS methods to help pilots in loss of thrust emergencies, such as the Hudson River ditching incident of US Airways 1549 in January 2009.  Loss of thrust emergencies-e.g., induced by bird/drone strikes or fuel exhaustion-create the need for dynamic data-driven flight trajectory planning to advise pilots or control UAVs.  We developed an initial damaged aircraft model that can use sensor data to update the aircraft's gliding performance characteristics taking into account dynamics such as partial power and icing conditions and be able to generate plausible trajectories in sub-second time.  Our damaged aircraft model is parameterized on a baseline glide ratio for a clean aircraft configuration assuming best gliding airspeed on straight flight. The model predicts purely geometric criteria for flight trajectory generation, namely, glide ratio and turn radius for different bank angles and drag configurations. Given actual aircraft performance data, we dynamically infer the baseline glide ratio to update the damaged aircraft model. We further introduce a trajectory utility function to rank trajectories for safety. In the Hudson River case study, a baseline glide ratio of 17.25:1 enabled us to generate trajectories up to 28 seconds after the birds strike, whereas, a 19:1 baseline glide ratio enabled us to generate trajectories up to 36 seconds after the birds strike.  The results of this study have been presented at the Second International Conference on InfoSymbiotics / DDDAS (Dynamic Data Driven Applications Systems) held at MIT, Cambridge, Massachusetts in August, 2017.  We have published a preliminary arXiv technical report and have submitted an article to IEEE Transactions on Aerospace and Electronic Systems currently under review.       Last Modified: 02/07/2018       Submitted by: Carlos A Varela]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
