<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CrowdSight: A Crowdsourcing Platform for Catalyzing and Studying User-Centered Innovation in Engineering Design</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Jablokow</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kjabloko@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928360</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this research project is to develop the theory and implementation of a novel computational design method that enables rapid generation of feedback on product designs from a scalable audience of potential users. Many product innovations fail because the needs of users were not adequately considered during the design process, in large part because gathering user feedback is expensive and slow. This award will enable fundamental research on techniques that leverage online crowdsourcing for generating helpful, affordable, and timely feedback on preliminary product designs from an external audience. The ability to generate feedback on-demand will have a transformative impact by enabling engineering designers to develop product innovations that better satisfy the needs of heterogeneous users. The results from this research can also lead to improvements in commercial feedback services and increased confidence in the use of these services, thereby promoting activity in this niche of the U.S. economy. This research synthesizes techniques from several disciplines including engineering design, human-computer interaction, and computer science. The multi-disciplinary approach will help broaden participation of under-represented groups in research and positively impact engineering education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The design method will be shaped by studying the discourse of product design reviews and implemented by extending an existing platform developed in prior research. Using the extended platform as an online testbed, software methods will be developed that address fundamental problems for crowdsourcing design feedback such as the inability to generate feedback under time constraints. The results will considerably improve the quality, predictability, and affordability of crowdsourced design feedback and will generalize to other domains. Experiments will also be conducted to measure the impact of using the integrated platform on authentic design processes. The platform will be released as open source to benefit the research community and members of society such as entrepreneurs and amateurs who are pursuing product innovations as part of their personal or professional goals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1462693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian P Bailey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bpbailey@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173336106</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000287885</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1464</Code>
<Text>ESD-Eng &amp; Systems Design</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>067E</Code>
<Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068E</Code>
<Text>DESIGN THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>073E</Code>
<Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~400001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-dabf3b9f-7fff-63a0-921f-198ae52e624f"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Gathering formative feedback from potential users is critical for catalyzing user-centered innovation in engineering design. Feedback helps the designer discover unexpected problems with preliminary prototypes and gain insight. Despite its value, feedback from potential users is often difficult to acquire due to a designer's limited resources.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Through this award, the PI developed novel techniques, tools, and experimental results to enhance the acquisition and interpretation of user feedback in engineering design. To aid feedback acquisition, this project produced new experimental results describing how designers leverage online communities for gathering user feedback and the characteristics of written feedback that promote sharing revised prototypes, thereby making online communities more effective for the design innovation process. A second outcome was new experimental results showing the effectiveness of online mentorship, where the same potential user provides feedback throughout the design process, and presenting a prototype in the context of its design process for improving feedback quality. Once acquired, a designer must interpret the feedback received. Interpretation is difficult because feedback from multiple users often contains ambiguities, different perspectives, and conflicting opinions. A third significant outcome of this project was the development of new techniques that aid the interpretation of feedback written by multiple users and experimental results showing the effectiveness of these techniques. These techniques include the development of an activity that guides a designer through an explicit process of interpreting a collection of feedback and a novel software tool that allows a designer to interactively explore the topic and opinion structure within a feedback collection.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The research outcomes of this project have enabled new pedagogies in engineering design education (e.g., teaching students new methods for collecting and interpreting user feedback on design projects) and these pedagogies have been implemented in courses taught by the PI. The award has created research opportunities for four doctoral students, three master's students, and five undergraduate students. These students received training in design, computer science, experimentation, and scientific communication. More broadly, the research opportunities and pedagogical advances enabled by this award have contributed to a U.S. workforce that is better equipped to develop and use technology for user-centered innovation in engineering design.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;P&nbsp;Bailey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Gathering formative feedback from potential users is critical for catalyzing user-centered innovation in engineering design. Feedback helps the designer discover unexpected problems with preliminary prototypes and gain insight. Despite its value, feedback from potential users is often difficult to acquire due to a designer's limited resources. Through this award, the PI developed novel techniques, tools, and experimental results to enhance the acquisition and interpretation of user feedback in engineering design. To aid feedback acquisition, this project produced new experimental results describing how designers leverage online communities for gathering user feedback and the characteristics of written feedback that promote sharing revised prototypes, thereby making online communities more effective for the design innovation process. A second outcome was new experimental results showing the effectiveness of online mentorship, where the same potential user provides feedback throughout the design process, and presenting a prototype in the context of its design process for improving feedback quality. Once acquired, a designer must interpret the feedback received. Interpretation is difficult because feedback from multiple users often contains ambiguities, different perspectives, and conflicting opinions. A third significant outcome of this project was the development of new techniques that aid the interpretation of feedback written by multiple users and experimental results showing the effectiveness of these techniques. These techniques include the development of an activity that guides a designer through an explicit process of interpreting a collection of feedback and a novel software tool that allows a designer to interactively explore the topic and opinion structure within a feedback collection. The research outcomes of this project have enabled new pedagogies in engineering design education (e.g., teaching students new methods for collecting and interpreting user feedback on design projects) and these pedagogies have been implemented in courses taught by the PI. The award has created research opportunities for four doctoral students, three master's students, and five undergraduate students. These students received training in design, computer science, experimentation, and scientific communication. More broadly, the research opportunities and pedagogical advances enabled by this award have contributed to a U.S. workforce that is better equipped to develop and use technology for user-centered innovation in engineering design.          Last Modified: 07/02/2020       Submitted by: Brian P Bailey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
