<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mechano-Biologically Informed Molecular Models of Flow Sensitive Biopolymers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1161993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1161993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In human bodies, bleeding is stopped by forming a clot at the site of vascular damage.  Under rapid blood flow conditions associated with injury, the plasma protein von Willebrand Factor (vWF) plays an indispensable role in sticking to both platelets and collagen on damaged vessel walls, allowing the formation of platelet plugs.  vWF effectively senses blood flow, changing conformation in high flow from a compact globule to an elongated shape; this reveals binding sites on vWF for platelets and collagen.  Abnormalities in vWF adhesion are involved in the pathogenesis of many cardiovascular diseases, such as von Willebrand disease (affecting 1 to 2% of world's population), thrombosis and arteriosclerosis.  Although basic biological properties of vWF have been elucidated, little is known about the detailed biomechanical properties of vWF and how these properties dictate its structure and function in varying flow environments.   Such information can abet not only better understanding of vWF; it can provide insight for the design of synthetic molecules in pursuit of targeted drug therapies, advancing federal interests in health and medicine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will establish, for the first time, a generalized experimental and theoretical platform to investigate the mechanical properties of complicated, multi-domain molecules such as vWF.  The platform advanced will provide transformative predictive capability for how flow sensitive biopolymers behave in specific vascular flow scenarios and how that behavior depends on molecular architecture and biological surface chemistry.  A single-molecule force spectroscopy will be implemented to systematically probe the mechanical response of vWF monomer fragments, monomers, and multimers; data so obtained will be used to optimize new coarse grain molecular models that predict vWF mechanical behavior with unprecedented quantitative accuracy.  The model's predictive capabilities will be further enhanced via fluorescence microscopy analysis of vWF in microfluidic flow chambers with systematically functionalized surfaces.  The optimized model will be used to explore how changes to molecular architecture influence biological functionality in varying flow conditions.  This work will enable a detailed understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying conformational changes of vWF and lay crucial groundwork toward biologically inspired materials design and the development of biomimetic devices that resemble the functionality of known biopolymers.  In addition, the study will fill the long-standing knowledge gap on the mechanobiology of vWF, and potentially offer new therapeutic approaches to treat von Willebrand disease.  This project will educate both undergraduate and graduate STEM students in experimental and theoretical aspects of biomolecular investigation, emphasizing the need for multi-disciplinary, diverse collaborations between practitioners of experiment, computation, and theory.  Such immersive STEM educational experiences will best prepare students to confront technological challenges of the future.  Through associated outreach efforts, this work will showcase for both technical and non-technical societal audiences the power of high performance computing in exploring complex molecular behavior and advancing new solutions in human health and wellness.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1463234</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alparslan</FirstName>
<LastName>Oztekin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alparslan Oztekin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alo2@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107584343</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xuanhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xuanhong Cheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xuc207@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107582002</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000078990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaohui</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaohui Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xiz310@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107582939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574943</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edmund</FirstName>
<LastName>Webb III</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edmund B Webb III</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebw210@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107585168</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000601323</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808264444</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068570936</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180150001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Packard Labs, 19 Memorial Dr. W.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8047</Code>
<Text>NIGMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4075</Code>
<Text>NSF/NIGMS Initiative-Mathematical Bio</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~385403</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~383219</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~393371</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When we suffer an injury in the form of a cut, bleeding ensues and must be stopped by formation of a blood clot.&nbsp;&nbsp;Clots initiate formation when platelets in the bloodstream bind to collagen exposed on injured blood vessel walls.&nbsp;&nbsp;However, for some injuries, bleeding can be significant enough to generate flow fields that prevent platelets and collagen from binding.&nbsp;&nbsp;In such scenarios, the human glycoprotein von Willebrand Factor (vWF) plays a crucial role in forming blood clots. vWF molecules are large (i.e. macromolecular) polymers that nonetheless adopt a highly compact conformation in typical blood flow.&nbsp;&nbsp;However, when vWF proteins are subject to hydrodynamic forces in regions where flow rate is high (such as near vascular injuries), they undergo significant elongation, reaching lengths of up to 10 microns.&nbsp;&nbsp;In undergoing this conformational change, vWF proteins reveal previously shielded binding sites for platelets and collagen, thereby abetting interaction between them and leading to the so-called clotting cascade.</p> <p>vWF proteins are essential to the initiation of clot formation and are thus critical to human wellness.&nbsp;&nbsp;It is estimated that 2% of the human population suffer from bleeding disorders associated with dysfunctional vWF behavior.&nbsp;&nbsp;Furthermore, medical implants have been identified as potentially altering blood flow in their vicinity so as to cause pathological behavior in vWF, leading to potential bleeding issues. &nbsp;Understanding the intricate connections between flow conditions in the blood, corresponding mechanical environment around vWF proteins, and their conformational (and reactivity) response to external (hydrodynamic) forces will permit more effective treatment of disorders as well as the design of medical devices that avoid unwanted vWF behavior.&nbsp;&nbsp;However, such understanding is still lacking.&nbsp;&nbsp;For example, it has been recently revealed that a domain in each monomer of a vWF polymer (i.e. the A2 domain) plays multiple important roles in the proper functioning of the protein.&nbsp;&nbsp;But details about those roles remain unknown.&nbsp;&nbsp;It is also unclear how the conformation of an entire protein, or multimer, relates to behavior at the monomer or sub-monomer scale, where important biological reactions take place.</p> <p>To expand our knowledge around this important molecular system and to develop, in general, a better understanding of how mechanical environment influences molecular conformation, we have combined atomic scale molecular dynamics simulations, coarse grain Brownian dynamics simulations, single molecule force spectroscopy, and microfluidic molecular visualization techniques to a study of vWF.&nbsp;&nbsp;In so doing, the outcomes listed below have been achieved; these outcomes have been documented in 17 peer-reviewed journal articles and conference proceedings as well as multiple invited and contributed presentations.</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Atomic force microscopy and optical tweezer experiments were used to reveal the mechanical response of vWF at the multimer, monomer, and sub-monomer scale, for both healthy vWF and mutant structures.</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Atomic scale molecular dynamics simulations were performed to explore the response of the vWF A2 domain &ndash; a sub-monomer molecular structure that is critical to vWF functionality &ndash; to mechanical loading; multiple structural variants were explored that have been proposed as being relevant to understanding vWF associated bleeding disorders (see Images 1 and 2).</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Experimental and atomic scale simulation data on the mechanical response of vWF were used to develop a model that is capable of describing the behavior of vWF multimers, or proteins, in varying flow conditions similar to those present in the human bloodstream (see Images 3 and 4).</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The model developed is sufficiently computationally efficient to permit modeling of large multimers that are relevant to understanding vWF protein functionality; furthermore, the model permits accurate prediction of sub-monomer (i.e. domain) scale reactivity of the protein.&nbsp;&nbsp;As an example of the model&rsquo;s capabilities, a companion experimental/simulation study of the response of tethered vWF proteins to shear flow was performed and remarkable correspondence was found between experiment and simulation (see Images 5 and 6).&nbsp;&nbsp;This coupling of experiment, simulation, and theory permits previously unattainable insight into the functionality of a fascinating molecular system at the heart of human health.</p> <p>Collectively, this work supported by NSF has manifested models and revealed information that will enable more deterministic engineering of treatments for bleeding disorders associated with dysfunctional vWF.&nbsp;Furthermore, such resources will help inspire the development of synthetic molecular systems capable of mimicking flow induced conformational changes but in highly controlled ways.&nbsp;Such entities have the potential to enable targeted drug therapy, a challenging goal of current medical research.&nbsp;</p> <p>Coupled to the scientific outcomes listed above, outreach activities have been developed and implemented.&nbsp;&nbsp;To date, approximately 300 first through third grade students have seen the presentation, &lsquo;Fluid Dynamic!&rsquo; and that outreach activity has continued beyond the project duration.&nbsp;&nbsp;High school students and undergraduates have engaged with the project, abetting their interest in STEM pursuits.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Edmund&nbsp;B&nbsp;Webb Iii</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When we suffer an injury in the form of a cut, bleeding ensues and must be stopped by formation of a blood clot.  Clots initiate formation when platelets in the bloodstream bind to collagen exposed on injured blood vessel walls.  However, for some injuries, bleeding can be significant enough to generate flow fields that prevent platelets and collagen from binding.  In such scenarios, the human glycoprotein von Willebrand Factor (vWF) plays a crucial role in forming blood clots. vWF molecules are large (i.e. macromolecular) polymers that nonetheless adopt a highly compact conformation in typical blood flow.  However, when vWF proteins are subject to hydrodynamic forces in regions where flow rate is high (such as near vascular injuries), they undergo significant elongation, reaching lengths of up to 10 microns.  In undergoing this conformational change, vWF proteins reveal previously shielded binding sites for platelets and collagen, thereby abetting interaction between them and leading to the so-called clotting cascade.  vWF proteins are essential to the initiation of clot formation and are thus critical to human wellness.  It is estimated that 2% of the human population suffer from bleeding disorders associated with dysfunctional vWF behavior.  Furthermore, medical implants have been identified as potentially altering blood flow in their vicinity so as to cause pathological behavior in vWF, leading to potential bleeding issues.  Understanding the intricate connections between flow conditions in the blood, corresponding mechanical environment around vWF proteins, and their conformational (and reactivity) response to external (hydrodynamic) forces will permit more effective treatment of disorders as well as the design of medical devices that avoid unwanted vWF behavior.  However, such understanding is still lacking.  For example, it has been recently revealed that a domain in each monomer of a vWF polymer (i.e. the A2 domain) plays multiple important roles in the proper functioning of the protein.  But details about those roles remain unknown.  It is also unclear how the conformation of an entire protein, or multimer, relates to behavior at the monomer or sub-monomer scale, where important biological reactions take place.  To expand our knowledge around this important molecular system and to develop, in general, a better understanding of how mechanical environment influences molecular conformation, we have combined atomic scale molecular dynamics simulations, coarse grain Brownian dynamics simulations, single molecule force spectroscopy, and microfluidic molecular visualization techniques to a study of vWF.  In so doing, the outcomes listed below have been achieved; these outcomes have been documented in 17 peer-reviewed journal articles and conference proceedings as well as multiple invited and contributed presentations.  1)    Atomic force microscopy and optical tweezer experiments were used to reveal the mechanical response of vWF at the multimer, monomer, and sub-monomer scale, for both healthy vWF and mutant structures.  2)    Atomic scale molecular dynamics simulations were performed to explore the response of the vWF A2 domain &ndash; a sub-monomer molecular structure that is critical to vWF functionality &ndash; to mechanical loading; multiple structural variants were explored that have been proposed as being relevant to understanding vWF associated bleeding disorders (see Images 1 and 2).  3)    Experimental and atomic scale simulation data on the mechanical response of vWF were used to develop a model that is capable of describing the behavior of vWF multimers, or proteins, in varying flow conditions similar to those present in the human bloodstream (see Images 3 and 4).  4)    The model developed is sufficiently computationally efficient to permit modeling of large multimers that are relevant to understanding vWF protein functionality; furthermore, the model permits accurate prediction of sub-monomer (i.e. domain) scale reactivity of the protein.  As an example of the model’s capabilities, a companion experimental/simulation study of the response of tethered vWF proteins to shear flow was performed and remarkable correspondence was found between experiment and simulation (see Images 5 and 6).  This coupling of experiment, simulation, and theory permits previously unattainable insight into the functionality of a fascinating molecular system at the heart of human health.  Collectively, this work supported by NSF has manifested models and revealed information that will enable more deterministic engineering of treatments for bleeding disorders associated with dysfunctional vWF. Furthermore, such resources will help inspire the development of synthetic molecular systems capable of mimicking flow induced conformational changes but in highly controlled ways. Such entities have the potential to enable targeted drug therapy, a challenging goal of current medical research.   Coupled to the scientific outcomes listed above, outreach activities have been developed and implemented.  To date, approximately 300 first through third grade students have seen the presentation, ‘Fluid Dynamic!’ and that outreach activity has continued beyond the project duration.  High school students and undergraduates have engaged with the project, abetting their interest in STEM pursuits.       Last Modified: 01/29/2020       Submitted by: Edmund B Webb Iii]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
