<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Theoretical and Experimental Study of Mechanical Properties in Ultrafine-Grained Alloys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>219550.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>219550</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alewis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Magnesium alloys are the lightest of all structural metallic materials, and are becoming of increasing interest due to their combination of low-density, moderate strength and stiffness, availability and recyclability.  In particular, these properties are of direct relevance to the automobile, rail and aerospace industries that seek to replace heavier components with lighter ones, and thus minimize fuel usage. Despite the increased interest, magnesium alloys suffer from not being strong enough, and more so, that components have to be heated and shaped at very high temperatures, which is economically prohibitive for transportation manufacturers. This award supports fundamental research to acquire knowledge that will enable synergistic increases in strength and lowering of the processing temperature to ambient temperatures, thereby solving two important barriers to usage at one time.  This research will intersect at the boundaries of materials science, mechanics and manufacturing in a highly relevant way.  It will attract, educate and enable students from underrepresented groups to gain the knowledge and confidence to directly address the rigorous, evolving needs in U.S. industry and government for lightweight materials in energy efficient transportation.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cast magnesium alloys have suffered from poor ambient temperature plasticity due to the lack of necessary active slip systems. This problem is compounded in wrought processed alloys wherein highly anisotropic textures limit uniform material flow. On the other hand, nanocrystalline materials with grain sizes below 100nm have exceptional and desirable properties when compared to their course-grained counterparts, including concurrent increases in strength and ductility.  Motivated by this, the goals of this project are 1) to uncover the underpinning mechanisms for ambient temperature plasticity in bulk, fully dense, nano-grained magnesium alloys using novel processing approaches and microstructure-based modeling; and 2) to exploit the subsequent knowledge to predictably design and fabricate low-temperature formable magnesium alloys. In terms of broader scientific ramifications, the development of a tractable and systematic experimental and modeling framework will represent a major advance over current semi-empirical methods for designing nano-grained alloys with tailored microstructures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1463656</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kiran</FirstName>
<LastName>Solanki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kiran Solanki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kiran.Solanki@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000601610</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>080E</Code>
<Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~219550</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The highly-collaborative approach between the two universities, University of California Riverside and Arizona State University, is to discover the mechanisms for plasticity in nanograined Mg-alloys and enable predictable room temperature formability.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major goals of the project are to</p> <p>a) Uncover the underpinning mechanisms for ambient temperature plasticity in bulk, fully dense, Mg-alloys using novel processing approaches and microstructure-based modeling; and</p> <p>b) Exploit the subsequent knowledge to predictably design and fabricate low-temperature formable Mg-alloys.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Experiments have shown that</p> <ol> <li>It is shown for the first time that the higher deformation energy associated with dynamic strain-rates, coupled with high-triaxiality, promotes detwinning and texture evolution in HCP alloys with high c/a ratio</li> <li>Deformation along the rolling direction (RD) is highly influenced by the local stress state combined with high strain rates.</li> <li>Twin-twin interaction dominates deformation along the RD at high stress triaxiality and low strain rate (10<sup>-3</sup> s-1).</li> <li>De-twinning along with texture change occurs along the RD at high stress triaxiality and high strain rate (10<sup>3</sup> &ndash; 10<sup>4</sup> s-1)</li> <li>Further, experiments show that the tension &ndash; compression asymmetry seems to vanish along with shallower than the traditional sigmoidal curve in case of compression when subjected to a forward tensile loading immediately followed by a reversed compressive loading</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Modeling efforts have led to</p> <ol> <li>The addition of Ce, Y or Zr in Mg decreases the shear resistance across all the possible slip systems when compared to pure Mg</li> <li>The least resistant slip system changed from the basal partial to prismatic slip system, due to the addition of Ce, Y or Zr, which will alter the macroscopic plastic behavior, thereby improving the formability of Mg alloys.</li> <li>Activity of prismatic and pyramidal slip systems increase up on addition of Ce, Y and Zr solute atoms respectively to pure Mg.</li> <li>The addition of Ce, Y or Zr solute atoms increases the shearability of prismatic slip system.</li> <li>The results also reveal that the substitution of a Sn, Li or Zn atom increases the ideal shear resistance of Mg (strengthening).</li> <li>The dominant slip system in Mg was found to change from the basal partial (0001)&nbsp;to prismatic (100)[110] with the addition of a Ce or Zr solute atom; whereas, the addition of a Sn, Li or Zn solute atom had negligible effect on the plastic anisotropy. </li> <li>The electronic density of states calculations show that the contribution from d states of Ce and Zr solute atoms decreases the electronic structure stability of their respective solid solution, thereby enhancing slip activities.</li> <li>With the addition of yttrium, the creep rate in the secondary region decreases and the creep deformation mechanism is changed from grain boundary decohesion to grain boundary rotation/sliding.</li> <li>Grain boundary sliding simulations using MS show a reduction in the excess energy needed for sliding of (101 &#773;1), (101 &#773;2),(101 &#773;3) and (101 &#773;6)&nbsp; with the addition of yttrium. Hence, yttrium has a softening effect on the sliding of boundaries which suggests that the experimentally observed high temperature beneficial effects of yttrium addition is likely to be attributed to some combination of other reported creep strengthening mechanisms or phenomena such as formation of stable yttrium oxides at grain boundaries, increased forest dislocation based hardening, or large grain boundary yttria and precipitate denuded zones near the grain boundaries causing material softening.</li> </ol> <p>10.&nbsp; Yttrium is found to lower the dislocation nucleation and motion energetics on all the slip systems of Mg-alloy. This profound effect owns to the charge transfer from Yttrium atom to the surrounding magnesium atoms.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has had a substantial impact in terms of human capital development by</p> <p>Supporting two PhD students who worked on the experimental and modeling aspects of the project. Both the experiments and modeling promote research and education while also providing meaningful science outcomes in experimental and computational fields and unifying multidisciplinary areas of science and engineering with a common theme. Topical studies in specialty areas, including dislocation dynamics and plasticity at multiple scales, were integrated into this work as a cornerstone for a successful research program that will continue to flourish well beyond the scope of this project. Also, the long-term societal impact of this work will be to accelerate development of light metal alloys by linking microstructure structures to governing deformation mechanisms for lightweight applications. Overall, The Ph.D. students, undergraduate students and technicians involved in the project developed analytical and experimental expertise in a variety of areas including characterization, micro-scale testing, crystallography and modeling at different length scales.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Kiran&nbsp;Solanki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The highly-collaborative approach between the two universities, University of California Riverside and Arizona State University, is to discover the mechanisms for plasticity in nanograined Mg-alloys and enable predictable room temperature formability.     The major goals of the project are to  a) Uncover the underpinning mechanisms for ambient temperature plasticity in bulk, fully dense, Mg-alloys using novel processing approaches and microstructure-based modeling; and  b) Exploit the subsequent knowledge to predictably design and fabricate low-temperature formable Mg-alloys.     Experiments have shown that  It is shown for the first time that the higher deformation energy associated with dynamic strain-rates, coupled with high-triaxiality, promotes detwinning and texture evolution in HCP alloys with high c/a ratio Deformation along the rolling direction (RD) is highly influenced by the local stress state combined with high strain rates. Twin-twin interaction dominates deformation along the RD at high stress triaxiality and low strain rate (10-3 s-1). De-twinning along with texture change occurs along the RD at high stress triaxiality and high strain rate (103 &ndash; 104 s-1) Further, experiments show that the tension &ndash; compression asymmetry seems to vanish along with shallower than the traditional sigmoidal curve in case of compression when subjected to a forward tensile loading immediately followed by a reversed compressive loading         Modeling efforts have led to  The addition of Ce, Y or Zr in Mg decreases the shear resistance across all the possible slip systems when compared to pure Mg The least resistant slip system changed from the basal partial to prismatic slip system, due to the addition of Ce, Y or Zr, which will alter the macroscopic plastic behavior, thereby improving the formability of Mg alloys. Activity of prismatic and pyramidal slip systems increase up on addition of Ce, Y and Zr solute atoms respectively to pure Mg. The addition of Ce, Y or Zr solute atoms increases the shearability of prismatic slip system. The results also reveal that the substitution of a Sn, Li or Zn atom increases the ideal shear resistance of Mg (strengthening). The dominant slip system in Mg was found to change from the basal partial (0001) to prismatic (100)[110] with the addition of a Ce or Zr solute atom; whereas, the addition of a Sn, Li or Zn solute atom had negligible effect on the plastic anisotropy.  The electronic density of states calculations show that the contribution from d states of Ce and Zr solute atoms decreases the electronic structure stability of their respective solid solution, thereby enhancing slip activities. With the addition of yttrium, the creep rate in the secondary region decreases and the creep deformation mechanism is changed from grain boundary decohesion to grain boundary rotation/sliding. Grain boundary sliding simulations using MS show a reduction in the excess energy needed for sliding of (101 &#773;1), (101 &#773;2),(101 &#773;3) and (101 &#773;6)  with the addition of yttrium. Hence, yttrium has a softening effect on the sliding of boundaries which suggests that the experimentally observed high temperature beneficial effects of yttrium addition is likely to be attributed to some combination of other reported creep strengthening mechanisms or phenomena such as formation of stable yttrium oxides at grain boundaries, increased forest dislocation based hardening, or large grain boundary yttria and precipitate denuded zones near the grain boundaries causing material softening.   10.  Yttrium is found to lower the dislocation nucleation and motion energetics on all the slip systems of Mg-alloy. This profound effect owns to the charge transfer from Yttrium atom to the surrounding magnesium atoms.        The project has had a substantial impact in terms of human capital development by  Supporting two PhD students who worked on the experimental and modeling aspects of the project. Both the experiments and modeling promote research and education while also providing meaningful science outcomes in experimental and computational fields and unifying multidisciplinary areas of science and engineering with a common theme. Topical studies in specialty areas, including dislocation dynamics and plasticity at multiple scales, were integrated into this work as a cornerstone for a successful research program that will continue to flourish well beyond the scope of this project. Also, the long-term societal impact of this work will be to accelerate development of light metal alloys by linking microstructure structures to governing deformation mechanisms for lightweight applications. Overall, The Ph.D. students, undergraduate students and technicians involved in the project developed analytical and experimental expertise in a variety of areas including characterization, micro-scale testing, crystallography and modeling at different length scales.       Last Modified: 03/08/2019       Submitted by: Kiran Solanki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
