<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI: Melt Processable Polymer Nanocomposites for Low Friction and Low Wear Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>385593.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>385593</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nearly every machine has at least one performance-critical sliding interface. Joints, bushings and bearings must operate reliably with low friction and low wear in order for the machine to move and perform desired tasks. The costs of friction and wear are estimated to be greater than $500 billion per year in the U.S. alone. There is a broad and substantial need to develop new materials for sustainable sliding applications. This award supports the development of an ultralow-wearing polymer system that can be manufactured by injection molding and other desirable manufacturing techniques. The relationship between DuPont and Lehigh University will enable the technical, industrial and commercial development of this material. Finally, despite the obvious impacts, education on tribology (friction and wear) is insufficient in the US, falling behind many countries. This project addresses these challenges through increased education, exposure and interest in tribology at all levels of society, including: 1) hands-on K-12 tribology experiments, 2) incorporating tribology in Lehigh engineering curriculum, 3) graduate and undergraduate student training at Lehigh and DuPont labs, and 4) provide industry engineers with seminars and online resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) Program award supports a collaboration among researchers at Lehigh University and DuPont, to develop and study ultralow-wear melt processable fluoropolymer composites with goals of 1) understanding the relationship between tribological performance and material structure, composition, processing and operating conditions and 2) developing a complete mechanistic understanding of the complex tribomechanical and tribochemical processes in the sliding wear of ultralow wear perfluoropolymers. The intellectual merit is rooted in a mechanistic understanding of the substantial (&gt;10,000 x) improvement in wear performance of perfluoropolymers (e.g. perfluoroalkoxy -a melt processable fluoropolymer) with &lt; 5 vol percent nanofillers. The coupled, multi-scale, physical, material, mechanical and chemical mechanisms have been largely elusive. The hypothesized mechanism includes tribochemical chain scission of the fluoropolymer resulting in a transfer film that is covalently attached to the surface of a countersample as well as formation of virtual crosslinks (multiple end groups bonded to the nanofiller) that stabilize the wear surface of the polymer. The research will use student-built instruments to directly validate the hypothesized mechanism that in situ tribochemical reaction products alter the properties of otherwise inert fluoropolymers. A multi-faceted characterization approach will systematically test the hypotheses and discover new mechanisms of these materials that could, ultimately, enable science-based design of materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1463141</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Blackman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory Blackman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Gregory.S.Glackman@usa.dupont.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3027745025</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Krick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon A Krick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bkrick@eng.famu.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506450141</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Junk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher P Junk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Christopher.P.Junk@dupont.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3027745025</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667248</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808264444</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068570936</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~385593</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Polymers (plastics) are ubiquitous in modern consumer products and industrial applications; they offer the ability to produce complex parts at high quantities at relatively low costs, while providing many other unique properties as compared with other engineering and building materials. Perfluoropolymers are a unique set of polymers that offer added benefits, including higher temperature limits and low friction coefficients. This means that they can replace many traditional materials in sliding applications, such as joints, bushings and hinges if they can overcome two shortcomings: 1) Wear and 2) Melt processability. This research was overwhelmingly successful in revealing the fundamental mechanisms responsible for reducing wear in perfluoropolymers, including polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE; tradename Teflon) and perfluoroalkoxy alkanes (PFA) polymers. The project achieved the following outcomes:</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong><em>Technical:</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>1. We used advanced chemical and mechanical characterization techniques to understand why certain types of alumina fillers can reduce the wear rate of PTFE by three to four orders of magnitude.</p> <p>2. We validated the proposed tribochemical mechanism for wear using FTIR.</p> <p>3. We collaborated with Sandia National Laboratories Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies (CINT) to perform nanoindentation on the filler particles to develop a predictive method on what filler materials can produce ultralow wear composites.</p> <p>4. From this, we now understand how to design polymer composite systems that are more than 10,000 times more wear resistant than the unfilled base polymers. A key outcome is an invention disclosure for ultralow wear, magnetic fluoropolymer composites. We also have a starting point for fluoropolymer composite-based systems that are even more remarkable than the fluoropolymer/alumina systems.</p> <p>5. We explored PFA as an alternative to PTFE-based composites to mitigate PTFE's deficiency in that it is not melt processable. Here, we discovered PFA-alumina composites, a new class of ultralow wear materials that can be injection molded. This can facilitate its use in complex or high-production-quantity parts.</p> <p>6. We performed fundamental wear experiments on PFA to understand how sliding-induced stresses cause microstructural and chemical changes to the polymer at near room temperature. This includes discovering that:&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>a. Microstructural changes of fluoropolymers caused by sliding-induced stresses</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>b. A low temperature crystal transition can can be erased by sliding-induced shear stresses</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>c. Crystallinity of wear debris is higher than in bulk polymer- never reported previously for PFA</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>d. Molecular weight of the wear debris is smaller in wear debris with new endgroups</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>e. Tribochemical reactions more likely to occur in amorphous region of polymer composite. Furthermore, comonomer content and processing conditions can be modified to promote additional amorphous regions within the microstructure of PFA. This could be used to promote tribochemical reactions in PFA-alumina composite materials to achieve ultralow wear faster.</p> <p>7. We systematically tested relationship between tribological performance and material structure, composition, processing and operating conditions. We measured wear rate of all multiple PFA (varying copolymer type and percent) and alumina compositions in multiple environments over 25 km of slidin. We tested polymer composites in multiple sliding environments. Confirmed tribochemistry hypothesis. Found that atmospheric water concentration is essential for ultralow wear fluoropolymers. Wear rate was nearly 100x higher in dry nitrogen and submerged water environment. We tested external surface as compared to internal surface of injection-molded PFA-alumina composites (ie bulk vs "mold skin") to determine how processing affects alumina particle distribution and concentration which in turn controls the tribological properties of these composites. (Processing-Structure-Property relationship). At lower concentrations of Alumina particles (5 wt. % Al2O3) higher wear was observed on certain surfaces of the injection molded part. Wear rate was independent of mold location for PFA -alumina composites with 7.5 and 10 wt.% alumina. From these observations, designers may optimize the amount of alumina to maximize tribological performance without hindering the manufacturability of the PFA-alumina composites.</p> <p>&nbsp;Outreach:</p> <p>1. We performed hands-on K-12 tribology experiments at Lehigh University Materials Camp and the Society for Tribologists and lubrication engineers STEM outreach program</p> <p>2. Trained graduate and undergraduate students in research techniques, including polymer characterization and tribology methods</p> <p>3. Developed online resources for tribology education</p> <p>4. Presented at and connected with several companies on the applications and possible impacts of ultralow wear polymers on their indusrties</p> <p>In summary, all objectives were successful, with nearly all disseminated through publication or in manuscript preparation/submission stages. The <em><strong>key result </strong></em>was understanding the relationship between tribological performance and material structure, composition, material processing and system operating conditions of perfluorocopolymer and alumina composites enabled us to develop a complete mechanistic understanding of the complex tribomechanical and tribochemical processes in the sliding wear of ultra-low-wear perfluorocopolymer composites. This has enabled us to design new, ultralow wear material systems, beyond what we initially imagined in the proposal. This includes polymer-polymer systems with even better tribological properties than these polymer-ceramic systems, as well as an application-inspired, multifunctional polymer-metal system.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2020<br>      Modified by: Brandon&nbsp;A&nbsp;Krick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1463141/1463141_10357394_1579291284533_Mechanism--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1463141/1463141_10357394_1579291284533_Mechanism--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mechanism for ultralow wear fluoropolymer composites"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1463141/1463141_10357394_1579291284533_Mechanism--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mechanism for ultralow wear fluoropolymer composites"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This schematic documents the mechanisms for ultralow wear PTFE/alumina and PFA/alumina composites. This includes the role of a friable filler, humid air, sliding-induced bond breaking and tribochemistry resulting in new surface films that promote ultralow wear behavior.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brandon A Krick</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Brandon&nbsp;A&nbsp;Krick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mechanism for ultralow wear fluoropolymer composites</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Polymers (plastics) are ubiquitous in modern consumer products and industrial applications; they offer the ability to produce complex parts at high quantities at relatively low costs, while providing many other unique properties as compared with other engineering and building materials. Perfluoropolymers are a unique set of polymers that offer added benefits, including higher temperature limits and low friction coefficients. This means that they can replace many traditional materials in sliding applications, such as joints, bushings and hinges if they can overcome two shortcomings: 1) Wear and 2) Melt processability. This research was overwhelmingly successful in revealing the fundamental mechanisms responsible for reducing wear in perfluoropolymers, including polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE; tradename Teflon) and perfluoroalkoxy alkanes (PFA) polymers. The project achieved the following outcomes:   Technical:   1. We used advanced chemical and mechanical characterization techniques to understand why certain types of alumina fillers can reduce the wear rate of PTFE by three to four orders of magnitude.  2. We validated the proposed tribochemical mechanism for wear using FTIR.  3. We collaborated with Sandia National Laboratories Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies (CINT) to perform nanoindentation on the filler particles to develop a predictive method on what filler materials can produce ultralow wear composites.  4. From this, we now understand how to design polymer composite systems that are more than 10,000 times more wear resistant than the unfilled base polymers. A key outcome is an invention disclosure for ultralow wear, magnetic fluoropolymer composites. We also have a starting point for fluoropolymer composite-based systems that are even more remarkable than the fluoropolymer/alumina systems.  5. We explored PFA as an alternative to PTFE-based composites to mitigate PTFE's deficiency in that it is not melt processable. Here, we discovered PFA-alumina composites, a new class of ultralow wear materials that can be injection molded. This can facilitate its use in complex or high-production-quantity parts.  6. We performed fundamental wear experiments on PFA to understand how sliding-induced stresses cause microstructural and chemical changes to the polymer at near room temperature. This includes discovering that:    a. Microstructural changes of fluoropolymers caused by sliding-induced stresses   b. A low temperature crystal transition can can be erased by sliding-induced shear stresses   c. Crystallinity of wear debris is higher than in bulk polymer- never reported previously for PFA   d. Molecular weight of the wear debris is smaller in wear debris with new endgroups   e. Tribochemical reactions more likely to occur in amorphous region of polymer composite. Furthermore, comonomer content and processing conditions can be modified to promote additional amorphous regions within the microstructure of PFA. This could be used to promote tribochemical reactions in PFA-alumina composite materials to achieve ultralow wear faster.  7. We systematically tested relationship between tribological performance and material structure, composition, processing and operating conditions. We measured wear rate of all multiple PFA (varying copolymer type and percent) and alumina compositions in multiple environments over 25 km of slidin. We tested polymer composites in multiple sliding environments. Confirmed tribochemistry hypothesis. Found that atmospheric water concentration is essential for ultralow wear fluoropolymers. Wear rate was nearly 100x higher in dry nitrogen and submerged water environment. We tested external surface as compared to internal surface of injection-molded PFA-alumina composites (ie bulk vs "mold skin") to determine how processing affects alumina particle distribution and concentration which in turn controls the tribological properties of these composites. (Processing-Structure-Property relationship). At lower concentrations of Alumina particles (5 wt. % Al2O3) higher wear was observed on certain surfaces of the injection molded part. Wear rate was independent of mold location for PFA -alumina composites with 7.5 and 10 wt.% alumina. From these observations, designers may optimize the amount of alumina to maximize tribological performance without hindering the manufacturability of the PFA-alumina composites.   Outreach:  1. We performed hands-on K-12 tribology experiments at Lehigh University Materials Camp and the Society for Tribologists and lubrication engineers STEM outreach program  2. Trained graduate and undergraduate students in research techniques, including polymer characterization and tribology methods  3. Developed online resources for tribology education  4. Presented at and connected with several companies on the applications and possible impacts of ultralow wear polymers on their indusrties  In summary, all objectives were successful, with nearly all disseminated through publication or in manuscript preparation/submission stages. The key result was understanding the relationship between tribological performance and material structure, composition, material processing and system operating conditions of perfluorocopolymer and alumina composites enabled us to develop a complete mechanistic understanding of the complex tribomechanical and tribochemical processes in the sliding wear of ultra-low-wear perfluorocopolymer composites. This has enabled us to design new, ultralow wear material systems, beyond what we initially imagined in the proposal. This includes polymer-polymer systems with even better tribological properties than these polymer-ceramic systems, as well as an application-inspired, multifunctional polymer-metal system.          Last Modified: 01/17/2020       Submitted by: Brandon A Krick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
