<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Global Chlorination: A General Synthetic Strategy towards Chlorosulfolipid Natural Products</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jin Cha</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922461</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project funded by the Chemical Synthesis program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Rendy Kartika of Louisiana State University (LSU) is investigating the conversion of stereochemically complex aliphatic polyols to the corresponding alkyl polychlorides. In addition to introducing new chlorination technology to the toolbox of organic reactions, this research provides invaluable educational experience for student researchers, empowering them to be competitive in the STEM workforce.  Funding of this project strengthens Professor Kartika's established efforts to train students from underrepresented groups and women, and help build organic synthesis at LSU.  The broader impact of this work benefits from two outreach activities: 1) the LSU ChemDemo project, and 2) the Louisiana Organic Chemistry Symposium (LOCS). ChemDemo is an established service-learning activity that directly exposes LSU undergraduates enrolled in large general chemistry courses to hands-on chemistry experiments performed for K-12 students in the Baton Rouge area.  LOCS is a one-day symposium that Professor Kartika established at LSU in 2013 and is repeating in 2016.  The event brings together chemistry graduate and undergraduate students in the Gulf South region to broaden dissemination of contemporary organic chemistry research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is focused on developing a viable general strategy towards the total synthesis of chlorosulfolipids and their congeners. Due to the gap in the knowledge concerning stereoselective reactions involving polychlorinated hydrocarbons, the complex structural features in chlorosulfolipids present significant challenges for structural elucidation and total synthesis. The strategy builds on synthetic methods that convert stereocomplementary aliphatic 1,2- and 1,3-diols to their respective 1,2- and 1,3-dichlorides in a stereoselective manner.  This study continues with the design of convergent synthesis of chlorosulfolipid natural product danicalipin A, highlighted by global chlorination of the corresponding polyol precursor as the key step in the total synthesis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1464788</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rendy</FirstName>
<LastName>Kartika</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rendy Kartika</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkartika@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255785086</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000647961</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University & Agricultural and Mechanical College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6878</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~290000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The funding of this project has enabled the development of new deoxychlorination technology to produce chlorine-containing organic molecules, known as organochlorines.&nbsp;&nbsp;Organochlorines are an important class of organic molecules, as they are significant for industrial, agricultural, and pharmaceutical applications.&nbsp;&nbsp;Organochlorines also serve as valuable precursors in organic reactions, and they have been utilized in various synthetic transformations.&nbsp;&nbsp;As a result of this widespread utility, research in new reactions development for the creation of carbon-chlorine bonds remains an important topic in organic chemistry.</p> <p>Our work in this field has resulted in a series of new deoxychlorination reactions that readily convert alcohols, ketones, and epoxides to their corresponding value-added, complex organochlorines in a stereo- and chemoselective manner using a mixture of triphosgene and nitrogen-containing organic bases.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our new reactions are performed under mild conditions and are&nbsp;very simple to operate without the need of inert or anhydrous conditions.&nbsp;&nbsp;Furthermore, triphosgene exists as a stable, non-hygroscopic crystalline material at room temperature that permits easy and safe handling.&nbsp;&nbsp;The crude materials from our reactions frequently exhibit high purity of the products, therefore rendering column chromatography unnecessary.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our reactions are also atom economical, as the contributing chloride ions are abundantly masked within triphosgene.</p> <p>For broader impacts, this project has enabled the training of several well-rounded chemists.&nbsp;&nbsp;Three Ph.D., one M.S., and five B.S. students have completed their studies as a result, and they are now contributing in the STEM workforce in the US.&nbsp;&nbsp;The equipment fund from this project has improved the organic synthesis research infrastructure in the PI&rsquo;s laboratory through the purchase of GC-MS.&nbsp;&nbsp;Results from this project have been disseminated in several national and regional conferences and published in various high-impact journals.&nbsp;&nbsp;An outreach effort in this project has been realized in students' participation of in the LSU ChemDemo program, which directly exposes LSU students to teach hands-on chemistry experiments in local K-12 schools.&nbsp;&nbsp;The assessment goals of ChemDemo, which are reflected in the students&rsquo; essays are twofold: 1) By teaching K-12 students, LSU students gain a mastery of the chemistry which they choose to perform and the experience of communicating chemistry concepts to age-appropriate audience.&nbsp;&nbsp;2) ChemDemo provides opportunities for LSU students to engage scientifically with the broader community in Baton Rouge, especially those from disadvantaged backgrounds and underrepresented groups.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Rendy&nbsp;Kartika</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464788/1464788_10370736_1575050091293_ReactionScheme--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464788/1464788_10370736_1575050091293_ReactionScheme--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reaction Schemes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464788/1464788_10370736_1575050091293_ReactionScheme--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reaction Schemes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Reaction schemes depicting new deoxychlorination reactions enabled by triphosgene and nitrogen-containing organic bases</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rendy Kartika</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rendy&nbsp;Kartika</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reaction Schemes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The funding of this project has enabled the development of new deoxychlorination technology to produce chlorine-containing organic molecules, known as organochlorines.  Organochlorines are an important class of organic molecules, as they are significant for industrial, agricultural, and pharmaceutical applications.  Organochlorines also serve as valuable precursors in organic reactions, and they have been utilized in various synthetic transformations.  As a result of this widespread utility, research in new reactions development for the creation of carbon-chlorine bonds remains an important topic in organic chemistry.  Our work in this field has resulted in a series of new deoxychlorination reactions that readily convert alcohols, ketones, and epoxides to their corresponding value-added, complex organochlorines in a stereo- and chemoselective manner using a mixture of triphosgene and nitrogen-containing organic bases.  Our new reactions are performed under mild conditions and are very simple to operate without the need of inert or anhydrous conditions.  Furthermore, triphosgene exists as a stable, non-hygroscopic crystalline material at room temperature that permits easy and safe handling.  The crude materials from our reactions frequently exhibit high purity of the products, therefore rendering column chromatography unnecessary.  Our reactions are also atom economical, as the contributing chloride ions are abundantly masked within triphosgene.  For broader impacts, this project has enabled the training of several well-rounded chemists.  Three Ph.D., one M.S., and five B.S. students have completed their studies as a result, and they are now contributing in the STEM workforce in the US.  The equipment fund from this project has improved the organic synthesis research infrastructure in the PI’s laboratory through the purchase of GC-MS.  Results from this project have been disseminated in several national and regional conferences and published in various high-impact journals.  An outreach effort in this project has been realized in students' participation of in the LSU ChemDemo program, which directly exposes LSU students to teach hands-on chemistry experiments in local K-12 schools.  The assessment goals of ChemDemo, which are reflected in the students’ essays are twofold: 1) By teaching K-12 students, LSU students gain a mastery of the chemistry which they choose to perform and the experience of communicating chemistry concepts to age-appropriate audience.  2) ChemDemo provides opportunities for LSU students to engage scientifically with the broader community in Baton Rouge, especially those from disadvantaged backgrounds and underrepresented groups.           Last Modified: 11/29/2019       Submitted by: Rendy Kartika]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
