<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mechanistic Studies of the Photoactivation of Metal- Hydride, Halide and Oxo Bonds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>880000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>880000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>laanders@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922934</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division is funding Professor Daniel Nocera of Harvard University to study catalytic processes that can generate hydrogen from light and simple compounds.  Fuels are compounds that react with an oxidant, usually oxygen, to release energy. At the molecular level, when a fuel is burned, the bonds in high energy compounds rearrange to form new bonds in lower energy compounds, and the energy released in this bond rearrangement is used to power our world. Most fuels in our society are derived from coal, oil and natural gas; namely fossil fuels, the bonds of which are rearranged with the bonds of oxygen to generate carbon dioxide and water, which enter the atmosphere.  One way to avoid the formation of carbon dioxide is to cut the connection between fuels and carbon and to use hydrogen as a fuel. There are two sources of hydrogen that can be generated using solar irradiation: water or hydrohalic acid (for example, a hydrogen atom bonded to a chlorine atom); however, hydrogen cannot be generated by shining light directly on water or hydrohalic acid. A catalyst must be used that will capture the light and then act as an intermediary in the bond rearrangement reaction. Professor Nocera is developing new catalysts that can absorb light and then convert hydrohalic acids into hydrogen and elemental halogen.  The new compounds, reactions and techniques resulting from this research are likely to impact realted areas of science and could result in new energy generation technologies.  Professor Nocera continues to be involved in raising public awareness of the global energy problem and the role that science, and especially chemistry, can play in addressing the energy challenge. Research discoveries in this area are being conveyed to the public through a variety of forums including news media, radio programs, movies and other broadcast venues. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The  Nocera group is developing new catalysts for photochemical HX splitting and, in parallel,  is studying the mechanisms of such reactions.  The storage of renewable energy in the form of fuels requires the rearrangement of bonds with low energy content to ones of high energy content, and bonds of important energy consequence are H-H, X-X and O=O. New metal compounds based on Rh, Ni, Fe and Mn are being synthesized that can provide insight into these energy conversion processes. Critical intermediates that promote the requisite bond activation are being studied using advanced spectroscopic techniques, including the application of time-resolved X-ray crystallography and nanoparticle-based time-resolved resonance Raman spectroscopy for the identification of the critical M-H and M-X intermediates, and magnetic resonance techniques (intermediate-field ENDOR, ELDOR-detected NMR and single-crystal polarized neutron diffraction) for the identification of M-O intermediates. With knowledge of the stereoelectronic properties of the critical intermediates, photocycles are being constructed to drive energetically uphill reactions, which are at the basis for renewable energy conversion.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1464232</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Nocera</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel G Nocera</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dnocera@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174958904</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12 Oxford St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8397</Code>
<Text>Hydrogen Storage or Generation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Photoredox Catalysis</strong></p> <p>The most important criterion in any photochemical technology such as photovoltaic devices or artificial photosynthetic systems is its quantum efficiency, i.e. the conversion of incoming photons to the desired outcome. To be able to outcompete conventional technologies, high quantum efficiencies are imperative to increase productivity while lowering associated costs. Key outcomes of our photoredox work in the last year have been (i) the determination of the rate constants for a photoredox hydroamidation reaction involving five intermediates allowing us to identify the energy-wasting and nonproductive back reaction and (ii) the determination of both a dark and light reaction cycle for redox-mediated Ni-catalyzed aryl etherification that allowed the reaction to be run under both photoredox and electrochemical conditions.</p> <p>We used nanosecond time-resolved spectroscopy to obtain quantitative mechanistic information on the photoredox catalytic hydroamidation reaction. By following the dynamics of the different transient intermediates formed after photoelectron transfer, we build a rare example of a complete mechanism for a photoredox catalytic reaction (Figure 1) and identify the major pathways responsible for the observed low quantum efficiency. Building on this knowledge, we optimize the reaction conditions to produce a significant increase in the quantum efficiency of the synthetic method.</p> <p>We proposed a reaction cycle for redox-mediated, Ni-catalyzed aryl etherification under both photoredox and electrochemically mediated conditions. We demonstrate that a self-sustained Ni(I/III) cycle is operative in both cases by chemically synthesizing and characterizing a common paramagnetic Ni intermediate and establishing its catalytic activity. Furthermore, deleterious pathways leading to off-cycle Ni(II) species have been identified, allowing us to discover optimized conditions for achieving self-sustained reactivity at a &sim;15- fold increase in the quantum yield and a &sim;3-fold increase in the faradaic yield (Figure 2). These results highlight the importance of leveraging insight of complete reaction cycles for increasing the efficiency of redox-mediated reactions.</p> <p><strong>Oxygen Chemistry</strong></p> <p>Chromium species are the active sites in a variety of heterogeneous catalysts, such as the Phillips catalyst, which is composed of Cr ions supported by SiO<sub>2</sub> and is used to produce polyethylene. Among the catalytically relevant oxidation states of chromium is Cr<sup>IV</sup>. Families of neutral, homoleptic, four-coordinate complexes, CrL<sub>4</sub>, with a variety of monoanionic, monodentate ligands, such as L = alkyls, aryls, amides, ketimides (R<sub>2</sub>C = N<sup>&minus;</sup>), alkoxides, and siloxides, are available and can provide information regarding Cr sites in heterogeneous materials. For example, the previously reported siloxide, Cr(DTBMS)<sub>4</sub>, where DTBMS = <sup>&minus;</sup>OSiMet<em><sup>t</sup></em>Bu<sub>2</sub> (ditert-butylmethylsiloxide), may be considered a molecular analogue of Cr<sup>IV</sup> supported by SiO<sub>2</sub>. Such CrL<sub>4</sub> complexes can have either a singlet (S = 0) or triplet (S = 1) spin ground state. We set out to understand this complex electronic structure using a combination of EPR and computational methods. HFEPR of Cr(DTBMS)<sub>4</sub> in the solid state showed the presence of three very similar triplet species with the major component having D = +0.556 cm<sup>&minus;1</sup> (Figure 3). Classical ligand-field theory (LFT) and quantum chemical theory (QCT), including ab initio methods, used EPR and electronic absorption spectra to give us a complete picture of the electronic structure of Cr(DTBMS)<sub>4</sub> (Figure 4), and other complexes of formula Cr(ER<sub>n</sub>)<sub>4</sub>, E = C, n = 3; E = N, n = 2; E = O, n = 1; E = F, n = 0. Computations showed the importance of ligand steric bulk and of &pi;-bonding in controlling the subtleties of electronic structure of CrL<sub>4</sub> species. These electronic structure results, including zfs, which is a measure of excited state accessibility, for both triplet and singlet excited states, shed light on the catalytic activity of paramagnetic Cr species possibly present in various catalytic cycles.</p> <p><strong>Phosphorus Chemistry</strong></p> <p>Phosphorus is an essential element for life and holds tremendous importance in the purview of commodity chemical synthesis. Mined phosphate rock is the typical P(V) starting material for all P chemistry, and it is processed in a linear, unsustainable way, by being transformed through the P(0) state of white phosphorus and then reoxdized back up to P(III) compounds. A more sustainable process that would underpin a circular P economy is a direct P(V) to P(III) conversion. The direct, two-electron reduction of P(V) oxoacids to their synthetically useful P(III) counterparts, therefore, is of considerable interest since this reaction is governed by a smaller thermodynamic penalty. We reported a direct electrochemical conversion fo P(V) to P(III) assisted by Lewis acids, and moreover defined a general mechanism (Figure 5) for Lewis-acid assisted P(V) to P(III) conversions. The reported electrochemical methodology bypasses the use of high-energy-density reagents and suggests a general strategy for the electrochemical reduction of thermodynamically stable X=O (X = main group element) bonds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2019<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;G&nbsp;Nocera</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453104408_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453104408_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figures for Outcomes report"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453104408_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figures for Outcomes report"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figures 1 and 2</div> <div class="imageCredit">PI lab and ACS pubs</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;G&nbsp;Nocera</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figures for Outcomes report</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453182206_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453182206_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figures for Outcomes report"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453182206_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figures for Outcomes report"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figures 3 and 4</div> <div class="imageCredit">PI labs and ACS pubs</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;G&nbsp;Nocera</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figures for Outcomes report</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453269050_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453269050_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figures for Outcomes report"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1464232/1464232_10377085_1574453269050_2019NSFOutcomesFigures_Page_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figures for Outcomes report"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5</div> <div class="imageCredit">PI labs and ACS pubs</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;G&nbsp;Nocera</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figures for Outcomes report</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Photoredox Catalysis  The most important criterion in any photochemical technology such as photovoltaic devices or artificial photosynthetic systems is its quantum efficiency, i.e. the conversion of incoming photons to the desired outcome. To be able to outcompete conventional technologies, high quantum efficiencies are imperative to increase productivity while lowering associated costs. Key outcomes of our photoredox work in the last year have been (i) the determination of the rate constants for a photoredox hydroamidation reaction involving five intermediates allowing us to identify the energy-wasting and nonproductive back reaction and (ii) the determination of both a dark and light reaction cycle for redox-mediated Ni-catalyzed aryl etherification that allowed the reaction to be run under both photoredox and electrochemical conditions.  We used nanosecond time-resolved spectroscopy to obtain quantitative mechanistic information on the photoredox catalytic hydroamidation reaction. By following the dynamics of the different transient intermediates formed after photoelectron transfer, we build a rare example of a complete mechanism for a photoredox catalytic reaction (Figure 1) and identify the major pathways responsible for the observed low quantum efficiency. Building on this knowledge, we optimize the reaction conditions to produce a significant increase in the quantum efficiency of the synthetic method.  We proposed a reaction cycle for redox-mediated, Ni-catalyzed aryl etherification under both photoredox and electrochemically mediated conditions. We demonstrate that a self-sustained Ni(I/III) cycle is operative in both cases by chemically synthesizing and characterizing a common paramagnetic Ni intermediate and establishing its catalytic activity. Furthermore, deleterious pathways leading to off-cycle Ni(II) species have been identified, allowing us to discover optimized conditions for achieving self-sustained reactivity at a &sim;15- fold increase in the quantum yield and a &sim;3-fold increase in the faradaic yield (Figure 2). These results highlight the importance of leveraging insight of complete reaction cycles for increasing the efficiency of redox-mediated reactions.  Oxygen Chemistry  Chromium species are the active sites in a variety of heterogeneous catalysts, such as the Phillips catalyst, which is composed of Cr ions supported by SiO2 and is used to produce polyethylene. Among the catalytically relevant oxidation states of chromium is CrIV. Families of neutral, homoleptic, four-coordinate complexes, CrL4, with a variety of monoanionic, monodentate ligands, such as L = alkyls, aryls, amides, ketimides (R2C = N&minus;), alkoxides, and siloxides, are available and can provide information regarding Cr sites in heterogeneous materials. For example, the previously reported siloxide, Cr(DTBMS)4, where DTBMS = &minus;OSiMettBu2 (ditert-butylmethylsiloxide), may be considered a molecular analogue of CrIV supported by SiO2. Such CrL4 complexes can have either a singlet (S = 0) or triplet (S = 1) spin ground state. We set out to understand this complex electronic structure using a combination of EPR and computational methods. HFEPR of Cr(DTBMS)4 in the solid state showed the presence of three very similar triplet species with the major component having D = +0.556 cm&minus;1 (Figure 3). Classical ligand-field theory (LFT) and quantum chemical theory (QCT), including ab initio methods, used EPR and electronic absorption spectra to give us a complete picture of the electronic structure of Cr(DTBMS)4 (Figure 4), and other complexes of formula Cr(ERn)4, E = C, n = 3; E = N, n = 2; E = O, n = 1; E = F, n = 0. Computations showed the importance of ligand steric bulk and of &pi;-bonding in controlling the subtleties of electronic structure of CrL4 species. These electronic structure results, including zfs, which is a measure of excited state accessibility, for both triplet and singlet excited states, shed light on the catalytic activity of paramagnetic Cr species possibly present in various catalytic cycles.  Phosphorus Chemistry  Phosphorus is an essential element for life and holds tremendous importance in the purview of commodity chemical synthesis. Mined phosphate rock is the typical P(V) starting material for all P chemistry, and it is processed in a linear, unsustainable way, by being transformed through the P(0) state of white phosphorus and then reoxdized back up to P(III) compounds. A more sustainable process that would underpin a circular P economy is a direct P(V) to P(III) conversion. The direct, two-electron reduction of P(V) oxoacids to their synthetically useful P(III) counterparts, therefore, is of considerable interest since this reaction is governed by a smaller thermodynamic penalty. We reported a direct electrochemical conversion fo P(V) to P(III) assisted by Lewis acids, and moreover defined a general mechanism (Figure 5) for Lewis-acid assisted P(V) to P(III) conversions. The reported electrochemical methodology bypasses the use of high-energy-density reagents and suggests a general strategy for the electrochemical reduction of thermodynamically stable X=O (X = main group element) bonds.             Last Modified: 11/22/2019       Submitted by: Daniel G Nocera]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
