<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CRII: SaTC: Privacy-Enhancing User Interfaces Based on Individualized Mental Models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>159586.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175586</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technology advances have brought numerous benefits to people and society, but also heightened risks to privacy. This project will investigate mechanisms and build tools to help people make privacy-aware decisions in different online contexts.  The outcomes will help people to better understand their own privacy preferences and behavior, and enable them to better manage their privacy on the Internet.  The project will create designs that can be integrated into mobile app markets and web browsers. The results will also inform Internet standards and governmental policies on Internet privacy. In addition, this project will have important educational and training benefits at the undergraduate and graduate levels, including privacy-related class projects and modules. These training opportunities will help students to become more aware of potential privacy issues in technologies and develop technical skills in building privacy-enhancing mechanisms. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate two main ideas: individualized mental models of privacy, and a universal privacy dashboard. People often have differing mental models of privacy, or preferences that are context-dependent. However, it has been shown that people?s actual decisions or behaviors often divert from their stated privacy preferences. Motivated by the theory of contiguity from learning sciences, this project will examine whether people will make privacy-preserving decisions when their individualized mental models and their decision choices are presented to them contiguously in time and space (e.g., on the same user interface). This project will also explore the universal privacy dashboard as a principled way to provide transparency regarding individual's mental privacy models and behaviors in two example domains:  online tracking and Android app permissions. This dashboard approach will enable people to monitor, reflect, and if technically feasible, directly change their privacy decisions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For further information see the project web site at: http://salt.ischool.syr.edu/privacymirror/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1464347</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yang</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yang Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yvw@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172440401</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629765</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[School of Information Studies]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441190</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[114 Hinds Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8228</Code>
<Text>CISE Resrch Initiatn Initiatve</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~175586</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Technologies advance by leaps and bounds, from widely adopted technologies such as the Internet and smart phones to emerging technologies such as smart homes. In parallel, there is also ubiquitous tracking and surveillance in our society, such as location tracking on our phones, web tracking and online behavioral advertising (OBA), and smart devices in our homes that can identify or infer our activities and even interests. &nbsp;Increasingly, people's lives are fraught with heightened challenges to protect their privacy.</p> <p>This project aims to understand people's privacy concerns and preferences, investigate mechanisms and build tools in different application contexts, such as mobile apps, online behavioral advertising (OBA), and smart home devices.</p> <p>This project has several important findings: (1) what factors affect people's attitudes toward data collection, usage and sharing by mobile apps, OBA and smart homes; (2) people's mental models of how emerging technologies such as OBA and smart home work, and in turn how these mental models could affect people's attitudes and behaviors; (3) people tend to care more about what information about them is being collected than who collects those pieces of information in the context of OBA; and (4) smart home devices could pose privacy risks to not only the owners/users of these devices but also bystanders, such as other family members or guests, and the privacy expectations of the owners and bystanders might be in conflict.</p> <p>Furthermore, this project has developed novel techniques for protecting people's privacy. For instance, this project developed personalized user interfaces for end users that can help them behave in a way that reflects their stated privacy preferences. The project team has also presented results from this project to technology companies as well as at the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), the U.S. government agency that provides consumer protection. In an effort to further translate the research results of this project into practice, the project team is in the process of applying for a patent.</p> <p>Last but not the least, this project has trained many students with diverse background (e.g., computer science, information science, psychology, design) in conducting research, particularly in the area of privacy. Some of these students are from under-represented groups. Many students applied what they learned from this project in their internships or full-time jobs in the technology industry. For instance, one Latino student interned in the privacy team of a big company. One female student works as a full-time privacy analyst for another big company.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Yang&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Technologies advance by leaps and bounds, from widely adopted technologies such as the Internet and smart phones to emerging technologies such as smart homes. In parallel, there is also ubiquitous tracking and surveillance in our society, such as location tracking on our phones, web tracking and online behavioral advertising (OBA), and smart devices in our homes that can identify or infer our activities and even interests.  Increasingly, people's lives are fraught with heightened challenges to protect their privacy.  This project aims to understand people's privacy concerns and preferences, investigate mechanisms and build tools in different application contexts, such as mobile apps, online behavioral advertising (OBA), and smart home devices.  This project has several important findings: (1) what factors affect people's attitudes toward data collection, usage and sharing by mobile apps, OBA and smart homes; (2) people's mental models of how emerging technologies such as OBA and smart home work, and in turn how these mental models could affect people's attitudes and behaviors; (3) people tend to care more about what information about them is being collected than who collects those pieces of information in the context of OBA; and (4) smart home devices could pose privacy risks to not only the owners/users of these devices but also bystanders, such as other family members or guests, and the privacy expectations of the owners and bystanders might be in conflict.  Furthermore, this project has developed novel techniques for protecting people's privacy. For instance, this project developed personalized user interfaces for end users that can help them behave in a way that reflects their stated privacy preferences. The project team has also presented results from this project to technology companies as well as at the Federal Trade Commission (FTC), the U.S. government agency that provides consumer protection. In an effort to further translate the research results of this project into practice, the project team is in the process of applying for a patent.  Last but not the least, this project has trained many students with diverse background (e.g., computer science, information science, psychology, design) in conducting research, particularly in the area of privacy. Some of these students are from under-represented groups. Many students applied what they learned from this project in their internships or full-time jobs in the technology industry. For instance, one Latino student interned in the privacy team of a big company. One female student works as a full-time privacy analyst for another big company.          Last Modified: 12/01/2019       Submitted by: Yang Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
