<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Combinatorics in Geometry, Physics, and Representation Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>480000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Combinatorics is the study of discrete structures such as permutations, combinations, subsets, and so on.  This research project studies combinatorial problems that arise from algebra, geometry, and theoretical physics.  One of the topics to be studied is the classification of electrical resistor networks consisting of finitely many resistors.  In this problem, one studies whether the structure of an electrical network can be recovered by performing measurements at particular nodes.  Another problem to be studied is the understanding of the combinatorics of high-energy particle scattering experiments.  These computations have been related to the combinatorics of permutations and other related projects.  A third problem is the study of certain discrete two-dimensional surfaces in high dimensional space, called membranes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator's work is in algebraic combinatorics.  Topics to be pursued include: (a) Development of the theory of Laurent phenomenon algebras, originally introduced in joint work with Pavlo Pylyavskyy.  These LP algebras generalize cluster algebras by allowing exchange polynomials to have arbitrarily many monomials, rather than just two. (b) The study of the algebraic deRham cohomology of cluster algebras, which may have applications to the calculation of higher extensions of Verma modules.  (c) A development of a positive analogue of polymatroids, called polypositroids.  These polytopes turn out to have remarkable properties, and appear to be related to certain discrete minimal surfaces called membranes. (d) The study of a parabolic analogue of Whittaker functions.  The aim is to study solutions to the quantum D-module for a generalized partial flag variety.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1464693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Lam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Lam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tfylam@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347635034</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105778</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Combinatorics is the study of finite or discrete structures.&nbsp; This project studied and developed connections between combinatorics and geometry, physics, and representation theory.</p> <p>One of the main achievements of this project is the study of combinatorial and topological properties of "Positive geometries".&nbsp; The classical example of these geometries are convex polytopes such as cubes, tetrahedra, octahedra, and so on.&nbsp; More recently, positive geometries known as "amplituhedra" have been found to appear in high-energy theoretical physics.&nbsp; An important problem in particle physics is to develop models to predict outcomes of particle accelerator experiments.&nbsp; Scattering amplitudes encode this information, and a growing subject at the interface of mathematics and physics concerns the investigation of positive geometries whose volumes encode scattering amplitudes.</p> <p>Another main achievement of this project is a new bridge between Schubert calculus and knot theory.&nbsp; Schubert calculus is a branch of enumerative geometry concerned with counting solutions to problems such as "how many lines intersect four fixed lines in three-dimensional space"?&nbsp; Knot theory is concerned with the classificaiton of knots, closed loops inside three-dimensional space that can be knotted.&nbsp; This project has shown that invariants of certain knots control the geometry of spaces appearing in Schubert calculus.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>A diverse group of graduate and undergraduate students were involved as part of this project, and these students were trained in mathematical research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/06/2021<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Lam</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Combinatorics is the study of finite or discrete structures.  This project studied and developed connections between combinatorics and geometry, physics, and representation theory.  One of the main achievements of this project is the study of combinatorial and topological properties of "Positive geometries".  The classical example of these geometries are convex polytopes such as cubes, tetrahedra, octahedra, and so on.  More recently, positive geometries known as "amplituhedra" have been found to appear in high-energy theoretical physics.  An important problem in particle physics is to develop models to predict outcomes of particle accelerator experiments.  Scattering amplitudes encode this information, and a growing subject at the interface of mathematics and physics concerns the investigation of positive geometries whose volumes encode scattering amplitudes.  Another main achievement of this project is a new bridge between Schubert calculus and knot theory.  Schubert calculus is a branch of enumerative geometry concerned with counting solutions to problems such as "how many lines intersect four fixed lines in three-dimensional space"?  Knot theory is concerned with the classificaiton of knots, closed loops inside three-dimensional space that can be knotted.  This project has shown that invariants of certain knots control the geometry of spaces appearing in Schubert calculus.    A diverse group of graduate and undergraduate students were involved as part of this project, and these students were trained in mathematical research.       Last Modified: 07/06/2021       Submitted by: Thomas Lam]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
