<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chemical Connectomics: Nonlinear Dynamics of Electrochemical Reaction Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>387763.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406002</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms (CSDM-A) Program of the Division of Chemistry is funding Professor Istvan Z. Kiss of Saint Louis University to investigate complex, far-from-equilibrium charge transfer chemical reactions that take place on networks imposed by dynamic environments of electrochemical devices (e.g., sensors and batteries). The identification of organizing principles and experimental characterization of far-from-equilibrium systems have broad applications in physical, chemical, and biological systems. The investigation is relevant to needs of industrial applications of galvanic and electrolytic cells. The oscillatory electrochemical media test theories on synchronization and network dynamics that have importance in circadian rhythms and hypersynchronous neural discharges in epileptic seizures.  The project includes outreach activities aimed at middle school, high school and college students and the general public through the "Nonlinear Corner," and conveys novel scientific notions of nonlinear science and the emergence of complex, intelligent behavior of abiotic systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Professor Istvan Kiss and his research group address three specific aims that are based on fundamental scientific problems in analytical chemistry utilizing multi-electrodes, design specifics of batteries and electrolysis cells, and energy distribution networks: (1) Test the hypothesis that emergent electrochemical networks in multi-electrode microfluidic flow cells can describe the complex dynamical phenomena, (2) explore self-organized spatio-temporal behavior in cathode-anode multi-electrodes, and (3) explore the pattern formation of electrochemical reactions that take place on a designed network facilitated by a resistance interface. The construction of versatile emergent and engineered networks provides a new geometrical space for the chemical reactions to take place. The extraction of network topology contributes to the establishment of Chemical Connectomics, the science of connected reactions in dynamic environments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1465013</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Istvan</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Istvan Z Kiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>izkiss@slu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149772139</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243198</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Saint Louis University</Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3149773925</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>221 N. Grand Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050220722</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAINT LOUIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050220722</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Saint Louis University]]></Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3501 Laclede Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9101</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~387763</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~18239</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electrochemical devices (e.g., batteries), push electricity between the two polarities (+ and - sign) through the use of electrochemical reactions: on one end electrons are generated on the metal (electrode) surface; these electrons then flow through the wires, operate electrical devices, and then consumed at other end through another reaction. To avoid catastrophic failure of battery operation (e.g., explosion), it is essential for the process to complete in a rather stable, uniform manner. However, electrochemical reactions in such operating environments tend to develop critical phenomena leading widely oscillating behavior in time and nonuniform discharges in space. The project explored the organizing principles of such so-called self-organized, emergent reactive properties of electrochemical reaction systems.</p> <p>Present approaches to solve these problems largely rely on construction of very complicated mathematical (partial differential) equations, and solving them with computers. However, even with the use of supercomputers, one cannot simulate every possible operation condition. Instead, we use nonlinear dynamics (a branch of mathematics and physics) to construct simplified models for the chemical system, and characterize the stability of the generated patterns. In this simplified model, the battery is composed of compartments (chemical reactions) with rather uniform properties, and the patterns occur by coupling between the compartments. Then, one can use the powerful graph theory of dynamical systems to predict the generic behavior of the system (e.g., explosion or stabilization of a given pattern).</p> <p>The approach was based on three complementary approaches. First, we constructed networks of electrochemical reactions, where the existence of fundamentally novel types of chemical pattern formation was confirmed. We have shown that the strict conditions for formation of stationary patterns formulated by Allen Turing for regular chemical systems (e.g, in Petri dish) are much more relaxed in tree networks; such tree networks can easily form domains of localized chemical reactivity. Similarly, with chemical reactions that generate oscillations, a pattern called 'chimera' state was observed. In this case, in a network composed of two modules of densely connected components, one module can show completely uniform, while the other rather desynchronized pattern. Formation of such structures in a simple chemical system attracts attention from other fields of physics and biology, for example, could provide a framework for understanding hemispheric sleep in marine animals and birds.</p> <p>Now that we have seen that networks play important role in chemical pattern formation, we posed the question of what type of network can occur in electrochemical devices? For this, we needed a mathematical technique, which after a test run, can analyse causality between units even if the presence of hundreds of compartment. We developed a new technique, ICON, with which the interactions among reacting sites can be precisely decoded, even for highly nonlinear chemical reactions with large heterogeneities. Such high fidelity prediction of the spatiotemporal pattern was not previously possible, e.g., with methods based on kinetic models, because of the inability to extract theoretical and experimental information on the origin of heterogeneities and the timing of the interactions between the regulated chemical reactions. &nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, we applied the experimental and modeling techniques in two practical examples. We built a lab-on-a-chip device, where complex chemical reactions can be investigated. Such devices with simple reactions are often used in sensors. Integration of complex reaction is a major challenge because the interaction of many different types of processes (e.g., chemical reactions, mass transfer, and potential drops in the electrolyte) can produce a plethora of unexpected behaviors. We managed to decrypt the interaction through the electrolyte, which showed a range of coupling (uni- or bi-directional, positive or negative), depending on the cell design. In a second example, we created a multi-electrode anode (electron generator) and a single-electrode cathode (electron consumer) system. By careful analysis, we showed that the system behaves similarly to the quorum sensing mechanism of bacteria colonies, which can sense its own cell density and generate a synchronize response of synchronized chemical activity above a critical value. The research projects trained 7 graduate and 3 undergraduate students. &nbsp;</p> <p>The project also involved a community engagement through the development of a 'Nonlinear Corner' at Saint Louis University. We hosted 5 high school students, who participated in developing demonstration experiments of chemical chaos. The experiments show that electrochemical cells can exhibit complex behavior, but we can use physics and mathematics to decrypt this complexity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649809720_fig_rot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649809720_fig_rot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rotating wave patterns with a ring network."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649809720_fig_rot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rotating wave patterns with a ring network."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">All possible patterns recorded in experiments with a ring network. The electrodissolution of nickel can be uniform (inner circle), or exhibit 1-4 high activity locations (red color).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z. Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rotating wave patterns with a ring network.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649865778_fig_quorum--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649865778_fig_quorum--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Network structure of cathode-anode interactions."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649865778_fig_quorum--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Network structure of cathode-anode interactions."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A multiple anode (A) - single cathode (C) electrochemical system can be represented by a star network where the interaction mechanism is through a common media. Activity only occurs when a quorum of anode reaction sites is present.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z. Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Network structure of cathode-anode interactions.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649942279_fig_tree--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649942279_fig_tree--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Localized activity in a tree network."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577649942279_fig_tree--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Localized activity in a tree network."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Electrochemical reactions taking place on a tree network of electrodes can be localized to domains generating a stationary pattern.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z. Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Localized activity in a tree network.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577650004396_fig_micro--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577650004396_fig_micro--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Patterns with a microfluidic flow channel."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577650004396_fig_micro--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Patterns with a microfluidic flow channel."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The oscillatory nickel electrodissolution with three electrodes can exhibit partial synchronization with the two downstream (top), upstream (middle), or the two distant (bottom) electrodes.  Circles: electrodes. Triangle and square: reference and counter electrodes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z. Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Patterns with a microfluidic flow channel.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577651684477_fig_chimera--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577651684477_fig_chimera--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chimera pattern"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1465013/1465013_10394554_1577651684477_fig_chimera--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chimera pattern"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A modular network exhibits chimera state with one group (left) exhibiting uniform  state on the other (right) a desynchronized state.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z. Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chimera pattern</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Electrochemical devices (e.g., batteries), push electricity between the two polarities (+ and - sign) through the use of electrochemical reactions: on one end electrons are generated on the metal (electrode) surface; these electrons then flow through the wires, operate electrical devices, and then consumed at other end through another reaction. To avoid catastrophic failure of battery operation (e.g., explosion), it is essential for the process to complete in a rather stable, uniform manner. However, electrochemical reactions in such operating environments tend to develop critical phenomena leading widely oscillating behavior in time and nonuniform discharges in space. The project explored the organizing principles of such so-called self-organized, emergent reactive properties of electrochemical reaction systems.  Present approaches to solve these problems largely rely on construction of very complicated mathematical (partial differential) equations, and solving them with computers. However, even with the use of supercomputers, one cannot simulate every possible operation condition. Instead, we use nonlinear dynamics (a branch of mathematics and physics) to construct simplified models for the chemical system, and characterize the stability of the generated patterns. In this simplified model, the battery is composed of compartments (chemical reactions) with rather uniform properties, and the patterns occur by coupling between the compartments. Then, one can use the powerful graph theory of dynamical systems to predict the generic behavior of the system (e.g., explosion or stabilization of a given pattern).  The approach was based on three complementary approaches. First, we constructed networks of electrochemical reactions, where the existence of fundamentally novel types of chemical pattern formation was confirmed. We have shown that the strict conditions for formation of stationary patterns formulated by Allen Turing for regular chemical systems (e.g, in Petri dish) are much more relaxed in tree networks; such tree networks can easily form domains of localized chemical reactivity. Similarly, with chemical reactions that generate oscillations, a pattern called 'chimera' state was observed. In this case, in a network composed of two modules of densely connected components, one module can show completely uniform, while the other rather desynchronized pattern. Formation of such structures in a simple chemical system attracts attention from other fields of physics and biology, for example, could provide a framework for understanding hemispheric sleep in marine animals and birds.  Now that we have seen that networks play important role in chemical pattern formation, we posed the question of what type of network can occur in electrochemical devices? For this, we needed a mathematical technique, which after a test run, can analyse causality between units even if the presence of hundreds of compartment. We developed a new technique, ICON, with which the interactions among reacting sites can be precisely decoded, even for highly nonlinear chemical reactions with large heterogeneities. Such high fidelity prediction of the spatiotemporal pattern was not previously possible, e.g., with methods based on kinetic models, because of the inability to extract theoretical and experimental information on the origin of heterogeneities and the timing of the interactions between the regulated chemical reactions.    Finally, we applied the experimental and modeling techniques in two practical examples. We built a lab-on-a-chip device, where complex chemical reactions can be investigated. Such devices with simple reactions are often used in sensors. Integration of complex reaction is a major challenge because the interaction of many different types of processes (e.g., chemical reactions, mass transfer, and potential drops in the electrolyte) can produce a plethora of unexpected behaviors. We managed to decrypt the interaction through the electrolyte, which showed a range of coupling (uni- or bi-directional, positive or negative), depending on the cell design. In a second example, we created a multi-electrode anode (electron generator) and a single-electrode cathode (electron consumer) system. By careful analysis, we showed that the system behaves similarly to the quorum sensing mechanism of bacteria colonies, which can sense its own cell density and generate a synchronize response of synchronized chemical activity above a critical value. The research projects trained 7 graduate and 3 undergraduate students.    The project also involved a community engagement through the development of a 'Nonlinear Corner' at Saint Louis University. We hosted 5 high school students, who participated in developing demonstration experiments of chemical chaos. The experiments show that electrochemical cells can exhibit complex behavior, but we can use physics and mathematics to decrypt this complexity.          Last Modified: 12/29/2019       Submitted by: Istvan Z Kiss]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
