<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Structural characterization of organometallic reaction intermediates and vibrational mechanics of water cages with temperature-controlled cryogenic ion spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>520000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>520000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms program is supporting fundamental research of Professor Mark A. Johnson at Yale University.  Johnson is developing a new type of scientific instrument that yields precise structural information on complex molecular architectures extracted from solution.  Under this grant, he will expand the scope of the method to enable the capture and structural characterization of key reaction intermediates that underlie the mechanisms of small molecule (e.g., alkenes, H2O, H2) activation by contemporary homogeneous organometallic catalysts.  The motivation to identify these transient species is that, at present, much of the effort in catalyst design involves extensive trial and error based on overall yield, while little is often known about exactly what aspects of the chemical transformation are being affected by the various modifications.  Students and visiting faculty involved in this endeavor integrate elements of bioanalytical chemistry with atomic, molecular and optical (AMO) physics to create a new platform for chemical analysis. As such, this program directly interfaces physical chemistry students with immediate challenges addressed by synthetic colleagues, and consequently prepares a new generation of scientists with a versatile skill set, well centered in the chemical sciences.  An ongoing and extensive collaboration with theoretical colleague Prof. Anne McCoy at Ohio State further broadens the impact of the work by creating an interactive venue for young theorists to sharpen their skills on emergent scientific themes. Graduate students and postdocs directly involved in the project also work in close collaborations with laboratories in Germany.  This also contributes to their preparedness to perform at an increasingly competitive international level in the elite arena of basic science. Closer to home, this program integrates faculty from undergraduate institutions through summer research opportunities, and students from nearby universities without graduate programs are incorporated into ongoing work by carrying out senior research projects at Yale. Finally, this program has a longstanding tradition of opening its doors to students in the New Haven schools to illustrate how the basic science principles they are learning are in play at the foundation of the new methods under development. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Cryogenic Ion Vibrational Predissociation Spectroscopy (CVIP) is a new instrumental technique which integrates mass spectrometry with high resolution infrared spectroscopy. One key feature of the approach is the implementation of cryogenic processing of the gas phase ions to effectively quench the reactive species into well-defined structures that yield sufficiently sharp features in their vibrational spectra to allow structure determination. This is carried out using vibrational predissociation spectroscopy of very weakly bound adducts attached to target ions in a custom built, radio frequency ion trap held at 5K.  In addition to its application to catalysis, the proposed work also addresses key unanswered questions regarding the critical local interactions that underlie bulk behavior of pure water as well as the layer of water molecules in direct contact with charged solutes. Because the microscopic behavior of water is central to so many fields of science, this aspect of the work is ongoing, and has impacted efforts ranging from the mechanism of vision to the remediation of heavy metals in contaminated environments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1465100</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark A Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mark.johnson@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034325226</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000451814</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208047</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 Prospect Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~520000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>This grant supported an experimental physical chemistry effort at Yale University. The specific aim of our project was to exploit the capabilities of a new type of instrumentation, largely developed by our team over the past decade, that can determine the structures of very fragile molecular assemblies at low temperature by combining the precision of laser spectroscopy with the extreme sensitivity of mass spectrometry.&nbsp; In our approach, species in solution are isolated in the gas phase, cooled close to absolute zero using cryogenic ion trapping techniques, separated according to mass-to-charge ratio, and subjected to structure determination using vibrational spectroscopy carried out using two infrared lasers. This hybrid capability is a new and powerful type of chemical analysis that can isolate the molecular-level rearrangements that define the pathways controlled at the macroscopic scale in the course of chemical synthesis.&nbsp;</span><span>&nbsp;</span><span>One example central to this grant has been the capture and identification of key reaction intermediates in the alkali metal ion (potassium in this case)-mediated transformation of the very stable N</span><sub>2</sub><span>&nbsp;molecule into compounds that feature NH chemical bonds. That application was carried out in close collaboration with Yale synthetic chemist Patrick Holland, who designed the reaction strategy. Together, we demonstrated the utility of our hybrid instrument to elucidate individual NH bond formation events that ultimately lead to the formation of stable products. This success illustrated how the new instrument can reveal structural details of chemical transformations that are inaccessible to traditional methods of chemical analysis.&nbsp;</span><span>&nbsp;</span><span>We leveraged that feature in another collaborative study, this time with synthetic chemist Scott Miller at Yale, in which we captured and characterized metabolites, species that are generated in very low abundance when the body digests drugs. Characterization of these species is a critically important step that must be overcome before a drug can be cleared for general use, and is very expensive because the metabolite yields are so small. In this case, we demonstrated that the structures and chemical identities of the metabolites formed by digestion of the commonly used drug, Diovan</span><sup>(R)</sup><span>&nbsp;</span><span>&nbsp;</span><span>(Valsartan), used to control blood pressure, could be readily determined using advanced capabilities of our instrument that can efficiently sort out the structures of individual species, including those that are embedded in complex mixtures and have the same mass-to-charge ratio (isomers). &nbsp;</span><br /><br /><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The work outlined above addresses the broader impact of our custom instrumentation in the chemical sciences. As physical chemists, however, we are also exploring fundamental questions about the structure of water and the special nature of water at the air-water interface. Because water is pervasive across all branches of chemistry and biology, there is an extensive, world-wide effort to simulate its properties in extreme environments from first principles. Our new instrument provides an unprecedented way to monitor how individual water molecules, and even single OH oscillators within a water molecule, contribute to the behavior of bulk water at the interface. This information is critically important for the simulation of spectral patterns obtained using surface-selective spectroscopic schemes, which in turn are the benchmarks most commonly used&nbsp;</span><span>to test the accuracy of theoretical methods. However, because the spectra of interfacial water at room temperature are broad and largely unstructured, they often do not challenge fundamental theoretical assumptions. By isolating the spectral behavior of interfacial water at the molecular level, we have provided detailed benchmarks upon which to build secure theoretical frameworks. We developed a methodology by which small, cage-like structures of water molecules enclosing a metal ion are isolated. These structures naturally form when a sheet of 20 water molecules, only one water molecule thick, wraps around a metal ion. We then used isotopes to block out 19 of the&nbsp;20 waters in the sheet, and monitored the behavior of the single remaining H</span><sub>2</sub><span>O molecule embedded in the surface. The results are the first of their kind, and were reported in a 2019 article in&nbsp;</span><em>Science</em><span>. This effort was carried out in collaboration with theoretical chemist Anne McCoy (U. Washington), and established how the various spectroscopically distinct ways that a water molecule can lock into the web of hydrogen bonds</span><span>&nbsp;are encoded in the correlated frequencies between the two OH oscillators. The results also describe a new feature that appears in the spectrum when the OH stretching vibration interacts with the bending motion of the molecule. This work is on-going under current NSF support, where we are extending the measurements to completely deconstruct the molecular-level motions underlying the vibrational spectrum of interfacial water.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;A&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This grant supported an experimental physical chemistry effort at Yale University. The specific aim of our project was to exploit the capabilities of a new type of instrumentation, largely developed by our team over the past decade, that can determine the structures of very fragile molecular assemblies at low temperature by combining the precision of laser spectroscopy with the extreme sensitivity of mass spectrometry.  In our approach, species in solution are isolated in the gas phase, cooled close to absolute zero using cryogenic ion trapping techniques, separated according to mass-to-charge ratio, and subjected to structure determination using vibrational spectroscopy carried out using two infrared lasers. This hybrid capability is a new and powerful type of chemical analysis that can isolate the molecular-level rearrangements that define the pathways controlled at the macroscopic scale in the course of chemical synthesis.  One example central to this grant has been the capture and identification of key reaction intermediates in the alkali metal ion (potassium in this case)-mediated transformation of the very stable N2 molecule into compounds that feature NH chemical bonds. That application was carried out in close collaboration with Yale synthetic chemist Patrick Holland, who designed the reaction strategy. Together, we demonstrated the utility of our hybrid instrument to elucidate individual NH bond formation events that ultimately lead to the formation of stable products. This success illustrated how the new instrument can reveal structural details of chemical transformations that are inaccessible to traditional methods of chemical analysis.  We leveraged that feature in another collaborative study, this time with synthetic chemist Scott Miller at Yale, in which we captured and characterized metabolites, species that are generated in very low abundance when the body digests drugs. Characterization of these species is a critically important step that must be overcome before a drug can be cleared for general use, and is very expensive because the metabolite yields are so small. In this case, we demonstrated that the structures and chemical identities of the metabolites formed by digestion of the commonly used drug, Diovan(R)  (Valsartan), used to control blood pressure, could be readily determined using advanced capabilities of our instrument that can efficiently sort out the structures of individual species, including those that are embedded in complex mixtures and have the same mass-to-charge ratio (isomers).     The work outlined above addresses the broader impact of our custom instrumentation in the chemical sciences. As physical chemists, however, we are also exploring fundamental questions about the structure of water and the special nature of water at the air-water interface. Because water is pervasive across all branches of chemistry and biology, there is an extensive, world-wide effort to simulate its properties in extreme environments from first principles. Our new instrument provides an unprecedented way to monitor how individual water molecules, and even single OH oscillators within a water molecule, contribute to the behavior of bulk water at the interface. This information is critically important for the simulation of spectral patterns obtained using surface-selective spectroscopic schemes, which in turn are the benchmarks most commonly used to test the accuracy of theoretical methods. However, because the spectra of interfacial water at room temperature are broad and largely unstructured, they often do not challenge fundamental theoretical assumptions. By isolating the spectral behavior of interfacial water at the molecular level, we have provided detailed benchmarks upon which to build secure theoretical frameworks. We developed a methodology by which small, cage-like structures of water molecules enclosing a metal ion are isolated. These structures naturally form when a sheet of 20 water molecules, only one water molecule thick, wraps around a metal ion. We then used isotopes to block out 19 of the 20 waters in the sheet, and monitored the behavior of the single remaining H2O molecule embedded in the surface. The results are the first of their kind, and were reported in a 2019 article in Science. This effort was carried out in collaboration with theoretical chemist Anne McCoy (U. Washington), and established how the various spectroscopically distinct ways that a water molecule can lock into the web of hydrogen bonds are encoded in the correlated frequencies between the two OH oscillators. The results also describe a new feature that appears in the spectrum when the OH stretching vibration interacts with the bending motion of the molecule. This work is on-going under current NSF support, where we are extending the measurements to completely deconstruct the molecular-level motions underlying the vibrational spectrum of interfacial water.       Last Modified: 12/17/2019       Submitted by: Mark A Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
