<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Resilience of Caribbean octocorals following Hurricanes Irma and Maria</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>126722.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>126722</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel J. Thornhill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dthornhi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928143</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Disturbance and subsequent recovery have been key factors in the dynamics of coral reef populations, but in the Caribbean, there has been a steady decline in the abundance of hard corals accompanied by increased abundance of algae.  This characterization overlooks the observation that at some sites for which there are quantitative data, the abundances of octocorals (sea fans and sea plumes) have increased.  Closer inspection of those data reveals that octocorals have also declined at times, but unlike hard corals, they recovered and are now more abundant in at least some locations than 30 years ago. The change in abundances of these organisms would appear to due to the greater resilience of octocorals. The damage inflicted by Hurricanes Irma and Maria on the south shore of St. John, U.S. Virgin Is. provides a window into these processes.  Abundances of hard corals on these reefs have been monitored for the past 30 years and the octocorals have been followed for the past 4 years. Colonization of the newly opened space on the reef will be studied to determine if further shifts in abundances can be expected and to understand the basis for the greater resilience of octocoral populations.  Characterizing the resilience of octocorals relative to hard corals will have implications for the fate of Caribbean reefs in a world subject of increasing levels of stress. This will be of importance to policy makers and managers, because hard corals and octocorals provide substantially different ecosystem services. In addition to its impact on our fundamental understanding of reef processes, the grant will support the training of graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Coral reefs have been recognized to be disturbance driven systems for over 50 years and disturbance has been considered to be important in maintaining diversity of reef communities. However, the past 30 years has been characterized by declines in the abundances of scleractinians, often associated with acute events such as hurricanes and bleaching events. A knowledge of the effects of disturbance and subsequent recovery that occurs during these events is critical to understanding the changes in reef structure that have occurred in the last 30 years.  At sites for which there are data, changes in the relative abundance of scleractinians and octocorals appear to coincide with disturbance followed by octocoral recovery and a lack of scleractinian recovery. This change must reflect changes in larval supply, settlement, and/or survival, and those differences should be greatest following disturbance. The effects of Hurricanes Irma and Maria on the south shore of St. John provide the opportunity to characterize recruitment following disturbance and identify the processes that may limit successful recruitment on contemporary reefs. Data are already available on the abundance of octocoral and scleractinian species over the past 4 years, and annual censuses have provided data on octocoral recruitment and survival and species level characterizations of octocoral abundances. Recruitment and survival are also being related to spatial complexity of the habitat at the scale of mm and cm and the effects on hurricane driven changes in that spatial complexity will also be assessed. The frequency and intensity of disturbances will at the least continue at historical or greater levels.  The comparison of data from before and now after disturbance will provide a powerful assessment of the resilience of octocorals and scleractinians and the role of recruitment and recruit survival in their relative resilience. Thus the effects of Hurricanes Irma and Maria provide a window on the nature of future reefs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1801475</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Lasker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard R Lasker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hlasker@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166454870</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165580</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142600001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[126 Cooke Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>074Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Irma 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1174</Code>
<Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8556</Code>
<Text>Coral Reefs</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~126722</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>After centuries of human-mediated disturbances on Caribbean reefs, the appearance and composition of modern Caribbean coral reefs are vastly different from those described in the 1950s. On many reefs, stony corals have not recovered from an array of both natural and anthropogenic hazards.&nbsp; Many of these reefs now have an abundance of fleshy algae, but at other locations organisms such as octocorals, also known as gorgonian corals, and sponges have become the visually dominant organisms.</p> <p>Increases in octocoral abundance over the last few decades suggest that octocorals may represent a substitute for stony corals on present-day Caribbean reefs. However, the persistence of octocoral communities will depend on their ability to survive and recover from disturbances that have depressed stony coral abundance. The passage of Hurricanes Irma and Maria over St John, Virgin Islands in 2017 provided opportunity to assess the resilience of octocoral communities that had been studied over the preceding 4 years.&nbsp;</p> <p>The hurricanes depressed the densities of juvenile and adult octocoral colonies as much as 47%. However, there were only weak effects on octocorals measured as both the number of species present and the relative abundances of the octocoral species. Differences in the makeup of communities that existed prior to the hurricanes were still present after the hurricanes. The density of octocoral recruits (individuals that were &le; 5 cm high) was lower in the year following the hurricanes, but returned to pre-hurricane densities in 2019. Persistently high octocoral recruitment provides a mechanism supporting ecological resilience of these communities. Octocorals provide only a subset of the ecosystem services that stony corals historically generated, but our observations illustrate how ?octocoral forests? can become the structurally dominant community on Caribbean reefs. However, that assessment does not incorporate further environmental degradation; continuing environmental degradation is a threat to all tropical marine communities.</p> <p>The research provides critical information on the potential futures of Caribbean coral reefs.&nbsp; The products of the research include a submitted technical publication, two presentations to professional meetings, and TV and radio interviews discussing the project finding.&nbsp; Two graduate students, 3 undergraduates, and a volunteer received professional training over the course of the study. Trainees working on the project included 4 women.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Howard&nbsp;R&nbsp;Lasker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1801475/1801475_10524426_1577729521630_DSCN0359--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1801475/1801475_10524426_1577729521630_DSCN0359--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Octocorals at Booby Rock, St John, Virgin Islands following Hurricanes Irma and Maria"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1801475/1801475_10524426_1577729521630_DSCN0359--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Octocorals at Booby Rock, St John, Virgin Islands following Hurricanes Irma and Maria"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The image illustrates the dramatic reduction in octocoral abundance that occurred at Booby Rock.  While many healthy colonies remained the large amount of open space is indicative of colonies being ripped from the substratum by wave action.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard Lasker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Howard&nbsp;R&nbsp;Lasker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Octocorals at Booby Rock, St John, Virgin Islands following Hurricanes Irma and Maria</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1801475/1801475_10524426_1577728868464_BoobyRk_20130801_005--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1801475/1801475_10524426_1577728868464_BoobyRk_20130801_005--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Octocorals at Booby Rock, St John, Virgin Islands in 2013"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1801475/1801475_10524426_1577728868464_BoobyRk_20130801_005--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Octocorals at Booby Rock, St John, Virgin Islands in 2013"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Octocoral forest at Booby Rock in 2013, illustrating the high density of colonies prior to Hurricanes Irma and Maria</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard Lasker</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Howard&nbsp;R&nbsp;Lasker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Octocorals at Booby Rock, St John, Virgin Islands in 2013</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ After centuries of human-mediated disturbances on Caribbean reefs, the appearance and composition of modern Caribbean coral reefs are vastly different from those described in the 1950s. On many reefs, stony corals have not recovered from an array of both natural and anthropogenic hazards.  Many of these reefs now have an abundance of fleshy algae, but at other locations organisms such as octocorals, also known as gorgonian corals, and sponges have become the visually dominant organisms.  Increases in octocoral abundance over the last few decades suggest that octocorals may represent a substitute for stony corals on present-day Caribbean reefs. However, the persistence of octocoral communities will depend on their ability to survive and recover from disturbances that have depressed stony coral abundance. The passage of Hurricanes Irma and Maria over St John, Virgin Islands in 2017 provided opportunity to assess the resilience of octocoral communities that had been studied over the preceding 4 years.   The hurricanes depressed the densities of juvenile and adult octocoral colonies as much as 47%. However, there were only weak effects on octocorals measured as both the number of species present and the relative abundances of the octocoral species. Differences in the makeup of communities that existed prior to the hurricanes were still present after the hurricanes. The density of octocoral recruits (individuals that were &le; 5 cm high) was lower in the year following the hurricanes, but returned to pre-hurricane densities in 2019. Persistently high octocoral recruitment provides a mechanism supporting ecological resilience of these communities. Octocorals provide only a subset of the ecosystem services that stony corals historically generated, but our observations illustrate how ?octocoral forests? can become the structurally dominant community on Caribbean reefs. However, that assessment does not incorporate further environmental degradation; continuing environmental degradation is a threat to all tropical marine communities.  The research provides critical information on the potential futures of Caribbean coral reefs.  The products of the research include a submitted technical publication, two presentations to professional meetings, and TV and radio interviews discussing the project finding.  Two graduate students, 3 undergraduates, and a volunteer received professional training over the course of the study. Trainees working on the project included 4 women.          Last Modified: 12/30/2019       Submitted by: Howard R Lasker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
