<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New Approaches for Spatial Distribution Dynamics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/31/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73967.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>73967</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cheryl Eavey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ceavey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927269</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will improve understanding of spatial inequality dynamics through methodological advances in measurement and modeling.  Understanding the nature of spatial inequality dynamics is vital to both basic social science and to public policy, yet existing methods and models provide incomplete views of these spatial dynamics.  While a central focus of inequality research has been on the evolution of the aggregate income distribution, much less attention has been directed at the spatial pattern of inequality and pattern dynamics.  Spatial inequalities can have important implications for social cohesion, economic growth, and the design of policies targeted at reducing the level of inequality.  The advances produced in the project will have wide applicability.  In addition to spatial income inequality dynamics, many other social and economic phenomena have distributions that evolve in space and time.  Software packages will be delivered as open-source projects and accompanied with extensive tutorials and documentation to facilitate broad dissemination across the social sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will develop new analytical methods for the study of spatial dynamics of income inequality; specifically, new approaches will be developed to measuring changes in the distributional characteristics of those dynamics that incorporate their spatial dependence and heterogeneity.  The new approaches will include both global measures that report summary properties of the spatial dynamics as well as local indicators that can be used to identify hot-spots of locations that are important drivers of the overall dynamics or are outliers from the global trends.  Analytical and simulation based evaluations of the statistical properties of the new measures will be conducted, and empirical applications involving regional income inequalities will be carried out.  These new analytics will be incorporated into enhanced versions of two open-source spatial analysis packages: Python Spatial Analysis Library and Space-Time Analysis of Regional Systems.  The former provides social scientists who wish to develop custom applications with access to a modular library that can be used in conjunction with existing software to enable the new space-time analytics.  The latter is a user-friendly analytical and visualization package that can facilitate exploratory investigation of spatial distribution dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1801801</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergio</FirstName>
<LastName>Rey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergio Rey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Sergio.Rey@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518275535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000509827</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[university of california]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925219800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 University Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~73966</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-5162d4fc-7fff-47d5-dfb8-a60f10f4a4e5"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Spatial inequalities can have important implications for social cohesion, economic growth, and the design of policies targeted at reducing the level of inequality. Though understanding the nature of spatial inequality dynamics is vital, existing methods and models provide incomplete views of these spatial dynamics. While a central focus of inequality research has been on the evolution of the aggregate income distribution, much less attention has been directed at the spatial pattern of inequality and the temporal dynamics of spatial pattern. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project is focused on improving the understanding of spatial inequality dynamics through methodological advances in measurement and modeling. More specifically, this project (1) explores the statistical properties of existing approaches that have been applied to the study of regional income inequality and (2) develops spatially explicit global and local measures for studying the role of spatial context in the evolution of regional income distributions. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For the former (1), this project published papers on adopting Monte Carlo simulations to investigate properties of classical stochastic dominance statistics, Markov-based income mobility measures and rank-based exchange mobility measures, all of which assume samples to be independently and identically distributed (i.i.d), and found that their analytical properties fail to hold in a regional context where the samples could be spatially autocorrelated or spatially heterogeneous. In other words, the application of these classical statistics to regional income inequality dynamics should proceed with caution as the sampling distribution could be impaired by the presence of spatial effects. Therefore, new analytics that integrates space into empirical analysis are strongly desired. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For the latter (2), local indicators of mobility association (LIMA) which could reveal the hot and cold spots of regional income rank exchanges over time has been derived, their properties examined via Monte Carlo simulations and these indicators have been applied to the study of provincial income inequality dynamics of China 1978-2012; alternative approaches to simulating discrete Markov chains with spatial dependence and heterogeneity have been implemented and are forming the basis for examining new tests for these effects in empirical studies of regional inequality dynamics; new smoothed estimators for Markov and spatial Markov chains model which are shown to be superior to classical maximum likelihood estimators when the sample size is small have been proposed.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The newly proposed spatially explicit methods have been implemented in python and integrated into the widely used open source python library - Python Spatial Analysis Library (PySAL) </span><a href="http://pysal.org/"><span>http://pysal.org/</span></a><span> and more specifically its submodule </span><span>giddy</span><span> </span><a href="https://giddy.readthedocs.io/"><span>https://giddy.readthedocs.io/</span></a><span>. Since the beginning of the project in 2014, the PI has directed 7 releases of PySAL since the start of this project and held more than 10 workshops on space and space-time data analysis with PySAL at national and international conferences including NARSC, SciPy, AAG, FOSS4G, GIScience for the dissemination of these new spatial analytical methods.</span><span> To facilitate the usage of these sophisticated methods for users who might not be familiar with python programming, a highly interactive web-based visual analytics toolkit has been developed on top of PySAL - Space-Time Analysis of Regional Systems (STARS) </span><a href="http://sarasen.asuscomm.com/STARS/"><span>http://sarasen.asuscomm.com/STARS/</span></a><span> as shown in Figure 1 (attached).</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Sergio&nbsp;Rey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1801801/1801801_10326868_1539108125215_ScreenShot2018-10-09at11.00.12AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1801801/1801801_10326868_1539108125215_ScreenShot2018-10-09at11.00.12AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STARS (Web Prototype)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1801801/1801801_10326868_1539108125215_ScreenShot2018-10-09at11.00.12AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STARS (Web Prototype)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Web-based Space-Time Analysis of Regional Systems (STARS) is an open-source package designed for the dynamic exploratory analysis of data measured for areal units at multiple points in time.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Center for Geospatial Sciences, UCR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sergio&nbsp;Rey</div> <div class="imageTitle">STARS (Web Prototype)</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Spatial inequalities can have important implications for social cohesion, economic growth, and the design of policies targeted at reducing the level of inequality. Though understanding the nature of spatial inequality dynamics is vital, existing methods and models provide incomplete views of these spatial dynamics. While a central focus of inequality research has been on the evolution of the aggregate income distribution, much less attention has been directed at the spatial pattern of inequality and the temporal dynamics of spatial pattern.     This project is focused on improving the understanding of spatial inequality dynamics through methodological advances in measurement and modeling. More specifically, this project (1) explores the statistical properties of existing approaches that have been applied to the study of regional income inequality and (2) develops spatially explicit global and local measures for studying the role of spatial context in the evolution of regional income distributions.     For the former (1), this project published papers on adopting Monte Carlo simulations to investigate properties of classical stochastic dominance statistics, Markov-based income mobility measures and rank-based exchange mobility measures, all of which assume samples to be independently and identically distributed (i.i.d), and found that their analytical properties fail to hold in a regional context where the samples could be spatially autocorrelated or spatially heterogeneous. In other words, the application of these classical statistics to regional income inequality dynamics should proceed with caution as the sampling distribution could be impaired by the presence of spatial effects. Therefore, new analytics that integrates space into empirical analysis are strongly desired.     For the latter (2), local indicators of mobility association (LIMA) which could reveal the hot and cold spots of regional income rank exchanges over time has been derived, their properties examined via Monte Carlo simulations and these indicators have been applied to the study of provincial income inequality dynamics of China 1978-2012; alternative approaches to simulating discrete Markov chains with spatial dependence and heterogeneity have been implemented and are forming the basis for examining new tests for these effects in empirical studies of regional inequality dynamics; new smoothed estimators for Markov and spatial Markov chains model which are shown to be superior to classical maximum likelihood estimators when the sample size is small have been proposed.    The newly proposed spatially explicit methods have been implemented in python and integrated into the widely used open source python library - Python Spatial Analysis Library (PySAL) http://pysal.org/ and more specifically its submodule giddy https://giddy.readthedocs.io/. Since the beginning of the project in 2014, the PI has directed 7 releases of PySAL since the start of this project and held more than 10 workshops on space and space-time data analysis with PySAL at national and international conferences including NARSC, SciPy, AAG, FOSS4G, GIScience for the dissemination of these new spatial analytical methods. To facilitate the usage of these sophisticated methods for users who might not be familiar with python programming, a highly interactive web-based visual analytics toolkit has been developed on top of PySAL - Space-Time Analysis of Regional Systems (STARS) http://sarasen.asuscomm.com/STARS/ as shown in Figure 1 (attached).                Last Modified: 10/09/2018       Submitted by: Sergio Rey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
