<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Green, Biocompatible Enzymatic Disinfectants for Broad-spectrum Inhibition and Removal of Microbial Contamination in Packaged Produce</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199576.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199576</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on producing custom enzymes designed to break down polysaccharides which form the foundation of common microbial biofilms. The enzymes can be used in an aqueous solution that can be applied to food during cleaning and processing to remove biofilm-forming microbes. The use of a safe and green enzyme-based disinfectant is important because of the rising frequency of food-borne illness and associated outbreaks linked to microbial contamination from pathogens such as E. coli and Salmonella. In addition, these enzymes offer an opportunity to replace harsh chemical cleaning agents with biocompatible, safe and green alternatives.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will result in a family of cleaning products formulated for a wide range of uses in cleaning of produce and other packaged foods. The uniqueness of the enzyme-based cleaning products are (1) ability to engineer specificity and target a broad range of microbial biofilms, (2) ability to select enzymes that retain activity under actual cleaning conditions, (3) ability to discriminate between pathogen and non-pathogen microbial biofilms, (4) demonstrated methods for high-yield production and (5) providing a safe, biocompatible alternative to current chemical cleaning agents. Collectively these features provide a new, green and targeted alternative to current industry standard chemical disinfectants such as peracetic acid in this market space.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses key gaps in knowledge required to translate this technology to the marketplace. Chemical disinfectants and mechanical disruption often have limited efficacy against microbial biofilms, allowing potential pathogens to persist in processing environments despite cleaning and cause foodborne illness. Furthemore, biofilm chemical structure is often complex and heterogeneous due to the presence of multiple microbes present within a biofilm community. This technology addresses both of these gaps by engineering enzymes that can degrade chemically heterogeneous biofilms, and can act synergistically with other cleaning methods or alone to enhance removal of microbial pathogens present during food processing. In particular, the project utilizes some leading industry partners such as Highland Fresh Technologies who will assist in designing and simulating actual process conditions under which application testing can be performed to determine amount per use and method of application. Also, production costs during scale-up will be calculated to identify critical costs associated with the final product. Additionally, post-doctoral fellows and graduate students working on this project will receive technology translation expertise, working to answer critical questions necessary to identify production costs, business plan development as well as direct exposure to key industry partners to design and execute key testing of products.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1801612</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Berger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryan W Berger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bwb2k@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349242016</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000531484</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/06/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044833</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1001 North Emmet Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~199576</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this work was to pursue commercialization of enzymatic disinfectants to remove microbial contamination from packaged produce. Recent major outbreaks of E. coli linked to Romaine lettuce the past 3 years (2017-2019) have raised the visibility and importance of this topic in terms of food safety, as well as highlighted the many outstanding challenges that remain in addressing risks to food safety both pre- and post-harvest.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major outcomes of this project were the development, benchmarking and commercialization of enzymatic disinfectants to eliminate microbial pathogens that contribute to pre- and post-harvest food spoilage as well as pose a major risk to human health. Specifically, we have (1) identified and developed multiple enzymatic disinfectants in the laboratory, including efficacy testing against a wide range of bacterial (E. coli, Salmonella, Listeria) and fungal (Botrytis, Aspergillus) pathogens (2) benchmarked efficacy in partnership with major food packagers and processers using actual pilot-scale processes and (3) successfully launched a start-up company (Lytos Technologies) to bring these technologies to market. Our first product we will bring to market is a green, organic biopesticide which outperforms chemical pesticides in field trials, with additional products targeting bacterial pathogens currently in development. At Lytos, we seek to empower growers with effective, organic alternatives to crop protection while ensuring consumers can enjoy products the way they were meant to be enjoyed: safe, green and chemical free.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this work have led to job creation in the growing biotech industry in Charlottesville; Lytos currently employs multiple full-time scientists and technical staff, and is growing in terms of manufacturing and distribution. Wine is a major industry in Virginia, contributing over $1 Bil USD in revenue to the state annually; through direct engagement and partnerships with local wineries, we are supporting growers who seek green, organic alternatives to chemical pesticides. This grant has also provided valuable educational opportunities for students to learn customer discovery and business model development. In particularl Lytos is co-founded/led by a former student (Eckersley) that trained in the PIs (Berger) laboratory, as well as internship opportunities for undergraduates and graduate students to learn more about the start-up process and contribute to the growth and success of an early-stage biotech. The PI (Berger) has also integrated key concepts (manufacturing, customer discovery, business model development, product registration, scale-up, regulatory considerations, product life cycle) into the introduction to biotechnology course (CHE 2246) offered at UVA to educate students on how to pursue commercialization of biotechnologies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Bryan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Berger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this work was to pursue commercialization of enzymatic disinfectants to remove microbial contamination from packaged produce. Recent major outbreaks of E. coli linked to Romaine lettuce the past 3 years (2017-2019) have raised the visibility and importance of this topic in terms of food safety, as well as highlighted the many outstanding challenges that remain in addressing risks to food safety both pre- and post-harvest.     The major outcomes of this project were the development, benchmarking and commercialization of enzymatic disinfectants to eliminate microbial pathogens that contribute to pre- and post-harvest food spoilage as well as pose a major risk to human health. Specifically, we have (1) identified and developed multiple enzymatic disinfectants in the laboratory, including efficacy testing against a wide range of bacterial (E. coli, Salmonella, Listeria) and fungal (Botrytis, Aspergillus) pathogens (2) benchmarked efficacy in partnership with major food packagers and processers using actual pilot-scale processes and (3) successfully launched a start-up company (Lytos Technologies) to bring these technologies to market. Our first product we will bring to market is a green, organic biopesticide which outperforms chemical pesticides in field trials, with additional products targeting bacterial pathogens currently in development. At Lytos, we seek to empower growers with effective, organic alternatives to crop protection while ensuring consumers can enjoy products the way they were meant to be enjoyed: safe, green and chemical free.     The broader impacts of this work have led to job creation in the growing biotech industry in Charlottesville; Lytos currently employs multiple full-time scientists and technical staff, and is growing in terms of manufacturing and distribution. Wine is a major industry in Virginia, contributing over $1 Bil USD in revenue to the state annually; through direct engagement and partnerships with local wineries, we are supporting growers who seek green, organic alternatives to chemical pesticides. This grant has also provided valuable educational opportunities for students to learn customer discovery and business model development. In particularl Lytos is co-founded/led by a former student (Eckersley) that trained in the PIs (Berger) laboratory, as well as internship opportunities for undergraduates and graduate students to learn more about the start-up process and contribute to the growth and success of an early-stage biotech. The PI (Berger) has also integrated key concepts (manufacturing, customer discovery, business model development, product registration, scale-up, regulatory considerations, product life cycle) into the introduction to biotechnology course (CHE 2246) offered at UVA to educate students on how to pursue commercialization of biotechnologies.          Last Modified: 12/17/2019       Submitted by: Bryan W Berger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
