<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Eighth (8th) International Symposium on Environmental Hydraulics; Notre Dame, Indiana; June 4-7, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nanderso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924715</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for early career scientists to attend the International Symposium on Environmental Hydraulics hosted by the University of Notre Dame in the summer of 2018.  The conference will bring together a broad range of early-career, mid-career, and senior scientists in differing fields with the goal of stimulating cross-fertilization and establishing commonalities in work.  NSF funding will allow registration fees to be cut for graduate students, ensuring robust participation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 8th International Symposium on Environmental Hydraulics will be held on the campus of the University of Notre Dame on June 4-7th, 2018.  The goal of the workshop is to bring together a diverse group of scientists and engineers working in the area of environmental hydraulics, including relevant topics in environmental fluid dynamics, on a common platform to present recent findings, exchange ideas, foster collaborations and welcome junior researchers and students to the broader hydraulics community. Environmental Hydraulics encompasses a range of topics including pollutant reactions and transport in air and water, eco-hydraulics, sediment transport, fundamental fluid mechanics, river and coastal morphology, natural hazard prediction and mitigation, high performance computational applications, and many others.  The commonality in these topics is the application of fluid mechanics to the physical/chemical/ecological/built environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1802531</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew B Kennedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Andrew.B.Kennedy.117@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746316686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513703</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harindra</FirstName>
<LastName>Fernando</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harindra J Fernando</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Fernando.10@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746319346</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000558733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Overview<br />The 8th International Symposium on Environmental Hydraulics was held June 4-7, 2018 at the University of Notre Dame in Notre Dame, Indiana. The 230 attendees came from 21 countries around the world, and included 108 student registrations. Participants gave 210 oral presentations on a wide variety of topics including atmospheric, oceanic, urban, lacustrine, riverine, egological, and groundwater flows. Registration costs were kept low through support from NSF, the Army Research Office, and the University of Notre Dame.<br />Intellectual Merit<br />The Symposium brought together experts from around the world in different aspects of Environmental Hydraulics and Environmental Fluid Mechanics. Because of the wide range of topics and the manageable number of participants, there was considerable cross-fertilization through attendance in tracks that the participants might not necessarily visit in more narrowly-focused conferences.&nbsp;The number of oral presentations was 210, just slightly lower than the total number of attendees, with beginning graduate students and a few undergraduates attending but not presenting.&nbsp;<br />Broader Impacts<br />Thanks to generous support, the Symposium was able to charge extremely low registration fees, particularly for students. Early student registrations were only $50, which was much less than the cost per participant. This allowed many students to attend who otherwise would not have been able, and was the source of much positive feedback. The organizers were also able to provide participant support to many of the attendees in order to defray costs. Overall, the Symposium provided opportunities for a diverse group of participants to learn and advance the state of the art.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;B&nbsp;Kennedy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview The 8th International Symposium on Environmental Hydraulics was held June 4-7, 2018 at the University of Notre Dame in Notre Dame, Indiana. The 230 attendees came from 21 countries around the world, and included 108 student registrations. Participants gave 210 oral presentations on a wide variety of topics including atmospheric, oceanic, urban, lacustrine, riverine, egological, and groundwater flows. Registration costs were kept low through support from NSF, the Army Research Office, and the University of Notre Dame. Intellectual Merit The Symposium brought together experts from around the world in different aspects of Environmental Hydraulics and Environmental Fluid Mechanics. Because of the wide range of topics and the manageable number of participants, there was considerable cross-fertilization through attendance in tracks that the participants might not necessarily visit in more narrowly-focused conferences. The number of oral presentations was 210, just slightly lower than the total number of attendees, with beginning graduate students and a few undergraduates attending but not presenting.  Broader Impacts Thanks to generous support, the Symposium was able to charge extremely low registration fees, particularly for students. Early student registrations were only $50, which was much less than the cost per participant. This allowed many students to attend who otherwise would not have been able, and was the source of much positive feedback. The organizers were also able to provide participant support to many of the attendees in order to defray costs. Overall, the Symposium provided opportunities for a diverse group of participants to learn and advance the state of the art.       Last Modified: 01/01/2019       Submitted by: Andrew B Kennedy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
