<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Southwest Local Algebra Meeting 2018</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the participation in the Southwest Local Algebra Meeting 2018, to be held at the University of Arkansas in Fayetteville on February 24-25, 2018. This conference will encourage professional networking and interactions between students and faculty with interests in ring theory, broadly interpreted, from institutions in the Southwest region. The meeting will provide an effective environment for scientific interaction, thanks to inspiring talks from established experts, ample time dedicated to graduate students poster presentations and opportunities for participants to begin new collaborations and exploring new research directions. About 50 participants are expected, including students and both junior and senior faculty from throughout the Southwest and South. The participation of students from underrepresented minority groups, women, untenured faculty and faculty at non-PhD granting institutions is particularly encouraged. Six experts will deliver hour-long talks on topics within their areas of specialty; the lectures will be accessible to graduate students. The meeting will also feature three hour-long poster sessions in which the participating students will present and discuss their research with the participants. More information can be found at the conference webpage http://www.math.ttu.edu/~lchriste/slam2018.html.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The study of rings, in the broadest sense, is essential in many branches of mathematics, including commutative and non-commutative geometry, number theory, coding theory, group representations and cryptography. The speakers are specialists in differential graded algebras, intersection multiplicities, Rees algebras, Lie theory, representations of finite and algebraic groups, algebraic combinatorics, complexity theory, homological methods. This variety of interests among our speakers should provide directions for new algebraic interactions between all participants and expand their potential research horizons.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1803445</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>markj@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5015756333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000159705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Jorgensen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Jorgensen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>djorgens@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172725507</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387928</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lars</FirstName>
<LastName>Christensen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lars W Christensen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Lars.W.Christensen@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8067422580</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000405751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louiza</FirstName>
<LastName>Fouli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louiza Fouli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lfouli@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5756462201</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544138</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paolo</FirstName>
<LastName>Mantero</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paolo Mantero</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pmantero@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795753351</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000759441</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1125 W. Maple Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[316 Administration Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191429745</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055600001</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 2"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The 2018 Southwest Local Algebra Meeting took place at the University of Arkansas, in Fayetteville, AR on February 24-25, 2018. This was the ninth annual Southwest Local Algebra Meeting. The first eight meetings took place at the University of Texas-Arlington in 2010, New Mexico State University in 2011, Texas Tech University in 2012, the University of Arizona in 2013, Texas A&amp;M University in 2014, Oklahoma State University in 2015, Texas State University in 2016 and University of New Mexico in 2017. The purpose of the meeting was to facilitate interactions between young and senior mathematicians, with interests in ring theory, broadly interpreted, from institutions in the Southwest.</span></p> <p><span>Participants met at the University of Arkansas for talks, graduate student poster sessions, and mathematical discussions. The six speakers were Matthew Day (University of Arkansas), Jonathan Kujawa (University of Oklahoma), Joseph Landsberg (Texas A&amp;M University), Hema Srinivasan (University of Missouri), Peder Thompson (Texas Tech University), and Bernd Ulrich (Purdue University) who surveyed topics at the intersection of commutative algebra, combinatorics, algebraic geometry, representation theory, homological algebra and geometric group theory. Each speaker gave a talk that was accessible to the graduate students in the audience, often illustrating connections between basic material learned in graduate school with the latest research in the field.</span></p> <p><span>Ten graduate students from eight different institutions presented posters durring the three hours of poster sessions, explaining their research to other students and faculty. The posters were entitled "<em>Cohen-Macaulay property of Rees algebras of modules"&nbsp;</em>(Alessandra Costantini, Purdue University), "<em>A new classification of D8"</em>&nbsp;(Nathan Jones, Texas State University), "<em>c-Ulrich modules" </em>(Justin Lyle, University of Kansas), "<em>Ext modules and regularity of Pfaffian thickenings" </em>(Michael Perlman, University of Notre Dame), "<em>Projective normality<br /> and normal presentation on varieties with nef canonical bundle" </em>(Debaditya Raychaudhury, University of Kansas), "<em>Perfect hypergraphs"&nbsp;</em></span>(Jonathan O'Rourke, Tulane University), "<em>A canonical form for neural codes" </em>(Alexander Ruys de Perez, Texas A&amp;M University), "<em>Counterexamples for Cohen-Macaulayness of lattice ideals" </em>(Aleksandra Sobieska, Texas A&amp;M University), "<em>Edge ideals of weighted oriented graphs" </em>(Jonathan Toledo, CINESTAV), "<em>Noncommutative discriminants and poisson primes" </em>(Kurt Trample, Louisiana State University)</p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The total attendance was 51. Participants came from states inside and outside the region, including Arkansas, California, Indiana, Kansas, Louisiana,&nbsp;Missouri, New Mexico, Oklahoma, and Texas. The participants included students from underrepresented minority groups, women, and faculty at all career stages and from different types of institutions. Most of the NSF support was used from travel and lodging for students and faculty with limited access to travel funds.</span></p> <p><span>Intellectual merit: The study of rings, in the broadest sense, is at the intersection of many branches of mathematics including commutative and non- commutative geometry, group representations, number theory, coding theory and cryptography, and touches on even more, such as combinatorics, homotopy theory and statistics. Algebraists in the Southwest region pursue research on a variety of topics under the umbrella of pure and applied ring theory. Because of the extension of the Southwest region, professional interactions between experts and graduate students in the region are challenging. The meeting achieved the goal of bringing together students, post-doctoral researchers and faculty from a variety of institutions for inspired talks with ample time for scientific interaction and professional networking. Furthermore, at the meeting, several faculty members working on related research problems using different approaches began fruitful conversations about common research interests and possible combination of their methods, we expect these interaction to lead to research collaborations.</span></p> <p><span>Broader impacts: The Southwest region is home to a number of non-Ph.D. granting institutions. Faculty at these institutions have relative access to travel funds which limits their abilities of attend meetings where cutting-edge research is discussed. The relative proximity of the meeting venue and the availability of participant support offered them an opportunity to connect or reconnect with research groups in their geographical region. For several graduate students this was one of the very first scientific meetings attended, and provided them a smooth introduction to professional circles. The ample time dedicated to graduate students poster presentations helped the presenters - and the young graduate students - to interact with faculty members from other institutions in the same geographical region, in an almost 1 to 1 setting. For instance, an outcome of these interactions was that some students were invited to give their first talk at departmental seminars or other professional meetings. Moreover, several graduate students from non-Ph.D. granting institutions spoke with current faculty at doctoral institutions to discuss their Ph.D. possibilities in the region. We anticipate that these connections will help students in their academic pursuits.</span></p> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Paolo&nbsp;Mantero</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     The 2018 Southwest Local Algebra Meeting took place at the University of Arkansas, in Fayetteville, AR on February 24-25, 2018. This was the ninth annual Southwest Local Algebra Meeting. The first eight meetings took place at the University of Texas-Arlington in 2010, New Mexico State University in 2011, Texas Tech University in 2012, the University of Arizona in 2013, Texas A&amp;M University in 2014, Oklahoma State University in 2015, Texas State University in 2016 and University of New Mexico in 2017. The purpose of the meeting was to facilitate interactions between young and senior mathematicians, with interests in ring theory, broadly interpreted, from institutions in the Southwest.  Participants met at the University of Arkansas for talks, graduate student poster sessions, and mathematical discussions. The six speakers were Matthew Day (University of Arkansas), Jonathan Kujawa (University of Oklahoma), Joseph Landsberg (Texas A&amp;M University), Hema Srinivasan (University of Missouri), Peder Thompson (Texas Tech University), and Bernd Ulrich (Purdue University) who surveyed topics at the intersection of commutative algebra, combinatorics, algebraic geometry, representation theory, homological algebra and geometric group theory. Each speaker gave a talk that was accessible to the graduate students in the audience, often illustrating connections between basic material learned in graduate school with the latest research in the field.  Ten graduate students from eight different institutions presented posters durring the three hours of poster sessions, explaining their research to other students and faculty. The posters were entitled "Cohen-Macaulay property of Rees algebras of modules" (Alessandra Costantini, Purdue University), "A new classification of D8" (Nathan Jones, Texas State University), "c-Ulrich modules" (Justin Lyle, University of Kansas), "Ext modules and regularity of Pfaffian thickenings" (Michael Perlman, University of Notre Dame), "Projective normality  and normal presentation on varieties with nef canonical bundle" (Debaditya Raychaudhury, University of Kansas), "Perfect hypergraphs" (Jonathan O'Rourke, Tulane University), "A canonical form for neural codes" (Alexander Ruys de Perez, Texas A&amp;M University), "Counterexamples for Cohen-Macaulayness of lattice ideals" (Aleksandra Sobieska, Texas A&amp;M University), "Edge ideals of weighted oriented graphs" (Jonathan Toledo, CINESTAV), "Noncommutative discriminants and poisson primes" (Kurt Trample, Louisiana State University)     The total attendance was 51. Participants came from states inside and outside the region, including Arkansas, California, Indiana, Kansas, Louisiana, Missouri, New Mexico, Oklahoma, and Texas. The participants included students from underrepresented minority groups, women, and faculty at all career stages and from different types of institutions. Most of the NSF support was used from travel and lodging for students and faculty with limited access to travel funds.  Intellectual merit: The study of rings, in the broadest sense, is at the intersection of many branches of mathematics including commutative and non- commutative geometry, group representations, number theory, coding theory and cryptography, and touches on even more, such as combinatorics, homotopy theory and statistics. Algebraists in the Southwest region pursue research on a variety of topics under the umbrella of pure and applied ring theory. Because of the extension of the Southwest region, professional interactions between experts and graduate students in the region are challenging. The meeting achieved the goal of bringing together students, post-doctoral researchers and faculty from a variety of institutions for inspired talks with ample time for scientific interaction and professional networking. Furthermore, at the meeting, several faculty members working on related research problems using different approaches began fruitful conversations about common research interests and possible combination of their methods, we expect these interaction to lead to research collaborations.  Broader impacts: The Southwest region is home to a number of non-Ph.D. granting institutions. Faculty at these institutions have relative access to travel funds which limits their abilities of attend meetings where cutting-edge research is discussed. The relative proximity of the meeting venue and the availability of participant support offered them an opportunity to connect or reconnect with research groups in their geographical region. For several graduate students this was one of the very first scientific meetings attended, and provided them a smooth introduction to professional circles. The ample time dedicated to graduate students poster presentations helped the presenters - and the young graduate students - to interact with faculty members from other institutions in the same geographical region, in an almost 1 to 1 setting. For instance, an outcome of these interactions was that some students were invited to give their first talk at departmental seminars or other professional meetings. Moreover, several graduate students from non-Ph.D. granting institutions spoke with current faculty at doctoral institutions to discuss their Ph.D. possibilities in the region. We anticipate that these connections will help students in their academic pursuits.           Last Modified: 05/03/2019       Submitted by: Paolo Mantero]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
