<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Novel Spontaneous Four-wave Mixing Techniques for Photon-pair Generation and Hyperentanglement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>290000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>290000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Entanglement plays a crucial role in many quantum information protocols.  This project will help researchers understand and control the generation of entanglement, and hyperentanglement, using novel spontaneous four-wave mixing techniques.  The researchers' work on hyperentanglement generation in an optical fiber will also enable a new type of quantum information encoding, which is a step towards enhancing the information capacity carried on a single photon and thus allowing faster secure communication.  Their development of an efficient technique for probing hyperentanglement will enable other investigators to quickly and precisely engineer photon-pair sources  for quantum applications. This research on photon-pair generation via Raman interaction is expected to clarify the process in which the photons are created, towards the realization of a new type of photon-pair source that is better suited for quantum applications such as quantum computation, quantum communication and precision sensing.  To help inform the public about the quantum nature of light, the investigators will develop a display illustrating the concept of wave-particle duality for the University of Illinois physics building lobby and engineering open house. They will also present public outreach lectures and introduce course material that gives undergraduate students insight into the quantum properties of light. The research will also provide professional training to graduate and undergraduate students in quantum optics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Due to the ubiquitous use of photon-pair sources in quantum research and quantum applications, there have been major efforts to develop novel sources that produce photons in specific application-required quantum states. The investigators will develop a new type of photon-pair source based on the Raman interaction in crystalline materials, wherein the emission of photons is mediated by resonant excitation of a phonon, thus affecting the photon spectral properties in a way that differentiates this process from the traditional techniques of spontaneous parametric downconversion (SPDC) or spontaneous four-wave mixing (SFWM). Specifically, the researchers expect this process to naturally reduce spectral intra-correlations within the photon-pair, as opposed to SPDC and SFWM, for which special engineering techniques must be used that often result in unsatisfactory outcomes. They anticipate the research community will find further use for the newly developed principles in other Raman systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1806572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Lorenz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia O Lorenz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vlorenz@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173003306</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545435</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Offir</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Offir Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>offir@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173007106</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000760105</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 South Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~290000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
