<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Frontiers of Mathematical Biology: Modeling, Computation and Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38980.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38980</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The international conference "Frontiers of Mathematical Biology: Modeling, Analysis and Computation" will take place at the University of Central Florida in Orlando, Florida, on May 2-4, 2018. The meeting, supported by the NSF Mathematical Biology Program, will bring together researchers in mathematical and biological sciences to disseminate their most recent progress on using mathematics to study subjects ranging from cancer and neural sciences to ecology and chemical reactions. This project encourages the participation of graduate students and early career researchers. Participants will include leading international researchers as well as postdocs and graduate students. The schedule includes six plenary talks given by senior researchers, seventy invited and contributed talks (including twenty by early career participants), and mentoring activities for younger researchers. Special effort will be made to attract recent PhD recipients and graduate students to participate in conference activities, particularly underrepresented minorities and female scientists. The conference will help to establish new collaborations as well as to refresh existing collaborations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broad theme of the conference is the analysis of mathematical models using differential equations to study temporal and spatiotemporal dynamics in biology. Special topics include: cancer stem cells in primary breast cancer tissues and cell lines and the role of non-linear growth kinetics; pattern formation in coupled cell networks; spread of spatial disturbances in chemical reactions and Turing pattern formation leading to structure and coloration during development; and systematic approaches to large-scale coupled systems of differential equations which describe the chemical signaling and control upon which life systems are constructed. The conference will foster development of new ideas and innovative tools through collaboration between researchers from different mathematical disciplines and biologists. This conference will facilitate scientific interactions between a new generation of US mathematicians and leading senior researchers in mathematics and biology, enhanced by mentoring activities before the meeting. Plenary speakers will be encouraged to reach a broader audience, give non-technical surveys of current research in their field, and suggest new research directions. More information is available on the conference website:&lt;br/&gt;                       http://sciences.ucf.edu/math/mathbio&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1806830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuanwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Qi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuanwei Qi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yuanwei.qi@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078232810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Nevai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Nevai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anevai@math.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078821120</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhisheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Shuai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhisheng Shuai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Zhisheng.Shuai@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078235251</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000685935</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4000 CNTRL Florida BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~38980</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
