<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Degradation and Resilience of Seagrass Ecosystem Structure and Function following a Direct Impact by Hurricane Harvey</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199722.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199722</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel J. Thornhill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dthornhi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928143</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Disturbance has long been recognized as a major organizing force in marine communities with the potential to shape biodiversity. Hurricanes provide a natural experiment to understand how acute physical disturbances (storm surge and wind energy) may interact with longer-term changes in environmental conditions (salinity or turbidity) to alter the structure and function of ecological communities. As models indicate that hurricane intensity and precipitation will increase with a warming climate, understanding the response and recovery of coastal ecosystems is of critical societal importance. Harvey made landfall as a Category Four hurricane on the Texas coast on August 25, 2017, bringing extreme rainfall as the storm stalled over the middle Texas coast. The heavy rainfall and freshwater run-off created a low salinity lens that continues to persist two months later. Seagrass ecosystems may be particularly vulnerable because they grow on shallow, soft-sediment bottoms (and thus are easily dislodged or buried) and because seagrasses are sensitive to changes in salinity and turbidity. The societal implications of seagrass loss are well recognized: seagrasses provide highly valuable ecosystem services of large economic value for estuarine and nearshore dependent fisheries, serve as nursery habitats, and sequester gigatons of carbon on a global scale. Using measurements of the health and function of the seagrass and of the community for which it is habitat, the PIs are assessing the impact of the hurricane and of the persistent freshwater lens. Context is provided by looking at non-impacted sites and by six prior years of data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the overarching question: How do intense physical disturbances in conjunction with chronic chemophysical perturbations affect loss and recovery of seagrass community structure and function, including local production, trophic linkages, and metazoan community diversity? To understand the impacts of Hurricane Harvey on seagrass ecosystems across the middle Texas coast, the investigators are (1) documenting losses in physical habitat structure, (2) teasing apart independent and interactive effects of multiple stressors associated with storm events on biodiversity and ecosystem function, and (3) identifying factors that promote resilience following disturbance.  A state-wide seagrass monitoring program with six years of data from areas within Harvey's path and surrounding seagrass systems will provide invaluable context. The investigators are measuring seagrass structure, employing a Before-After-Control-Impact design at sites that experienced severe physical damage and appropriate reference sites. In situ loggers deployed after the storm track the evolution of the low salinity event together with seagrass physiological stress measurements (e.g. chlorophyll fluorescence, pigment loss, reduced growth). Changes in seagrass habitat function is assessed through measurements of faunal biodiversity within impacted and reference sites sampled via cores, benthic push nets, and seine nets. Tethering assays of seagrass blades and common invertebrate prey enables comparison trophic interactions across sites that vary in disturbance impact. These data are used to create models of ecosystem response to an extreme disturbance event and identify factors that best predict recovery of the physical structure of the habitat and of associated ecosystem functions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1807143</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Dunton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth H Dunton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ken.dunton@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3617496744</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000176703</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeager</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lauren Yeager</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lyeager@utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3617496776</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000638838</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UT Austin Marine Science Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Port Aransas</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>783735015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 Channelview Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>071Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Harvey 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1097</Code>
<Text>DIVERSITY: ROLE IN ECOSYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~199722</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-f60acef3-7fff-f1de-54a5-9647043e9752"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Hurricanes may have severe impacts on both human and natural coastal communities.&nbsp; This award provided us with the opportunity to measure the ways a major storm, Hurricane Harvey, reshaped coastal seagrass habitats in Texas.&nbsp; We documented severe, but localized, impacts of the hurricane on seagrass habitats in Corpus Christi and Aransas Bays. These impacts included patchy, but significant losses in seagrass cover in areas that experienced the strongest winds. Most of the negative impacts of the Hurricane seem to be driven by the physical damage caused by winds and storm surge, rather than the effects of rainfall and nutrient run-off in this area. Interestingly, we observed that seagrasses grew very fast at sites that experienced more freshwater run-off after the storm. This was likely caused by higher nutrient levels in the water for longer time periods at these sites. This may have helped seagrass recover more quickly after the hurricane in places where the roots were not damaged. In places where damage to the below ground tissues occurred (e.g. loss and uprooting of roots and rhizomes),&nbsp; we expect that seagrass recovery will take much longer.</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>At sites where seagrasses were damaged, we found different types of animal communities compared to less disturbed sites, although not a lower number or biodiversity of animals. The types of fauna living at the study sites varied greatly throughout the year. We believe impacts on fauna may have occurred at different scales (in space or time) than we surveyed, and caution that lack of long-term data on seagrass fauna make the true effects of the hurricane difficult to detect.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>In comparing impacts of the Hurricane Harvey on seagrasses to impacts in other coastal ecosystems, it appears that seagrasses were relatively resistant to the storm (did not show as large of changes from the pre-storm baseline) when compared to other variables. Seagrasses may be less resilient, however, as recovery times (months to years) for areas that were damaged is expected to be much longer than for other habitats or systems (e.g., freshwater streams).&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>This award had many positive impacts on students ranging from the K-12 to PhD level.&nbsp; Research for one PhD and one Master&rsquo;s students&rsquo; theses were funded in part by this award.&nbsp; Also, five undergraduate students were trained in research techniques in the lab and in the marine environment. The results of this project were also used to build a high-school level science lesson.&nbsp; This lesson taught about how seagrass health is tracked, how the hurricane impacted seagrasses in Texas, and valuable map reading skills. This lesson plan was delivered to 15 local teachers in a summer teacher workshop. </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Lauren&nbsp;Yeager</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Hurricanes may have severe impacts on both human and natural coastal communities.  This award provided us with the opportunity to measure the ways a major storm, Hurricane Harvey, reshaped coastal seagrass habitats in Texas.  We documented severe, but localized, impacts of the hurricane on seagrass habitats in Corpus Christi and Aransas Bays. These impacts included patchy, but significant losses in seagrass cover in areas that experienced the strongest winds. Most of the negative impacts of the Hurricane seem to be driven by the physical damage caused by winds and storm surge, rather than the effects of rainfall and nutrient run-off in this area. Interestingly, we observed that seagrasses grew very fast at sites that experienced more freshwater run-off after the storm. This was likely caused by higher nutrient levels in the water for longer time periods at these sites. This may have helped seagrass recover more quickly after the hurricane in places where the roots were not damaged. In places where damage to the below ground tissues occurred (e.g. loss and uprooting of roots and rhizomes),  we expect that seagrass recovery will take much longer.   At sites where seagrasses were damaged, we found different types of animal communities compared to less disturbed sites, although not a lower number or biodiversity of animals. The types of fauna living at the study sites varied greatly throughout the year. We believe impacts on fauna may have occurred at different scales (in space or time) than we surveyed, and caution that lack of long-term data on seagrass fauna make the true effects of the hurricane difficult to detect.    In comparing impacts of the Hurricane Harvey on seagrasses to impacts in other coastal ecosystems, it appears that seagrasses were relatively resistant to the storm (did not show as large of changes from the pre-storm baseline) when compared to other variables. Seagrasses may be less resilient, however, as recovery times (months to years) for areas that were damaged is expected to be much longer than for other habitats or systems (e.g., freshwater streams).    This award had many positive impacts on students ranging from the K-12 to PhD level.  Research for one PhD and one Master’s students’ theses were funded in part by this award.  Also, five undergraduate students were trained in research techniques in the lab and in the marine environment. The results of this project were also used to build a high-school level science lesson.  This lesson taught about how seagrass health is tracked, how the hurricane impacted seagrasses in Texas, and valuable map reading skills. This lesson plan was delivered to 15 local teachers in a summer teacher workshop.              Last Modified: 04/01/2020       Submitted by: Lauren Yeager]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
