<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:  Collaborative Research:  Sponge resilience in the face of multiple stressors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>63446.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>63446</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel J. Thornhill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dthornhi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928143</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the past several decades, coral reefs worldwide have undergone a transition from being dominated by the corals themselves to being dominated by sponges or algae. The causes of these changes are complex, but they include both natural stressors, such as diseases and hurricanes, and impacts from human activities, such as coastal development and climate change. There are over 600 species of sponges on Caribbean coral reefs, and they serve many important ecological roles, including nutrient cycling, providing food and shelter for other reef animals, and producing a tremendous diversity of chemical compounds that are important for controlling species interactions on the reef, and may serve as potential new drugs. In spite of their importance on coral reefs, there are many aspects of sponge biology that remain unknown, including how they respond to different types of stressors. Coral reefs in St. Thomas, in the U.S. Virgin Islands, are exposed to different levels of man-made stressors, depending upon their proximity to coastal development, and the sponge assemblages on these reefs also vary with levels of human impacts. In September 2017, St. Thomas was devastated by two Category 5 hurricanes in a row. Since, unlike corals, virtually nothing is known about what happens to sponge communities in the aftermath of hurricanes, the research team will use a combination of field ecology and population genetics approaches to determine how sponge communities respond and recover from these devastating storms and whether prior exposure to land-based stressors affects their recovery. Researchers at the Universities of Mississippi, Alabama and the Virgin Islands will participate in this RAPID project, and will provide training opportunities for students and postdoctoral researchers, especially from underrepresented groups. Information will be provided to resource managers in the Virgin Islands, along with outreach programs to community groups in St. Thomas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to assess the impacts of single (e.g., hurricanes) versus multiple (e.g., hurricanes and land-based sources of pollution) stressors on the resilience, recovery, and recruitment of sponge communities in St. Thomas, U.S.V.I.  Given the growing dominance of sponges on coral reefs worldwide, understanding the responses of sponges to natural and anthropogenic stressors is increasingly important. The investigators will leverage multiple years of data on sponge assemblages from several sites around the island of St. Thomas that varied in their levels of exposure to local land-based stressors prior to Hurricanes Irma and Maria, and evaluate changes to these diverse assemblages over time, beginning within 3 months of these devastating storms.  Using a combination of natural and experimentally cleared plots, the investigators will assess the progress of sponge succession and whether the presence of algae interferes with sponge recruitment and recovery. Subsamples of recruits and nearby conspecifics will be collected to evaluate population genetic diversity and potential sources of new individuals. The data resulting from this project will provide critical insights into sponge resilience in response to hurricanes at sites previously exposed to land-based stressors, the initiation of succession within sponge communities, potential predictors of successional trajectory, and genetic diversity within sponge populations following a storm event. This information will help identify factors that inhibit coral recovery and potential approaches to enhance resilience of coral reefs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1808233</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Olson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie B Olson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jolson@as.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053482633</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481112</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[152 Rose Admin. / Box 870104]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045632635</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>808245794</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354860005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>074Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Irma 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1097</Code>
<Text>DIVERSITY: ROLE IN ECOSYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8556</Code>
<Text>Coral Reefs</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~63446</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project assessed the impacts of back-to-back category 5 hurricanes Irma and Maria on the benthic communities inhabiting shallow coral reefs around St. Thomas, USVI. We compared pre-hurricane surveys of benthic communities on permanent transects at six sites with those conducted at 2, 6, 14, and 20 months post-hurricanes. At 2 months, there were no significant storm-related effects on coral and macroalgal cover, although sponge cover declined by 24.9%. Many individual upright sponges were lost but these losses were partially offset by an increase in the number of sponges encrusting on substrate and recruitment of new sponges (or regrowth of severely damaged individuals) was observed within 2 months of the hurricanes. Although sponge communities recovered to varying degrees at the sites over the subsequent two years, upright sponges only started to recover 14 months after the hurricanes. Coral cover declined following the hurricanes and showed mixed recovery over subsequent months, with some sites increasing in coral cover in late 2017 and early 2018 with other sites continuing to decline. The introduction of stony coral tissue loss disease at some sites beginning in late 2018 and continuing into 2019, which decimated coral communities, made analyses of coral cover at the later timepoints difficult. Macroalgal cover was extremely variable over time at the sites, but on the reefs where it increased may impact the recruitment, recovery or survival of small corals and sponges. The reefs did not return to pre-hurricane species assemblages during the duration of this project and it is not yet known when they will reach a stable community and what species will be present in that community. To help us understand how damaged reefs are repopulated, we sought to evaluate whether new sponge recruits were derived from larvae dispersed from spatially distant reefs or nearby individuals using population genetic analyses. Small samples of adult and newly recruited sponge individuals of three commonly occurring species were collected for this work and small changes in their genetic information are being examined to identify the sources for the new individuals. These studies are on-going.</p> <p>The scientists involved in this project provided training workshops on sponge ecology and identification for numerous graduate students and employees of various governmental agencies, non-profit organizations, and the University of the Virgin Island. Results from these studies have been provided to the USVI Department of Planning and Natural Resources annually and shared with other scientists at a variety of national and international scientific conferences and research seminars. Social media platforms such as Facebook and Twitter were used to distribute our findings with the broader USVI community along with annual presentations at Reef Fest. As the intensity of hurricanes continues to escalate, understanding their impacts, both on land and on nearshore environments, will be increasingly important to evaluate resilience.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2021<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;B&nbsp;Olson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735263599_BuckIslandbeforehurricanes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735263599_BuckIslandbeforehurricanes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Buck Island before"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735263599_BuckIslandbeforehurricanes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Buck Island before"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image shows the reef at Buck Island prior to being hit by two category 5 hurricanes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Deborah Gochfeld</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;B&nbsp;Olson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Buck Island before</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735198450_UVIstudentssurveyingquadrats--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735198450_UVIstudentssurveyingquadrats--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Squadrats"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735198450_UVIstudentssurveyingquadrats--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Squadrats"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A number of graduate students assisting this project with fieldwork. These 'Squadrats' were essential for completing the project objectives.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Deborah Gochfeld</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;B&nbsp;Olson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Squadrats</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735116479_Researchparticipants--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735116479_Researchparticipants--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Research Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735116479_Researchparticipants--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Research Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Each field expedition provided opportunities for training and the help was greatly appreciated.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Deborah Gochfeld</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;B&nbsp;Olson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Research Participants</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735383320_BuckIslandafterhurricanes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735383320_BuckIslandafterhurricanes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Buck Island after"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1808233/1808233_10525375_1612735383320_BuckIslandafterhurricanes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Buck Island after"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This was the condition of the reef at Buck Island after being hit by two category 5 hurricanes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Deborah Gochfeld</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;B&nbsp;Olson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Buck Island after</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project assessed the impacts of back-to-back category 5 hurricanes Irma and Maria on the benthic communities inhabiting shallow coral reefs around St. Thomas, USVI. We compared pre-hurricane surveys of benthic communities on permanent transects at six sites with those conducted at 2, 6, 14, and 20 months post-hurricanes. At 2 months, there were no significant storm-related effects on coral and macroalgal cover, although sponge cover declined by 24.9%. Many individual upright sponges were lost but these losses were partially offset by an increase in the number of sponges encrusting on substrate and recruitment of new sponges (or regrowth of severely damaged individuals) was observed within 2 months of the hurricanes. Although sponge communities recovered to varying degrees at the sites over the subsequent two years, upright sponges only started to recover 14 months after the hurricanes. Coral cover declined following the hurricanes and showed mixed recovery over subsequent months, with some sites increasing in coral cover in late 2017 and early 2018 with other sites continuing to decline. The introduction of stony coral tissue loss disease at some sites beginning in late 2018 and continuing into 2019, which decimated coral communities, made analyses of coral cover at the later timepoints difficult. Macroalgal cover was extremely variable over time at the sites, but on the reefs where it increased may impact the recruitment, recovery or survival of small corals and sponges. The reefs did not return to pre-hurricane species assemblages during the duration of this project and it is not yet known when they will reach a stable community and what species will be present in that community. To help us understand how damaged reefs are repopulated, we sought to evaluate whether new sponge recruits were derived from larvae dispersed from spatially distant reefs or nearby individuals using population genetic analyses. Small samples of adult and newly recruited sponge individuals of three commonly occurring species were collected for this work and small changes in their genetic information are being examined to identify the sources for the new individuals. These studies are on-going.  The scientists involved in this project provided training workshops on sponge ecology and identification for numerous graduate students and employees of various governmental agencies, non-profit organizations, and the University of the Virgin Island. Results from these studies have been provided to the USVI Department of Planning and Natural Resources annually and shared with other scientists at a variety of national and international scientific conferences and research seminars. Social media platforms such as Facebook and Twitter were used to distribute our findings with the broader USVI community along with annual presentations at Reef Fest. As the intensity of hurricanes continues to escalate, understanding their impacts, both on land and on nearshore environments, will be increasingly important to evaluate resilience.           Last Modified: 02/07/2021       Submitted by: Julie B Olson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
