<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Petascale Polar Topography Production</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The polar regions are changing faster than any other region of the Earth, with accelerating rates of coastal erosion, permafrost loss, glacier thinning, and other changes. Yet the poles are also among the least well observed regions, due to both their relative inaccessibility and coverage limitations in prior global surveys by remote sensing.  The project will use the high performance computing capabilities of Blue Waters to produce high-resolution, high-quality, time-dependent, and openly distributed digital elevation models (DEMs) for the Earth's poles. This data set is needed for measuring and understanding rapid, ongoing changes to the polar landscapes, as well as for impact mitigation and adaptation planning by polar communities. The produced DEMs will be distributed at no cost to the science community and public at large.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will use Blue Waters to produce 2m resolution DEMs with absolute accuracies of approximately 1m or better and relative accuracies of 0.2m over the Antarctic and Arctic regions.  The project incorporates the capability for repeat, high-resolution and high-precision topographic mapping in the form of sub-meter stereoscopic imagery from the DigitalGlobe constellation of five polar-orbiting sun-synchronous Earth imagers (WorldView 1-4 and GeoEye-1), as well as the archive of IKONOS and QuickBird.  These satellites images allow for precise stereo photogrammetric DEM construction from overlapping image pairs over a wide range of terrain types and light conditions, including the "flat white" interior of ice sheets and shadowed mountain faces. The time-dependent collection of DEMs will be invaluable to scientists studying change in the polar region.   Resources for obtaining and maintaining the imagery, tools for post-processing the results, software development time, and methods for distributing the DEMs have been secured by the project.  All DEMs will be publically distributed through the Polar Geospatial Center (PGC) website and a consortium including the National Geospatial Agency (NGA) and NASA, as well as Amazon web services and the geospatial software company ESRI.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1810976</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Morin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul J Morin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lpaul@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126260505</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>Howat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ian M Howat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ihowat@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8313452320</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Nguyen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles T Nguyen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ctn@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126244673</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Myoung-Jong</FirstName>
<LastName>Noh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Myoung-Jong Noh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>noh.56@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142923805</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000694404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
<LastName>Porter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claire Porter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>porte254@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126260505</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700319</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551081062</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1954 Buford Ave., Suite R280]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~14999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3f23ad72-7fff-8acf-45b9-e9ca4f28ae55">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Reference Elevation Model of Antarctica (REMA) and ArcticDEM provides the first, high resolution terrain map of nearly the entire continent. Since each REMA grid point has a timestamp, any past or future point observation of elevation provides a measurement of elevation change.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These datasets provide corrections for a wide range of remote sensing processing activities, such image orthorectification and interferometry, and provide constraints for geodynamic and ice flow modeling, mapping of grounding lines, and surface processes. They also provide a powerful new resource for field logistics planning.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The elevation is constructed from hundreds of thousands of individual stereoscopic Digital Elevation Models (DEM) extracted from pairs of submeter (0.32 to 0.5 m) resolution DigitalGlobe satellite imagery, including data from WorldView-1, WorldView-2, and WorldView-3, and a small number from GeoEye-1, acquired between 2009 and 2017, with most collected in 2015 and 2016, over the austral summer seasons (mostly December to March).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Each individual DEM was vertically registered to satellite altimetry measurements from</span><a href="https://earth.esa.int/web/eoportal/satellite-missions/c-missions/cryosat-2"><span> </span><span>Cryosat-2</span></a><span> and</span><a href="https://icesat.gsfc.nasa.gov/icesat/"><span> </span><span>ICESat</span></a><span>, resulting in absolute uncertainties of less than 1 m over most of its area, and relative uncertainties of decimeters.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These elevation datasets cover both poles from 60 degrees north to the pole and 60 Degrees south to the pole including all of Alaska, Greenland, Kamchatka and the sub-Antarctic Islands. This is 20% of the land surface of Earth and is about 40 million square kilometers.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;J&nbsp;Morin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The Reference Elevation Model of Antarctica (REMA) and ArcticDEM provides the first, high resolution terrain map of nearly the entire continent. Since each REMA grid point has a timestamp, any past or future point observation of elevation provides a measurement of elevation change. These datasets provide corrections for a wide range of remote sensing processing activities, such image orthorectification and interferometry, and provide constraints for geodynamic and ice flow modeling, mapping of grounding lines, and surface processes. They also provide a powerful new resource for field logistics planning. The elevation is constructed from hundreds of thousands of individual stereoscopic Digital Elevation Models (DEM) extracted from pairs of submeter (0.32 to 0.5 m) resolution DigitalGlobe satellite imagery, including data from WorldView-1, WorldView-2, and WorldView-3, and a small number from GeoEye-1, acquired between 2009 and 2017, with most collected in 2015 and 2016, over the austral summer seasons (mostly December to March). Each individual DEM was vertically registered to satellite altimetry measurements from Cryosat-2 and ICESat, resulting in absolute uncertainties of less than 1 m over most of its area, and relative uncertainties of decimeters. These elevation datasets cover both poles from 60 degrees north to the pole and 60 Degrees south to the pole including all of Alaska, Greenland, Kamchatka and the sub-Antarctic Islands. This is 20% of the land surface of Earth and is about 40 million square kilometers.             Last Modified: 09/24/2020       Submitted by: Paul J Morin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
