<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Large-Scale Behavior of Interacting Particle Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Interacting particle systems form a mathematical framework for systems with interacting components that arise in a variety of fields in science and engineering. Examples include, among many others, financial institutions interacting with each other via borrowing and lending, synchronization of neurons in the brain via electrical signals, and physical particles interacting through the (e.g. electromagnetic) potential they themselves generate. In many situations, the systems involved are large, e.g. the number of neurons in a given part of the human brain is on the order of a million. The goal of the project is to advance the quantitative understanding of such large interacting particle systems, relying on stochastic and deterministic partial differential equations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will tackle equations describing the large scale behavior of interacting particle systems and the blowups arising thereby. More specifically, blowups in Stefan problems for parabolic partial differential equations governing the limiting particle density in particle systems interacting through the hitting times will be investigated by a combination of probabilistic and analytic techniques. In particular, the exact timing of blowups will be determined, and the existence and uniqueness of a suitable solution will be established beyond the time of the first blowup. In addition, Gaussian approximations for the hitting times in interacting particle systems will be derived using the limiting stochastic partial differential equations. Finally, solutions to the latter arising from interacting particle systems will be shown to coincide with the entropy solutions arising naturally in the analysis of partial differential equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1811723</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mykhaylo</FirstName>
<LastName>Shkolnikov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mykhaylo Shkolnikov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mykhaylo@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681713</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Sherrerd Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project was centered around two types of objects: so-called free boundary problems, which arise in finance, material science, neuroscience and physics among others, and so-called conditional McKean-Vlasov equations, which are of great importance in stochastic modeling, e.g., in finance.</p> <p>The free boundary problems studied in this project describe the behavior of financial systems under distress, the shapes resulting from electrodeposition, the collective behavior of neurons in a part of the human brain, and the growth of crystals among other things. In this project, a new "probabilistic" concept of solution has been introducted for a variety of free boundary problems. This new solution concept is both more amenable to mathematical analysis and provides a more detailed description of the solution, capturing systemic crises in finance, dendritic growth in material science, synchronization of neurons in neuroscience, and rapid freezing of supercooled liquids in physics, to name a few examples.</p> <p>The conditional McKean-Vlasov equations studied in this project make an appearance whenever a stochastic model capturing the day-to-day snapshots of a system is enhanced to have more realistic dynamic features. A prominent example is given by the stochastic local volatility model in finance, wherein a local volatility model capturing the prices of the traded European options is enhanced to provide a more realistic model for the evolution of the prices for the underlying stocks. Despite its widespread use by major investment firms the mathematical understanding of the stochastic local volatility model is in its infancy. (We do not even know if the model is well-posed, i.e., if the widely used formulation of the model actually makes sense.) In this project, the PI and his collaborators have taken a significant step in establishing the well-posedness of the stochastic local volatility model. In addition, new results for general conditional McKean-Vlasov equations have been obtained, e.g., a connection between them and stochastic Fokker-Planck equations referred to as a superposition principle.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2021<br>      Modified by: Mykhaylo&nbsp;Shkolnikov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project was centered around two types of objects: so-called free boundary problems, which arise in finance, material science, neuroscience and physics among others, and so-called conditional McKean-Vlasov equations, which are of great importance in stochastic modeling, e.g., in finance.  The free boundary problems studied in this project describe the behavior of financial systems under distress, the shapes resulting from electrodeposition, the collective behavior of neurons in a part of the human brain, and the growth of crystals among other things. In this project, a new "probabilistic" concept of solution has been introducted for a variety of free boundary problems. This new solution concept is both more amenable to mathematical analysis and provides a more detailed description of the solution, capturing systemic crises in finance, dendritic growth in material science, synchronization of neurons in neuroscience, and rapid freezing of supercooled liquids in physics, to name a few examples.  The conditional McKean-Vlasov equations studied in this project make an appearance whenever a stochastic model capturing the day-to-day snapshots of a system is enhanced to have more realistic dynamic features. A prominent example is given by the stochastic local volatility model in finance, wherein a local volatility model capturing the prices of the traded European options is enhanced to provide a more realistic model for the evolution of the prices for the underlying stocks. Despite its widespread use by major investment firms the mathematical understanding of the stochastic local volatility model is in its infancy. (We do not even know if the model is well-posed, i.e., if the widely used formulation of the model actually makes sense.) In this project, the PI and his collaborators have taken a significant step in establishing the well-posedness of the stochastic local volatility model. In addition, new results for general conditional McKean-Vlasov equations have been obtained, e.g., a connection between them and stochastic Fokker-Planck equations referred to as a superposition principle.         Last Modified: 08/02/2021       Submitted by: Mykhaylo Shkolnikov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
