<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Seventeenth Exotic Beam Summer School</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support for students to participate in the Seventeenth Summer School on Exotic Beam (EBSS) Physics at the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, July 24 - 29, 2018.  The school is designed for graduate students, senior undergraduate students who are actively involved in research and postdocs (within 2 years of their degree). The school will consist of morning lectures and hands-on activities in the afternoons. Students will also have an opportunity to present their research. The aim of the summer school is to educate the next generation of scientists that will drive the research at the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB) when it comes online and other existing rare isotope facilities. In years to come, substantial progress in low-energy nuclear physics will have a broad impact on society, ranging from our understanding of the origin of the elements to the enhancement of national security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous sessions of these summer schools have had broad participation of under-represented minorities, with slightly more than 30% of the participants of the Fifteenth EBSS being female. The organizers of the Seventeenth EBSS will continue the use of accepted best practices to increase diversity and have an inclusive summer school&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1811777</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Wrede</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Wrede</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wrede@nscl.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5179087581</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700323</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1233</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The study of unstable nuclei that have unusual ratios of protons to neutrons is one of the frontiers of science. Investigating these rare isotopes is critical for understanding the synthesis of the chemical elements in stellar explosions as well as the fundamental nature of the nuclear forces that bind atomic nuclei together. Scientific progress in this field is driven by the development of exotic beams in present and next-generation rare-isotope beam facilities including the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB), which is currently under construction on the campus of Michigan State University.</p> <p>Nuclear physics is a broad discipline, influencing our knowledge of subjects as diverse as weakly-bound nuclei, many-body quantum theory, the super heavy elements, and the inner structure of neutron stars. Applications based on nuclear science and technologies include medical diagnostics and therapies, materials science, and national security. The Exotic Beam Summer School 2018 (EBSS2018), which was the seventeenth installment of EBSS series, was held June 24-30, 2018 at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory to educate and train the next generation of scientists that will drive research with rare-isotope beams.</p> <p>EBSS2018 was jointly organized by Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Argonne National Laboratory, the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory at Michigan State University, and ARUNA. Currently, ARUNA consists of nuclear accelerator laboratories at Florida State University, Ohio University, Texas A&amp;M University, University of Kentucky, University of Notre Dame, University of Washington, Hope College, Union College, University of Massachusetts-Lowell, and Triangle University Nuclear Laboratory. The school is funded by these institutions, as well as the US National Science Foundation and Department of Energy. 34 participants (mostly graduate students) attended EBSS2018 and received two types of training:</p> <p>1.&nbsp;During the morning, they received lectures given by experts in the field of exotic beam physics. These lectures focused on experimental and theoretical aspects of nuclear physics as well as interdisciplinary subjects such as nuclear astrophysics and societal applications.</p> <p>2. During the afternoon, students participated in a variety of hands-on activities, which included specific techniques and tools used in the field of exotic beam physics and their applications.</p> <p>A unique feature of this summer school series is the combination of lectures and hands-on activities, which allows students to apply the lecture materials immediately in practice.</p> <p>In addition, the participants in the school presented their own research to their peers and the lecturers and directors in a poster session and student seminars. The interaction between the students and the experts is an important component of the program.</p> <p>In 2008, the United States Department of Energy approved the design and construction of FRIB, which will provide beams of&nbsp;exotic nuclei with unmatched intensities, exceeding what is available today by orders of magnitude. Intense beams available at FRIB will facilitate a wide variety of studies in nuclear structure,&nbsp;astrophysics, fundamental symmetries and societal applications. There is a large community of scientists interested in working with rare isotope beams; for example, the FRIB User Organization currently has over 1,400 members and is growing. In order to maximize the scientific output of FRIB when it begins operating, there must be a&nbsp;workforce trained in both the physics of exotic beams and in the practical techniques of carrying out an experiment. This summer school series is designed to specifically address this need - to&nbsp;ensure that a new generation of scientists from a broad range of institutions and backgrounds is trained, motivated, and equipped to push the field forward to new and important breakthroughs.</p> <p>The school web site is https://sites.google.com/lbl.gov/ebss2018.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Christopher L H&nbsp;Wrede</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The study of unstable nuclei that have unusual ratios of protons to neutrons is one of the frontiers of science. Investigating these rare isotopes is critical for understanding the synthesis of the chemical elements in stellar explosions as well as the fundamental nature of the nuclear forces that bind atomic nuclei together. Scientific progress in this field is driven by the development of exotic beams in present and next-generation rare-isotope beam facilities including the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB), which is currently under construction on the campus of Michigan State University.  Nuclear physics is a broad discipline, influencing our knowledge of subjects as diverse as weakly-bound nuclei, many-body quantum theory, the super heavy elements, and the inner structure of neutron stars. Applications based on nuclear science and technologies include medical diagnostics and therapies, materials science, and national security. The Exotic Beam Summer School 2018 (EBSS2018), which was the seventeenth installment of EBSS series, was held June 24-30, 2018 at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory to educate and train the next generation of scientists that will drive research with rare-isotope beams.  EBSS2018 was jointly organized by Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Argonne National Laboratory, the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory at Michigan State University, and ARUNA. Currently, ARUNA consists of nuclear accelerator laboratories at Florida State University, Ohio University, Texas A&amp;M University, University of Kentucky, University of Notre Dame, University of Washington, Hope College, Union College, University of Massachusetts-Lowell, and Triangle University Nuclear Laboratory. The school is funded by these institutions, as well as the US National Science Foundation and Department of Energy. 34 participants (mostly graduate students) attended EBSS2018 and received two types of training:  1. During the morning, they received lectures given by experts in the field of exotic beam physics. These lectures focused on experimental and theoretical aspects of nuclear physics as well as interdisciplinary subjects such as nuclear astrophysics and societal applications.  2. During the afternoon, students participated in a variety of hands-on activities, which included specific techniques and tools used in the field of exotic beam physics and their applications.  A unique feature of this summer school series is the combination of lectures and hands-on activities, which allows students to apply the lecture materials immediately in practice.  In addition, the participants in the school presented their own research to their peers and the lecturers and directors in a poster session and student seminars. The interaction between the students and the experts is an important component of the program.  In 2008, the United States Department of Energy approved the design and construction of FRIB, which will provide beams of exotic nuclei with unmatched intensities, exceeding what is available today by orders of magnitude. Intense beams available at FRIB will facilitate a wide variety of studies in nuclear structure, astrophysics, fundamental symmetries and societal applications. There is a large community of scientists interested in working with rare isotope beams; for example, the FRIB User Organization currently has over 1,400 members and is growing. In order to maximize the scientific output of FRIB when it begins operating, there must be a workforce trained in both the physics of exotic beams and in the practical techniques of carrying out an experiment. This summer school series is designed to specifically address this need - to ensure that a new generation of scientists from a broad range of institutions and backgrounds is trained, motivated, and equipped to push the field forward to new and important breakthroughs.  The school web site is https://sites.google.com/lbl.gov/ebss2018.       Last Modified: 06/14/2019       Submitted by: Christopher L H Wrede]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
