<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Ant community responses to a 1000-year flooding event</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>103115</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Gruner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Extreme weather events, such as catastrophic fires or floods, are expected to become more likely under global environmental change. Scientists have a relatively poor understanding of how such extreme events influence the abundance of plants and animals, including species that affect human well-being such as pollinators or invasive pests.  Improving this scientific understanding requires that we learn from natural disasters. This project examines how extreme flooding associated with Hurricane Harvey in August 2017 affected the abundance and community composition of ants in the Big Thicket region of east Texas. This region hosts dozens of native ant species that provide valuable ecosystem services, such as decomposition and pest control, as well as noxious invasive species (fire ants and tawny crazy ants). The researchers will use "before" and "after" samples to test the hypothesis that Hurricane Harvey disrupted east Texas ant communities, favoring an increase in abundance and extent of invasive ants. The research will be conducted in coordination with the National Park Service, who hope to learn more about the ecological effects of Hurricane Harvey. The scientists will communicate their results to the public in the Texas communities of Houston and Beaumont, which were affected by fire ants and strongly affected by Harvey's floodwaters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ecological theory suggests that the relative abundance and even presence of species in communities may be driven as much by historical contingencies associated with rare events as by filtering from average environmental conditions. Forecasts for environmental change in the 21st century include an increase in frequency of extreme events, and ecologists are increasingly called upon to predict their consequences. The researchers will study how the 1,000-year flooding associated with Hurricane Harvey modified the taxonomic and functional trait composition of Big Thicket ant communities. The researchers will leverage three years of pre-event sampling to contrast the abundance, diversity, and species composition of ant communities before and after Harvey's floodwaters. Importantly, pre-event work demonstrated that exotic ant species had begun to penetrate the intact native communities. The researchers will evaluate whether Hurricane Harvey increased opportunities for invasion by exotic ants. They will conduct monthly pitfall sampling at 19 established sites to document changes in ant communities, and test whether changes in response to the hurricane are transient or represent new stable states. They will also assemble a functional trait database for these communities to test whether taxonomic shifts were driven by the filtering of species-specific traits that confer tolerance to flooding. Functional traits of interest include risk-spreading strategies such as polygyny (multiple queens per colony) and polydomy (multiple nesting locations). As the floodwaters have just now receded in the study area, there is an urgent window of opportunity to study the dynamics of ecological response and recovery.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1811225</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Solomon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott E Solomon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>solomons@si.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2026331003</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000421921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tom.miller@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133484218</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000534715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Bengston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah E Bengston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbengsto@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8605754534</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000689548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 Main St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>071Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Harvey 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7744</Code>
<Text>RAHSS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9261</Code>
<Text>RESRCH ASSIST-MINORITY H.S. ST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~103115</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Extreme weather events are increasing in frequency, likely as a signature of anthropogenic global climate change. Ecologists are seeking to understand how these events affect arthropod communities, which provide valuable ecosystem services (like pollination and decomposition) to humans. The 2017 Atlantic hurricane season was one of the most active on record, and included Hurricane Harvey. Harvey deposited 50-60 inches of rain in east Texas, causing the region's most severe flooding in recorded history. This project was designed to understand how the floodwaters of Hurricane Harvey affected the ant communities of Big Thicket National Preserve in east Texas. This region is a hotspot of native ant diversity and also includes two exotic invasive species, the red imported fire ant and the tawny crazy ant, a recent arrival. The scientific team analyzed ant community samples from 18 sites before and after the storm to assess how the abundance, diversity, and spatial distribution of native and invasive species were affected by Hurricane Harvey.</p> <p>The scientific team reported two major findings. First, and most surprisingly, the signal of disruption by Hurricane Harvey was very short-lived: ant abundance and diversity were depressed immediately after the flood but quickly recovered to pre-Harvey levels, with no apparent longer-term effects. This was true of native ant species, whose pre- and post-Harvey communities were very similar in richness and composition. It was also true of the invasive species, whose abundance and spatial extent throughout the Big Thicket region were similar pre- and post-Harvey. Second, the two invasive ants exerted very different ecological effects. The recent invader (crazy ants, Nylanderia fulva) appeared to strongly suppress native ants through rapid domination of food resources, while fire ants (Solenopsis invicta) did not appear to negatively affect native ant communities. Collectively, the results show remarkable resilience of ground-nesting ant communities to catastrophic flooding. Hurricane Harvey did not appear to promote invasion by exotic ant species, but at least one of these species does threaten native communities and should be a target of management efforts. The results raise new questions about why some communities (like east Texas ants) can easily "ride out" extreme weather events while others are highly sensitive to these perturbations.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to its scientific outputs, the project also provided training opportunities for high school, undergraduate, and graduate students. The scientific team developed a citizen science project to engage high school students in the Big Thicket region in documenting the spread of invasive ants.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Extreme weather events are increasing in frequency, likely as a signature of anthropogenic global climate change. Ecologists are seeking to understand how these events affect arthropod communities, which provide valuable ecosystem services (like pollination and decomposition) to humans. The 2017 Atlantic hurricane season was one of the most active on record, and included Hurricane Harvey. Harvey deposited 50-60 inches of rain in east Texas, causing the region's most severe flooding in recorded history. This project was designed to understand how the floodwaters of Hurricane Harvey affected the ant communities of Big Thicket National Preserve in east Texas. This region is a hotspot of native ant diversity and also includes two exotic invasive species, the red imported fire ant and the tawny crazy ant, a recent arrival. The scientific team analyzed ant community samples from 18 sites before and after the storm to assess how the abundance, diversity, and spatial distribution of native and invasive species were affected by Hurricane Harvey.  The scientific team reported two major findings. First, and most surprisingly, the signal of disruption by Hurricane Harvey was very short-lived: ant abundance and diversity were depressed immediately after the flood but quickly recovered to pre-Harvey levels, with no apparent longer-term effects. This was true of native ant species, whose pre- and post-Harvey communities were very similar in richness and composition. It was also true of the invasive species, whose abundance and spatial extent throughout the Big Thicket region were similar pre- and post-Harvey. Second, the two invasive ants exerted very different ecological effects. The recent invader (crazy ants, Nylanderia fulva) appeared to strongly suppress native ants through rapid domination of food resources, while fire ants (Solenopsis invicta) did not appear to negatively affect native ant communities. Collectively, the results show remarkable resilience of ground-nesting ant communities to catastrophic flooding. Hurricane Harvey did not appear to promote invasion by exotic ant species, but at least one of these species does threaten native communities and should be a target of management efforts. The results raise new questions about why some communities (like east Texas ants) can easily "ride out" extreme weather events while others are highly sensitive to these perturbations.   In addition to its scientific outputs, the project also provided training opportunities for high school, undergraduate, and graduate students. The scientific team developed a citizen science project to engage high school students in the Big Thicket region in documenting the spread of invasive ants.       Last Modified: 05/05/2020       Submitted by: Thomas Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
