<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for Student Travel for the Spring 2018 Technical Meeting of the Eastern State Section of the Combustion Institute</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Song-Charng Kong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is to partially support the travel expenses of graduate and undergraduate students in attending the 2018 Spring Technical Meeting of the Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute. This conference, to be held at the Penn State University, is a gathering of combustion researchers in academia, industry, and government from the East Coast region of the United States. The technical program of the conference consists of a series of plenary lectures, contributed oral presentations, and information social gatherings. Experiences in attending technical conferences are extremely beneficial to students. These experiences will not only help with the students' professional development, but also stimulate their critical thinking in formulating future research directions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because of its effect on energy conversion and environmental quality, the understanding of combustion processes and practical combustion systems is of paramount importance to society. Exchange of information at conferences increases the rate at which research breakthroughs can be made to make combustion more efficient and cleaner with fuel-flexibility. A particular focus of this conference is on graduate and undergraduate students by providing an opportunity for these students to present and get feedback on their research. This award will be used to offset the travel expenses of non-local students in an effort to increase student participation at the meeting, particularly students from underrepresented institutions that may not have the financial means to fully support student travel to conferences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1812790</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Connor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacqueline A O'Connor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jxo22@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148631502</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000664463</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Xuan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuan Xuan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yux19@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651372</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000682700</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Pennsylvania State University]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168047000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em>Overview:</em></span> The Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute 2018 Spring Technical Meeting was held on the campus of the Pennsylvania State University in State College, Pennsylvania during the dates March 4 to 7, 2018. The meeting consisted of four invited lectures, a workshop on technical writing, a workshop on mentoring for promoting diversity and inclusion, 135 contributed presentations, and a conference banquet. Conference attendance included 179 delegates, of which 109 were students.&nbsp; The funds from the National Science Foundation were used to support non-local graduate student (i.e., not Penn State students) travel to the conference.&nbsp; To receive travel support, graduate students were required to be the lead author on a contributed presentation, be enrolled at an institution within the geographic area of the Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute, and be accompanied by an advisor or senior co-author on their work.&nbsp; Forty-four eligible students from 19 universities were provided awards of no greater than $348.83 per person.</p> <p><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></em>: The technical sessions included recent research on topics across a broad range of areas related to combustion science: reaction kinetics, laminar flames, turbulent flames, sprays and droplets, coal, biomass, and new devices, heterogeneous combustion, soot, fire, IC and GT engines. In addition, invited lectures were delivered on the topics of reaction kinetics (Prof. William H. Green, Massachusetts Institute of Technology), hypersonic propulsion (Prof. Harsha K. Chelliah, University of Virginia), firescapes in the mid-Atlantic (Prof. Erica Smithwick, Pennsylvania State University), and the role of ozone in combustion (Prof. Wenting Sun, Georgia Institute of Technology).</p> <p><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></em>: The travel support for the graduate students enabled many of them to attend the conference to present their research findings and exchange other researchers. In addition, a major thrust of the conference, since it is so heavily attended by students, focuses on professional development. At this conference, multiple workshops were held on the use of open-source software, technical writing, and diversity. Dr. Bryan Weber, visiting Assistant Professor at the University of Connecticut, led the workshop on the open-source software (Cantera). Dr. Catherine Berdanier, Assistant Teaching Professor at the Pennsylvania State University, led the workshop on writing technical reviews. Dr. Jacqueline O&rsquo;Connor, Assistant Professor at the Pennsylvania State University, facilitated the workshop on diversity and inclusion with the goal of developing a mentor network within the Combustion Institute. In addition, an informal, early-career faculty mixer event was held for young faculty and post-doctoral scholars.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Yuan&nbsp;Xuan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview: The Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute 2018 Spring Technical Meeting was held on the campus of the Pennsylvania State University in State College, Pennsylvania during the dates March 4 to 7, 2018. The meeting consisted of four invited lectures, a workshop on technical writing, a workshop on mentoring for promoting diversity and inclusion, 135 contributed presentations, and a conference banquet. Conference attendance included 179 delegates, of which 109 were students.  The funds from the National Science Foundation were used to support non-local graduate student (i.e., not Penn State students) travel to the conference.  To receive travel support, graduate students were required to be the lead author on a contributed presentation, be enrolled at an institution within the geographic area of the Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute, and be accompanied by an advisor or senior co-author on their work.  Forty-four eligible students from 19 universities were provided awards of no greater than $348.83 per person.  Intellectual Merit: The technical sessions included recent research on topics across a broad range of areas related to combustion science: reaction kinetics, laminar flames, turbulent flames, sprays and droplets, coal, biomass, and new devices, heterogeneous combustion, soot, fire, IC and GT engines. In addition, invited lectures were delivered on the topics of reaction kinetics (Prof. William H. Green, Massachusetts Institute of Technology), hypersonic propulsion (Prof. Harsha K. Chelliah, University of Virginia), firescapes in the mid-Atlantic (Prof. Erica Smithwick, Pennsylvania State University), and the role of ozone in combustion (Prof. Wenting Sun, Georgia Institute of Technology).  Broader Impacts: The travel support for the graduate students enabled many of them to attend the conference to present their research findings and exchange other researchers. In addition, a major thrust of the conference, since it is so heavily attended by students, focuses on professional development. At this conference, multiple workshops were held on the use of open-source software, technical writing, and diversity. Dr. Bryan Weber, visiting Assistant Professor at the University of Connecticut, led the workshop on the open-source software (Cantera). Dr. Catherine Berdanier, Assistant Teaching Professor at the Pennsylvania State University, led the workshop on writing technical reviews. Dr. Jacqueline O?Connor, Assistant Professor at the Pennsylvania State University, facilitated the workshop on diversity and inclusion with the goal of developing a mentor network within the Combustion Institute. In addition, an informal, early-career faculty mixer event was held for young faculty and post-doctoral scholars.          Last Modified: 06/07/2018       Submitted by: Yuan Xuan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
