<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Regularized Poisson Boltzmann Model for Fast Computation of the Ensemble Average Polar Solvation Energy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>230000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>230000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative research project will develop mathematical models and simulation tools for studying the interactions between large biological molecules, for example proteins, and surrounding water molecules modeling an aqueous environment. The energy computation for characterizing such interactions is complex because the structures of biomolecules are not completely fixed or rigid, and the surrounding water molecules are also in constant motion. Thus, to deliver quantities that are comparable with experimentally-measurable energies, one must account for these conformational changes in the corresponding mathematical description.  A new theoretical model will be formulated in this project by combining appropriate biophysical considerations with mathematical advances, allowing simulations to mimic the effect of conformational changes in both macromolecule and water atoms. The proposed mathematical development will benefit researchers in molecular biosciences and biophysics. Moreover, the proposed models and algorithms will be implemented in DelPhi, which is distributed free of charge to academic users, to ensure extensive usage by practitioners from mathematics, chemistry, physics, and biology. In addition, this project will provide interdisciplinary research and training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students in biological modeling, computation and mathematical analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Experimentally-observable solvation energies are ensemble averaged. However, direct Poisson-Boltzmann (PB) calculations of such energies require the generation of a representative ensemble of structures in terms of thousands of snapshots, which is computationally very expensive. Tremendous savings in computational time can be achieved if one can calculate the ensemble average solvation energy by employing a single structure by mimicking the effect of conformation changes of macromolecules via heterogeneous dielectric distributions.  In this project, a novel super-Gaussian PB model will be formulated embodying three key innovations: (1) incorporation of environment-dependent atomic characteristics of macromolecules within the continuum electrostatic partial differential equation (PDE); (2) development of a novel, regularized formulation to treat singular charges, with new elliptic PDEs developed through rigorous mathematical analysis: partial charges and water molecules (inside cavities, bonded to the protein, and in bulk solvent) will no longer be modeled as homogeneous spatial regions as in the current Gaussian model, but will reflect the flexibility of the entire solute-solvent system; and (3) elimination of the need to determine a sharp molecular surface, for macromolecules in both vacuum and water environments.  Model benchmarking and biological applications tests will be carried out for validation, and the resulting tool will be incorporated into the widely-used DelPhi program package for computing ensemble-average solvation energies. This project is supported jointly by the Division of Mathematical Sciences Mathematical Biology Program, the Division of Chemistry Chemical Theory, Models and Computational Methods Program, and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1812930</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shan</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shan Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>szhao@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053485303</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000326967</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[152 Rose Admin. / Box 870104]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045632635</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>808245794</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama Tuscaloosa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354780005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 University Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6881</Code>
<Text>Chem Thry, Mdls &amp; Cmptnl Mthds</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~230000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
