<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Catalytic Hydrodeoxygenation of Sugar Acids to Dicarboxylic Acids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Exploratory research will be conducted to assess the feasibility of potentially transformative catalyst technology for manufacturing dicarboxylic acids from renewable sources of carbon such as lignocellulosic biomass.  Current industrial processes for these acids - which are used widely in the production of polymers, pharmaceuticals, solvents, textiles, and plastics - rely on petrochemical feedstocks derived from fossil sources, and utilize relatively harsh conditions and energy-intensive separations. Biomass sources potentially offer a more direct synthesis route while contributing to energy sustainability.  The study will address challenges associated with specific chemical reactions at oxygen-containing groups in the carbon structure, while also exploring catalyst formulations that decrease the need for expensive precious metal catalyst components.&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;Recently, interest has surged in the production of dicarboxylic acids from renewable sources, mainly via fermentation of glucose or through further processing of waste byproducts from natural bio-processing such as tartaric acid from wine-making. Specifically, the study will target two model tartaric acid reactions: deoxydehydration to maleic acid and hydrodeoxygenation to succinic acid, both carried out in commonly available solvents. The study will address two overarching objectives, 1) the development of a heterogeneous catalyst comprised of rhenium oxide supported on gallium-promoted cerium dioxide, and 2) a study of the catalytic performance of the rhenium oxide catalysts, prepared in various ways, on the deoxydehydration and hydrodeoxygenation of vicinal diols in tartaric acid.  A key aspect of the study is the extent to which supporting the rhenium oxide on the gallium-promoted cerium dioxide can enhance the stability of the catalyst while eliminating the need for common precious metal components such as palladium or iridium, thus paving the way for more durable and lower cost catalysts.  Successful demonstration of the proposed catalyst formulation depends on the extent to which the gallium-promoted cerium oxide support can both stabilize isolated monomeric rhenium oxide species (of varying oxidation state) and achieve the facile dissociation of hydrogen gas, as required for the sequential hydrogenation reactions and for regeneration of the active rhenium site.  Both of those functions are typically achieved through the incorporation of palladium in the catalyst synthesis.  Data suggesting the possibility of eliminating the expensive noble metal component, while stabilizing the active rhenium species, would open a path to transformative catalyst technologies for producing dicarboxylic acids from biorenewable carbon feedstocks.  The study also includes an education plan aimed at increasing the involvement of undergraduate Hispanic women in research, and enhancing undergraduate curricula at the PI's institution in key areas related to nanotechnology, engineering materials, and renewable energy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1817297</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yomaira</FirstName>
<LastName>Pagan-Torres</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yomaira J Pagan-Torres</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yomairaj.pagan@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7878312065</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez</Name>
<CityName>Mayaguez</CityName>
<ZipCode>006809000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7878312065</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Call Box 9000</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Road 108 Km 1.0]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175303262</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>090051616</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>006819000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The central research goal of this project is to develop heterogeneous catalysts for the selective removal of vicinal hydroxyl groups from biomass-derived oxygenates to produce saturated linear aliphatic dicarboxylic acids. The model reaction studied was the hydrodeoxygenation (HDO) of tartaric acid to succinic acid. In this project, the approach was to combine materials synthesis, spectroscopic characterization, and reaction kinetics to determine structure-activity relationships for HDO catalysts containing hydrogen dissociating metals (Pd, Pt, and Rh) and metal redox centers (MoO<sub>x</sub>, ReO<sub>x</sub>, and WO<sub>x</sub>). In the HDO of tartaric acid to succinic acid, the Pd-containing catalyst combined with MoO<sub>x</sub> resulted in the highest succinic acid formation rate and selectivity. Results obtained from spectroscopic characterization studies indicate the main role of Pd is to activate molecular hydrogen, which assists in the formation of reduced Mo(V) centers. These reduced Mo(V) centers coordinate with the internal hydroxyl groups of tartaric acid, leading to C-O bond cleavage and the formation of malic acid as a reaction intermediate. The hydroxylated metal redox center is then reduced in the presence of hydrogen, thus regenerating an active Mo(V)<sup> </sup>site that facilitates the subsequent C-O bond cleavage of malic acid to succinic acid. The catalytic cycle proposed for tartaric acid HDO over supported MoO<sub>x</sub>-Pd is based on the cleavage of C-O bonds by redox metal centers containing oxygen vacancies.</p> <p>The development of the supported MoO<sub>x</sub>-Pd catalyst through this research project has opened opportunities for the selective processing of molecules derived from a renewable source of carbon, such as biomass, to produce platform chemicals typically obtained from petroleum-derived feedstocks.&nbsp;A postdoctoral researcher and four Hispanic undergraduate students have been mentored and educated through this research project. The findings obtained in this project have been disseminated in eight technical presentations and a peer-reviewed publication.&nbsp; These research results have also been incorporated into the core Chemical Engineering Kinetics and Catalysis course at the University of Puerto Rico-Mayaguez.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/20/2021<br>      Modified by: Yomaira&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pagan-Torres</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The central research goal of this project is to develop heterogeneous catalysts for the selective removal of vicinal hydroxyl groups from biomass-derived oxygenates to produce saturated linear aliphatic dicarboxylic acids. The model reaction studied was the hydrodeoxygenation (HDO) of tartaric acid to succinic acid. In this project, the approach was to combine materials synthesis, spectroscopic characterization, and reaction kinetics to determine structure-activity relationships for HDO catalysts containing hydrogen dissociating metals (Pd, Pt, and Rh) and metal redox centers (MoOx, ReOx, and WOx). In the HDO of tartaric acid to succinic acid, the Pd-containing catalyst combined with MoOx resulted in the highest succinic acid formation rate and selectivity. Results obtained from spectroscopic characterization studies indicate the main role of Pd is to activate molecular hydrogen, which assists in the formation of reduced Mo(V) centers. These reduced Mo(V) centers coordinate with the internal hydroxyl groups of tartaric acid, leading to C-O bond cleavage and the formation of malic acid as a reaction intermediate. The hydroxylated metal redox center is then reduced in the presence of hydrogen, thus regenerating an active Mo(V) site that facilitates the subsequent C-O bond cleavage of malic acid to succinic acid. The catalytic cycle proposed for tartaric acid HDO over supported MoOx-Pd is based on the cleavage of C-O bonds by redox metal centers containing oxygen vacancies.  The development of the supported MoOx-Pd catalyst through this research project has opened opportunities for the selective processing of molecules derived from a renewable source of carbon, such as biomass, to produce platform chemicals typically obtained from petroleum-derived feedstocks. A postdoctoral researcher and four Hispanic undergraduate students have been mentored and educated through this research project. The findings obtained in this project have been disseminated in eight technical presentations and a peer-reviewed publication.  These research results have also been incorporated into the core Chemical Engineering Kinetics and Catalysis course at the University of Puerto Rico-Mayaguez.          Last Modified: 05/20/2021       Submitted by: Yomaira J Pagan-Torres]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
