<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Developing a Minor in Data Science at Johnson C. Smith University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149466.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149466</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities - Undergraduate program provides support to design, implement, study and assess efforts to increase the numbers of students and the quality of their preparation by strengthening science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education and research. This project at Johnson C. Smith University provides a strategic approach to enhance the computer science curriculum in the area of data science to increase student recruitment, retention and success.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project seeks to develop curricula and co-curricular activities for an undergraduate minor in data science. It is envisioned that these approaches will improve the retention and graduation rates of STEM majors at the university. The curriculum will be developed with collaborative input from an advisory committee comprised of industry and academic representatives. Five new courses will be developed and one existing course will be enhanced. Special consideration will be made to support the inclusion of interested students with little or no prior computing experience. The project is guided by formative and summative evaluation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1818681</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Felesia</FirstName>
<LastName>Stukes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Felesia Stukes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fstukes@jcsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7043781133</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000756489</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johnson C. Smith University</Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<ZipCode>282165302</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7043781006</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 Beatties Ford Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071057806</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNSON C. SMITH UNIVERSITY, INCORPORATED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071057806</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johnson C. Smith University]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282165302</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Beatties Ford Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~149466</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The "Developing a Minor in Data Science at Johnson C. Smith University" project is a one-year initiative to develop curricula and co-curricular activities to lay the groundwork for an undergraduate minor in Data Science. Data Science utilizes computing to create or extract insights from data in various forms to derive social and economic value. With the rapid growth of data sets in various industries such as healthcare, biotechnology, and business there is unlimited career potential for undergraduates with this high-demand expertise. The project objectives include 1) Develop curricula for an undergraduate minor in Data Science; 2) Increase interest and participation in undergraduate and graduate level computing degrees; and 3) Enhance faculty knowledge, teaching, and research in Data Science.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>The intellectual merit </strong>provides a Data Science Minor curriculum and implementation framework for other academic institutions seeking to address skills gaps to meet growing industry demands. The outcomes include the enhancement of two existing analytics courses and established groundwork for four new courses. Given the broad applicability of data science, this project successfully launched an interdisciplinary undergraduate research program which targets all majors. Additionally, the project increased institutional capacity through faculty and educator professional development. Overall, this effort resulted in new data science education for 30 undergraduate students, and provided professional development to ten higher education faculty and 15 high school teachers. These outcomes enabled faculty, teachers, and students to solve data-driven problems using methods they would not have otherwise had the capacity or expertise to apply. This project led to the successful development of interdisciplinary, sustainable pathways to computing.</p> <p><strong>The broader impacts</strong> of this project increased interest, preparation, and enrollment in computing courses among groups traditionally underrepresented. Activities were intentionally designed to emphasize a relationship between data, computing, society, and culture using research-based pedagogical methods to help increase women's participation across various majors. Other impacts have involved student and faculty conference presentations as well as dissemination to industry, K-12 and science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) professional organizations.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Felesia&nbsp;Stukes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The "Developing a Minor in Data Science at Johnson C. Smith University" project is a one-year initiative to develop curricula and co-curricular activities to lay the groundwork for an undergraduate minor in Data Science. Data Science utilizes computing to create or extract insights from data in various forms to derive social and economic value. With the rapid growth of data sets in various industries such as healthcare, biotechnology, and business there is unlimited career potential for undergraduates with this high-demand expertise. The project objectives include 1) Develop curricula for an undergraduate minor in Data Science; 2) Increase interest and participation in undergraduate and graduate level computing degrees; and 3) Enhance faculty knowledge, teaching, and research in Data Science.   The intellectual merit provides a Data Science Minor curriculum and implementation framework for other academic institutions seeking to address skills gaps to meet growing industry demands. The outcomes include the enhancement of two existing analytics courses and established groundwork for four new courses. Given the broad applicability of data science, this project successfully launched an interdisciplinary undergraduate research program which targets all majors. Additionally, the project increased institutional capacity through faculty and educator professional development. Overall, this effort resulted in new data science education for 30 undergraduate students, and provided professional development to ten higher education faculty and 15 high school teachers. These outcomes enabled faculty, teachers, and students to solve data-driven problems using methods they would not have otherwise had the capacity or expertise to apply. This project led to the successful development of interdisciplinary, sustainable pathways to computing.  The broader impacts of this project increased interest, preparation, and enrollment in computing courses among groups traditionally underrepresented. Activities were intentionally designed to emphasize a relationship between data, computing, society, and culture using research-based pedagogical methods to help increase women's participation across various majors. Other impacts have involved student and faculty conference presentations as well as dissemination to industry, K-12 and science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) professional organizations.        Last Modified: 08/09/2020       Submitted by: Felesia Stukes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
