<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UNS:  Developing Cross-Assembly Phage As A Marker of Human Fecal Pollution in the Environment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>274676.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>274676</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1510925&lt;br/&gt;Bibby&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More than four decades after the Clean Water Act, approximately 40% of our Nation's waterways still do not meet the goal of "fishable and swimmable." A significant challenge in meeting this goal is identifying sources of pollution, and specifically quantifying human fecal pollution. Recently, a highly abundant bacteriophage (a bacterial virus), named Cross-Assembly Phage, was identified in the human gut by metagenomics data mining. This bacteriophage is more abundant than all other known bacteriophages in the human gut combined, and appears to be human specific. This project will demonstrate the utility of the Cross-Assembly Phage assay through a demonstration study in the Allegheny River, including correlation with other fecal source tracking markers and viral pathogens; and investigate the global abundance and ubiquity of Cross-Assembly Phage in sewage with the assistance of international collaborators. Additionally, this project will involve the Pittsburgh Water Microbiome project as an educational and outreach task. In this project, middle-school student citizen-scientists will sample water, including water from Pittsburgh's three rivers, and the microbial ecology of the water samples will be analyzed by engineering undergraduate students. This effort will educate both citizen-scientists and undergraduate engineering students about microbiology and water quality. The Carnegie Science Center has committed to include an interactive kiosk on the project in an upcoming exhibit.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project represents a potentially transformative step forward in pollution source tracking, through the development of a human-specific, abundant viral marker of human fecal pollution in the environment. In addition to the water quality field, the proposed research will have significant impact on other fields, including food safety and human microbiome research. The PI is well qualified to conduct the proposed research, with significant experience in environmental virology, as well as an initial publication investigating the potential of Cross-Assembly Phage as a pollution source tracking marker. Additionally, the project has committed collaborators to assist with distinct project tasks, namely specificity testing for the qPCR assay and international sample collection. The project team has access to all necessary resources to complete the proposed research. Both the technical and educational aspects of the proposed work have significant benefits to society. Pollution impacts have rendered many of the nation's waterways not "fishable or swimmable"; developing an improved marker of human fecal pollution in Cross-Assembly Phage will enable more accurate regulation and beach closures, as well as more economical investments to control sources of pollution. The results from this project will be disseminated both in the peer-reviewed literature and conference proceedings as well as via outreach.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1818412</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Bibby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Bibby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbibby@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746311130</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>015E</Code>
<Text>Pollutant fate and transport</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~274674</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Existing microbial fecal pollution indicators (e.g., <em>E. coli</em>) are poor representatives of viruses, and viruses are predicted to account for the greatest fraction fo infectious risk in sewage contaminated water. In this project we developed cross-assembly phage as a viral fecal pollution indicator. Cross-assembly phage is a recently discovered bacteriophage that is highly abundant in the human gut, making it ideal for this application. First, we evaluated greater than 300 potential PCR primer targets. We then down-selected potential PCR primers based upon increasely stringent performance evaluations - namely, high specificity to and high concentrations in human sewage. Ultimately, we identified two PCR primer pairs that met our desired performance criteria. We then evaluated the performance of these primers in an urban stream known to receive sewage overflows. This effort was successful in identifying cross-assembly phage in environmental waters and found that cross-assembly phage&nbsp;concentrations correlated with rain events (sewage inputs). Cross-assembly phage also correlated with othe fecal pollution indicators, such as the molecular marker HF183 and <em>E. coli</em>. The final primary objective was to evaluate the presence of&nbsp;cross-assembly phage in sewage globally. Collaborative efforts through this project demonstrated that&nbsp;cross-assembly phage is present in sewage globally, and targeted efforts evaluated the concentration of&nbsp;cross-assembly phage in sewage in select countries. Beyond these primary research goals, efforts through this project evaluated&nbsp;cross-assembly phage persistence in the environment, removal through wastewater treatment, and potential use for infectious risk estimation. These efforts found that&nbsp;cross-assembly phage has similar persistence and removal to viral molecular targets, and has the potential to reduce the current level of acceptable disease burden in contaminated water.&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond primary research contributions, this project contributed to multiple educational opportunities for elementary and middle school students, and undergraduate and graduate researchers.</p> <p>Ultimately, the work supported by this project&nbsp;contributes to improved methods to protect human health and water quality.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2020<br>      Modified by: Kyle&nbsp;Bibby</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Existing microbial fecal pollution indicators (e.g., E. coli) are poor representatives of viruses, and viruses are predicted to account for the greatest fraction fo infectious risk in sewage contaminated water. In this project we developed cross-assembly phage as a viral fecal pollution indicator. Cross-assembly phage is a recently discovered bacteriophage that is highly abundant in the human gut, making it ideal for this application. First, we evaluated greater than 300 potential PCR primer targets. We then down-selected potential PCR primers based upon increasely stringent performance evaluations - namely, high specificity to and high concentrations in human sewage. Ultimately, we identified two PCR primer pairs that met our desired performance criteria. We then evaluated the performance of these primers in an urban stream known to receive sewage overflows. This effort was successful in identifying cross-assembly phage in environmental waters and found that cross-assembly phage concentrations correlated with rain events (sewage inputs). Cross-assembly phage also correlated with othe fecal pollution indicators, such as the molecular marker HF183 and E. coli. The final primary objective was to evaluate the presence of cross-assembly phage in sewage globally. Collaborative efforts through this project demonstrated that cross-assembly phage is present in sewage globally, and targeted efforts evaluated the concentration of cross-assembly phage in sewage in select countries. Beyond these primary research goals, efforts through this project evaluated cross-assembly phage persistence in the environment, removal through wastewater treatment, and potential use for infectious risk estimation. These efforts found that cross-assembly phage has similar persistence and removal to viral molecular targets, and has the potential to reduce the current level of acceptable disease burden in contaminated water.   Beyond primary research contributions, this project contributed to multiple educational opportunities for elementary and middle school students, and undergraduate and graduate researchers.  Ultimately, the work supported by this project contributes to improved methods to protect human health and water quality.       Last Modified: 09/25/2020       Submitted by: Kyle Bibby]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
