<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Culture-independent Rapid Bacterial Isolation and Identification</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project aims to develop and demonstrate the feasibility of a system that can identify a broad range of bacteria in &lt; 1 hour directly from blood. Existing diagnostic systems require 2-6 days to identify the bacteria, which delays treatment using appropriate antibiotics. Sepsis, which is often caused by a bacterial infection, contributes to up to half of all hospital deaths in the US largely due to complications arising from delays or inappropriate treatment (which is mainly because of lack of information regarding the infection-causing bacteria). It is the most expensive hospital-treated condition in the United States ? representing $20.3 billion in healthcare costs. The proposed system aims to sharply reduce the time to provide information needed by physicians, enabling them to initiate treatment using the appropriate antibiotic rapidly. This is expected to lead to significant reductions in costs, complications, and mortality. Further, by eliminating the need for culturing, new insights into bacterial behavior can be acquired contributing to additional fundamental knowledge of bacteria. This knowledge will aid antibiotic discovery efforts, improve understanding of mechanisms of drug resistance, support new biomanufacturing processes through faster detection of bacterial contamination of pharmaceutical products and foods, and characterization of the microbiome.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The challenges of rapid bacterial identification are primarily in two areas ? sample preparation, that eliminates the need for culturing, and multiplex identification, to cover the diverse range of bacterial species capable of causing infection. The proposed work is based on leveraging the differential response between bacteria and the cells in a sample matrix to selectively break down the sample matrix, but not bacteria, such that the largest lysis debris is smaller than intact bacteria. The debris is subsequently separated from intact bacteria using a size-based technique enabling rapid isolation of a broad range of bacteria directly from the sample. A novel Fourier-transform infrared microspectroscopy system is then used to identify the isolated bacteria at clinically relevant concentrations. No bacteria-specific reagents are employed. The proposed Phase I work addresses the highest risk technical hurdles in the process. Isolating and detecting low concentration of bacteria directly from blood is accomplished through the three objectives of this project that optimize the purification and bacterial recovery from the sample, identification accuracy, and performance of the integrated system relative to the traditional culturing-based method.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819613</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Krishnamurthy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajesh Krishnamurthy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rk@3idx.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3015156380</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000670268</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>3I Diagnostics, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Germantown</CityName>
<ZipCode>208764064</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3015156380</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>20271 Goldenrod Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[V5]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078811235</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>3I DIAGNOSTICS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[3i Diagnostics]]></Name>
<CityName>Gaithersburg</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>208781822</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[708 Quince Orchard Road, 250-D]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Phase I project aimed to optimize two process steps in the 3iDx system to achieve sensitive and specific detection of bacteria directly from blood within 1 hour. The chief technical hurdles at the time of the proposal were to ensure high recovery and sensitive detection of the bacteria directly from blood. The project effort successfully addressed the two main hurdles. The results from the Phase I effort also demonstrated the ability to differentiate bacteria, including strains with differing antibiotic susceptibilities, using their FTIR spectra. We fabricated prototypes of the separation cartridge for isolating intact bacteria from blood and of the FTIR spectrometer for analyzing the isolated bacteria. These results and prototypes demonstrate the feasibility of rapidly isolating and identifying bacteria directly from blood, without culturing, in &le; 1 hour. This means that in a clinical setting a physician could have the information they need to determine optimum treatment options from the start. The overall mission of 3iDx is to transform treatment of bloodstream infections by quickly identifying pathogens to enable targeted antibiotic treatments. The Phase 1 results suggest the feasibility of doing so. These results permit us to initiate the next step in commercializing this universal pathogen capture and identification system.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Rajesh&nbsp;Krishnamurthy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Phase I project aimed to optimize two process steps in the 3iDx system to achieve sensitive and specific detection of bacteria directly from blood within 1 hour. The chief technical hurdles at the time of the proposal were to ensure high recovery and sensitive detection of the bacteria directly from blood. The project effort successfully addressed the two main hurdles. The results from the Phase I effort also demonstrated the ability to differentiate bacteria, including strains with differing antibiotic susceptibilities, using their FTIR spectra. We fabricated prototypes of the separation cartridge for isolating intact bacteria from blood and of the FTIR spectrometer for analyzing the isolated bacteria. These results and prototypes demonstrate the feasibility of rapidly isolating and identifying bacteria directly from blood, without culturing, in &le; 1 hour. This means that in a clinical setting a physician could have the information they need to determine optimum treatment options from the start. The overall mission of 3iDx is to transform treatment of bloodstream infections by quickly identifying pathogens to enable targeted antibiotic treatments. The Phase 1 results suggest the feasibility of doing so. These results permit us to initiate the next step in commercializing this universal pathogen capture and identification system.       Last Modified: 03/03/2020       Submitted by: Rajesh Krishnamurthy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
