<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Commercialization of low-cost micro birdbath resonant gyroscope</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224903.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224903</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercialization potential of this project is to address the need for a small, low-cost, and high-accuracy angular rate and angular orientation sensor (also known as a gyroscope) for a wide range of applications.  Gyroscopes are desired by many emerging applications such as inertial measurement units for small satellites such as CubeSats, autonomous vehicles, drones, and high-end wearable electronics.  These applications require a gyroscope with a similar price (&lt; $10) but ~10,000 times better accuracy than those currently used in smartphones.  The birdbath resonator gyroscope (BRG) is a novel micro-electro-mechanical systems (MEMS) gyroscope with a strong potential to satisfy the needs of these applications due to significantly better resonance quality and mechanical symmetry than current silicon gyroscopes.  The economic impact of BRGs will be enormous since many industries can utilize high-performance gyroscopes to monitor the dynamics of their systems, provide positional awareness, and improve the performance of other parts of these systems.  Availability of low-cost and high-performance gyroscopes will enable users to further understand their applications and explore their limits and applicability across a broad range of societal needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to develop a new batch-level microfabrication technology to enable the commercialization of low-cost, very high-performance MEMS gyroscope from fused-silica.  Gyroscopes available today are either accurate but large and expensive (example: hemispherical resonator gyroscope), or small and cheap but inaccurate (example: smartphone gyroscopes).  High-accuracy silicon MEMS gyroscopes in research are small and accurate but expensive.  This is because silicon has fundamentally low mechanical resonance quality factor (Q) so it is difficult to manufacture high-accuracy gyroscopes with a high yield.  The BRG is a gyroscope made from fused-silica and capable of having low cost, small size, and high performance.  Its fused silica micro mechanical resonator can achieve significantly higher Q than silicon, which allows the BRG to be manufactured with a high yield.  The BRG fabrication process uses a blowtorch to reflow-mold a fused silica substrate into three-dimensional hollow shells with dimensions of several 10s of micrometers to several millimeters with high geometrical accuracy.  The proposed research will significantly enhance our understanding of the relationships among size, design, and process on the performance of the BRG as well as the relationship among detailed process parameters, yield and reproducibility on cost.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819893</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jae Yoong</FirstName>
<LastName>Cho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jae Yoong Cho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jycho@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346788600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000739980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Enertia Microsystems Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481059463</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7346788600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2972 Barclay Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080465900</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ENERTIA MICROSYSTEMS INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092122</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1301 Beal Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~224903</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Birdbath Resonator Gyroscope (BRG) is the world's first MEMS fused-silica three-dimensional shell gyroscope.&nbsp;&nbsp;A research-grade prototype of the BRG, reported from the University of Michigan, has demonstrated an in-run bias stability with 0.001-0.01 degrees per hour, which is the by far the most accurate performance reported from a MEMS gyroscope. &nbsp;The BRG has a potential to be manufactured at price as low cost as existing MEMS gyroscopes. &nbsp;Due to its excellent performance, small size, and low cost, the BRG could replace gyroscopes in existing markets and be used in many new applications such as autonomous vehicles, wearable consumer and medical electronics devices, robots, drones, underwater vehicles, and space satellites.</p> <p>In Phase 1, we built a portable prototype of the BRG. The prototype was built with a commercially available readout and control electronic system. The prototype demonstrated excellent in-run bias stability of ~0.01 deg/h at room temperature without temperature control. &nbsp;The device also demonstrated very good bias repeatability. &nbsp;We built a control system to adaptively suppress bias drift over a wide tempeture range. &nbsp;We completed a theoretical study of relationship between gyroscope's electromechanical properties (Q, capacitance, drive amplitude) and performance (bias stability, angle random walk, bandwidth).</p> <p>We verified that BRG can achieve low cost and high performance. In Phase 2, we will develop an improved device structure, a low-cost batch process fabrication process, and an improved readout and control electronic system of the BRG.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2020<br>      Modified by: Jae Yoong&nbsp;Cho</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591502710650_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591502710650_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Micro birdbath resonator gyroscope (BRG)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591502710650_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Micro birdbath resonator gyroscope (BRG)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">BRG consists of a 3D fused silica micro resonator and sixteen capacitive electrodes surrounding the perimeter of the resonator.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Enertia Microsystems Inc.</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jae Yoong&nbsp;Cho</div> <div class="imageTitle">Micro birdbath resonator gyroscope (BRG)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591503185535_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591503185535_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Micro birdbath resonator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591503185535_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Micro birdbath resonator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Micro birdbath resonator (diameter = 5mm)</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Michigan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jae Yoong&nbsp;Cho</div> <div class="imageTitle">Micro birdbath resonator</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591503324208_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591503324208_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BRG Prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819893/1819893_10554323_1591503324208_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BRG Prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">BRG prototype contains a vacuum-packaged electromechanical resonator, frontend ASIC, and FPGA</div> <div class="imageCredit">Enertia Microsystems Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jae Yoong&nbsp;Cho</div> <div class="imageTitle">BRG Prototype</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Birdbath Resonator Gyroscope (BRG) is the world's first MEMS fused-silica three-dimensional shell gyroscope.  A research-grade prototype of the BRG, reported from the University of Michigan, has demonstrated an in-run bias stability with 0.001-0.01 degrees per hour, which is the by far the most accurate performance reported from a MEMS gyroscope.  The BRG has a potential to be manufactured at price as low cost as existing MEMS gyroscopes.  Due to its excellent performance, small size, and low cost, the BRG could replace gyroscopes in existing markets and be used in many new applications such as autonomous vehicles, wearable consumer and medical electronics devices, robots, drones, underwater vehicles, and space satellites.  In Phase 1, we built a portable prototype of the BRG. The prototype was built with a commercially available readout and control electronic system. The prototype demonstrated excellent in-run bias stability of ~0.01 deg/h at room temperature without temperature control.  The device also demonstrated very good bias repeatability.  We built a control system to adaptively suppress bias drift over a wide tempeture range.  We completed a theoretical study of relationship between gyroscope's electromechanical properties (Q, capacitance, drive amplitude) and performance (bias stability, angle random walk, bandwidth).  We verified that BRG can achieve low cost and high performance. In Phase 2, we will develop an improved device structure, a low-cost batch process fabrication process, and an improved readout and control electronic system of the BRG.       Last Modified: 06/07/2020       Submitted by: Jae Yoong Cho]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
