<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Risk-Aware Motion Planning for Autonomous Vehicles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to enable autonomous vehicles to make risk-aware decisions at high-speed, by reasoning about the uncertain movements of the people and cars around them to anticipate risks and react defensively. This technology will make new technical approaches to safety and risk viable for the first time. It will enable autonomous cars to drive at regular speeds in dense, highly populated urban environments while reducing the likelihood of accidents - thereby resulting in faster, safer urban autonomous driving. This will increase public trust in autonomous cars and accelerate the development of a new industry which could reshape transportation, freeing people from the need to drive their own cars and increasing their free time and productivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to develop a specialized processor for risk-aware motion planning for autonomous vehicles. Motion planning is a critical problem for autonomous cars, which must decide how to move through space to reach a designated goal without colliding with a static obstacle, another vehicle, or a pedestrian. Existing approaches can only construct a few plans per second, and assume that the other road-users will continue on their current trajectories. This is acceptable for highways but not for urban driving, where distances are short and other road-users can change behavior suddenly. This project aims to develop a prototype of a specialized motion planning processor that plans in milliseconds, enabling it to consider all likely future movements of other road-users to anticipate risks and react defensively. This proposal aims to evaluate the feasibility of the processor by designing a prototype, demonstrating that it results in safer driving at normal speeds in urban environments, and quantifying its performance improvements over existing solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819302</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Howard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter M Howard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter@rtr.ai</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7815880142</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000751948</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Realtime Robotics Inc</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>022101625</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7815880142</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>27 Wormwood St Ste 110</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080306310</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REALTIME ROBOTICS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Realtime Robotics Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022102326</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12 Channel St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p> <div>Our target customers are companies seeking to deliver autonomous<br />vehicles or provide the technology required to provide autonomy to<br />vehicle manufacturers. These customers include personal car<br />manufacturers (Tesla, Toyota, Ford, etc.), existing and future car<br />sharing services (Uber, Lyft, Zoox, Ford, etc), and companies that<br />focus specifically on technology for autonomy (e.g., Google, Samsung,<br />Intel, etc). All of these companies are striving to achieve the goal<br />of fully autonomous vehicles--driving at normal speeds, with lower<br />power and minimal risk of accidents--and a key remaining hurdle is<br />low-power, risk-aware motion planning.&nbsp; Motion planning is the process<br />of computing the movements that the vehicle should take in order to<br />reach its goals while minimizing the risk of collisions.</div> <div></div> <div>Current autonomous vehicles perform motion planning through the use of<br />high-performance commodity processors, including graphics processing<br />units (GPUs). These processors consume kilowatts of power, yet cannot<br />plan fast enough to accommodate uncertain behaviors in other agents<br />(cars, bicycles, and pedestrians).&nbsp; Autonomous cars currently employ<br />sub-optimal schemes to work around their inability to perform<br />low-power, risk-aware motion planning, such as driving abnormally<br />slowly.</div> <div></div> <div>We have developed a novel processor design that performs low-power,<br />extremely high-speed motion planning for autonomous vehicles. All<br />existing solutions rely on writing software to run on commodity<br />processors, an approach that is fundamentally insufficient for<br />embedding risk awareness in the motion planning process. Our project<br />is the very first special-purpose motion processor for autonomous<br />vehicles. To achieve our goals, our design has to incorporate<br />probabilistic knowledge about agents, model and assess the compound<br />risk of each candidate motion plan, and choose the lowest risk path at<br />sufficiently high frequency.&nbsp; If ultimately successful, our technology<br />will positively disrupt the entire transportation market by enabling<br />rapid adoption of autonomous vehicles, since they will be thus able to<br />behave like and safely co-exist with human driven vehicles.</div> <div></div> <div>This project has led to one very important outcome: we have<br />demonstrated that our high-speed motion planning technology can<br />indeed reduce accidents in urban scenarios.&nbsp; We have developed a<br />sophisticated simulator that models an urban environment--complete<br />with other cars, bicyclists, and pedestrians--and the behaviors of an<br />autonomous vehicle both with and without our technology.&nbsp; The<br />simulator convincingly shows that our motion planner avoids accidents<br />in two ways.&nbsp; First, its sheer speed enables it to re-plan more<br />quickly when unexpected events occur.&nbsp; Second, its ability to plan<br />fast enough to accommodate multiple possible behaviors from all of the<br />other agents enables it to proactively identify motion plans that will<br />avoid accidents.</div> <div></div> <div>This project succeeded in demonstrating that our motion planning<br />processor design can avoid accidents and save lives.&nbsp; This project now<br />serves as the basis for the next phase of this project: implementing<br />our processor design in hardware.</div> </p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;M&nbsp;Howard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Our target customers are companies seeking to deliver autonomous vehicles or provide the technology required to provide autonomy to vehicle manufacturers. These customers include personal car manufacturers (Tesla, Toyota, Ford, etc.), existing and future car sharing services (Uber, Lyft, Zoox, Ford, etc), and companies that focus specifically on technology for autonomy (e.g., Google, Samsung, Intel, etc). All of these companies are striving to achieve the goal of fully autonomous vehicles--driving at normal speeds, with lower power and minimal risk of accidents--and a key remaining hurdle is low-power, risk-aware motion planning.  Motion planning is the process of computing the movements that the vehicle should take in order to reach its goals while minimizing the risk of collisions.  Current autonomous vehicles perform motion planning through the use of high-performance commodity processors, including graphics processing units (GPUs). These processors consume kilowatts of power, yet cannot plan fast enough to accommodate uncertain behaviors in other agents (cars, bicycles, and pedestrians).  Autonomous cars currently employ sub-optimal schemes to work around their inability to perform low-power, risk-aware motion planning, such as driving abnormally slowly.  We have developed a novel processor design that performs low-power, extremely high-speed motion planning for autonomous vehicles. All existing solutions rely on writing software to run on commodity processors, an approach that is fundamentally insufficient for embedding risk awareness in the motion planning process. Our project is the very first special-purpose motion processor for autonomous vehicles. To achieve our goals, our design has to incorporate probabilistic knowledge about agents, model and assess the compound risk of each candidate motion plan, and choose the lowest risk path at sufficiently high frequency.  If ultimately successful, our technology will positively disrupt the entire transportation market by enabling rapid adoption of autonomous vehicles, since they will be thus able to behave like and safely co-exist with human driven vehicles.  This project has led to one very important outcome: we have demonstrated that our high-speed motion planning technology can indeed reduce accidents in urban scenarios.  We have developed a sophisticated simulator that models an urban environment--complete with other cars, bicyclists, and pedestrians--and the behaviors of an autonomous vehicle both with and without our technology.  The simulator convincingly shows that our motion planner avoids accidents in two ways.  First, its sheer speed enables it to re-plan more quickly when unexpected events occur.  Second, its ability to plan fast enough to accommodate multiple possible behaviors from all of the other agents enables it to proactively identify motion plans that will avoid accidents.  This project succeeded in demonstrating that our motion planning processor design can avoid accidents and save lives.  This project now serves as the basis for the next phase of this project: implementing our processor design in hardware.        Last Modified: 12/10/2018       Submitted by: Peter M Howard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
