<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Novel Immuno-Nutrition Properties of a Single Cell Protein to Abate Soy-Induced Enteritis in Aquafeeds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to develop a protein replacement for soy-based marine animal diets to improve yield through effective nutrition and enhanced animal welfare. Aquafeeds represent &gt;50% of the cost of production, and losses due to mortality can be as high as 50% in certain commercial species. A novel feed ingredient that contains immuno-nutritional properties to address these inefficiencies could be considered a game-changer to the industry. Fish are the most resource-efficient sources of animal protein, a healthy source of food for people, and will be one of the ways to address food security. As the surface of the planet is greater than two-thirds ocean, one estimate suggests, if managed properly, just 2% of this vast resource could produce enough food for all of mankind. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to expand previous studies that suggested a novel single cell protein (SCP) is a significant candidate to serve as a fishmeal alternative. In addition, SCP also may contain functional properties that improve growth performance and survival. The SCP tested previously supported improved feed conversion ratios (FCR) as compared to conventional diets, while at the same time, statistically relevant improvements in survival of carnivorous fish and shrimp.  It also was observed that SCP relieved secondary disease complications associated with diets, such as gastro-enteritis. With hundreds of marketable species in aquaculture, and an industry that is just 50 years old, the collective understanding of aquatic animal nutrition is in its infancy. In this project, a carnivorous Seriola species will be used as a model organism to serve as an additional reference point beyond salmon. Targeted components of the SCP will be enhanced (or deleted) to determine the effect of leading immuno-nutritional candidates on the animals' ability to digest more completely inputs like soy bean meal (SBM). The effectiveness of SCPs in emerging commercial fish diets has yet to be fully elucidated, and the results of this study may have implications towards lower-cost feed formulations and optimized nutrition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819652</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
<LastName>Feinberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Larry Feinberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lfeinberg@knipbio.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4136278149</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000687069</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>KnipBio Inc</Name>
<CityName>Harvard</CityName>
<ZipCode>014511501</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4136278149</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>142 Still River Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079130093</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KNIPBIO, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[KnipBio]]></Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018523550</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Canal Street, 4th Floor M2D2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Aquaculture is the fastest growing sector in food production and one of the healthiest, least environmentally impactful, animal proteins available for our rapidly growing population. The UN-FAO prediction based on the human population growth rate and current per capita consumption estimates that an additional 23 million tons of aquafeed will be required by 2030. This number is staggering, and will require us to produce more than our current land and ocean biomass can sustainably support. In light of this ever-increasing pressure, the race for additional protein sources is now well underway. Avenues to close this gap include the conservation of existing supplies (i.e. renderings), improved efficiencies in plant biology (e.g. soy biotechnology) and novel protein alternatives (primarily insect or microbial protein). At KnipBio we focus on microbial protein sources, commonly referred to as single cell protein (SCP).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>SCP has a number of advantages over competing technologies including robust process economics, no requirement for additional arable land or fisheries, a diversity of utilizable feedstocks, and the wide array of process intensification options available. These attributes combine to produce an excellent animal feed which is in large part divorced from environmental and economic fluctuations. The results are a feed that can fuel the American aquaculture industry with no additional land requirements</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our product, KnipBio Meal (KBM) which is based on the microbial species <em>Methylobacterium extorquens</em>, is a protein source specifically developed with broad applicability to the aquaculture industry in mind. We have shown successful inclusion in feed for a number of different fish species as well as crustaceans (shrimp). During these trials we observed that in certain conditions there was, in addition to serving as a food source, also a positive health impact, leading to higher survival rates, and thus the potential for increased profits to farmers. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The focus of our NSF SBIR Phase I project was to investigate the health benefits of feeding KBM to shrimp and trout. These species represent a substantial percentage of the total global aquaculture market and therefore serves as an excellent representative model.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We generated a cohort of engineered strains that either produce greater or lesser quantities of compounds we believe may be responsible for the observed health improvements. These were then tested in controlled environments against a baseline control feed. We were able to confirm that KBM does indeed impart health benefits above and beyond a control feed in both shrimp and trout. By comparing our standard form of KBM against those produced from our engineered strains we were also able to identify the most likely compounds responsible for this improvement.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These exciting results, and the intellectual property generated from them, would not have been possible withou the support provided by the NSF SBIR program. Of additional note, during the time of this award, our product was awarded Generally Regarded As Safe (GRAS) status by the FDA for finfish. This will allow our customers to purchase KBM with confidence, further improving our value proposition.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, looking ahead, the results of the Phase I trials, combined with a TEA, and interviews of key stakeholders have convinced us of the utility of these aforementioned health benefits in entering the market. Simultaneously, we believe there is substantial market demand for a product that contains these positive traits, while supplying high quality protein at the lowest possible cost. Our NSF SBIR Phase II proposal will seek to leverage the learnings from these studies and enable KnipBio to further support the development of a robust American aquaculture industry and creating high paying jobs in rural areas of the United States.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/20/2019<br>      Modified by: Larry&nbsp;Feinberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Aquaculture is the fastest growing sector in food production and one of the healthiest, least environmentally impactful, animal proteins available for our rapidly growing population. The UN-FAO prediction based on the human population growth rate and current per capita consumption estimates that an additional 23 million tons of aquafeed will be required by 2030. This number is staggering, and will require us to produce more than our current land and ocean biomass can sustainably support. In light of this ever-increasing pressure, the race for additional protein sources is now well underway. Avenues to close this gap include the conservation of existing supplies (i.e. renderings), improved efficiencies in plant biology (e.g. soy biotechnology) and novel protein alternatives (primarily insect or microbial protein). At KnipBio we focus on microbial protein sources, commonly referred to as single cell protein (SCP).     SCP has a number of advantages over competing technologies including robust process economics, no requirement for additional arable land or fisheries, a diversity of utilizable feedstocks, and the wide array of process intensification options available. These attributes combine to produce an excellent animal feed which is in large part divorced from environmental and economic fluctuations. The results are a feed that can fuel the American aquaculture industry with no additional land requirements     Our product, KnipBio Meal (KBM) which is based on the microbial species Methylobacterium extorquens, is a protein source specifically developed with broad applicability to the aquaculture industry in mind. We have shown successful inclusion in feed for a number of different fish species as well as crustaceans (shrimp). During these trials we observed that in certain conditions there was, in addition to serving as a food source, also a positive health impact, leading to higher survival rates, and thus the potential for increased profits to farmers.       The focus of our NSF SBIR Phase I project was to investigate the health benefits of feeding KBM to shrimp and trout. These species represent a substantial percentage of the total global aquaculture market and therefore serves as an excellent representative model.     We generated a cohort of engineered strains that either produce greater or lesser quantities of compounds we believe may be responsible for the observed health improvements. These were then tested in controlled environments against a baseline control feed. We were able to confirm that KBM does indeed impart health benefits above and beyond a control feed in both shrimp and trout. By comparing our standard form of KBM against those produced from our engineered strains we were also able to identify the most likely compounds responsible for this improvement.      These exciting results, and the intellectual property generated from them, would not have been possible withou the support provided by the NSF SBIR program. Of additional note, during the time of this award, our product was awarded Generally Regarded As Safe (GRAS) status by the FDA for finfish. This will allow our customers to purchase KBM with confidence, further improving our value proposition.     Finally, looking ahead, the results of the Phase I trials, combined with a TEA, and interviews of key stakeholders have convinced us of the utility of these aforementioned health benefits in entering the market. Simultaneously, we believe there is substantial market demand for a product that contains these positive traits, while supplying high quality protein at the lowest possible cost. Our NSF SBIR Phase II proposal will seek to leverage the learnings from these studies and enable KnipBio to further support the development of a robust American aquaculture industry and creating high paying jobs in rural areas of the United States.       Last Modified: 08/20/2019       Submitted by: Larry Feinberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
