<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A Compact Home Power Generator using a Free-Piston Engine</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224249.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224249</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to sell affordable backup generators that provide 23 kilowatts, for operating a home's lights and appliances. With power outages due to natural disasters and an aging power grid becoming ever more frequent, and with society increasingly reliant on electricity to power not only lights and household appliances, but also computers, wireless routers, and medical devices, back-up power is an increasingly critical need. This SBIR's portable generator is expected to be more than an order of magnitude lower cubic size and weight, all at a reduced cost compared to existing generators.  The broader impact of this project is its significant benefits to the environment by providing backup power at high fuel efficiency (i.e. less consumption of non-renewable fossil fuels) and low emissions of hydrocarbons, particulate matter, carbon monoxide, and smoke.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to address the shortcomings of residential-use backup generators currently on the market. Available backup generators are either small and affordable but can only power a single appliance; or able to power most of a home's needs but cumbersome and expensive. This project will demonstrate the potential for implementing a free-piston internal combustion engine that will maximize fuel efficiency; minimize size; decrease dependence on lubricating oil; and incorporate an engine management system. The objective of the current effort is the engine, while the functioning compact generator will be developed in the next phase. In this free-piston engine design, the two pistons oscillate with forces in balance and reduced side-loads to the pistons, yielding a long-lasting high-speed engine. The pilot work included modification of the cylinder intake ports; addition of a modified squish band and dome to the cylinder head; and use of low-friction bearing materials yielding a successful prototype that runs on regular gasoline. The engineers will continue implementing, testing, and improving on these modifications. The successful completion of this project will yield an efficient, compact, low-weight, and low-emissions generator that produces 23 kilowatts of usable power that runs on standard pump gasoline.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819821</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Araujo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto F Araujo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>afa928@aol.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7862801246</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000765335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alfadan Inc</Name>
<CityName>Miramar</CityName>
<ZipCode>330273249</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7862801246</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3350 SW 139 Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080975694</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALFADAN, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alfadan Inc]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>330273249</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~224249</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF SBIR Phase I project proposes to address the shortcomings of residential-use back-up generators that are currently on the market. Currently available back-up generators are either small and affordable ones that can only power a single appliance, or heavy and expensive ones that can run most of a home's needs. During the duration of the Phase I project, Alfadan demonstrated the potential for implementing a free piston internal combustion engine that will maximize fuel efficiency relative to the size of the generator; minimize dependence on lubricating oil by incorporating combinations of new materials; and incorporate an engine management system that will maximize the potential of the proprietary engine design.</p> <p>The present 23 kilowatt generators manufactured by Generac, Honda and others are big, heavy and expensive. (80 cu. ft.; 1,700 lbs.; cost $8000 to $15,000). The Alfadan generator incorporates a lightweight free-piston engine that is small (2.9 cu. ft.; 50 lbs.), produces 23 kilowatts of power and will sell for less than $5,000. This generator will disrupt the present commercial space by supplanting far bigger and costlier 23 kilowatt generators now on the market.</p> <p>The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR project is to sell affordable backup generators that provide enough power to operate 80% of a home's lights and appliances. With power outages due to natural disasters and an aging power grid becoming ever more frequent, and with society increasingly reliant on electricity to power not only lights and household appliances, but also computers, wireless routers, and medical devices, back-up power is an increasingly critical need.As larger companies adopt the innovations introduced here, there is potential for even lower-cost models to enter the market. The broader impact of this project is its significant benefits to the environment by providing backup power at high fuel efficiency (i.e. less consumption of non-renewable fossil fuels) and low emissions of hydrocarbons, particulate matter, carbon monoxide, and smoke.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/26/2019<br>      Modified by: Alberto&nbsp;F&nbsp;Araujo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1819821/1819821_10549832_1551216990585_enginephoto--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1819821/1819821_10549832_1551216990585_enginephoto--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Assembled Alfadan AD120 engine"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1819821/1819821_10549832_1551216990585_enginephoto--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Assembled Alfadan AD120 engine"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Assembled Alfadan AD120 engine</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alfadan Copyright 2019</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alberto&nbsp;F&nbsp;Araujo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Assembled Alfadan AD120 engine</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF SBIR Phase I project proposes to address the shortcomings of residential-use back-up generators that are currently on the market. Currently available back-up generators are either small and affordable ones that can only power a single appliance, or heavy and expensive ones that can run most of a home's needs. During the duration of the Phase I project, Alfadan demonstrated the potential for implementing a free piston internal combustion engine that will maximize fuel efficiency relative to the size of the generator; minimize dependence on lubricating oil by incorporating combinations of new materials; and incorporate an engine management system that will maximize the potential of the proprietary engine design.  The present 23 kilowatt generators manufactured by Generac, Honda and others are big, heavy and expensive. (80 cu. ft.; 1,700 lbs.; cost $8000 to $15,000). The Alfadan generator incorporates a lightweight free-piston engine that is small (2.9 cu. ft.; 50 lbs.), produces 23 kilowatts of power and will sell for less than $5,000. This generator will disrupt the present commercial space by supplanting far bigger and costlier 23 kilowatt generators now on the market.  The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR project is to sell affordable backup generators that provide enough power to operate 80% of a home's lights and appliances. With power outages due to natural disasters and an aging power grid becoming ever more frequent, and with society increasingly reliant on electricity to power not only lights and household appliances, but also computers, wireless routers, and medical devices, back-up power is an increasingly critical need.As larger companies adopt the innovations introduced here, there is potential for even lower-cost models to enter the market. The broader impact of this project is its significant benefits to the environment by providing backup power at high fuel efficiency (i.e. less consumption of non-renewable fossil fuels) and low emissions of hydrocarbons, particulate matter, carbon monoxide, and smoke.                   Last Modified: 02/26/2019       Submitted by: Alberto F Araujo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
