<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Fast Focus and Zoom in Microscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will enable fast focusing and zoom in microscopy with an optomechanical system consisting of micro-electro-mechanical systems (MEMS) mirrors. The microscope add-on will enable fast 3D imaging in wide-field microscopes and increase focusing and zoom speeds by 100x when compared with conventional methods in confocal and multiphoton microscopy. The technology allows the sample stage and objective lens turret to remain stationary during experiments. It will increase throughput, preserve sensitive samples, enable observation of dynamic events, and reduce training time. The innovation will spur significant discovery in understanding dynamic reactions that occur in in vivo and in vitro microscopy. The initial target market has an estimated gross revenue of $75M. The technology also promises to benefit 3D imaging systems for manufacturing or machine vision, optical coherence tomography, and endoscopic imaging systems by providing high speed and agile focus control. While MEMS are ubiquitous in mobile platforms and the automotive industry for motion sensing, they have not yet permeated other markets or imaging systems to the same extent. With recent advances in fabrication and performance of optical MEMS devices, bringing this type of technology to other platforms can spark greater commercialization of the technology in non-traditional areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is foremost the demonstration of a novel optomechanical system with MEMS mirrors for independent control of focusing and zoom in microscopy. MEMS mirrors are a type of varifocus element. They remain stationary while their voltage-controlled, configurable surface shapes allow for fast focusing and attendant correction of spherical aberration. Fast MEMS mirrors, with sufficient diameters for 2x zoom and significant focusing capability, have not previously been demonstrated in literature or commercially. By producing and characterizing fast, large-diameter MEMS mirrors for this project, knowledge of varifocus elements will be advanced. This project will also continue to define standard optical design practices to best utilize varifocus elements, since traditional optical analyses assume fixed focal length lenses or mirrors. The project objectives are three-fold: 1) fabricate large-diameter MEMS mirrors with greater than 40% yield, 2) characterize their focusing range and dynamic behavior, and 3) demonstrate them in a focus and zoom system suitable as a microscopy add-on component.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819493</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Lukes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah Lukes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slukes@agilefocusdesigns.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4065819228</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000698529</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Agile Focus Designs, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<ZipCode>597156056</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4064511497</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 W Kagy Blvd Ste D #215</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079839877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AGILE FOCUS DESIGNS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Agile Focus Designs, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597156056</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[280 W Kagy Blvd Ste D #215]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Agile Focus Designs enables fast focusing and zoom in microscopy, thereby mitigating the need to flip objective lenses during an experiment. This provides the microscopist true flexibility in the imaging space, where magnification and focus location can be independently altered at video rates. For this Phase I award, we manufactured a prototype system that is capable of 1x-2x magnification over a wide focus range at rates greater than 500&nbsp;Hz. The prototype exceeded the proposed customer metrics of 1x-1.75x and 300&nbsp;Hz.</p> <p class="Default">The foundation of the technology stems from micro-electromechanical systems (MEMS) mirrors that perform variable focus. To achieve 2x magnification change with infinite conjugate imaging, one MEMS mirror must be twice the size of the others. Freestanding deformable membrane mirrors are usually less than 5-6&nbsp;mm in diameter. This is due to difficulties that arise in maintaining flatness and good optical quality surfaces when the mirrors have no structural support except for at the perimeter of the mirrors. For this award, we demonstrated successful release of 10-mm-diameter freestanding deformable membrane mirrors. They had high optical quality and flatness, as well as a focal range from 365&nbsp;mm to infinity. Their 3&nbsp;dB bandwidth exceeded the design goal of 300&nbsp;Hz.</p> <p class="Default">Feasibility for a commercial fast focus and zoom system has been demonstrated and exceeded expectations. Agile Focus Designs will continue working with it&rsquo;s commercial avenues to get the product to market.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Lukes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Agile Focus Designs enables fast focusing and zoom in microscopy, thereby mitigating the need to flip objective lenses during an experiment. This provides the microscopist true flexibility in the imaging space, where magnification and focus location can be independently altered at video rates. For this Phase I award, we manufactured a prototype system that is capable of 1x-2x magnification over a wide focus range at rates greater than 500 Hz. The prototype exceeded the proposed customer metrics of 1x-1.75x and 300 Hz. The foundation of the technology stems from micro-electromechanical systems (MEMS) mirrors that perform variable focus. To achieve 2x magnification change with infinite conjugate imaging, one MEMS mirror must be twice the size of the others. Freestanding deformable membrane mirrors are usually less than 5-6 mm in diameter. This is due to difficulties that arise in maintaining flatness and good optical quality surfaces when the mirrors have no structural support except for at the perimeter of the mirrors. For this award, we demonstrated successful release of 10-mm-diameter freestanding deformable membrane mirrors. They had high optical quality and flatness, as well as a focal range from 365 mm to infinity. Their 3 dB bandwidth exceeded the design goal of 300 Hz. Feasibility for a commercial fast focus and zoom system has been demonstrated and exceeded expectations. Agile Focus Designs will continue working with it?s commercial avenues to get the product to market.          Last Modified: 07/31/2019       Submitted by: Sarah Lukes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
