<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Manganese Oxide-Carbon Nanosheet Anodes for Extreme High Power Lithium Ion Batteries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) project is the advancement of improved lithium ion batteries. The project will evaluate new battery chemistry enabling more rapid charging rates then currently available in the worldwide energy storage marketplace. Such high power density batteries would cater to a major emerging battery segment where current lithium ion battery technologies fall dramatically short. Successful development of this innovation will provide benefits to both current and future applications. Clearly, large scale deployment of a markedly superior energy storage device will have significant societal benefits by accelerating the move away from fossil fuel in many applications and products. For instance, a viable regenerative braking energy storage technology based on the proposed technology would result in a tremendous reduction in electricity used by subway trains, with a concomitant reduction of CO2 emissions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project proposes to address the core of the microstructure - performance relations in energy storing materials, answering a series of fundamental questions regarding how a charge carrier is reversibly or irreversibly stored at high rates in manganese oxide - carbon nanocomposite anodes. In conventional LIBs, it is the graphite-based anode that limits charging rates, with catastrophic lithium metal plating and dendrite growth occurring at increased currents. It is expected that many of the existing "Graphite - Inherited" paradigms regarding fast rate in anodes would be done away with, or substantially redefined with the proposed approach for designing high power lithium ion batteries based on an inexpensive hemp-derived carbon nanosheets and nanostructured manganese oxide anodes. A much clearer understanding of the synthesis - structure - property relations in such nanocomposites will have wide-reaching scientific and technological implications. Research and development activities will focus on structural optimization and manufacturing scalability along with fabrication and testing of near-commercial pouch cell form factors in order to demonstrate device-level performance and commercial viability of the proposed technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819877</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rahul</FirstName>
<LastName>Mukherjee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rahul Mukherjee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rahul.mukherjee@enermat-tech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2177783410</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000703838</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Mitlin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Mitlin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.mitlin2@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152613440</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000707165</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>EnerMat Technologies, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Clifton Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>120653810</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852332143</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>51 Orchardview Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079968211</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ENERMAT TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[EnerMat Technologies, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Clifton Park</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>120653810</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[51 Orchardview Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Today, the industry has widely turned to lithium metal batteries to achieve high energy densities and good rate capabilities. However, lithium metal anodes suffer from serious safety concerns due to their potential to form dendrites, resulting in thermal runaway, shorting and overall catastrophic failure of the batteries. It is well known that such failures in lithium batteries can have devastating effects on the end-use application. This has resulted in an urgency to identify alternate advanced anode materials that can push the boundaries of lithium ion batteries while not compromising on safety.</p> <p>In this regard, the project investigated a novel manganese oxide / carbon nanosheet composite anode as an advanced battery electrode material for high power density applications. <strong>The composite anode delivered capacities close to 400 mAh/g, even at a current density as high as 744 mA/g (corresponding to a rate capability of approximately 2C or charge/discharge in 30 minutes).</strong> For reference, commercial graphite anodes typically deliver between 300 mAh/g and 350 mAh/g at much slower rates (lithium ion batteries are generally rated at C/10 or charge/discharge in 10 hours).</p> <p><strong>Further, the team confirmed that the novel anode architecture could still deliver excellent energy density without any observable signs of plating across all the ranges of C-rate that were tested. </strong>Plating is considered a precursor to dendrite formation and should therefore be avoided to prevent an unforeseen failure of the battery. This is particularly problematic for lithium metal anodes, as described above, but is also a significant challenge for advanced anode materials that suffer from irreversible side-reactions, low diffusivity or high defect concentration. For example, plating has been widely reported for graphene-based anodes and along with graphene?s cost and scalability limitations, plating has continued to remain a major impediment in its commercialization potential. However, due to the inherent properties of the manganese oxide / carbon nanosheet composite anode, plating was eliminated, even at high rates of charge and discharge.</p> <p><strong>Finally, the team carefully studied and tailored the properties and synthesis process of the nano-materials in order to demonstrate scalability</strong> ? an aspect critical to determine commercial viability of nano-scale energy storage materials.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact: </strong>The team successfully demonstrated production scalability of carbon nano-sheets, a graphene-like carbon material that offers high conductivity and charge storage capacities. <strong>Beyond the scope of this project, carbon nano-sheets can open up a wide scale of potential applications previously dominated by graphene.</strong> Despite significant efforts, graphene has been unable to demonstrate performance when produced in bulk, primarily due to its loss of structural properties attributed to factors such as defects and agglomeration. Further, it has been challenging thus far to produce graphene at a commercially relevant cost point. <strong>Not only was carbon nano-sheets produced in bulk, where the team scaled from gram-scale production in a laboratory environment to kilogram-scale production in a chemical manufacturing line, it was achieved by not compromising the estimated pricing structure.</strong> This was accomplished by ensuring that the chemical precursors were non-toxic and inexpensive and the process was inherently scalable. At this stage, the team expects carbon nano-sheets to cost around $20-$40 per kilogram, well within the range of conductive carbon such as Super P (estimated high volume pricing is ~$20 per kilogram and estimated low volume pricing is ~$2,250 per kilogram) and significantly cheaper than graphene (estimated to be anywhere between $1,000 and $100,000 per kilogram). It is to be noted here that establishing low and high-volume pricing structure is critical to understand the supply chain and scalability. Our estimates were calculated using a medium volume approximation of raw materials and manufacturing overheads.</p> <p><strong>In addition to scalability studies and during the course of this project, the team also identified a critical sheathing approach that could protect high surface area nano-scale materials. This would not only reduce the first cycle capacity loss that is attributed to the initial formation of solid electrolyte interphase and an impediment to commercialization of several advanced materials including silicon, it could also potentially allow an increase in the concentration of active nano-material composites.</strong> This would directly result in higher capacities (or energy density) and an extended cycle life.</p> <p>Finally, the project also involved a graduate student and provided him with a unique experience of transitioning from laboratory-scale research to commercially relevant testing protocols and standards. The interactions with chemical manufacturers and prototyping plants is an aspect that is critical to the wholesome learning experience of students and prepares them better for their next role ? be it in academia or industry.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Rahul&nbsp;Mukherjee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819877/1819877_10559709_1585578436218_ProjectOutcomesSummaryFig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819877/1819877_10559709_1585578436218_ProjectOutcomesSummaryFig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Outcomes Summary"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1819877/1819877_10559709_1585578436218_ProjectOutcomesSummaryFig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Outcomes Summary"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A. Kilogram-scale carbon nano-sheets batch produced in a pilot line; B. Rate capability and batch-to-batch repeatability of manganese oxide / carbon nano-sheets composite electrodes; C. Capacity and performance stability of manganese oxide / carbon nano-sheet composite electrodes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dave Mitlin, Rahul Mukherjee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rahul&nbsp;Mukherjee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Outcomes Summary</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Today, the industry has widely turned to lithium metal batteries to achieve high energy densities and good rate capabilities. However, lithium metal anodes suffer from serious safety concerns due to their potential to form dendrites, resulting in thermal runaway, shorting and overall catastrophic failure of the batteries. It is well known that such failures in lithium batteries can have devastating effects on the end-use application. This has resulted in an urgency to identify alternate advanced anode materials that can push the boundaries of lithium ion batteries while not compromising on safety.  In this regard, the project investigated a novel manganese oxide / carbon nanosheet composite anode as an advanced battery electrode material for high power density applications. The composite anode delivered capacities close to 400 mAh/g, even at a current density as high as 744 mA/g (corresponding to a rate capability of approximately 2C or charge/discharge in 30 minutes). For reference, commercial graphite anodes typically deliver between 300 mAh/g and 350 mAh/g at much slower rates (lithium ion batteries are generally rated at C/10 or charge/discharge in 10 hours).  Further, the team confirmed that the novel anode architecture could still deliver excellent energy density without any observable signs of plating across all the ranges of C-rate that were tested. Plating is considered a precursor to dendrite formation and should therefore be avoided to prevent an unforeseen failure of the battery. This is particularly problematic for lithium metal anodes, as described above, but is also a significant challenge for advanced anode materials that suffer from irreversible side-reactions, low diffusivity or high defect concentration. For example, plating has been widely reported for graphene-based anodes and along with graphene?s cost and scalability limitations, plating has continued to remain a major impediment in its commercialization potential. However, due to the inherent properties of the manganese oxide / carbon nanosheet composite anode, plating was eliminated, even at high rates of charge and discharge.  Finally, the team carefully studied and tailored the properties and synthesis process of the nano-materials in order to demonstrate scalability ? an aspect critical to determine commercial viability of nano-scale energy storage materials.  Broader Impact: The team successfully demonstrated production scalability of carbon nano-sheets, a graphene-like carbon material that offers high conductivity and charge storage capacities. Beyond the scope of this project, carbon nano-sheets can open up a wide scale of potential applications previously dominated by graphene. Despite significant efforts, graphene has been unable to demonstrate performance when produced in bulk, primarily due to its loss of structural properties attributed to factors such as defects and agglomeration. Further, it has been challenging thus far to produce graphene at a commercially relevant cost point. Not only was carbon nano-sheets produced in bulk, where the team scaled from gram-scale production in a laboratory environment to kilogram-scale production in a chemical manufacturing line, it was achieved by not compromising the estimated pricing structure. This was accomplished by ensuring that the chemical precursors were non-toxic and inexpensive and the process was inherently scalable. At this stage, the team expects carbon nano-sheets to cost around $20-$40 per kilogram, well within the range of conductive carbon such as Super P (estimated high volume pricing is ~$20 per kilogram and estimated low volume pricing is ~$2,250 per kilogram) and significantly cheaper than graphene (estimated to be anywhere between $1,000 and $100,000 per kilogram). It is to be noted here that establishing low and high-volume pricing structure is critical to understand the supply chain and scalability. Our estimates were calculated using a medium volume approximation of raw materials and manufacturing overheads.  In addition to scalability studies and during the course of this project, the team also identified a critical sheathing approach that could protect high surface area nano-scale materials. This would not only reduce the first cycle capacity loss that is attributed to the initial formation of solid electrolyte interphase and an impediment to commercialization of several advanced materials including silicon, it could also potentially allow an increase in the concentration of active nano-material composites. This would directly result in higher capacities (or energy density) and an extended cycle life.  Finally, the project also involved a graduate student and provided him with a unique experience of transitioning from laboratory-scale research to commercially relevant testing protocols and standards. The interactions with chemical manufacturers and prototyping plants is an aspect that is critical to the wholesome learning experience of students and prepares them better for their next role ? be it in academia or industry.       Last Modified: 03/30/2020       Submitted by: Rahul Mukherjee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
