<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: 3D Printing of Bisphenol A-free Polycarbonates for Customizable Cell/Tissue Culture Platforms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop customizable cell/tissue culture platforms using a new class of 3D printable bisphenol A-free polycarbonate (BFP) materials and a rapid 3D printing system. The 3D cell culture market was valued at $683 million in 2017 with an exponential projected growth in revenue valued at $1.7 billion by 2022. The rapid growth in this sector is primarily driven by the demand for custom-made 3D cell/tissue models that more accurately recapitulate the human in vivo biology in comparison to conventional animal models and planar cell culture systems. 3D cell/tissue models have the potential to provide more physiologically relevant responses for the drug discovery industry which is estimated to reach $86 billion in 2022. The proposed strategy of using BFP and a fully integrated benchtop 3D printing system will facilitate the production of different cell/tissue culture platforms on demand and enable rapid iteration of different designs to drive forward the development of more clinically relevant cell/tissue models for a broad market in pharmaceuticals, biotechnology, and biological studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies in: (1) the development of novel 3D printable BFP materials with tunable material properties using green chemistry, and (2) the rapid 3D printing of customizable cell/tissue culture prototypes to support various 3D cell/tissue models. The material development will include the establishment of a reagent library and optimization of the green chemistry process. The relevant material properties such as stiffness, elasticity, optical transparency, and small molecule adsorption will be characterized and optimized. These materials will then be printed using a rapid light-based 3D printer to prototype cell/tissue culture platforms followed by evaluation of their performance. In particular, 3D printing precision and resolution will be characterized and optimized by varying a range of fabrication parameters such as light exposure time and intensity. Next, the efficacy of the prototypes under cell culture conditions will be assessed based on device integrity, material degradation, as well as changes in mechanical and optical properties. Various cells/tissues will also be cultured on these prototype devices to evaluate biocompatibility. These achievements will provide customized culture platforms to facilitate the engineering of more physiologically relevant in vitro models for accelerating drug discovery and biological studies in both industry and academia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819239</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Zhu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wzhu@allegro3d.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8589977741</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000751937</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Allegro 3D, Inc</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921212217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8586993298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6868 Nancy Ridge Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080671490</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALLEGRO 3D, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Allegro 3D, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921212248</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6404 Nancy Ridge Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project is to develop a rapid 3D printing system and a new class of photopolymerizable polycarbonates &nbsp;that is free of bisphenol A (BPA) to create customizable 3D printed cell/tissue culture platforms. Th research activities include: (1) expanding the reagent library and investigating the green chemistry synthesis routes for 3D printable BPA free polycarbonates; (2) characterizing the material properties of the new BPA free polycarbonates, including the mechanical, optical, thermal, chemical, and biological properties; (3) developing a rapid 3D optical printing platform and optimize the 3D printing process with the new BPA free polycarbonates; (4) 3D printing cell/tissue culture devices with the BPA free polycarbonates and evaluating the cell/tissue growth on these devices.</p> <p>This work has led to significant outcomes including: (1) A green chemistry synthesis route has been developed to synthesize BPA free polycarbonates, which eliminates the hazardous impacts of BPA on human health and the environment. (2) A new class of BPA free polycarbonates with controllable material properties (i.e. mechanical, thermal, optical, and biological properties) has been synthesized for various needs in the biomedical fields. The new BPA free polycarbonates successfully overcame the small molecular absorption problem associated with polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS). Moreover, these new polycarbonates are 3D printable with our rapid optical 3D printer, which enables the fabrication of customized biomedical devices on demand. (3) A rapid optical 3D printing platform has been developed with superior printing resolution, speed, flexibility, and scalability compared to the conventional nozzle-based 3D printers. Our 3D printing platform can not only work with our new polycarbonate inks, but also print with various other biomaterials and cells to construct biomedical devices and biological tissues. (4) Customizable microwell arrays have been 3D printed with the BPA free polycarbonates for high-throughput culture of 3D cell spheroids or organoids. High cell viability on our 3D printed polycarbonate devices were achieved, indicating the excellent biocompatibility of our material and fabrication process. Moreover, a surface modification method has been developed to modify the hydrophobicity of the 3D printed polycarbonate devices for optimal performance in assisting the organoid formation.</p> <p>Ongoing commercialization efforts include: (1) having interviewed potential customers from the pharmaceutical industry, biotechnology companies, hospitals, and research institutes to identify the minimum viable product and the beachhead market; (2) having attended major conferences to promote our company and find collaborations for our platform technology; (3) having discovered some early adopter candidates of our beta machines and materials; (4) having established collaboration with a local biotechnology company and started pilot studies to apply our bioprinting platform technology in the tissue engineering and regenerative medicine field.</p> <p>From a broader perspective, the rapid 3D bioprinting system developed in this project leads to a revolutionary platform technology for the 3D bioprinting industry. Its novel design and architecture enable scalable high-throughput bioprinting with superior printing resolution and speed compared to the conventional nozzle-based 3D printers. The green chemistry used for synthesizing the new BPA-free polycarbonate materials inspires new synthesis pathways for other materials to eliminate the hazardous materials and products to improve human health and the environment. The 3D printing platform combined with a new class of biomaterials offers great opportunities in engineering novel biomedical devices and biological tissues for various applications such as drug screening, regenerative medicine, and diagnostics, which will ultimately lead to improved healthcare and environment that benefits the society.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Wei&nbsp;Zhu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project is to develop a rapid 3D printing system and a new class of photopolymerizable polycarbonates  that is free of bisphenol A (BPA) to create customizable 3D printed cell/tissue culture platforms. Th research activities include: (1) expanding the reagent library and investigating the green chemistry synthesis routes for 3D printable BPA free polycarbonates; (2) characterizing the material properties of the new BPA free polycarbonates, including the mechanical, optical, thermal, chemical, and biological properties; (3) developing a rapid 3D optical printing platform and optimize the 3D printing process with the new BPA free polycarbonates; (4) 3D printing cell/tissue culture devices with the BPA free polycarbonates and evaluating the cell/tissue growth on these devices.  This work has led to significant outcomes including: (1) A green chemistry synthesis route has been developed to synthesize BPA free polycarbonates, which eliminates the hazardous impacts of BPA on human health and the environment. (2) A new class of BPA free polycarbonates with controllable material properties (i.e. mechanical, thermal, optical, and biological properties) has been synthesized for various needs in the biomedical fields. The new BPA free polycarbonates successfully overcame the small molecular absorption problem associated with polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS). Moreover, these new polycarbonates are 3D printable with our rapid optical 3D printer, which enables the fabrication of customized biomedical devices on demand. (3) A rapid optical 3D printing platform has been developed with superior printing resolution, speed, flexibility, and scalability compared to the conventional nozzle-based 3D printers. Our 3D printing platform can not only work with our new polycarbonate inks, but also print with various other biomaterials and cells to construct biomedical devices and biological tissues. (4) Customizable microwell arrays have been 3D printed with the BPA free polycarbonates for high-throughput culture of 3D cell spheroids or organoids. High cell viability on our 3D printed polycarbonate devices were achieved, indicating the excellent biocompatibility of our material and fabrication process. Moreover, a surface modification method has been developed to modify the hydrophobicity of the 3D printed polycarbonate devices for optimal performance in assisting the organoid formation.  Ongoing commercialization efforts include: (1) having interviewed potential customers from the pharmaceutical industry, biotechnology companies, hospitals, and research institutes to identify the minimum viable product and the beachhead market; (2) having attended major conferences to promote our company and find collaborations for our platform technology; (3) having discovered some early adopter candidates of our beta machines and materials; (4) having established collaboration with a local biotechnology company and started pilot studies to apply our bioprinting platform technology in the tissue engineering and regenerative medicine field.  From a broader perspective, the rapid 3D bioprinting system developed in this project leads to a revolutionary platform technology for the 3D bioprinting industry. Its novel design and architecture enable scalable high-throughput bioprinting with superior printing resolution and speed compared to the conventional nozzle-based 3D printers. The green chemistry used for synthesizing the new BPA-free polycarbonate materials inspires new synthesis pathways for other materials to eliminate the hazardous materials and products to improve human health and the environment. The 3D printing platform combined with a new class of biomaterials offers great opportunities in engineering novel biomedical devices and biological tissues for various applications such as drug screening, regenerative medicine, and diagnostics, which will ultimately lead to improved healthcare and environment that benefits the society.          Last Modified: 07/03/2019       Submitted by: Wei Zhu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
