<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  IoT System for Small Arms Detection and Response</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rick Schwerdtfeger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project views an IoT firearms detection system in the lens of the military due to their immediate need of such a device and associated data. In addition, a foothold in the military will allow for and influence the adoption in downstream markets such as private security and law enforcement who have already expressed interest in piloting and adopting this technology once fully developed. However, the broader goal and impact of this system more importantly grants the potential to save lives. Whether this system will be used in the military, law enforcement, or private citizens in cases of home and self defense, successful implementation and commercialization of the first firearms detection system will grant the capabilities to objectively monitor and leverage firearm usage data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project aims to research, develop, and commercialize an integrated IoT system dedicated to detecting and processing small arms firearm discharges. The challenge in achieving the goals of this project is two-fold: one to create an IoT system that satisfies the stringent and high standards of the customer and two, to create value within the data collected by these IoT sensors. The proposed research and development covers the creation of a prototype device as well as generating a roadmap based on product and user feedback towards effective use of the data to ensure commercial success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1819949</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Deng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Deng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>williamdeng@armaments.us</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2063954868</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000752029</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Armaments Research Company, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Bethesda</CityName>
<ZipCode>208162608</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2063954868</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6422 Broad St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042252925</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARMAMENTS RESEARCH COMPANY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Armaments Research Company LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981182516</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5231 57th Ave S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through the support of an NSF SBIR Phase I Grant, Armaments Research Company, Inc (ARC) has been successful in creating and validating the core functionality of a cost-effective firearms usage monitoring system with law enforcement as the intended customer.</p> <p>Law enforcement personnel in the United States are often faced with staffing shortages, resulting in symptoms such as increased response times, decreased morale, and increased stress. Technology has supplied non-lethal options such as tasers and recording capabilities for after action reviews through body cameras but has had little impact in decreasing the cognitive burden and workload on officers. Not only can these technologies be ineffective, the latest technological push, body cameras,&nbsp;have yet to provide real-time feedback to protect and safeguard officers and parties involved. Officers involved in dangerous situations are often unable to radio in for help or medical assistance. Seconds and minutes go by in a rapidly evolving situation. Officers are expected and required to not only turn on their body cameras but also radio in the details, both actions are unnatural and unintuitive. Technological innovation is much needed to help evolve the ways in which law enforcement can effectively respond to developing situations, particularly where a firearm may be used.</p> <p>The ARC system consists of Internet of Things (IoT) sensors embedded into ruggedized housing that replaces or augments existing firearm grips without influencing the firing mechanism. The system does not prevent discharges but allows for the collection and transmission of real time data on firearm usage and discharges through natural behavior. The data collected can be used to provide real time situational awareness around deployed firearms and decrease response times for first responders and medical teams in the event that a firearm is used.</p> <p>During the period of performance for the SBIR Phase I Grant, ARC has made significant strides in understanding and classifying discharges and firearm activity through machine learning as well as iterating proof of concept hardware and software designs based on customer feedback. Through the support of NSF, ARC has garnered the interest of key stakeholders within law enforcement and have identified key pilots for follow-on projects with law enforcement agencies across the country.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2019<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;Deng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through the support of an NSF SBIR Phase I Grant, Armaments Research Company, Inc (ARC) has been successful in creating and validating the core functionality of a cost-effective firearms usage monitoring system with law enforcement as the intended customer.  Law enforcement personnel in the United States are often faced with staffing shortages, resulting in symptoms such as increased response times, decreased morale, and increased stress. Technology has supplied non-lethal options such as tasers and recording capabilities for after action reviews through body cameras but has had little impact in decreasing the cognitive burden and workload on officers. Not only can these technologies be ineffective, the latest technological push, body cameras, have yet to provide real-time feedback to protect and safeguard officers and parties involved. Officers involved in dangerous situations are often unable to radio in for help or medical assistance. Seconds and minutes go by in a rapidly evolving situation. Officers are expected and required to not only turn on their body cameras but also radio in the details, both actions are unnatural and unintuitive. Technological innovation is much needed to help evolve the ways in which law enforcement can effectively respond to developing situations, particularly where a firearm may be used.  The ARC system consists of Internet of Things (IoT) sensors embedded into ruggedized housing that replaces or augments existing firearm grips without influencing the firing mechanism. The system does not prevent discharges but allows for the collection and transmission of real time data on firearm usage and discharges through natural behavior. The data collected can be used to provide real time situational awareness around deployed firearms and decrease response times for first responders and medical teams in the event that a firearm is used.  During the period of performance for the SBIR Phase I Grant, ARC has made significant strides in understanding and classifying discharges and firearm activity through machine learning as well as iterating proof of concept hardware and software designs based on customer feedback. Through the support of NSF, ARC has garnered the interest of key stakeholders within law enforcement and have identified key pilots for follow-on projects with law enforcement agencies across the country.          Last Modified: 06/12/2019       Submitted by: William Deng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
