<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Digital Oil Level Indicator Feasibility Study</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224779.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224779</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rick Schwerdtfeger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to provide the agriculture market a long-term solution to the problem of premature wear on components from oil leaks  by digitally monitoring oil levels in combines. The proposed product could be adapted to many industries including agriculture, mining, construction, marine water craft, chemical storage, military vehicles, and water storage. The proposed product will preemptively warn equipment operators of low lubrication levels thereby saving customers money from repairs or replacement of new systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will address the need of digitally monitoring oil lubrication levels while producing a highly accurate measurement in real-time. The solution will be non-contacting unlike current solutions that provide a single low-level alarm or rely on manual checks. The prototype will be put in a simulated as well as real-time environment to investigate endurance, accuracy, stability, longevity, reliability and ease of installation. Objectives include: (1) Find a solution/configuration to accurately monitor rapid level changes; (2) Verify the hardware can withstand harsh conditions (extreme temperatures, high vibration); (3) Software testing; and (4) Analyze different reservoirs to see how the product can be easily mounted.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1820266</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dikeman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allan Dikeman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>learnedengineering@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3092214231</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000764400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Digital Dipstick Company</Name>
<CityName>Tremont</CityName>
<ZipCode>615689252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3092214231</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>600 S Sampson St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080963829</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DIGITAL DIPSTICK COMPANY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Digital Dipstick Company]]></Name>
<CityName>Tremont</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>615689252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 S Sampson St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~224779</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The major goal of this project was to validate to ability to monitor oil levels with LiDAR. This would include three key objectives which were; identifying appropriate hardware, concept research and design and complete prototype development builds.</span></p> <p><span>Hardware:<br /> The company research the proper hardware to be used in the prototype. This included a Particle Electron that could connect to 3G telecommunications in order to provide IoT services, a housing for sensor and the Electron and a LiDAR sensor.</span></p> <p><span>Concept Research and Design:<br /> The company worked with an engineering firm, Integris, to expand software off the companies preexisting software design. A Gantt chart with project deadlines and requirements was followed throughout the entire project. </span></p> <p><span>Prototype Development and Build:<br /> The final assembly utilized the machines existing reservoir caps modified with the LiDAR sensors installed inside them. The sensor cap for the hydraulic oil was success in monitoring the level.</span></p> <p><span>Hardware:<br /> A 3D printed insert was created for the Electron to hold the supporting components. The supporting components were a battery, LCD screen, antenna and connectors. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The company was involved in two major activities, development of the base software and field testing. The software was built to communicate with the LiDAR sensor to provide a level readout for the operator. The software including alerts if a level went below the manufactures threshold. The company installed the prototypes onto three machines to test in filed conditions. This data was critical in discovering any issues before bringing the product to market.</span></p> <p><span>After in field testing was completed the company concluded that the technology can provide an accurate level monitoring system. The LiDAR sensor provides the ability to quickly warn operators when an oil leak is detected. Perhaps the most valuable data point was in the market research. Through customer discovery&rsquo;s the company learned that this is indeed a pain point with farmers. </span></p> <p><span>The product will have a likely impact on equipment that uses oil lubrication. The ability to monitor the level will ensure a safe operation. Leaks that would normally cause premature wear or catastrophic failures will be avoided. The data of oil consumption will be highly valuable for equipment manufacturers. Oil consumption data for engines is a good indication on health and longevity. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Allan&nbsp;Dikeman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project was to validate to ability to monitor oil levels with LiDAR. This would include three key objectives which were; identifying appropriate hardware, concept research and design and complete prototype development builds.  Hardware:  The company research the proper hardware to be used in the prototype. This included a Particle Electron that could connect to 3G telecommunications in order to provide IoT services, a housing for sensor and the Electron and a LiDAR sensor.  Concept Research and Design:  The company worked with an engineering firm, Integris, to expand software off the companies preexisting software design. A Gantt chart with project deadlines and requirements was followed throughout the entire project.   Prototype Development and Build:  The final assembly utilized the machines existing reservoir caps modified with the LiDAR sensors installed inside them. The sensor cap for the hydraulic oil was success in monitoring the level.  Hardware:  A 3D printed insert was created for the Electron to hold the supporting components. The supporting components were a battery, LCD screen, antenna and connectors.      The company was involved in two major activities, development of the base software and field testing. The software was built to communicate with the LiDAR sensor to provide a level readout for the operator. The software including alerts if a level went below the manufactures threshold. The company installed the prototypes onto three machines to test in filed conditions. This data was critical in discovering any issues before bringing the product to market.  After in field testing was completed the company concluded that the technology can provide an accurate level monitoring system. The LiDAR sensor provides the ability to quickly warn operators when an oil leak is detected. Perhaps the most valuable data point was in the market research. Through customer discovery?s the company learned that this is indeed a pain point with farmers.   The product will have a likely impact on equipment that uses oil lubrication. The ability to monitor the level will ensure a safe operation. Leaks that would normally cause premature wear or catastrophic failures will be avoided. The data of oil consumption will be highly valuable for equipment manufacturers. Oil consumption data for engines is a good indication on health and longevity.           Last Modified: 12/12/2018       Submitted by: Allan Dikeman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
