<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: The Role of Writing in Tracing Social Interaction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12594.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12594</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Writing is more than a visual medium for communicating information - it is also a cultural practice that must be understood in context. Researchers studying the transmission or spread of cultural practices in the ancient past rely largely on material and physical remains. Archaeology is especially well-suited to address these questions because it combines a critical engagement with material culture with a concern with change and interaction over time and space. In this context, writing presents an ideal case for exploring cultural transmission because of the material traces that it leaves and because its physical aspects are often ignored at the expense of its more abstract message. Mallory Matsumoto (Brown University) will undertake dissertation research to understand the production and transmission of writing. In addition to fostering interdisciplinary collaboration between archaeology, epigraphy, and anthropology, this work will demonstrate how interaction in one cultural context may affect another, an issue relevant to understanding both the past and the present. In addition to contributing to current understanding of pre-Columbian Maya civilization, the results will be especially relevant to contemporary Maya communities given their current efforts revive the hieroglyphic script as a symbol of identity and cultural heritage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This dissertation research will examine if and how the networks through which writing is transmitted overlap with other contexts of cultural exchange. Its case study will be the ancient Maya hieroglyphic writing system, which was used for over 1500 years in areas of what are now Mexico, Guatemala, Belize, and Honduras. Critically, the writing system was shared among pre-Columbian Maya communities who were not only separated by space and time, but also were never politically unified. Although the decipherment of Maya hieroglyphs has advanced significantly in recent decades, scholars still do not understand how the writing system developed and spread. The investigator will analyze the form of Maya inscriptions and the hieroglyphs they contain to reconstruct which settlements were sharing which writing techniques, how these patterns changed over time, and how they related to interactions in other contexts like politics, warfare, or trade.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1821867</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Houston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Houston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Stephen_Houston@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4019548375</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000503434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mallory</FirstName>
<LastName>Matsumoto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mallory Matsumoto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mallory_matsumoto@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342277939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000748969</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~12594</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For her dissertation research, co-PI Mallory Matsumoto (Brown University) undertook documentation and analysis of ancient Maya hieroglyphic inscriptions from Mexico, Guatemala, Belize, and Honduras. The hieroglyphic script was shared for over 1500 years among pre-Columbian Maya communities who were not only separated by space and time, but also were never politically unified. Scholars are now able to read most Maya hieroglyphic texts, but still do not understand how the writing system developed and spread.</p> <p>Based on photographs, drawings, and 3D images obtained during visits to sites, museums, and archives, the investigator examined the form of form of Maya inscriptions and their hieroglyphs to reconstruct which settlements were sharing which writing techniques, how these patterns changed over time, and how they related to interactions in other social contexts, especially dynastic politics.&nbsp;This interdisciplinary research between archaeology, epigraphy, and anthropology will demonstrate the role of cultural transmission in facilitating relations within and across political boundaries and the potential for identifying these phenomena in the past.&nbsp;</p> <p>In museums and storage facilities in Mexico and Guatemala where the co-PI collaborated with local partners to photograph hieroglyphic inscriptions, copies of images created during documentation were distributed to these partners before departure.&nbsp;In the year following completion of the NSF DDRIG award period, the co-PI will complete analysis of the documented inscriptions and compile the results in the form of a dissertation on the production and transmission of writing in the pre-Columbian Maya region.&nbsp;Following completion of the dissertation, she will make the results&nbsp;publicly available through peer-reviewed publications and storage in online, open-access repositories. She will also disseminate the research to academics and interested publics through presentations in the United States and Latin America.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Mallory&nbsp;Matsumoto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For her dissertation research, co-PI Mallory Matsumoto (Brown University) undertook documentation and analysis of ancient Maya hieroglyphic inscriptions from Mexico, Guatemala, Belize, and Honduras. The hieroglyphic script was shared for over 1500 years among pre-Columbian Maya communities who were not only separated by space and time, but also were never politically unified. Scholars are now able to read most Maya hieroglyphic texts, but still do not understand how the writing system developed and spread.  Based on photographs, drawings, and 3D images obtained during visits to sites, museums, and archives, the investigator examined the form of form of Maya inscriptions and their hieroglyphs to reconstruct which settlements were sharing which writing techniques, how these patterns changed over time, and how they related to interactions in other social contexts, especially dynastic politics. This interdisciplinary research between archaeology, epigraphy, and anthropology will demonstrate the role of cultural transmission in facilitating relations within and across political boundaries and the potential for identifying these phenomena in the past.   In museums and storage facilities in Mexico and Guatemala where the co-PI collaborated with local partners to photograph hieroglyphic inscriptions, copies of images created during documentation were distributed to these partners before departure. In the year following completion of the NSF DDRIG award period, the co-PI will complete analysis of the documented inscriptions and compile the results in the form of a dissertation on the production and transmission of writing in the pre-Columbian Maya region. Following completion of the dissertation, she will make the results publicly available through peer-reviewed publications and storage in online, open-access repositories. She will also disseminate the research to academics and interested publics through presentations in the United States and Latin America.          Last Modified: 05/31/2020       Submitted by: Mallory Matsumoto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
