<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning IUCRC at The University of Arkansas:  Center for Infrastructure Trustworthiness in Energy Systems (CITES)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Perhaps more than any other piece of critical infrastructure, today's power delivery systems are critical to the welfare of the country and its citizens. All other systems, from agriculture, transportation, and manufacturing to telecommunications are dependent on safe, reliable delivery of power. Faulty systems, as in the case of the northeastern US failures of 1965, environmental factors, as in the northeastern US failures of 2003, physical attacks, as in the 2013 northern California outages, or cyber attacks, as in the 2015 attacks in Ukraine, have all led to human suffering and loss of productivity as the result of this interdependence. The Center for Infrastructure Trustworthiness in Energy Systems (CITES) IUCRC will enable our nation to limit impact of these cyber-physical attacks on national security by providing capabilities that: seek to prevent such attacks, rapidly detect attacks that do occur, enable robust infrastructure that continues to operate in the presence of such attacks, and quickly restore the nation's infrastructure after attack.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Historically, as the systems that controlled energy delivery systems (EDS) became more complex, their components became increasingly interconnected. Systems originally intended for closed, serial systems were exposed to adversarial environments without state-of-the-art designs for cybersecurity; merely connecting to such services was often enough to exert complete control over the processes they oversee. While the modern EDS designs are fully aware of these limitations, after substantial academic research and industry infrastructure investment, the legacy of such systems persists. CITES seeks to address these legacy implications through a unique academic and industry partnership aimed at: (i) ensuring that legacy systems and providers continue to learn from the nascent science of cybersecurity and failures and improvements in other domains; and (ii) addressing the unique nature of threats to the critical EDS infrastructure. These dual goals require tightly integrated research and industry partnerships to solve not only the problems as they exist today, but to insure the continued reliability of our nation's EDS infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1822152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Homer</FirstName>
<LastName>Mantooth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Homer A Mantooth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mantooth@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795754838</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000355582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qinghua</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qinghua Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>qinghual@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795756416</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1125 W. Maple Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[316 Administration Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191429745</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055600001</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~14999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project was to support development and execution of a planning meeting that introduced the theme of the IUCRC, named Center for Infrastructure Trustworthiness in Energy Systems (CITES), to potential industry members. A goal was to assess the level of interest in such an IUCRC and collect input on the technical directions of most interest to attendees.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, the University of Arkansas worked in collaboration with University of Illinois to strategically plan the center in aspects such as center organization, leadership, administration and funding management. They attended the very helpful Bootcamp organized by NSF, and conducted a set of interviews with many organizations in the energy sector to discover their needs for such an IUCRC center and determine our value proposition. The held the planning meeting in April 2019 at Champaign, IL, which was attended by around 20 industry organizations. The meeting was comprised of an overview of CITES, NSF presentation on the IUCRC program, presentations of six potential projects, and an industry-led discussion on areas of research interest and need.&nbsp;</p> <p>Below is a summary of key outcomes.&nbsp; 1)&nbsp;The Center has obtained strong financial commitment interest from the industry. About 10 organizations have orally stated that they will join the center if this center is founded. They represent a wide variety of stakeholders in the energy sector, including electric utilities, independent system operators, electric cooperatives, research institutes, device vendors, and software vendors.&nbsp; 2) The Center received varying degrees of support for most of the projects presented in the planning meeting, and discussions about these presentations led to refinement in the researchers' notion of what a project would entail. The industry-led discussions also identified other research directions of interest and need not represented by the six presentations. Integrating all the industry feedback, the team has identified an initial set of research areas that are of strong interest to the industry, and plans to explore these areas. &nbsp;3) The Center has defined its Value Proposition that covers a wide range of values to industry members such as student hiring, cybersecurity tools, and community building.&nbsp; 4) The Center has defined its membership structure that includes Full Member, Associate Member, Small-Business Member, and In-Kind Member, and also defined the tiered benefits for them.&nbsp; 5) The Center has defined its leadership structure and management strategies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Qinghua&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project was to support development and execution of a planning meeting that introduced the theme of the IUCRC, named Center for Infrastructure Trustworthiness in Energy Systems (CITES), to potential industry members. A goal was to assess the level of interest in such an IUCRC and collect input on the technical directions of most interest to attendees.   In this project, the University of Arkansas worked in collaboration with University of Illinois to strategically plan the center in aspects such as center organization, leadership, administration and funding management. They attended the very helpful Bootcamp organized by NSF, and conducted a set of interviews with many organizations in the energy sector to discover their needs for such an IUCRC center and determine our value proposition. The held the planning meeting in April 2019 at Champaign, IL, which was attended by around 20 industry organizations. The meeting was comprised of an overview of CITES, NSF presentation on the IUCRC program, presentations of six potential projects, and an industry-led discussion on areas of research interest and need.   Below is a summary of key outcomes.  1) The Center has obtained strong financial commitment interest from the industry. About 10 organizations have orally stated that they will join the center if this center is founded. They represent a wide variety of stakeholders in the energy sector, including electric utilities, independent system operators, electric cooperatives, research institutes, device vendors, and software vendors.  2) The Center received varying degrees of support for most of the projects presented in the planning meeting, and discussions about these presentations led to refinement in the researchers' notion of what a project would entail. The industry-led discussions also identified other research directions of interest and need not represented by the six presentations. Integrating all the industry feedback, the team has identified an initial set of research areas that are of strong interest to the industry, and plans to explore these areas.  3) The Center has defined its Value Proposition that covers a wide range of values to industry members such as student hiring, cybersecurity tools, and community building.  4) The Center has defined its membership structure that includes Full Member, Associate Member, Small-Business Member, and In-Kind Member, and also defined the tiered benefits for them.  5) The Center has defined its leadership structure and management strategies.          Last Modified: 12/07/2019       Submitted by: Qinghua Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
