<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning IUCRC Arizona State University: Center for Networked Embedded, Smart and Trusted Things NESTT</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Arizona State University will collaborate with The University of Arizona, University of Southern California, Southern Illinois University Carbondale and the University of Connecticut to plan for the formation of a new Industry University Cooperative Research Center (IUCRC), called Center for Networked Embedded, Smart and Trusted Things (NESTT).  Companies from a wide spectrum of industries will be recruited and will work jointly with faculty to create a portfolio of industry-ranked, multi-disciplinary research projects to develop innovative solutions to fundamental technological and societal challenges posed by Internet of Things (IoT). The outcome will be a proposal to establish NESTT as an IUCRC. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ASU will work with its partners to organize workshops involving industry leaders and academic researchers to draft the research agenda for NESTT, aimed at accelerating IoT technology development and transfer to industry, and make opportunities from the IoT equitable, safe and secure for all. ASU expertise will include edge and Fog computing; safe and secure cyber-physical systems; machine learning, data analytics; trustworthy, networked embedded systems; robotics and industrial IoT; smart cities and transportation systems; sensors and wearable electronics; IoT governance, technology-related law and ethics, and business models. NESTT at ASU will further the participation of underrepresented students in STEM disciplines.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IoT will become the foundational technology for every major industry.  NESTT?s technological innovations and holistic multi-disciplinary design will lower the barriers to the adoption IoT technologies which will accelerate the delivery of significant economic, societal and environmental returns. The enormous wealth of data generated from such IoT systems will also lead to new discoveries and inventions in many scientific disciplines as scientific communities further embrace data-driven research.  The planning for NESTT will include working with industry partners to develop innovative ways for recruiting (in industry and academia) underrepresented students in STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The agenda and documentation of activities for the NESTT IUCRC planning meetings will be made available on ASU's website for the Center for Embedded Systems (https://embedded.asu.edu ). It will be maintained until the establishment of NESTT, and then merged with the NESTT site.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1822169</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarma</FirstName>
<LastName>Vrudhula</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarma K Vrudhula</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vrudhula@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807274152</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000124788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~14999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This is the outcomes report for the planning grant to establish a new IUCRC named "Center for Network-Embedded, Smart and Safe Things".&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Challenge:</strong> The Internet of Things (IoT) refers to the digitization of the world -- the process of embedding microelectronic devices with integrated sensing, computing, actuation and communication functions in almost any object on the planet. By 2025, it is expected that 20B to 30B devices will be deployed. Every human and every business in the world will be impacted as devices come to life &ndash; in ways increasingly more complex and personal than asking Alexa to play your favorite song or looking to your iWatch to track your heart rate and steps. As devices access more personal data and will have the ability to act on the data, difficult challenges in technology, in business, and on society must be addressed.</p> <p>On the technology front, machine learning and data analytics are expected to play a central role in the IoT. This is a wide-open research area that involves distributed, real-time computations that occur over a large and dynamically changing environment. The hardware and software components for the IoT will be created and owned by different companies, requiring sharing of data, raising issues of how to monetize the technology, liability, data ownership, IP ownership, ensuring equitable benefits of the technology, regulatory mechanisms to ensure privacy, security, and safety, and standardization to enable interoperability and transparency, and many other unforeseen consequences of the IoT. For society at large, keeping users and data safe will be of the utmost concern.</p> <p>The scale of the IoT and the extent of its impact evokes a mixture of euphoria and alarm because many intuitively realize that technology solutions alone, ignoring law, business and societal impact, may not only be useless but may in many cases, may be harmful to society.</p> <p><strong>Solution:</strong> To address these challenges, Arizona State University (ASU), in partnership with the Southern Illinois University Carbondale (SIUC), the University of Southern California (USC), the University of Arizona (UA) and the University of Connecticut (UConn) propose to establish a new multi-university research center, named NESST, which stands for Networked-Embedded, Smart and Safe Things. During this planning grant, the universities hosted a workshop to gain input from industry on the viability of the NESST concept, to further define NESST&rsquo;s scope, and plan the center&rsquo;s mission and structure.</p> <p>Outcomes:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Hosted a successful workshop</strong>: The planning grant brought together industry representatives (50 representatives from 37 companies), faculty researchers (21 faculty from 5 universities), graduate students (10 from 5 universities), and the NSF (3 representatives). The group reviewed and evaluated 21 proposed research projects and engaged in lively discussions about the need for this type of center, research content areas, and their level of interest in joining the center. The presiding National Science Foundation project manager remarked that this was one of the best planning grant meetings he had seen, with strong backing of the universities, support team, and site and center leadership. He felt that this center is positioned well for success.</li> <li><strong>Gained proof of concept</strong>: Workshop attendees provided feedback on research topics and identified research priorities. While companies had different perceptions of the proposed research topics based on their own organizational priorities, most confirmed the important of NESST&rsquo;s mission and expressed interest in joining the center. Of particular importance was the intellectual merit of the center&rsquo;s work, as it strives to provide holistic solutions from the start by going beyond the traditional industry-university projects that involve only science and engineering, and enabling, to the maximum extent possible and where appropriate, collaboration between and science and engineering with law, business, societal impact of technology, ethics, sustainability, and industrial design. Traditional engineering project deliverables will now include legal opinions, business models, ethical uses, studies of societal and environmental impact, and so on.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Created center plan:&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong>In preparation for the workshop, the 5 participating universities spent 8 months strategizing, evaluating priorities and defining research, and making plans for the center. After solidifying this during the industry workshop the NESST&rsquo;s mission and operations plan was finalized and will be detailed in a full proposal. In brief, NESST will work to make things smarter, safer, and universally useful. It will do this by enabling hardware and software systems to sense, collect, analyze, communicate and/or control their environments.&nbsp; Industry-led research projects conducted at NESST&rsquo;s universities engage the world&rsquo;s best minds in solving fundamental IoT engineering problems, untangling the legal conundrums of IoT, and improving business operations. Through this collaboration, NESST will also produce a skilled workforce that is trained to build even smarter and safer things for the future.</li> </ol><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Sarma&nbsp;K&nbsp;Vrudhula</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This is the outcomes report for the planning grant to establish a new IUCRC named "Center for Network-Embedded, Smart and Safe Things".    Challenge: The Internet of Things (IoT) refers to the digitization of the world -- the process of embedding microelectronic devices with integrated sensing, computing, actuation and communication functions in almost any object on the planet. By 2025, it is expected that 20B to 30B devices will be deployed. Every human and every business in the world will be impacted as devices come to life &ndash; in ways increasingly more complex and personal than asking Alexa to play your favorite song or looking to your iWatch to track your heart rate and steps. As devices access more personal data and will have the ability to act on the data, difficult challenges in technology, in business, and on society must be addressed.  On the technology front, machine learning and data analytics are expected to play a central role in the IoT. This is a wide-open research area that involves distributed, real-time computations that occur over a large and dynamically changing environment. The hardware and software components for the IoT will be created and owned by different companies, requiring sharing of data, raising issues of how to monetize the technology, liability, data ownership, IP ownership, ensuring equitable benefits of the technology, regulatory mechanisms to ensure privacy, security, and safety, and standardization to enable interoperability and transparency, and many other unforeseen consequences of the IoT. For society at large, keeping users and data safe will be of the utmost concern.  The scale of the IoT and the extent of its impact evokes a mixture of euphoria and alarm because many intuitively realize that technology solutions alone, ignoring law, business and societal impact, may not only be useless but may in many cases, may be harmful to society.  Solution: To address these challenges, Arizona State University (ASU), in partnership with the Southern Illinois University Carbondale (SIUC), the University of Southern California (USC), the University of Arizona (UA) and the University of Connecticut (UConn) propose to establish a new multi-university research center, named NESST, which stands for Networked-Embedded, Smart and Safe Things. During this planning grant, the universities hosted a workshop to gain input from industry on the viability of the NESST concept, to further define NESST’s scope, and plan the center’s mission and structure.  Outcomes:  Hosted a successful workshop: The planning grant brought together industry representatives (50 representatives from 37 companies), faculty researchers (21 faculty from 5 universities), graduate students (10 from 5 universities), and the NSF (3 representatives). The group reviewed and evaluated 21 proposed research projects and engaged in lively discussions about the need for this type of center, research content areas, and their level of interest in joining the center. The presiding National Science Foundation project manager remarked that this was one of the best planning grant meetings he had seen, with strong backing of the universities, support team, and site and center leadership. He felt that this center is positioned well for success. Gained proof of concept: Workshop attendees provided feedback on research topics and identified research priorities. While companies had different perceptions of the proposed research topics based on their own organizational priorities, most confirmed the important of NESST’s mission and expressed interest in joining the center. Of particular importance was the intellectual merit of the center’s work, as it strives to provide holistic solutions from the start by going beyond the traditional industry-university projects that involve only science and engineering, and enabling, to the maximum extent possible and where appropriate, collaboration between and science and engineering with law, business, societal impact of technology, ethics, sustainability, and industrial design. Traditional engineering project deliverables will now include legal opinions, business models, ethical uses, studies of societal and environmental impact, and so on.   Created center plan:  In preparation for the workshop, the 5 participating universities spent 8 months strategizing, evaluating priorities and defining research, and making plans for the center. After solidifying this during the industry workshop the NESST’s mission and operations plan was finalized and will be detailed in a full proposal. In brief, NESST will work to make things smarter, safer, and universally useful. It will do this by enabling hardware and software systems to sense, collect, analyze, communicate and/or control their environments.  Industry-led research projects conducted at NESST’s universities engage the world’s best minds in solving fundamental IoT engineering problems, untangling the legal conundrums of IoT, and improving business operations. Through this collaboration, NESST will also produce a skilled workforce that is trained to build even smarter and safer things for the future.        Last Modified: 02/03/2020       Submitted by: Sarma K Vrudhula]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
