<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nanophotonics of RE/DNA/nanotube materials: From bio-sensing-on-chip to live stem cell measurements</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>109517.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>109517</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>plane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract Title: Fundamental physics and biosensing applications of composite fluorescent nanomaterials rare-earths combined with DNA-enclosed carbon nanotubes&lt;br/&gt;Nontechnical:&lt;br/&gt;Nanomaterials have influenced drastically several aspects of modern life, one of those is associated with their power in medicine and health care. This research involves rare-earth based materials due to their excellent fluorescence rare earths have already found a significant application niche in lighting, solar cells, sensors, biological and medical diagnostics and imaging. The bioimaging applications will be further advanced in this project. It is a continuation of the previous study in which rare-earths were combined with a unique nanocarbon material, so called single-wall nanotubes. Nanotubes by themselves has been already used in various miniaturized sensors, which are so extremely small that can be placed on a fabric thread. Most recently this group proposed using nanotubes enclosed in the DNA for studying live cells and has obtained promising results. It has been already demonstrated how nanomaterials could improve sensing capabilities of rare-earths. New project will extend this study and focus on nanotubes as tiny antennas to magnify the optical signals received by rare-earths. Due to small (nanometer) scale of these optical elements they can penetrate inside the cells and transmit the biologically relevant information from there, potentially improving our knowledge about how cells work as building blocks of organisms and helping medicine and health sciences in solving their current problems. This research is accompanied by a vigorous outreach program, aimed both on the local community and STEM students nationwide.&lt;br/&gt;Technical:&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on developing and studying materials for bioimaging based on the rare-earth complexes with single-wall nanotubes and single strand DNA. Significance of this research is in developing a new biosensing material. Since single-wall nanotubes have diameters of only a few nanometers, they are comparable to many biological macromolecules such as enzymes, antibodies, DNA plasmids, etc. and may interact with intracellular environment. This makes them increasingly relevant for new opportunities in biomedical research and applications. Though at early stage, this project enlighten us about how the living organisms, at the cell level, may be influenced by new modern nanomaterials (nanotubes) upon ingestion. Using optical non-destructing characterization the fate of the nanotubes inside the cells has been already determined on the previous stage of the project. In the course of new project the team will work on intertwined theoretical and experimental tasks, including experimental optical characterization and theory of near-field electromagnetic modes in the hybrid materials of nanotubes-DNA-rare-earth-ions; exploring performance of these nanomaterials for bio-sensing applications in photonic-crystals and inside bio-mimetic hydrogels; studying the role of hotspots in nanotube materials and their influence on the photoluminescence of rare-earth ions and/or DNA; experimental studies of modulation of optical response of photonic crystals  incorporating biosensing materials inside its lattice; application of these nanomaterials inside micro-fluidics sensing system and to studying in vitro neural stem cell. A series of samples will be studied, prepared at Lehigh University as well as at University of Utah, LANL and NIST via the collaboration links. A diverse program for dissemination of those results involves research advising and teaching at Lehigh, outreach at local schools (Palisades High School, Moravian Academy), participation in exhibition at a school children development National facility (the DaVinci Discovery Center), STEM enhancement programs via local Community Colleges (NCCC, LCTI and LCCC) and local Kutztown University, REU and GAAN programs within the Physics Department.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1822736</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Slava</FirstName>
<LastName>Rotkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Slava V Rotkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rotkin@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148633087</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000307321</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~109517</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Among nanomaterials, one- and two-dimensional (rod-like and sheet-like) materials are perspective for biotechnology applications. In this project 2D graphene (atomically thin layer made of carbon atoms) and 1D nanotubes (graphene scrolled in tiny cylinder) were studied. Nanotubes were wrapped with nucleic acids (DNA and RNA) such that these functional nanomaterials can be internalized inside living cells. New optical methods were developed to resolve challenge of detecting individual particles with very small dimensions inside the cells.</p> <p>When penetrating the cells, nanomaterials produce strong enough optical signal which makes them attractive for imaging and biosensing. Nanotubes functionalized with artificial DNA were shown to induce biological processes in (mouse) stem cells, changing the fate of conversion of stem cells in developed neurons. Potentially, this may lead to using these nanomaterials for tissue engineering.</p> <p>Advanced theoretical methods were developed to describe the optical response of nanomaterials. While rod-like nanotubes were shown to behave, under specific conditions, like nanoscale antennas and strongly enhance optical response of the dyes (rare earth ions in this case). The sheet like structures of graphene possess so called plasmonic waves, that propagate along atomically thin layers bearing information about the material.</p> <p>A large cohort of students, ranging from high-school interns to Ph.D. students, worked on sub-projects in this program, being introduced to STEM fields.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2019<br>      Modified by: Slava&nbsp;V&nbsp;Rotkin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572216970523_JMCB-cover-image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572216970523_JMCB-cover-image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Micro-Raman Imaging of nanotubes inside stem cells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572216970523_JMCB-cover-image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Micro-Raman Imaging of nanotubes inside stem cells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Raman imaging of DNA-wrapped single-wall carbon nanotubes inside neural stem cells?, back-cover for  Journal of Materials Chemistry B, the Carbon Nanostructures in Biology and Medicine themed issue, v.5 (32), Royal Society of Chemistry, (2017)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Image courtesy Tetyana Ignatova, Sabrina S. Jedlicka, Slava V. Rotkinand Nicolle R. Fuller, Sayo-Art LLC, designer.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Slava&nbsp;V&nbsp;Rotkin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Micro-Raman Imaging of nanotubes inside stem cells</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572217114910_micro-Raman-imaging-of-NT--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572217114910_micro-Raman-imaging-of-NT--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DNA functionalized NT as intra-cell sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572217114910_micro-Raman-imaging-of-NT--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DNA functionalized NT as intra-cell sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Concept of intra&#8208;cell sensor or delivery vector. (a) DNA&#8208;wrapped NT for complementary DNA attachment.  (b) Micro-Raman image of DNA:NT complexes (two, as shown in magnified view in inset.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Slava V. Rotkin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Slava&nbsp;V&nbsp;Rotkin</div> <div class="imageTitle">DNA functionalized NT as intra-cell sensor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572217362680_viability-of-stem-cells-to-nanomaterial--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572217362680_viability-of-stem-cells-to-nanomaterial--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Images of stem cell internalized with nanotubes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1822736/1822736_10376594_1572217362680_viability-of-stem-cells-to-nanomaterial--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Images of stem cell internalized with nanotubes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Confocal microscopy images of C17.2 cells: non-treated (a,c,e) and after 8 hour incubation with 50 ng/mL of NT (b,d,f). Cell were fixed and stained for: actin, nucleus (a,b), nestin (c,d), and tubulin (e,f). (g) Cell population during the 21 day cycle (5 day in inset).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Journal of Materials Chemistry B, the Carbon Nanostructures in Biology and Medicine themed issue, v.5 (32), Royal Society of Chemistry, (2017)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Slava&nbsp;V&nbsp;Rotkin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Images of stem cell internalized with nanotubes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Among nanomaterials, one- and two-dimensional (rod-like and sheet-like) materials are perspective for biotechnology applications. In this project 2D graphene (atomically thin layer made of carbon atoms) and 1D nanotubes (graphene scrolled in tiny cylinder) were studied. Nanotubes were wrapped with nucleic acids (DNA and RNA) such that these functional nanomaterials can be internalized inside living cells. New optical methods were developed to resolve challenge of detecting individual particles with very small dimensions inside the cells.  When penetrating the cells, nanomaterials produce strong enough optical signal which makes them attractive for imaging and biosensing. Nanotubes functionalized with artificial DNA were shown to induce biological processes in (mouse) stem cells, changing the fate of conversion of stem cells in developed neurons. Potentially, this may lead to using these nanomaterials for tissue engineering.  Advanced theoretical methods were developed to describe the optical response of nanomaterials. While rod-like nanotubes were shown to behave, under specific conditions, like nanoscale antennas and strongly enhance optical response of the dyes (rare earth ions in this case). The sheet like structures of graphene possess so called plasmonic waves, that propagate along atomically thin layers bearing information about the material.  A large cohort of students, ranging from high-school interns to Ph.D. students, worked on sub-projects in this program, being introduced to STEM fields.       Last Modified: 10/27/2019       Submitted by: Slava V Rotkin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
