<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2018 Shipboard Scientific Support Equipment: R/V Atlantic Explorer</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>13656.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>13656</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jholik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927711</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A request is made to fund shipboard scientific support equipment on the R/V Atlantic Explorer, a 168? general purpose research vessel owned and operated by Bermuda Institute of Ocean Science (BIOS) as part of the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System.  BIOS is a U.S. 501 (c) 3 and 509 (a) not-for-profit research and educational institution incorporated in the state of New York, and geographically located on the Island of Bermuda. The mission of the ship is to support funded science research throughout the Central Atlantic but specifically work in support of the Bermuda Atlantic Time-series (BATS) program. RV Atlantic Explorer had 120 days funded in 2017, all but 7 of which were for NSF. In 2018, the vessel is scheduled to sail 183 days with 178 (98%) of them funded by NSF. With this proposal, BIOS provides technical descriptions and rationale for the acquisition of the following Shipboard Scientific Support Equipment:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2 ea Furuno Radar Systems $84,471 &lt;br/&gt;34 ea Survival Suits $13,656 &lt;br/&gt;Tachometer $20,284 &lt;br/&gt;      $118,411 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under Merit Review Criterion 2 of the Proposal Guidelines (NSF 13-589). It provides infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF).  The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1823057</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bates</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas R Bates</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nick.bates@bios.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4412971880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000338553</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Quentin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Quentin Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>quentin.lewis@bios.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4412971880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000716980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Mathews</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas J Mathews</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nick.mathews@bios.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4412971880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000755035</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences (BIOS), Inc.</Name>
<CityName>St. George's    GE01</CityName>
<ZipCode/>
<PhoneNumber>4412971880</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>17 Biological Station</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Ferry Reach]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>Bermuda</CountryName>
<StateName/>
<StateCode/>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>875635161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BERMUDA INSTITUTE OF OCEAN SCIENCES (BIOS) INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences (BIOS), Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>St. George's    GE01</CityName>
<StateCode/>
<ZipCode/>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17 Biological Station]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>BD</CountryCode>
<CountryName>Bermuda</CountryName>
<StateName/>
<CountryFlag>0</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5416</Code>
<Text>SHIPBOARD SCIENTIFIC SUPP EQUI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~13656</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was made to the Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences  (BIOS), for safety equipment on the R/V ATLANTIC EXPLORER -  specifically, 34 new Immersion Suits. These suits were purchased and  installed aboard the ship, to replace old suits that were near the end  of their service life.</p> <p>The R/V ATLANTIC EXPLORER is one of the U.S research  vessels in the UNOLS Academic Research Fleet. The vessel is stationed in  Bermuda.</p> <p>The total funding awarded for this grant was $13,656, and not $118,411 as shown  on the research.gov webpage for this award. The other two items  orignally requested in the proposal, 2 Furuno radars and an EMI shaft  tachometer system, were not funded in this grant. The new radars have not yet been purchased, and the new EMI Shaft Tachometer System was purchased and installed during the January 20 - March 31, 2019 shipyard repair period. The shaft tachometer system was approved for purchase with operating funds from the 2019 Ship Operations grant; specifically, from the MOSA budget (Major Overhaul).</p> <p>Total cost for  the 34 new installed Immersion Suits was $11,898.32, and thus, $1,757.68  will remain with NSF after this award terminates. It is anticipated that a new proposal in CY 2020 will be made to purchase the new radars, as part of the ship's navigation equipment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/05/2019<br>      Modified by: Quentin&nbsp;Lewis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was made to the Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences  (BIOS), for safety equipment on the R/V ATLANTIC EXPLORER -  specifically, 34 new Immersion Suits. These suits were purchased and  installed aboard the ship, to replace old suits that were near the end  of their service life.  The R/V ATLANTIC EXPLORER is one of the U.S research  vessels in the UNOLS Academic Research Fleet. The vessel is stationed in  Bermuda.  The total funding awarded for this grant was $13,656, and not $118,411 as shown  on the research.gov webpage for this award. The other two items  orignally requested in the proposal, 2 Furuno radars and an EMI shaft  tachometer system, were not funded in this grant. The new radars have not yet been purchased, and the new EMI Shaft Tachometer System was purchased and installed during the January 20 - March 31, 2019 shipyard repair period. The shaft tachometer system was approved for purchase with operating funds from the 2019 Ship Operations grant; specifically, from the MOSA budget (Major Overhaul).  Total cost for  the 34 new installed Immersion Suits was $11,898.32, and thus, $1,757.68  will remain with NSF after this award terminates. It is anticipated that a new proposal in CY 2020 will be made to purchase the new radars, as part of the ship's navigation equipment.          Last Modified: 06/05/2019       Submitted by: Quentin Lewis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
