<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Temporality and Changing Parameters of Citizenship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19596.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19596</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>What does it mean to be a citizen in the contemporary world? Guest worker programs, refugee status, and other forms of protected but temporary legal status challenge traditional expectations of national belonging. Ambiguous populations can appear to fall through the cracks. This creates problems for policy makers who need to protect a nation's sovereignty and also be responsive to economic and humanitarian demands. It can also be an obstacle for social scientists seeking to develop new understandings of the dynamics of changing relationships between people and places. The research funded by this award takes up the challenge of this difficult problem by using intensive ethnographic methods to build new practical and theoretical understandings of citizenship from the ground up. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be conducted by University of California, Irvine, anthropology doctoral candidate Jennifer A. Zelnick, who is supervised by Dr. Eleana Kim. The focal population will be people of Cambodian origin, some of whom are legally resident in Long Beach, California, and some of whom have been involuntarily relocated back to Cambodia. This shifting residency makes them appropriate for research on the ambiguities of national belonging and the consequences of these ambiguities. The researcher will conduct her investigation in both sites. She will pay particular attention to socio-demographics, movement histories, official and bureaucratic encounters, and family and social networks. Data will be collected through participant observation, interviews, kinship mapping, and archival research. Findings from this research will produce the rich, micro-level data needed by both policy makers and social scientists to understand the nature and limits of citizenship in the world today.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1823363</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eleana</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eleana Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eleana.kim@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498249298</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000585291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Zelnick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer A Zelnick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jzelnick@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000748981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926975100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3332 Social &Behavioral Sciences]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~19596</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported dissertation research in cultural anthropology on migration and citizenship among refugees. The project focused on the deportation of Cambodian-American refugees who were legal permanent residents (LPRs) of the United States.&nbsp;This project asks: what happens when individuals are deported to a place where they may not have been born, where they may have never lived, and where they lack legal documentation? To answer these questions, the co-PI conducted 20 months of ethnographic research in Cambodia and California, with deportees and their families, nongovernmental organizations and community-based organizations, lawyers, law enforcement, bureaucrats and elected officials, and community advocates who work with deportees in various capacities. The research was conducted in three phases:</p> <p>1. Phnom Penh, Cambodia (August 2018-May 2019) [supplemental trips to Battambang, Cambodia]</p> <p>2. Battambang, Cambodia (May 2019-August 2019) [supplemental trips to Phnom Penh, Cambodia]</p> <p>3. Long Beach, Los Angeles California (August 2019-April 2020) [supplemental trips to the Bay Area, California, and Phnom Penh and Battambang, Cambodia]</p> <p>NSF Funding supported phases one and two .</p> <p>Across all research phases and fieldsites, the project repositions deportation not as an ending point, but as an event on a continuum of life experiences connect by repeated displacements.<strong>&nbsp;</strong>The findings indicate that complex variables including documentation, Khmer language skills, job training and accessibility, family support and (re)construction, disability, community-based organization and NGO support, and physical appearance coalesce to determine individual outcomes. Continued, extreme violence manifest as exponentially higher rates of incarceration recidivism, as well as premature death and permanent injury are major concerns. The resulting ethnography provides insights about exile, diaspora, and resettlement&nbsp;in the specific context of deportation from the United States to Cambodia for LPRs.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: This project examines how individuals and communities whose lives have been repeatedly shaped by U.S. state power experience multiple, overlapping forms of precarity including liminal legality (Menj&iacute;var 2006) and legal abjectivity (Gonzales and Chavez 2012). Although Cambodian-American deportees live at the margins of both the U.S. and Cambodian state and nation, they are simultaneously central to understandings of how U.S. political and military involvement produce stateless, highly precarious legal subjects. When Cambodian-American LPRs and their families were living in Cambodia and in refugee camps, their lives were intimately entangled with the U.S. due to the American War in Vietnam, U.S. nonintervention in the Khmer Rouge, and the U.S.'s role in resettlement. Once in the U.S., Cambodian-Americans continued to encounter the U.S. state in their daily lives (Ong 2003; Tang 2015). Drawing upon ethnographies of the structural violence of poverty and life in the inner city (Bourgois 2003; Tang 2015), interactions with law enforcement, and the U.S. deportation regime (De Genova and Peutz 2010), this project asks, how do Cambodian-Americans experience multiple forms of political, legal, economic, and social precarity? As such, this project contributes to anthropological understandings about how multiple forms of violence and precarity coalesce around U.S. state power.<span> </span>Additionally, this project examines how deportation contributes to the formation of a transnational imaginary of the U.S. and Cambodia, and how this is experienced and understood by deportees and their families. Rather than figuring deportation as an endpoint, the experiences of Cambodian-American deportable refugees and their families suggests deportation is a process that contributes to global flows of people, ideas, and goods. Whereas the anthropology of transnationalism primarily examines the phenomenon in relation to flexible citizens (Ong 1999), the deportation of Cambodian-American LPRs suggests that subjects who experience legal, socioeconomic, and political precarity can simultaneously engage in transnational movements and flows. In other words, although Cambodian-American deportees are stateless people who experience perpetual exile, legal unbelonging, discardability and abjectivity (Gonzales and Chavez 2012), and social disparagement in both the U.S. and Cambodia, this project contributes to anthropological theories of transnationalism by examining how these individuals simultaneously engage in, shape, and even create transnational communities and networks.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact: This project provides insights about how refugees with precarious legal statuses in countries of resettlement encounter and navigate deportation, and the ways in which deportees contribute to and create transnational networks, spaces, and flows. This research will also contribute to greater public awareness of Cambodian-Americans' precarious lives and the social trauma of displacement. Through the development of course materials; academic, non-academic, and policy publications and presentations; the broader impacts of this project aim to disseminate this project's knowledge rapidly, for the benefit of relevant stakeholders in Cambodia, the United States, and around the world where refugees interact with deportation regimes.&nbsp;In addition to the broad social, political, and legal impacts of this research, this study directly contributes to the training of a doctoral student of anthropology who aspires to work as a professor and practicing anthropologist. This research will serve as the basis for the co-PI?s dissertation, which she plans to publish in academic, civil society, and public policy contexts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/14/2020<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;A&nbsp;Zelnick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported dissertation research in cultural anthropology on migration and citizenship among refugees. The project focused on the deportation of Cambodian-American refugees who were legal permanent residents (LPRs) of the United States. This project asks: what happens when individuals are deported to a place where they may not have been born, where they may have never lived, and where they lack legal documentation? To answer these questions, the co-PI conducted 20 months of ethnographic research in Cambodia and California, with deportees and their families, nongovernmental organizations and community-based organizations, lawyers, law enforcement, bureaucrats and elected officials, and community advocates who work with deportees in various capacities. The research was conducted in three phases:  1. Phnom Penh, Cambodia (August 2018-May 2019) [supplemental trips to Battambang, Cambodia]  2. Battambang, Cambodia (May 2019-August 2019) [supplemental trips to Phnom Penh, Cambodia]  3. Long Beach, Los Angeles California (August 2019-April 2020) [supplemental trips to the Bay Area, California, and Phnom Penh and Battambang, Cambodia]  NSF Funding supported phases one and two .  Across all research phases and fieldsites, the project repositions deportation not as an ending point, but as an event on a continuum of life experiences connect by repeated displacements. The findings indicate that complex variables including documentation, Khmer language skills, job training and accessibility, family support and (re)construction, disability, community-based organization and NGO support, and physical appearance coalesce to determine individual outcomes. Continued, extreme violence manifest as exponentially higher rates of incarceration recidivism, as well as premature death and permanent injury are major concerns. The resulting ethnography provides insights about exile, diaspora, and resettlement in the specific context of deportation from the United States to Cambodia for LPRs.   Intellectual Merit: This project examines how individuals and communities whose lives have been repeatedly shaped by U.S. state power experience multiple, overlapping forms of precarity including liminal legality (Menj&iacute;var 2006) and legal abjectivity (Gonzales and Chavez 2012). Although Cambodian-American deportees live at the margins of both the U.S. and Cambodian state and nation, they are simultaneously central to understandings of how U.S. political and military involvement produce stateless, highly precarious legal subjects. When Cambodian-American LPRs and their families were living in Cambodia and in refugee camps, their lives were intimately entangled with the U.S. due to the American War in Vietnam, U.S. nonintervention in the Khmer Rouge, and the U.S.'s role in resettlement. Once in the U.S., Cambodian-Americans continued to encounter the U.S. state in their daily lives (Ong 2003; Tang 2015). Drawing upon ethnographies of the structural violence of poverty and life in the inner city (Bourgois 2003; Tang 2015), interactions with law enforcement, and the U.S. deportation regime (De Genova and Peutz 2010), this project asks, how do Cambodian-Americans experience multiple forms of political, legal, economic, and social precarity? As such, this project contributes to anthropological understandings about how multiple forms of violence and precarity coalesce around U.S. state power. Additionally, this project examines how deportation contributes to the formation of a transnational imaginary of the U.S. and Cambodia, and how this is experienced and understood by deportees and their families. Rather than figuring deportation as an endpoint, the experiences of Cambodian-American deportable refugees and their families suggests deportation is a process that contributes to global flows of people, ideas, and goods. Whereas the anthropology of transnationalism primarily examines the phenomenon in relation to flexible citizens (Ong 1999), the deportation of Cambodian-American LPRs suggests that subjects who experience legal, socioeconomic, and political precarity can simultaneously engage in transnational movements and flows. In other words, although Cambodian-American deportees are stateless people who experience perpetual exile, legal unbelonging, discardability and abjectivity (Gonzales and Chavez 2012), and social disparagement in both the U.S. and Cambodia, this project contributes to anthropological theories of transnationalism by examining how these individuals simultaneously engage in, shape, and even create transnational communities and networks.   Broader Impact: This project provides insights about how refugees with precarious legal statuses in countries of resettlement encounter and navigate deportation, and the ways in which deportees contribute to and create transnational networks, spaces, and flows. This research will also contribute to greater public awareness of Cambodian-Americans' precarious lives and the social trauma of displacement. Through the development of course materials; academic, non-academic, and policy publications and presentations; the broader impacts of this project aim to disseminate this project's knowledge rapidly, for the benefit of relevant stakeholders in Cambodia, the United States, and around the world where refugees interact with deportation regimes. In addition to the broad social, political, and legal impacts of this research, this study directly contributes to the training of a doctoral student of anthropology who aspires to work as a professor and practicing anthropologist. This research will serve as the basis for the co-PI?s dissertation, which she plans to publish in academic, civil society, and public policy contexts.           Last Modified: 05/14/2020       Submitted by: Jennifer A Zelnick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
