<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Synergy: Collaborative Research: Mapping and Querying Underground Infrastructure Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>158458.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>158458</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the challenges toward achieving the vision of smart cities is improving the state of the underground infrastructure. For example, large US cities have thousands of miles of aging water mains, resulting in hundreds of breaks every year, and a large percentage of water consumption that is unaccounted for. The goal of this project is to develop models and methods to generate, analyze, and share data on underground infrastructure systems, such as water, gas, electricity , and sewer networks. The interdisciplinary team of investigators from the University of Illinois at Chicago, Brown University, and Northwestern University will leverage partnerships with the cities of Chicago and Evanston, Illinois, to make the approach and findings relevant to their stakeholders. Research results will be incorporated in courses at the three institutions. Outreach efforts include events for K-12 students to develop awareness about underground infrastructure from a data and computational perspective. The results of the project will ultimately help municipalities maintain and renovate civil infrastructure in a more effective manner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cities are cyber-physical systems on a grand scale, and developing a precise knowledge of their infrastructure is critical to building a foundation for the future smart city. This proposal takes an information centric approach based on the complex interaction among thematic data layers to developing, visualizing, querying, analyzing, and providing access to a comprehensive representation of the urban underground infrastructure starting from incomplete and imprecise data. Specifically, the project has the following main technical components: (1) Generation of accurate GIS-based representations of underground infrastructure systems from paper maps, CAD drawings, and other legacy data sources; (2) Visualization of multi-layer networks combining schematic overview diagrams with detailed geometric representations; (3) Query processing algorithms for integrating spatial, temporal, and network data about underground infrastructure systems; (4) Data analytics spanning heterogeneous geospatial data sources and incorporating uncertainty and constraints; (5) Selective access to stakeholders on a need-to-know basis and facilitating data sharing; and (6) Evaluation in collaboration with the cities of Chicago and Evanston.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1823279</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Goce</FirstName>
<LastName>Trajcevski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Goce P Trajcevski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gocet25@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152942176</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304901</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500111153</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2520 Osborn Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~158458</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project targeted the domain of underground infrastructure systems in urban environments. Specifically, given the aging of various infrastructure components, the impacts of natural hazards (floods, earthquakes) and the need to install new components (e.g., fiber optics) &ndash; the broad problem of efficient and effective maintenance and repair becomes a paramount. In this context, the project has investigated a smart data management framework for underground infrastructure systems, collaboratively addressing the contexts of map construction, data integration, data analytics, security, and visualization.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The project is part of an NSF-funded collaborative effort by investigators working at Brown University, Iowa State University (initially parts conducted at Northwestern University), and University of Illinois at Chicago.</p> <p>Following is the summary of major project outcomes from the perspective of data analytics and integration:</p> <p>Considering that the data pertaining to urban infrastructure may have both spatial and semantic components (categorical as well as numerical), in collaboration with the project partners from UIC and Brown, we developed novel indexing techniques and query processing algorithms to efficiently process semantic-aware range queries. A specific aspect of the work catered to incorporating the uncertainty, both in the query syntax as well as its processing. Complementary to this, we also investigated the novel problem of generating a semantically diverse set of objects that are reachable within certain (travel-time or travel-distance) bounds.</p> <p>Motivated by the need to determine where to place a crew with spatially limited operational capabilities, and yet ensure a maximal coverage of serviceable object while ensuring a &ldquo;lower bound&rdquo; on the number of objects from a particular class &ndash; we introduced a novel variant of the MaxRS (Maximum Range-Sum) query. We extended the solution to cater to dynamic scenarios whereby new objects (with particular semantic attributes) can be inserted, and some of the existing objects can be deleted. In addition, we considered the variant of the MaxRS problem applied to spatial shapes, instead of point-objects.</p> <p>Another broad class of problems that we tackled was combining the time series kind of evolution with the spatial constraints (i.e., multiple data related to CO concentration or water flow, and associated with particular spatial locations). Extending the traditional similarity type of (k)NN queries, we investigated the impact of different data compression techniques on the outcomes of the similarity and correlation, under different distance functions. Complementary to these efforts, we also developed deep learning approaches for addressing UIL (User Identity Linkage), topic participation prediction, and information diffusion problems.</p> <p>Two PhD students were partially supported at Iowa State University, and one PhD student was partially supported at Northwestern University (thesis defended in 2018). &nbsp;In addition, the project provided training opportunities for multiple undergraduate students via Senior Design projects and Honor Mentoring program &ndash; leading to 17 undergraduates co-authoring conference papers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/25/2021<br>      Modified by: Goce&nbsp;P&nbsp;Trajcevski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project targeted the domain of underground infrastructure systems in urban environments. Specifically, given the aging of various infrastructure components, the impacts of natural hazards (floods, earthquakes) and the need to install new components (e.g., fiber optics) &ndash; the broad problem of efficient and effective maintenance and repair becomes a paramount. In this context, the project has investigated a smart data management framework for underground infrastructure systems, collaboratively addressing the contexts of map construction, data integration, data analytics, security, and visualization.    The project is part of an NSF-funded collaborative effort by investigators working at Brown University, Iowa State University (initially parts conducted at Northwestern University), and University of Illinois at Chicago.  Following is the summary of major project outcomes from the perspective of data analytics and integration:  Considering that the data pertaining to urban infrastructure may have both spatial and semantic components (categorical as well as numerical), in collaboration with the project partners from UIC and Brown, we developed novel indexing techniques and query processing algorithms to efficiently process semantic-aware range queries. A specific aspect of the work catered to incorporating the uncertainty, both in the query syntax as well as its processing. Complementary to this, we also investigated the novel problem of generating a semantically diverse set of objects that are reachable within certain (travel-time or travel-distance) bounds.  Motivated by the need to determine where to place a crew with spatially limited operational capabilities, and yet ensure a maximal coverage of serviceable object while ensuring a "lower bound" on the number of objects from a particular class &ndash; we introduced a novel variant of the MaxRS (Maximum Range-Sum) query. We extended the solution to cater to dynamic scenarios whereby new objects (with particular semantic attributes) can be inserted, and some of the existing objects can be deleted. In addition, we considered the variant of the MaxRS problem applied to spatial shapes, instead of point-objects.  Another broad class of problems that we tackled was combining the time series kind of evolution with the spatial constraints (i.e., multiple data related to CO concentration or water flow, and associated with particular spatial locations). Extending the traditional similarity type of (k)NN queries, we investigated the impact of different data compression techniques on the outcomes of the similarity and correlation, under different distance functions. Complementary to these efforts, we also developed deep learning approaches for addressing UIL (User Identity Linkage), topic participation prediction, and information diffusion problems.  Two PhD students were partially supported at Iowa State University, and one PhD student was partially supported at Northwestern University (thesis defended in 2018).  In addition, the project provided training opportunities for multiple undergraduate students via Senior Design projects and Honor Mentoring program &ndash; leading to 17 undergraduates co-authoring conference papers.          Last Modified: 01/25/2021       Submitted by: Goce P Trajcevski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
