<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Forest engineers, bureaucrats, and the constitution of information</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6659.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6659</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The production of accurate and reliable information about rainforests and other difficult-to-survey environments constitutes an enduring challenge for state bureaucrats, scientists, and engineers. Yet the grounded processes through which key environmental information is produced have received little study.  The research supported by this award takes up this problem through an anthropological investigation of the technical and bureaucratic practices through which state environmental information is created, transmitted, and applied.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be carried out by Columbia University doctoral student, Eduardo Romero Dianderas, with oversight from Dr. Elizabeth A. Povinelli.  The researcher will focus on the work of engineers and bureaucrats in the Amazonia region of Loreto, Peru, as a case study. He will collect data at multiple points in the chain of information production and application. In the field, he will document how engineers conduct research to generate technical data about the region. In state and associational offices, he will follow the engineering data as they are communicated to bureaucrats and as bureaucrats deploy them for technical judgments and public decisions. Research methods will include participant observation, analysis of paper and digital documents, and semi-structured interviews. This approach will shed light on what technical and bureaucratic environmental information includes and what it excludes, such as the knowledge and perspectives of indigenous inhabitants of these environments. It will also clarify the relevant communicative and technological infrastructures.  Findings from this research will help policy makers determine the potentials and limitations of the data on which they base their policies. The research also will contribute to building more robust theories of the production, communication, and comprehension of scientific data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1823929</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Povinelli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Povinelli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ep2122@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9176225926</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000359707</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Romero Dianderas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eduardo Romero Dianderas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>er2770@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000765901</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100277235</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL IMPLICATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~6659</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Eduardo Romero Dianderas has completed research for his dissertation &ldquo;Forest engineers, bureaucrats and the constitution of state rainforest information in Peruvian Amazonia&rdquo;. During his funding period, he spent 12 months in the region of Loreto, Peruvian Amazonia, conducting interviews and observations in state offices and other settings within the city of Iquitos, and joining rainforest trips commanded by engineers in order to examine how they produce technical and bureaucratic information about rainforests. Eduardo primarily focused in the dilemmas and controversies that emerge as engineers strive to constitute legal and technical facts about rainforests, such as what species does a tree belong to, how much timber volume does certain log yields, or what are the topographic boundaries of an indigenous property title. In his work, Eduardo followed scientists as they walked through rainforests and debated about these matters, navigated through rivers and streams, and inscribed data in various kinds of analogue and digital media that would later come to circulate in state bureaucratic settings.&nbsp;</p> <p>Eduardo was able to satisfactorily fulfill all of the activities he had programmed in his methodological design, including the completion of a total 150 days participating in rainforest trips and the conduction of around 160 interviews with different stakeholders. The collected data is composed of interview notes and transcriptions and detailed observation notes about engineers&rsquo; work both in the rainforest and in state offices. Similarly, Eduardo has been able to access various archival sources both in Lima and in Iquitos that relate to various aspects of contemporary rainforest governance in Peru.&nbsp;</p> <p>Although still preliminary, Eduardo&rsquo;s research has confirmed many of its initial hypothesis and intuitions, particularly those surrounding the frictions between, on the one hand, the desires on the part of bureaucrats and policy makers to increase the resolution and accuracy of rainforest information and, on the other hand, the rhythms and dynamics of the rainforest itself, which tend towards irreducible degrees of uncertainty, ambiguity and mixture. At this point, a large point of the dissertation will thus consist of exploring, across various themes and cases such as tree identification procedures, topographic surveys for indigenous titling, and log volume calculations, how is this tension constantly unfolding in the activities of engineers. Eduardo plans on mobilizing this ethnographic material in order to push forward an ethical and political reflection about the limits of contemporary dreams of perfect transparency and fully accurate technical information, especially in the context of today's general excitement with the possibilities of digital technologies. In this sense, he will seek to use his research to explore models and considerations that are sometimes not taken into account in policy-making discussions about the Amazon rainforest.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Eduardo plans on completing the writing of his dissertation by May 2022.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/17/2020<br>      Modified by: Eduardo&nbsp;Romero Dianderas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Eduardo Romero Dianderas has completed research for his dissertation "Forest engineers, bureaucrats and the constitution of state rainforest information in Peruvian Amazonia". During his funding period, he spent 12 months in the region of Loreto, Peruvian Amazonia, conducting interviews and observations in state offices and other settings within the city of Iquitos, and joining rainforest trips commanded by engineers in order to examine how they produce technical and bureaucratic information about rainforests. Eduardo primarily focused in the dilemmas and controversies that emerge as engineers strive to constitute legal and technical facts about rainforests, such as what species does a tree belong to, how much timber volume does certain log yields, or what are the topographic boundaries of an indigenous property title. In his work, Eduardo followed scientists as they walked through rainforests and debated about these matters, navigated through rivers and streams, and inscribed data in various kinds of analogue and digital media that would later come to circulate in state bureaucratic settings.   Eduardo was able to satisfactorily fulfill all of the activities he had programmed in his methodological design, including the completion of a total 150 days participating in rainforest trips and the conduction of around 160 interviews with different stakeholders. The collected data is composed of interview notes and transcriptions and detailed observation notes about engineers’ work both in the rainforest and in state offices. Similarly, Eduardo has been able to access various archival sources both in Lima and in Iquitos that relate to various aspects of contemporary rainforest governance in Peru.   Although still preliminary, Eduardo’s research has confirmed many of its initial hypothesis and intuitions, particularly those surrounding the frictions between, on the one hand, the desires on the part of bureaucrats and policy makers to increase the resolution and accuracy of rainforest information and, on the other hand, the rhythms and dynamics of the rainforest itself, which tend towards irreducible degrees of uncertainty, ambiguity and mixture. At this point, a large point of the dissertation will thus consist of exploring, across various themes and cases such as tree identification procedures, topographic surveys for indigenous titling, and log volume calculations, how is this tension constantly unfolding in the activities of engineers. Eduardo plans on mobilizing this ethnographic material in order to push forward an ethical and political reflection about the limits of contemporary dreams of perfect transparency and fully accurate technical information, especially in the context of today's general excitement with the possibilities of digital technologies. In this sense, he will seek to use his research to explore models and considerations that are sometimes not taken into account in policy-making discussions about the Amazon rainforest.    Eduardo plans on completing the writing of his dissertation by May 2022.           Last Modified: 02/17/2020       Submitted by: Eduardo Romero Dianderas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
