<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Relationship of the Spatial/Temporal Variability of Rain to Scaling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>142244.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142244</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nanderso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924715</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Scientists have been studying the non-homogeneity of rainfall for decades.  Simply put, raindrops collide, break apart, cluster, and spread out on their way to the ground.  This introduces a variety of fall speeds, drop sizes, and instantaneous rainfall intensities that have significant impacts on a wide range of topics from flood forecasting to erosion to communications system availability.  This research project will take advantage of a newly developed network of rain sensors to conduct a multitude of studies on rainfall characteristics.  The main societal impacts fall under the umbrella of public safety and productivity.  Rainfall characteristics are important for weather radars and weather forecast models for flood prediction, and for the prediction of communications drop-outs along land links and satellites.  Undergraduate students will participate in the research, allowing for development of the next generation of scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team will continue their studies into the spatial and temporal variability of rainfall with an enhanced focus on scaling.  The team will perform structural and statistical exploration of rain by collecting and analyzing time series rain observations over a newly configured network that consists of two 2D video disdrometers (2DVD), six 1D optical disdrometers (1DVD), and 21 Laser Precipitation Monitors (LPM).  The objectives to be addressed during the work period include:  exploring the frequency of the statistical heterogeneity of rain in a wider variety of meteorological conditions,  comparing 2DVD observations to those interpolated over a small network of LPMs, characterizing the 1DVD estimates with those of different neighboring instruments, using 2DVD data to detect structures having scales relevant to radar Bragg scatter from precipitation, expanding our understanding of the scaling of DSD and their integrated parameters in statistically homogeneous conditions and in a variety of different meteorological conditions, beginning preliminary observations of the effect of measurements at different heights above ground, and combining 2DVD observations from two instruments for unique simultaneity studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1823334</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Larsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael L Larsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>LarsenML@cofc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8439534973</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000615197</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of Charleston</Name>
<CityName>CHARLESTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>294240001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8439534973</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>66 GEORGE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073723322</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLLEGE OF CHARLESTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073723322</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of Charleston]]></Name>
<CityName>Charleston</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>294240001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[66 George Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~142244</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was devoted to continuing a series of investigations related to undersanding the impacts of rain's variability in space and time.</p> <p>Everyday experiences clearly demonstrate that rain is variable; talk to any farmer and they will tell you that the amount of rain falling on one field can be significantly different than the amount of rain they got on another field on their property. The total amount of rainfall isn't the only thing that's important, though -- in rain science, it turns out that the same amount of liquid water falling with a few large drops can have significantly different impacts than the same amount of water falling distributed among many small drops. Physical processes and properties like erosion, rain detectability by radar, frequency and impacts of drop collisions, drop evaporation efficiency, and drop fall speed all behave differently for drops of different size.</p> <p>Because drops of larger size interact with the world differently than drops of smaller sizes, careful rain measurements often need to account not only for how much total rain accumulated, but also how many of each size of drop were detected in a rain event. Fortunately, there are instruments (called "disdrometers" for DIStribution of DROps METERS) that are able to not only detect the total amount of rainfall but also report back the number, size, and fall speeds of drops of different size.</p> <p>Disdrometer measurements are used for a variety of purposes. For example, many scientific studies try to use measurements from disdrometers to determine if radar observations are giving accurate estimates of the true rainfall at a location. This intercomparision is tricky, though; an individual radar pixel corresponds to a spatial region that includes a large volume and often billions of raindrops, whereas a disdrometer is usually a much smaller instrument that might only detect tens of thousands to hundreds of thousands of drops in a day. The radar measures rain through a complicated series of interactions between light and billions of simultaneously suspended droplets with a lot if inherent assumptions about the specific nature of the interaction, whereas the disdrometer instruments involve a much more direct measurement of each drop individually by studying either the strength of the impact of a drop with a surface, the amount of light blocked in a simple light beam, or a direct image of each drop, etc.</p> <p>Getting this intercomparison between radars and disdrometers right is important -- it helps us use our radars more effectively and helps us understand the physics of rainfall better, but the variability of raindrops in a population of billions of drops (seen by the radar) and a much smaller population of individual drops (seen by disdrometers) are far different.</p> <p>If rain fell perfectly randomly, then there are a bunch of mathematical tools we could use to convert the variability of the large volumes of droplets to the smaller volumes of disdrometer detections but -- unfortunately -- even everyday experiences tell us that rain is <em>not</em>&nbsp;perfectly random on all reasonable space and time scales. If it was raining two minutes ago, it is more likely to be raining now than if it <em>wasn't</em>&nbsp;raining two minutes ago. The degree of the space and time clustering/structure of rain is debated and a big part of the work we were doing here.</p> <p>In investigating these questions, we studied a variety of loosely related other topics. For example, we found that one of the more popular disdrometer instruments had a flaw in its internal design so that some of the information it was reporting was in error; we found a way to fix that. We also ended up studying not only how rain droplets cluster in time and space, but also how things like cloud droplets cluster and we studied how the clustering of airborne obstacles might affect how light is transmitted through the obstacles -- which has implications not just for rain science, but also for cloud physics, the study of air quality, and even for how a radar itself works in the first place. We have also begun to study some new rain disdrometers that may have the advantages of being able to see smaller drops than other disdrometers, and we've begun to look carefully at how rain varies not just in time or in horizontal space (e.g. one farmer's field to another) but also how it varies vertically. Since rain can evaporate or collide with other drops as it falls, and since rain is detected by radars when it is still in the sky but we care more about its properties when it hits the ground, these statistical behaviors and how they vary vertically is going to be critically important in the future.</p> <p>Moving forward, we are hoping to continue to investigate these questions so that quantiative rainfall estimation is improved.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;L&nbsp;Larsen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was devoted to continuing a series of investigations related to undersanding the impacts of rain's variability in space and time.  Everyday experiences clearly demonstrate that rain is variable; talk to any farmer and they will tell you that the amount of rain falling on one field can be significantly different than the amount of rain they got on another field on their property. The total amount of rainfall isn't the only thing that's important, though -- in rain science, it turns out that the same amount of liquid water falling with a few large drops can have significantly different impacts than the same amount of water falling distributed among many small drops. Physical processes and properties like erosion, rain detectability by radar, frequency and impacts of drop collisions, drop evaporation efficiency, and drop fall speed all behave differently for drops of different size.  Because drops of larger size interact with the world differently than drops of smaller sizes, careful rain measurements often need to account not only for how much total rain accumulated, but also how many of each size of drop were detected in a rain event. Fortunately, there are instruments (called "disdrometers" for DIStribution of DROps METERS) that are able to not only detect the total amount of rainfall but also report back the number, size, and fall speeds of drops of different size.  Disdrometer measurements are used for a variety of purposes. For example, many scientific studies try to use measurements from disdrometers to determine if radar observations are giving accurate estimates of the true rainfall at a location. This intercomparision is tricky, though; an individual radar pixel corresponds to a spatial region that includes a large volume and often billions of raindrops, whereas a disdrometer is usually a much smaller instrument that might only detect tens of thousands to hundreds of thousands of drops in a day. The radar measures rain through a complicated series of interactions between light and billions of simultaneously suspended droplets with a lot if inherent assumptions about the specific nature of the interaction, whereas the disdrometer instruments involve a much more direct measurement of each drop individually by studying either the strength of the impact of a drop with a surface, the amount of light blocked in a simple light beam, or a direct image of each drop, etc.  Getting this intercomparison between radars and disdrometers right is important -- it helps us use our radars more effectively and helps us understand the physics of rainfall better, but the variability of raindrops in a population of billions of drops (seen by the radar) and a much smaller population of individual drops (seen by disdrometers) are far different.  If rain fell perfectly randomly, then there are a bunch of mathematical tools we could use to convert the variability of the large volumes of droplets to the smaller volumes of disdrometer detections but -- unfortunately -- even everyday experiences tell us that rain is not perfectly random on all reasonable space and time scales. If it was raining two minutes ago, it is more likely to be raining now than if it wasn't raining two minutes ago. The degree of the space and time clustering/structure of rain is debated and a big part of the work we were doing here.  In investigating these questions, we studied a variety of loosely related other topics. For example, we found that one of the more popular disdrometer instruments had a flaw in its internal design so that some of the information it was reporting was in error; we found a way to fix that. We also ended up studying not only how rain droplets cluster in time and space, but also how things like cloud droplets cluster and we studied how the clustering of airborne obstacles might affect how light is transmitted through the obstacles -- which has implications not just for rain science, but also for cloud physics, the study of air quality, and even for how a radar itself works in the first place. We have also begun to study some new rain disdrometers that may have the advantages of being able to see smaller drops than other disdrometers, and we've begun to look carefully at how rain varies not just in time or in horizontal space (e.g. one farmer's field to another) but also how it varies vertically. Since rain can evaporate or collide with other drops as it falls, and since rain is detected by radars when it is still in the sky but we care more about its properties when it hits the ground, these statistical behaviors and how they vary vertically is going to be critically important in the future.  Moving forward, we are hoping to continue to investigate these questions so that quantiative rainfall estimation is improved.       Last Modified: 05/29/2021       Submitted by: Michael L Larsen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
