<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Linking microbial diversity, gene expression, and the transformation of terrestrial organic matter in major U.S. rivers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>257670.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>262991</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rivers and streams are the major conduits for transporting of Earth's carbon from the land to the oceans.  Much of the carbon is in a dissolved organic form, and it serves as food for aquatic microorganisms.  The challenge is that the chemical diversity of dissolved organic carbon is very great, and the genetic diversity of aquatic microbes is also immense.  Accordingly, this project will use state-of-the art genomic methods to study the diversity and specific functions of these microorganisms.  The results will fill a critical gap in understanding the specific metabolic capabilities of these microbes and how they carry out the key ecosystem function of transforming and metabolizing highly complex, riverborne dissolved organic carbon.  The data that will be collected are important for predicting the impacts of land-use change, nutrient use, and shifting climate on freshwater quality across the USA.  The research involves a collaboration with the Yale Peabody Museum Evolution program for inner-city New Haven high-school students to train interns and develop an interactive museum exhibit on U.S. rivers. The project will also train a postdoctoral researcher, and undergraduate and graduate students, including members of underrepresented groups in science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to describe interactions and feedbacks between watershed diversity, microbial functional diversity, and dissolved organic matter (DOM) chemistry in 36 large U.S. rivers, and to experimentally link gene expression with DOM degradation in five of them (the Altamaha, Columbia, Mississippi, St. Lawrence and Yukon). River sampling will be conducted in collaboration with a U.S. Geological Survey stream network. This research will address the concept that microbial genetic mechanisms in river ecosystems are closely linked to climate and landscape features that control river environmental conditions, particularly DOM quality. This concept implies that microbial function is shaped by DOM composition, climate, and river chemistry. These shaping forces alter the functional genetic capabilities required for competitive success within riverine microbial communities, and, thus, drive shifts in functional gene expression and phylogenetic composition, that, in turn, increase the efficiency of DOM metabolism and biogeochemical processes. Three hypotheses are to be tested: (1) the functional genetic composition and gene expression patterns of riverine microbial communities are correlated with the composition of riverine DOM; (2) community gene expression patterns vary predictably in response to shifts in the available forms of DOM; and, (3) the composition of riverine bacterial communities correlates with the composition of riverine DOM over space and time, and varies with watershed-specific climatic factors. The first hypothesis will be addressed with an empirical study of microbial community gene content (metagenomics), gene expression (metatranscriptomics), and DOM diversity (high-resolution analytical chemistry) during four seasons in five rivers that encompass a broad range of DOM composition. The second hypothesis will be addressed with an experimental study to identify active organisms and genes expressed by freshwater microbial metabolism. The third hypothesis will be addressed with an empirical study of microbes, DOM, and river chemistry in 36 major U.S. rivers. Statistical approaches being developed through a Microsoft-sponsored international working group (BioGeoChemistry Data System) will be applied to link microbial and DOM data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1824723</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aron</FirstName>
<LastName>Stubbins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aron Stubbins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>a.stubbins@northeastern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7575158778</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000644234</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~254991</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Collaborative Research: Linking microbial diversity, gene expression, and the transformation of terrestrial organic matter in major U.S. rivers</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Byron C. Crump, Oregon State University</p> <p>Aron Stubbins, Northeastern University</p> <p>Brett A. Poulin, U.S. Geological Survey, Denver, CO</p> <p>George R. Aiken, U.S. Geological Survey, Denver, CO</p> <p>Peter Raymond, Yale University</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Scientific Merit</em></strong>. Riverine dissolved organic matter (DOM) is important to the global carbon budget and can drive essential local ecosystems processes. Riverine bacteria rely on DOM for sustenance and, in using DOM, alter its composition and convert a portion to CO<sub>2</sub>. The relationship between microbes and DOM is a crucial but poorly understood shaper of river ecosystem function. This is, in part, because of the challenge of linking the remarkable genetic diversity of bacteria and the remarkable chemical diversity of DOM. This project, which came to be called ROMEO (River Organic Matter and Environmental &lsquo;Omics), used new and cutting-edge tools in genetics and DOM geochemistry to describe in molecular detail how bacterial communities alter riverine DOM during transport from land to sea. We described in detail the river microbiome of the United States (U.S.) through DNA sequencing of hundreds of samples collected over 6 years from 36 major U.S. rivers. We also revealed interactions and feedbacks between watershed characteristics, microbial genetic diversity, and DOM chemistry in 5 large U.S. rivers (Altamaha, Columbia, Mississippi, St. Lawrence, Yukon) and experimentally identified the genes and organisms involved in degradation of riverine DOM.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major findings of this project were (1) DOM in U.S. rivers shares many of the same compounds but the relative abundance and total concentration of these compounds varies seasonally and spatially among rivers; (2) DOM composition from headwaters to mouths of major U.S. rivers is influenced by the residence time of water in river channels (i.e., river network travel time); (3) U.S. river microbiomes are similar across the country but they have variable seasonal patterns depending on whether rivers are mostly free-flowing (2 seasonal communities in winter and summer), ice-covered in winter (3 seasonal communities in winter, spring, and summer-fall) or heavily impounded (4 seasonal communities); (4) Across rivers and seasons, microbial genomic diversity (measured as gene abundances) correlates with inorganic environmental characteristics of rivers such as nutrient concentrations, alkalinity, and temperature, but the ecological functions of these microbes (measured as gene expression) correlates with organic matter composition; (5) Using gene expression data, we identified pools of DOM molecules that are associated with critical microbial ecosystem functions including photosynthesis, carbon fixation, nitrogen cycling, and aromatic carbon degradation.<em></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Broader Impacts</em></strong>. Understanding how microbial genetic and functional diversity interacts with DOM is important for predicting the impacts of land-use change, nutrient use, and shifting climate on local and global environmental cycles. The ROMEO project produced large, publicly available datasets of microbiome DNA sequences and DOM chemistry from major U.S. rivers that can be paired with highly detailed water quality data collected by the U.S. Geological Survey. To visualize some of these data and to train students in river ecology, the project developed a map-based data visualization tool with the help of the Oregon State University Open Oregon State program to promote the investigation of water quality data using colors and shading on a map of major U.S. river watersheds (<a href="https://web.oregonstate.education/oc-434-watershed-analysis">https://web.oregonstate.education/oc-434-watershed-analysis</a>). The project also established an internationally recognized FT-ICR mass spectrometer capacity for natural organic matter analysis at Northeastern University. The ROMEO project trained twenty-three undergraduate interns, four postdoctoral scientists, two graduate students, and three technicians whose professional development is strongly linked to this project, its objectives, and its publications. These young scientists learned to conduct their own research as part of a larger collaborative effort. This project also provided course material for use by the Principal Investigators, who teach undergraduate and graduate courses at their home institutions including Estuarine Ecology, Synthesis in Pelagic Ecology, and Biological Oceanography at Oregon State University, and Environmental Geochemistry at Northeastern University.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Aron&nbsp;Stubbins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report     Collaborative Research: Linking microbial diversity, gene expression, and the transformation of terrestrial organic matter in major U.S. rivers     Byron C. Crump, Oregon State University  Aron Stubbins, Northeastern University  Brett A. Poulin, U.S. Geological Survey, Denver, CO  George R. Aiken, U.S. Geological Survey, Denver, CO  Peter Raymond, Yale University     Scientific Merit. Riverine dissolved organic matter (DOM) is important to the global carbon budget and can drive essential local ecosystems processes. Riverine bacteria rely on DOM for sustenance and, in using DOM, alter its composition and convert a portion to CO2. The relationship between microbes and DOM is a crucial but poorly understood shaper of river ecosystem function. This is, in part, because of the challenge of linking the remarkable genetic diversity of bacteria and the remarkable chemical diversity of DOM. This project, which came to be called ROMEO (River Organic Matter and Environmental ‘Omics), used new and cutting-edge tools in genetics and DOM geochemistry to describe in molecular detail how bacterial communities alter riverine DOM during transport from land to sea. We described in detail the river microbiome of the United States (U.S.) through DNA sequencing of hundreds of samples collected over 6 years from 36 major U.S. rivers. We also revealed interactions and feedbacks between watershed characteristics, microbial genetic diversity, and DOM chemistry in 5 large U.S. rivers (Altamaha, Columbia, Mississippi, St. Lawrence, Yukon) and experimentally identified the genes and organisms involved in degradation of riverine DOM.     The major findings of this project were (1) DOM in U.S. rivers shares many of the same compounds but the relative abundance and total concentration of these compounds varies seasonally and spatially among rivers; (2) DOM composition from headwaters to mouths of major U.S. rivers is influenced by the residence time of water in river channels (i.e., river network travel time); (3) U.S. river microbiomes are similar across the country but they have variable seasonal patterns depending on whether rivers are mostly free-flowing (2 seasonal communities in winter and summer), ice-covered in winter (3 seasonal communities in winter, spring, and summer-fall) or heavily impounded (4 seasonal communities); (4) Across rivers and seasons, microbial genomic diversity (measured as gene abundances) correlates with inorganic environmental characteristics of rivers such as nutrient concentrations, alkalinity, and temperature, but the ecological functions of these microbes (measured as gene expression) correlates with organic matter composition; (5) Using gene expression data, we identified pools of DOM molecules that are associated with critical microbial ecosystem functions including photosynthesis, carbon fixation, nitrogen cycling, and aromatic carbon degradation.     Broader Impacts. Understanding how microbial genetic and functional diversity interacts with DOM is important for predicting the impacts of land-use change, nutrient use, and shifting climate on local and global environmental cycles. The ROMEO project produced large, publicly available datasets of microbiome DNA sequences and DOM chemistry from major U.S. rivers that can be paired with highly detailed water quality data collected by the U.S. Geological Survey. To visualize some of these data and to train students in river ecology, the project developed a map-based data visualization tool with the help of the Oregon State University Open Oregon State program to promote the investigation of water quality data using colors and shading on a map of major U.S. river watersheds (https://web.oregonstate.education/oc-434-watershed-analysis). The project also established an internationally recognized FT-ICR mass spectrometer capacity for natural organic matter analysis at Northeastern University. The ROMEO project trained twenty-three undergraduate interns, four postdoctoral scientists, two graduate students, and three technicians whose professional development is strongly linked to this project, its objectives, and its publications. These young scientists learned to conduct their own research as part of a larger collaborative effort. This project also provided course material for use by the Principal Investigators, who teach undergraduate and graduate courses at their home institutions including Estuarine Ecology, Synthesis in Pelagic Ecology, and Biological Oceanography at Oregon State University, and Environmental Geochemistry at Northeastern University.       Last Modified: 08/31/2020       Submitted by: Aron Stubbins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
