<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for 8 Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar on Rock Deformation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>32125.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>32125</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sharlan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927707</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project provides for travel and registration costs for graduate students and postdoctoral researchers to attend the 2018 Gordon Research Conference Seminar on Integrated Approaches to Rock Deformation. The conference will be held at Proctor Academy in Andover, New Hampshire from August 19th to the 24th, 2018. In additional to the conference itself, there will be a Research Seminar the weekend prior (August 18th, 19th), which will focus on research contributions from early career researchers. The activities supported by this proposal include cutting-edge present cutting-edge research that spans a range of methodologies and materials, over a variety of spatial and temporal scales, to develop an integrated perspective on rock deformation. The program will showcase recent advances and future trends in rock deformation and applications in structural geology, seismology, geodesy, geodynamics, planetary geology, and energy &amp; environmental engineering. The GRS provides a unique opportunity for early-career scientists to come together in a highly stimulating and non-intimidating environment to discuss current research and build networks that can lead to a lifetime of collaboration and scientific achievement. In addition, the project will contribute to broadening of participation of underrepresented groups in science, technology, and mathematics (STEM) through recruitment of participants from underrepresented groups. The Gordon Research Conference and associated Gordon Research Seminar will foster development of new research directions in rock mechanics and will contribute to the development of a diverse and globally competitive STEM workforce. The conference program includes topics of societal relevance that bear on the understanding of geologic hazards, which is of benefit to society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1824129</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Morgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia K Morgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>morganj@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133486330</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000166833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conference]]></Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~32125</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our first-order understanding of rock deformation is limited by our ability to observe and interpret natural phenomena or their relict signatures in the rocks. However, such observations allow us to define fundamental hypotheses that can be tested, in particular, by way of experiments and models, ultimately yielding deeper insights into rock deformation in nature. For example, both seismic and post-seismic deformation can be documented geodetically, but the remote nature of the data and their dramatic spatial and temporal variations, do not resolve the specific processes responsible. Deformation experiments under controlled conditions can narrow down the possibilities, while numerical modeling serves to extrapolate these results back to natural conditions. Thus, a fully integrated approach to rock deformation, one combining observation, interpretation, experimentation, and finally, physical or numerical modeling, is the key to furthering our understanding of the deformation behavior of complex Earth and planetary systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The 2018 Gordon Research Conference on Rock Deformation presented cutting-edge research that spans a wide range of methodologies, materials, over a variety of spatial and temporal scales, with an eye on developing this integrated perspective on rock deformation. Presentations covered brittle and ductile deformation, from microstructures to mantle rheology, with applications to earthquake mechanics, geodynamics, geohazards, geoengineering, and more. The conference drew together international experts at the forefronts of their fields, both early-career and senior investigators, enabling the free exchange of ideas. The collegial and open atmosphere of the Gordon Research Conference, combining programmed sessions and discussions, as well as opportunities for informal gatherings in the afternoons, evenings and during meals, provided a forum for scientists from different disciplines to brainstorm together, while developing new cross-disciplinary collaborations in a range of research areas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Gordon Research Seminar (GRS), was held immediately before the Conference and was tightly integrated into the Gordon Research Conference, in order to ensure the continuous flow of content and discussions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Mechanisms of rock deformation depend on many factors, including stress state, temperature, pressure, loading rate, composition, and fluid content. Variations in these factors throughout the lithosphere account for the wide range of deformation processes that drive plate tectonics, with implications for natural hazards (<em>e.g.</em>, earthquakes, volcanoes), economic resources (<em>e.g.</em>, ore deposits, hydrocarbons), and the geomorphic signature of Earth&rsquo;s surface. Building a more unified understanding of rock deformation requires the synthesis of many disparate data sets and analysis techniques that can account for spatial and temporal scales spanning several orders of magnitude. In this seminar, we invited contributions investigating deformation under conditions ranging from Earth&rsquo;s surface to the upper mantle, at rates ranging from seconds to millions of years, and length scales ranging from atomic to global. In particular, we encourage studies integrating field, laboratory, geodetic, geophysical, and/or modeling techniques to address outstanding questions in the field of rock deformation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Julia&nbsp;K&nbsp;Morgan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our first-order understanding of rock deformation is limited by our ability to observe and interpret natural phenomena or their relict signatures in the rocks. However, such observations allow us to define fundamental hypotheses that can be tested, in particular, by way of experiments and models, ultimately yielding deeper insights into rock deformation in nature. For example, both seismic and post-seismic deformation can be documented geodetically, but the remote nature of the data and their dramatic spatial and temporal variations, do not resolve the specific processes responsible. Deformation experiments under controlled conditions can narrow down the possibilities, while numerical modeling serves to extrapolate these results back to natural conditions. Thus, a fully integrated approach to rock deformation, one combining observation, interpretation, experimentation, and finally, physical or numerical modeling, is the key to furthering our understanding of the deformation behavior of complex Earth and planetary systems.     The 2018 Gordon Research Conference on Rock Deformation presented cutting-edge research that spans a wide range of methodologies, materials, over a variety of spatial and temporal scales, with an eye on developing this integrated perspective on rock deformation. Presentations covered brittle and ductile deformation, from microstructures to mantle rheology, with applications to earthquake mechanics, geodynamics, geohazards, geoengineering, and more. The conference drew together international experts at the forefronts of their fields, both early-career and senior investigators, enabling the free exchange of ideas. The collegial and open atmosphere of the Gordon Research Conference, combining programmed sessions and discussions, as well as opportunities for informal gatherings in the afternoons, evenings and during meals, provided a forum for scientists from different disciplines to brainstorm together, while developing new cross-disciplinary collaborations in a range of research areas.     The Gordon Research Seminar (GRS), was held immediately before the Conference and was tightly integrated into the Gordon Research Conference, in order to ensure the continuous flow of content and discussions.     Mechanisms of rock deformation depend on many factors, including stress state, temperature, pressure, loading rate, composition, and fluid content. Variations in these factors throughout the lithosphere account for the wide range of deformation processes that drive plate tectonics, with implications for natural hazards (e.g., earthquakes, volcanoes), economic resources (e.g., ore deposits, hydrocarbons), and the geomorphic signature of Earth?s surface. Building a more unified understanding of rock deformation requires the synthesis of many disparate data sets and analysis techniques that can account for spatial and temporal scales spanning several orders of magnitude. In this seminar, we invited contributions investigating deformation under conditions ranging from Earth?s surface to the upper mantle, at rates ranging from seconds to millions of years, and length scales ranging from atomic to global. In particular, we encourage studies integrating field, laboratory, geodetic, geophysical, and/or modeling techniques to address outstanding questions in the field of rock deformation.          Last Modified: 12/27/2018       Submitted by: Julia K Morgan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
