<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in DRMS: Harnessing Anger to Promote Activism: Exploring the Efficacy and Emotional Flow of Persuasive Anger Appeals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27054.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27054</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Strategic communicators are increasingly interested in ways to galvanize the public and policymakers to take action to offset clear threats to human and planetary health. To motivate civic engagement with health and environmental issues, communicators would benefit from exploring messaging strategies that go beyond informational portrayals of an issue to engage audiences on an emotional level. To this end, this research explores the viability of persuasive anger appeals. According to persuasion theory, anger-arousing messages must not only evoke anger in order to change attitudes and behaviors; they must also instill beliefs about the efficacy of taking action. The theory, however,  has been imprecise about what those efficacy beliefs entail. Because anger tends to motivate a desire to retaliate against a perceived wrongdoer, it follows that anger may have the strongest effects on persuasive outcomes when the audience believes that a particular action will punish the wrongdoer, a new concept the researchers call retributive efficacy. As such, we expect an anger appeal to be most effective when it evokes anger toward culprits of these harms and then communicates how a recommended response will effectively punish the offender. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In examining persuasive anger appeals, the researchers use two issues for which there is scientific consensus about the magnitude of the problem and the need for collective solutions. Three studies examine how to design messages that harness anger about perceived  injustices (referred to as moral anger) and how to translate that emotion into activism. Study 1 uses a cross-sectional survey design to validate a proposed measure of retributive efficacy. Studies 2 and 3 build on the first study by experimentally testing messages that instill moral anger and retributive efficacy. Additionally, study 3 explores the extent to which evoked anger temporally evolves during exposure to such messages -- a phenomenon called emotional flow. Study findings offer risk communicators direct, theory-informed guidance on how to craft maximally effective persuasive appeals to anger. The research also contribute to our theoretical understanding of anger appeals, which have received far less scholarly attention than appeals to other emotions like fear or humor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1824212</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Niederdeppe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Niederdeppe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdn56@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072559706</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000624802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christofer</FirstName>
<LastName>Skurka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christofer J Skurka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cjs396@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000768621</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148534301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[476 Mann Library Bilding]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~27054</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many people are quick to emphasize the destructive side of anger, yet there is reason to believe (and research to suggest) that anger can also be a force for social good, motivating collective action to address societal problems. The overarching goal of this project was to study how and when persuasive appeals to anger can promote civic engagement outcomes that include support for social policies and intentions to engage in political behaviors. We tested our predictions across two contexts: climate change (directing anger toward fossil fuel companies for misleading the public about the risks their actions pose for climate change) and childhood obesity (directing anger toward soda companies for targeting children with advertising for sugary drinks).</p> <p>First, we argued that a persuasive anger appeal would be most influential when it (a) describes a transgression committed by a culprit (e.g., fossil fuel companies, soda companies) then (b) communicates that taking action will punish the wrongdoer. This second element of the message is a new concept that we introduce called <em>retributive efficacy</em>, defined as beliefs about whether a course of action will have a negative impact on a perceived wrongdoer. Two studies challenged this prediction. Data from a cross-sectional survey indicated that retributive efficacy (and other efficacy beliefs) may matter less (not more) for people who are angry about the issue compared to people who are not angry. In an experiment manipulating anger and retributive efficacy appeals in pilot-tested messages, we found that conveying retributive efficacy may be ineffective because audiences find the messaging to be domineering or abrasive. If anything, our data suggest that mentioning retributive efficacy may polarize audiences, persuading audiences who are favorable toward the issue but backfiring among audiences who are unfavorable toward the issue. In contrast, an appeal that included general cues about the proposed solutions' effectiveness (relative to a control message) promoted support for public policies regardless of initial attitudes.</p> <p>Second, we examined the emotional flow of anger appeals. That is, emotional responses to a persuasive emotional appeal probably are not static; the intensity of anger likely rises and falls during exposure to the message. Confirming our exception, we found that anger intensity increased in response to the first part of the anger appeal, which described the harmful actions of corporate culprits. Anger intensity then deceased upon exposure to the second part of the message, which emphasized the actions the public can take to address the issue. We also examined how the emotional flow trajectory related to message persuasiveness. Different patterns were predictive of different persuasive outcomes. Whereas it may be useful to increase then decrease anger when it comes to affecting policy support or personal behaviors, it may be useful to increase then sustain anger to bring about activism.</p> <p>These results shed light on the conditions under which persuasive anger appeals can be effective. From a theoretical standpoint, this work advances our understanding on the role of anger in persuasion, which persuasion scholars have largely neglected relative to other emotions like fear, guilt, and humor. From a practical standpoint, our results offer public communicators insight into ways to best design persuasive anger appeals to promote civic engagement with wicked issues facing society. These findings are especially promising given that our results were generally similar across the domains we studied (climate change, childhood obesity). We therefore suspect that our findings would hold for communicators looking to harness anger for social good in other health, environmental, and science contexts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Christofer&nbsp;J&nbsp;Skurka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many people are quick to emphasize the destructive side of anger, yet there is reason to believe (and research to suggest) that anger can also be a force for social good, motivating collective action to address societal problems. The overarching goal of this project was to study how and when persuasive appeals to anger can promote civic engagement outcomes that include support for social policies and intentions to engage in political behaviors. We tested our predictions across two contexts: climate change (directing anger toward fossil fuel companies for misleading the public about the risks their actions pose for climate change) and childhood obesity (directing anger toward soda companies for targeting children with advertising for sugary drinks).  First, we argued that a persuasive anger appeal would be most influential when it (a) describes a transgression committed by a culprit (e.g., fossil fuel companies, soda companies) then (b) communicates that taking action will punish the wrongdoer. This second element of the message is a new concept that we introduce called retributive efficacy, defined as beliefs about whether a course of action will have a negative impact on a perceived wrongdoer. Two studies challenged this prediction. Data from a cross-sectional survey indicated that retributive efficacy (and other efficacy beliefs) may matter less (not more) for people who are angry about the issue compared to people who are not angry. In an experiment manipulating anger and retributive efficacy appeals in pilot-tested messages, we found that conveying retributive efficacy may be ineffective because audiences find the messaging to be domineering or abrasive. If anything, our data suggest that mentioning retributive efficacy may polarize audiences, persuading audiences who are favorable toward the issue but backfiring among audiences who are unfavorable toward the issue. In contrast, an appeal that included general cues about the proposed solutions' effectiveness (relative to a control message) promoted support for public policies regardless of initial attitudes.  Second, we examined the emotional flow of anger appeals. That is, emotional responses to a persuasive emotional appeal probably are not static; the intensity of anger likely rises and falls during exposure to the message. Confirming our exception, we found that anger intensity increased in response to the first part of the anger appeal, which described the harmful actions of corporate culprits. Anger intensity then deceased upon exposure to the second part of the message, which emphasized the actions the public can take to address the issue. We also examined how the emotional flow trajectory related to message persuasiveness. Different patterns were predictive of different persuasive outcomes. Whereas it may be useful to increase then decrease anger when it comes to affecting policy support or personal behaviors, it may be useful to increase then sustain anger to bring about activism.  These results shed light on the conditions under which persuasive anger appeals can be effective. From a theoretical standpoint, this work advances our understanding on the role of anger in persuasion, which persuasion scholars have largely neglected relative to other emotions like fear, guilt, and humor. From a practical standpoint, our results offer public communicators insight into ways to best design persuasive anger appeals to promote civic engagement with wicked issues facing society. These findings are especially promising given that our results were generally similar across the domains we studied (climate change, childhood obesity). We therefore suspect that our findings would hold for communicators looking to harness anger for social good in other health, environmental, and science contexts.          Last Modified: 02/03/2020       Submitted by: Christofer J Skurka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
