<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for an International Meeting on Monsoons and Tropical Rain Belts; Trieste, Italy; July 2-5, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds participation of students and early-career US researchers in a workshop on the dynamics of monsoons and tropical rain belts to be held 2-5 July 2018 at the International Center for Theoretical Physics in Trieste, Italy. The workshop, sponsored by the World Climate Research Program (WCRP), brings together researchers with expertise in tropical convection and precipitation, theoretical climate dynamics, climate modeling, and paleoclimate records.  The goal is to develop a better understanding of the fundamental processes responsible for the behavior of monsoons and tropical rain belts in past, present, and likely future climates. The event contributes to the advancement of science by providing an assessment of the state of the science, providing a venue for students and early-career scientists to interact with leading researchers in the field, and coordinating research efforts around the globe. Travel funds provided under this award are distributed through a competitive application process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award has intellectual merit as it addresses fundamental questions in tropical meteorology and monsoon dynamics. It has broader impacts by training the next generation of scientists in this research area. In addition, the questions addressed in the workshop are of societal interest given the large portion of the world's population living in areas affected by monsoons and tropical precipitation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1824715</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michela</FirstName>
<LastName>Biasutti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michela Biasutti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>biasutti@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658512</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000433031</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109648000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Science must provide reliable predictions of year-to-year variability and long-term changes of monsoon rainfall in order to support decision-making by farmers, policy makers, and other stakeholders in many tropical countries. Unfortunately our understanding and modeling skills are still falling short of this task. To tackle these shortcomings, scholars with expertise in theory, modeling, and observations came together at the &ldquo;2nd WCRP Grand Challenge on Cloud Circulation and Climate Sensitivity Workshop on Monsoons and Tropical Rain Belts" at the International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) in Trieste, Italy. Scholars and researchers shared their different perspectives on monsoon dynamics and variability (which included timescales ranging from sub-seasonal weather to millennial-scale paleo climate), and also taught a week-long summer school on tropical dynamics and modeling. This NSF award funded students and early-career researchers to travel to Trieste to participate in the two-week training.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span><br /></span></p> <p> <div>The US students supported by this award benefited from direct instruction by world-famous scientists, exposure to the newest research on monsoons, and hands-on training using &nbsp;tools that they can apply in their own research. Moreover, &nbsp;through group project and day-to-day interactions, they built strong connections with leaders in the field and with their peers, who are slated to become leaders in their own right. Students also had the option to participate in a side program on inclusion, professional ethics, and diversity designed to form ethical leaders, according to the recommendation of the National Academies and our professional society.&nbsp;</div> <div></div> <div>The center that hosted the workshop is a teaching and research institute affiliated with UNESCO and has as its mission creating bridges between developed and developing countries, thus researchers from Asia and Africa were also present, alongside scholars from the universities of Europe and the Anglo-Saxon world. Given the global reach of climate variability and climate change, these trans-national connection across researchers are especially important. This NSF award &nbsp;allowed US students and early career scientists to be included in this integration effort and to benefit from it in future international collaborations and projects.&nbsp;&nbsp;</div> </p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2019<br>      Modified by: Michela&nbsp;Biasutti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1824715/1824715_10533477_1558625979197_ICTP2018--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1824715/1824715_10533477_1558625979197_ICTP2018--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Participants at the summer school"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1824715/1824715_10533477_1558625979197_ICTP2018--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Participants at the summer school"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group photo of participants at the ICTP summer school on climate dynamics.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ICTP</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michela&nbsp;Biasutti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Participants at the summer school</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1824715/1824715_10533477_1558626075995_Group_photo_ICTP2018--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1824715/1824715_10533477_1558626075995_Group_photo_ICTP2018--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Participants at the workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1824715/1824715_10533477_1558626075995_Group_photo_ICTP2018--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Participants at the workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group photo of the participants to the workshop on monsoons and tropical rain belts</div> <div class="imageCredit">ICTP</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michela&nbsp;Biasutti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Participants at the workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Science must provide reliable predictions of year-to-year variability and long-term changes of monsoon rainfall in order to support decision-making by farmers, policy makers, and other stakeholders in many tropical countries. Unfortunately our understanding and modeling skills are still falling short of this task. To tackle these shortcomings, scholars with expertise in theory, modeling, and observations came together at the "2nd WCRP Grand Challenge on Cloud Circulation and Climate Sensitivity Workshop on Monsoons and Tropical Rain Belts" at the International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) in Trieste, Italy. Scholars and researchers shared their different perspectives on monsoon dynamics and variability (which included timescales ranging from sub-seasonal weather to millennial-scale paleo climate), and also taught a week-long summer school on tropical dynamics and modeling. This NSF award funded students and early-career researchers to travel to Trieste to participate in the two-week training.       The US students supported by this award benefited from direct instruction by world-famous scientists, exposure to the newest research on monsoons, and hands-on training using  tools that they can apply in their own research. Moreover,  through group project and day-to-day interactions, they built strong connections with leaders in the field and with their peers, who are slated to become leaders in their own right. Students also had the option to participate in a side program on inclusion, professional ethics, and diversity designed to form ethical leaders, according to the recommendation of the National Academies and our professional society.   The center that hosted the workshop is a teaching and research institute affiliated with UNESCO and has as its mission creating bridges between developed and developing countries, thus researchers from Asia and Africa were also present, alongside scholars from the universities of Europe and the Anglo-Saxon world. Given the global reach of climate variability and climate change, these trans-national connection across researchers are especially important. This NSF award  allowed US students and early career scientists to be included in this integration effort and to benefit from it in future international collaborations and projects.          Last Modified: 05/24/2019       Submitted by: Michela Biasutti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
