<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>LSAMP BD: UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO, PUERTO RICO LOUIS STOKES ALLIANCE FOR MINORITY PARTICIPATION</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1058802.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1058802</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Martha James</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mjames@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) program assists universities and colleges in diversifying the STEM workforce through the development of highly competitive students from groups historically underrepresented in STEM&lt;br/&gt;disciplines: African-Americans, Alaska Natives, American Indians, Hispanic Americans, Native Hawaiians, and Native Pacific Islanders. The goal of the LSAMP Bridge to the Doctorate (BD) Activity is to increase the number and competitiveness of STEM&lt;br/&gt;graduate students from historically underrepresented minority populations, with emphasis on STEM doctoral matriculation and completion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2018-2020 Puerto Rico LSAMP BD (PR-LSAMP-BD) program will recruit twelve (12) alumni from the Territory and LSAMP institutions nationwide for STEM postbaccalaureate studies at the University of Puerto Rico-Rio Piedras (UPR).  UPR's BD program will provide multidisciplinary training in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) disciplines at the graduate level to enable a seamless transition from the STEM baccalaureate degree to STEM doctoral studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Students will receive intense STEM mentoring through participation in faculty mentored research in disciplines such as biological sciences, math and physical sciences, computer science, environmental sciences, engineering and geological sciences.  Activities also include STEM professional development activities such as national and international research and conference attendance.  In addition, UPR's BD program will implement activities that develop mentoring and teambuilding skills. The Role Model Seminar series will bring the BD Fellows into contact with successful nationally and internationally recognized researchers thereby creating a mentoring environment that further equips the Fellows.  A BD Council has been established to strengthen advisement, counseling and mentorship to the participants as well as address continued sustainability of the program.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Student support in the form of stipends and cost of education are provided for two years for each student. The institution commits to assisting the students financially through completion of the STEM doctoral program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Evaluative activities will assess outcomes of students' accomplishments relating to retention, degree completion, and career progress. Social psychological outcomes related to career goals and expectations related to STEM identity development will also&lt;br/&gt;be assessed. Outcomes will be disseminated broadly through the institution's website, scholarly journals, and presentations at STEM professional conferences. These efforts will increase the diversity of STEM academic leadership and contribute to the growing&lt;br/&gt;literature on broadening participation in STEM at the graduate and post-graduate level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program will continue to coordinate its activities with other NSF-funded projects that are managed by the&lt;br/&gt;Resource Center for Science and Engineering (RCSE) and by pertinent UPR graduate programs. The activities implemented will increase the number of Puerto Rican STEM undergraduate students who apply and are admitted to STEM PhD programs, and&lt;br/&gt;increase the number of these students who obtain STEM doctoral degrees.  Since 2003, forty-seven BD fellows have earned STEM doctoral degrees and 140 students have participated in the program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1826558</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Nicolau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eduardo Nicolau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eduardo.nicolau@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7877634949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000661471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Puerto Rico</Name>
<CityName>San Juan</CityName>
<ZipCode>009261117</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7872500000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Jardin Botanico 1187</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Jardin Botanico 1187]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090051616</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>090051616</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Puerto Rico]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>009313344</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~1058802</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Funding over the 2018-2020 academic years, this Program, housed at the University of Puerto Rico&rsquo;s Central Administration Resource Center for Science &amp; Engineering, supported and mentored twelve former PR-LSAMP Undergraduate students that began graduate studies in August 2018.&nbsp;</p> <p>Twelve students were selected among PR-LSAMP participants that were newly admitted to graduate programs at the University of Puerto Rico&rsquo;s Rio Piedras (UPRRP) and Mayaguez (UPRM) campuses.&nbsp; The distribution by field of study of the fellows was: 6 in Biology (5 UPRRP, 1 UPRM), 1 in Bio-Engineering (UPRM), 1 in Biological Oceanography (UPRM); 2 in Chemistry (UPRRP), 1 in Environmental Science (UPRRP) and 1 in Mathematics (UPRRP)</p> <p>All of the selected fellows were Hispanic and 11 successfully completed the requirements of their respective graduate programs over the project&rsquo;s intended funding period of two-years. &nbsp;At the end of two years the fellows had GPAs over 3.00 (on a 4.00-point system) and the average GPA was 3.71.&nbsp; The total number of credits approved at the end of the period ranged from 28 to 41 with an average of 31.&nbsp;</p> <p>Besides being recipients of a $32K annual stipend and multiple benefits, BDP fellows participated in a series of program sponsored activities geared to better equip them to excel in their graduate studies and to foster in them a high valuation for multidisciplinary research that should enrich their future careers as independent researchers. As part of the BD support program to enhance the academic preparation of the BD fellows the students participated in a total of 54 professional development activities.The twelve fellows were supported for travel to scientific activities (i.e. scientific meetings, short courses and workshops) at national and international venues. The Cohort of students were able to travel a total of 24 times, including an on-site workshop on the Geology of the Domincan Republic. Other venues were: the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, New York, the Emerging Researchers Conference 2019 Washington DC, the IEEE International Conference in Bioinformatics, Madrid, Spain; the AAAS meeting, among others.&nbsp;</p> <p>Moreover, all fellows presented their scientific research findings in the Puerto Rico Interdisciplinary Scientific Meeting (PRISM), the largest scientific meeting in Puerto Rico.&nbsp;Also, all the BDP fellows received workshops on how to be successful when applying to the NSF-GRFP fellowship. This effort resulted in one GRFP award and one Honorable Mention for the 2020 NSF GRFP Cycle.</p> <p>At the end of the project 11 of the initial 12 fellows remained in the pipeline with expectations for graduation ranging from 1 to 4 years.&nbsp; The totality of these fellows has progressed to degree candidacy and two completed a Masters Degree. All the fellows that continued their progress are currently supported by other soureces of funding includng: NSF-GRFP, NIH-RISE, NASA Space Grant, George Washington Carver Fellowship, BioXFEEL Fellowship among others. Two of the fellows have continued their PhD's at US Institutions (University of Utah and Purdue University.)</p> <p>Finally, as the PR-LSAMP Bridge to the Doctorate Program projects itself into the future of Puerto Rican youth pursuing careers in STEM fields we proudly report that our fellows served as role models to approximately 1180 High School Students during presentations in 26 public schools. Furthermore, all of our fellows provided long term one-to-one mentorship for 12 undergraduate research students that will prospectively continue the work inspired by their research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/19/2020<br>      Modified by: Eduardo&nbsp;Nicolau</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Funding over the 2018-2020 academic years, this Program, housed at the University of Puerto Rico’s Central Administration Resource Center for Science &amp; Engineering, supported and mentored twelve former PR-LSAMP Undergraduate students that began graduate studies in August 2018.   Twelve students were selected among PR-LSAMP participants that were newly admitted to graduate programs at the University of Puerto Rico’s Rio Piedras (UPRRP) and Mayaguez (UPRM) campuses.  The distribution by field of study of the fellows was: 6 in Biology (5 UPRRP, 1 UPRM), 1 in Bio-Engineering (UPRM), 1 in Biological Oceanography (UPRM); 2 in Chemistry (UPRRP), 1 in Environmental Science (UPRRP) and 1 in Mathematics (UPRRP)  All of the selected fellows were Hispanic and 11 successfully completed the requirements of their respective graduate programs over the project’s intended funding period of two-years.  At the end of two years the fellows had GPAs over 3.00 (on a 4.00-point system) and the average GPA was 3.71.  The total number of credits approved at the end of the period ranged from 28 to 41 with an average of 31.   Besides being recipients of a $32K annual stipend and multiple benefits, BDP fellows participated in a series of program sponsored activities geared to better equip them to excel in their graduate studies and to foster in them a high valuation for multidisciplinary research that should enrich their future careers as independent researchers. As part of the BD support program to enhance the academic preparation of the BD fellows the students participated in a total of 54 professional development activities.The twelve fellows were supported for travel to scientific activities (i.e. scientific meetings, short courses and workshops) at national and international venues. The Cohort of students were able to travel a total of 24 times, including an on-site workshop on the Geology of the Domincan Republic. Other venues were: the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, New York, the Emerging Researchers Conference 2019 Washington DC, the IEEE International Conference in Bioinformatics, Madrid, Spain; the AAAS meeting, among others.   Moreover, all fellows presented their scientific research findings in the Puerto Rico Interdisciplinary Scientific Meeting (PRISM), the largest scientific meeting in Puerto Rico. Also, all the BDP fellows received workshops on how to be successful when applying to the NSF-GRFP fellowship. This effort resulted in one GRFP award and one Honorable Mention for the 2020 NSF GRFP Cycle.  At the end of the project 11 of the initial 12 fellows remained in the pipeline with expectations for graduation ranging from 1 to 4 years.  The totality of these fellows has progressed to degree candidacy and two completed a Masters Degree. All the fellows that continued their progress are currently supported by other soureces of funding includng: NSF-GRFP, NIH-RISE, NASA Space Grant, George Washington Carver Fellowship, BioXFEEL Fellowship among others. Two of the fellows have continued their PhD's at US Institutions (University of Utah and Purdue University.)  Finally, as the PR-LSAMP Bridge to the Doctorate Program projects itself into the future of Puerto Rican youth pursuing careers in STEM fields we proudly report that our fellows served as role models to approximately 1180 High School Students during presentations in 26 public schools. Furthermore, all of our fellows provided long term one-to-one mentorship for 12 undergraduate research students that will prospectively continue the work inspired by their research.       Last Modified: 08/19/2020       Submitted by: Eduardo Nicolau]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
