<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Total Organic Carbon/Total Nitrogen Analyzer for Interdisciplinary Research and Teaching at Georgia Gwinnett College</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>39931.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>39931</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) and Chemical Instrumentation P(CRIF) programs.  Professor Elizabeth Sudduth from Georgia Gwinnett College and colleagues Seungjin Lee and Sang H Park have acquired a total organic carbon/total nitrogen analyzer.  This instrument uses an analysis technique that is historic and fundamental to analyzing samples. This is combustion analysis which by combusting (burning or oxidizing) a sample can provide the content of elements such as carbon and nitrogen.  This a basic analytical tool for environmental analysis of materials in water, or water treatment. The research to be conducted is largely localized to the Georgia region. It provides undergraduate students training in measurement, data analysis, and instrumentation usage valuable as they go on to future technical employment or to higher level training.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of this analyzer is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. It especially aids the characterization of the effects of urbanization and beaver activity on patterns in organic carbon and nitrogen concentrations and ecosystem functions in urban streams. The instrument is necessary for the evaluation of the efficiency of surface water treatment and recycling processes for sustainable nutrients for the investigation of nitrogenous disinfection byproducts formation potential of Gwinnett County's drinking water source. The analyzer also helps investigators and students in characterizing the composition of atmospheric aerosols and dry atmospheric deposition rates of nitrogen, and for the characterization of combustion exhaust gas from a diesel generator using fuel blends of commercial ultra-low sulfur diesel and biodiesel synthesized on campus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1826920</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seungjin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<EmailAddress>seungjin.lee@ggc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sang</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<EmailAddress>spark1@ggc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Sudduth</LastName>
<EmailAddress>esudduth@ggc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Gwinnett College</Name>
<CityName>Lawrenceville</CityName>
<ZipCode>300437409</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6784075875</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 University Center Lane</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
