<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI-TT: Bioresorbable multi-functional optical sensor for brain implant</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>252131</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this PFI project: During clinical, surgical and rehabilitation steps, various sensor/monitor techniques are used to monitor brain function and other physiological parameters. However, current sensors are hard, rigid, bulky and dependent on fragile cables that can act as a nidus for infection in contaminated traumatic wounds. The associated surgical retrieval procedures, meanwhile, are costly and they subject patients to distress associated with re-operation and expose them to additional complications. On the other hand, bioresorbable electronics can be used for post-surgical monitoring of organ, tissue, implant, and wound health without the need for surgical extraction, thus reducing the risk of infection and complications during and after the surgical processes. The proposed innovation will open up numerous and diverse applications in medical, security, and consumer markets. Bioresorbable electronics can potentially move much closer to commercial reality in the next few years, with the promise of revolutionary advances in health care and environmental protection, resulting in broad social and economic impacts. Technology leadership in these areas will increase the economic competitiveness of the United States, advancing the health and welfare of the American public, enhancing partnerships between academia and industry, and developing an American STEM workforce that is globally competitive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is to develop a bioresorbable bio-implantable multi-functional optical probe for simultaneous monitoring of brain intracranial pressure (ICP), temperature, and oxygenation. The initial target market of the technology is brain monitors for the efficient treatment of patients during recovery following a severe Traumatic brain injury (TBI). With this NSF PFI-PR project, various technical challenges at the interface between optics, electronic/optical materials, processes of bio-resorption, brain interfaces, advanced manufacturing, and commercial scaling will be addressed. The modular design approach proposed here involves an implantable bioresorbable probe head coupled to a pluggable/flexible external optical head, to shorten the product design cycle and reduce the cost. The self-compensating design for the fully bioresorbable optical/temperature sensor system will ensure accurate readings of physiological parameters, which are typically sensitive to environmental variations. A built-in self-calibration evanescent waveguide sensor pair enables autonomous long-term sensor accuracy. This bioresorbable systems can be designed to have the specific functional lifetimes, after which all of the constituent materials under complete bio-absorption, thereby eliminating the need for surgery, and associated risks to the patient, to remove the devices. Additionally, electrically passive operation and complete immunity to electromagnetic interference represent two important advantages of the proposed optical pressure sensors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1827693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Rogers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John A Rogers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrogers@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172444979</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000370729</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weidong</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weidong Zhou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wzhou@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172721227</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000257406</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roozbeh</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghaffari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roozbeh Ghaffari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rghaffari@neurolux.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172513686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000768236</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~52132</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>The proposed project </em>is to develop a <em>bioresorbable</em> <em>bio-implantable</em> <em>multi-functional</em> <em>optical probe</em> for simultaneous monitoring of brain intracranial pressure (ICP), temperature, and oxygenation. The initial target market of the technology is brain monitors for the efficient treatment of patients during recovery following a severe Traumatic brain injury (TBI). With this NSF PFI-PR project, various technical challenges at the interface between optics, electronic/optical materials, processes of bio-resorption, brain interfaces, advanced manufacturing, and commercial scaling will be addressed. The modular design approach proposed here involves an implantable bioresorbable probe head coupled to a pluggable/flexible external optical head, to shorten the product design cycle and reduce the cost. The self-compensating design for the fully bioresorbable optical/temperature sensor system will ensure accurate readings of physiological parameters, which are typically sensitive to environmental variations. A built-in self-calibration evanescent waveguide sensor pair enables autonomous long-term sensor accuracy. This bioresorbable systems can be designed to have the specific functional lifetimes, after which all of the constituent materials under complete bioabsorption, thereby eliminating the need for surgery, and associated risks to the patient, to remove the devices. Additionally, electrically passive operation and complete immunity to electromagnetic interference represent two important advantages of the proposed optical pressure sensors.</p> <p><em>The</em> <em>broader impact/commercial potential of this PFI project: </em>During clinical, surgical and rehabilitation steps, various sensor/monitor techniques are used to monitor brain function and other physiological parameters. However, current sensors are hard, rigid, bulky and dependent on fragile cables that can act as a nidus for infection in contaminated traumatic wounds. The associated surgical retrieval procedures, meanwhile, are costly and they subject patients to distress associated with re-operation and expose them to additional complications. On the other hand, bioresorbable electronics can be used for post-surgical monitoring of organ, tissue, implant, and wound health without the need for surgical extraction, thus reducing the risk of infection and complications during and after the surgical processes. The proposed innovation will open up numerous and diverse applications in medical, security, and consumer markets. Bioresorbable electronics can potentially move much closer to commercial reality in the next few years, with the promise of revolutionary advances in health care and environmental protection, resulting in broad social and economic impacts. Technology leadership in these areas will increase the economic competitiveness of the United States, advancing the health and welfare of the American public, enhancing partnerships between academia and industry, and developing an American STEM workforce that is globally competitive.</p> <p class="PrgrNormal"><em>Major Contributions and Impacts: </em>Through this NSF PFI project support, we have addressed these key technical barriers in the process of developing a complete bio-implantable optical and temperature sensing platform for commercial application. The project resulted in 3 high impact journal publications, one conference presentations so far. Major technical &nbsp;have been on developing temperature and pressure sensors that are bio-resorbable, implantable and also with high accuracy and free of interference from measurement conditions.</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">(1) We designed, fabricated and tested a set of optical FPI pressure and temperature sensors on conventional optical fiber, which can be implanted into intracranial spaces for brain pressure monitoring. We thoroughly studied the parameters that affects the performance of sensors of this type;</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">(2) We designed, fabricated and tested photonic crystal type of temperature and pressure sensor that work in free space. Such sensors can be implemented for intraocular pressure/temperature monitoring and tracking;</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">(3) We design and simulated F-P type pressure sensor with temperature compensation utilizing photonic crystal elements, such design can potentially solve the inherent thermal interference issue and any F-P type pressure sensor with sealed membrane chamber;</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">(4) We developed bio-resorbable optical waveguide for multi-functional ICP and oxygenation sensor, this optical element can be implanted as platforms to deploy temperature, pressure, oxygenation level sensing elements;</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">(5) We designed, fabricated, and tested a bio-implantable angle independent free-space multilayer temperature sensor that can be implanted into deep tissue for long term temperature monitoring. This design resolved the interference of measurement angle for any free space optical devices and can be integrated with other sensing elements that will be implanted into deep tissues, intraocular or intravascular spaces.</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">(6) We collaborated with DQD, characterized the VCSEL devices they fabricated. The work on design and simulation of grating couple is also completed to combine with the micro-lens assisted VCSEL emission steering and tilting.</p> <p class="PrgrNormal">With the above designs of sensing and coupling schemes, further work to integrate multiple sensing elements onto a single platform is plausible such that it provides high accurate sensing of temperature, pressure and more parameters that are critical for clinical diagnostics of intraocular, intracranial and intravascular diseases. Further work to integrate active elements would also be of interests to create miniaturized complex sensing units.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/31/2021<br>      Modified by: Weidong&nbsp;Zhou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The proposed project is to develop a bioresorbable bio-implantable multi-functional optical probe for simultaneous monitoring of brain intracranial pressure (ICP), temperature, and oxygenation. The initial target market of the technology is brain monitors for the efficient treatment of patients during recovery following a severe Traumatic brain injury (TBI). With this NSF PFI-PR project, various technical challenges at the interface between optics, electronic/optical materials, processes of bio-resorption, brain interfaces, advanced manufacturing, and commercial scaling will be addressed. The modular design approach proposed here involves an implantable bioresorbable probe head coupled to a pluggable/flexible external optical head, to shorten the product design cycle and reduce the cost. The self-compensating design for the fully bioresorbable optical/temperature sensor system will ensure accurate readings of physiological parameters, which are typically sensitive to environmental variations. A built-in self-calibration evanescent waveguide sensor pair enables autonomous long-term sensor accuracy. This bioresorbable systems can be designed to have the specific functional lifetimes, after which all of the constituent materials under complete bioabsorption, thereby eliminating the need for surgery, and associated risks to the patient, to remove the devices. Additionally, electrically passive operation and complete immunity to electromagnetic interference represent two important advantages of the proposed optical pressure sensors.  The broader impact/commercial potential of this PFI project: During clinical, surgical and rehabilitation steps, various sensor/monitor techniques are used to monitor brain function and other physiological parameters. However, current sensors are hard, rigid, bulky and dependent on fragile cables that can act as a nidus for infection in contaminated traumatic wounds. The associated surgical retrieval procedures, meanwhile, are costly and they subject patients to distress associated with re-operation and expose them to additional complications. On the other hand, bioresorbable electronics can be used for post-surgical monitoring of organ, tissue, implant, and wound health without the need for surgical extraction, thus reducing the risk of infection and complications during and after the surgical processes. The proposed innovation will open up numerous and diverse applications in medical, security, and consumer markets. Bioresorbable electronics can potentially move much closer to commercial reality in the next few years, with the promise of revolutionary advances in health care and environmental protection, resulting in broad social and economic impacts. Technology leadership in these areas will increase the economic competitiveness of the United States, advancing the health and welfare of the American public, enhancing partnerships between academia and industry, and developing an American STEM workforce that is globally competitive. Major Contributions and Impacts: Through this NSF PFI project support, we have addressed these key technical barriers in the process of developing a complete bio-implantable optical and temperature sensing platform for commercial application. The project resulted in 3 high impact journal publications, one conference presentations so far. Major technical  have been on developing temperature and pressure sensors that are bio-resorbable, implantable and also with high accuracy and free of interference from measurement conditions. (1) We designed, fabricated and tested a set of optical FPI pressure and temperature sensors on conventional optical fiber, which can be implanted into intracranial spaces for brain pressure monitoring. We thoroughly studied the parameters that affects the performance of sensors of this type; (2) We designed, fabricated and tested photonic crystal type of temperature and pressure sensor that work in free space. Such sensors can be implemented for intraocular pressure/temperature monitoring and tracking; (3) We design and simulated F-P type pressure sensor with temperature compensation utilizing photonic crystal elements, such design can potentially solve the inherent thermal interference issue and any F-P type pressure sensor with sealed membrane chamber; (4) We developed bio-resorbable optical waveguide for multi-functional ICP and oxygenation sensor, this optical element can be implanted as platforms to deploy temperature, pressure, oxygenation level sensing elements; (5) We designed, fabricated, and tested a bio-implantable angle independent free-space multilayer temperature sensor that can be implanted into deep tissue for long term temperature monitoring. This design resolved the interference of measurement angle for any free space optical devices and can be integrated with other sensing elements that will be implanted into deep tissues, intraocular or intravascular spaces. (6) We collaborated with DQD, characterized the VCSEL devices they fabricated. The work on design and simulation of grating couple is also completed to combine with the micro-lens assisted VCSEL emission steering and tilting. With the above designs of sensing and coupling schemes, further work to integrate multiple sensing elements onto a single platform is plausible such that it provides high accurate sensing of temperature, pressure and more parameters that are critical for clinical diagnostics of intraocular, intracranial and intravascular diseases. Further work to integrate active elements would also be of interests to create miniaturized complex sensing units.             Last Modified: 01/31/2021       Submitted by: Weidong Zhou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
