<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CC* Network Design and Implementation for Small Institutions: Rural Campus Connectivity for Research and Teaching on the Prairie</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>362589.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>362589</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project provides cyberinfrastructure upgrades at Dordt College for an Internet2 connection and enhanced network connectivity between campus locations, data sources, and computing resources. Through the application of data-intensive multi-omics and biostatistics research (such as high-throughput genotyping and phenotyping) at agricultural and prairie sites, these upgrades are designed to equip ongoing research to better understand, first hand, land-use impacts on local ecology and microbiome, prairie genetics, soil erosion, nutrient uptake and loss, carbon sequestration, drought susceptibility, and water quality. The Rural Campus Connectivity for Research and Teaching on the Prairie project also connects Dordt College to national research and education resources and enhances its STEM education impact by providing cutting-edge research, teaching, and outreach opportunities through collaborative, interdisciplinary, and data-driven science for undergraduate students and STEM teachers-in-training.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of this cyberinfrastructure project is the installation and connection of a fiber optic line from the rurally-situated Dordt College campus to an Internet2 connection point. Campus network upgrades also include the development of a Science DMZ and associated services such as Federated ID Management, data transfer management, performance monitoring through the implementation of a PerfSONAR measurement node, and wireless connectivity to a rural satellite campus. A new network switch will be used as the hub of the 10Gbps DMZ to connect local storage, compute clusters and instrumentation to the existing campus network and Internet2.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1827210</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Tintle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan Tintle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nathan.tintle@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7127226264</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508737</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Channon</FirstName>
<LastName>Visscher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Channon Visscher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cvisscher@spacescience.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7127226249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000578735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nick</FirstName>
<LastName>Breems</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nick Breems</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Nick.Breems@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7127226264</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000689669</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kari</FirstName>
<LastName>Sandouka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kari Sandouka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kari.sandouka@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7127226264</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000769598</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Donselaar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>722</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Van Donselaar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian.vandonselaar@dordt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7127226264</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000769601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dordt University, Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>Sioux Center</CityName>
<ZipCode>512501606</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7127226264</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>498 4th Avenue NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078009222</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DORDT UNIVERSITY, INCORPORATED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dordt College]]></Name>
<CityName>Sioux Center</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>512501606</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[498 4th Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~362589</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Dordt University completed the main objectives of the CC* Network Design and Implementation for Small Institutions project: <em>Rural Campus Connectivity for Research and Teaching on the Prairie</em>, developed to implement campus cyberinfrastructure upgrades and enhance network connectivity. Throughout the first year of the award (2018-2019), the Dordt CC*NDI team worked in consultation with partnering collaborators at the University of Minnesota to explore and assess a range of design and implementation scenarios for connectivity and networking upgrades. Members of the Dordt CC*NDI team also participated in the NSF Campus Cyberinfrastructure PI Workshop in 2018 and 2019. In the second year of the award (2019-2020), Dordt University began deployment of the infrastructure upgrades, completed in late 2020. This deployment includes:&nbsp;</p> <ul class="ul1"> <li class="li1">Implementation of a 10Gb physical internet connection through a contract with the Iowa Communications Network (a state-administered network designed to provide connectivity to government agencies, hospitals, libraries, and schools, including higher education institutions). This provides direct connection to the Internet2 research network, with the high throughput and low latency needed for next-generation access to large data sets available through our research partners.<span>&nbsp;</span></li> <li class="li1">Installation of a fiber connection between the main campus of Dordt University and the Dordt University Agricultural Stewardship Center (ASC), a satellite campus located in a rural setting three miles away from the main campus. This installation provides high-speed connectivity between the main campus and satellite campus, including access to the campus science network. This connection enables a wide variety of STEM reasearch and teaching applications at the Ag Stewardship Center.<span>&nbsp;</span></li> <li class="li1">Development of a 10Gbps campus science network based upon Science DMZ architecture principles. This network includes a data transfer node and a perfSONAR node to monitor network performance. Compute facilities in the science DMZ include our existing <em>Beaker</em> cluster, and the upcoming <em>Bunsen</em> cluster that will be implemented in the summer of 2021 (NSF-MRI #2018705).</li> </ul> <p class="p1">These infrastructure upgrades significantly enhance campus network connectivity between campus locations, expanded data storage, instrument and computing resources (including a new high-performance computing cluster), and researchers/teachers on campus, as well as providing expanded connectivity to regional and national collaborators and the broader research &amp; education network fabric. <span>&nbsp;</span>&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The development of a high-speed connection between the central campus and the satellite campus locations has allowed for relocation of some STEM faculty/staff and research projects to the agricultural/rural satellite campus. This connectivity is also provides new opportunities for in-situ data-driven research over a range of topics including ecology, soil genetics, nutrient uptake and loss, aquaponics, drought susceptibility, and water quality. Moreover, the networking infrastructure upgrades help support Dordt University initiatives in STEM research and education, including training in biological statistics, STEM-Ed outreach programs, the development of an undergraduate data science program, expanded research experience for undergraduates (REU) programs, and increased reliance on virtual scientific collaboration and teaching.</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/20/2021<br>      Modified by: Channon&nbsp;Visscher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Dordt University completed the main objectives of the CC* Network Design and Implementation for Small Institutions project: Rural Campus Connectivity for Research and Teaching on the Prairie, developed to implement campus cyberinfrastructure upgrades and enhance network connectivity. Throughout the first year of the award (2018-2019), the Dordt CC*NDI team worked in consultation with partnering collaborators at the University of Minnesota to explore and assess a range of design and implementation scenarios for connectivity and networking upgrades. Members of the Dordt CC*NDI team also participated in the NSF Campus Cyberinfrastructure PI Workshop in 2018 and 2019. In the second year of the award (2019-2020), Dordt University began deployment of the infrastructure upgrades, completed in late 2020. This deployment includes:   Implementation of a 10Gb physical internet connection through a contract with the Iowa Communications Network (a state-administered network designed to provide connectivity to government agencies, hospitals, libraries, and schools, including higher education institutions). This provides direct connection to the Internet2 research network, with the high throughput and low latency needed for next-generation access to large data sets available through our research partners.  Installation of a fiber connection between the main campus of Dordt University and the Dordt University Agricultural Stewardship Center (ASC), a satellite campus located in a rural setting three miles away from the main campus. This installation provides high-speed connectivity between the main campus and satellite campus, including access to the campus science network. This connection enables a wide variety of STEM reasearch and teaching applications at the Ag Stewardship Center.  Development of a 10Gbps campus science network based upon Science DMZ architecture principles. This network includes a data transfer node and a perfSONAR node to monitor network performance. Compute facilities in the science DMZ include our existing Beaker cluster, and the upcoming Bunsen cluster that will be implemented in the summer of 2021 (NSF-MRI #2018705).  These infrastructure upgrades significantly enhance campus network connectivity between campus locations, expanded data storage, instrument and computing resources (including a new high-performance computing cluster), and researchers/teachers on campus, as well as providing expanded connectivity to regional and national collaborators and the broader research &amp; education network fabric.    The development of a high-speed connection between the central campus and the satellite campus locations has allowed for relocation of some STEM faculty/staff and research projects to the agricultural/rural satellite campus. This connectivity is also provides new opportunities for in-situ data-driven research over a range of topics including ecology, soil genetics, nutrient uptake and loss, aquaponics, drought susceptibility, and water quality. Moreover, the networking infrastructure upgrades help support Dordt University initiatives in STEM research and education, including training in biological statistics, STEM-Ed outreach programs, the development of an undergraduate data science program, expanded research experience for undergraduates (REU) programs, and increased reliance on virtual scientific collaboration and teaching.         Last Modified: 05/20/2021       Submitted by: Channon Visscher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
