<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EDGE:   Creation of a Genetically Tractable Cephalopod Model using the Hawaiian Bobtail Squid</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edda Thiels</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ethiels@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928167</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cephalopods are the most behaviorally complex invertebrates, exhibiting sophistication on par with higher vertebrates. They have a highly complex system for camouflage, enabling them to blend in with their environment instantaneously. They have an advanced ability for learning and memory. They have large brains (the common octopus has 6 times as many nerve cells as a rat). These and other innovations have evolved along an independent trajectory from the vertebrates, the only other similarly advanced group. By studying cephalopods, much can be learned regarding biological complexity; however, these studies have lagged due to the lack of a suitable cephalopod model system. Over the past 30 years, genetically tractable model organisms like the fruit fly and lab mouse have driven biological discovery. This project aims to develop the Hawaiian Bobtail Squid into the first genetically tractable cephalopod model. This species is ideal because it is small, it can be cultured through its entire lifecycle, and it reaches sexual maturity in as little as two and a half months. The project involves the establishment of a large-scale culture facility at the Marine Biological Laboratory to provide specimens for genetic manipulation. Husbandry methods are perfected to culture these organisms through multiple generations. Finally, techniques for genome editing are developed. All resources developed under this project, including animals and methods for gene knockouts, are shared with the scientific community of cephalopod enthusiasts through workshops. Additional efforts include assistance with the incorporation of cephalopod biology into educational curricula for undergraduate students, and into public outreach activities, such as exhibits at science museums. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a group, the coleoid cephalopods exhibit extraordinary novelties, many that are poised to promote biological discovery across disciplines. For example, they have by far the largest brains of any invertebrate, and show behavioral sophistication comparable to advanced vertebrates. Through convergence, they have evolved camera-type eyes and the biomechanical capabilities of their appendages inspire robotic design. Conspicuous symbioses with marine microbes make some species ideal models for studying symbioses. Recently sequenced genomes and transcriptomes have uncovered molecular novelties. In octopus, for example, large-scale expansions of cell adhesion molecules may help explain how complex nervous systems are assembled. Other studies indicate that cephalopods use RNA editing at unprecedented levels to diversify genetic information. Taken together, these phenomena underscore the vast potential of cephalopods to broaden our understanding of fundamental and unexplored area in biology; however, the field has struggled to advance without a genetically tractable model. The cephalopod community has lacked a model because the husbandry of these organisms is difficult. This work overcomes a key bottleneck in cephalopod research by developing Euprymna scolopes, the Hawaiian Bobtail Squid, into a genetically tractable model. This species is ideal because it is small, it can be cultured through its lifecycle, and it reaches sexual maturity rapidly. To accomplish the project goals, a lifecycle culture facility is established and protocols for genome editing using CRISPR-Cas9 are developed. Animals produced by this facility are offered to the scientific community. Protocols for husbandry and genome editing are disseminated through workshops.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1827509</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosenthal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua Rosenthal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrosenthal@mbl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082897253</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000246546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marine Biological Laboratory</Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082897243</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7 M B L ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001933779</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARINE BIOLOGICAL LABORATORY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marine Biological Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7 MBL Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>050Z</Code>
<Text>EDGE Enabling Discovery through Genomic</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As models for research, the coleoid cephalopods offer tremendous opportunities for discovery based on their biological innovations. They possess the largest nervous system of any invertebrate and express the most sophisticated behaviors. For example, an adult octopus has about as many neurons as a dog, but they are organized in a completely manner. Their ability to learn and remember has been compared to that of crows and, on a cellular level, shares mechanistic similarities to that of mammals. Cephalopod eyes are structurally similar to our own, but they have converged on this design via an independent evolutionary trajectory. Many species of cephalopods have elaborate systems to generate near-perfect, on-demand camouflage that are unparalleled in animals. They also can edit their genetic information as it passes through messenger RNA molecules and they deploy this capability on a massive scale to meet the needs of a changing environment. These and other biological novelties make them attractive for research.</p> <p>In general, genetically tractable model organisms drive modern biological discovery. Researchers take advantage of them to interrogate gene function so that they can better understand the mechanisms that underlie biological processes. Unfortunately, there are no genetically tractable cephalopod models, and this has impeded research. As a group, cephalopods are difficult to rear in captivity because they are very sensitive to changes in water quality, only eat specific items that vary with their life-stage and require precise environmental control to promote reproduction. Because of this, the specimens that are required to work out methods for gene manipulation have not been available. The goal of this grant was to remedy this situation. First, we established conditions for continuous culture of <em>Euprymna berryi</em>, a bobtail squid from the Western Pacific. We then created a culture facility that produces animals to meet scientific demand. Specimens from our culture have been provided to research and education across the country and throughout the world. Using these animals, researchers on our team developed protocols to knockout specific genes using the CRISPR-Cas9 system. We also were able to breed knockout individuals into distinct genetic lines. These advances represent a first for cephalopods and greatly expand research capabilities using these animals. <em>Euprymna berryi</em> is an excellent model for research and is now in a good position to drive future biological discovery.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;Rosenthal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As models for research, the coleoid cephalopods offer tremendous opportunities for discovery based on their biological innovations. They possess the largest nervous system of any invertebrate and express the most sophisticated behaviors. For example, an adult octopus has about as many neurons as a dog, but they are organized in a completely manner. Their ability to learn and remember has been compared to that of crows and, on a cellular level, shares mechanistic similarities to that of mammals. Cephalopod eyes are structurally similar to our own, but they have converged on this design via an independent evolutionary trajectory. Many species of cephalopods have elaborate systems to generate near-perfect, on-demand camouflage that are unparalleled in animals. They also can edit their genetic information as it passes through messenger RNA molecules and they deploy this capability on a massive scale to meet the needs of a changing environment. These and other biological novelties make them attractive for research.  In general, genetically tractable model organisms drive modern biological discovery. Researchers take advantage of them to interrogate gene function so that they can better understand the mechanisms that underlie biological processes. Unfortunately, there are no genetically tractable cephalopod models, and this has impeded research. As a group, cephalopods are difficult to rear in captivity because they are very sensitive to changes in water quality, only eat specific items that vary with their life-stage and require precise environmental control to promote reproduction. Because of this, the specimens that are required to work out methods for gene manipulation have not been available. The goal of this grant was to remedy this situation. First, we established conditions for continuous culture of Euprymna berryi, a bobtail squid from the Western Pacific. We then created a culture facility that produces animals to meet scientific demand. Specimens from our culture have been provided to research and education across the country and throughout the world. Using these animals, researchers on our team developed protocols to knockout specific genes using the CRISPR-Cas9 system. We also were able to breed knockout individuals into distinct genetic lines. These advances represent a first for cephalopods and greatly expand research capabilities using these animals. Euprymna berryi is an excellent model for research and is now in a good position to drive future biological discovery.          Last Modified: 01/27/2021       Submitted by: Joshua Rosenthal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
