<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI-TT: Development of Metabolic Imaging to Improve Treatment of Infertility</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>285504</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kaitlin Bratlie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbratlie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922638</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this PFI project is primarily the advancement of the commercialization of a system to improve clinical in vitro fertilization (IVF). IVF is currently the most effective treatment for infertility, but success rates for IVF remain low, with only ~30% of cycles resulting in live birth which, in turn, leads to high financial and emotional costs. Improving the success rate of IVF would help IVF patients and the approximately 10% of couples who suffer from infertility, and would lead to broad societal and economic benefit. The proposed work makes use of advanced imaging and computational image analysis, and has a tight integration between biology, physics, engineering, clinical medicine, and commercialization. Undergraduate, graduate students, and postdocs, will benefit from this interdisciplinary environment and training. This effort will help increase the involvement of women and underrepresented minorities in science, innovation, and technological commercialization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project tests and develops the use of metabolic imaging as a means to non-invasively measure oocyte quality. Metabolic imaging of oocytes holds great promise for improving IVF success rates: the current inability to determine oocyte quality is one of the major impediments to better IVF treatment, and oocyte quality is believed to be determined by oocyte metabolism. Previous and preliminary data demonstrated that metabolic imaging does not harm mouse oocytes and that it can be used to measure biologically meaningful metabolic differences between different mouse oocytes. The proposed project will expand on that work to investigate the safety and utility of the technology on in vitro matured human oocytes (clinically useless, otherwise discarded material). It is necessary to perform such safety tests before attempting to use metabolic imaging in a clinical setting. This work will also provide information on the metabolism of human oocytes, which is of fundamental import, with broad application for development, infertility, and birth defects. Furthermore, a clinical instrument must be robust and integrate into the clinical workflow. A key challenge is image and data analysis. Thus, this project also seeks to develop and validate fully automated image and data analysis procedures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1827309</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Needleman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Needleman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dan.needleman@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173846730</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000509407</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021381903</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[52 Oxford St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~42221</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~43283</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In vitro fertilization (IVF) has revolutionized the treatment of infertility and currently accounts for over 1% of births in the U.S. However, the success rate for IVF is low, only ~30% of cycles result in live birth, resulting in great emotional and financial costs. One of the most significant reason for these low success rates are limitations to current approaches for selecting high quality oocytes and corresponding embryos for transfer. The current standard method is a morphological examination with conventional transmitted light microscopy. Prior studies have demonstrated that mitochondria are crucial for oocytes and embryos, and defects in mitochondrial metabolism are associated with a reduction in viability. The present project sought to further the development of metabolic imaging, via two-photon fluorescence lifetime imaging microscopy, as a quantitative, non-invasive approach to improve clinical IVF treatment. The work furthered the improvement of the technology regarding safety, reproducibility, and usability. During this project, students and postdocs were trained in interdisciplinary work that entailed a tight integration between biology, physics, engineering, clinical medicine, and commercialization. The completed work advanced the commercialize effort, with the ultimate goal of bringing novel technology to clinic to aid IVF patients and the 10% of couples who suffer from infertility.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Needleman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In vitro fertilization (IVF) has revolutionized the treatment of infertility and currently accounts for over 1% of births in the U.S. However, the success rate for IVF is low, only ~30% of cycles result in live birth, resulting in great emotional and financial costs. One of the most significant reason for these low success rates are limitations to current approaches for selecting high quality oocytes and corresponding embryos for transfer. The current standard method is a morphological examination with conventional transmitted light microscopy. Prior studies have demonstrated that mitochondria are crucial for oocytes and embryos, and defects in mitochondrial metabolism are associated with a reduction in viability. The present project sought to further the development of metabolic imaging, via two-photon fluorescence lifetime imaging microscopy, as a quantitative, non-invasive approach to improve clinical IVF treatment. The work furthered the improvement of the technology regarding safety, reproducibility, and usability. During this project, students and postdocs were trained in interdisciplinary work that entailed a tight integration between biology, physics, engineering, clinical medicine, and commercialization. The completed work advanced the commercialize effort, with the ultimate goal of bringing novel technology to clinic to aid IVF patients and the 10% of couples who suffer from infertility.          Last Modified: 08/30/2020       Submitted by: Daniel Needleman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
