<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBE-RCUK: Co-location of manufacturing and innovation:  drivers and impacts of technological innovation along the wind energy global value chain</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270918.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270918</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many high-technology industries, including clean technology industries, have seen major geographical shifts over the past two decades in which companies expand or move manufacturing of their component supply chain to new countries. These manufacturing shifts raise questions that are important for policy, economic competitiveness, and research. Specifically, what are the reasons for firms to alter or refocus their geographic strategies and physical locations, and whether doing so changes the nature and direction of innovation that such firms undertake. This project examines these questions through the case of the global wind technology industry, where both the demand for and manufacturing of wind turbines have shifted from the United States and Europe to emerging economies, including China. The shifts in the location of manufacturing from countries at the frontier of technology to newer markets can potentially shape R&amp;D strategies, technological innovation, and competitive advantage in the wind sector. Given policy targets for wind deployment in emerging and developing countries, additional expansion of the manufacturing of different wind turbine components to new countries is expected, which means it is important to understand the possible tradeoffs associated with the manufacturing shifts. This research informs the design of policies that spur local manufacturing, economic competitiveness, and technology development in globally-distributed, modern manufacturing industries. It also highlights the ways in which manufacturing shifts affect the ability of technological innovation to meet climate and environmental challenges in the long term, thus supporting design of national and international policies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project analyzes the types of manufacturing that have shifted geographically and, most crucially, whether and how these international shifts in manufacturing impact the direction of innovation in the wind industry. The research focuses on component manufacturers who are often small and medium enterprises (or SMEs) that supply to original equipment manufacturers (OEMs), i.e., the 10-15 manufacturers that assemble wind turbines worldwide. SMEs are particularly relevant for a country's economy as they comprise, for example in the United States, over ninety percent of employer firms. Manufacturing SMEs must innovate to produce goods at increasingly lower costs and/or to develop new capabilities to stay competitive. The project relies on novel data of the wind supply chain at the firm level and a comprehensive mixed-methods approach, including the analysis of global data on OEM-supplier relationships, public policies, component technologies, semi-structured interviews, and patents. In understanding innovation in the global value chain for wind energy that includes both SMEs and larger OEMs, the results of the project contribute to the understanding of what drives decisions by different types of firms to manufacture in their home country or internationally, and whether the location of manufacturing influences the technological focus of innovation and the time-horizon of R&amp;D activities undertaken in a particular industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1829252</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hultman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan E Hultman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hultman@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014053429</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000309981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/16/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hultman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan E Hultman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hultman@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014053429</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000309981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kavita</FirstName>
<LastName>Surana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kavita Surana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ksurana@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000755727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/16/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>003Z</Code>
<Text>SBE-RCUK MOU</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~270918</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-2820b44a-7fff-bf41-1a17-f168f4b0b31b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Scholars and policymakers are grappling with the challenge of enabling innovation across multiple industries to deliver long-term net-zero goals as well as support green growth. Technology suppliers and manufacturers embedded in global value chains are central to delivering these goals because they can help create job opportunities while also shaping the direction of innovation. However, these suppliers find it hard to stay competitive given the globally dispersed nature of most modern industries and the many manufacturing shifts to China and other emerging economies.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The goals of the project were to study (a) the drivers of international shifts of manufacturing location across the global value chain for wind energy technology and (b) how these shifts in manufacturing have impacted the nature and direction of technological innovation in the sector. We focused on wind energy because it, like other clean energy industries, is highly policy driven and may not always behave like other high-tech industries.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The results from the project have been shared with decision makers through widely disseminating research (publications, conferences, workshops). These results are associated with the following publications.</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Surana, K. and Doblinger, C., Anadon, Laura D. and Hultman, N. (2020). Effects of technology complexity on the emergence and evolution of wind industry manufacturing locations along global value chains. </span><em>Nature Energy.&nbsp;</em></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Doblinger C., Surana K., Li D., Hultman, N., Anadon L.D. (2021). Are clean energy technology suppliers in global value chains innovating to meet long-term climate goals? Manuscript submitted for peer review.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Sharma, A., Surana K., George M. (2021). Do clean energy duties generate employment benefits? Manuscript submitted for peer review.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Li D., Anadon L.D., Surana K. (2021). Climbing the global value chain ladder: the relationship between local manufacturing capabilities, demand and the complexity of wind exports and innovation across Chinese regions. Manuscript in progress.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project makes the following</span><span>&nbsp;contributions to research.</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, we advance the understanding of suppliers in global value chains. We identify that the technology complexity of components can drive the locations where new suppliers emerge and how they evolve over time. Our research suggests that it is not just the firm strategy (of the suppliers or their original equipment manufacturers) or public policy that matters for building supply chains but also the technology characteristics of the components.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Second, we advance knowledge on the direction of innovation by introducing the temporal dimension of innovation that complements the existing perspectives on novelty. This temporal dimension is critical for ensuring that innovation addresses long-term societal goals such as climate change.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Third, we extend the existing understanding of what happens to innovation when suppliers work with firms in emerging economies such as China. Our results highlight the importance of policy-induced demand for clean energy technologies and show that international collaborations coupled with demand can enhance long-term innovation in such technologies. Our results also show that restricting international relationships through trade duties does not benefit employment.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project contributes to broader impact for society in the following ways.</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, the project has contributed to developing leadership and international collaborations in research. The project was primarily led by women and five of the eight researchers involved in the project (across the US and UK teams) were women in a field where they are underrepresented. The project directly engaged three Ph.D. students in the research as graduate research assistants. The project also allowed international linkages and very close collaborations with the University of Cambridge, UK and TU Munich, Germany, bringing together valuable international and interdisciplinary perspectives on the topics of global value chains and innovation.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Second, the topic of spurring innovation in global value chains has become prominent in the last few years as countries and regions seek to stay competitive in globally dispersed modern industries. Our project offers evidence as well as actionable pathways for decision makers on how to manage economic development and climate change goals through innovation and manufacturing, despite the increasingly globalized nature of manufacturing industries.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Third, accelerating innovation in clean energy technologies across the value chain is critical for achieving long term societal and climate change goals. Our focus on the temporal dimension of innovation can be a useful lens for decision makers to steer innovation in a direction that is on track to meet such goals. Our results can be applied to other similar clean energy industries or technologies as geothermal, concentrated solar, offshore wind, grid infrastructures, electric vehicles, large-scale direct air capture, and large buildings (as consumers of energy technologies).</span></p> </li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/15/2021<br>      Modified by: Nathan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hultman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Scholars and policymakers are grappling with the challenge of enabling innovation across multiple industries to deliver long-term net-zero goals as well as support green growth. Technology suppliers and manufacturers embedded in global value chains are central to delivering these goals because they can help create job opportunities while also shaping the direction of innovation. However, these suppliers find it hard to stay competitive given the globally dispersed nature of most modern industries and the many manufacturing shifts to China and other emerging economies. The goals of the project were to study (a) the drivers of international shifts of manufacturing location across the global value chain for wind energy technology and (b) how these shifts in manufacturing have impacted the nature and direction of technological innovation in the sector. We focused on wind energy because it, like other clean energy industries, is highly policy driven and may not always behave like other high-tech industries.  The results from the project have been shared with decision makers through widely disseminating research (publications, conferences, workshops). These results are associated with the following publications.   Surana, K. and Doblinger, C., Anadon, Laura D. and Hultman, N. (2020). Effects of technology complexity on the emergence and evolution of wind industry manufacturing locations along global value chains. Nature Energy.    Doblinger C., Surana K., Li D., Hultman, N., Anadon L.D. (2021). Are clean energy technology suppliers in global value chains innovating to meet long-term climate goals? Manuscript submitted for peer review.   Sharma, A., Surana K., George M. (2021). Do clean energy duties generate employment benefits? Manuscript submitted for peer review.   Li D., Anadon L.D., Surana K. (2021). Climbing the global value chain ladder: the relationship between local manufacturing capabilities, demand and the complexity of wind exports and innovation across Chinese regions. Manuscript in progress.   The project makes the following contributions to research.   First, we advance the understanding of suppliers in global value chains. We identify that the technology complexity of components can drive the locations where new suppliers emerge and how they evolve over time. Our research suggests that it is not just the firm strategy (of the suppliers or their original equipment manufacturers) or public policy that matters for building supply chains but also the technology characteristics of the components.   Second, we advance knowledge on the direction of innovation by introducing the temporal dimension of innovation that complements the existing perspectives on novelty. This temporal dimension is critical for ensuring that innovation addresses long-term societal goals such as climate change.   Third, we extend the existing understanding of what happens to innovation when suppliers work with firms in emerging economies such as China. Our results highlight the importance of policy-induced demand for clean energy technologies and show that international collaborations coupled with demand can enhance long-term innovation in such technologies. Our results also show that restricting international relationships through trade duties does not benefit employment.    The project contributes to broader impact for society in the following ways.   First, the project has contributed to developing leadership and international collaborations in research. The project was primarily led by women and five of the eight researchers involved in the project (across the US and UK teams) were women in a field where they are underrepresented. The project directly engaged three Ph.D. students in the research as graduate research assistants. The project also allowed international linkages and very close collaborations with the University of Cambridge, UK and TU Munich, Germany, bringing together valuable international and interdisciplinary perspectives on the topics of global value chains and innovation.   Second, the topic of spurring innovation in global value chains has become prominent in the last few years as countries and regions seek to stay competitive in globally dispersed modern industries. Our project offers evidence as well as actionable pathways for decision makers on how to manage economic development and climate change goals through innovation and manufacturing, despite the increasingly globalized nature of manufacturing industries.   Third, accelerating innovation in clean energy technologies across the value chain is critical for achieving long term societal and climate change goals. Our focus on the temporal dimension of innovation can be a useful lens for decision makers to steer innovation in a direction that is on track to meet such goals. Our results can be applied to other similar clean energy industries or technologies as geothermal, concentrated solar, offshore wind, grid infrastructures, electric vehicles, large-scale direct air capture, and large buildings (as consumers of energy technologies).         Last Modified: 08/15/2021       Submitted by: Nathan E Hultman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
