<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GRC/GRS Plasmonics and Nanophotonics Harvesting, Generating, and Manipulating Light at the Nanoscale. To Be Held at The Grand Summit Hotel, in Sunday River, ME, on July 8-13, 2018.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The overarching goal of this GRC is to advance the leading edge of plasmonics and nanophotonics research by providing a forum where substantial interactions between top researchers and future leaders can stimulate new thinking, facilitate collaborations, and connect minds.  The speakers and discussion leaders at the GRC on Plasmonics and Nanophotonics are some of the most active and world renowned scientists in the field. It includes both senior, well established leaders in the field along with junior scientists and leaders in Nanophotonics. After every speaker there is allocated time for discussion on the speakers topic. There is ample unstructured time in the afternoons for collaborations. The lively poster sessions that have been a Hallmark of the meeting also encourage discussions and collaboration. Support from NSF ECCS will be used to fund speakers, students and some junior researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The seventh biennial Gordon Conference on Plasmonics and Nanophotonics will be held at Grand Summit Hotel at Sunday River, ME, from July 8-13, 2018, preceded by a Gordon Research Seminar on Plasmonics (GRS, July 7-8). The fields of plasmonics and nanophotonics encompass the science and engineering of optical interactions with nanostructures. Prospects of enhanced light harvesting, subwavelength confinement and strong local electromagnetic fields near nanoscale objects have motivated extensive investigation of nanooptical phenomena. As a result of these investigations, applications of plasmonics and nanophotonics have reached across various disciplines, ranging from chemistry to material science, biology, medicine, information, energy, and communications. Examples of topics that have recently emerged and will be extensively discussed in this year's meeting include: quantum mechanical effects, plasmon-induced hot carrier generation, plasmon-enabled photocatalysis  and biotechnology, dielectric nanophotonics, novel sustainable materials, and metasurfaces. In the spirit of the GRC concept, the intent of this meeting is to promote the exchange of ideas and the building of strong relationships among academic, industrial, and government researchers working in the multidisciplinary field of Plasmonics and Nanophotonics. The preceding Gordon Research Seminar is being held to help include more graduate students and young researchers in the field. Speakers, as well as poster presenters, will be encouraged to emphasize advances, unpublished work, new ideas, and speculations for the future on a variety of current topics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1829229</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Nordlander</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter J Nordlander</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nordland@surf.rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7135275171</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The fields of plasmonics and nanophotonics encompass the science and engineering of optical interactions with nanostructures. Prospects of enhanced light harvesting, subwavelength confinement and strong local electromagnetic fields near nanoscale objects have motivated extensive investigation of nanooptical phenomena. As a result of these investigations, applications of plasmonics and nanophotonics have reached across various disciplines, ranging from chemistry to material science, biology, medicine, information, energy, and communications. Examples of topics that have recently emerged and were discussed at this year's meeting included: quantum mechanical effects, plasmon-induced hot carrier generation, plasmon-enabled chemistry and biotechnology, dielectric nanophotonics, novel sustainable materials, and metasurfaces.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Inspired by the huge success of the previous six Gordon Research Conferences on Plasmonics in 2006, 2008, 2010, 2012, 2014, and 2016, the 2018 GRC on Plasmonics and Nanophotonics brought together some of the most active world-renowned senior and junior scientists in the field to deliver exciting, cutting-edge, and thought-provoking invited lectures and to actively engage in extensive scientific discussions and interaction with researchers, students, and postdoctoral fellow participants. After each lecture, there was ample time for lively discussion and question-and-answer sessions among invited speakers, discussion leaders, and all participants. There was unstructured time in the afternoons where the free flow of ideas and discussion among all participants was highly encouraged, and there was also stimulating poster sessions by participants, which was one of the highlights of Gordon Research Conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Nordlander</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The fields of plasmonics and nanophotonics encompass the science and engineering of optical interactions with nanostructures. Prospects of enhanced light harvesting, subwavelength confinement and strong local electromagnetic fields near nanoscale objects have motivated extensive investigation of nanooptical phenomena. As a result of these investigations, applications of plasmonics and nanophotonics have reached across various disciplines, ranging from chemistry to material science, biology, medicine, information, energy, and communications. Examples of topics that have recently emerged and were discussed at this year's meeting included: quantum mechanical effects, plasmon-induced hot carrier generation, plasmon-enabled chemistry and biotechnology, dielectric nanophotonics, novel sustainable materials, and metasurfaces.     Inspired by the huge success of the previous six Gordon Research Conferences on Plasmonics in 2006, 2008, 2010, 2012, 2014, and 2016, the 2018 GRC on Plasmonics and Nanophotonics brought together some of the most active world-renowned senior and junior scientists in the field to deliver exciting, cutting-edge, and thought-provoking invited lectures and to actively engage in extensive scientific discussions and interaction with researchers, students, and postdoctoral fellow participants. After each lecture, there was ample time for lively discussion and question-and-answer sessions among invited speakers, discussion leaders, and all participants. There was unstructured time in the afternoons where the free flow of ideas and discussion among all participants was highly encouraged, and there was also stimulating poster sessions by participants, which was one of the highlights of Gordon Research Conferences.          Last Modified: 12/07/2018       Submitted by: Peter J Nordlander]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
