<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NRI: FND: COLLAB: Intuitive, Wearable Haptic Devices for Communication with Ubiquitous Robots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>327242.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>367242</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This National Robotics Initiative (NRI) project will promote the progress of science and beneficially impact human health and quality of life by developing wearable soft robotic devices with distributed tactile stimulation that enable new forms of communication. Human-robot interactions will be commonplace in the near future.  In applications such as self-driving cars and physically assistive devices, interaction will require effective and intuitive bidirectional communication.  Transferring information through vision and sound can be slow and inappropriate in many circumstances.  This project focuses on haptic (touch-based) robotics to enable communication in a salient but private manner that alleviates demands on other sensory channels. This project serves the national interest by advancing knowledge in the fields of human perception, psychology and neuroscience, while developing novel, convergent technology that integrates concepts across the fields of robotics, haptics, and control engineering. Project results will be disseminated through tactile haptic devices for education and publicly available software and data. The project aims to broaden participation of underrepresented groups in engineering through outreach programs, public lab tours, and the mentoring of female and minority graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Wearable haptic systems have the potential to enable private, salient communication between humans and intelligent systems through an underutilized sensory channel (somatosensation). In this research, information will be transmitted through the haptic channel via wearable, ubiquitous, soft robotic devices that provide both passive and active touch interactions with the human user. This research is comprised of four main objectives. First, a characterization of human perception of the forearm will set the requirements for the frequency, amplitude, directions, spacing, and temporal actuation patterns for a two-dimensional array of haptic stimulators that are able to convey a range of haptic cues. Second, the project will develop a wearable, soft, haptic device able to stimulate the skin of one forearm, while also providing mechanical stimuli that are intended to be explored by the fingertips of the other hand. Third, the project will develop rendering algorithms for the haptic device that take into consideration human perceptual abilities for passive stimulation of the arm and active exploration by the fingertips. Fourth, the project team will create application scenarios to evaluate and refine the system. Wearable haptic systems have potential to improve human health and well-being through a variety of applications including: physical cueing for rehabilitation/movement therapy; explosive ordnance defusing; feedback from assistive devices including mobile robots in the home; tactile communication to enable design and e-commerce; immersion in virtual worlds for education; and the facilitation of remote interaction between people.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1830146</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcia</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Malley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marcia K O'Malley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>omalleym@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133483545</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274808</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~327242</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~16000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
