<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development and Application of Efficient High-order Semi-Lagrangian Schemes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>55590.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>55590</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding behaviors of plasmas plays an increasingly important role in modern science and engineering such as thermo-nuclear fusion, satellite amplifier, and computer chip manufacturing. A fundamental model in plasma physics is the Vlasov-Maxwell system, which is a nonlinear kinetic transport model describing the dynamics of charged particles due to the self-consistent electromagnetic forces. As predictive simulation tools in studying the complex kinetic system, efficient, reliable and accurate transport schemes are of fundamental significance. The main numerical challenges in such studies lie in the high dimensionality, nonlinear coupling, and inherent multi-scale nature in both space and time. Another application concerned in this project is in atmospheric science. One example is the chemistry-climate model in the study of evolution of stratospheric ozone and many other chemical constituents. The present generation of global climate models include hundreds of tracer species in order to adequately represent complex physical and chemical processes, resulting in huge computational cost in computer simulations. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The PI will develop and analyze a class of efficient, reliable and highly accurate numerical methods for transport problems in plasma physics and atmospheric science. A semi-Lagrangian framework will be devised by employing a high order discontinuous Galerkin spatial discretization to take advantage of its many attractive properties, such as flexibility, compactness, and excellent ability to resolve features involving multiple scales. By a careful design in the scheme formulation, the proposed scheme is free of splitting error and able to conserve total mass of the system. Motivated by the work of PI on developing a fast asymptotic preserving Maxwell solver that is capable of recovering the magneto-static limit, the temporal scale separation issue associated with the Vlasov-Maxwell simulations will be addressed. For the applications in the global chemistry-climate modeling, the new schemes can be conveniently adapted to the spherical transport simulations based on the cubed-sphere geometry. Theoretical issues including the stability analysis and error estimates will be investigated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1830838</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Guo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Guo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>weimath.guo@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5175809991</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000687229</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~55590</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Transport phenomena are ubiquitous in nature, which are described mathematically by the so-called transport equations. One celebrated example is the kinetic models arising in a wide range of disciplines, including plasma physics, gas dynamics, semiconductor modeling, socioeconomics, among others. &nbsp;Simulations of transport equations are challenging due to the underlying multiscale features, nonlinearity, multi-physics coupling, and possible high dimensionality. The project establishes an effective framework for simulating transport equations with accuracy, robustness, and efficiency. In particular, a novel computational tool is developed, which is able to resolve complex structures of the solution with desired accuracy. Moreover, the approximation is carefully updated by following the inherent characteristics of the transport equation, and hence the simulation becomes unconditionally stable and highly efficient. The developed framework provides an ideal foundation to simulate the kinetic models. Besides the accuracy and stability, the simulation can further preserve several key physics properties of the kinetic models including mass conservation and positivity preservation, which are critical for reliability and robustness of the simulation. The developed framework is further extended to simulate general transport-dominated models, in which other physics processes are also involved such as diffusion and collision. The boarder impact of the project lies in the advances of both numerical and theoretical tools which either directly or have potential to address some of the longstanding challenges in the real-world transport simulations.</p> <p>Another outcome of the project is the development of effective computational tools to simulate complex models with high dimensionality, which are prevalent in virtually every field of science and engineering. One example is the Vlasov-Maxwell system which plays a fundamental role in plasma physics. Among many existing challenges for Vlasov-Maxwell simulations (e.g., formation of filamentation structures), the curse of dimensionality and the associated huge computational cost have been a key obstacle for high-dimensional computations. The methodology developed in the project can greatly alleviate the curse of dimensionality and simulate the challenging Vlasov-Maxwell system with desired accuracy and manageable recourses. Moreover, the simulation can effectively capture the inherent filamentation structures developed in the solution of the Vlasov-Maxwell system. The project outcome is highly multidisciplinary and hence can benefit many fields across science and engineering. For example, the proposed research will have a direct impact on quantum mechanics for simulating the challenging electronic Schrodinger equations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2020<br>      Modified by: Wei&nbsp;Guo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Transport phenomena are ubiquitous in nature, which are described mathematically by the so-called transport equations. One celebrated example is the kinetic models arising in a wide range of disciplines, including plasma physics, gas dynamics, semiconductor modeling, socioeconomics, among others.  Simulations of transport equations are challenging due to the underlying multiscale features, nonlinearity, multi-physics coupling, and possible high dimensionality. The project establishes an effective framework for simulating transport equations with accuracy, robustness, and efficiency. In particular, a novel computational tool is developed, which is able to resolve complex structures of the solution with desired accuracy. Moreover, the approximation is carefully updated by following the inherent characteristics of the transport equation, and hence the simulation becomes unconditionally stable and highly efficient. The developed framework provides an ideal foundation to simulate the kinetic models. Besides the accuracy and stability, the simulation can further preserve several key physics properties of the kinetic models including mass conservation and positivity preservation, which are critical for reliability and robustness of the simulation. The developed framework is further extended to simulate general transport-dominated models, in which other physics processes are also involved such as diffusion and collision. The boarder impact of the project lies in the advances of both numerical and theoretical tools which either directly or have potential to address some of the longstanding challenges in the real-world transport simulations.  Another outcome of the project is the development of effective computational tools to simulate complex models with high dimensionality, which are prevalent in virtually every field of science and engineering. One example is the Vlasov-Maxwell system which plays a fundamental role in plasma physics. Among many existing challenges for Vlasov-Maxwell simulations (e.g., formation of filamentation structures), the curse of dimensionality and the associated huge computational cost have been a key obstacle for high-dimensional computations. The methodology developed in the project can greatly alleviate the curse of dimensionality and simulate the challenging Vlasov-Maxwell system with desired accuracy and manageable recourses. Moreover, the simulation can effectively capture the inherent filamentation structures developed in the solution of the Vlasov-Maxwell system. The project outcome is highly multidisciplinary and hence can benefit many fields across science and engineering. For example, the proposed research will have a direct impact on quantum mechanics for simulating the challenging electronic Schrodinger equations.          Last Modified: 12/16/2020       Submitted by: Wei Guo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
