<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Support: 2019 Metal Powder Industries Federation (MPIF) Annual Conference;  Phoenix, Arizona; June 23-26, 2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>42333.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>42333</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports 40 graduate and undergraduate students studying at US institutions to participate in the 2019 PowderMET sponsored by the Metal Powder Industries Federation. This premier powder metallurgy conference acts as a bridge between industries, government laboratories, and academic institutions. The award provides student participants with opportunities to exchange ideas with leading researchers and engineers from worldwide industrial and governmental facilities, as well as with students and faculty from both domestic and international schools. In addition to nurturing a powder metallurgy community, participants will learn the latest research areas and results in powder metallurgy. Powder metallurgy is a topic with applications in literally every portion of the manufacturing sector in the American economy, and therefore directly impacts economic welfare and national security in the short term by promulgating information, but in the long term by recruiting high-quality engineers and scientists into this field. The workforce needs of powder metallurgy have not been met for decades; with a workforce that will see large retirements in the next few years, recruitment of current graduate students is essential for this industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project provides the student participants with opportunities to exchange ideas with leading researchers and engineers from worldwide industrial and governmental facilities, as well as with students and faculty from both domestic and international universities. In addition to nurturing a global powder metallurgy (traditional press &amp; sinter, metal injection molding, isostatic pressing, and metal additive manufacturing) vision, participants will learn the latest research areas and results in the fields of interest. These opportunities will not only improve the participants' knowledge in the field but also develop scientists and engineers who are ideally suited to craft the next generation of designs in powder metallurgy that will push the nation's manufacturing capabilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1832745</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jing</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jing Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jz29@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3172787186</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000665951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kester</FirstName>
<LastName>Clarke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kester Clarke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kclarke@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3033842301</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000715823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University Purdue University Indianapolis]]></Name>
<CityName>Indianapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>462025160</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[799 W. Michigan St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~42333</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit.&nbsp; The NSF supported students presented their posters and participate in the conference poster award competition. The relationships with conference participants assisted the students in determining their specific areas of interest in this broad field and create colleagues for future interactions and potential collaborations.</p> <p>Broader Impacts. The NSF grant provided support for 40 selected students with the opportunity to participate in the POWDERMET2019/AMPM2019 annual conferences. The conferences pulled together a broad range of disciplines that define PM and the people who have made significant advances. The conferences not only stimulated learning and training for the students, but also allowed them to be exposed to new research concepts and interact with the researchers defining them. In addition to acquiring knowledge and an appreciation of the breadth of PM and metal AM, becoming involved with professional societies has motivated their intellectual curiosity through developing a network of professional contacts and resources. Additionally, APMI International, a professional society aligned with MPIF through shared staff, has provided a 12-month complimentary membership to encourage professional society participation.&nbsp; This contact network has continued to support students in the long term, throughout their professional career. Underrepresented groups have been given priority in the NSF grant during the selection process, targeting their involvement and ultimate retention in careers related to powder metallurgy and additive manufacturing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Jing&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1832745/1832745_10562198_1575426411244_2019NSFConferenceGrantrecipients--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1832745/1832745_10562198_1575426411244_2019NSFConferenceGrantrecipients--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2019 student receipients"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1832745/1832745_10562198_1575426411244_2019NSFConferenceGrantrecipients--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2019 student receipients"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF grant student recipients at PowderMET2019 conference</div> <div class="imageCredit">MPIF</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jing&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">2019 student receipients</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit.  The NSF supported students presented their posters and participate in the conference poster award competition. The relationships with conference participants assisted the students in determining their specific areas of interest in this broad field and create colleagues for future interactions and potential collaborations.  Broader Impacts. The NSF grant provided support for 40 selected students with the opportunity to participate in the POWDERMET2019/AMPM2019 annual conferences. The conferences pulled together a broad range of disciplines that define PM and the people who have made significant advances. The conferences not only stimulated learning and training for the students, but also allowed them to be exposed to new research concepts and interact with the researchers defining them. In addition to acquiring knowledge and an appreciation of the breadth of PM and metal AM, becoming involved with professional societies has motivated their intellectual curiosity through developing a network of professional contacts and resources. Additionally, APMI International, a professional society aligned with MPIF through shared staff, has provided a 12-month complimentary membership to encourage professional society participation.  This contact network has continued to support students in the long term, throughout their professional career. Underrepresented groups have been given priority in the NSF grant during the selection process, targeting their involvement and ultimate retention in careers related to powder metallurgy and additive manufacturing.          Last Modified: 12/03/2019       Submitted by: Jing Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
