<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop for Women in Machine Learning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Hwa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rhwa@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927148</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Since 2006, the annual workshop for Women in Machine Learning (WiML) has brought together women researchers of all levels, from industry and academia, to exchange research ideas and build mentoring and networking relationships.  The one-day workshop has been especially beneficial for junior graduate students, giving them a supportive environment in which to present their research (in many cases, for the first time) and enabling them to meet peers and more senior researchers. Networking opportunities have helped senior graduate students and postdoctoral fellows find jobs following graduation.  Indirectly, by retaining women in the field, WiML assists in the development of research products by women. Women continue to be underrepresented in the machine learning community. The ability to meet and interact with other women (role models and colleagues) in a technical environment allows women to build confidence in sharing their work; it is the most often cited benefit of the workshop.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop achieves these goals via events including the following. (1) Invited talks by established researchers. Technical talks by researchers from academia and industry share core machine learning research as well as serve as role models. (2) Contributed talks and posters by students provide opportunities for graduate students to showcase their own research and raise the presenters' visibility among their peers. (3) Research and career advice roundtable discussions. WiML matches senior researchers with junior researchers in small discussion and mentoring groups. The support from senior women, many of whom were previous attendees, speaks to how WiML is creating a lasting community where women help retain women in the field. WiML is primarily a technical event. Attendees have substantive technical discussions with other attendees, and many attendees go on to stay in contact with colleagues they meet at WiML as research collaborators. WiML has an established pipeline of senior women who continue to return to the workshop each year to encourage and mentor younger researchers.  WiML has also helped with publicity and coordination when other organizations wanted to host events for women, such as lunches at conferences or more local events.  The WiML Board has released a public directory of women in machine learning (with over 1,300 entries) to assist event organizers in finding female speakers and panelists.  Thus, in addition to the workshop, WiML is becoming the de facto source for connecting and finding women in machine learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1833154</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
<LastName>Broderick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tamara A Broderick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tbroderick@CSAIL.MIT.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000727242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since 2006, the annual workshop for Women in Machine Learning (WiML) has brought together women researchers of all levels, from industry and academia, to exchange research ideas and build mentoring and networking relationships. This particular grant has supported travel for students at US institutions so that they could attend the 2018 and 2019 workshops.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The workshop has been especially beneficial for junior researchers, giving them a supportive environment in which to present their research (in many cases, for the first time) and enabling them to meet peers and more senior researchers. Networking opportunities have helped senior graduate students and postdoctoral fellows find jobs following graduation. Indirectly, by retaining women in the field, WiML has assisted in the development of research products by women. Women continue to be underrepresented in the machine learning community. The ability to meet and interact with other women&mdash;role models and colleagues&mdash;in a technical environment allows women to build confidence in sharing their work; it is the most often cited benefit of the workshop.</p> <p><br />The workshop continues to achieve these goals via events including the following. (1) Invited talks by established researchers. Technical talks by researchers from academia and industry share core machine learning research as well as serve as role models. (2) Contributed talks and posters by students provide opportunities for graduate students to showcase their own research and raise the presenters&rsquo; visibility among their peers. (3) Research and career advice mentoring opportunities from senior researchers.</p> <p><br />WiML is primarily a technical event. Attendees have substantive technical discussions with other attendees, and many attendees go on to stay in contact with colleagues they meet at WiML as research collaborators. WiML has an established pipeline of senior women who continue to return to the workshop each year to encourage and mentor younger researchers.&nbsp; WiML has also helped with publicity and coordination when other organizations wanted to host events for women&mdash;such as lunches at conferences or more local events.&nbsp; The WiML Board has released a public directory of women in machine learning to assist event organizers in finding female speakers and panelists.&nbsp; Thus, in addition to the workshop, WiML is becoming the de facto source for connecting and finding women in machine learning.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2021<br>      Modified by: Tamara&nbsp;A&nbsp;Broderick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since 2006, the annual workshop for Women in Machine Learning (WiML) has brought together women researchers of all levels, from industry and academia, to exchange research ideas and build mentoring and networking relationships. This particular grant has supported travel for students at US institutions so that they could attend the 2018 and 2019 workshops.     The workshop has been especially beneficial for junior researchers, giving them a supportive environment in which to present their research (in many cases, for the first time) and enabling them to meet peers and more senior researchers. Networking opportunities have helped senior graduate students and postdoctoral fellows find jobs following graduation. Indirectly, by retaining women in the field, WiML has assisted in the development of research products by women. Women continue to be underrepresented in the machine learning community. The ability to meet and interact with other women&mdash;role models and colleagues&mdash;in a technical environment allows women to build confidence in sharing their work; it is the most often cited benefit of the workshop.   The workshop continues to achieve these goals via events including the following. (1) Invited talks by established researchers. Technical talks by researchers from academia and industry share core machine learning research as well as serve as role models. (2) Contributed talks and posters by students provide opportunities for graduate students to showcase their own research and raise the presenters’ visibility among their peers. (3) Research and career advice mentoring opportunities from senior researchers.   WiML is primarily a technical event. Attendees have substantive technical discussions with other attendees, and many attendees go on to stay in contact with colleagues they meet at WiML as research collaborators. WiML has an established pipeline of senior women who continue to return to the workshop each year to encourage and mentor younger researchers.  WiML has also helped with publicity and coordination when other organizations wanted to host events for women&mdash;such as lunches at conferences or more local events.  The WiML Board has released a public directory of women in machine learning to assist event organizers in finding female speakers and panelists.  Thus, in addition to the workshop, WiML is becoming the de facto source for connecting and finding women in machine learning.       Last Modified: 08/09/2021       Submitted by: Tamara A Broderick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
