<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pure and Applied Model Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the international conference "Pure and Applied Model Theory" taking place October 25-28, 2018 at the University of Illinois at Chicago. The subject of the conference is model theory, with an emphasis on connections between deep results in pure model theory and applications. Several talks will also touch on connections to algebra, analysis, combinatorics, number theory, infinitary logic, and descriptive set theory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will feature more than twenty talks by leaders in the field. This meeting provides an opportunity for interactions among U.S. and European model theorists, with multiple benefits for both. In addition to the talks, graduate students and junior researchers in attendance will have the opportunity to disseminate their research through a poster session. Financial support to attend the conference will preferentially be given to graduate students, postdoctoral associates, and junior faculty who may not otherwise be able to attend the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1834578</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Baldwin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John T Baldwin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbaldwin@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129963041</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000394443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Freitag</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James E Freitag</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jfreitag@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2174155531</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599309</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S. Marshfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MB 502, M/C 551]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098987217</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The conference Pure and Applied Model Theory took place in Fall of 2018 thanks to support from the University of Illinois at Chicago and the National Science Foundation under award number 1834578. The conference brought together international experts in model theory for talks over 4 days. The conference featured talks in virtually every area of modern model theory, including stability theory and generalizations, infinitary logic, o-minimality, appliocations to difference and differential equations, combinatorics, and number theory.&nbsp;</p> <p>The funding of the NSF particularly allowed for the participation of many graduate students and early career mathematicians. In total, more than 90 non-local mathematicians attended the conference.&nbsp;</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the conference stemmed mainly from the dissemination of high impact mathematical research and opporitunities for collaboration.&nbsp;Speakers at the conference included Boris Zilber, Rahim Moosa, Caroline Terry, Matthiass Aschenbrenner, Lou van den Dries, Ozlem Beylarsan, Alice Medvedev, Maryanthe Malliaris, Chris Laskowski, Paola D'Aquino, Will Boney, Alex Wilkie, Angus Macintyre, Pierre Simon, Charles Steinhorn, Elizabeth Bouscaren, Thomas Scanlon, Zoe Chatzidakis, Gabriel Conant, Anand Pillay, Sergei Starchenko, Artem Chernikov, and Julia Knight.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of the conference centered around training of graduate students and early career mathematicians. More than 40 graduate students attended the meeting.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2019<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;E&nbsp;Freitag</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1834578/1834578_10548750_1576251474144_MarkerPoster_NSF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1834578/1834578_10548750_1576251474144_MarkerPoster_NSF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Conference Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1834578/1834578_10548750_1576251474144_MarkerPoster_NSF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Conference Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference poster for Pure and Applied Model Theory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Freitag</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;E&nbsp;Freitag</div> <div class="imageTitle">Conference Poster</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1834578/1834578_10548750_1576252716835_uic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1834578/1834578_10548750_1576252716835_uic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The University of Illinois at Chicago"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1834578/1834578_10548750_1576252716835_uic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The University of Illinois at Chicago"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The conference took place on campus at the University of Illinois at Chicago.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UIC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;E&nbsp;Freitag</div> <div class="imageTitle">The University of Illinois at Chicago</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The conference Pure and Applied Model Theory took place in Fall of 2018 thanks to support from the University of Illinois at Chicago and the National Science Foundation under award number 1834578. The conference brought together international experts in model theory for talks over 4 days. The conference featured talks in virtually every area of modern model theory, including stability theory and generalizations, infinitary logic, o-minimality, appliocations to difference and differential equations, combinatorics, and number theory.   The funding of the NSF particularly allowed for the participation of many graduate students and early career mathematicians. In total, more than 90 non-local mathematicians attended the conference.   The intellectual merit of the conference stemmed mainly from the dissemination of high impact mathematical research and opporitunities for collaboration. Speakers at the conference included Boris Zilber, Rahim Moosa, Caroline Terry, Matthiass Aschenbrenner, Lou van den Dries, Ozlem Beylarsan, Alice Medvedev, Maryanthe Malliaris, Chris Laskowski, Paola D'Aquino, Will Boney, Alex Wilkie, Angus Macintyre, Pierre Simon, Charles Steinhorn, Elizabeth Bouscaren, Thomas Scanlon, Zoe Chatzidakis, Gabriel Conant, Anand Pillay, Sergei Starchenko, Artem Chernikov, and Julia Knight.   The broader impacts of the conference centered around training of graduate students and early career mathematicians. More than 40 graduate students attended the meeting.        Last Modified: 12/13/2019       Submitted by: James E Freitag]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
