<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Current Developments in Mathematics Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Spiroff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspiroff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for graduate students and early-career postdocs to participate in the conference "Current Developments in Mathematics" which will be held November 16-17, 2018 at the Harvard University Science Center in Cambridge, Massachusetts. The CDM conference is jointly sponsored by Harvard University and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The purpose of the conference is to provide a forum for the latest significant theories and research developments in various branches of advanced mathematics.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Topics presented by prominent speakers include a diverse variety of mathematical research including differential geometry, topology, number theory, algebraic geometry, algebraic topology, stochastic analysis, algebraic combinatorics, Hodge theory, geometric analysis, probability theory, and symplectic geometry. More information can be found at the conference website: www.math.harvard.edu/cdm&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1835084</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shing-Tung</FirstName>
<LastName>Yau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shing-Tung Yau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yau@math.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174950836</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460207</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Oxford Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~15500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Current Developments in Mathematics conference for the year 2019 was organized by David Jerison, Paul Seidel, and Nike Sun from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology; and Denis Auroux, Lauren Williams, Horng-Tzer Yau, and Shing-Tung Yau from Harvard University. It was held from November 22--23 in the Science Center, Lecture Hall C at Harvard University. Five prominent mathematicians working at the forefront of their fields were invited to speak. Graduate students, recent Ph.D.s, and members of underrepresented groups were especially encouraged to participate and apply for support.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>The talks were well-attended by students, postdocs, faculty, and colleagues.</p> <p>Over 150 current students, postdoctoral fellows, and junior faculty attended the CDM 2019 conference. Attendees came from the local Boston and New England area, the New York and mid-Atlantic area, as well as more distant parts of the United States including the Midwest and West coast as well as Canada, China, Europe, and India. The organizers and participants found the conference very successful. Draft versions of the talks were gathered into a booklet which was made available to participants.&nbsp;</p> <p>The following speakers gave talks:</p> <ul> <li>Jun Li (Shanghai Center for Mathematical Sciences): <em>A proof of the structure results of BCOV and YY on the GW invariants of the quintic CY threefolds&nbsp;<br /><br /></em></li> <li>Andre Neves (Chicago): <em>Recent progress on minimal surfaces<br /><br /></em></li> <li>Subhash Khot (NYU): <em>Hardness of Approximation: &nbsp;From the PCP Theorem to the 2-to-2 Games Theorem &amp;&nbsp;</em><em>Characterization of Non-expanding Sets in the Grassmann Graph<br /><br /></em></li> <li>Svetlana Jitomirskaya (UC Irvine): <em>Critical phenomena, arithmetic phase transitions, and universality: &nbsp;some recent results on the almost Mathieu operator<br /><br /></em></li> <li>Geordie Williamson (U Sydney): <em>Parity sheaves and modular representations&nbsp;</em></li> </ul> <p>The conference provided an occasion for researchers of diverse backgrounds to discuss and exchange opinions. Young researchers and graduate students were able to access both fellow researchers and established experts. Over 50 speakers, faculty, and participants including graduate students and postdocs attended the banquet which was jointly funded by the Harvard and MIT Mathematics departments.&nbsp;</p> <p>A diverse group of graduate students and recent Ph.Ds took advantage of the opportunity for travel support.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The conference was advertised on the web at Harvard, AMS, and other organizations. Print posters and email announcements were sent to mathematics departments at US and foreign universities. Registration via website was open in advance of the conference. Graduate students, recent Ph.Ds, and members of underrepresented groups were actively encouraged to apply for support.</p> <p>The conference website continues to be a significant source of information for participants.</p> <p>The conference proceedings will be published in the series, <em>Current Developments in Mathematics</em>.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/08/2020<br>      Modified by: Shing-Tung&nbsp;Yau</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Current Developments in Mathematics conference for the year 2019 was organized by David Jerison, Paul Seidel, and Nike Sun from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology; and Denis Auroux, Lauren Williams, Horng-Tzer Yau, and Shing-Tung Yau from Harvard University. It was held from November 22--23 in the Science Center, Lecture Hall C at Harvard University. Five prominent mathematicians working at the forefront of their fields were invited to speak. Graduate students, recent Ph.D.s, and members of underrepresented groups were especially encouraged to participate and apply for support.     The talks were well-attended by students, postdocs, faculty, and colleagues.  Over 150 current students, postdoctoral fellows, and junior faculty attended the CDM 2019 conference. Attendees came from the local Boston and New England area, the New York and mid-Atlantic area, as well as more distant parts of the United States including the Midwest and West coast as well as Canada, China, Europe, and India. The organizers and participants found the conference very successful. Draft versions of the talks were gathered into a booklet which was made available to participants.   The following speakers gave talks:  Jun Li (Shanghai Center for Mathematical Sciences): A proof of the structure results of BCOV and YY on the GW invariants of the quintic CY threefolds    Andre Neves (Chicago): Recent progress on minimal surfaces   Subhash Khot (NYU): Hardness of Approximation:  From the PCP Theorem to the 2-to-2 Games Theorem &amp; Characterization of Non-expanding Sets in the Grassmann Graph   Svetlana Jitomirskaya (UC Irvine): Critical phenomena, arithmetic phase transitions, and universality:  some recent results on the almost Mathieu operator   Geordie Williamson (U Sydney): Parity sheaves and modular representations    The conference provided an occasion for researchers of diverse backgrounds to discuss and exchange opinions. Young researchers and graduate students were able to access both fellow researchers and established experts. Over 50 speakers, faculty, and participants including graduate students and postdocs attended the banquet which was jointly funded by the Harvard and MIT Mathematics departments.   A diverse group of graduate students and recent Ph.Ds took advantage of the opportunity for travel support.   The conference was advertised on the web at Harvard, AMS, and other organizations. Print posters and email announcements were sent to mathematics departments at US and foreign universities. Registration via website was open in advance of the conference. Graduate students, recent Ph.Ds, and members of underrepresented groups were actively encouraged to apply for support.  The conference website continues to be a significant source of information for participants.  The conference proceedings will be published in the series, Current Developments in Mathematics.        Last Modified: 10/08/2020       Submitted by: Shing-Tung Yau]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
