<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSCI Elements: Software - PFSTRASE - A Parallel FileSystem TRacing and Analysis SErvice to Enhance Cyberinfrastructure Performance and Reliability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>385893.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>385893</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Beverly</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rbeverly@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927068</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will develop an open-source software service, the Parallel FileSystem TRacing and Analysis SErvice (PFSTRASE), that improves the reliability and performance of data storage systems for the nation?s largest supercomputers.  As simulations and computations represent reality more faithfully they grow commensurately in scale along with the size of the data they consume and generate.  To handle the storage and movement of this data, supercomputing systems are built on the backbone of massively parallel data storage systems.  Due to their parallel nature these storage systems are capable of moving data at hundreds of times the speed of conventional storage systems, enabling otherwise impractical computations.  The performance capabilities these storage systems provide is accompanied by a complexity that results in them often functioning significantly less than optimally and even in some instances failing.  This results in wasted computational time and ultimately lost scientific progress.  The state of development of tools that could cast light on these problems and improve storage system reliability and performance is inadequate for current and future computing systems.  PFSTRASE will fill this gap by continually and automatically monitoring storage system health and performance, providing insights through an easy to use interface that will improve the reliability and performance of storage and supercomputer systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Parallel filesystems (PFSs) are the most critical high-availability components of High Performance Computing (HPC) architectures, providing input/output (I/O) services to running computations, the environment that users and system services operate in, and storage for applications and data. Because of this central role, failure or performance degradation events in the PFS impact every user of an HPC resource. PFS events must be dealt with quickly and effectively by system administrators; however, there is typically insufficient information to establish precise causal relationships between PFS activity and events, impeding the implementation of timely and targeted remedies. To fill this information gap, an open-source Parallel FileSystem TRacing and Analysis SErvice (PFSTRASE) that traces and analyzes the requisite data to establish causal relationships between PFS activity and both realized and imminent events will be developed. This project will implement the service for the open-source Lustre filesystem, which is the most commonly used PFS at large-scale HPC sites. Loads for specific PFS directory and file operations will be measured and incorporated into the service to construct authentic server load contributions from every job, process, and user. The service?s infrastructure will continuously monitor the entire PFS and generate a real-time, seamless representation that connects contributions of jobs, processes, and users to storage server loads, network bandwidth, and storage capacities. The infrastructure will provide an easily navigable web interface that presents this data, both real-time and historical, in a visual format.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1835135</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard T Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rtevans@tacc.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199095284</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000721178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 West Braker Lane, Ste 11072]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>077Z</Code>
<Text>CSSI-1: Cyberinfr for Sustained Scientif</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~385893</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
