<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building the Event Horizon Telescope:  Observing Black Holes with Schwarzschild Radius Resolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>431655.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>431655</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Kurczynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is a massive black hole at the center of our galaxy, and similar objects at the centers of other galaxies, objects that distort spacetime by the strength of their immense gravitational fields.  Spatially, a black hole is phenomenally compact.  Nonetheless, Dr. Doeleman and his colleagues, utilizing the combined millimeter-wave radio signals from an array of radiotelescopes located on different continents, will image the event horizon of a black hole.  The combination of high frequency and long interferometer baselines will produce an unprecedented high spatial resolution, and this project presents a scientifically compelling way to utilize it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop broadband very-long-baseline interferometry (VLBI) instrumentation matched to the millimeter- and submillimeter-wave receivers now in use at radiotelescopes suitable for use in the intercontinental array.  With commercially available digital signal processing devices incorporated into custom systems, the instrumentation to be built will achieve 8 GHz of bandwidth in each polarization.  That broad bandwidth is critical for maximizing system sensitivity.  The resulting VLBI network will achieve, at 1.3 mm wavelength, tens of microarcseconds of angular resolution on the sky.  Earlier observations by this team have measured structure on the scale of the Schwarzschild radius of the black hole at the center of our galaxy, and this project plans to observe and image the actual black hole event horizon.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The hardware developed under this program will be made available to the astronomy community.  High-school teachers, undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows will be involved in the research program.  Valuable hands-on training in instrumentation will be provided that will be valuable on other modern radiotelescopes.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funding for this project is being provided by NSF's Division of Astronomical Sciences through its Advanced Technologies and Instrumentation program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1835254</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheperd</FirstName>
<LastName>Doeleman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheperd S Doeleman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sdoeleman@haystack.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7819815904</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000434335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021381516</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174967923</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 Garden St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Stop 23]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003261823</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>161906193</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021381516</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[60 Garden Street Mail Stop 23]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~431655</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Black holes are the most mysterious objects in the Cosmos, and those that are located at the centers of galaxies can be millions or even billions of times more massive than our Sun.&nbsp;&nbsp;Capturing an image of such an object was, for many decades, thought to be impossible.&nbsp;&nbsp;For one, the tremendous gravity of the black hole creates an event horizon, a one-way membrane where the gravitational pull is so strong that light cannot escape.&nbsp;&nbsp;And even if light could escape, black holes are the smallest objects predicted by Einstein's theory of gravity, so no ordinary telescope could hope to see one.&nbsp;&nbsp;And yet, astronomers and physicists have passionately pursued this goal.&nbsp;&nbsp;It would allow us to study in detail how gravity works in the most extreme natural laboratory in the Universe, and we could directly observe how black holes power the intense activity that illuminates the centers of most galaxies.&nbsp;</p> <p>This NSF award allowed our team of astronomers to build and deploy some of the new instrumentation that made this goal a reality.&nbsp;&nbsp;Through NSF support we developed high speed digital recording systems and installed them at radio dishes around the world to create a virtual Earth-sized telescope with the greatest resolving power possible from the surface of our planet.&nbsp;&nbsp;At the Submillimeter Telescope on Mt. Graham in Arizona and the Submillimeter Array in Hawaii, our new instruments captured and recorded radio waves from the edge of a black hole six billion times more massive than our Sun that lies at the center of the Virgo A galaxy.&nbsp;&nbsp;These recordings, made in April 2017, were then combined with similar recordings made at exactly the same time at other radio facilities (the total array included Hawaii, Arizona, Chile, Spain, Mexico and the South Pole) to make the first image of a supermassive black hole.&nbsp;&nbsp;Work at these other sites was led either by us through other grant awards, or by our scientific collaborators.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our results were announced on April 10th, 2019, almost exactly 100 years after Einstein produced his theory of gravity that led to the prediction of what a black hole would look like.&nbsp;&nbsp;The image we made was startlingly similar to these predictions: a bright ring formed by light bending in the immense gravity of the black hole.&nbsp;&nbsp;By measuring the exact size of this ring, our team was able to derive the mass of the black hole and confirm Einstein's gravity to the precision of our measurements.&nbsp;&nbsp;The array we built is called the <strong>Event Horizon Telescope</strong> (EHT).</p> <p>This result has had tremendous impact across the&nbsp;sciences.&nbsp;&nbsp;New tests of gravity now become possible through horizon-scale measurements that will become more precise as the EHT expands in capability.&nbsp;&nbsp;Similarly, the process of inflow and outflow around supermassive black holes at the centers of galaxies - how they 'eat' - can now be studied in extraordinary detail.&nbsp;&nbsp;This NSF award has also planted the seeds for the next steps we will take by supporting work at new EHT sites in Greenland and Kitt Peak (another station in Arizona).&nbsp;&nbsp;At Kitt Peak this award supplied an atomic clock, which ensures that the recordings made during our observations are stable enough to be combined with recordings at other participating sites (these clocks lose only 1 second every 10 million years).&nbsp;&nbsp;At Greenland, new equipment we installed allows remote monitoring of the atomic clock already installed there.&nbsp;&nbsp;These new sites and development of many others will form a 'next-generation' EHT that will make the first 'movies' of black holes.&nbsp;&nbsp;Imagine having a front row seat to true black hole 'cinema' where we can see the event horizon evolve in real-time.</p> <p>For these reasons, the black hole image resonated strongly with the curious public.&nbsp;&nbsp;And we believe it has also struck a chord that cuts across cultures because of the international teamwork required to carry out this project.&nbsp;&nbsp;It has shown what humanity can do when we work together on problems that at first seem impossible - we can succeed.&nbsp;&nbsp;At a time when so many issues divide us, the EHT is an example of how we might tackle even greater global challenges that we will face in the future.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>We are deeply grateful for NSF's support, to the citizens of the United States who have invested in this research, and to our international partners and colleagues for joining with us in this exciting project.&nbsp;&nbsp;It is a privilege to be able to report back on our discoveries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Sheperd&nbsp;S&nbsp;Doeleman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1835254/1835254_10290176_1585740645179_msri_globe--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1835254/1835254_10290176_1585740645179_msri_globe--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The Event Horizon Telescope Array"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1835254/1835254_10290176_1585740645179_msri_globe--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The Event Horizon Telescope Array"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stations used in 2017 to make the first black hole image are shown in yellow.  New sites due to come on line soon are in orange, and those under development are in red.  Possible new sites for a 'next-generation' EHT are shown in blue.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Center for Astrophysics | Harvard & Smithsonian</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sheperd&nbsp;S&nbsp;Doeleman</div> <div class="imageTitle">The Event Horizon Telescope Array</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1835254/1835254_10290176_1585761064865_eso1907a_aas_copy_cropped--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1835254/1835254_10290176_1585761064865_eso1907a_aas_copy_cropped--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image of the Supermassive Black Hole M87"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1835254/1835254_10290176_1585761064865_eso1907a_aas_copy_cropped--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image of the Supermassive Black Hole M87"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image shows the ring of light formed by radio waves bending in the immense gravity of a black hole with a mass that is 6.5 billion times that of our Sun.  The dark region at the center is caused by light disappearing through the event horizon, and is three times the size of our Solar System.</div> <div class="imageCredit">The Event Horizon Telescope Collaboration</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sheperd&nbsp;S&nbsp;Doeleman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image of the Supermassive Black Hole M87</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Black holes are the most mysterious objects in the Cosmos, and those that are located at the centers of galaxies can be millions or even billions of times more massive than our Sun.  Capturing an image of such an object was, for many decades, thought to be impossible.  For one, the tremendous gravity of the black hole creates an event horizon, a one-way membrane where the gravitational pull is so strong that light cannot escape.  And even if light could escape, black holes are the smallest objects predicted by Einstein's theory of gravity, so no ordinary telescope could hope to see one.  And yet, astronomers and physicists have passionately pursued this goal.  It would allow us to study in detail how gravity works in the most extreme natural laboratory in the Universe, and we could directly observe how black holes power the intense activity that illuminates the centers of most galaxies.   This NSF award allowed our team of astronomers to build and deploy some of the new instrumentation that made this goal a reality.  Through NSF support we developed high speed digital recording systems and installed them at radio dishes around the world to create a virtual Earth-sized telescope with the greatest resolving power possible from the surface of our planet.  At the Submillimeter Telescope on Mt. Graham in Arizona and the Submillimeter Array in Hawaii, our new instruments captured and recorded radio waves from the edge of a black hole six billion times more massive than our Sun that lies at the center of the Virgo A galaxy.  These recordings, made in April 2017, were then combined with similar recordings made at exactly the same time at other radio facilities (the total array included Hawaii, Arizona, Chile, Spain, Mexico and the South Pole) to make the first image of a supermassive black hole.  Work at these other sites was led either by us through other grant awards, or by our scientific collaborators.  Our results were announced on April 10th, 2019, almost exactly 100 years after Einstein produced his theory of gravity that led to the prediction of what a black hole would look like.  The image we made was startlingly similar to these predictions: a bright ring formed by light bending in the immense gravity of the black hole.  By measuring the exact size of this ring, our team was able to derive the mass of the black hole and confirm Einstein's gravity to the precision of our measurements.  The array we built is called the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT).  This result has had tremendous impact across the sciences.  New tests of gravity now become possible through horizon-scale measurements that will become more precise as the EHT expands in capability.  Similarly, the process of inflow and outflow around supermassive black holes at the centers of galaxies - how they 'eat' - can now be studied in extraordinary detail.  This NSF award has also planted the seeds for the next steps we will take by supporting work at new EHT sites in Greenland and Kitt Peak (another station in Arizona).  At Kitt Peak this award supplied an atomic clock, which ensures that the recordings made during our observations are stable enough to be combined with recordings at other participating sites (these clocks lose only 1 second every 10 million years).  At Greenland, new equipment we installed allows remote monitoring of the atomic clock already installed there.  These new sites and development of many others will form a 'next-generation' EHT that will make the first 'movies' of black holes.  Imagine having a front row seat to true black hole 'cinema' where we can see the event horizon evolve in real-time.  For these reasons, the black hole image resonated strongly with the curious public.  And we believe it has also struck a chord that cuts across cultures because of the international teamwork required to carry out this project.  It has shown what humanity can do when we work together on problems that at first seem impossible - we can succeed.  At a time when so many issues divide us, the EHT is an example of how we might tackle even greater global challenges that we will face in the future.    We are deeply grateful for NSF's support, to the citizens of the United States who have invested in this research, and to our international partners and colleagues for joining with us in this exciting project.  It is a privilege to be able to report back on our discoveries.          Last Modified: 04/01/2020       Submitted by: Sheperd S Doeleman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
