<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for the 38th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS 18)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matt Mutka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmutka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927344</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is to assist US-based graduate students to attend the 38th Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS 2018) in Vienna, Austria. Participation in ICDCS and similar conferences is a valuable and important part of the graduate school experience. It provides students with the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers, and exposes students to leading work and practical industry practices in this important area of research.  The long-term merits of this program's impact on distributed computing research is well established. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will be held in Vienna, Austria, July 2-5, will span four days and will consist of technical paper presentations, panels, industry presentations, posters, and demonstrations.  It will also feature keynote speeches from leading researchers and practitioners in the field.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funds will be dispersed with preference given to students who would not otherwise be able to attend the conference and students who are not already scheduled to present a paper, paying particular attention to diversity and relevance of the student's research interest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1836366</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaodong Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zhang@cse.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142922770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported the travel of students and junior faculty from US universities to attend the 38th IEEE International Conference on Distributed computing Systems (ICDCS). This conference has made significant impacts to the computing community since it was founded in 1979. The&nbsp;published papers have influenced the design and implemntation of many distributed systems, software and applications in the society today.</p> <p>ICDCS 2018 was held on July 2-8, 2018 in Vienna, Austria. This year's conference accepted 98 papers from 451 submissions (less than 22% acceptance rate). In addition to the main conference, there&nbsp;were 10 related workshops organized before, during, and after the conference. The goal of the travel grant was to encourage students, who may typically have financial obstacles, to attend ICDCS 2018.</p> <p>We received 30 applications, and gave nine NSF awards. Jointly with IEEE, we supported two female students, and one African-American student. Besides technical paper presentations, the conference offered a wide range of technical activities including technical committee meetings and keynote talks. Attending such a high-caliber technical conference is extremely valuable for future researchers and IT professionals. Participants were exposed to interact with peer graduate students, researchers, and experts from all over the world, gaining knowledge that is likely to inspire them to make innovation in the field.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Xiaodong&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported the travel of students and junior faculty from US universities to attend the 38th IEEE International Conference on Distributed computing Systems (ICDCS). This conference has made significant impacts to the computing community since it was founded in 1979. The published papers have influenced the design and implemntation of many distributed systems, software and applications in the society today.  ICDCS 2018 was held on July 2-8, 2018 in Vienna, Austria. This year's conference accepted 98 papers from 451 submissions (less than 22% acceptance rate). In addition to the main conference, there were 10 related workshops organized before, during, and after the conference. The goal of the travel grant was to encourage students, who may typically have financial obstacles, to attend ICDCS 2018.  We received 30 applications, and gave nine NSF awards. Jointly with IEEE, we supported two female students, and one African-American student. Besides technical paper presentations, the conference offered a wide range of technical activities including technical committee meetings and keynote talks. Attending such a high-caliber technical conference is extremely valuable for future researchers and IT professionals. Participants were exposed to interact with peer graduate students, researchers, and experts from all over the world, gaining knowledge that is likely to inspire them to make innovation in the field.       Last Modified: 07/04/2019       Submitted by: Xiaodong Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
