<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: The Relationship between Agriculture and Population Distribution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wolfgang Alders, of the University of California, Berkeley, will undertake research to study settlement patterns among Swahili communities prior to and during the development of the plantation economy in Zanzibar, from AD 1500-1850. The mid-19th-century plantation system in Zanzibar is described as an imported social landscape run predominately by Omani landowners, and worked by enslaved people drawn from many parts of East Africa. However, it is also clear that the plantation system was built on top of at least a millennium of settlement by indigenous Swahili coastal people on Zanzibar, which is largely undocumented outside the coastal rim prior to the 19th century. As such, the project contributes to the archaeology of the colonial early modern period in an African context, and breaks new ground by investigating the junctures between understandings of Zanzibar's 19th-century plantation societies and the long-term archaeology of Swahili communities. The research will build on work in coastal East African archaeology to consider the ways that rural Swahili people were entangled in both local and global social and political processes in the western Indian Ocean. The research will advance the academic and intellectual development of a graduate student. It will also contribute to understanding from a worldwide perspective of how traditional communities are integrated into broader international networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will survey landscapes across the western and eastern landscapes of north-central Zanzibar (Unguja) Island, Tanzania. The western part of Zanzibar is an ideal place for elucidating the courses of settlement in relation to the development of plantation economies, since these regions lie within the most fertile agricultural parts of the island. The eastern regions play an important role for comparative survey data, since they are rockier, less suitable for agriculture, and were possibly an area of refuge for people dispossessed from the prime plantation land. Judgmental surveys starting from above-ground 19th-century plantation sites will be used to inform probabilistic shovel test-pit surveys across the larger region. This evidence will be used to chart long-term Swahili settlement in the rural countryside from AD 1500-1850, and to elucidate how settlement related to social and ecological histories at different scales.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1836770</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Maher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa A Maher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maher@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106423392</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667992</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wolfgang</FirstName>
<LastName>Alders</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wolfgang Alders</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alders@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5105754392</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000769616</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project used archaeological methods to understand the long-term history of 19<sup>th</sup>-century clove plantation regions in Zanzibar, Tanzania. Zanzibar is an island off the coast of Tanzania, which underwent significant transformations in the 19<sup>th</sup> century as urban areas developed into a wealthy commercial nexus for the ivory and slave trade in East Africa, while landowners in rural areas developed intensive clove farming using enslaved East Africans for labor. The island lies offshore of the Swahili coast, an area stretching from Somalia to Mozambique that has been united by shared cultural practices, the religion of Islam, and specific settlement formations since at least the 8<sup>th</sup> century AD. Survey results showed patterns of settlement in inland areas from the 11<sup>th</sup> to 19<sup>th</sup> centuries, as well as evidence for craft production and consumption of imported luxury ceramics from the Indian Ocean rim, China, and Europe.</p> <p>Systematic archaeological surveys showed that from the 16<sup>th</sup>-19<sup>th</sup> centuries AD, settlement intensified across various environmental zones in inland Zanzibar and related to a phase of agricultural intensification that became the foundation of the 19<sup>th</sup>-20<sup>th</sup>-century clove plantation economy. Furthermore, these surveys also detected an early phase of settlement expansion from the 11<sup>th</sup>-14<sup>th</sup> centuries AD in inland areas. While many small hamlets and field houses of the late 2<sup>nd</sup> millennium were detected outside any areas of earlier settlement, some of the largest 19<sup>th</sup>-century sites developed directly over or adjacent to earlier village sites. For instance, a 19<sup>th</sup>-20<sup>th</sup>-century sugar plantation was built directly over an 11<sup>th</sup>-14<sup>th</sup>-century village, which also had evidence for 16<sup>th</sup>-18<sup>th</sup>-century occupations based on local ceramic decorations. The results suggest mostly continuous occupation in many rural areas from the earliest phase of settlement to the present.</p> <p>While the Swahili settlements on the coastal fringe of Zanzibar island are well-understood, the areas in the interior were only known prior to this survey from the 19<sup>th</sup> century onward, as clove plantations developed and intensified. This survey has systematically charted and described the long-term history for a sample of the inland region, to better understand the relationships between rural inland sites and their coastal counterparts from the period of earliest settlement to the 19<sup>th</sup> century. Through an examination of settlement patterns and ceramic types across a variety of microenvironments, the research addressed long-term social change in small-scale communities. The project also aimed to understand changes in human activities in ecological contexts and landscapes of the past and present. This broader project directly addresses these concerns through an approach that integrates ethnographic research on present-day land use with archaeological investigations of long-term land use in the past.</p> <p>This research also involved training and instructing American and Zanzibari students in remote sensing technologies, ceramic analysis, geoarchaeological methods, GIS analysis, statistical analysis, and social and political theory. The project involved collaboration with museum officials in Zanzibar and Tanzanian students, for fieldwork and analysis. Furthermore, results from this research are displayed and presented in public outreach events about the nature and results of research for audiences in both the USA and Zanzibar. This outreach helps to broaden an understanding of social histories in Africa and globally.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595887196501_DSC_0381--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595887196501_DSC_0381--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rice plain, western region"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595887196501_DSC_0381--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rice plain, western region"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Settlement in the western region was sparse before the 18th and 19th centuries, when small field houses and hamlets developed around agricultural areas.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wolfgang Alders</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rice plain, western region</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886063994_19th_century--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886063994_19th_century--rgov-800width.jpg" title="19th century imported ceramics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886063994_19th_century--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="19th century imported ceramics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Assemblage of 19th century imported ceramics from Europe, India, Arabia, and China</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wolfgang Alders</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</div> <div class="imageTitle">19th century imported ceramics</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886254130_kiricacha_ceramics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886254130_kiricacha_ceramics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ceramics, AD 1100-1300"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886254130_kiricacha_ceramics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ceramics, AD 1100-1300"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Locally-made decorated ceramics from a site dated to AD 1100-1300</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wolfgang Alders</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ceramics, AD 1100-1300</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886903134_DSC_0268--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886903134_DSC_0268--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Stone structure, possible oven"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595886903134_DSC_0268--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Stone structure, possible oven"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Remains of a stone structure with a semi-circular interior space, possibly an oven, from a site dated to the 16th-19th centuries.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wolfgang Alders</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</div> <div class="imageTitle">Stone structure, possible oven</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595887090166_DSC_0239--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595887090166_DSC_0239--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dry-stone wall, or bigili"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595887090166_DSC_0239--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dry-stone wall, or bigili"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stacked stone wall, made without mortar, at a small site in the eastern region, with early 2nd millennium materials and a later reoccupation from the 16th-19th century. Oral histories attest that these walls were made to protect crops from animals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wolfgang Alders</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dry-stone wall, or bigili</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595885880054_19thc_ceramics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595885880054_19thc_ceramics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="16th-19th century local ceramics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1836770/1836770_10585180_1595885880054_19thc_ceramics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="16th-19th century local ceramics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Bottom left ceramics with impressed dashes on the shoulder are likely 16th-18th century; ceramics with arcs on the shoulder are likely 19th century</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wolfgang Alders</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wolfgang&nbsp;Alders</div> <div class="imageTitle">16th-19th century local ceramics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project used archaeological methods to understand the long-term history of 19th-century clove plantation regions in Zanzibar, Tanzania. Zanzibar is an island off the coast of Tanzania, which underwent significant transformations in the 19th century as urban areas developed into a wealthy commercial nexus for the ivory and slave trade in East Africa, while landowners in rural areas developed intensive clove farming using enslaved East Africans for labor. The island lies offshore of the Swahili coast, an area stretching from Somalia to Mozambique that has been united by shared cultural practices, the religion of Islam, and specific settlement formations since at least the 8th century AD. Survey results showed patterns of settlement in inland areas from the 11th to 19th centuries, as well as evidence for craft production and consumption of imported luxury ceramics from the Indian Ocean rim, China, and Europe.  Systematic archaeological surveys showed that from the 16th-19th centuries AD, settlement intensified across various environmental zones in inland Zanzibar and related to a phase of agricultural intensification that became the foundation of the 19th-20th-century clove plantation economy. Furthermore, these surveys also detected an early phase of settlement expansion from the 11th-14th centuries AD in inland areas. While many small hamlets and field houses of the late 2nd millennium were detected outside any areas of earlier settlement, some of the largest 19th-century sites developed directly over or adjacent to earlier village sites. For instance, a 19th-20th-century sugar plantation was built directly over an 11th-14th-century village, which also had evidence for 16th-18th-century occupations based on local ceramic decorations. The results suggest mostly continuous occupation in many rural areas from the earliest phase of settlement to the present.  While the Swahili settlements on the coastal fringe of Zanzibar island are well-understood, the areas in the interior were only known prior to this survey from the 19th century onward, as clove plantations developed and intensified. This survey has systematically charted and described the long-term history for a sample of the inland region, to better understand the relationships between rural inland sites and their coastal counterparts from the period of earliest settlement to the 19th century. Through an examination of settlement patterns and ceramic types across a variety of microenvironments, the research addressed long-term social change in small-scale communities. The project also aimed to understand changes in human activities in ecological contexts and landscapes of the past and present. This broader project directly addresses these concerns through an approach that integrates ethnographic research on present-day land use with archaeological investigations of long-term land use in the past.  This research also involved training and instructing American and Zanzibari students in remote sensing technologies, ceramic analysis, geoarchaeological methods, GIS analysis, statistical analysis, and social and political theory. The project involved collaboration with museum officials in Zanzibar and Tanzanian students, for fieldwork and analysis. Furthermore, results from this research are displayed and presented in public outreach events about the nature and results of research for audiences in both the USA and Zanzibar. This outreach helps to broaden an understanding of social histories in Africa and globally.       Last Modified: 07/27/2020       Submitted by: Wolfgang Alders]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
