<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for the 256th National Meeting and Exposition of the American Chemical Society Symposium "Block Polymer Synthesis and Self-Assembly", Boston, MA (August 19-23, 2018)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL AND NONTECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Funds in the amount of $5000 are requested for support of US based participants in the symposium on "Block Polymer Synthesis and Self-Assembly", to be held as part of the ACS POLY Division at the  2018 National ACS meeting in Boston MA, August 18-22, 2018. The funds will be used to pay the meeting registration fees for postdoc, junior faculty, and other scientists in the early stages of post PhD independent research. The symposium will cover a broad array of topics in newest developments in block polymer synthesis, self-assembly , characterization and morphology. Emphasis will be given to presentations by junior workers in the field and their associated new directions with the goal of encouraging future STEM  development and people-power in the field.  The symposium includes both invited and contributed speakers. Of the sixteen invited speakers listed, two are postdocs, seven are assistant professors and two are from industry. Contributed papers include a majority from junior researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1836411</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lynd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathaniel Lynd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lynd@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122322534</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000699619</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The DMR-POL program provided funding to reimburse travel to the 256<sup>th</sup>National Meeting and Exposition of the American Chemical Society in Boston, MA, August 19&ndash;23, 2018 to speakers invited to present in a symposium titled &ldquo;Block Polymer Synthesis and Self-Assembly.&rdquo; The symposium discussed the future innovation of block polymer synthesis and self-assembly by attracting researchers with a diverse spectrum of technical expertise to a single forum. Emerging challenges in block polymer materials were featured by providing broad exposure to junior researchers who are expanding the frontiers of knowledge in new directions. Researchers with expertise in synthesis, self-assembly, characterization, industry, and theory filled the roster of speakers and participants in networking activities. Block polymer materials represent a key nanotechnology that forms the basis for a broad range of established and emerging technologies such as patterned media, semiconductor manufacturing, biomedical/pharmaceutical materials, elastomers, and energy recovery, storage, and generation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The symposium advanced knowledge by providing a forum to engage with the latest developments in the field of block polymer synthesis and self-assembly. A particular emphasis of the symposium was presenting the work of junior workers in the field and their associated new research directions. The broad audience in attendance at the American Chemical Society meeting will provide ample opportunity for cross-fertilization across academic and industrial disciplines, where the newest ideas of academia meet the needs of industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The symposium will further the goal of broadening participation in the enterprise of research. The broader impacts of the proposed symposium were predicated on both the cross-fertilization between academia and industry, and also on broadening exposure to a diverse group of early career researchers. For academic-industrial cross-fertilization, the newest ideas of academia will meet the current needs of industry. Representative scientists from industry have been invited to speak at the symposium in order to guarantee presence. Contributed talks from graduate students and postdocs provided exposure to the youngest STEM researchers in our field, while invited presentations provided a strategic opportunity to draw appropriate audiences, and also to provide a venue to feature diverse tenure-track early-career faculty as emerging leaders in block polymer materials science.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Nathaniel&nbsp;Lynd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The DMR-POL program provided funding to reimburse travel to the 256thNational Meeting and Exposition of the American Chemical Society in Boston, MA, August 19&ndash;23, 2018 to speakers invited to present in a symposium titled "Block Polymer Synthesis and Self-Assembly." The symposium discussed the future innovation of block polymer synthesis and self-assembly by attracting researchers with a diverse spectrum of technical expertise to a single forum. Emerging challenges in block polymer materials were featured by providing broad exposure to junior researchers who are expanding the frontiers of knowledge in new directions. Researchers with expertise in synthesis, self-assembly, characterization, industry, and theory filled the roster of speakers and participants in networking activities. Block polymer materials represent a key nanotechnology that forms the basis for a broad range of established and emerging technologies such as patterned media, semiconductor manufacturing, biomedical/pharmaceutical materials, elastomers, and energy recovery, storage, and generation.     The symposium advanced knowledge by providing a forum to engage with the latest developments in the field of block polymer synthesis and self-assembly. A particular emphasis of the symposium was presenting the work of junior workers in the field and their associated new research directions. The broad audience in attendance at the American Chemical Society meeting will provide ample opportunity for cross-fertilization across academic and industrial disciplines, where the newest ideas of academia meet the needs of industry.     The symposium will further the goal of broadening participation in the enterprise of research. The broader impacts of the proposed symposium were predicated on both the cross-fertilization between academia and industry, and also on broadening exposure to a diverse group of early career researchers. For academic-industrial cross-fertilization, the newest ideas of academia will meet the current needs of industry. Representative scientists from industry have been invited to speak at the symposium in order to guarantee presence. Contributed talks from graduate students and postdocs provided exposure to the youngest STEM researchers in our field, while invited presentations provided a strategic opportunity to draw appropriate audiences, and also to provide a venue to feature diverse tenure-track early-career faculty as emerging leaders in block polymer materials science.          Last Modified: 09/29/2019       Submitted by: Nathaniel Lynd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
