<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference in Commutative Algebra</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in a conference on commutative algebra, KUMUNU 2018, which will be held at the University of Kansas, Lawrence, Oct 13-14, 2018. KUMUNU (which is named for its original participating institutions: the University of Kansas, the University of Missouri, Columbia, and the University of Nebraska, Lincoln) is an annual conference (held since 1999) for commutative algebraists in the Great Plains region. Major goals specific to KUMUNU 2018 are to broaden the geographic reach of the conference, promote a connection between commutative algebra and related areas, and showcase the research of early career mathematicians. To promote connections between commutative algebra and other areas, talks from some experts on tropical geometry, convex geometry, and optimization are included. The conference will also include a poster session for junior researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The general goal of KUMUNU is to provide a setting to share cutting-edge mathematical research and promote collaborations among algebraists in or within driving distance of the Great Plains region. KUMUNU 2018 aims to advance mathematics through the dissemination of new and innovative results and techniques via research talks. These talks are intended to inspire participating mathematicians and promote collaboration. Invited speakers are David Eisenbud (University of California), Raymond Heitmann (University of Texas), Siamak Yassemi (University of Tehran), Ryo Takahashi (Nagoya University), Jason McCullough (Iowa State University), Parangarma Sarkar (University of Missouri), Kyungyong Lee (University of Nebraska).  Informal discussions between talks will help spread new results and ideas. Talks will be held from noon on Saturday to noon on Sunday, thereby minimizing expenses for participants. Award funds will defray one night's accommodation and travel expenses, with an emphasis on support of graduate students and early-career researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1836048</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hailong</FirstName>
<LastName>Dao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hailong Dao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hdao@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7858643651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Katz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Katz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlk53@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7858643441</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000723851</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<ZipCode>660457552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076248616</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KANSAS CENTER FOR RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007180078</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Kansas Center for Research, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2385 Irving Hill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~11000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>KUMUNU (which is named for its original participating institutions (the University of Kansas, the University of Missouri?Columbia, and the University of Nebraska?Lincoln) has been an annual conference for commutative algebraists in the Great Plains region since 1999. In 2018 the conference was held in Lawrence, Kansas (the weekend of October 13-14). <br /><br />Overall, there were 70&nbsp; participants from 15&nbsp; different institutions.&nbsp; Of the participants, 12 were women (18 %). <br /><br />As per tradition, the conference invited a number of local&nbsp; institutions and some outside speakers. For the 2018 KUMUNU, the speakers were&nbsp; (1 female, 5 males)<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Raymond Heitmann, University of Texas <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Jack Jeffries, University of Michigan <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Kyungyong Lee, University of Nebraska <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Jason McCullough, Iowa State University <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Ryo Takahashi, Nagoya University <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Parangamar Sarkar, University of Missouri <br /><br />The talks were excellent and very well-received. They&nbsp; covered a number of topics at the forefront of research in commutative algebra and related areas. Some of them are on topics connecting different areas. For example, Heitmann talked about extended plus closure and connections to the new breakthrough of perfectoid spaces. Jeffries talked about new work classifying singularities using differential operators.&nbsp;&nbsp; Lee discussed how to use cluster algebra to study indecomposable modules over artinian Gorenstein rings. Takahashi solved the question of when every ideal is isomorphic to a trace ideal and McCullough talked about singularities of Rees-like algebras, a new construction that features in the disproof of the Eisenbud-Goto conjecture. Last but not least, Sarkar (a postdoc at Missouri), talked about mixed multiplicities of general filtrations. <br /><br /><br /><br />The conference also hold a poster session where young people can present and talk about their works. Twelve posters were presented by graduate students and postdocs from University of Kansas,&nbsp; Purdue, University of Arkansas, University of Nebraska, University of Mississippi, Notre Dame University. The topics are broad: symbolic defects of edge ideals, Rees algebra of module of differentials, generalized Serre?s conditions, finite type for syzygies of Cohen-Macaulay, derived categories of locally complete intersections, etc. The posters attracted initiated comments and lively conversations.&nbsp; <br /><br /><br />Due to some generous help from KU and the handwork of local students and faculties, the conference ran very smoothly and left a very positive&nbsp; impression to the participants. <br /><br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Hailong&nbsp;Dao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ KUMUNU (which is named for its original participating institutions (the University of Kansas, the University of Missouri?Columbia, and the University of Nebraska?Lincoln) has been an annual conference for commutative algebraists in the Great Plains region since 1999. In 2018 the conference was held in Lawrence, Kansas (the weekend of October 13-14).   Overall, there were 70  participants from 15  different institutions.  Of the participants, 12 were women (18 %).   As per tradition, the conference invited a number of local  institutions and some outside speakers. For the 2018 KUMUNU, the speakers were  (1 female, 5 males)         Raymond Heitmann, University of Texas          Jack Jeffries, University of Michigan          Kyungyong Lee, University of Nebraska          Jason McCullough, Iowa State University          Ryo Takahashi, Nagoya University          Parangamar Sarkar, University of Missouri   The talks were excellent and very well-received. They  covered a number of topics at the forefront of research in commutative algebra and related areas. Some of them are on topics connecting different areas. For example, Heitmann talked about extended plus closure and connections to the new breakthrough of perfectoid spaces. Jeffries talked about new work classifying singularities using differential operators.   Lee discussed how to use cluster algebra to study indecomposable modules over artinian Gorenstein rings. Takahashi solved the question of when every ideal is isomorphic to a trace ideal and McCullough talked about singularities of Rees-like algebras, a new construction that features in the disproof of the Eisenbud-Goto conjecture. Last but not least, Sarkar (a postdoc at Missouri), talked about mixed multiplicities of general filtrations.     The conference also hold a poster session where young people can present and talk about their works. Twelve posters were presented by graduate students and postdocs from University of Kansas,  Purdue, University of Arkansas, University of Nebraska, University of Mississippi, Notre Dame University. The topics are broad: symbolic defects of edge ideals, Rees algebra of module of differentials, generalized Serre?s conditions, finite type for syzygies of Cohen-Macaulay, derived categories of locally complete intersections, etc. The posters attracted initiated comments and lively conversations.     Due to some generous help from KU and the handwork of local students and faculties, the conference ran very smoothly and left a very positive  impression to the participants.            Last Modified: 05/30/2020       Submitted by: Hailong Dao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
