<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on Real Time Data Analytics for Resilient Electric Grid. To Be Held in Portland, Oregon, August 4-5, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49992.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49992</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Availability of data from massive sensors deployment enables novel data-driven monitoring and control strategies in the power grid with improved decision support for enhancing resiliency. This workshop will focus on identifying the problem with evolving smart grid complexity and the recent advancements in possible solutions to enable resiliency of the power grid, specifically focused on utilizing real-time data analytics. This workshop will have top expert in data analytics, cyber security, resiliency and electric grid operation from federal agencies, utilities, ISOs, vendors, and NSF awardee and underrepresented minority and women participants will be highly encouraged. Although the majority of the participants will be from the power and energy area, some selected experts from data science and analytics will be invited to participate in the workshop.  This will allow the participants to learn about best practices in other areas to implement in power and energy systems. Strategies identified by the stakeholders at the workshop will result in exchange of ideas and educational content, in the preparation of a highly-trained workforce to manage the complex grid of the future. Research needs identified by the stakeholders will result in better investment by federal agencies and advancing the Nation towards the resilient electric grid.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will result in new strategies and ideas for data-science approaches to enable resiliency of the electric grid. Phasor measurement units (PMUs) provide real time situational awareness and decision support. Distribution automation and smart meters enables advanced volt-var control, real time load behavior tracking, outage management and transactive control. Enhanced visibility of low voltage distribution network enabled by data sensors may help energy producers and consumers to better manage their energy portfolio for resilient operation. Furthermore, an increasing number of digital devices and sensor data in this cyber-physical electric grid also need solutions for data anomalies and cyber-security management.  One of the focus areas of this workshop is real time data analytics to enable resilient electric grid. Big data is generated and monitored ubiquitously in smart grids, but largely unexploited in discovering knowledge and new solutions for critical smart grid applications. Robust data analytics solutions are critical towards the optimized operation to enhance the resiliency of the smart grid. Hence this workshop will focus on real time data analytics to enhance situational awareness and decision support to enhance resiliency of the power grid. Results of the workshop will be disseminated through web for wider distribution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1836329</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anurag</FirstName>
<LastName>Srivastava</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anurag K Srivastava</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anurag.srivastava@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042933017</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527048</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington State University</Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 641060]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WSU Energy Systems Innovation Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Pullman</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>991642752</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[355 Spokane Street/EME 31]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~49992</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major goal of this project was to organize a workshop to bring together data scientist and power engineering experts to exchange ideas to solve emerging electric grid resiliency problems and spur new ideas of impactful research. This workshop was organized in August 2018 in Portland, OR and more than 70 experts in data science and power engineering from academia and industry participated to exchange ideas and in brainstorming.</p> <p>The major outcomes based on the discussions at the workshop were: a)&nbsp;Predictive model for the situational awareness is much needed to trigger any proactive control in the power grid to enable resiliency. Combination of data analytics solutions ranging from statistical and machine learning techniques guided by physics are needed for situational awareness and decision making in the electric grid, b) Applications of data analytics for large-scale dynamic system like power grid are still in fancy and very challenging, c) Close collaborations among industry, academia and vendors are required to solve cyber-physical resiliency of the electric grid, d) Open source &ldquo;data&rdquo; sandbox and electric grid resiliency use cases are required for data scientist to try alternative algorithms and e) Additional opportunities are needed to enable enhanced collaborations among data scientists and power engineers to solve electric grid resiliency problems.Proceedings of the workshop in terms of presentations are available at:&nbsp;<a href="https://sgdril.eecs.wsu.edu/workshop_conferences/real-time-data-analytics-for-the-resilient-electric-grid/">https://sgdril.eecs.wsu.edu/workshop_conferences/real-time-data-analytics-for-the-resilient-electric-grid/</a></p> <p>Enabling resiliency of the electric grid has the direct impact on society and to keeping the power on to critical facilities such as hospitals and fire department even during extreme events will save life and billions of dollars.&nbsp;The workshop provided a platform for discussion and exchange of idea between experts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Anurag&nbsp;K&nbsp;Srivastava</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The major goal of this project was to organize a workshop to bring together data scientist and power engineering experts to exchange ideas to solve emerging electric grid resiliency problems and spur new ideas of impactful research. This workshop was organized in August 2018 in Portland, OR and more than 70 experts in data science and power engineering from academia and industry participated to exchange ideas and in brainstorming.  The major outcomes based on the discussions at the workshop were: a) Predictive model for the situational awareness is much needed to trigger any proactive control in the power grid to enable resiliency. Combination of data analytics solutions ranging from statistical and machine learning techniques guided by physics are needed for situational awareness and decision making in the electric grid, b) Applications of data analytics for large-scale dynamic system like power grid are still in fancy and very challenging, c) Close collaborations among industry, academia and vendors are required to solve cyber-physical resiliency of the electric grid, d) Open source "data" sandbox and electric grid resiliency use cases are required for data scientist to try alternative algorithms and e) Additional opportunities are needed to enable enhanced collaborations among data scientists and power engineers to solve electric grid resiliency problems.Proceedings of the workshop in terms of presentations are available at: https://sgdril.eecs.wsu.edu/workshop_conferences/real-time-data-analytics-for-the-resilient-electric-grid/  Enabling resiliency of the electric grid has the direct impact on society and to keeping the power on to critical facilities such as hospitals and fire department even during extreme events will save life and billions of dollars. The workshop provided a platform for discussion and exchange of idea between experts.           Last Modified: 08/01/2019       Submitted by: Anurag K Srivastava]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
