<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Protein interactions regulate iron storage and utilization in bacteria</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>496314.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>496314</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaroslaw Majewski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmajewsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927278</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project outcomes will fill a major gap in our fundamental understanding of bacterial iron metabolism in the pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Several strains of this pathogen have developed multidrug resistance, causing severe challenges for the treatment of hospital infections  that  affect  burn  victims,  cancer  patients  and  cystic  fibrosis  patients  with chronic lung infections. The present proposal, while fundamental in nature, is also likely to expose bacterial iron metabolism as a vulnerability that can be exploited in future development of therapies that target bacterial iron homeostasis. The project will train graduate and undergraduate students in a multidisciplinary environment that draws from the diverse fields of chemistry, biochemistry, spectroscopy, structural biology and microbiology. In addition, the Harvest of Hope Leadership Academy (HHLA) at the University of Kansas (KU) hosts a summer residential academy for high school students from migrant farm-work background. The Project Director, in collaboration with the HHLA Program Director, will organize and lead students on tours  of Core  Research  laboratories,  where  students  will have  the opportunity  to meet  and interact with the Core Laboratory Directors. HHLA students who become KU undergraduates are mentored during their first year by the College Assistance Migrant Program (CAMP) organization  at KU. Two deserving  students  from the CAMP  program  will be recruited  each summer to participate in research activities related to the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The  project  will  test  a  new  model  for  bacterial  iron  homeostasis,  whereby  the  interactions between  two proteins  in P. aeruginosa  (BfrB and Bfd) enable the bacterial  cells to correctly sense changes in intracellular free iron levels and to efficiently incorporate iron into iron-utilizing proteins. BfrB is an iron storage protein and Bfd is a ferredoxin required for iron mobilization from BfrB. The accepted model of bacterial iron homeostasis assumes that iron storage proteins function simply as iron accumulators and that accumulated iron is mobilized to the cytosol only when  bacterial  cells  face  iron-limiting  conditions.  The  new  model  posits  that  the  BfrB:Bfd interaction, by facilitating iron flux out of BfrB, enables a dynamic equilibrium between free iron in the cytosol and iron stored in BfrB, which is crucial for the cells to sense and react to changes in free iron levels. The revised model also suggests that iron mobilization from BfrB is required for the efficient incorporation of iron into iron-utilizing proteins, so that inhibition of the BfrB:Bfd interaction  will  result  in  inefficient  iron  incorporation  into  iron-utilizing  enzymes,  which  will adversely affect important physiological process that depend on iron-containing proteins and enzymes. This proposed path is different from that in the accepted model, where the source of iron  for  iron-utilizing  proteins  is  assumed  to  be  the  free  iron  in  the  cytosol.  The investigators  have  also discovered a small molecule probe that inhibits the BfrB:Bfd interaction, and obtained evidence that this molecule enhances the killing activity of some existing antibiotics. Hence, the project also aims to obtain a fundamental understanding how the antibiotic activity is enhanced by inhibitors of the BfrB:Bfd interaction.  These studies will be guided by the idea that irreversible  accumulation  of iron in BfrB,  which  is  caused  by  the  small  molecule  inhibitor  of  the  BfrB:Bfd  interaction,  severely restricts the intracellular iron needed to support crucial metabolic processes required to fend antibiotic-induced stress.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1837877</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mario</FirstName>
<LastName>Rivera</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mario Rivera</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mrivera@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255781527</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485226</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<CountyName>EAST BATON ROUGE</CountyName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University and A & M College]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<CountyName>EAST BATON ROUGE</CountyName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Himes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~496314</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
