<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Community Track DCL 18-060: Exploring Roles of Universities, Data Centers, Data Repositories and Publishers in Data Re-Use</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Beth Plale</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Scientists are faced with an ever increasing array of options for data publication and a growing set of requirements to meet grant and journal directives. General purpose data repositories, data archives with journals or university libraries, domain-specific data repositories or broader project management and collaborative environments that provide some data publication services (e.g., issuing DOIs) are just a few of the options available. How should scientists choose among these options? How effective are these alternatives in meeting the multiple objectives for data publication, including discoverability, recording of sufficient metadata for reliable re-use, reproducibility of scientific results, convenience for data provider, and persistence. The investigator proposes to organize a workshop that brings together key stakeholders in data reuse.  The workshop targets research carried out in the geosciences and is an activity connected with the South Big Data Regional Innovation Hub.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1838572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hooper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard P Hooper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.hooper@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273211</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000212728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021555530</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 College Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7414</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported a workshop that brought together organizations that have different roles and responsibilities for data publication. Collecting data is the most expensive undertaking in scientific projects so figuring out how scientists can reuse data collected for other projects is important for the most effficient use of tax dollars.</p> <p>This project focused on two scientific domains--hydrology (the study of water and water quality) and low-temperature geochemistry (broadly, the study of how rocks weather to become soil as well as how minerals contribute to the cycling of various elements). Both of these scientific domains operate data centers to publish data for their respective disciplines. At the same time, there have developed other data publications centers that publish any kind of data, and, to assist their professors, university libraries have been expanding support of data publication. Publishers who print academic journals have begun to require data availability statements from the scientists for the articles that are publioshed in their journals; historically, these journals also have published data as supplementary materials. Many academic publishers subscribe to the FAIR doctrine that states that data should be Finable, Accessible, Interpretable, and Reproducible.</p> <p>These different activities arose somewhat independently and are not coordinated. This workshop explored data publication from the perspective of each of these entities and posed the following questions:</p> <ul> <li>What is the most effective data publication strategy to achieve the goals of the FAIR doctrine?</li> <li>What are the synergies among these different groups to sustain data publication most efficiently?</li> <li>Are the existing standards for data indexing, data transmission, and metadata describing data to allow the different repositories to be interoperable?</li> </ul> <p>The following recommendations emerged from the workshop and are being published in an academic journal:</p> <ul> <li>I<strong>mprove support for journal article-based data access and data citation</strong>. Journal publishers and some funders now require that data be published alongside a scientific journal article or deposited inan appropriate repository and then cited in the article. The journal article provides important context for the data that should enable more meaningful data re-use.</li> <li><strong>Enhance support for reproducible science</strong>. Ensuring reproducibility and verifiability of scientific results is an important reason for publishing data and should be recognized as an essential form of data reuse. Repositories must acknowledge that reproducing results described in scientific articlesmay require more than just making data files available. Inclusion of scripts and/or executableworkflows along with instructions on how to use them along with data is an important step toward ensuring that potential data consumers can retrace the steps of the individual investigators and build upon their results.</li> <li><strong>Encourage publication of curated reference data collections rather than data publications</strong>. Some of the most widely (re)used and cited datasets are large-scale, long-term, curated data sets. New reference data sets are being created and can now be more easily published.&nbsp;Reference data sets are highly curated, have a specified context and use, and have been certified as sufficient for one or more specific purposes by experts.</li> <li><strong>Advance interoperability standards for sharing data and metadata among repositories</strong>. Due to the many stakeholders and potential ways in which data could be shared and reused, we need to move away from practice that requires potential data users to know which repository data resides in before they can determine whether it exists. Data users should be able to discover data, regardlessof where they are hosted. Additionally, repositories should be able to catalog and/or reference data holdings initially deposited elsewhere, regardless of location</li> <li><strong>Develop partnerships with university libraries offering data services</strong>. In addition to maintaining their traditional role as provisioner and manager of scholarly collections, many university libraries have begun establishing data services.Trained data librarians help researchers develop data management plans prior to grant proposal submission and then again with data publication strategies, including dataset arrangement, creation of accompanying documentation, and selection of appropriate repositories for ongoing projects. Indeed, data librarians are well positioned to offer advice to scientists related to technical best practices that promote the sharing of high-quality datasets.</li> <li><strong>Develop more specific data management plans.</strong> Given the low success rates and time pressures on submitting grant proposals, data management plans are rarely considered with the same level ofdetail as other proposal materials and often use boilerplate language aimed at meeting funding agency requirements.&nbsp;It may bemore effective to require a basic data management plan at the time of grant proposal submission,followed by a more detailed plan after the funding decision is made, but prior to releasing the funds.</li> </ul> <p>The <em>intellectual merit</em>&nbsp;of this workshop was the assessment of the state of data publication for various perspectives to identify possible synergies. The <em>broader impacts</em>&nbsp;of this project is more effective and efficient data publication and re-use to advance scientific research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;P&nbsp;Hooper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported a workshop that brought together organizations that have different roles and responsibilities for data publication. Collecting data is the most expensive undertaking in scientific projects so figuring out how scientists can reuse data collected for other projects is important for the most effficient use of tax dollars.  This project focused on two scientific domains--hydrology (the study of water and water quality) and low-temperature geochemistry (broadly, the study of how rocks weather to become soil as well as how minerals contribute to the cycling of various elements). Both of these scientific domains operate data centers to publish data for their respective disciplines. At the same time, there have developed other data publications centers that publish any kind of data, and, to assist their professors, university libraries have been expanding support of data publication. Publishers who print academic journals have begun to require data availability statements from the scientists for the articles that are publioshed in their journals; historically, these journals also have published data as supplementary materials. Many academic publishers subscribe to the FAIR doctrine that states that data should be Finable, Accessible, Interpretable, and Reproducible.  These different activities arose somewhat independently and are not coordinated. This workshop explored data publication from the perspective of each of these entities and posed the following questions:  What is the most effective data publication strategy to achieve the goals of the FAIR doctrine? What are the synergies among these different groups to sustain data publication most efficiently? Are the existing standards for data indexing, data transmission, and metadata describing data to allow the different repositories to be interoperable?   The following recommendations emerged from the workshop and are being published in an academic journal:  Improve support for journal article-based data access and data citation. Journal publishers and some funders now require that data be published alongside a scientific journal article or deposited inan appropriate repository and then cited in the article. The journal article provides important context for the data that should enable more meaningful data re-use. Enhance support for reproducible science. Ensuring reproducibility and verifiability of scientific results is an important reason for publishing data and should be recognized as an essential form of data reuse. Repositories must acknowledge that reproducing results described in scientific articlesmay require more than just making data files available. Inclusion of scripts and/or executableworkflows along with instructions on how to use them along with data is an important step toward ensuring that potential data consumers can retrace the steps of the individual investigators and build upon their results. Encourage publication of curated reference data collections rather than data publications. Some of the most widely (re)used and cited datasets are large-scale, long-term, curated data sets. New reference data sets are being created and can now be more easily published. Reference data sets are highly curated, have a specified context and use, and have been certified as sufficient for one or more specific purposes by experts. Advance interoperability standards for sharing data and metadata among repositories. Due to the many stakeholders and potential ways in which data could be shared and reused, we need to move away from practice that requires potential data users to know which repository data resides in before they can determine whether it exists. Data users should be able to discover data, regardlessof where they are hosted. Additionally, repositories should be able to catalog and/or reference data holdings initially deposited elsewhere, regardless of location Develop partnerships with university libraries offering data services. In addition to maintaining their traditional role as provisioner and manager of scholarly collections, many university libraries have begun establishing data services.Trained data librarians help researchers develop data management plans prior to grant proposal submission and then again with data publication strategies, including dataset arrangement, creation of accompanying documentation, and selection of appropriate repositories for ongoing projects. Indeed, data librarians are well positioned to offer advice to scientists related to technical best practices that promote the sharing of high-quality datasets. Develop more specific data management plans. Given the low success rates and time pressures on submitting grant proposals, data management plans are rarely considered with the same level ofdetail as other proposal materials and often use boilerplate language aimed at meeting funding agency requirements. It may bemore effective to require a basic data management plan at the time of grant proposal submission,followed by a more detailed plan after the funding decision is made, but prior to releasing the funds.   The intellectual merit of this workshop was the assessment of the state of data publication for various perspectives to identify possible synergies. The broader impacts of this project is more effective and efficient data publication and re-use to advance scientific research.       Last Modified: 12/13/2019       Submitted by: Richard P Hooper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
