<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Meeting: Cnidofest: A workshop on cnidarian model organism biology, September 6-9, 2018, St. Augustine, FL</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evan Balaban</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebalaban@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928421</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Cnidarian Model Systems Meeting (Cnidofest 2018) will take place September 6-9, 2018 at the University of Florida's Whitney Laboratory for Marine Bioscience in St. Augustine, Florida. This meeting will focus on cnidarians, a group of mostly marine animals that includes jellyfish, sea anemones, and corals, with a focus on animals that are considered "emerging model systems" species that are particularly well-suited for answering important biological questions. Recent breakthroughs in technology have allowed researchers to answer a greater diversity of biological questions using cnidarians, and rapid progress is occurring in many fields, especially developmental biology, neurobiology, and physiology. The growing North American cnidarian research community will meet at Cnidofest 2018 to discuss their latest research findings, exchange ideas, learn about new technologies, and form collaborations. The meeting emphasizes interactions between experienced scientists and trainees, with a focus on increasing diversity. The ultimate goal of the meeting is to foster the growth, intellectual diversity, and collaborative spirit of the cniderian research community at a time when it is rapidly expanding (in both size and diversity of research questions).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cnidarians are excellent laboratory models for making fundamental biological discoveries, including in neurobiology, developmental biology, physiology, and biomechanics. Many qualities make cnidarians great laboratory models: 1) They have simple, well-understood body plans as well as fascinating life cycles. 2) They hold an informative phylogenetic position as the clade that is sister to bilaterians; discoveries made in cnidarians are often reflective of deeply conserved processes. 3) Many life stages of cnidarians are transparent, making them amenable to live imaging. 4) Some cnidarians are models for studying self/non-self recognition and others are used to study intracellular symbioses, such as those found in reef-building corals. 5) Many cnidarians are great models for studying regeneration, stem cells, and aging. These topics will be the major scientific focus of the meeting. In addition, the meeting will emphasize new technological approaches that will greatly enhance cnidarian research. Two technology speakers will present seminars on emerging technologies 1) microfluidics for measuring neural circuit activity and behavior and 2) single cell RNA sequencing for understanding development. Providing a platform for the interaction of cnidarian scientists at all levels will greatly benefit the community. Interactions will be fostered among participants through a dynamic schedule that includes traditional oral presentation sessions, lightning talks, poster presentations, and plenty of time to encourage informal discussion over breaks and meals, which are all done as one group. The ultimate goal is to grow and diversify the community in terms of breadth of research topics and broadening participation by multiple groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1838379</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Schnitzler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christine Schnitzler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christine.schnitzler@whitney.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9044614000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000538817</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Celina</FirstName>
<LastName>Juliano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Celina Juliano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cejuliano@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307547700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000716471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Augustine</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>320808610</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9505 Ocean Shore Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1119</Code>
<Text>Animal Developmental Mechanism</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7712</Code>
<Text>Organization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7713</Code>
<Text>Activation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1096</Code>
<Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~24000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cnidarian animals (corals, jellyfish, sea anemones, hydroids) hold a key position in the tree of animal life. As the sister group to most animals, they are useful to addressing the origin of many animal features. Cnidarians are relatively simple morphologically and can be used to study biological features that are difficult to access in other organisms. Cnidarians have many unique traits and properties that make them useful for addressing unanswered questions across many biological disciplines. The goal of this project was to organize a conference (Cnidofest) to share information and promote the community that studies cnidarians. Cnidarians have been used to make foundational discoveries in areas such as regeneration, developmental biology, and neurobiology and they have the potential to impact many other areas of biology. The community of researchers that study these animals is substantial but still small relative to other &lsquo;model system&rsquo; communities, so progress in advancing experimental methods has been somewhat slow. Cnidofest provided a forum for the North American community of cnidarian biologists to meet, exchange ideas, form collaborations and nurture the next generation of researchers. We prioritized creating an inclusive and supportive environment to welcome and mentor young researchers because it is essential for these researchers to grow their networks and to succeed to allow our community to grow stronger. A large number of oral presentations at the conference (68%) were given by students and postdoctoral researchers. All junior scientists that presented posters were given the opportunity to also present their work to the entire group in short talks. In a post-conference survey, participants indicated that the format of the meeting promoted meaningful interactions between junior and senior researchers. We also invited two technology speakers who focused on modern technologies that can be applied to cnidarian animal models. Our post-conference survey indicated that the vast majority of attendees (84%) plan to attend the next Cnidofest conference, which is a testament to the success of Cnidofest 2018. Cnidofest 2020 is scheduled to be held on the campus of UC-Davis September 9-13, 2020 and planning is underway. The establishment of a biennial conference in North America for cnidarian researchers will serve as a focal point for growing and diversifying our community and for highlighting discoveries and advances with cnidarians.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Christine&nbsp;Schnitzler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cnidarian animals (corals, jellyfish, sea anemones, hydroids) hold a key position in the tree of animal life. As the sister group to most animals, they are useful to addressing the origin of many animal features. Cnidarians are relatively simple morphologically and can be used to study biological features that are difficult to access in other organisms. Cnidarians have many unique traits and properties that make them useful for addressing unanswered questions across many biological disciplines. The goal of this project was to organize a conference (Cnidofest) to share information and promote the community that studies cnidarians. Cnidarians have been used to make foundational discoveries in areas such as regeneration, developmental biology, and neurobiology and they have the potential to impact many other areas of biology. The community of researchers that study these animals is substantial but still small relative to other ?model system? communities, so progress in advancing experimental methods has been somewhat slow. Cnidofest provided a forum for the North American community of cnidarian biologists to meet, exchange ideas, form collaborations and nurture the next generation of researchers. We prioritized creating an inclusive and supportive environment to welcome and mentor young researchers because it is essential for these researchers to grow their networks and to succeed to allow our community to grow stronger. A large number of oral presentations at the conference (68%) were given by students and postdoctoral researchers. All junior scientists that presented posters were given the opportunity to also present their work to the entire group in short talks. In a post-conference survey, participants indicated that the format of the meeting promoted meaningful interactions between junior and senior researchers. We also invited two technology speakers who focused on modern technologies that can be applied to cnidarian animal models. Our post-conference survey indicated that the vast majority of attendees (84%) plan to attend the next Cnidofest conference, which is a testament to the success of Cnidofest 2018. Cnidofest 2020 is scheduled to be held on the campus of UC-Davis September 9-13, 2020 and planning is underway. The establishment of a biennial conference in North America for cnidarian researchers will serve as a focal point for growing and diversifying our community and for highlighting discoveries and advances with cnidarians.       Last Modified: 09/03/2019       Submitted by: Christine Schnitzler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
