<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EaGER: Inclusions of fluid-related minerals in diamonds from the transition zone or lower mantle</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40366.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40366</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Although the surface of the Earth can be easily observed at many scales, the interior of the Earth is opaque and not accessible. There are only a small number of samples of minerals and rocks that derive from depths greater than 100 km.  Natural diamonds are not only the hardest natural materials we know but also our most valuable resources for direct interrogation of greater depths in the Earth's interior.  This Early Grant for Exploratory Research (EaGER) will support the study of a few precious diamond inclusions that are rich in fluid-bearing minerals, such as ice and calcite. The project will explore new methods in the study of unusual diamond inclusion, using state-of-the-art spectroscopic tools. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this EaGER is to expand on recent studies that have reported the occurrence of inclusions of ice-VII in diamonds from locations in Africa and China. Other inclusions of fluid-related crystalline precipitates such as magnesian calcite and halite have been identified and are expected to have residual pressures of 5-12 GPa and up to 25 GPa. Other inclusions of minerals of high residual pressure such as ilmenite and taenite have also been identified as inclusions that might have formed within the Transition Zone and lower mantle. This EaGER will extend the preliminary study to constrain pressure- and temperature regimes of fluid occurrences in the Transition Zone by analyzing a larger number of diamond inclusions using synchrotron micro-XRD and-XRF, optical spectroscopy, and subsequent EPMA wherever applicable. The results should contribute to to our understanding of the global water- and carbon budget by using an entirely combination of methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1838330</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oliver</FirstName>
<LastName>Tschauner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oliver Tschauner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>olivert@physics.unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7028951357</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000475252</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nevada Las Vegas</Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<ZipCode>891549900</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7028951357</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4505 MARYLAND PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098377336</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UNLV]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>891544002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4505 Maryland Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~40366</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Inclusions of minerals in diamonds from the Earth's transition zone and lower mantle are identified and characterized with the goal of determining a) pressure and temperature of their entrapment (and thereby regions of diamond growth in the deep mantle), and b) analyzing the trace element patterns of these deep -mantle inclusions. The project succeeded in identifying one of the global geochemical endmembers of the Earth&rsquo;s mantle, the s.c. HIMU-endmember,&nbsp; as dominated by fluid-release from slabs subducted to the shallow transition zone. For the first time, pressure, temperature, and composition of a high-pressure mineral assemblage could be uniquely correlated with a global geochemical signature and the prominent role of the transition zone of the mantle in the budget of heat-generating elements, rare-earths, and other incompatible elements was confirmed by these results. <br />The approach in this project has been very different from earlier work. In earlier studies, inclusions in diamonds were identified optically, then retrieved from the host diamond by polishing or crushing and examined at ambient conditions by EPMA, crystal structure analysis, or optical spectroscopy. This approach removed information about remnant pressure of inclusions, which constraints the pressure of entrapment of the inclusions. Furthermore, many high-pressure minerals are not retrievable. Hence, valuable information is lost. Therefore, in this project inclusions of high-pressure minerals were identified with synchrotron micro-X-ray diffraction first, their remnant pressures determined, then the inclusions were chemically analysed. This approach resulted in the discovery of high-pressure phases previously unknown from nature, such as solid N2 in the s.c. delta-loc phase, CaSiO3 in the perovskite-structure, the 10A-phase, a dense hydrous magnesium silicate. All these phases are messengers about their origin in the deep Earth&rsquo;s mantle.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2020<br>      Modified by: Oliver&nbsp;Tschauner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Inclusions of minerals in diamonds from the Earth's transition zone and lower mantle are identified and characterized with the goal of determining a) pressure and temperature of their entrapment (and thereby regions of diamond growth in the deep mantle), and b) analyzing the trace element patterns of these deep -mantle inclusions. The project succeeded in identifying one of the global geochemical endmembers of the Earth’s mantle, the s.c. HIMU-endmember,  as dominated by fluid-release from slabs subducted to the shallow transition zone. For the first time, pressure, temperature, and composition of a high-pressure mineral assemblage could be uniquely correlated with a global geochemical signature and the prominent role of the transition zone of the mantle in the budget of heat-generating elements, rare-earths, and other incompatible elements was confirmed by these results.  The approach in this project has been very different from earlier work. In earlier studies, inclusions in diamonds were identified optically, then retrieved from the host diamond by polishing or crushing and examined at ambient conditions by EPMA, crystal structure analysis, or optical spectroscopy. This approach removed information about remnant pressure of inclusions, which constraints the pressure of entrapment of the inclusions. Furthermore, many high-pressure minerals are not retrievable. Hence, valuable information is lost. Therefore, in this project inclusions of high-pressure minerals were identified with synchrotron micro-X-ray diffraction first, their remnant pressures determined, then the inclusions were chemically analysed. This approach resulted in the discovery of high-pressure phases previously unknown from nature, such as solid N2 in the s.c. delta-loc phase, CaSiO3 in the perovskite-structure, the 10A-phase, a dense hydrous magnesium silicate. All these phases are messengers about their origin in the deep Earth’s mantle.       Last Modified: 07/14/2020       Submitted by: Oliver Tschauner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
