<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:  Unraveling riverine sulfate using minor oxygen isotopes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100413.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100413</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Philip Bennett</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over geological timescales, weathering reactions involving minerals on the land surface have regulated the amounts of important gases such as oxygen and carbon dioxide in Earth's atmosphere.  This award funds research that will explore the potential for a new method to provide constraints on one such reaction in Earth history: the oxidation of the mineral pyrite.  Over the geological past, global variation in the amount of pyrite that has been oxidized provides a critical link between Earth's carbon and sulfur cycles, while a record of this history may be preserved by sulfate minerals in marine sediments.  The researchers will generate a proof-of-concept data set that takes advantage of information that can be gathered from a rare and difficult-to-measure stable isotope in dissolved and mineral sulfate: 17-oxygen.  This novel method will be applied to previously collected and well-characterized water samples from a major river system draining the Himalaya Range.  This pilot data set will provide important information about the mechanisms that control the isotopic composition of dissolved sulfate and will help to unravel the record that is preserved in marine sediments. The award will also provide mentoring for a postdoctoral fellow who has contributed to the design and planning of this project and will provide the individual with opportunities for leadership roles within the research group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award funds the exploration of the potential for a new proxy to quantify geological rates of pyrite oxidation, based on the minor oxygen stable isotope (17-O) preserved in sulfate produced by pyrite oxidation. Because pyrite oxidation both consumes oxygen and generates acidity that dissolves carbonate rocks and produces CO2, it has been suggested that changes in pyrite oxidation rates may have acted to stabilize fluctuations in atmospheric CO2. Although pyrite oxidation is a critical link between Earth's carbon and sulfur cycles, the application of a 17-O proxy in marine sulfate is limited by our understanding of sulfate generation and translation through fluvial systems. This work would begin to narrow this gap by generating a proof-of-concept data set from well-characterized river samples from a major river system draining the Himalaya Range that has already been measured for 34-S and 18-O composition of dissolved sulfate. The researchers will add measurements of the 17O composition of dissolved sulfate from these samples to investigate the potential sources and subsequent recycling of sulfate in downstream floodplains. The riverine 17-O-sulfate data set will provide a rigid framework with which to interpret 17-O records in the marine sulfate record.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1839341</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David T Johnston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnston@eps.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174965024</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1033 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~100413</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">The minor oxygen isotope compositions (&#8710;17O) of atmospheric O2 and CO2 are primarily regulated by their relative concentrations. Pyrite oxidation during chemical weathering on land consumes O2 and generates sulfate that is carried to the ocean by rivers. The &#8710;17O values of marine sulfate deposits have thus been proposed to quantitatively track ancient atmospheric conditions. This proxy assumes direct O2 incorporation into terrestrial pyrite oxidation-derived sulfate, but a mechanistic understanding of pyrite oxidation&mdash;including oxygen sources&mdash;in weathering environments remains elusive. To address this issue, this proposal supported the measurements of sulfate source estimates and &#8710;17O from modern rivers transecting the Annapurna Himalaya, Nepal. Sulfate in high-elevation headwaters is quantitatively sourced by pyrite oxidation, but resulting &#8710;17O values imply no direct tropospheric O2 incorporation. Rather, our results necessitate incorporation of oxygen atoms from alternative, 17O- enriched sources such as reactive oxygen species. Sulfate &#8710;17O decreases significantly when moving into warm, low-elevation tributaries draining the same bedrock lithology. We interpret this to reflect overprinting of the pyrite oxidation-derived &#8710;17O anomaly by microbial sulfate reduction and reoxidation, consistent with previously described major sulfur and oxygen isotope relationships. The geologic application of sulfate &#8710;17O as a proxy for past pO2/pCO2 should consider both 1) alternative oxygen sources during pyrite oxidation and 2) secondary overprinting by microbial recycling.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;T&nbsp;Johnston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The minor oxygen isotope compositions (&#8710;17O) of atmospheric O2 and CO2 are primarily regulated by their relative concentrations. Pyrite oxidation during chemical weathering on land consumes O2 and generates sulfate that is carried to the ocean by rivers. The &#8710;17O values of marine sulfate deposits have thus been proposed to quantitatively track ancient atmospheric conditions. This proxy assumes direct O2 incorporation into terrestrial pyrite oxidation-derived sulfate, but a mechanistic understanding of pyrite oxidation&mdash;including oxygen sources&mdash;in weathering environments remains elusive. To address this issue, this proposal supported the measurements of sulfate source estimates and &#8710;17O from modern rivers transecting the Annapurna Himalaya, Nepal. Sulfate in high-elevation headwaters is quantitatively sourced by pyrite oxidation, but resulting &#8710;17O values imply no direct tropospheric O2 incorporation. Rather, our results necessitate incorporation of oxygen atoms from alternative, 17O- enriched sources such as reactive oxygen species. Sulfate &#8710;17O decreases significantly when moving into warm, low-elevation tributaries draining the same bedrock lithology. We interpret this to reflect overprinting of the pyrite oxidation-derived &#8710;17O anomaly by microbial sulfate reduction and reoxidation, consistent with previously described major sulfur and oxygen isotope relationships. The geologic application of sulfate &#8710;17O as a proxy for past pO2/pCO2 should consider both 1) alternative oxygen sources during pyrite oxidation and 2) secondary overprinting by microbial recycling.          Last Modified: 06/29/2020       Submitted by: David T Johnston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
