<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning Grant: Engineering Research Center for Soft Energy and Power</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dana L. Denick</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddenick@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928866</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Planning Grants for Engineering Research Centers competition was run as a pilot solicitation within the ERC program.  Planning grants are not required as part of the full ERC competition, but intended to build capacity among teams to plan for convergent, center-scale engineering research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the rise of flexible, and/or wearable electronics, there is currently no power source that satisfactorily matches the "soft" mechanical properties of the object to be powered. Envisioned applications potentially include sensors, medical devices (e.g. cochlear implants), intelligent packaging, and clothing that converts body heat into electricity to power devices like a mobile phone. Further mechanical integration of power, electronic and thermal management technologies will have major targeted societal impact on the quality of life of millions of workers and individuals; as well as to dramatically improve safety and well-being. A barrier to this challenge is that researchers often focus on an individual component, without holistically addressing the integrated system itself. Therefore, the main goal of this engineering research center planning grant is to identify and build a dynamic team of academic, industry, and national lab stakeholders that will focus on the common goal of soft energy and power, in which each stakeholder's expertise is impactful and synergetic. The Texas A&amp;M University team plans to strategically utilize these planning funds for the engagement of partners for development of an engineering research center (ERC) proposal on the topic of Soft Energy and Power (SEP). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mechanically integrated, "soft" energy and power (SEP) currently faces many challenges, which can only be met by integrating expertise and know-how from a diverse team using a convergent approach. The currently perceived challenges include: 1) balancing mechanical properties with energy generation and/or storage properties, 2) integration between the human form and the device to be powered, 3) long-term durability and 4) cost, economics, and environmental (life cycle) considerations. Initially proposed ERC SEP thrusts include wearables, structural energy and power, intelligent packaging, and systems and design. These thrusts rest upon the knowledge of transport, kinetics, actuation, thermal management, systems design, battery safety, phase change materials, and mechanics of integrated composite materials. To this end, the planning grant will enable the formation of the ERC team, which will include university faculty, key industrial partners, and national laboratories. Together, the team will be involved in the identification and refinement of the goals and the associated engineering barriers upon which to focus in the ERC proposal. Specifically, the outcomes of this planning grant will be that ERC SEP (1) thrusts will be vetted and selected, (2) the team membership will form, evolve, and expand, (3) new technologies and knowledge bases will be identified, and (4) an ERC proposal will be submitted, as appropriate. This will be achieved through workshops to be held at Texas A&amp;M University in Fall 2018 and Spring 2019, and systematic team (academe, industry, government) meetings to drive the common agenda and formulate a powerful and impactful NSF ERC proposal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1840453</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edwin</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edwin L Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elt@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5087406061</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000097252</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Svetlana</FirstName>
<LastName>Sukhishvili</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Svetlana A Sukhishvili</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>svetlana@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794589840</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yossef</FirstName>
<LastName>Elabd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yossef A Elabd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elabd@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798457506</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000236235</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jaime</FirstName>
<LastName>Grunlan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jaime C Grunlan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jgrunlan@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798453027</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000333975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jodie</FirstName>
<LastName>Lutkenhaus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jodie Lutkenhaus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jodie.lutkenhaus@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798452682</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000510316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433122</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3122 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1480</Code>
<Text>ERC-Eng Research Centers</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>127E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ENERGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1480</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Intellectual Merit. </em>With the rise of soft, flexible, or incorporated electronics there is currently no power source that comes anywhere near matching the mechanical properties of the object to be powered. With mechanically integrated energy and power, an entirely flexible, stretchable, or structural device could be realized. By integrating energy and power with generation and storage, it is conceptually possible to achieve a device that extracts power from environmental input, removing the need for traditional charging from the grid. As an additional benefit, energy and power mechanically integrated into its parent device offers simplification in design, light-weighting, and extremely low form factor. Further mechanical integration of power, electronic and thermal management technologies will have major targeted societal impact on the quality of life of millions of workers and individuals; as well as dramatically improve the safety and well-being of US and global citizens.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts.</em> Overall, the broader impact of this planning grant was that it initiated sustained and deep discussions and relationships among industry, government, and academic stakeholders on the topic multifunctional energy&nbsp; and power. This planning grant enabled the formation and team-building of a preliminary Engineering Research Center (ERC) team that included university faculty, key industrial partners, and National Labs. A workshop was held in August 2019 to foster team-building, to identify new collaborators and stakeholders, and to specify challenges and barriers. The workshop had over 60 attendees from Texas A&amp;M University, Air Force Research Laboratory, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, University of Houston, Xerion Advanced Battery, U.S. Army Research Laboratory, Lynntech Inc, ExxonMobil, Georgia Institute of Technology, Kuraray, Florida State University, NASA, The Boeing Company, The University of Texas at Austin, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Case Western Reserve University, SABIC, University of Florida, ANP Technologies, Northwestern University, University of Alabama, University of Pittsburgh, University of Rochester, Rice University, and DuPont. Following the event, a survey revealed that respondents perceived that the best applications for multifunctional energy and power will be wearable,&nbsp; ground transportation systems, and aerospace systems. ERC team members then utilized the remaining time to follow-up and build upon these new connections through one-on-one meetings are virtual conferences.</p> <p>Although the team did not pursue ERC funding this last round, members of the team pursued several larger-scale multi-PI funding opportunities as a result of the relationships built out of this ERC planning grant. In 2019, Lutkenhaus led the TAMU Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (MRSEC) effort which included topics on radical-containing polymers, neuromorphics, and multifunctional adaptive materials. Unfortunately, the MRSEC was not selected. Sukhishvili participated in the TAMU MRSEC effort, and also has become a team member on the DOE BENEFIT grant supported by the DOE Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy-EERE on the topic of thermal energy storage for building thermal regulation. Thomas was part of a team (Carnegie Mellon, Georgia Tech, Rice and TAMU) that wrote a white paper MURI proposal (for $7.5M) on Polymer-based Field and Redox Induced Thermal Switches<strong>.&nbsp; </strong>Many of the concepts that were advanced were strongly influenced by the contacts made at the ERC Workshop and the contacts from the contacts. Unfortunately, the white paper was not selected for the full proposal but important research ideas and strengthened collaborative connections were made. In 2020, Boyd, Naraghi and Lutkenhaus submitted a proposal to NASA (not funded) and another one to NSF (pending) on the subject of structural energy storage. In 2019, Grunlan led the Texas A&amp;M component of a Department of Energy &ndash; Bird Foundation proposal, which included the development of thermoelectric materials that could recycle waste heat for the oil and gas industries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Jodie&nbsp;Lutkenhaus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit. With the rise of soft, flexible, or incorporated electronics there is currently no power source that comes anywhere near matching the mechanical properties of the object to be powered. With mechanically integrated energy and power, an entirely flexible, stretchable, or structural device could be realized. By integrating energy and power with generation and storage, it is conceptually possible to achieve a device that extracts power from environmental input, removing the need for traditional charging from the grid. As an additional benefit, energy and power mechanically integrated into its parent device offers simplification in design, light-weighting, and extremely low form factor. Further mechanical integration of power, electronic and thermal management technologies will have major targeted societal impact on the quality of life of millions of workers and individuals; as well as dramatically improve the safety and well-being of US and global citizens.  Broader Impacts. Overall, the broader impact of this planning grant was that it initiated sustained and deep discussions and relationships among industry, government, and academic stakeholders on the topic multifunctional energy  and power. This planning grant enabled the formation and team-building of a preliminary Engineering Research Center (ERC) team that included university faculty, key industrial partners, and National Labs. A workshop was held in August 2019 to foster team-building, to identify new collaborators and stakeholders, and to specify challenges and barriers. The workshop had over 60 attendees from Texas A&amp;M University, Air Force Research Laboratory, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, University of Houston, Xerion Advanced Battery, U.S. Army Research Laboratory, Lynntech Inc, ExxonMobil, Georgia Institute of Technology, Kuraray, Florida State University, NASA, The Boeing Company, The University of Texas at Austin, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Case Western Reserve University, SABIC, University of Florida, ANP Technologies, Northwestern University, University of Alabama, University of Pittsburgh, University of Rochester, Rice University, and DuPont. Following the event, a survey revealed that respondents perceived that the best applications for multifunctional energy and power will be wearable,  ground transportation systems, and aerospace systems. ERC team members then utilized the remaining time to follow-up and build upon these new connections through one-on-one meetings are virtual conferences.  Although the team did not pursue ERC funding this last round, members of the team pursued several larger-scale multi-PI funding opportunities as a result of the relationships built out of this ERC planning grant. In 2019, Lutkenhaus led the TAMU Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (MRSEC) effort which included topics on radical-containing polymers, neuromorphics, and multifunctional adaptive materials. Unfortunately, the MRSEC was not selected. Sukhishvili participated in the TAMU MRSEC effort, and also has become a team member on the DOE BENEFIT grant supported by the DOE Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy-EERE on the topic of thermal energy storage for building thermal regulation. Thomas was part of a team (Carnegie Mellon, Georgia Tech, Rice and TAMU) that wrote a white paper MURI proposal (for $7.5M) on Polymer-based Field and Redox Induced Thermal Switches.  Many of the concepts that were advanced were strongly influenced by the contacts made at the ERC Workshop and the contacts from the contacts. Unfortunately, the white paper was not selected for the full proposal but important research ideas and strengthened collaborative connections were made. In 2020, Boyd, Naraghi and Lutkenhaus submitted a proposal to NASA (not funded) and another one to NSF (pending) on the subject of structural energy storage. In 2019, Grunlan led the Texas A&amp;M component of a Department of Energy &ndash; Bird Foundation proposal, which included the development of thermoelectric materials that could recycle waste heat for the oil and gas industries.             Last Modified: 03/11/2021       Submitted by: Jodie Lutkenhaus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
