<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Community Planning for Scalable Cyberinfrastructure to Support Multi-Messenger Astrophysics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16002.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16002</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Miller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wlmiller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927886</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Multi-Messenger Astrophysics (MMA) is an exciting new field of science that combines traditional astronomy with the brand new ability to measure phenomena such as gravitational waves and high-energy neutrino particles that originate from celestial objects. MMA was galvanized when the collision of two neutron stars (labeled GW/GRB 170817A) was detected last year by multiple large science instruments including the NSF-funded Laser Interferometer Gravitational-wave Observatory (LIGO), its sister gravitational wave observatory VIRGO in Italy, NASA's Fermi gamma-ray telescope in space, and many other optical and radio telescopes world-wide. These multiple measurements of just one event improved our estimate of the speed of gravity to phenomenal precision, confirmed that neutron star mergers are the origin of the heavier atomic elements, and gave us a measurement of the radii of neutron stars to about one kilometer accuracy. Over the next decade, LIGO will identify dozens of such events per year. In parallel, the NSF-supported IceCube neutrino observatory at the U.S. South Pole Station and other neutrino and cosmic ray observatories are detecting high-energy cosmic rays from distant cosmological sources; and the new NSF-led Large Synoptic Survey Telescope and upcoming radio astronomy facilities will come online to survey the skies with unprecedented speed and depth throughout the Universe. While each kind of astronomical observing system will bring fascinating new discoveries, it is in their combination - through MMA - that transformative new insights into some of the most fundamental questions about the Universe can be realized: What is the nature of the highest-energy cosmic particle accelerators? What are the properties of cold and hot bulk matter at supra-nuclear densities? How do black holes form and evolve, across their full range of masses, and throughout cosmic time?&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The promise of Multi-Messenger Astrophysics can be realized only if sufficient cyberinfrastructure is available to rapidly handle, combine, and analyze the very large-scale distributed data from all the types of astronomical measurements. This project seeks to carry out community planning for scalable cyberinfrastructure to support MMA. The primary goal is to identify the key questions and cyberinfrastructure projects required by the community to take full advantage of the substantial investments in current facilities, and to realize the enormous potential of the multiple imminent next-generation projects over the decade to come. Two products of the project will be: 1) a community white paper that presents an in-depth analysis of the cyberinfrastructure needs and the opportunities for collaborations among astronomers, computer scientists, and data scientists; and 2) a strategic plan for a scalable cyberinfrastructure institute for multi-messenger astrophysics laying out its proposed mission, identifying the highest priority areas for cyberinfrastructure research and development for the US-based multi-messenger astrophysics community, and presenting a strategy for managing and evolving a set of services that benefits and engages the entire community.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project advances the objectives of the National Strategic Computing Initiative (NSCI) and the objectives of "Harnessing the Data Revolution" and "Windows on the Universe, two of the 10 Big Ideas for Future NSF Investments.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by the Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure in the Directorate for Computer &amp; Information Science &amp; Engineering and the Division of Astronomical Sciences and the Division of Physics in the Directorate of Mathematical &amp; Physical Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1841590</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tyce</FirstName>
<LastName>DeYoung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tyce R DeYoung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tdeyoung@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5178845715</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/15/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudio</FirstName>
<LastName>Kopper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudio Kopper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>koppercl@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5178845574</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000791571</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488246405</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1798</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7244</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7684</Code>
<Text>CESER-Cyberinfrastructure for</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>020Z</Code>
<Text>OAC Facility Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>062Z</Code>
<Text>Harnessing the Data Revolution</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>069Z</Code>
<Text>Windows on the Universe (WoU)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16002</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ba8c2590-7fff-8a4f-0868-85e2fe17d76c"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Astronomy and astrophysics have flourished in the last several decades as new observatories enabled by new technologies have unlocked the depths of the universe from radio waves to gamma rays. Astronomical observations have also expanded to include new messengers that explore our universe beyond light and other electromagnetic phenomena with neutrinos and gravitational waves.&nbsp; All the while, observers have become increasingly adept at both characterizing the static sky and uncovering the fantastic transient phenomena that permeate our universe such as exploding stars and colliding black holes and neutron stars. In 1987 an exploding star called a supernova was observed for the first time with both conventional telescopes and a global network of neutrino observatories. In 2017, colliding neutron stars were observed with both gravitational waves and a host of telescopes. Just a month later, neutrinos were observed in conjunction with gamma-ray flares of an active galactic center. It is now firmly established that joint observations from multiple messengers dramatically improve inferences.&nbsp; However, it has also been established that it is not easy for researchers from different fields, projects and observatories to efficiently communicate with one another to observe rare, rapidly changing transient events. This award focused on community planning to accelerate the pace and impact of multi-messenger observations through improved cyberinfrastructure.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Through a series of workshops, scientific conferences, virtual town-halls, and public Zoom meetings, members of this project sought to identify the challenges facing multi-messenger astrophysics and uncovered that:&nbsp; there are substantial obstacles to communication and collaboration between the researchers from different fields, projects and observatories that can prevent close coordination in time-critical moments; scientific inferences on joint observations are stifled by heterogenous data and a lack of common infrastructure and scientific analysis tools; and tighter coupling between the modeling and observation communities would dramatically improve the potential for new discoveries.&nbsp; While some of these problems are specific to a given domain or group of researchers, it is clear that there is a need for a community effort to provide dependable, supported cyberinfrastructure that are too broad for any one group or investigator to tackle independently.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The culmination of information gathering and community planning was the creation of a series of white papers that serve as components of the conceptualization of an institute for cyberinfrastructure in support of multi-messenger astrophysics. These whitepapers tackle: data management, communication and collaboration; analysis, inference and machine learning; modeling and theory; systems and software development; education, training and workforce development; and management. The whitepapers are open for public comment and are intended to capture the vision of the entire community for common ground that helps to ensure that multi-messenger astrophysics is more than the sum of its parts.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The work completed in this project was, by its nature, of broad impact in the scientific community, but multi-messenger astrophysics is also of interest to the public as it has potential to uncover fundamental knowledge about the origin and fate of the universe and the processes that lead to the conditions favorable for life itself, which are questions not solely answerable in Earth-based laboratories.&nbsp; Furthermore, the vision put forward by this project for a scalable institute for multi-messenger astrophysics establishes a clear mission to train the next generation of scientists in technology and methods.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Claudio&nbsp;Kopper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Astronomy and astrophysics have flourished in the last several decades as new observatories enabled by new technologies have unlocked the depths of the universe from radio waves to gamma rays. Astronomical observations have also expanded to include new messengers that explore our universe beyond light and other electromagnetic phenomena with neutrinos and gravitational waves.  All the while, observers have become increasingly adept at both characterizing the static sky and uncovering the fantastic transient phenomena that permeate our universe such as exploding stars and colliding black holes and neutron stars. In 1987 an exploding star called a supernova was observed for the first time with both conventional telescopes and a global network of neutrino observatories. In 2017, colliding neutron stars were observed with both gravitational waves and a host of telescopes. Just a month later, neutrinos were observed in conjunction with gamma-ray flares of an active galactic center. It is now firmly established that joint observations from multiple messengers dramatically improve inferences.  However, it has also been established that it is not easy for researchers from different fields, projects and observatories to efficiently communicate with one another to observe rare, rapidly changing transient events. This award focused on community planning to accelerate the pace and impact of multi-messenger observations through improved cyberinfrastructure.     Through a series of workshops, scientific conferences, virtual town-halls, and public Zoom meetings, members of this project sought to identify the challenges facing multi-messenger astrophysics and uncovered that:  there are substantial obstacles to communication and collaboration between the researchers from different fields, projects and observatories that can prevent close coordination in time-critical moments; scientific inferences on joint observations are stifled by heterogenous data and a lack of common infrastructure and scientific analysis tools; and tighter coupling between the modeling and observation communities would dramatically improve the potential for new discoveries.  While some of these problems are specific to a given domain or group of researchers, it is clear that there is a need for a community effort to provide dependable, supported cyberinfrastructure that are too broad for any one group or investigator to tackle independently.    The culmination of information gathering and community planning was the creation of a series of white papers that serve as components of the conceptualization of an institute for cyberinfrastructure in support of multi-messenger astrophysics. These whitepapers tackle: data management, communication and collaboration; analysis, inference and machine learning; modeling and theory; systems and software development; education, training and workforce development; and management. The whitepapers are open for public comment and are intended to capture the vision of the entire community for common ground that helps to ensure that multi-messenger astrophysics is more than the sum of its parts.    The work completed in this project was, by its nature, of broad impact in the scientific community, but multi-messenger astrophysics is also of interest to the public as it has potential to uncover fundamental knowledge about the origin and fate of the universe and the processes that lead to the conditions favorable for life itself, which are questions not solely answerable in Earth-based laboratories.  Furthermore, the vision put forward by this project for a scalable institute for multi-messenger astrophysics establishes a clear mission to train the next generation of scientists in technology and methods.             Last Modified: 01/28/2021       Submitted by: Claudio Kopper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
