<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference: Emergent Technologies for Intelligent Networks of Sensors and Actuators Conference, TO BE Held in Washington DC, March 2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21545.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21545</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lawrence Goldberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lgoldber@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928339</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed project seeks financial support to support invited speakers and conference organization needs at a meeting to be held in March 2019 in Washington, DC. The "Emergent Technologies for Intelligent Networks of Sensors and Actuators" Conference will focus on bringing together a multidisciplinary and interdisciplinary group of researchers whose ideas can help advance the conception and development of intelligence in wireless systems and networks that will revolutionize the way we live and change the industries and the economy. This conference will foster advances in understanding of intelligence and the conception and development of future intelligent systems or networks which will transform the society.  The conference's objectives and approach are inspired by Intelligent Wireless Networks of Sensors and Actuators that are a digital business innovation concept making Internet-of-Things service-oriented architectures, and advanced human-computer interactions converge to a more agile, flexible, and proactive management of unexpected events.  The convergence of technologies that were uniquely independent such as, analog and digital, software and hardware, packaging and electronic materials, in addition to a convergence of their cyber-biophysical capabilities in terms of curiosity-driven intelligence, and multi-brain control and decision making will be a key topic of the conference.  The Conference is expected to play a key role in identifying new directions in understanding of intelligence and the conception and development of future intelligent systems or networks which will transform the society. It will promote the convergence of diverse groups of designers, innovative ideas, demonstration of concepts and commercialization of products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1841238</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Katehi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda P Katehi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>katehi@exchange.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5303048850</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472154</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriel</FirstName>
<LastName>Rebeiz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriel M Rebeiz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rebeiz@ece.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585348001</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhi</FirstName>
<LastName>Ding</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhi Ding</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zding@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307524625</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162105</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoguang</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoguang Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lxgliu@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000614896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California - Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Av, ASB 1041]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~21545</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When incorporating artificial intelligence in today?s systems we do not design for intelligence. We only incorporate intelligent functions as a system accessory in a predetermined yet ad-hoc fashion.&nbsp;Big data and artificial intelligence are undoubtedly important innovations. They have an enormous potential in catalyzing economic value and social progress, from personalized healthcare to smart cities. It is totally possible, however, that the lack of a rigorous process that guides the design of such intelligence may lead&nbsp;&nbsp;to systems that will not benefit society and may become detrimental to citizen?s freedoms. These concerns have become more pubic recently and will not be resolved unless the design of intelligence follows the same robust and open processes as the one we have historically used in the development of wireless systems and networks. As we negotiate the narrative for the design of intelligence in highly distributed wireless systems, the fundamental question that needs to be addressed is ?<strong><em>What is cognition, how does it relate to intelligence and how do we design for it?.</em></strong><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through extensive discussions, the topic of the Conference evolved to <em><strong>Embodied Intelligence for Electronics</strong></em>. The interactions between the members of the organizing committee provided the opportunity to develop design pathways that will result in intelligent systems characterized by robustness, trustworthiness, scalability, survivability and social compatibility. The mission of the conference was to&nbsp;bring together a multidisciplinary and interdisciplinary group of researchers whose ideas would help advance the conception and development of intelligence in wireless systems and networks that will revolutionize the way we live and change our industries and our economy. Due to Covid19 the conference which was scheduled for May 4, 2020 did not take place, but the work done in advance of it has answered many questions about cognition and intelligence and has led into new research directions both in the design of intelligent electronics as well as the design of soft robotics with capabilities of unsupervised learning.&nbsp;&nbsp;In place of the conference, the organizing committee decided to design a lecture series which will take place between November 2020 and February 2021.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2020<br>      Modified by: Linda&nbsp;P&nbsp;Katehi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When incorporating artificial intelligence in today?s systems we do not design for intelligence. We only incorporate intelligent functions as a system accessory in a predetermined yet ad-hoc fashion. Big data and artificial intelligence are undoubtedly important innovations. They have an enormous potential in catalyzing economic value and social progress, from personalized healthcare to smart cities. It is totally possible, however, that the lack of a rigorous process that guides the design of such intelligence may lead  to systems that will not benefit society and may become detrimental to citizen?s freedoms. These concerns have become more pubic recently and will not be resolved unless the design of intelligence follows the same robust and open processes as the one we have historically used in the development of wireless systems and networks. As we negotiate the narrative for the design of intelligence in highly distributed wireless systems, the fundamental question that needs to be addressed is ?What is cognition, how does it relate to intelligence and how do we design for it?.    Through extensive discussions, the topic of the Conference evolved to Embodied Intelligence for Electronics. The interactions between the members of the organizing committee provided the opportunity to develop design pathways that will result in intelligent systems characterized by robustness, trustworthiness, scalability, survivability and social compatibility. The mission of the conference was to bring together a multidisciplinary and interdisciplinary group of researchers whose ideas would help advance the conception and development of intelligence in wireless systems and networks that will revolutionize the way we live and change our industries and our economy. Due to Covid19 the conference which was scheduled for May 4, 2020 did not take place, but the work done in advance of it has answered many questions about cognition and intelligence and has led into new research directions both in the design of intelligent electronics as well as the design of soft robotics with capabilities of unsupervised learning.  In place of the conference, the organizing committee decided to design a lecture series which will take place between November 2020 and February 2021.          Last Modified: 08/08/2020       Submitted by: Linda P Katehi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
