<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Professional Experiences for Students in Plasma Science: Student Travel Support to Attend the 2018 Gaseous Electronics Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10530.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10530</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support student participation at the 71st Annual Gaseous Electronics Conference (GEC) is to be held November 5-8, 2018, in Portland, OR. The GEC has a long and venerable history in pursuit of the foundational physical and chemical processes occurring in partially ionized, collisional plasmas, encompassing the interactions between atoms, molecules, charged particles, photons, waves, and fields. The GEC has a strong tradition of encouraging and promoting student participation. Attending research conferences is an important educational experience for students that cannot be replicated at their home institutions. The GEC provides opportunities for students to expand their networks, to learn about cutting edge research, and to develop and hone their professional communication skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GEC is a place to welcome students into a global professional community where they can envision themselves spending their careers. The GEC program is organized with coffee breaks mid-morning and mid-afternoon, as a way of facilitating conversation among participants. At the 2018 GEC, intentional steps are being taken to create a more inclusive conference atmosphere for those from groups not well represented at the conference.  These steps include a reconsideration of the GEC experience to add a commitment to diversity and inclusivity to its reputation as a premier venue for gaseous electronics research. Although demographic changes in research communities have slower time constants than might be desirable, the activities enabled by this award have the potential for long term impact by introducing new traditions into the GEC institutional memory. This approach includes introduction of several tested professional development and social events intended to appeal to early career attendees, including students and those from underrepresented groups. Questions added to the post-conference survey will help to assess need for, interest in and effectiveness of the added events, and responses will be used to guide planning for subsequent years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1841343</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Wendt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy E Wendt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wendt@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082628407</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380775</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061607</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1415 Engineering Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10530</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This one-year award was in support of student participation and expanded inclusion at the 71st Annual Gaseous Electronics Conference was held November 5-8, 2018, in Portland, OR. The GEC has a long and venerable history in pursuit of the foundational physical and chemical processes occurring in partially ionized, collisional plasmas, encompassing the interactions between atoms, molecules, charged particles, photons, waves, and fields. The GEC, with 400-600 attendees at a typical meeting, has maintained an excellent reputation for the quality of discourse among conference attendees conveying scientific information, viewpoints, and approaches (experimental, theoretical, modeling, and numerical simulation) toward the goal of understanding at a fundamental level. The 2018 GEC was co-located with the 60th Annual Meeting of the APS Division of Plasma Physics (DPP). While the GEC and APS DPP ran independent conferences held simultaneously in the same venue, the GEC teamed up with DPP to create several joint technical sessions, and co-location provided an opportunity for scientific ?cross fertilization? between the communities.</p> <p>The GEC has a strong tradition of encouraging and promoting student participation. Attending research conferences is an important educational experience for students that cannot be replicated at their home institutions. The GEC provides opportunities for students to expand their networks, to learn about cutting edge research, and to develop and hone their profes- sional communication skills. Workshops on current leading-edge topics are provided for students, and a student research and presentation competition is held. Student participation in the GEC is particularly important to the professional development of young scientists and engineers in the field and to the vibrancy and long-term health of the GEC. A primary goal for this project was to provide travel and conference registration funds to support students in U.S. graduate programs to attend the 2018 GEC - 14 students were supported.</p> <p>We also believe that the GEC is a place to welcome students into a global professional community where they can envision themselves spending their careers. &nbsp;At the 2018 GEC, we took intentional steps to create a more inclusive conference atmosphere for those from groups not well represented at the conference. Through co-location with DPP, the GEC had a unique opportunity to take advantage of the ?economies of scale? of a larger conference to offer an expanded menu of conference activities beyond the technical program. Each year at its annual meeting, DPP typically offers a number of non-technical activities that provide professional development and community building through events such as a lunch-time career panel, a Women in Plasma Physics (WIPP) panel discussion and reception, and an LGBTQ networking dinner. In 2018, DPP and GEC co-sponsored these events, and partial support for the WIPP panel was provided by this grant to the GEC. GEC also contributed to the expenses associated with the events it participated in, such as child care grants, and promoted them to the GEC community through conference announcements and registration information.</p> <p><br />Another major goal of this effort was a reconsideration of the GEC experience, i.e., to add a commitment to diversity and inclusivity to its reputation as a premier venue for gaseous electronics research. Although demographic changes in research communities have slower time constants than the one year duration of this grant, this project has the potential for long term impact by introducing new traditions into the GEC institutional memory that will persist from one meeting to the next. This approach includes introduction of several tested professional development and social events intended to appeal to early career attendees, including students and all GEC participants from underrepresented groups. Questions added to the post-conference survey helped to assess need for, interest in and effctiveness of the added events, and responses were used to guide planning for subsequent years. &nbsp;Plans for the 2019 and 2020 GECs include several of the activities introduced in 2018 with this NSF support, including gender-related events, care giver and child room and child care grants.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Amy&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wendt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This one-year award was in support of student participation and expanded inclusion at the 71st Annual Gaseous Electronics Conference was held November 5-8, 2018, in Portland, OR. The GEC has a long and venerable history in pursuit of the foundational physical and chemical processes occurring in partially ionized, collisional plasmas, encompassing the interactions between atoms, molecules, charged particles, photons, waves, and fields. The GEC, with 400-600 attendees at a typical meeting, has maintained an excellent reputation for the quality of discourse among conference attendees conveying scientific information, viewpoints, and approaches (experimental, theoretical, modeling, and numerical simulation) toward the goal of understanding at a fundamental level. The 2018 GEC was co-located with the 60th Annual Meeting of the APS Division of Plasma Physics (DPP). While the GEC and APS DPP ran independent conferences held simultaneously in the same venue, the GEC teamed up with DPP to create several joint technical sessions, and co-location provided an opportunity for scientific ?cross fertilization? between the communities.  The GEC has a strong tradition of encouraging and promoting student participation. Attending research conferences is an important educational experience for students that cannot be replicated at their home institutions. The GEC provides opportunities for students to expand their networks, to learn about cutting edge research, and to develop and hone their profes- sional communication skills. Workshops on current leading-edge topics are provided for students, and a student research and presentation competition is held. Student participation in the GEC is particularly important to the professional development of young scientists and engineers in the field and to the vibrancy and long-term health of the GEC. A primary goal for this project was to provide travel and conference registration funds to support students in U.S. graduate programs to attend the 2018 GEC - 14 students were supported.  We also believe that the GEC is a place to welcome students into a global professional community where they can envision themselves spending their careers.  At the 2018 GEC, we took intentional steps to create a more inclusive conference atmosphere for those from groups not well represented at the conference. Through co-location with DPP, the GEC had a unique opportunity to take advantage of the ?economies of scale? of a larger conference to offer an expanded menu of conference activities beyond the technical program. Each year at its annual meeting, DPP typically offers a number of non-technical activities that provide professional development and community building through events such as a lunch-time career panel, a Women in Plasma Physics (WIPP) panel discussion and reception, and an LGBTQ networking dinner. In 2018, DPP and GEC co-sponsored these events, and partial support for the WIPP panel was provided by this grant to the GEC. GEC also contributed to the expenses associated with the events it participated in, such as child care grants, and promoted them to the GEC community through conference announcements and registration information.   Another major goal of this effort was a reconsideration of the GEC experience, i.e., to add a commitment to diversity and inclusivity to its reputation as a premier venue for gaseous electronics research. Although demographic changes in research communities have slower time constants than the one year duration of this grant, this project has the potential for long term impact by introducing new traditions into the GEC institutional memory that will persist from one meeting to the next. This approach includes introduction of several tested professional development and social events intended to appeal to early career attendees, including students and all GEC participants from underrepresented groups. Questions added to the post-conference survey helped to assess need for, interest in and effctiveness of the added events, and responses were used to guide planning for subsequent years.  Plans for the 2019 and 2020 GECs include several of the activities introduced in 2018 with this NSF support, including gender-related events, care giver and child room and child care grants.          Last Modified: 11/17/2019       Submitted by: Amy E Wendt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
