<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Facilitating International Collaboration to Advance Engineering Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Cruz-Pol</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>scruzpol@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922928</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Science Foundation (NSF) established the Engineering Research Centers (ERC) program in order to advance collaborative, interdisciplinary, innovative engineering research and education. Currently, one of NSF's objectives for the ERC program is to explore how meaningful center-to-center collaboration within the US and internationally may be expanded.  Developing opportunities for in-person, collaborative learning between US and international research leaders and funding agency staff has the potential to increase such collaboration through the identification and prioritization of common interests, and through opportunities for relationship building across centers and agencies. Ultimately, the goal of these efforts is to increase and enhance engineering research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through this project, VentureWell will work with NSF and the ERC community to explore and develop new approaches to international center-to-center collaboration, specifically through convenings of the US and international center-level engineering research communities, science agencies, and relevant domain experts. VentureWell will bring continuity to these activities and work closely with key stakeholders in developing and implementing a strategy for exploring and developing approaches to increasing international center-to-center collaboration. The workshops VentureWell will organize will advance understanding of the conditions that enable increased international center-to-center collaboration and identify efficient approaches and mechanisms to set the conditions for fruitful collaboration and connections among these high-performing science centers. Finally, VentureWell will summarize and synthesize findings from these activities, including best practices, lessons learned, successes, and challenges so that learnings from these activities can inform future work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1842119</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Weilerstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip J Weilerstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pweilerstein@nciia.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135872172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000041172</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Collegiate Inventors and Innovators Alliance</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359682</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135872172</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 Venture Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>110907578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL COLLEGIATE INVENTORS &amp; INNOVATORS ALLIANCE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Collegiate Inventors and Innovators Alliance]]></Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010359682</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Venture Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1480</Code>
<Text>ERC-Eng Research Centers</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>114E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: OTHER RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL PLAN &amp; WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~299994</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-009183e8-7fff-35e9-c7b9-d758802d4ac2">&nbsp;</span>One of the National Science Foundation (NSF)'s key objectives for the Engineering Research Centers (ERC) program is to increase center-to-center collaboration within the US and internationally. Through this award, VentureWell worked with NSF and with the ERC community to explore and develop new approaches to international center-to-center collaboration, specifically through engagement of the US and international center-level engineering research communities, science agencies, and relevant domain experts. Each stage of the project built upon the previous one based on community feedback, and three discrete stages of the project can be identified: two in-person convenings and a longer-term research project, culminating in the opening of the Portal for International Collaboration Resources on the NSF-ERC website.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The workshops </span><span>helped stakeholders identify efficient approaches and mechanisms to set the conditions for fruitful collaboration and connections among engineering centers. </span><span>They brought together a range of ERCs to share learnings from and inspire interest in further iterations of the pilot of the Center-to-Center (C2C) international collaboration funding mechanism, and to narrow these broader discussions by focusing on the workforce development outcomes of international collaborations. </span><span>The workshops also created the necessary conditions for NSF and a community of individuals drawn from leading&nbsp; science-funding agencies worldwide to engage openly and constructively to address barriers to international collaboration as an integral component to improve outcomes for research they fund. Details of workshop activities and outcomes can be found in the attached public-facing reports VentureWell published following each workshop.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Iteratively building on findings from the workshops, NSF and VentureWell identified a need across stakeholder groups for a centralized, public access site that would house virtual resources relating to international collaboration. The resource was designed with the objective of enabling ERC leaders to develop and design sustainable, high-impact international collaborations. To this end, VentureWell collaborated with NSF's contracted website manager to create the Portal for International Collaboration Resources on the NSF-ERC website. The resources are organized into three distinct sections: contextual research regarding the value added by international collaborations across each of an ERC's foundational components; a database of international engineering research centers, and information of interest on those centers; and corresponding international funding agency information. Database design and information discovery processes were determined through consultation across stakeholder groups, and in close collaboration with NSF.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The activities supported by this EAGER grant identified and characterized systemic, highly complex, and interrelated boundaries to advancing interest in and execution of international collaborations for ERCs. The Portal serves as a proof-of-concept knowledge management tool that could prove highly valuable as systemic barriers to international collaboration are addressed. Use of the Portal, with ongoing data maintenance, could even be used as a metric to show progress towards the goal of more borderless science. VentureWell looks forward to future opportunities to frame and propose novel solutions to improve the conceptualization and achievements of international collaborations for ERCs.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;J&nbsp;Weilerstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  One of the National Science Foundation (NSF)'s key objectives for the Engineering Research Centers (ERC) program is to increase center-to-center collaboration within the US and internationally. Through this award, VentureWell worked with NSF and with the ERC community to explore and develop new approaches to international center-to-center collaboration, specifically through engagement of the US and international center-level engineering research communities, science agencies, and relevant domain experts. Each stage of the project built upon the previous one based on community feedback, and three discrete stages of the project can be identified: two in-person convenings and a longer-term research project, culminating in the opening of the Portal for International Collaboration Resources on the NSF-ERC website.  The workshops helped stakeholders identify efficient approaches and mechanisms to set the conditions for fruitful collaboration and connections among engineering centers. They brought together a range of ERCs to share learnings from and inspire interest in further iterations of the pilot of the Center-to-Center (C2C) international collaboration funding mechanism, and to narrow these broader discussions by focusing on the workforce development outcomes of international collaborations. The workshops also created the necessary conditions for NSF and a community of individuals drawn from leading  science-funding agencies worldwide to engage openly and constructively to address barriers to international collaboration as an integral component to improve outcomes for research they fund. Details of workshop activities and outcomes can be found in the attached public-facing reports VentureWell published following each workshop. Iteratively building on findings from the workshops, NSF and VentureWell identified a need across stakeholder groups for a centralized, public access site that would house virtual resources relating to international collaboration. The resource was designed with the objective of enabling ERC leaders to develop and design sustainable, high-impact international collaborations. To this end, VentureWell collaborated with NSF's contracted website manager to create the Portal for International Collaboration Resources on the NSF-ERC website. The resources are organized into three distinct sections: contextual research regarding the value added by international collaborations across each of an ERC's foundational components; a database of international engineering research centers, and information of interest on those centers; and corresponding international funding agency information. Database design and information discovery processes were determined through consultation across stakeholder groups, and in close collaboration with NSF. The activities supported by this EAGER grant identified and characterized systemic, highly complex, and interrelated boundaries to advancing interest in and execution of international collaborations for ERCs. The Portal serves as a proof-of-concept knowledge management tool that could prove highly valuable as systemic barriers to international collaboration are addressed. Use of the Portal, with ongoing data maintenance, could even be used as a metric to show progress towards the goal of more borderless science. VentureWell looks forward to future opportunities to frame and propose novel solutions to improve the conceptualization and achievements of international collaborations for ERCs.       Last Modified: 01/28/2021       Submitted by: Philip J Weilerstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
