<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: A Magneto-Inductive Framework for Seamless Monitoring of Joint Kinematics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>191000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Nilsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wnilsen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922568</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Today's gold-standard for monitoring joint kinematics entails the use of reflective markers placed upon the human body and tracked by infrared cameras. While technique is limited to laboratory environments, alternative approaches are also restricted to contrived environments, are obtrusive and error-prone, or obstruct natural movement. This EAGER research will overall these challenges by developing a new class of garments that rely on embroidered E-textile coils to monitor joint kinematics in the individual's natural environment. As a result of this work, new and unexplored opportunities are envisioned for applications as diverse as healthcare, sports, and manufacturing work. This research is also anticipated to re-define the term "wearables" from bulk, rigid on-body sensors to seamlessly functionalized fabrics. Alongside the technical work, creative education and outreach efforts are proposed that leverage the hands-on and inter-disciplinary appeal of E-textiles to inspire students in the field, attract females in engineering, and educate the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This EAGER research aims to explore the feasibility of an untested but potentially transformative magneto-inductive framework for monitoring joint kinematics in the individual's natural environment while overcoming shortcomings in the state-of-the-art. The proposed framework relies on E-textile coils embroidered into garments (leggings, sleeves, etc.) to seamlessly monitor joint flexion/rotation, reaching out to applications as diverse as sports, rehabilitation, gaming, human-machine interaction, and more. Technologies reported to date for monitoring joint kinematics are bounded to contrived environments (cameras); are obtrusive and suffer from integration drift (inertial measurement units); require line-of-sight (time-of-flight sensors); and/or obstruct natural movement (bending/deformation sensors). By contrast, this EAGER research leverages a compelling analogy between transformer principles and joint flexion/rotation to realize a new class of coil-functionalized garments that overcome the limitations above. Our research will first explore the feasibility of monitoring joint flexion (irrespective of limb rotation) via wrap-around coils. Concurrent monitoring of joint flexion and rotation will then be explored via hybrid wrap-around/longitudinal coils. Real-world considerations will finally be brought into play to enhance the knowledgebase. Without loss of generality, focus will be on the knee joint; yet success of this research is expected to build the confidence and tools necessary to monitor flexion/rotation of other joints and, ultimately, full-body motion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1842531</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asimina</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiourti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asimina Kiourti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kiourti.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6146888735</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000709119</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432121166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1330 Kinnear Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8062</Code>
<Text>SCH Type II: INT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~175000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~16000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
