<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A chemical assay kit for the high-throughput screening of chiral amine enantiomeric excess</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project seeks to commercialize new sensor technologies that enable the rapid measurement of the handedness of molecular mixtures.   Like screws and keys, many molecules possess a certain handedness that can be important when interacting with living systems.  This issue is vital to pharmaceutical research, where one handed form of a drug may result in benefits while the opposite form may cause harmful side effects.  Consequently, measuring the handedness of molecular mixtures is of paramount importance in modern pharmaceutical research.  However, conventional approaches to making these measurements are often too slow for modern pharmaceutical discovery and development research where high-throughput experiments on hundreds or even thousands of samples per day are performed.  This project aims to remove this bottleneck by leveraging a recently introduced new instrument and commercializing reagent kits that have been shown in academic laboratories to achieve a much faster and simpler method for measuring the handedness of molecular mixtures.  Making this improved technology widely available to the greater research and development community has the potential to streamline drug development efforts at reduced cost and minimized waste production, which is expected to increase profit margins and create new jobs in research, development and manufacturing, resulting in substantial benefit to the health and economy of the United States.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The innovation of this project comprises a series of optical sensors, developed during a decade of fundamental research in the participating laboratories, which will allow rapid eescreening of a variety of asymmetric reactions. The focus of this unprecedented enterprise is to validate selected sensors against pharmaceutically relevant compounds, determine the error of the optical assays by comparison with traditional techniques such as chiral HPLC, to evaluate the robustness in the presence of potential interferants, and to apply a sensor in the analysis of an asymmetric reaction using multi-well plate technology. The development of a user-friendly kit will include the testing of different methods for the creation of pre-dispensed dried sensors that can be reconstituted without leaving behind residues that might increase the error margin beyond a few percent which is generally acceptable for high-throughput screening applications. The final outcome will be a convenient mix-and-measure protocol that enables rapid analysis of hundreds of small-scale asymmetric reaction mixtures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1843626</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Dragna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin M Dragna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>justin.dragna@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5125603231</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000781635</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ENANTIOSENSE LLC</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787234648</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5125603231</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1900 SIMOND AVE APT 1064</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>081227794</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ENANTIOSENSE LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Enantiosense LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787234648</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1900 simond ave 1064]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Organic chemistry theory is primarily derived from empirical evidence. Trial-and-error plays an enormous role in all research, but it is especially true in the discovery of new chemical reactions. The funding from this Phase I grant was used by EnantioSense to begin development of a new tool called the EnantioScreen Platform to aid researchers in the trial-and-error discovery reactions. In particular, the tool being developed is useful in the discovery of asymmetric reactions, which are particularly challenging to discover. The scientific impact of the work done during Phase I is a deeper understanding of the fundamental problems associated with measuring the success of asymmetric reactions, which may ultimately lead to speeding up their discovery. The work EnantioSense has done in Phase I lays a foundation for a shift in how reactions are discovered and points to a new research paradigm in asymmetric reaction discovery.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The societal impact of the research done in Phase I stems from the application of asymmetric reactions in drug discovery. Asymmetric reaction discovery is often the bottleneck in the development of asymmetric drugs. The development of the EnantioScreen Platform in Phase I provides the beginning of a roadmap on how to free up this bottleneck. The completion of this roadmap will result in faster access to new therapeutic molecules by society.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In terms of educational impact, EnantioSense used the Phase I funding to encourage innovation and collaboration in chemistry, which has become increasingly necessary to address the complex science and technology issues facing society that go beyond a single research group or company&rsquo;s expertise. Phase I of this grant was done in collaboration with The University of Texas at Austin and Georgetown University. A graduate student from Georgetown University moved to Austin to participate in research at The University of Texas at Austin. In addition to supporting her graduate education in the development of chiral analysis methods, EnantioSense supported her participation in customer development interviews and business development to aid in her understanding of translating innovations from academia to commercial applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The innovative tool developed by EnantioSense in this Phase I grant has impacted the fundamental science of chemistry through providing a roadmap for accelerating the discovery of new asymmetric reactions, society by potentially increasing the speed of drug discovery, and educationally in its collaborations with universities and the support of a graduate student.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Justin&nbsp;M&nbsp;Dragna</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[           Organic chemistry theory is primarily derived from empirical evidence. Trial-and-error plays an enormous role in all research, but it is especially true in the discovery of new chemical reactions. The funding from this Phase I grant was used by EnantioSense to begin development of a new tool called the EnantioScreen Platform to aid researchers in the trial-and-error discovery reactions. In particular, the tool being developed is useful in the discovery of asymmetric reactions, which are particularly challenging to discover. The scientific impact of the work done during Phase I is a deeper understanding of the fundamental problems associated with measuring the success of asymmetric reactions, which may ultimately lead to speeding up their discovery. The work EnantioSense has done in Phase I lays a foundation for a shift in how reactions are discovered and points to a new research paradigm in asymmetric reaction discovery.                The societal impact of the research done in Phase I stems from the application of asymmetric reactions in drug discovery. Asymmetric reaction discovery is often the bottleneck in the development of asymmetric drugs. The development of the EnantioScreen Platform in Phase I provides the beginning of a roadmap on how to free up this bottleneck. The completion of this roadmap will result in faster access to new therapeutic molecules by society.              In terms of educational impact, EnantioSense used the Phase I funding to encourage innovation and collaboration in chemistry, which has become increasingly necessary to address the complex science and technology issues facing society that go beyond a single research group or company’s expertise. Phase I of this grant was done in collaboration with The University of Texas at Austin and Georgetown University. A graduate student from Georgetown University moved to Austin to participate in research at The University of Texas at Austin. In addition to supporting her graduate education in the development of chiral analysis methods, EnantioSense supported her participation in customer development interviews and business development to aid in her understanding of translating innovations from academia to commercial applications.              The innovative tool developed by EnantioSense in this Phase I grant has impacted the fundamental science of chemistry through providing a roadmap for accelerating the discovery of new asymmetric reactions, society by potentially increasing the speed of drug discovery, and educationally in its collaborations with universities and the support of a graduate student.                   Last Modified: 11/18/2019       Submitted by: Justin M Dragna]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
