<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Robotics Launchpad - A Design-Driven Educational Robotics Framework</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224959.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224959</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase I project aims to bring together computational thinking, mechanism design, and design process to create a new framework for design-driven robotics education for K-12 schools and camps. This work would result in a platform for 1) teaching students Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) topics and 2) providing them critical hands-on experience designing, prototyping, and programming machines. By enabling students to exercise their creativity via an intuitive design interface and a minimalist novel robot kit, this project advances the students' ability to innovate and invent machines and robots. Driven by a need to keep pace with the evolving techno- and socio-economic requirements and remain competitive, schools and camps are increasingly adopting STEM and Robotics programs and products. This framework would fill that void that currently exists in the educational market. This project is closely aligned with the NSF's mandate to support development of a strong STEM workforce. The proposed design-driven educational robotics framework has the potential to fulfill these needs, improve public scientific literacy and engagement with science and technology, and positively impact the U.S. educational robotics market, which is expected to grow to $2.7 billion by 2021.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research seeks to develop a novel design-driven educational robotics framework encompassing 1) a modular, customizable, and compatible with off-the shelf electronics hardware kit consisting of rigid and compliant parts for rapid prototyping of robot structures and mechanisms, 2) a multi-modal mobile app for synthesis and simulation of robot motions, 3) a web-based CAD interface for designing users' custom robot parts that interface seamlessly with the kit, and 4) instructional material and curriculum for middle and high-schools. The hardware would provide a suite of planar parts with unique design capabilities to support creation of 3D geometry of robots and structures. The novel structural elements would give rise to a new method of enforcing geometric and kinematic constraints and provide flexibility in choice of material and manufacturing process. While the new connection methods are much more intuitive and simpler, they also closely mirror the way engineered structures are created in practice. The mobile app based on the latest mechanism synthesis research imbued with a multi-modal graphical user interface will allow creation of robot assemblies and their motions before constructing their corresponding physical models and provide necessary skills and experience in the design process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1843476</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anurag</FirstName>
<LastName>Purwar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anurag Purwar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anurag.purwar@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316328542</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642463</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Poyu</FirstName>
<LastName>Chuang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Poyu Chuang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>purwar@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6319432268</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000766258</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mechanismic Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Dix Hills</CityName>
<ZipCode>117468335</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6319432268</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>133 Village Hill Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080691997</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MECHANISMIC INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Long Island High Technology Incubator]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117903350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[25 Health Sciences Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>Education Products</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~224959</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-0f8d94ed-7fff-bf88-6860-9b594876c203"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I project aims to bring together computational thinking, mechanism design, and the design process to create a new framework for design-driven robotics education for middle to high schools and STEM camps. The state of the art commercially available educational robotic systems emphasize 1) instruction-driven prototyping of robot structures using a large number of specialized parts, and 2) programming them without providing any intuition behind the design process or path to creating mechanism design concepts for the realization of the motion of the robots. By leveraging the results from the latest NSF-funded research in developing a data-driven paradigm for mechanism synthesis and enabling students to exercise their creativity via an intuitive design interface and a minimalist novel robot kit, this project advances the students ability to innovate and invent machines and robots.</span></p> <p dir="ltr">The major goals of this project were to develop a novel design-driven educational robotics platform called SnappyXO<sup>TM</sup> Design (<a href="http://www.snappyxo.com" target="_blank">http://www.snappyxo.com</a>) consisting of 1) a patented low-cost, modular, and customizable hardware, 2) a web-based multi-modal software application for mechanism and robot design, and 3) instructional material and curriculum for STEM and robotics education for middle and high-school students.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In what follows, we are highlighting the major accomplishments under the stated goals:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>1. Hardware:</strong><span> We have developed a unified hardware library of planar modular components -- flexible connectors, rigid parts, and mounts for sensors, actuators, and controllers -- to define and create the space of possible designs for machines and robots. This is a unified design since the students all the way from elementary to post-secondary use the same components, albeit under different kit configurations. The hardware was tested among 1000+ elementary, middle, and high-school students from different school districts in Long Island. It has also been used by more than 1000 postsecondary students. Feedback from the students and teachers helped refine the design further.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The USPTO granted U.S. patent #10,561,958 on the key hardware technology in February this year.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>2. Software: </strong><span>While the hardware enables physical prototyping of robots, the motion design software in our product is a critical piece in teaching students the process of robot motion design using linkage-based mechanisms and creation of customized robot parts. This software allows students to design their own robot parts and even create completely new robot kits and highly customizable parts compatible with the SnappyXO kits while leveraging our connection technology. This alone sets this product apart from competitors.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The app is currently hosted at </span><a href="http://motiongenpro.appspot.com/"><span>http://motiongenpro.appspot.com</span></a><span> and offers users a sketch-based interface to draw N-bar planar mechanisms, simulate them, and export them for physical prototyping. This is where the true education lies when students and practitioners can appreciate the interplay between motion and the geometry. In addition, the app also provides a machine-learning driven synthesis function where a user sketches a motion path and in turn receives several conceptual designs for realizing motions of a robot.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Since its completion, the app has been used and tested by middle and high school students. It is also now being used in undergraduate and graduate level design, robotics, and kinematics classes.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This is the first web-based motion design app of its kind in the world, which provides a rich interface with sophisticated functions for kinematic synthesis and simulation of mechanisms, not seen in the leading commercially available Computer-Aided Design and Engineering softwares.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>3. Curriculum and Projects:</strong><span> Our hardware and software provide the basic building blocks for students to virtually and physically prototype mechanisms, machines, and robots. But, it is our new Engineering Design and Robotics curriculum, which completes students' learning and education.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We have developed 1) a 10-lessons curriculum on "Engineering Design with SnappyXO" for elementary to middle school students available at </span><a href="https://www.snappyxo.com/category/lessons/curriculum/"><span>https://www.snappyxo.com/category/lessons/curriculum</span></a><span>,&nbsp; 2) a 5-lessons curriculum on "Robotics with SnappyXO" available at </span><a href="https://www.snappyxo.com/category/lessons/robotics"><span>https://www.snappyxo.com/category/lessons/robotics</span></a><span>, and 3) SnappyXO projects at </span><a href="https://www.snappyxo.com/projects/"><span>https://www.snappyxo.com/projects/</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These lesson plans bring together three separate Engineering disciplines, viz Mechanical- and Electrical- and Electronics-Engineering and Computer Science in an engaging way.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>SnappyXO Projects app was developed primarily for informal STEM learning environments and individual users, makers and hobbyists. it contains a series of hands-on projects that one can do on their own if they have the product. Projects are categorized by the kit complexity. The app is available for download for free from </span><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/snappyxoprojects/id1530128561%20"><span>https://apps.apple.com/us/app/snappyxoprojects/id1530128561 </span></a><span>and </span><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.snappyxoprojects&amp;hl=en_US"><span>https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.snappyxoprojects&amp;hl=en_US</span></a><span>.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project is closely aligned with the NSF's mandate to support development of a strong STEM workforce and help fill the 2.4 million STEM jobs that are vacant according to the current Bureau of Labor Statistics. The proposed design-driven educational robotics framework has the potential to fulfill these needs, improve public scientific literacy and engagement with science and technology, and positively impact the U.S. educational robotics market, which is expected to grow to $2.7 billion by 2021.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Poyu&nbsp;Chuang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474062940_Overlayimageforfbmarketing--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474062940_Overlayimageforfbmarketing--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SnappyXO Design kits"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474062940_Overlayimageforfbmarketing--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SnappyXO Design kits"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SnappyXO Design</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mechanismic Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Poyu&nbsp;Chuang</div> <div class="imageTitle">SnappyXO Design kits</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474250348_motiondesignV2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474250348_motiondesignV2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Motion Design using MotionGen Pro"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474250348_motiondesignV2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Motion Design using MotionGen Pro"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Use MotionGen Pro to design mechanisms for robots</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anurag Purwar</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Poyu&nbsp;Chuang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Motion Design using MotionGen Pro</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474335736_mainimage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474335736_mainimage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Kids playing with SnappyXO Robots"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474335736_mainimage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Kids playing with SnappyXO Robots"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Kids playing with SnappyXO Robots</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anurag Purwar</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Poyu&nbsp;Chuang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Kids playing with SnappyXO Robots</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474495567_MotionGenProCapture4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474495567_MotionGenProCapture4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Walking Robot in MotionGen Pro"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1843476/1843476_10588841_1601474495567_MotionGenProCapture4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Walking Robot in MotionGen Pro"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Walking Robot in MotionGen Pro</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anurag Purwar</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Poyu&nbsp;Chuang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Walking Robot in MotionGen Pro</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I project aims to bring together computational thinking, mechanism design, and the design process to create a new framework for design-driven robotics education for middle to high schools and STEM camps. The state of the art commercially available educational robotic systems emphasize 1) instruction-driven prototyping of robot structures using a large number of specialized parts, and 2) programming them without providing any intuition behind the design process or path to creating mechanism design concepts for the realization of the motion of the robots. By leveraging the results from the latest NSF-funded research in developing a data-driven paradigm for mechanism synthesis and enabling students to exercise their creativity via an intuitive design interface and a minimalist novel robot kit, this project advances the students ability to innovate and invent machines and robots. The major goals of this project were to develop a novel design-driven educational robotics platform called SnappyXOTM Design (http://www.snappyxo.com) consisting of 1) a patented low-cost, modular, and customizable hardware, 2) a web-based multi-modal software application for mechanism and robot design, and 3) instructional material and curriculum for STEM and robotics education for middle and high-school students. In what follows, we are highlighting the major accomplishments under the stated goals: 1. Hardware: We have developed a unified hardware library of planar modular components -- flexible connectors, rigid parts, and mounts for sensors, actuators, and controllers -- to define and create the space of possible designs for machines and robots. This is a unified design since the students all the way from elementary to post-secondary use the same components, albeit under different kit configurations. The hardware was tested among 1000+ elementary, middle, and high-school students from different school districts in Long Island. It has also been used by more than 1000 postsecondary students. Feedback from the students and teachers helped refine the design further. The USPTO granted U.S. patent #10,561,958 on the key hardware technology in February this year.  2. Software: While the hardware enables physical prototyping of robots, the motion design software in our product is a critical piece in teaching students the process of robot motion design using linkage-based mechanisms and creation of customized robot parts. This software allows students to design their own robot parts and even create completely new robot kits and highly customizable parts compatible with the SnappyXO kits while leveraging our connection technology. This alone sets this product apart from competitors. The app is currently hosted at http://motiongenpro.appspot.com and offers users a sketch-based interface to draw N-bar planar mechanisms, simulate them, and export them for physical prototyping. This is where the true education lies when students and practitioners can appreciate the interplay between motion and the geometry. In addition, the app also provides a machine-learning driven synthesis function where a user sketches a motion path and in turn receives several conceptual designs for realizing motions of a robot. Since its completion, the app has been used and tested by middle and high school students. It is also now being used in undergraduate and graduate level design, robotics, and kinematics classes.  This is the first web-based motion design app of its kind in the world, which provides a rich interface with sophisticated functions for kinematic synthesis and simulation of mechanisms, not seen in the leading commercially available Computer-Aided Design and Engineering softwares. 3. Curriculum and Projects: Our hardware and software provide the basic building blocks for students to virtually and physically prototype mechanisms, machines, and robots. But, it is our new Engineering Design and Robotics curriculum, which completes students' learning and education. We have developed 1) a 10-lessons curriculum on "Engineering Design with SnappyXO" for elementary to middle school students available at https://www.snappyxo.com/category/lessons/curriculum,  2) a 5-lessons curriculum on "Robotics with SnappyXO" available at https://www.snappyxo.com/category/lessons/robotics, and 3) SnappyXO projects at https://www.snappyxo.com/projects/.  These lesson plans bring together three separate Engineering disciplines, viz Mechanical- and Electrical- and Electronics-Engineering and Computer Science in an engaging way.  SnappyXO Projects app was developed primarily for informal STEM learning environments and individual users, makers and hobbyists. it contains a series of hands-on projects that one can do on their own if they have the product. Projects are categorized by the kit complexity. The app is available for download for free from https://apps.apple.com/us/app/snappyxoprojects/id1530128561 and https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.snappyxoprojects&amp;hl=en_US. This project is closely aligned with the NSF's mandate to support development of a strong STEM workforce and help fill the 2.4 million STEM jobs that are vacant according to the current Bureau of Labor Statistics. The proposed design-driven educational robotics framework has the potential to fulfill these needs, improve public scientific literacy and engagement with science and technology, and positively impact the U.S. educational robotics market, which is expected to grow to $2.7 billion by 2021.       Last Modified: 09/30/2020       Submitted by: Poyu Chuang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
