<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for ACM BCB 2018: Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project provides travel support for students (graduate, undergraduate, and high school) to attend ACM SIGBio (Associate Computing Machinery Special Interest Group in Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics) annual International Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics (ACMBCB) in Washington DC during Aug. 29-Sept. 01, 2018 (http://acm-bcb.org/). ACMBCB2018 aims to provide an interactive forum that bridges computer science, mathematics, statistics, with biology and health, and to support advanced research, training, and outreach. It brings together top researchers, educators, practitioners, and students around the world to share innovative biological and medical discoveries, new informatics algorithms, new computational tools that will advance biological and health science, and improve national health. It consists of systematically organized activities such as plenary keynotes, workshops, tutorials, research oral sessions, poster sessions, and panels for researchers and practitioners from different disciplines to interact, to discuss, and to collaborate. It will encourage diverse groups of students, especially the underrepresented minority (women, minority, and disabled) to actively participate in conference activities, to grow ACM SIGBio community, and to advance the fast-growing interdisciplinary education and research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As part of this award activity, ACMBCB2018 will organize a Student Forum and "Women in Bioinformatics" panel with senior academic and industrial experts serving as the mentors. These mentors will provide feedback to attending students' research, and will share their personal experience and wisdom in career development. These students will write a short summary to report their ACMBCB2018 experience.  Overall, the project will assist students in gaining knowledge, to improve their visibility and to advance novel advancements in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1844455</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dongmei</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dongmei Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maywang@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043852954</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georiga Tech Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>Computational Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As the annual conference of ACM SIGBio, the ACM International Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics (ACMBCB) aims (1) to provide an interactive forum for researchers, practitioners, and students from around the world to promote scientific understanding and findings in bioscience, and (2) to strengthen interdisciplinary research across computer science, mathematics, statistics, biology, bioinformatics, and biomedicine. As its flagship annual conference, ACMBCB2018 in Washington DC on Aug. 29<sup>th</sup> ? Sept. 1st, 2018, (<a href="http://acm-bcb.org/">http://acm-bcb.org/</a>) provides researchers and practitioners a platform to bridge important interdisciplinary research areas in computer science, mathematics, statistics, biology, bioinformatics and biomedicine. While developing synergy of the research on bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics is not easy, it is particularly challenging for underrepresented (URM) groups (women, minority, and people with disabilities). &nbsp;The goals of this ACMBCB2018 NSF travel grant are to broaden the participation of young professionals (students and postdoctoral fellows who graduated during after Jan. 2018), and to broaden diversity of participation in ACMBCB2018. This NSF award enables young professionals to meet distinguished speakers, to present their own research ideas, to discuss any new research problems, and to foster new collaborations within joint computational, biomedical, and health communities. It also enables established researchers in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics to provide mentorship for the next generation young professionals to help cultivate this new interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary research field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The first key outcome is all the applicants put in technical work to summarize their ?Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics? related research, with both ?<em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broad Impact</span></em>? and ?<em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Property</span></em>? required by NSF. This practice alone has generated positive responses from both young professionals and their advisors. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The second key outcome is upon being reviewed and selected by the faculty committee, the NSF awardees presented in the research forum to share&nbsp;with the large research community. The research forum not only&nbsp;enabled these bright young professionals to exchange their research ideas, and but also enabled them to gain visibility among ACM bioinformatics and health informatics communities.&nbsp;Awardees are provided PPT template to present their research in The Young Professional Research Forum. This forum had attracted ACMBCB2018 attendees in addition to the awardees, their advisors, mentors, and peers. &nbsp;This NSF project broadened the participation of young professionals, and maximized their learning of advanced knowledge in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics through the well-planned and organized conference activities, and advances their future research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The third key outcome is as a requirement for receiving this NSF travel award, these awardees attended the entire conference (oral and poster sessions) to interact with top bioinformatics and health informatics researchers attending ACMBCB2018. Thus, this NSF project enables young professionals to meet distinguished speakers, to present their own research ideas, to discuss any new research problems, and to foster new collaborations in the joint computing, biology, and health communities. It also enables established researchers in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics to provide mentorship to the next generation young professionals to help cultivate the new interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary research field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The last outcome on is on diversity. One keynote speaker (Prof. Mona Singh, Princeton University), and both conference co-chairs are woman faculty (Amarda Shehu, George Mason University, and Cathy Wu, University of Delaware, USA). In addition, the PI of this NSF grant Prof. May D. Wang organized ?women in bioinformatics (WiB)? with seven panelists from academics, industry, and government lab to provide insights and suggestions on promoting under-represented groups (woman and minority) in this interdisciplinary area. Many NSF awardees attended the panel and actively participated in the discussion about the challenges and opportunities in promoting diversity in bioinformatics and health informatics. &nbsp;This women participation is significantly higher than the average percentage of women in computing, and is a unique highlight of ACMBCB2018.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Dongmei&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As the annual conference of ACM SIGBio, the ACM International Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics (ACMBCB) aims (1) to provide an interactive forum for researchers, practitioners, and students from around the world to promote scientific understanding and findings in bioscience, and (2) to strengthen interdisciplinary research across computer science, mathematics, statistics, biology, bioinformatics, and biomedicine. As its flagship annual conference, ACMBCB2018 in Washington DC on Aug. 29th ? Sept. 1st, 2018, (http://acm-bcb.org/) provides researchers and practitioners a platform to bridge important interdisciplinary research areas in computer science, mathematics, statistics, biology, bioinformatics and biomedicine. While developing synergy of the research on bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics is not easy, it is particularly challenging for underrepresented (URM) groups (women, minority, and people with disabilities).  The goals of this ACMBCB2018 NSF travel grant are to broaden the participation of young professionals (students and postdoctoral fellows who graduated during after Jan. 2018), and to broaden diversity of participation in ACMBCB2018. This NSF award enables young professionals to meet distinguished speakers, to present their own research ideas, to discuss any new research problems, and to foster new collaborations within joint computational, biomedical, and health communities. It also enables established researchers in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics to provide mentorship for the next generation young professionals to help cultivate this new interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary research field.     The first key outcome is all the applicants put in technical work to summarize their ?Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics? related research, with both ?Broad Impact? and ?Intellectual Property? required by NSF. This practice alone has generated positive responses from both young professionals and their advisors.       The second key outcome is upon being reviewed and selected by the faculty committee, the NSF awardees presented in the research forum to share with the large research community. The research forum not only enabled these bright young professionals to exchange their research ideas, and but also enabled them to gain visibility among ACM bioinformatics and health informatics communities. Awardees are provided PPT template to present their research in The Young Professional Research Forum. This forum had attracted ACMBCB2018 attendees in addition to the awardees, their advisors, mentors, and peers.  This NSF project broadened the participation of young professionals, and maximized their learning of advanced knowledge in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics through the well-planned and organized conference activities, and advances their future research.     The third key outcome is as a requirement for receiving this NSF travel award, these awardees attended the entire conference (oral and poster sessions) to interact with top bioinformatics and health informatics researchers attending ACMBCB2018. Thus, this NSF project enables young professionals to meet distinguished speakers, to present their own research ideas, to discuss any new research problems, and to foster new collaborations in the joint computing, biology, and health communities. It also enables established researchers in bioinformatics, computational biology, and health informatics to provide mentorship to the next generation young professionals to help cultivate the new interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary research field.     The last outcome on is on diversity. One keynote speaker (Prof. Mona Singh, Princeton University), and both conference co-chairs are woman faculty (Amarda Shehu, George Mason University, and Cathy Wu, University of Delaware, USA). In addition, the PI of this NSF grant Prof. May D. Wang organized ?women in bioinformatics (WiB)? with seven panelists from academics, industry, and government lab to provide insights and suggestions on promoting under-represented groups (woman and minority) in this interdisciplinary area. Many NSF awardees attended the panel and actively participated in the discussion about the challenges and opportunities in promoting diversity in bioinformatics and health informatics.  This women participation is significantly higher than the average percentage of women in computing, and is a unique highlight of ACMBCB2018.          Last Modified: 04/30/2020       Submitted by: Dongmei Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
