<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Radio-Frequency-Identification Based Seal &amp; Packaging Methods To Eliminate Counterfeiting And Tampering Of Physical Goods</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224470.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224470</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rick Schwerdtfeger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be on any industry or product category that suffers from product counterfeiting; that is to say on nearly every industry imaginable. It is estimated that the global counterfeit market will grow from $1.2 Trillion in 2017 to more than $1.8 Trillion by 2020. In an attempt to combat this trend, spending on anticounterfeit packaging will grow from $122 Billion in 2017 to $264 Billion by 2023. Of most dire concern, the counterfeit pharmaceutical industry is estimated at approximately $200 Billion, resulting in about 1 million deaths annually. Existing anti-counterfeit packaging techniques have proven largely ineffective in combating this counterfeiting problem. This project will result, for the first time, in packaging or seals that, without ambiguity, inform users of the authenticity, integrity, and provenance of any product outfitted with the project?s resultant technology. All stakeholders in a supply chain will be enabled to detect fake goods before they can be used or consumed. This increased visibility into the supply chain will also broaden enforcement opportunities for relevant entities and/or authorities and provide special benefit to those industries most urgently impacted: pharmaceuticals, military/defense products and high-priced goods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed innovation is a novel enhancement to Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) that seals any package or container to which it is attached and, when queried by a reader/interrogator (e.g. any modern smartphone), provides the status (i.e. tampered/un-tampered) and identity to the user or system. The project will produce the designs and manufacturing techniques required to create RFID-based seals that provide assurance of authenticity, integrity, and provenance for products to which these seals are applied. Research will be conducted on several specific hardware components required by this innovation and will produce the requisite software and cryptographic systems for the testing, design, and commercialization of this proposed solution to product counterfeiting. Developed software will provide the testing and development framework for commercial applications of the proposed anti-counterfeiting solution. Advances in hardware design, especially concerning the minimization of power requirements for the RFID-based seals and the manufacturing techniques for specific required hardware components (i.e. the components that detect tampering events) will be accomplished during this research project. Research and development activities will employ varied techniques including iterative design, 3D printing, and advanced electronics prototyping. This SBIR Phase I project will ultimately result in the design and validation of production-ready seals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1844217</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emil</FirstName>
<LastName>Tremblay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emil C Tremblay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emil@sgnt.io</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4802256500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000783453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SGNT LLC</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>857044075</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4802256500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>951 W ORANGE GROVE RD APT 77104</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>081279947</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SGNT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SGNT LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857044075</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[951 W Orange Grove Rd, Apt 77104]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~224470</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>SGNT </strong>has developed an innovative Radio-Frequency Identification (RFID) based device that wirelessly ensures the seal on any physical item to which it is applied has not been compromised. Conceptually this is like tamper-evident tape in which tamper-events are recorded within the material and reported through an RFID device. Furthermore, once the tamper event occurs, it cannot be reversed. To function, the platform requires construction of physical devices (hardware) authenticated by a secured cloud-based service (software). This technology is being developed to curtail the rapidly growing $1.5 trillion global counterfeit goods market, and to address pain-points in other industries where tamper-evidence is critical to security.</p> <p>SGNT achieved multiple accomplishments during the research project and was able to complete all the goals it had set. Prior to the project, the technology was conceptual and had not been physically constructed. By the end of the project, fully functioning devices had been designed, constructed, and tested. SGNT has been working towards identifying specific products that can be manufactured based on this technology, and this was a major milestone in creating scalable commercial products.</p> <p>Eight primary tasks were set and accomplished in the project, which include <strong>1.</strong> Tamper-sensing methods, <strong>2.</strong> Functional Software System for Device Testing, <strong>3.</strong> Integrated-Circuit (IC) Package Design, <strong>4.</strong> Printed Circuit Boards (PCB) construction, <strong>5.</strong> Flexible Material Construction of the IC Package Design,<strong> 6.</strong> Soft-Seal Prototype Construction, <strong>7.</strong> Hard-Seal Prototype Construction, and <strong>8.</strong> Definition and Tooling for Production.</p> <p>While all tasks were completed, some specific accomplishments are to be noted. Task 1 - Two tamper-sending methods were successfully built and tested instead of the original goal of one method. Task 2 - The Web-App Server, Mobile Application, and Device Provisioning software were all constructed and functioning. SGNT mobile authentication software was published in the Android and Apple stores. Task 6 - Functional seam-seal prototypes built with commercially scalable product potential. Task 7 -Functional hard-seal prototype constructed with path to commercial scale and go-to-market plan as first product.</p> <p>During this project, the National Science Foundation provided valuable guidance through the Beat the Odds Bootcamp and partnership with Dawnbreaker. This allowed the company to better understand the market-potential of the technology and help identify products that could be built based in the innovation. Furthermore, partnership with Dawnbreaker assisted in extensive and valuable market research which has helped SGNT identify a proper beachhead for their technology. As a result, SGNT has built relationships with packaging integration companies, manufacturers, component manufacturers and suppliers, and multiple customers with letters of intent (LOI's) to test and purchase products enabled with SGNT technology.</p> <p>Over the next 12-18 months SGNT will overcoming the technical and commercial challenges remaining in launching a large-scale commercial product that directly addresses pain-point in the Intermodal Shipping industry by launching hardware container seals. Feasibility of these seals are a direct result of the Phase I project. During this time-period SGNT will also continue development of soft-seals and integration into existing packaging solutions through additional research and development and in partnership with packaging solutions providers which relationships have already been established.<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>For this project, the work was completed at the SGNT facility located in Tucson, AZ. Key personnel include Emil Tremblay - CEO &amp; Principal Investigator (PI) (5 Person Months); Josh Gill - VP, Tech (4 Person Months); Dave Irving - Sr. Software Engineer (3 Person Months); and Kris Savage - Project Manager (1 Person Months). Additional personnel include Don Finkle - COO (1 Person Months); Tommy Rompel - VP, Operations (2 Person Months); and Travis Bradley - Electronics Tech (2 Person Months).</p> <p>The first change in approach during the project arose in Task 1 when developing tamper-evident methods. The original concept was integrated into packaging material but was not suitable for commercial scale products. The second method for tamper-detection was developed as a better solution for the application. Furthermore, the original tamper-detection method was found suitable for hardware seals (e.g. Bolt-Seals). Task 7 - Hard-Seal Prototype Construction was accomplished from this development change and a new product was identified as a result.&nbsp;</p> <p>The second significant change came in identifying the requirements for an IC necessary to construct SGNT devices. Originally SGNT sought to identify existing ICs on the market to fit this need, however only one chip was identified as suitable, and was used during the project. SGNT has identified the need to develop either a custom Application Specific Integrated Circuit (ASIC), or a custom System-In-Package (SIP) solution. SGNT has taken the necessary steps to develop and source this critical component at commercial scale over the next 12-18 months. Developing this custom solution also drastically reduces the cost of this component at scale by approximately 90%.</p> <p>While technical and commercial challenges lay ahead, the initial technical risk has been mitigated in the project, and SGNT has developed an 18-month strategy to overcome these obstacles.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Emil&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tremblay</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652500332_sgnt-tamper-evident-packing-demo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652500332_sgnt-tamper-evident-packing-demo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SGNT Tamper-Evident Packaging"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652500332_sgnt-tamper-evident-packing-demo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SGNT Tamper-Evident Packaging"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SGNT's tamper-evident innovation senses events within the material and securely reports it to the Radio Frequency Identification Sensor (RFID), which can be interrogated using any standard reader</div> <div class="imageCredit">SGNT INC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emil&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tremblay</div> <div class="imageTitle">SGNT Tamper-Evident Packaging</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652340235_por-sgnt-bolt-seal-1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652340235_por-sgnt-bolt-seal-1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SGNT Bolt-Seal Prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652340235_por-sgnt-bolt-seal-1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SGNT Bolt-Seal Prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A fully functional Intermodal Shipping container bolt-seal prototype developed by SGNT during the Phase I Project</div> <div class="imageCredit">SGNT INC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emil&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tremblay</div> <div class="imageTitle">SGNT Bolt-Seal Prototype</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652728250_sgnt-tech-scan-sample--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652728250_sgnt-tech-scan-sample--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SGNT Device Scanned by a Smartphone"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652728250_sgnt-tech-scan-sample--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SGNT Device Scanned by a Smartphone"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SGNT seals are scanned and authenticated on a secure cloud-based platform compatible with any modern smartphone</div> <div class="imageCredit">SGNT INC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emil&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tremblay</div> <div class="imageTitle">SGNT Device Scanned by a Smartphone</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652858796_sgnt-android-store-screenshot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652858796_sgnt-android-store-screenshot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SGNT Smartphone Application on Android Devices"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652858796_sgnt-android-store-screenshot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SGNT Smartphone Application on Android Devices"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SGNT Smartphone App published and available on the Android Platform</div> <div class="imageCredit">SGNT INC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emil&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tremblay</div> <div class="imageTitle">SGNT Smartphone Application on Android Devices</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652938816_sgnt-apple-store-screenshot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652938816_sgnt-apple-store-screenshot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SGNT Smartphone Application on Apple Devices"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1844217/1844217_10589523_1572652938816_sgnt-apple-store-screenshot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SGNT Smartphone Application on Apple Devices"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SGNT Smartphone App published and available on the Apple Platform</div> <div class="imageCredit">SGNT INC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emil&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tremblay</div> <div class="imageTitle">SGNT Smartphone Application on Apple Devices</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SGNT has developed an innovative Radio-Frequency Identification (RFID) based device that wirelessly ensures the seal on any physical item to which it is applied has not been compromised. Conceptually this is like tamper-evident tape in which tamper-events are recorded within the material and reported through an RFID device. Furthermore, once the tamper event occurs, it cannot be reversed. To function, the platform requires construction of physical devices (hardware) authenticated by a secured cloud-based service (software). This technology is being developed to curtail the rapidly growing $1.5 trillion global counterfeit goods market, and to address pain-points in other industries where tamper-evidence is critical to security.  SGNT achieved multiple accomplishments during the research project and was able to complete all the goals it had set. Prior to the project, the technology was conceptual and had not been physically constructed. By the end of the project, fully functioning devices had been designed, constructed, and tested. SGNT has been working towards identifying specific products that can be manufactured based on this technology, and this was a major milestone in creating scalable commercial products.  Eight primary tasks were set and accomplished in the project, which include 1. Tamper-sensing methods, 2. Functional Software System for Device Testing, 3. Integrated-Circuit (IC) Package Design, 4. Printed Circuit Boards (PCB) construction, 5. Flexible Material Construction of the IC Package Design, 6. Soft-Seal Prototype Construction, 7. Hard-Seal Prototype Construction, and 8. Definition and Tooling for Production.  While all tasks were completed, some specific accomplishments are to be noted. Task 1 - Two tamper-sending methods were successfully built and tested instead of the original goal of one method. Task 2 - The Web-App Server, Mobile Application, and Device Provisioning software were all constructed and functioning. SGNT mobile authentication software was published in the Android and Apple stores. Task 6 - Functional seam-seal prototypes built with commercially scalable product potential. Task 7 -Functional hard-seal prototype constructed with path to commercial scale and go-to-market plan as first product.  During this project, the National Science Foundation provided valuable guidance through the Beat the Odds Bootcamp and partnership with Dawnbreaker. This allowed the company to better understand the market-potential of the technology and help identify products that could be built based in the innovation. Furthermore, partnership with Dawnbreaker assisted in extensive and valuable market research which has helped SGNT identify a proper beachhead for their technology. As a result, SGNT has built relationships with packaging integration companies, manufacturers, component manufacturers and suppliers, and multiple customers with letters of intent (LOI's) to test and purchase products enabled with SGNT technology.  Over the next 12-18 months SGNT will overcoming the technical and commercial challenges remaining in launching a large-scale commercial product that directly addresses pain-point in the Intermodal Shipping industry by launching hardware container seals. Feasibility of these seals are a direct result of the Phase I project. During this time-period SGNT will also continue development of soft-seals and integration into existing packaging solutions through additional research and development and in partnership with packaging solutions providers which relationships have already been established.   For this project, the work was completed at the SGNT facility located in Tucson, AZ. Key personnel include Emil Tremblay - CEO &amp; Principal Investigator (PI) (5 Person Months); Josh Gill - VP, Tech (4 Person Months); Dave Irving - Sr. Software Engineer (3 Person Months); and Kris Savage - Project Manager (1 Person Months). Additional personnel include Don Finkle - COO (1 Person Months); Tommy Rompel - VP, Operations (2 Person Months); and Travis Bradley - Electronics Tech (2 Person Months).  The first change in approach during the project arose in Task 1 when developing tamper-evident methods. The original concept was integrated into packaging material but was not suitable for commercial scale products. The second method for tamper-detection was developed as a better solution for the application. Furthermore, the original tamper-detection method was found suitable for hardware seals (e.g. Bolt-Seals). Task 7 - Hard-Seal Prototype Construction was accomplished from this development change and a new product was identified as a result.   The second significant change came in identifying the requirements for an IC necessary to construct SGNT devices. Originally SGNT sought to identify existing ICs on the market to fit this need, however only one chip was identified as suitable, and was used during the project. SGNT has identified the need to develop either a custom Application Specific Integrated Circuit (ASIC), or a custom System-In-Package (SIP) solution. SGNT has taken the necessary steps to develop and source this critical component at commercial scale over the next 12-18 months. Developing this custom solution also drastically reduces the cost of this component at scale by approximately 90%.  While technical and commercial challenges lay ahead, the initial technical risk has been mitigated in the project, and SGNT has developed an 18-month strategy to overcome these obstacles.          Last Modified: 11/01/2019       Submitted by: Emil C Tremblay]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
