<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TRAVEL: Broadening Participation of Deaf Students in Sign Language Research: September 2019: Hamburg, Germany</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71100.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tyler Kendall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkendall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922434</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Deaf researchers are underrepresented in sign language research. The aim of this project is to broaden the participation of deaf individuals in disciplines that conduct sign language research. Funding from the National Science Foundation will be used to bring deaf college students from the U.S.A. to the Theoretical Issues in Sign Language Research (TISLR) conference, which will be hosted in Hamburg, Germany, during the summer of 2019, and to provide American Sign Language interpreting services for these students while attending the conference. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TISLR is the most significant and well-attended international conference on sign language research. The students will work with a team of mentors prior to the conference to discuss their research interests and to prepare for presentations at the conference. The mentors will also meet with the students during and after the conference to help them plan their research careers. The knowledge, resources, and networks the students will develop at TISLR will make them better equipped to pursue careers in sign language research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1844796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Lillo-Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane C Lillo-Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lillo.martin@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604860155</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Hauser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter C Hauser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pchgss@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854757447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000111745</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
<LastName>Kurz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kim Kurz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kim.Kurz@RIT.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854757525</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000638642</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rochester Institute of Tech]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Lomb Memorial]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~71100</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Normal1">Deaf researchers are underrepresented in sign language research. The major goal of this project was to broaden the participation of deaf individuals in disciplines that conduct sign language research. Funding was used to bring deaf graduate students to participate and present at the 13<sup>th</sup> annual meeting of the Theoretical Issues in Sign Language Research (TISLR) in Hamburg, Germany in September 2019. TISLR is the most significant and well-attended international sign language research conference. Sign language researchers from all over the world attend this conference. Thus, participation in this conference was an important step in the professional development of these deaf, American graduate students. The funding also allowed the provision of American Sign Language (ASL) interpreting services at the conference. With the ASL interpreting services, the students had access to the breadth of knowledge represented at the conference, and the opportunity to interact with the experts attending. The long-term projected outcome is an increase of <em>deaf</em> sign language researchers.</p> <p>A record number of deaf students applied for this travel award (<em>N</em> = 22) and the top eight were selected to be supported. These students got the opportunity to interact with the PI and co-PIs of this project before the conference, talk about their research, and some presented their research at TISLR. In effect, they introduced themselves to a large, international community of sign language researchers and potentially increased their career opportunities in this field.&nbsp;</p> <p>The students have disseminated information about their research and their participation at TISLR through social media platforms, such as Facebook. Through university publications, the Rochester Institute of Technology and one of its colleges, the National Technical Institute for the Deaf, have disseminated information about this grant and the participating students.&nbsp;</p> <p>The presence of a cohort of deaf students from the U.S. was an important indication that the number of deaf sign language researchers in the U.S. is growing. Researchers in the sign language field were impressed by the sophistication and high level of research presented by these American students. Such a presence is important for the further development of the field, as well as for maximizing career advancement opportunities for the students supported by this grant. The role of deaf scientists, including sign language researchers, goes well beyond the academic impact. Deaf scientists are underrepresented in STEM, and especially in sign language research. Society benefits when the full range of human diversity is included in all activities, including scholarly pursuits.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;C&nbsp;Hauser</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Deaf researchers are underrepresented in sign language research. The major goal of this project was to broaden the participation of deaf individuals in disciplines that conduct sign language research. Funding was used to bring deaf graduate students to participate and present at the 13th annual meeting of the Theoretical Issues in Sign Language Research (TISLR) in Hamburg, Germany in September 2019. TISLR is the most significant and well-attended international sign language research conference. Sign language researchers from all over the world attend this conference. Thus, participation in this conference was an important step in the professional development of these deaf, American graduate students. The funding also allowed the provision of American Sign Language (ASL) interpreting services at the conference. With the ASL interpreting services, the students had access to the breadth of knowledge represented at the conference, and the opportunity to interact with the experts attending. The long-term projected outcome is an increase of deaf sign language researchers.  A record number of deaf students applied for this travel award (N = 22) and the top eight were selected to be supported. These students got the opportunity to interact with the PI and co-PIs of this project before the conference, talk about their research, and some presented their research at TISLR. In effect, they introduced themselves to a large, international community of sign language researchers and potentially increased their career opportunities in this field.   The students have disseminated information about their research and their participation at TISLR through social media platforms, such as Facebook. Through university publications, the Rochester Institute of Technology and one of its colleges, the National Technical Institute for the Deaf, have disseminated information about this grant and the participating students.   The presence of a cohort of deaf students from the U.S. was an important indication that the number of deaf sign language researchers in the U.S. is growing. Researchers in the sign language field were impressed by the sophistication and high level of research presented by these American students. Such a presence is important for the further development of the field, as well as for maximizing career advancement opportunities for the students supported by this grant. The role of deaf scientists, including sign language researchers, goes well beyond the academic impact. Deaf scientists are underrepresented in STEM, and especially in sign language research. Society benefits when the full range of human diversity is included in all activities, including scholarly pursuits.          Last Modified: 08/24/2020       Submitted by: Peter C Hauser]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
