<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Using the National Organizations Study to Examine Developments in the Labor Force in the 21st Century</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>222858.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>222858</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports the addition of the National Organizations Survey (NOS) module to the 2018 General Social Survey.  The NOS is a hypernetwork sample of employers in the United States that will produce a nationally-representative sample of employers from the self-employed up to the largest public and private organizations. It will cover government agencies, private corporations, not-for-profits, and all other sectors.  In particular, the NOS will provide data on organizations' approach to occupational health and safety and to workplace health promotion.  The availability of these data, and their linkage to the General Social Survey will enable researchers to investigate questions of importance to employers and workers, and to national health and well-being.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will link the organizational-level data to respondent-level data from the General Social Survey (GSS), allowing examination of the effect of different types of employers with different employment policies and benefits on employees' assessment of job satisfaction, the quality of working life, and many other attitudes and behaviors.   Support for the addition of the NOS module is provided by the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health of the Centers for Disease Control (CDC/NIOSH).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1848602</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tom</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tom W Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smitht@norc.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7732566288</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000227063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Opinion Research Center</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372745</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7732566000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 E. 60th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069512291</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL OPINION RESEARCH CENTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069512291</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Opinion Research Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606372745</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1155 E. 60th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>R159</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~222858</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The National Opinion Research Center at the University of Chicago designed and conducted the National Organizations Study 2019-2020. It is a hypernetwork sample of the employers of respondents to the 2018 General Social Survey. It focused on employers with 10 or more employees in the private, non-profit, and governmental sectors. Informants from the employing organizations were contacted to collection information on the structure, operation, and human resources policies of the organization. The surveys were conducted both by telephone and by the Internet.&nbsp; The employing organization could choose which mode to use to complete the interview.</p> <p>Since the last National Organizations Study had been conducted in 2002, the state of the American labor force has undergone a number of&nbsp; important changes and employers have made alterations in their structure and operation and implemented adaptations in their organizational policies in general and their human resource practices in particular. The 2019-2020 National Organization Study updated information on the practices and policies of employers and how these have changed during the 21st century.</p> <p>The National Organization Study also revised methods for contacting and gaining cooperation from employer. The adding of the web survey on the Internet is one example of changes in the data collection protocols.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Tom&nbsp;W&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The National Opinion Research Center at the University of Chicago designed and conducted the National Organizations Study 2019-2020. It is a hypernetwork sample of the employers of respondents to the 2018 General Social Survey. It focused on employers with 10 or more employees in the private, non-profit, and governmental sectors. Informants from the employing organizations were contacted to collection information on the structure, operation, and human resources policies of the organization. The surveys were conducted both by telephone and by the Internet.  The employing organization could choose which mode to use to complete the interview.  Since the last National Organizations Study had been conducted in 2002, the state of the American labor force has undergone a number of  important changes and employers have made alterations in their structure and operation and implemented adaptations in their organizational policies in general and their human resource practices in particular. The 2019-2020 National Organization Study updated information on the practices and policies of employers and how these have changed during the 21st century.  The National Organization Study also revised methods for contacting and gaining cooperation from employer. The adding of the web survey on the Internet is one example of changes in the data collection protocols.       Last Modified: 11/06/2020       Submitted by: Tom W Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
