<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GEOPRISMS Postdoctoral Scholar proposal: Unravelling monogenetic volcanism in the Cascades Volcanic Range</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299666.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299666</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ktjohnso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927442</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Globally almost 1 billion people live in areas subject to volcanic hazards. In North America, the most populated region subject to significant volcanic hazards is the Pacific Northwest. Although the hazards associated with larger stratovolcanoes such as Mount St Helens and Mount Hood are reasonably well understood, a less studied type of volcano are the so call "monogenetic" centers, smaller volcanic cones that are widely distributed throughout the region. These typically consist of a small volcanic cone and associated lava fields. The amount of material erupted is typically less than a cubic kilometer total erupted volume, although larger examples also occur. However, within the Cascade Volcanic Range, there are thousands of this type of volcanic edifice. Their wide geographic distribution and overall short eruptive life span mean that the locations and effects of future eruptions are different to stratovolcanoes, and are more difficult to predict. Most monogenetic systems have not been studied in significant detail to predict future eruption behavior. This project seeks to gain greater understanding of the subsurface magmatic processes associated with monogenetic volcanism in the relatively populous Central Oregon region of the Cascades. In particular, the project will focus on the speed and style of magma movement through the volcanic edifice during eruptions, using a range of petrological and geochemical techniques. The project includes the training of a postdoctoral investigator.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will focus on a number of monogenetic centers in the Central Oregon area, including some related to Newberry Volcano (e.g. Lava Butte) and from the MacKenzie Pass area (Collier Cone, Little Belknap Crater). For the selected volcanoes zoned crystals, melt inclusions and melt embayments will be studied for diffusion chronometry of major elements, trace elements and volatile species analysis (CO2, H2O) to constrain the time between initiation of volcanic unrest and eruption to the surface. Magma ascent rates will also be calculated based on depth estimates from melt inclusions. The goal is to constrain the time between when a new eruption may be detected using remote means (typically seismic studies) and when actual eruptions might commence. Studies of melt inclusion and crystal compositions will also allow insight into the chemical and petrological complexity and structure of monogenetic magma plumbing systems. Overall the results of this work will significantly improve knowledge of subduction-related monogenetic volcanism and the hazard response required for these centers - a hitherto less well studied type of volcanism. Evaluating eruption style (effusive vs explosive) and ascent rates from volatile analysis, together with calculated diffusion chronometry timescales, will give new insight into monogenetic volcanism in a well characterized subduction zone system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1850779</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Kent</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam Kent</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adam.kent@geo.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417371205</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487278</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318674</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 Ocean Admin]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~299666</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
