<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Extracting the Backbone of Bipartite Projections</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>119904.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>119904</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate a new way to collect network data that would make answering social scientific questions involving social networks faster and more cost-effective.  Networks are widely recognized across multiple disciplines as critically important for understanding how information spreads (communications), how illnesses spread (public health), how legislation is passed (political science), how norms and customs form (sociology), how companies and governments coordinate economic activities (economics &amp; geography), how people form and maintain relationships (developmental psychology), and how threats to national security can be disrupted (intelligence).  Collecting data on these types of networks is often costly and impractical, which has limited progress in answering these questions.  Rather than attempt to measure directly the interactions between people (or companies, or cells, etc.), the new methods developed in this project will measure interactions indirectly by looking at patterns of similar behavior. For example, it would be impractical to ask everyone in a large city who they talk with, but we may be able to infer that two people talk with one another if they routinely attend the same events. This project will compare several different methods for making these inferences to determine which method (if any) is the most accurate. Identifying accurate methods for indirectly measuring networks is important because it will reduce the time and economic cost of answering research questions, such as those noted above, that have scientific and societal benefits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The inferential methods investigated in this project are known as methods of backbone extraction. Given a bipartite projection network in which two agents (e.g., people) share some artifacts in common (e.g., they attend the same events), these methods determine whether they share enough artifacts in common to warrant the inference that they are linked (e.g., they interact with each other). Methods for making such inferences differ primarily by whether they control for nothing (e.g., an unconditional threshold), for the number of artifacts each agent has (e.g., a hypergeometric threshold), or for both the number of artifacts each agent has and the number of agents each artifact has (e.g., the fixed and stochastic degree sequence models). After implementation of several existing methods in a publicly available package for the R software and evaluation of their computational complexity, their ability to accurately recover known (i.e., ground truth) networks with varying structural properties from synthetic bipartite data that contain varying amounts of noise will be compared. In addition, the performance of these methods using two publicly available benchmark empirical bipartite datasets that have known ground truths will be tested.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1851625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Sagan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce E Sagan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sagan@math.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173558329</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000466466</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Neal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zachary Neal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zpneal@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174321811</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000598734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241116</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[316 Physics Rd., Room 134B]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~119904</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview</strong><br />Social networks are difficult to measure directly, so researchers often use bipartite projections to measure them indirectly. A bipartite projection views two nodes as connected to the extent that they share attributes. For example, a bipartite projection can be used to measure political collaboration in the US Congress by viewing two legislators as connected to the extent that they sponsored the same bills. However, inferring social networks from bipartite projections is challenging because it requires determining how many attributes two nodes must share before they should be considered connected in the network. This project has developed several solutions to this challenge.<br /><br /><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong><br />We have developed or improved, tested, and implemented five ensemble models for extracting the backbone of bipartite projections: fixed fill model, fixed row model, fixed column model, stochastic degree sequence model, and fixed degree sequence model. Each of these models offers a statistical framework for determining whether a bipartite network and its projection provides evidence to infer that two nodes are connected. In some cases (e.g. fixed fill, fixed column), the models were newly developed and involved the derivation of parametric probability mass functions. In other cases (e.g. stochastic and fixed degree sequence), the models already existed but their speed and accuracy was improved. We find that the stochastic degree sequence model (SDSM) offers fast and high-quality inferences under a broad range of circumstances, and recommend its use. All models are now implemented in the "backbone" package for R.<br /><br /><strong>Products</strong><br />This project has led to several products, including peer-reviewed publications, software, and workshop materials. All the following products are freely available online:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&#9642;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Domagalski, R., Neal, Z. P., &amp; Sagan, B. (2021). Backbone: An R package for extracting the backbone of bipartite projections. <em>Plos one, 16(1)</em>, e0244363.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&#9642;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Neal, Z. P., Domagalski, R., &amp; Yan, X. (2022). Homophily in collaborations among US House Representatives, 1981-2018. <em>Social Networks, 68</em>, 97-106.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&#9642;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Neal, Z. P., Neal, J. W., &amp; Domagalski, R. (2021). False positives using social cognitive mapping to identify children's peer groups. <em>Collabra: Psychology, 7(1)</em>.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&#9642;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Neal, Z. P., Domagalski, R., &amp; Sagan, B. (2021). Analysis of Spatial Networks From Bipartite Projections Using the R Backbone Package. <em>Geographical Analysis</em>. <br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&#9642;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Neal, Z. P., Domagalski, R., &amp; Sagan, B. (2021). Comparing Models for Extracting the Backbone of Bipartite Projections. arXiv preprint arXiv:2105.13396.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&#9642;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Domagalski, R. J., Neal, Z. P., and Sagan, B. (2019). Backbone package. The Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN). https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=backbone</p> <p><br /><strong>Broader Impacts</strong><br />There is evidence that this work has had a broad impact on network analysis in several disciplines. First, the open-source backbone package has been installed over 14,000 times since its initial release. Second, despite their recency, the papers published from this project have been cited 13 times. Finally, in part through her participation on the project and through mentorship from the PI, Rachel Domagalski is on track to successfully defend a dissertation in Mathematics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Zachary&nbsp;Neal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview Social networks are difficult to measure directly, so researchers often use bipartite projections to measure them indirectly. A bipartite projection views two nodes as connected to the extent that they share attributes. For example, a bipartite projection can be used to measure political collaboration in the US Congress by viewing two legislators as connected to the extent that they sponsored the same bills. However, inferring social networks from bipartite projections is challenging because it requires determining how many attributes two nodes must share before they should be considered connected in the network. This project has developed several solutions to this challenge.  Intellectual Merit We have developed or improved, tested, and implemented five ensemble models for extracting the backbone of bipartite projections: fixed fill model, fixed row model, fixed column model, stochastic degree sequence model, and fixed degree sequence model. Each of these models offers a statistical framework for determining whether a bipartite network and its projection provides evidence to infer that two nodes are connected. In some cases (e.g. fixed fill, fixed column), the models were newly developed and involved the derivation of parametric probability mass functions. In other cases (e.g. stochastic and fixed degree sequence), the models already existed but their speed and accuracy was improved. We find that the stochastic degree sequence model (SDSM) offers fast and high-quality inferences under a broad range of circumstances, and recommend its use. All models are now implemented in the "backbone" package for R.  Products This project has led to several products, including peer-reviewed publications, software, and workshop materials. All the following products are freely available online:     &#9642;    Domagalski, R., Neal, Z. P., &amp; Sagan, B. (2021). Backbone: An R package for extracting the backbone of bipartite projections. Plos one, 16(1), e0244363.     &#9642;    Neal, Z. P., Domagalski, R., &amp; Yan, X. (2022). Homophily in collaborations among US House Representatives, 1981-2018. Social Networks, 68, 97-106.     &#9642;    Neal, Z. P., Neal, J. W., &amp; Domagalski, R. (2021). False positives using social cognitive mapping to identify children's peer groups. Collabra: Psychology, 7(1).     &#9642;    Neal, Z. P., Domagalski, R., &amp; Sagan, B. (2021). Analysis of Spatial Networks From Bipartite Projections Using the R Backbone Package. Geographical Analysis.      &#9642;    Neal, Z. P., Domagalski, R., &amp; Sagan, B. (2021). Comparing Models for Extracting the Backbone of Bipartite Projections. arXiv preprint arXiv:2105.13396.     &#9642;    Domagalski, R. J., Neal, Z. P., and Sagan, B. (2019). Backbone package. The Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN). https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=backbone   Broader Impacts There is evidence that this work has had a broad impact on network analysis in several disciplines. First, the open-source backbone package has been installed over 14,000 times since its initial release. Second, despite their recency, the papers published from this project have been cited 13 times. Finally, in part through her participation on the project and through mentorship from the PI, Rachel Domagalski is on track to successfully defend a dissertation in Mathematics.       Last Modified: 06/29/2021       Submitted by: Zachary Neal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
