<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel and Student PC Meeting Support for IEEE S&amp;P 2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>37000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>37000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Indrajit Ray</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>iray@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925387</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The IEEE Security and Privacy Symposium, sponsored by the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) is a top-tier venue for quick and wide dissemination of cutting-edge research results in cyber-security and privacy and has been for much of its 40-year history. Participation in this symposium gives students the opportunity to showcase their research and network with established researchers in the cyber security area. Such participation is an important part of graduate education in cyber security. The 2019 IEEE Security and Privacy Symposium will consist of approximately 60 technical papers including several Systematization of Knowledge papers, which provide a valuable background to students who are starting out in specific research areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides travel support to encourage participation in the 2019 IEEE Security and Privacy Symposium and its Student Program Committee meeting by students who would normally find it difficult to attend. Criteria for selection include evidence of a serious interest in the field, as demonstrated by coursework and/or project experience. Organizers encourage participation of women and students from other under-represented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1852720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yao</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yao Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yliu@cse.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8139745465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>TAMPA</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4202 E. Fowler Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~37000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The NSF grant funded<span>&nbsp;17 students to attend the student PC meeting of IEEE S&amp;P 2019, and&nbsp;21 students to attend this conference. Among funded conference attendees, 12 of them were women students and there was one African-American student. For conference travel award, we received 83 applications, with 32 applications from women students, 49 applicants from male students, and 2 applicants did not disclose the gender. Among the application pool, 71 applicants are PhD students, 6 applicants are master students, and 6 applicants are undergraduate students.</span></span></p> <p>We also conducted a survey to evaluate sutdent experience and below are the survey questions.</p> <p>Have you ever attended the symposium before?<br />What is your name?<br />Do you plan to attend the symposium/workshop in the future?<br />Is the student travel grant helpful to you?<br />Which university are you affiliated with?<br />Do you think attending the symposium/workshop can enrich your research capability?<br />Do you think the symposium /workshop a good venue to network with other researchers?<br />Which technical session do you find the most interesting?<br />Do you feel encouraged to work in the fields of security and privacy in the future?</p> <p>Summary of the survey results:</p> <p>From all student responses, 83.3% students indicate that they have attended the symposium before and 16.7% students are first-time attendees. 88.9% students indicate that&nbsp;the travel grant is helpful and the rest of students think that the travel grant may be helpful. All students indicate that (1) they would like to attend the conference in the future,&nbsp; (2) the travel grant can enrich their research capability, and (3) the conference is a good venue for them to network with other researchers. 94.4% students feel that they are encouraged to work in the fields of security and privacy.</p> <p><span><span><br /></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Yao&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF grant funded 17 students to attend the student PC meeting of IEEE S&amp;P 2019, and 21 students to attend this conference. Among funded conference attendees, 12 of them were women students and there was one African-American student. For conference travel award, we received 83 applications, with 32 applications from women students, 49 applicants from male students, and 2 applicants did not disclose the gender. Among the application pool, 71 applicants are PhD students, 6 applicants are master students, and 6 applicants are undergraduate students.  We also conducted a survey to evaluate sutdent experience and below are the survey questions.  Have you ever attended the symposium before? What is your name? Do you plan to attend the symposium/workshop in the future? Is the student travel grant helpful to you? Which university are you affiliated with? Do you think attending the symposium/workshop can enrich your research capability? Do you think the symposium /workshop a good venue to network with other researchers? Which technical session do you find the most interesting? Do you feel encouraged to work in the fields of security and privacy in the future?  Summary of the survey results:  From all student responses, 83.3% students indicate that they have attended the symposium before and 16.7% students are first-time attendees. 88.9% students indicate that the travel grant is helpful and the rest of students think that the travel grant may be helpful. All students indicate that (1) they would like to attend the conference in the future,  (2) the travel grant can enrich their research capability, and (3) the conference is a good venue for them to network with other researchers. 94.4% students feel that they are encouraged to work in the fields of security and privacy.          Last Modified: 03/02/2020       Submitted by: Yao Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
