<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GLOBE 23rd Annual Meeting: Intersections of Diverse Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>245089.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>245089</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Global Learning and Observations to Benefit the Environment (GLOBE) Program is a worldwide science and education community that currently consists of more than 125 U.S. Partners and 121 Partner Countries. It is a community of students, teachers, scientists, and citizens working together to better understand, sustain, and improve Earth's environment at local, regional, and global scales.&lt;br/&gt;The mission of GLOBE is to promote the teaching and learning of science; enhance environmental literacy and stewardship; and promote scientific discovery. More broadly, the GLOBE Program strives to expand the pipeline of future scientists and STEM professionals for industry, academia, and government as well as to engage citizens in collecting data about their local environment.&lt;br/&gt;The theme of the 23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting is Intersections of Diverse Environments. The location for the Annual Meeting, Detroit, Michigan, is positioned at the intersection of multiple types of diverse environments culturally, geographically, and economically. The municipality of Detroit, the largest town on the US-Canadian border, has a population of over 670,000 people and the metropolitan area is home to close to 6 million people. Within the urban downtown of Detroit is Belle Isle, a 982-acre island park in the Detroit River between Michigan and Ontario. Belle Isle includes an aquarium, conservatory, nature center, and natural areas to explore and discover (about 1/3 of the island is natural woodlands). The island, which is accessible by car and bus, is home to many types of small animals, birds, and insects. Protocol trainings will allow Annual Meeting participants to visit Belle Isle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At the Annual Meeting, the theme of Intersections of Diverse Environments will be explored further in multiple strands. These strands are: 1) Finding nature in urban landscapes; 2) Exploring changing environments, 3) GLOBE and technology, and 4) GLOBE gives back. GLOBE community members will be invited to propose talks based upon the themes. Additionally, trainings will be offered by NASA SciAct Earth Science Education awardees (GLOBE Mission EARTH, The AREN Project, Arctic and Earth SIGNs, and the NASA Earth Science Education Collaborative (NESEC)). Woven through all the strands will be the overarching theme of inclusion and diversity. All presenters will be asked to think about equity and inclusiveness for their talks, panels, and demonstrations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1852077</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Malmberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie Malmberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>malmberg@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034972649</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642739</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 Center Green Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078339587</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078339587</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCAR]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3090 Center Green Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~245089</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3d06d461-7fff-b88a-8529-eff6abd0cecf"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting<br />Theme: Intersections of Diverse Environments&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><em>Outcomes</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The 23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting, held in Detroit, Michigan, USA in July 2019, was a time for students, teachers, scientists, working group members, partners, country coordinators, and other community members to come together and share the most recent activities, research, and science related to GLOBE. Prior to the meeting, staff from the GLOBE Implementation Office, the meeting hosts, and community members from all over the world met multiple times, both virtually and in person, to plan the meeting. At the meeting, participants explored the theme of &ldquo;Intersections of Diverse Environments&rdquo; in four strands that encouraged participants to find nature in urban landscapes, explore changing environment, think about GLOBE and technology, and share how GLOBE gives back.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The 241 participants, including 58 students, from 35 countries took part in plenary sessions as well as oral and poster presentations, listened to keynote speakers, participated in an overnight student experience at Howell Nature Center, took part in hands-on science protocol trainings and demonstrations, and had time for sharing of cultures and experiences. Participants had a space to speak with program sponsors, the Regional Coordination Officers, and their peers from other countries. All presenters were asked to think about and share about diversity, equity, and inclusion in their presentations and demonstrations.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In a survey of adult participants, 97% of respondents (n=71) found the meeting to be excellent or good for providing a time to learn from experts and each other about GLOBE-related sciences and activities. Of the students who attended, 95% of the respondents (n=17) described their experience as excellent or good, 100% said the meeting increased their motivation to be involved in science-related activities, and 94% strongly agreed or agreed that the meeting made them want to learn more about science and the natural world.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><em>Intellectual Merit</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>At the 23rd Annual Meeting, GLOBE participants took part in science training, learned about education resources and activities, and discussed practices for incorporating GLOBE into the classroom and communities. Additionally, participants saw examples of students conducting and presenting authentic research that encouraged the integration of data-based evidence from the use of GLOBE protocols and learning activities. Partners learned about STEM equity and inclusion and plans for its greater emphasis in GLOBE. The community also saw an update on the GLOBE strategic plan and were able to ask questions about where GLOBE has been and where it is going. During the &ldquo;unconferecing&rdquo; session, participants were able to work with other community members on self-identified areas of interest.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><em>Broader Impacts</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The theme of </span><span>Intersections of Diverse Environments</span><span> was explored in multiple strands. These strands were: 1) Finding nature in urban landscapes, 2) Exploring changing environments, 3) GLOBE and technology, and 4) GLOBE gives back. GLOBE community members proposed talks based upon the strands. Keynote speakers, plenary talks, and the BE with GLOBE volunteer opportunity also addressed the strands. Woven through all the strands was the overarching theme of inclusion and diversity - all presenters were asked to think about equity and inclusiveness for their talks, panels, and demonstrations.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233885296_DSC06496_--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233885296_DSC06496_--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BE with GLOBE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233885296_DSC06496_--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BE with GLOBE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Volunteers helped Benefit the Environment (BE) with GLOBE at an urban garden in Detroit with Bees in the D</div> <div class="imageCredit">Autumn Burdick</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</div> <div class="imageTitle">BE with GLOBE</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233637547_U40A4135--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233637547_U40A4135--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poster Session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233637547_U40A4135--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poster Session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A GLOBE student shares information about her research with a GLOBE scientist</div> <div class="imageCredit">Will Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poster Session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233763489_U40A6769(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233763489_U40A6769(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Student Experience"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233763489_U40A6769(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Student Experience"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students collect data in a lake at Howell Nature Center during the Student Experience</div> <div class="imageCredit">Will Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Student Experience</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233456312_GroupPhoto--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233456312_GroupPhoto--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Participants - 23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580233456312_GroupPhoto--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Participants - 23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GLOBE participants at the Annual Meeting preparing for the final banquet.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Will Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Participants - 23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580234032958_U40A5046(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580234032958_U40A5046(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sharing of Resources"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580234032958_U40A5046(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sharing of Resources"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GLOBE Mission EARTH shares cloud activities with community members</div> <div class="imageCredit">Will Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sharing of Resources</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580234196429_U40A8283--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580234196429_U40A8283--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students Reporting Out"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1852077/1852077_10586562_1580234196429_U40A8283--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students Reporting Out"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students share their research from the student experience</div> <div class="imageCredit">Will Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Julie&nbsp;Malmberg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students Reporting Out</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting Theme: Intersections of Diverse Environments  Outcomes The 23rd GLOBE Annual Meeting, held in Detroit, Michigan, USA in July 2019, was a time for students, teachers, scientists, working group members, partners, country coordinators, and other community members to come together and share the most recent activities, research, and science related to GLOBE. Prior to the meeting, staff from the GLOBE Implementation Office, the meeting hosts, and community members from all over the world met multiple times, both virtually and in person, to plan the meeting. At the meeting, participants explored the theme of "Intersections of Diverse Environments" in four strands that encouraged participants to find nature in urban landscapes, explore changing environment, think about GLOBE and technology, and share how GLOBE gives back.  The 241 participants, including 58 students, from 35 countries took part in plenary sessions as well as oral and poster presentations, listened to keynote speakers, participated in an overnight student experience at Howell Nature Center, took part in hands-on science protocol trainings and demonstrations, and had time for sharing of cultures and experiences. Participants had a space to speak with program sponsors, the Regional Coordination Officers, and their peers from other countries. All presenters were asked to think about and share about diversity, equity, and inclusion in their presentations and demonstrations.    In a survey of adult participants, 97% of respondents (n=71) found the meeting to be excellent or good for providing a time to learn from experts and each other about GLOBE-related sciences and activities. Of the students who attended, 95% of the respondents (n=17) described their experience as excellent or good, 100% said the meeting increased their motivation to be involved in science-related activities, and 94% strongly agreed or agreed that the meeting made them want to learn more about science and the natural world.  Intellectual Merit At the 23rd Annual Meeting, GLOBE participants took part in science training, learned about education resources and activities, and discussed practices for incorporating GLOBE into the classroom and communities. Additionally, participants saw examples of students conducting and presenting authentic research that encouraged the integration of data-based evidence from the use of GLOBE protocols and learning activities. Partners learned about STEM equity and inclusion and plans for its greater emphasis in GLOBE. The community also saw an update on the GLOBE strategic plan and were able to ask questions about where GLOBE has been and where it is going. During the "unconferecing" session, participants were able to work with other community members on self-identified areas of interest.  Broader Impacts The theme of Intersections of Diverse Environments was explored in multiple strands. These strands were: 1) Finding nature in urban landscapes, 2) Exploring changing environments, 3) GLOBE and technology, and 4) GLOBE gives back. GLOBE community members proposed talks based upon the strands. Keynote speakers, plenary talks, and the BE with GLOBE volunteer opportunity also addressed the strands. Woven through all the strands was the overarching theme of inclusion and diversity - all presenters were asked to think about equity and inclusiveness for their talks, panels, and demonstrations.           Last Modified: 01/28/2020       Submitted by: Julie Malmberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
