<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal: Response of mercury cycling to disturbance and restoration of low-gradient forested watersheds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>93496</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebarrera@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927780</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Environmental pollution of mercury is a global concern. Due to foliar uptake of atmospheric mercury, forested ecosystem represents an important receptor of mercury pollution, while low-gradient forest watersheds in the southeastern United States represent hotspots for production of highly toxic methylmercury that poses a risk to humans and wildlife through consumption of fish and other high trophic level food sources. Throughout the southeastern region, there is an initiative to restore the native longleaf pine over the existing loblolly pine. The proposed research will examine how forest restoration affects various mercury cycling processes in southeastern coastal plain forests. This work will lead to an enhanced understanding of how forest restoration can affect the retention of mercury within watersheds and the production of toxic methylmercury. The proposed work will provide unique training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students of diverse academic backgrounds from the University of North Carolina at Greensboro (UNCG), a minority serving institution, the University of Michigan (U-M), and the Clemson University. Also, home-schooled students in the coastal region of South Carolina will be involved in the sample collection and processing in order to provide a more formal STEM training to these groups of children lacking resources. The principal investigators will integrate this research into teaching materials of existing classes, including field visits and case studies, and also carry out outreach to professional foresters to inform them about how forestry practices may alter mercury cycling. The work will be widely disseminated through seminars, conference presentations, and peer-reviewed publications.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project proposes to use stable mercury isotopes as an integrative tool to better understand the effects of short-term forest disturbance (prescribed fires, thinning, and clear cut) and longer-term forest restoration (switching back to native tree species with lower water demand) on mercury cycling in a low-gradient coastal forested watershed in South Carolina, where mercury methylation is extensive in poorly drained soils. The project will take place in a paired watershed at Santee Experimental Forest, a typical coastal plain forest headwater watershed. Specifically, the project will use stable mercury isotope ratios to monitor depositional pathways of mercury into the experimental forested watershed and also to distinguish the depositional pathways of mercury exported by the streams. Further, methylmercury isotopes measured in terrestrial and aquatic food web components will provide insights into methylmercury formation and degradation pathways during and after forest manipulation in the experimental watershed. Thus, the proposed work will provide a unique chance to test the utility of stable mercury isotopes for tracking atmospheric mercury deposition and mercury methylation and for following uptake of mercury from different sources into the food webs of both experimental and reference watersheds. Further, microcosm studies will be conducted in order to disentangle different environmental factors and their effects on mercury methylation in these forest soils. Through answering these interrelated questions, the proposed work will be able to reveal the effects of forest management on mercury deposition and methylmercury production in a forested ecosystem in the southeastern region of North America.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1852020</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Chow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex Chow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>achow@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646562424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juang</FirstName>
<LastName>Chong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juang Chong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>juanghc@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8436623526</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633183</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
<LastName>Trettin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carl C Trettin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ctrettin@fs.fed.us</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8433365602</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000664961</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Baruch Institute, Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>GEORGETOWN</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>294420596</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[177 Hobcaw Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~93496</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
