<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Topical Conference on Microbes at Biomedical Interfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14922.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14922</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Randy Duran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rduran@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925326</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As a field in need of new material design (Microbes at Biomedical Interfaces) as well as collaboration between the professionals and young researchers in medicine and engineering, the PI is organizing the Topical Conference on Microbes at Biomedical Interfaces. The Topical Conference on Microbes at Biomedical Interfaces chair is guiding the conference development and is a leader in the field. &lt;br/&gt;Conference Chair: Tagbo Niepa, PhD., University of Pittsburgh&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1853004</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriel</FirstName>
<LastName>Levesque-Tremblay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriel Levesque-Tremblay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gabrl@aiche.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6464951350</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000703681</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/05/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tagbo</FirstName>
<LastName>Niepa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tagbo Niepa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tniepa@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126247400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000754391</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/05/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Institute of Chemical Engineers</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100054020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6464951350</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>120 Wall Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[23rd floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073269003</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INSTITUTE OF CHEMICAL ENGINEERS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073269003</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Westin Convention Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152223808</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Penn Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~14922</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our increasing fundamental knowledge of infection control coupled with engineering capabilities to produce novel materials allows for innovative solutions to healthcare challenges. The purpose of the Microbes at Biomedical Interfaces topical conference was to bring together medical professionals as well as biomedical and chemical engineers to discuss ways in which their disciplines can collaborate to find new solutions to fundamental and applied problems limiting the development of new biocompatible materials and methods of minimizing the risk of pathogenic infections. The aims of the topical conference were threefold: to discuss the interaction of cells with the biomedical surfaces, to examine the usage and challenges of novel materials in healthcare, and to uncover new approaches for infection prevention.</p> <p>Student participation was highly encouraged at the topical conference, which featured an undergraduate poster competition as well as a graduate student oral competition, and the winners of both of these competitions were announced at the end of the conference. The conference featured five sessions: (1) Microbial Interaction with Bio interfaces, (2) Functional Interfaces to Control Pathogenic or Beneficial Microbes, (3) Electroactive Biomaterials to Sense and Control Microbial Infections, (4) Biocolloids, Biomolecules, and Nanomaterials of Medical Relevance, and (5) Multifunctional Biomaterials Addressing Current Healthcare Challenges.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Gabriel&nbsp;Levesque-Tremblay</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our increasing fundamental knowledge of infection control coupled with engineering capabilities to produce novel materials allows for innovative solutions to healthcare challenges. The purpose of the Microbes at Biomedical Interfaces topical conference was to bring together medical professionals as well as biomedical and chemical engineers to discuss ways in which their disciplines can collaborate to find new solutions to fundamental and applied problems limiting the development of new biocompatible materials and methods of minimizing the risk of pathogenic infections. The aims of the topical conference were threefold: to discuss the interaction of cells with the biomedical surfaces, to examine the usage and challenges of novel materials in healthcare, and to uncover new approaches for infection prevention.  Student participation was highly encouraged at the topical conference, which featured an undergraduate poster competition as well as a graduate student oral competition, and the winners of both of these competitions were announced at the end of the conference. The conference featured five sessions: (1) Microbial Interaction with Bio interfaces, (2) Functional Interfaces to Control Pathogenic or Beneficial Microbes, (3) Electroactive Biomaterials to Sense and Control Microbial Infections, (4) Biocolloids, Biomolecules, and Nanomaterials of Medical Relevance, and (5) Multifunctional Biomaterials Addressing Current Healthcare Challenges.          Last Modified: 03/23/2020       Submitted by: Gabriel Levesque-Tremblay]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
