<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PaySpray</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pamela McCauley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project (PaySpray) is to provide a platform in which the members offer their products or services to the network, increase their assets, and use them to reduce their debts. Each member of the system is a network node who is connected to the other members through financial links that represent debt or credit relationships. Once a transaction occurs between two members of a network, either inside a system or outside of it, the link including transaction information will be created between them. PaySpray owns the knowledge over all the networks supplies, demands, and transactions and finds the optimum way to suggest the services from members to members to close a cycle. Members can be individuals or companies, and services can be anything legal to be sold or done. A member of a cycle may be a member of multiple cycles. Services may exceed the amount of the owed money or be less than that, the remaining debt can be paid either by paying money or providing another service or entering into a new cycle. The object is to create a network that permits various type of payments, bartering and financial transactions to manage an individuals or organizations finances. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes Artificial intelligence on a platform that intelligently connects users for financial transactions.  Members may invite anyone to join their network that they have financial relationships with whether they are the payee  or recipient of the finances.  This process continues until   until a cycle is created.  The system permits multiple cycles, and members can participate in multiple cycles. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In developing the application, a heuristic complex network algorithm  was utilized to identify the possible loops, matching service and demand in the networks. This was also used as a means to improve the efficiency and optimize performance of the model. The research also applied machine learning algorithms (mainly Natural Language Processing) to extract the information from users, inputs and use the output of the ML model to match service and demands. As a future improvement, researchers will apply deep learning RNN models in order to detect the fraud services and demands in the app.  Currently the application is developed in AngularJS with MongoDB Databases and deployed on Amazon Web Service.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1854863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Dehghan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali Dehghan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dehghan.alex@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102702459</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000767233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/26/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Playa Vista</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[13151 Fountain Park Dr #C122]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>43</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA43</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PaySpray team completed an intensive customer discovery process through local and national NSF I-Corps programs in Dec 2018. The team conducted more than 160 interviews with potential users to find the right customer segment, customer value proposition and product market fit. The customer discovery outcomes indicated that college students could be the potential customer segment for the PaySpray technology. This is due to the fact that the PaySpray technology assists the members by reducing their debt, a significant pain point for college students who are among the lowest income demographics. Since college students generally live on a tight budget and have flexible hours, it would be more likely for them to use PaySpray for remedying their major pain point, i.e., debt. In a college environment, a large number of nodes (people) create a large number of small financial interactions which may potentially lead to more debt-canceling cycles. On the other hand, college students have flexible hours compared to the public and they are willing to allocate their free time to provide services leading to reduction or cancellation of their debt.&nbsp;</p> <p>To conclude, we learnt who would be our customer segment, customer value proposition and whether PaySpray is right product market fit.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2019<br>      Modified by: Ali&nbsp;Dehghan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PaySpray team completed an intensive customer discovery process through local and national NSF I-Corps programs in Dec 2018. The team conducted more than 160 interviews with potential users to find the right customer segment, customer value proposition and product market fit. The customer discovery outcomes indicated that college students could be the potential customer segment for the PaySpray technology. This is due to the fact that the PaySpray technology assists the members by reducing their debt, a significant pain point for college students who are among the lowest income demographics. Since college students generally live on a tight budget and have flexible hours, it would be more likely for them to use PaySpray for remedying their major pain point, i.e., debt. In a college environment, a large number of nodes (people) create a large number of small financial interactions which may potentially lead to more debt-canceling cycles. On the other hand, college students have flexible hours compared to the public and they are willing to allocate their free time to provide services leading to reduction or cancellation of their debt.   To conclude, we learnt who would be our customer segment, customer value proposition and whether PaySpray is right product market fit.           Last Modified: 05/24/2019       Submitted by: Ali Dehghan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
