<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Scalable Distributed MIMO: Towards Density-Proportional Capacity Scaling for Infrastructure Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>392605.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>392605</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proliferation of mobile devices is driving an ever-increasing demand on the capacity of infrastructure wireless networks, especially Wi-Fi. Current wireless networks can hardly meet this demand because they are interference limited -- per-user throughput decreases super-linearly with network density.  Adding more access points (APs) may worsen the problem, because the APs themselves interfere with each other.  The objective of this research is to overcome this fundamental limitation, and enable network capacity to scale proportionally with node density, by exploring a transformative architecture called Scalable Distributed MIMO (SDM). The principle behind SDM is to reorganize the APs into clusters. Within each cluster, the APs tightly synchronize and share data with each other. This enables them to cancel the mutual interference and scale network capacity with AP density. Different AP clusters contend for channel access in a self-organized manner, thus scaling capacity across an entire network. The long-term objective of SDM is to enable dense indoor infrastructure networks supporting Gbps per-user throughput, marking an important step towards the goals outlined in the National Broadband Plan.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To realize the SDM principle, the proposed research synthesizes a comprehensive framework of tasks spanning five years, including performance modeling/analysis, network protocol/algorithm design, and implementation/experimentation on a software radio testbed. In particular, the PI plans to (i) systematically explore ways of deploying AP clusters to balance the tradeoffs between system complexity, scalability, and compatibility with legacy networks;  (ii) design a new paradigm of cluster-centric network protocols that feature tight coordination between APs within a cluster and self-organization among different clusters;  (iii) develop new communications algorithms that tame the coordination overhead while maximizing cluster capacity, and translate the capacity gain into improved end-user experience.  The testbed used in the research tasks will be extended into a user-friendly educational platform that enhances the knowledge of wireless networks for students at different levels. The research and educational materials will be broadly disseminated for reproducibility of results.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/22/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1854472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xinyu</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xinyu Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xyzhang@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585346426</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000634123</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/22/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930407</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~13035</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~87259</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~99192</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~104499</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~88620</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Modern communications systems have been steadily advancing their link speed, from a few Mbps to multi-Gbps in the past two decades. Nonetheless, the actual network capacity perceived by end users lags far behind expectation. A nominal Gbps wireless network may only provision Mbps level per-user throughput in densely populated areas like conference venues, convention centers, multimedia classrooms, libraries and other public hotspots. This is primarily because the different transmitters compete and interfere with each other, which decreases the actual per-user throughput as network density increases.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The objective of this project is to explore scalable distributed MIMO (SDM), a new multi-antenna networking technology that can scale network capacity proportionally with network density. With SDM, the network operators can satisfy end-users&rsquo; growing traffic demand by simply deploying more infrastructure nodes within each coverage area. The specific research aims of SDM include (i) investigating mechanisms to decompose a large network into manageable clusters with minimum coordination overhead and without any intra-cluster interference; (ii) exploring distributed network protocols and communications algorithms to enable efficient and fair channel access among the clusters.</p> <p>To realize the SDM paradigm, the proposed research synthesizes a comprehensive framework of research thrusts, including performance modeling/analysis, network protocol/algorithm design, and implementation/experimentation on programmable radio platforms. The most significant research outcome of this project includes: (i) Designing a framework that scales the throughput of Multi-user MIMO (MU-MIMO) with the number of users, by strategically grouping the users, reducing the user selection overhead, and compressing the feedback messages. (ii) Designing large-scale MU-MIMO networking mechanisms which scale beyond a single network cell, by clustering and coordinating the network nodes at low overhead. &nbsp;(iii) Designing robust millimeter-wave network protocols, which facilitate efficient directional networking by coordinating distributed transmitters or by combining multiple phased array antennas. All these systems have been implemented on programmable radio testbeds and validated through comprehensive experiments.</p> <p>The SDM project has extended its impacts across academia and industry. (i) The research outcome has been disseminated through a record number of publications in top research venues, including ACM MobiCom, MobiHoc, IPSN, IEEE INFOCOM, etc. (ii) Part of the research outcome has been patented and shipped to an industry partner&rsquo;s 802.ac WiFi product line. The testbed implementation has been demonstrated in industry forums including UCSD&rsquo;s 5G&amp;Beyond forum. (iii) The software radio implementation of 802.11ac OFDM MU-MIMO has been released as open-source code to the research community. (iv) The mmWave MIMO testbed, as a side product from this project, has become open-source hardware/software, and is distributed to the research community through free loans and paid fabrication services. (v) 3 PhD students graduated out of this project, one of whom became an assistant professor in a US institution. A few MS students (including one female) have been inspired to continue their PhD study in top US institutions. Over the past project cycles, more than 10 undergraduate researchers have participated in the experimental parts of the projects, through volunteer work or paid research internship. Most of these undergraduate researchers decided to further their study in a graduate program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Xinyu&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104800399_NEMOx--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104800399_NEMOx--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NEMOx"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104800399_NEMOx--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NEMOx"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The NEMOx network architecture, in comparison to the traditional multi-cell wireless networks. (Copyright @ACM. Personal orclassroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributedfor profit or commercial advantage)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xinyu Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xinyu&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">NEMOx</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104877897_NURAtestbed--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104877897_NURAtestbed--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The NURA network MIMO testbed."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104877897_NURAtestbed--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The NURA network MIMO testbed."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The NURA network MIMO testbed (Copyright @IEEE)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xinyu Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xinyu&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">The NURA network MIMO testbed.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104961529_Hekaton--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104961529_Hekaton--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hekaton scalable massive MIMO architecture."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599104961529_Hekaton--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hekaton scalable massive MIMO architecture."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Hekaton scalable massive MIMO architecture. (Copyright @ACM. Personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xinyu Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xinyu&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hekaton scalable massive MIMO architecture.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599105053861_X-Array--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599105053861_X-Array--rgov-800width.jpg" title="X-Array millimeter-wave radio with multi-panel phased arrays."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1854472/1854472_10296632_1599105053861_X-Array--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="X-Array millimeter-wave radio with multi-panel phased arrays."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">X-Array millimeter-wave radio with multi-panel phased arrays. (Copyright @ACM. Personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xinyu Zhang</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xinyu&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">X-Array millimeter-wave radio with multi-panel phased arrays.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Modern communications systems have been steadily advancing their link speed, from a few Mbps to multi-Gbps in the past two decades. Nonetheless, the actual network capacity perceived by end users lags far behind expectation. A nominal Gbps wireless network may only provision Mbps level per-user throughput in densely populated areas like conference venues, convention centers, multimedia classrooms, libraries and other public hotspots. This is primarily because the different transmitters compete and interfere with each other, which decreases the actual per-user throughput as network density increases.      The objective of this project is to explore scalable distributed MIMO (SDM), a new multi-antenna networking technology that can scale network capacity proportionally with network density. With SDM, the network operators can satisfy end-users’ growing traffic demand by simply deploying more infrastructure nodes within each coverage area. The specific research aims of SDM include (i) investigating mechanisms to decompose a large network into manageable clusters with minimum coordination overhead and without any intra-cluster interference; (ii) exploring distributed network protocols and communications algorithms to enable efficient and fair channel access among the clusters.  To realize the SDM paradigm, the proposed research synthesizes a comprehensive framework of research thrusts, including performance modeling/analysis, network protocol/algorithm design, and implementation/experimentation on programmable radio platforms. The most significant research outcome of this project includes: (i) Designing a framework that scales the throughput of Multi-user MIMO (MU-MIMO) with the number of users, by strategically grouping the users, reducing the user selection overhead, and compressing the feedback messages. (ii) Designing large-scale MU-MIMO networking mechanisms which scale beyond a single network cell, by clustering and coordinating the network nodes at low overhead.  (iii) Designing robust millimeter-wave network protocols, which facilitate efficient directional networking by coordinating distributed transmitters or by combining multiple phased array antennas. All these systems have been implemented on programmable radio testbeds and validated through comprehensive experiments.  The SDM project has extended its impacts across academia and industry. (i) The research outcome has been disseminated through a record number of publications in top research venues, including ACM MobiCom, MobiHoc, IPSN, IEEE INFOCOM, etc. (ii) Part of the research outcome has been patented and shipped to an industry partner’s 802.ac WiFi product line. The testbed implementation has been demonstrated in industry forums including UCSD’s 5G&amp;Beyond forum. (iii) The software radio implementation of 802.11ac OFDM MU-MIMO has been released as open-source code to the research community. (iv) The mmWave MIMO testbed, as a side product from this project, has become open-source hardware/software, and is distributed to the research community through free loans and paid fabrication services. (v) 3 PhD students graduated out of this project, one of whom became an assistant professor in a US institution. A few MS students (including one female) have been inspired to continue their PhD study in top US institutions. Over the past project cycles, more than 10 undergraduate researchers have participated in the experimental parts of the projects, through volunteer work or paid research internship. Most of these undergraduate researchers decided to further their study in a graduate program.          Last Modified: 09/03/2020       Submitted by: Xinyu Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
