<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Exploring Racial Socialization Processes in Black Families</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>39184.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>39184</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwelkom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Directorate of Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences offers postdoctoral research fellowships to provide opportunities for recent doctoral graduates to obtain additional training, to gain research experience under the sponsorship of established scientists, and to broaden their scientific horizons beyond their undergraduate and graduate training. Postdoctoral fellowships are further designed to assist new scientists to direct their research efforts across traditional disciplinary lines and to avail themselves of unique research resources, sites, and facilities, including at foreign locations. This postdoctoral fellowship provides an emerging scholar-scientist with an opportunity to investigate the ways in which diverse Black families navigate the racial socialization of their youth in the 21st century. The well-being of Black children in the United States is a matter of grave public health significance. The unfortunate realities of Ferguson, MI, Baltimore, MD, Sanford, FL, Charleston, SC, McKinney, TX, Cleveland, OH, and Chicago, IL, have left many in our society with questions about how to provide youth with the triumvirate "affection, protection, and correction"  required to optimize their psychosocial wellbeing. Racial socialization (RS) is a process that has been associated with a number of positive outcomes. However, this research has largely assessed Black mothers (of mother-father households), has predominately used survey data, and has focused on retrospective reporting of RS, limiting our conceptual understanding of a crucial parenting practice. This project addresses these limitations, expanding the study of RS in a number of important ways.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project, entitled the "Black Family Racial Socialization Project" focuses on the development of three studies using both quantitative and qualitative methods, from the perspective of both parents and youth. The primary aim of the first study is to use survey and interview methods to elucidate the ways in which Black families representing a diverse structural spectrum (e.g., extended kin, blended families, LGBT couples) prepare themselves to undertake the RS of their children. The primary aim of the second study is to capture the synergistic and bidirectional nature of RS "in the moment", by using media (e.g., TV scenes, song lyrics, social media posts) to create and code ecologically-valid, family-level racial socialization conversations. The primary aim of the third study is to prospectively assess how Black parents and Black parents-to-be anticipate teaching their children about race "in the future". This study will utilize annual interviews and biannual surveys to monitor how intentions to socialize Black youth (and actual socialization behaviors) change over time, and to elucidate the principal factors that instigate such changes. Together, this research will lead to the development of a more complete conceptual framework that can be tested and instituted in future investigations. In addition, the findings from this research are expected to contribute to the development of effective interventions for Black families.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1854100</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevenson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard C Stevenson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>howards@gse.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158985666</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/25/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn C Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scjones4@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8048285522</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000709026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>105300446</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>105300446</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Commonwealth University]]></Name>
<CityName>Richmond</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>232842018</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[806 W Franklin]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~39184</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Racial socialization-communication about the significance and meaning of race- is a critical parenting practice among Black families. However, a major limitation in our field?s understanding of this construct has emanated from a lack of an intentional family systems focus on racial socialization, namely, understanding how Black families create and recreate agendas of racial socialization together. This project sought to improve our understanding through three studies. Study 1 of this project collected survey, interview, and observational data from over 40 caregiver dyads. These included a) interracial b) blended c) non-romantic co-parenting and d) extended and fictive families. Study 2 of this project was a survey-based study investigating the racial socialization dynamics among 200 Black families (parent-teen dyads). Study 3 of this project sought to capture the aspirational racial socialization of expecting parents, parents of infants and toddlers, and parents of pre-school aged youth. Each of these studies advanced our understanding of racial socialization processes (e.g., when, how, and why it works?) rather than just the <em>content </em>(i.e., what are the messages?) (Anderson, Jones, &amp; Stevenson, 2019; Jones et al., under review). Empirically, findings from Study 1 have been integrated with the PI?s previous investigation of dual-Black, heterosexual, married couples, to deepen both our understanding of which factors are associated with certain typologies of couples? RS patterns (Jones et al., under review) and critical aspects of co-parenting around race (Jones &nbsp;&nbsp;&amp; Neblett, in preparation). Findings from Study 2 have deepened our understanding of ways in which the linked lives of Black parents and youth can influence the ways in which familial racial socialization unfolds (Jones et al., under review). Conceptually, this research led to the development of a novel conceptual framework of culturally informed racial socialization coparenting (Jones, under review; McHale &amp; Jones, 2021). In addition to these empirical and conceptual contributions, the project provided the PI with extensive experience with a) community-based data collection with Black families, including identifying key partners; b) mixed methods data collection; c) rigorous analysis of both interview and observational data; and d) the integration of URM students into research activities. Lastly, the former NSF project has numerous broader impacts. Reflections from interviews with the families to date suggest that discussing this topic has been very welcomed by parents, as they are "on the battlefield" trying to navigate these discussions in real time, especially in light of the social unrest of 2020 and beyond. Furthermore, many families have indicated that the interview and observational components served as an ?intervention? of sorts for the family system, elucidating the importance of having these conversations proactively and intentionally in the future. The PI has utilized these research findings to contribute via multiple media appearances (i.e., podcasts, webinars).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2021<br>      Modified by: Shawn&nbsp;C&nbsp;Jones</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Racial socialization-communication about the significance and meaning of race- is a critical parenting practice among Black families. However, a major limitation in our field?s understanding of this construct has emanated from a lack of an intentional family systems focus on racial socialization, namely, understanding how Black families create and recreate agendas of racial socialization together. This project sought to improve our understanding through three studies. Study 1 of this project collected survey, interview, and observational data from over 40 caregiver dyads. These included a) interracial b) blended c) non-romantic co-parenting and d) extended and fictive families. Study 2 of this project was a survey-based study investigating the racial socialization dynamics among 200 Black families (parent-teen dyads). Study 3 of this project sought to capture the aspirational racial socialization of expecting parents, parents of infants and toddlers, and parents of pre-school aged youth. Each of these studies advanced our understanding of racial socialization processes (e.g., when, how, and why it works?) rather than just the content (i.e., what are the messages?) (Anderson, Jones, &amp; Stevenson, 2019; Jones et al., under review). Empirically, findings from Study 1 have been integrated with the PI?s previous investigation of dual-Black, heterosexual, married couples, to deepen both our understanding of which factors are associated with certain typologies of couples? RS patterns (Jones et al., under review) and critical aspects of co-parenting around race (Jones   &amp; Neblett, in preparation). Findings from Study 2 have deepened our understanding of ways in which the linked lives of Black parents and youth can influence the ways in which familial racial socialization unfolds (Jones et al., under review). Conceptually, this research led to the development of a novel conceptual framework of culturally informed racial socialization coparenting (Jones, under review; McHale &amp; Jones, 2021). In addition to these empirical and conceptual contributions, the project provided the PI with extensive experience with a) community-based data collection with Black families, including identifying key partners; b) mixed methods data collection; c) rigorous analysis of both interview and observational data; and d) the integration of URM students into research activities. Lastly, the former NSF project has numerous broader impacts. Reflections from interviews with the families to date suggest that discussing this topic has been very welcomed by parents, as they are "on the battlefield" trying to navigate these discussions in real time, especially in light of the social unrest of 2020 and beyond. Furthermore, many families have indicated that the interview and observational components served as an ?intervention? of sorts for the family system, elucidating the importance of having these conversations proactively and intentionally in the future. The PI has utilized these research findings to contribute via multiple media appearances (i.e., podcasts, webinars).          Last Modified: 08/18/2021       Submitted by: Shawn C Jones]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
