<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Rocky Mountain Mathematics Consortium Summer School: Inverse Problems in Imaging</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuliya Gorb</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ygorb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides participant support to the Rocky Mountain Mathematics Consortium (RMMC) summer school, to be held in June 2019 at the University of Wyoming. The summer school provides an intellectually stimulating environment for graduate students and junior faculty from various backgrounds in the Rocky Mountain area to learn and discuss immensely important subjects in mathematical sciences. The RMMC summer school held annually at the University of Wyoming since 1996. It has a long tradition of encouraging the participation of female graduate students and early-career researchers in mathematical sciences. The theme for the 2019 RMMC summer school is "Inverse problems in imaging''. The program of the 2019 summer school will take place over six days. It will include short courses on selected topics given by six lecturers. There will be working group sessions. The working groups will help channel scientific discussions and the exchange of ideas on open problems and challenges in the area of inverse problems and its applications in medical and geophysical imaging.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The program of  2019 RMMC summer school is split into several topics in inverse problems and imaging. The topics include regularization methods for inverse problems in imaging, optical imaging with biomedical applications, electrical impedance tomography (EIT) and the D-bar method, statistical inference for geophysical imaging, and integral equations, sampling methods and their applications in inverse scattering. The invited lecturers are leaders in these fields. The summer school not only provides an opportunity for young scientists, including graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty in the Rocky Mountain area to interact with some of the best mathematical scientists in inverse problems and imaging sciences but also introduces the state-of-the-art techniques and research in inverse problems and image sciences to the Rocky Mountain scientific community. The web link to the RMMC summer school is https://www.uwyo.edu/mathstats/rmmc/summer19/index.html.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1855584</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Long</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Long Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>llee@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3077664368</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000348416</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Department 3355]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF grant supported the 2019 Rocket Mountain Mathematics Consortium (RMMC) summer school. The summer school was held at the University of Wyoming from June 3 - June 8, 2019. The theme of the summer school was ?inverse problems in imaging?. There were six invited lecturers (three women) who delivered a total of thirty lectures in the summer school. Demographically, there were thirty-five registered participants (eleven women and two minorities). Among them, twenty-two were supported by the summer school, while thirteen were local participants. Twenty-six of the participants were from the RMMC member universities in the Rocky Mountain area. The others were from the universities in Texas, Kansas, Virginia, Maryland, Iowa, Florida, and Oregon. The academic background of the participants was diverse: five first-year Ph.D. students, four second-year, three third-year, and twelve fourth-year and above, including a post-doctoral researcher. Among the twenty-two participants supported by the grant, eight of them are females and fourteen are males.&nbsp;This NSF fund, of $25,000, paid for the dormitory and hotel rooms and the travel expenses for the participants and the invited lecturers. There was a $10,000 matching fund from the RMMC board to pay for the meals and other food expenses. The 2019 RMMC summer school provided an intellectually stimulating environment for graduate students and junior faculty from various backgrounds. It included short courses on selected topics given by six lecturers. There were working group sessions. The working group helped channel scientific discussions and the exchange of ideas on open problems and challenges in the area of inverse problems and its applications in medical and geophysical imaging. The scientific content of the summer school includes,(1) Introduction to linear inverse problems, regularization, and software. (2) Electrical impedance tomography (EIT) and the D-bar method. (3) Optical images with biomedical applications. (4) Statistical inference and geophysical imaging: regularizations, numerics, and algorithms. (5) Integral equations, sampling methods, and their applications in inverse scattering.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Long&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF grant supported the 2019 Rocket Mountain Mathematics Consortium (RMMC) summer school. The summer school was held at the University of Wyoming from June 3 - June 8, 2019. The theme of the summer school was ?inverse problems in imaging?. There were six invited lecturers (three women) who delivered a total of thirty lectures in the summer school. Demographically, there were thirty-five registered participants (eleven women and two minorities). Among them, twenty-two were supported by the summer school, while thirteen were local participants. Twenty-six of the participants were from the RMMC member universities in the Rocky Mountain area. The others were from the universities in Texas, Kansas, Virginia, Maryland, Iowa, Florida, and Oregon. The academic background of the participants was diverse: five first-year Ph.D. students, four second-year, three third-year, and twelve fourth-year and above, including a post-doctoral researcher. Among the twenty-two participants supported by the grant, eight of them are females and fourteen are males. This NSF fund, of $25,000, paid for the dormitory and hotel rooms and the travel expenses for the participants and the invited lecturers. There was a $10,000 matching fund from the RMMC board to pay for the meals and other food expenses. The 2019 RMMC summer school provided an intellectually stimulating environment for graduate students and junior faculty from various backgrounds. It included short courses on selected topics given by six lecturers. There were working group sessions. The working group helped channel scientific discussions and the exchange of ideas on open problems and challenges in the area of inverse problems and its applications in medical and geophysical imaging. The scientific content of the summer school includes,(1) Introduction to linear inverse problems, regularization, and software. (2) Electrical impedance tomography (EIT) and the D-bar method. (3) Optical images with biomedical applications. (4) Statistical inference and geophysical imaging: regularizations, numerics, and algorithms. (5) Integral equations, sampling methods, and their applications in inverse scattering.        Last Modified: 06/04/2020       Submitted by: Long Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
