<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symmetry and Geometry on the Southern Great Plains Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides participants support to the conference "Symmetry and Geometry on the Southern Great Plains" which will take place at the University of Oklahoma, April 26-28, 2019. The goal of the conference is to advances in Riemannian geometry in the presence of symmetry. Symmetry has long been used in Riemannian geometry as a tool for building natural classes of examples and for testing/forming conjectures. The meeting will bring together a broad cross-section of experts and young mathematicians to help promote new exchanges of ideas and techniques. The organizers the organizers will promote the conference to women and under-represented groups so as to increase their participation in the meeting. The meeting will feature a diverse array of speakers with speakers ranging from graduate students to postdocs to established researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The organizers plan for this meeting to be the first one in the series of yearly conferences held alternately at the University of Oklahoma and Wichita State University during the Spring semester. "Symmetry and Geometry on the Southern Great Plains" conferences will revolve around the interaction between symmetry and geometry, with key areas represented coming from: Homogeneous and low-cohomogeneity Spaces, Lie Groups, Metric geometry, Einstein metrics, Ricci solitons, Alexandrov geometry, and manifolds of positive and non-negative curvature. There will be a mix of research and expository talks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1856652</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Jablonski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Jablonski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jablo@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4053254757</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000521945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Searle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine E Searle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>catherine.searle@wichita.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3169783160</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Five Partners Place, Suite 3100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>848348348</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046862181</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oklahoma Norman Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730193003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span class="im">The conference Symmetry and Geometry on the Southern Great Plains was&nbsp;held January 24-26, 2020, at the University of Oklahoma in Norman, OK.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span><span>The conference highlighted recent advances in Riemannian Geometry in&nbsp;</span><span>the presence of symmetry.</span><span class="im"><br /><br />A broad range of topics was covered, including various aspects of&nbsp;Ricci curvature of left-invariant metrics on Lie groups, singular Riemannian foliations, Seiberg-Witten equations, spectral geometry,&nbsp;</span><span>Weitzenbock formulas, and complex geometry. The wide range of topics helped&nbsp;</span><span>to foster the cross-pollination of ideas, promote new collaborations, and&nbsp;</span><span>help participants stay informed of the breadth of current research in&nbsp;</span><span>these areas.</span><br /><br /><span>There were a total of 14 talks:&nbsp; 6 longer talks given by&nbsp;</span><span>invited speakers, and 8 shorter, contributed talks.&nbsp; There were a&nbsp;</span><span>total of 38 participants, with more than half from Oklahoma and nearby&nbsp;</span><span>states. Speakers were a mix of senior, junior, and&nbsp;</span><span>early-career researchers, postdocs, and graduate students, thus&nbsp;</span><span class="im">exposing younger scholars and graduate students to&nbsp;cutting-edge research being done by the senior members of the&nbsp;</span><span>community, advancing visibility of the work done by younger&nbsp;</span><span>scholars, and promoting the work by those postdocs and graduate&nbsp;</span><span>students who were on the job market at the time.</span><br /><br /><span>The conference was organized around the principles of diversity and&nbsp;</span><span>inclusion and the list of invited speakers reflected&nbsp;</span><span>these principles. Additionally, a networking lunch for mathematicians&nbsp;</span><span>identifying as female was held.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Jablonski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The conference Symmetry and Geometry on the Southern Great Plains was held January 24-26, 2020, at the University of Oklahoma in Norman, OK.  The conference highlighted recent advances in Riemannian Geometry in the presence of symmetry.  A broad range of topics was covered, including various aspects of Ricci curvature of left-invariant metrics on Lie groups, singular Riemannian foliations, Seiberg-Witten equations, spectral geometry, Weitzenbock formulas, and complex geometry. The wide range of topics helped to foster the cross-pollination of ideas, promote new collaborations, and help participants stay informed of the breadth of current research in these areas.  There were a total of 14 talks:  6 longer talks given by invited speakers, and 8 shorter, contributed talks.  There were a total of 38 participants, with more than half from Oklahoma and nearby states. Speakers were a mix of senior, junior, and early-career researchers, postdocs, and graduate students, thus exposing younger scholars and graduate students to cutting-edge research being done by the senior members of the community, advancing visibility of the work done by younger scholars, and promoting the work by those postdocs and graduate students who were on the job market at the time.  The conference was organized around the principles of diversity and inclusion and the list of invited speakers reflected these principles. Additionally, a networking lunch for mathematicians identifying as female was held.       Last Modified: 12/03/2020       Submitted by: Michael Jablonski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
