<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fiftieth Southeastern Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and Computing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgdewint@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922599</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 50th Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory and Computing will be held March 4-8, 2019 at Florida Atlantic University in Boca Raton. This conference has been held annually since 1970, in Baton Rouge, Louisiana and Boca Raton, Florida. The conference has grown to be the major annual event in its disciplines and plays a major role in disseminating results and in fostering collaborative work. It is not unusual for people who discuss mathematics with each other for the first time at this conference to become long-term collaborators in combinatorial research.  Its stress on the interplay among the covered topics has continued to be one of the distinctions of the conference.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hallmarks of the conference include its mixture of friendly informality and serious mathematical collaboration among participants, who traditionally include a large number of students, as well as faculty ranging from new PhDs to very senior researchers, coming from five or six continents.  There is a commitment to diversity, and wide participation by women.  All of this contributes to the strength, breadth and vitality of the international combinatorics community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference website is at http://www.math.fau.edu/combinatorics2019/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1856716</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Spyros</FirstName>
<LastName>Magliveras</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Spyros S Magliveras</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>spyros@fau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5612970274</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000265671</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frederick Hoffman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hoffman@fau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5612973345</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000475466</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Locke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen C Locke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000482677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida Atlantic University</Name>
<CityName>BOCA RATON</CityName>
<ZipCode>334316424</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5612970777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>777 GLADES RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004147534</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA ATLANTIC UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Atlantic University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boca Raton</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>334316424</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[777 Glades Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Department of Mathematical Sciences of Florida Atlantic University hosted the <a href="http://www.math.fau.edu/combinatorics2019/" target="_blank">50th Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory and Computing</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>(SEICCGTC) on March 4-8, 2019 on the FAU Boca Raton campus. In its 50th year, the conference drew over 400 attendees from across the world.&nbsp; The more than 220 contributed papers included special sessions on, &ldquo;Combinatorial Matrix Theory,&rdquo; (organized by David Brown and Leslie Hogben), &ldquo;Structured Families of Graphs and Orders,&rdquo; (organized by Karen Collins, Michal Stern, and Ann Trenk), and &ldquo;Papers from the Graduate Research Workshops in Combinatorics,&rdquo; (organized by Michael Ferrara and Michael Young).</p> <p>This year's SEICCGTC conference was welcomed by Provost Bret Danilowicz and Dean of Science Ata Sarajedini.&nbsp; The conference featured outstanding plenary lectures by distinguished speakers, including Kristen Lauter, Ronald Graham, Laszlo Babai, Fan Chung Graham, Jon Kleinberg, Martin Golumbic, Robin Wilson and Brooks Reid.&nbsp; Robin Wilson also gave a special presentation on, &ldquo;Combinatorics and Music.&rdquo; &nbsp;Topics of the talks included: the history of the conference and its disciplines, significant developments and new breakthroughs in the field, and exciting new research. An informal problem session was held Thursday afternoon. Abstracts for all the papers appeared in a program book distributed to participants at the Conference.</p> <p>Fan Chung received her Euler medal, and Robin Wilson received his Stanton medal, both awarded by the Institute of Combinatorics and Its Applications, at the banquet, March 6, 2019,, and there was special set of awards to Fred Hoffman, at a moving ceremony in honor of the 50<sup>th</sup> Southeastern.&nbsp; Support for the conference was again provided by grants from the National Security Agency Mathematical Sciences Program and The ICA.&nbsp; This year, the National Science Foundation provided a grant of $15,000, designated for student support. &nbsp;The Conference awarded partial support to thirty students, totaling $13,559.86, and paid $1160 to provide ASL translation for a student participant with impaired hearing.&nbsp; This came to a sum of $14,719.86.</p> <p>The journal, <em>Algorithms</em> awarded two scholarship projects, to graduate and undergraduate winners of our best student paper competition.&nbsp; An award for the best paper by an FAU student was presented by the Graduate College of FAU.&nbsp; <em>Algorithms </em>and the <em>Journal of Algebraic Combinatorics</em> published special issues commemorating the 50<sup>th</sup> Southeastern.&nbsp; Participants were invited to submit full copies of their papers to the refereed journal, <em>Congressus</em> <em>Numerantium.</em>&nbsp; The three volumes of the journal comprised of 58 papers from the Conference were distributed in July, 2020.</p> <p>The conference organizing committee of Frederick Hoffman, Stephen Locke and Ronald Mullin was aided by an advisory committee of David Brown, Joanna Ellis-Monoghan, Kim Factor, Sarah Holliday, Marc Lipman and Ivelisse Rubio.&nbsp; The conference received logistical support from the department, chaired by Rainer Steinwandt, and its staff, especially Emily Cimillo and Beth Broer.&nbsp; Technical support was provided by the technical staff of the CES College of Science, especially Andrew Gultz.&nbsp; The Program and Abstracts book was prepared by Alex Milbrand.&nbsp; Overall organization, operation, logistics, communication and outreach were superbly oordinated and supervised by Maria Provost.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Frederick&nbsp;Hoffman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Department of Mathematical Sciences of Florida Atlantic University hosted the 50th Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory and Computing (SEICCGTC) on March 4-8, 2019 on the FAU Boca Raton campus. In its 50th year, the conference drew over 400 attendees from across the world.  The more than 220 contributed papers included special sessions on, "Combinatorial Matrix Theory," (organized by David Brown and Leslie Hogben), "Structured Families of Graphs and Orders," (organized by Karen Collins, Michal Stern, and Ann Trenk), and "Papers from the Graduate Research Workshops in Combinatorics," (organized by Michael Ferrara and Michael Young).  This year's SEICCGTC conference was welcomed by Provost Bret Danilowicz and Dean of Science Ata Sarajedini.  The conference featured outstanding plenary lectures by distinguished speakers, including Kristen Lauter, Ronald Graham, Laszlo Babai, Fan Chung Graham, Jon Kleinberg, Martin Golumbic, Robin Wilson and Brooks Reid.  Robin Wilson also gave a special presentation on, "Combinatorics and Music."  Topics of the talks included: the history of the conference and its disciplines, significant developments and new breakthroughs in the field, and exciting new research. An informal problem session was held Thursday afternoon. Abstracts for all the papers appeared in a program book distributed to participants at the Conference.  Fan Chung received her Euler medal, and Robin Wilson received his Stanton medal, both awarded by the Institute of Combinatorics and Its Applications, at the banquet, March 6, 2019,, and there was special set of awards to Fred Hoffman, at a moving ceremony in honor of the 50th Southeastern.  Support for the conference was again provided by grants from the National Security Agency Mathematical Sciences Program and The ICA.  This year, the National Science Foundation provided a grant of $15,000, designated for student support.  The Conference awarded partial support to thirty students, totaling $13,559.86, and paid $1160 to provide ASL translation for a student participant with impaired hearing.  This came to a sum of $14,719.86.  The journal, Algorithms awarded two scholarship projects, to graduate and undergraduate winners of our best student paper competition.  An award for the best paper by an FAU student was presented by the Graduate College of FAU.  Algorithms and the Journal of Algebraic Combinatorics published special issues commemorating the 50th Southeastern.  Participants were invited to submit full copies of their papers to the refereed journal, Congressus Numerantium.  The three volumes of the journal comprised of 58 papers from the Conference were distributed in July, 2020.  The conference organizing committee of Frederick Hoffman, Stephen Locke and Ronald Mullin was aided by an advisory committee of David Brown, Joanna Ellis-Monoghan, Kim Factor, Sarah Holliday, Marc Lipman and Ivelisse Rubio.  The conference received logistical support from the department, chaired by Rainer Steinwandt, and its staff, especially Emily Cimillo and Beth Broer.  Technical support was provided by the technical staff of the CES College of Science, especially Andrew Gultz.  The Program and Abstracts book was prepared by Alex Milbrand.  Overall organization, operation, logistics, communication and outreach were superbly oordinated and supervised by Maria Provost.          Last Modified: 09/01/2020       Submitted by: Frederick Hoffman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
