<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Response of Single- and Multi-Walled Fullerenes and Endohedral Fullerenes to Photons and Charged Particles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>171000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The encapsulation of an atom or an atomic cluster, or even a smaller fullerene in a fullerene cage offers a unique natural laboratory in which to examine the behavior of the guest system in confinement. Studies of these endofullerenes can not only lead to intriguing effects at the atomic scale but also can probe subtleties of quantum effects in the nanometer region. The endo-fullerenes also hold the promise of exciting applications in areas including, quantum computations, superconductivity, biomedical fields, drug delivery research, magnetic resonance imaging, and organic photovoltaic devices.  Further, the discovery of endo-fullerenes in extraterrestrial environments indicates their astrophysical relevance. Hence, understanding the influence of the confining cage on the spectroscopy of the confined species and vice versa, are matters of great scientific interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A theoretical study of the response of these compounds to the external electromagnetic and charged particle fields will be performed in the current research. By employing this, the roles of (i) the collectivized plasmonic motion of electrons, (ii) the dopant-fullerene hybridization, and (iii) the oscillations due to multipath interferences between electrons liberated from various sites of the compound will be investigated. Spectroscopy of fullerenes and endo-fullerenes by fast, bare ion impact will also be considered to determine in detail the effects of dipole and non-dipole collective motions, and the interference between various multipole channels. Furthermore, calculations of the electron capture by positron impact on fullerenes and endo-fullerenes, forming positroniums, will be undertaken.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1100537</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>HIMADRI</FirstName>
<LastName>CHAKRABORTY</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>HIMADRI S CHAKRABORTY</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>himadri@nwmissouri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6605621715</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000406244</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwest Missouri State University</Name>
<CityName>MARYVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>644686001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6605621440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076253319</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWEST MISSOURI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076253319</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwest Missouri State University]]></Name>
<CityName>MARYVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>644686001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~57000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~57000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~57000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The encapsulation of an atom or a cluster of atoms, or even a smaller fullerene (buckyball made of carbon atoms) inside a larger fullerene cage offers a unique molecular-level laboratory in which to examine the behavior of the guest system in sub-nanometer to nanometer (1 billionth of a meter) size confinements. &nbsp;Studies of these so called endofullerenes can not only lead to intriguing effects at the atomic scale but also can probe processes within the nanometric space that can be accessed by the current technology. &nbsp;In fact, the endofullerenes hold the promise of exciting applications in areas including quantum computations, superconductivity, biomedical fields, drug delivery research, magnetic resonance imaging, and organic photovoltaic devices. Further, the discovery of endofullerenes in extraterrestrial environments indicates their astrophysical relevance.&nbsp; Hence, understanding the influence of the confining fullerene cage on the behavior of the confined species, and <em>vice versa</em>, are matters of great scientific interest.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A theoretical/computational study of the response of endofullerenes to the radiations was performed in this research. The research computational technique employed is the most complete approach among various other models available to study these systems. Work conducted as part of this NSF award helped to further improve the methodology and diversify its target applications.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;</strong>For atoms confined in a fullerene, our previous studies predicted huge enhancements and alterations in the atom&rsquo;s response to radiations. However, it was not known how the process would evolve if instead a smaller fullerene is confined. By examining couplings between such captive-captor pair, researchers were able to uncover fundamental effects, thereby substantially adding to the current knowledge. With capabilities of precision measurements being available, such findings should motivate experiments involving cluster-doped endofullerenes. Furthermore,<strong> </strong>advancements in technology for generating extremely short attosecond (1 billion billionth of a second) laser pulses enable study of the light-matter interaction time with unprecedented precision. Results from this program produced the best agreement so far with the argon atom&rsquo;s time-delay measurements. Encouraged, attosecond response studies of a fullerene molecule and several endofullerenes were carried out from the support in the current proposal. Given the hot topicality of attophysics research, the outcome may bridge the gap between atto- and nano-sciences to establish a new domain of research in &ldquo;atto-nano-science&rdquo;. Finally, another research area focused on processes wherein a light-driven stimulation was caused at one location inside the endofullerene compound which subsequently de-stimulates to transfer energy off-site to cause a dramatic response in a new location. The current research accessed processes in endofullerenes where such local stimulations are found to induce a global response. This is similar to an antenna-receiver pair at the molecular scale where the antenna couples to the incoming light and transfers energy globally to enhance the efficiency of the ultimate output by enabling the antenna to also contribute to the process in sync with the receiver. It is researchers&rsquo; hope that this effect and related knowledge will have significant utilization in nanoscale antenna technology.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/12/2015<br>      Modified by: Himadri&nbsp;S&nbsp;Chakraborty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The encapsulation of an atom or a cluster of atoms, or even a smaller fullerene (buckyball made of carbon atoms) inside a larger fullerene cage offers a unique molecular-level laboratory in which to examine the behavior of the guest system in sub-nanometer to nanometer (1 billionth of a meter) size confinements.  Studies of these so called endofullerenes can not only lead to intriguing effects at the atomic scale but also can probe processes within the nanometric space that can be accessed by the current technology.  In fact, the endofullerenes hold the promise of exciting applications in areas including quantum computations, superconductivity, biomedical fields, drug delivery research, magnetic resonance imaging, and organic photovoltaic devices. Further, the discovery of endofullerenes in extraterrestrial environments indicates their astrophysical relevance.  Hence, understanding the influence of the confining fullerene cage on the behavior of the confined species, and vice versa, are matters of great scientific interest.          A theoretical/computational study of the response of endofullerenes to the radiations was performed in this research. The research computational technique employed is the most complete approach among various other models available to study these systems. Work conducted as part of this NSF award helped to further improve the methodology and diversify its target applications.          For atoms confined in a fullerene, our previous studies predicted huge enhancements and alterations in the atomÆs response to radiations. However, it was not known how the process would evolve if instead a smaller fullerene is confined. By examining couplings between such captive-captor pair, researchers were able to uncover fundamental effects, thereby substantially adding to the current knowledge. With capabilities of precision measurements being available, such findings should motivate experiments involving cluster-doped endofullerenes. Furthermore, advancements in technology for generating extremely short attosecond (1 billion billionth of a second) laser pulses enable study of the light-matter interaction time with unprecedented precision. Results from this program produced the best agreement so far with the argon atomÆs time-delay measurements. Encouraged, attosecond response studies of a fullerene molecule and several endofullerenes were carried out from the support in the current proposal. Given the hot topicality of attophysics research, the outcome may bridge the gap between atto- and nano-sciences to establish a new domain of research in "atto-nano-science". Finally, another research area focused on processes wherein a light-driven stimulation was caused at one location inside the endofullerene compound which subsequently de-stimulates to transfer energy off-site to cause a dramatic response in a new location. The current research accessed processes in endofullerenes where such local stimulations are found to induce a global response. This is similar to an antenna-receiver pair at the molecular scale where the antenna couples to the incoming light and transfers energy globally to enhance the efficiency of the ultimate output by enabling the antenna to also contribute to the process in sync with the receiver. It is researchersÆ hope that this effect and related knowledge will have significant utilization in nanoscale antenna technology.       Last Modified: 11/12/2015       Submitted by: Himadri S Chakraborty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
