<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Limit Cycle Control for Soft, Caterpillar-Inspired Robots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>272990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>272990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The long-term goal of this work is to develop transformative technologies for the actuation and control of mobile, soft robots in challenging field applications, such as disaster relief.  This project is an innovative, feedback-based solution for enhancing soft-robot mobility.  This solution is inspired by the caterpillar Manduca sexta, a remarkable, multi-segmented invertebrate that crawls, climbs and burrows in many terrains.  Our approach is aimed at controlling the caterpillar-like, periodic movements of a fluid-filled soft robot, in which the robot's deformable structure makes it difficult to sense or model body configuration on-the-fly.  The research has two specific research aims.  Aim 1 will formulate a control design method for generating caterpillar-like gaits by exciting sustained oscillations (e.g., limit cycles) within a deformable, fluid-filled system.  Aim 2 will quantify the in vivo kinematics of burrowing caterpillars to identify how they adapt their gait in response to rich patterns of tactile stimuli.  New educational opportunities will be developed to foster interdisciplinary controls teaching for engineering and biology students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Soft robots offer tremendous potential to enhance mobility, for example, by burrowing through debris or maneuvering through complex terrain not accessible to conventional rigid robots.   The research will have a broader impact through its integration with the team's teaching activities.  Major advances in soft robot technology are likely to come from insights gained at the interface between systems biology and controls engineering.  Hence, existing courses will be modified to introduce undergraduate biologists to engineering control, and to introduce graduate engineers to neurobiology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1100452</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Trimmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry A Trimmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barry.trimmer@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273924</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103223</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Rife</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Rife</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jason.rife@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176274732</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000090073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[136 Harrison Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1632</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031E</Code>
<Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~272990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The long-term goal of this work was to develop novel robotic control technologies to enhance the mobility of soft, caterpillar-like robots.&nbsp; Such robots could provide a low-cost and effective tool for exploration, particularly in harsh environments inaccessible by humans.&nbsp; An important potential application is disaster relief, for example, in the wake of an earthquake when there is a need to explore a rubble pile to locate possible survivors.</p> <p>Developing control strategies for a soft, highly deformable robot is a difficult challenge.&nbsp; This research effort has addressed the challenge by observing biological organisms (e.g. the <em>Manduca sexta</em> caterpillar) in order to synthesize new fundamental theory to model crawling systems.&nbsp; To this end, a critical early component of our work was to develop inverse-dynamics models of crawling caterpillars.&nbsp; These computer tools processed video of crawling caterpillars, filmed in our labs at Tufts.&nbsp; The computer models abstracted the caterpillar structure (as a system of multiple deformable bodies), inferred animal configuration and motion (kinematics) from markers on the caterpillar body, and subsequently inferred internal forces within the caterpillar body.</p> <p>As an outcome of these early studies observing caterpillar motion, our team identified two key principles highly relevant to building soft, crawling robots. The two key principles are:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The physical structure of the soft crawler should encode the desired motion, both to reduce actuator forces (e.g. generated by muscles in an animal or motors in a robot) and to reduce minimize computer processing needed to generate actuator control commands.</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Robust crawling requires a simple, robust control law for gripping the substrate (i.e. the material across which the crawler is moving).</p> <p>Our research to characterize each of these principles resulted in training three graduate students and in the dissemination of research through eight publicly available reports (theses, papers, and technical reports).&nbsp;</p> <p>In exploring the first principle, that of intentionally designing crawler structure to complement feedback control, our team developed new methods for simultaneous design of both the physical and feedback components of a system.&nbsp; Our approach was to start with linear system analysis tools, extending these to compute key system design parameters given a desired repeated motion trajectory (e.g. the repeated motion of a robot during crawling).&nbsp; Subsequent work extended these concepts to nonlinear systems, allowing for the specification of desired trajectories as limit-cycles.</p> <p>In exploring the second principle, regarding gripping, our team developed a distributed control law to trigger gripping and release of a surface by individual segments of a crawler.&nbsp; The distributed control law responds to local stretch measurements and does not require any global information about the configuration of the crawler.&nbsp; This type of control law is both relevant as a model of animal behavior and relevant for implementing a practical crawling robot.&nbsp; Analytical studies showed that this controller was highly robust in maintaining crawling across a wide range of variations (number of segments in crawler, changes in segment mass, direction of crawling relative to gravity, etc.)</p> <p>In a final phase of the project, our team explored questions about how a group of crawlers might interact.&nbsp; This investigation contributed to the development of a distributed estimation method for coordinating the position of small robots given sensor measurements of the approximate bearing angle to other robots (as might be achieved from an acoustic communication system, for example).</p> <p>Project funding also supported the development of new training opportuni...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The long-term goal of this work was to develop novel robotic control technologies to enhance the mobility of soft, caterpillar-like robots.  Such robots could provide a low-cost and effective tool for exploration, particularly in harsh environments inaccessible by humans.  An important potential application is disaster relief, for example, in the wake of an earthquake when there is a need to explore a rubble pile to locate possible survivors.  Developing control strategies for a soft, highly deformable robot is a difficult challenge.  This research effort has addressed the challenge by observing biological organisms (e.g. the Manduca sexta caterpillar) in order to synthesize new fundamental theory to model crawling systems.  To this end, a critical early component of our work was to develop inverse-dynamics models of crawling caterpillars.  These computer tools processed video of crawling caterpillars, filmed in our labs at Tufts.  The computer models abstracted the caterpillar structure (as a system of multiple deformable bodies), inferred animal configuration and motion (kinematics) from markers on the caterpillar body, and subsequently inferred internal forces within the caterpillar body.  As an outcome of these early studies observing caterpillar motion, our team identified two key principles highly relevant to building soft, crawling robots. The two key principles are:  1)     The physical structure of the soft crawler should encode the desired motion, both to reduce actuator forces (e.g. generated by muscles in an animal or motors in a robot) and to reduce minimize computer processing needed to generate actuator control commands.  2)     Robust crawling requires a simple, robust control law for gripping the substrate (i.e. the material across which the crawler is moving).  Our research to characterize each of these principles resulted in training three graduate students and in the dissemination of research through eight publicly available reports (theses, papers, and technical reports).   In exploring the first principle, that of intentionally designing crawler structure to complement feedback control, our team developed new methods for simultaneous design of both the physical and feedback components of a system.  Our approach was to start with linear system analysis tools, extending these to compute key system design parameters given a desired repeated motion trajectory (e.g. the repeated motion of a robot during crawling).  Subsequent work extended these concepts to nonlinear systems, allowing for the specification of desired trajectories as limit-cycles.  In exploring the second principle, regarding gripping, our team developed a distributed control law to trigger gripping and release of a surface by individual segments of a crawler.  The distributed control law responds to local stretch measurements and does not require any global information about the configuration of the crawler.  This type of control law is both relevant as a model of animal behavior and relevant for implementing a practical crawling robot.  Analytical studies showed that this controller was highly robust in maintaining crawling across a wide range of variations (number of segments in crawler, changes in segment mass, direction of crawling relative to gravity, etc.)  In a final phase of the project, our team explored questions about how a group of crawlers might interact.  This investigation contributed to the development of a distributed estimation method for coordinating the position of small robots given sensor measurements of the approximate bearing angle to other robots (as might be achieved from an acoustic communication system, for example).  Project funding also supported the development of new training opportunities that encouraged interactions among students in both the natural sciences and engineering.  The principal investigator (a mechanical engineer) and the co-investigator (a biologist) collaborated to create several cross-discipli...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
