<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Unified Model and Robotic Implementation of Bio-Inspired Walking and Running</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499320.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>531320</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Massimo Ruzzene</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objectives of this award are to develop and implement a biomechanically relevant, unified theory of legged dynamics that spans walking and running, and to demonstrate this theory on a new bipedal robot, ATRIAS. To date, a legged machine whose dynamic behavior can approach the performance of human walking and running, including transitions between these two gaits, does not exist. The research will result in principled models of gait and gait transitions with human-like leg dynamics, in generalized models for manipulating cyclic hybrid dynamic systems to achieve different goal behaviors, and in the verification and demonstration of this new scientific understanding with a bipedal robot. The research progresses from analyzing simplified gait models that capture the essential dynamics of human locomotion to integrating these modules in a core dynamics model of human gait. Goal behavior manipulations will be approached using the influence of parameters on the shape of the Poincare map in these cyclic dynamic systems. Experimental verification on the robot will demonstrate and refine the theoretical progress. Deliverables include modeling and simulation software, experimental verification and demonstration on robot hardware, documentation of research results, and engineering student education and research experience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research will provide the opportunity to create control algorithms for powered legged systems that enable functionally versatile behaviors similar to animals and humans. Examples include prosthetic legs and exoskeletons that provide human users with human-like leg dynamics during walking, running, and the transitions between these gaits. Other examples include legged robots that achieve robust and efficient dynamic turning behaviors. The results will be disseminated to encourage commercial applications and further development. A simulation of the robot implementation of the results will be posted online to engage healthy competition in the development of control algorithms for powered legs. Graduate and undergraduate students will benefit through classroom integration, research involvement, and a "tree of mentoring" where the supported personnel will advise and mentor undergraduate robotics club students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1100232</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hurst</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan W Hurst</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jonathan.hurst@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417377010</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000528997</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hartmut</FirstName>
<LastName>Geyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hartmut Geyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hgeyer@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122681724</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7478</Code>
<Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~499320</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was centered on the idea of creating, controlling, and implementing a unified model for walking and running. &nbsp;The foundations for the project begin with the spring-mass model, derived from biomechanics studies of animal data, showing that a simple spring-mass model can describe behaviors of both walking and running.</p> <p>In the course of the project, we first demonstrated that simple control methods can control a spring-mass model from stepping in place, to a walking gait, smoothly to a running gait, and cna handle large unexpected disturbances such as large steps up or down.&nbsp;</p> <p>A significant portion of this work was then devoted to implementation and validation of the theoretical results. An important conclusion of this work is that many control methods for the ideal spring-mass model are, in realistic situations, extremely sensitive to noise and small errors or disturbances, and do not function on a real system.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a final result of this work, we created control methods that respect and recognize the spring-mass concept, while also considering the realistic limitations of robots. &nbsp;Our bipedal robot ATRIAS walked in 3D, with no external support or tether, and made a smooth speed transition to a running gait. Further, ATRIAS demonstrated robustness to large unexpected disturbances, from human kicks to walking or running over large unexpected disturbances. &nbsp;To our knowledge, ATRIAS is the first machine to reproduce the ground reaction forces of human walking. &nbsp;</p> <p>We hypothesized that the spring-mass model captures the physics of walking and running; and founded our hardware design and our control efforts on this hypothesis. After successfully achiving a walking gait, the ground reaction forces were measured and proved to match those of a human; thus, the ground reaction forces were not intentionally forced to match those of a human, but instead serve as strong evidence that ATRIAS captures the fundamental physics of human and animal gaits.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/22/2016<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Hurst</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1100232/1100232_10128521_1453484340415_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1100232/1100232_10128521_1453484340415_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ATRIAS at the stadium"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1100232/1100232_10128521_1453484340415_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ATRIAS at the stadium"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ATRIAS, a new bipedal robot, demonstrating walking and running gaits at the stadium</div> <div class="imageCredit">Oregon State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Hurst</div> <div class="imageTitle">ATRIAS at the stadium</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was centered on the idea of creating, controlling, and implementing a unified model for walking and running.  The foundations for the project begin with the spring-mass model, derived from biomechanics studies of animal data, showing that a simple spring-mass model can describe behaviors of both walking and running.  In the course of the project, we first demonstrated that simple control methods can control a spring-mass model from stepping in place, to a walking gait, smoothly to a running gait, and cna handle large unexpected disturbances such as large steps up or down.   A significant portion of this work was then devoted to implementation and validation of the theoretical results. An important conclusion of this work is that many control methods for the ideal spring-mass model are, in realistic situations, extremely sensitive to noise and small errors or disturbances, and do not function on a real system.   As a final result of this work, we created control methods that respect and recognize the spring-mass concept, while also considering the realistic limitations of robots.  Our bipedal robot ATRIAS walked in 3D, with no external support or tether, and made a smooth speed transition to a running gait. Further, ATRIAS demonstrated robustness to large unexpected disturbances, from human kicks to walking or running over large unexpected disturbances.  To our knowledge, ATRIAS is the first machine to reproduce the ground reaction forces of human walking.    We hypothesized that the spring-mass model captures the physics of walking and running; and founded our hardware design and our control efforts on this hypothesis. After successfully achiving a walking gait, the ground reaction forces were measured and proved to match those of a human; thus, the ground reaction forces were not intentionally forced to match those of a human, but instead serve as strong evidence that ATRIAS captures the fundamental physics of human and animal gaits.           Last Modified: 01/22/2016       Submitted by: Jonathan W Hurst]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
