<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2011 South East Regional Meeting On Numbers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3976.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3976</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tluo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928448</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>South East Regional Meeting On Numbers (SERMON) is a two-day meeting on number theory, taken in a very broad sense.  It is held annually each spring semester at rotating institutions and offers participants the opportunity to explore new ideas and concepts. A primary goal is to encourage collaborative efforts among number theorists and combinatorialists in the southeast by providing a friendly, informal setting where they can come together.  Another objective of SERMON meetings is to involve number theorists at all career stages; SERMON speakers include graduate students, junior faculty, and senior faculty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 23rd annual South East Regional Meeting On Numbers will be held on April 16-17, 2011 at the Armstrong Atlantic State University.  This yearly conference will feature 20 minute talks by students and faculty as well as one hour talks by one or more noted mathematicians.  A regional conference such as this encourages the participation of both graduate students and junior faculty and allows them to increase their understanding and advance their knowledge in ways that would otherwise not be available to them. The conference will also allow students and staff from teaching-oriented universities to connect with their colleagues from research-oriented universities. Particularly for students, this will expose them to career paths beyond the undergraduate level.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1101214</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sungkon</FirstName>
<LastName>Chang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sungkon Chang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Sungkon.Chang@armstrong.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9123442889</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545691</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ARMSTRONG STATE UNIVERSITY</Name>
<CityName>Savannah</CityName>
<ZipCode>314191997</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9123442666</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11935 ABERCORN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075857953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARMSTRONG STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>180655748</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ARMSTRONG STATE UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>Savannah</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>314191997</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11935 ABERCORN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~3976</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-indent: 0px; margin: 0px;">South East Regional Meeting On Numbers is a two-day meeting on number theory held annually each spring semester at rotating institutions in the southeast.&nbsp; This year we had thirty three participants, two invited speakers, and eight contributed speakers. Thirty&nbsp; participants attended all the talks given in the conference, and the students expressed that overall they enjoyed the conference.</p> <p style="text-indent: 0px; margin: 0px;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-indent: 0px; margin: 0px;">We accomplished our primary goals which are to encourage collaborative efforts among participants in the southeast by providing a friendly, informal setting, and to involve number theorists at all career stages.&nbsp; A regional  conference such as this encourages the participation of both  graduate students and junior faculty.&nbsp; In this year's conference  the speakers consisted of three senior faculty members, three junior faculty  members, one post-doc, and three graduate students.&nbsp; After the conclusion of the first day of the conference a social gathering was organized, which was well-attended by the participants.</p> <p style="text-indent: 0px; margin: 0px;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-indent: 0px; margin: 0px;">This year we had three faculty speakers from teaching oriented universities, and the conference was held at a teaching oriented university.&nbsp; The conference allowed students and faculty from teaching oriented universities to connect with&nbsp; students and faculty from research oriented universities, and it exposed the undergraduate students to career paths beyond the undergraduate level.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2011<br>      Modified by: Sungkon&nbsp;Chang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[South East Regional Meeting On Numbers is a two-day meeting on number theory held annually each spring semester at rotating institutions in the southeast.  This year we had thirty three participants, two invited speakers, and eight contributed speakers. Thirty  participants attended all the talks given in the conference, and the students expressed that overall they enjoyed the conference.   We accomplished our primary goals which are to encourage collaborative efforts among participants in the southeast by providing a friendly, informal setting, and to involve number theorists at all career stages.  A regional  conference such as this encourages the participation of both  graduate students and junior faculty.  In this year's conference  the speakers consisted of three senior faculty members, three junior faculty  members, one post-doc, and three graduate students.  After the conclusion of the first day of the conference a social gathering was organized, which was well-attended by the participants.   This year we had three faculty speakers from teaching oriented universities, and the conference was held at a teaching oriented university.  The conference allowed students and faculty from teaching oriented universities to connect with  students and faculty from research oriented universities, and it exposed the undergraduate students to career paths beyond the undergraduate level.       Last Modified: 12/29/2011       Submitted by: Sungkon Chang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
