<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dyson's gas in 2D and conformal field theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>308400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>308400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigator plans to work on the mathematical theory of Dyson's gas, in particular on problems related to conformal field theory. The main topics of the proposed research will be the following. (a) Dyson's gas in two dimensions: classical and quantum Laplacian growth, random normal matrices and general one-component plasma ensembles, bifurcations of the plasma droplets and the universality laws corresponding to different types of singularities, the Polyakov-Alvarez type formulas and the asymptotics of the partition function. (b) Conformal field theory: Dyson's gas approximation of conformal fields; conformal field theory of stochastic Loewner evolutions; SLE curves in Dyson's ensembles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dyson's gas is a classical model that relates to a great variety of interesting physical phenomena such as Hele-Shaw flows in hydrodynamics and fractional Hall effect in quantum mechanics. In mathematics, Dyson's gas is an important part of random matrix theory. The model has been intensively studied on the physical level but many fundamental problems remain open on the mathematical side. The investigator will focus on several such problems trying to bring together ideas from various areas of mathematics (complex analysis, probability theory, statistical mechanics) and theoretical physics (conformal field theory, non-equilibrium growth phenomena, disordered systems). The educational component of the proposal consists in the development of new graduate courses and in the organization of two long term research programs. The project will provide research and training opportunities for several graduate students and postdocs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1101735</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikolai</FirstName>
<LastName>Makarov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikolai Makarov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>makarov@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263954359</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~102810</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~102795</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~102795</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nikolai Makarov completed his project in the theory of 2D Dyson&rsquo;s gas ensembles supported by the NSF grant DMS-1101735. During the funding period, the research was focused on several fundamental open questions concerning the classical and quantum aspects of the theory, as well as on the relations to the Coulomb gas formalism in conformal field theory.</p> <p>The PI accomplished the main goals of the project and achieved a significant progress in the following problems of analysis and mathematical physics related to Dyson&rsquo;s gas theory:</p> <p>(i)&nbsp; computation of the (quasi) classical limit of Dyson&rsquo;s ensembles, derivation of the (Hele-Shaw &nbsp;type) equations for the evolution of equilibrium measure;</p> <p>(ii)&nbsp; characterization of local equilibrium droplets, &nbsp;applications to&nbsp; the inverse problem of potential theory;</p> <p>(iii) complete description of the topology of algebraic droplets and quadrature domains, applications to gravitational lensing;</p> <p>(iv) Gaussian field convergence of fluctuations in the random normal matrix model;</p> <p>(v)&nbsp; rescaling of Ward&rsquo;s identities in Dyson&rsquo;s ensembles and the universality laws for the distribution of eigenvalues near the boundary points of the droplet;</p> <p>(vi) mathematical justification of the Coulomb gas formalism in conformal field theory.</p> <p>The results and methods of the project have had an impact on several areas of mathematics: potential theory (the discovery of Hele-Shaw flows in equilibrium dynamics, the theory of local equilibrium droplets, the relation between quadrature domains and local droplets), &nbsp;complex analysis (the existence of certain type of extremal univalent functions,&nbsp; the new construction of harmonic &nbsp;polynomials with the maximal number of roots and their rational analogues), and random matrices (several key results concerning normal matrix model, the development of the new technique&nbsp; - &nbsp;the rescaled Ward&rsquo;s identities).&nbsp; As an important by-product, a new type of conformal dynamical systems associated with quadrature domains and the corresponding Schwarz reflections was discovered. Also, some results and ideas of the project may be of interest to theoretical physicists working in conformal field theory, quantum Hall effect, non-equilibrium growth phenomena, and disordered systems.</p> <p>The project provided research and training opportunities for several graduate students and postdocs. Makarov developed and taught three new graduate courses at Caltech: &ldquo;Coulomb gas in 2D&rdquo;, &ldquo;Mathematical introduction to conformal field theory&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Quadrature domains&rdquo;. Three of his graduate students successfully defended their PhD theses.&nbsp; In addition, the PI helped organize two long term programs and a conference on topics closely related to this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Nikolai&nbsp;Makarov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nikolai Makarov completed his project in the theory of 2D DysonÆs gas ensembles supported by the NSF grant DMS-1101735. During the funding period, the research was focused on several fundamental open questions concerning the classical and quantum aspects of the theory, as well as on the relations to the Coulomb gas formalism in conformal field theory.  The PI accomplished the main goals of the project and achieved a significant progress in the following problems of analysis and mathematical physics related to DysonÆs gas theory:  (i)  computation of the (quasi) classical limit of DysonÆs ensembles, derivation of the (Hele-Shaw  type) equations for the evolution of equilibrium measure;  (ii)  characterization of local equilibrium droplets,  applications to  the inverse problem of potential theory;  (iii) complete description of the topology of algebraic droplets and quadrature domains, applications to gravitational lensing;  (iv) Gaussian field convergence of fluctuations in the random normal matrix model;  (v)  rescaling of WardÆs identities in DysonÆs ensembles and the universality laws for the distribution of eigenvalues near the boundary points of the droplet;  (vi) mathematical justification of the Coulomb gas formalism in conformal field theory.  The results and methods of the project have had an impact on several areas of mathematics: potential theory (the discovery of Hele-Shaw flows in equilibrium dynamics, the theory of local equilibrium droplets, the relation between quadrature domains and local droplets),  complex analysis (the existence of certain type of extremal univalent functions,  the new construction of harmonic  polynomials with the maximal number of roots and their rational analogues), and random matrices (several key results concerning normal matrix model, the development of the new technique  -  the rescaled WardÆs identities).  As an important by-product, a new type of conformal dynamical systems associated with quadrature domains and the corresponding Schwarz reflections was discovered. Also, some results and ideas of the project may be of interest to theoretical physicists working in conformal field theory, quantum Hall effect, non-equilibrium growth phenomena, and disordered systems.  The project provided research and training opportunities for several graduate students and postdocs. Makarov developed and taught three new graduate courses at Caltech: "Coulomb gas in 2D", "Mathematical introduction to conformal field theory", and "Quadrature domains". Three of his graduate students successfully defended their PhD theses.  In addition, the PI helped organize two long term programs and a conference on topics closely related to this project.          Last Modified: 06/07/2016       Submitted by: Nikolai Makarov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
