<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interactions Among Climate, Land Use, Ecosystem Services and Society</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21916262</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy VanReken</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tvanreke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927378</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Research Infrastructure Improvement (RII) Award focuses on the terrestrial and&lt;br/&gt;aquatic ecosystem services in New Hampshire and their interactions with short and long&lt;br/&gt;term changes in climate and land use. The project will investigate the&lt;br/&gt;interdependence of ecosystems, climate change, and impacts on society. The work is&lt;br/&gt;scientifically significant and regionally relevant as ecosystem services are central to the&lt;br/&gt;well-being of New Hampshire residents and to the region's economy. The project&lt;br/&gt;brings together research universities, 2- and 4-year colleges, small businesses, local&lt;br/&gt;government, and non-profit organizations to address key issues related to ecosystems&lt;br/&gt;research, education, and workforce development in the state.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;This RII project will examine how climate variability and climate change affect and are&lt;br/&gt;affected by changes in land use, supply and demand balances of water resources, and&lt;br/&gt;dynamics of nutrients in New Hampshire's streams and rivers. The research program&lt;br/&gt;will build a statewide system of terrestrial and aquatic sensors as well as use aircraft&lt;br/&gt;remote sensing and satellite imagery. This infrastructure will provide information on&lt;br/&gt;forest structure, soil emission, water temperature, and nutrient levels with high spatial&lt;br/&gt;and temporal resolution than is currently possible. The new data will be used in&lt;br/&gt;climate, hydrological, and ecosystem models. The integration of observational and&lt;br/&gt;modeling work on forest and water ecosystems will lead the way to examine future&lt;br/&gt;scenarios of climate change and the potential impacts on ecosystem function. The&lt;br/&gt;project will survey public perceptions of climate change and land use and broadly&lt;br/&gt;disseminate the analyzed results to improve communication among the public, policy&lt;br/&gt;makers, and an interdisciplinary team of scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The project has a suite of activities that are well-integrated with research to promote&lt;br/&gt;education at all levels. The implementation of the research project will contribute to an&lt;br/&gt;improved understanding of the historical effects of climate, land use, and demographic&lt;br/&gt;changes. In addition, improved communication among researchers, policy makers, and&lt;br/&gt;the public is expected to enable informed decision-making by all stakeholders.&lt;br/&gt;Workforce development initiatives under this project include incentives to transfer from&lt;br/&gt;2-year to 4-year schools, and summer institutes for K-12 teachers, 2-year college&lt;br/&gt;faculty, and 4-H volunteers to be trained in the use of terrestrial and aquatic sensors,&lt;br/&gt;data collection methods and participation in research. The project includes distance&lt;br/&gt;learning programs and plans for web-based dissemination of research results.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1101245</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>McDowell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William H McDowell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bill.mcdowell@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038622249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/26/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
<LastName>Wake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cameron Wake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cameron.wake@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038622329</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Gardner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin H Gardner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kevin.gardner@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038624334</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000112652</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Howarth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard B Howarth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Richard.Howarth@Dartmouth.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6036462752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086152</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wilfred</FirstName>
<LastName>Wollheim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wilfred M Wollheim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wil.wollheim@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038620812</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000174481</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jane</FirstName>
<LastName>Nisbet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jane A Nisbet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jan.nisbet@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038620533</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000570770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>111089470</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY SYSTEM OF NEW HAMPSHIRE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001765866</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Hampshire]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7217</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Research Infrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5894856</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~2105144</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~1916262</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The New Hampshire NSF EPSCoR RII Track-1 award (#1101245), Interactions Among Climate, Land Use, Ecosystem Services, and Society, integrated ecosystem measurements, process-based models and social science to better understand how climate and land cover change affect key terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems across multiple scales. The project&rsquo;s goals were: 1) To understand how climate variability, climate change and human land use affect the ability of NH landscapes to provide essential aquatic and terrestrial ecosystem services across multiple scales, 2) To build capacity for competitive research in interdisciplinary ecosystem-related natural and social sciences, 3) To strengthen and diversify the STEM workforce pipeline in NH, and 4) To strengthen management and policy decision capacity in NH regarding ecosystems and their services to, and interactions with, society.</p> <p>Led by the University of New Hampshire, the Ecosystems &amp; Society project engaged researchers and educators from institutions of higher education, formal and informal science education providers, and citizen science networks. Academic partners included Dartmouth College, Plymouth State University, Keene State College, St. Anselm College, Great Bay Community College, and White Mountains Community College.</p> <p>A new climate dataset was created for New England, dynamically downscaling Earth-system model projections using the Weather Research and Forecasting Model. The resulting high-resolution dataset contains hourly output for the highest resolution domain and is the first climate projections for the region with such high frequency output for a long (55-year) time period. The dataset provides critical inputs for regional impact studies of climate change in such areas as climate extremes, water resources, economic impacts, and other decision-making elements crucial for sound regional planning. &nbsp;</p> <p>An aquatic sensor network was installed at stream headwater sites, large river sites and at a spatially extensive statewide aquatic network, integrated with a soil sensor system to provide coupled measurements of vegetation, soil conditions, snow cover and headwater stream response. Terrestrial and aquatic ecosystem process models were linked to simulate hydrologic and water quality characteristics related to ecosystem services at regional scales. For the first time, a sensor network was used to estimate whole river network nitrate removal, indicating the potential of sensor networks to improve understanding of water quality controls.&nbsp;</p> <p>Coupling a terrestrial and aquatic ecosystem model to understand the coupled effects of atmospheric change and land use change as they propagate through terrestrial and into aquatic ecosystems revealed how water quality may potentially change in the future under different scenarios.&nbsp; Climate scenarios, land use scenarios, and model biogeophysical results were translated into a suite of environmental indicators that represent conditions of the climate, land, and water domains relevant to important ecosystem services and designed to be readily understood by the general public.</p> <p>Human perceptions and response to ecosystems were measured to understand how decision makers and other residents perceive and value a range of ecosystem services. Researchers developed an integrated ecological-economic model on the tradeoffs between timber harvests, carbon uptake and storage, and surface albedo in the evaluation of forest management strategies. A novel use of deliberative multicriteria decision analysis assessed public attitudes and preferences concerning the ecosystem services generated by the upper Merrimack River watershed.</p> <p>The NH EPSCoR Data Discovery Center (<a href="http://ddc.unh.edu">ddc.unh.edu</a>), established by this project, is a comprehensive data management system, delivering a suite of data ingestion, hosting, query, visualization, and analysis tools directly to the project research teams. In addition, the DDC extends the visibility and utility of the project data sets to stakeholders throughout the state and region.</p> <p>This project produced 165 publications in peer-reviewed journals. It provided support to 299 individuals, including 52 faculty, 13 post-docs, 17 Ph.D students, 29 M.S. students, 108 undergraduate students, 56 technical staff and 24 other staff. New faculty were installed at two community colleges and two four-year colleges, and faculty from several other colleges were engaged in research and education projects supported by seed funds from this award.</p> <p>The Ecosystems &amp; Society project sponsored 17 initiatives to provide research or research training experiences such as citizen science networks, specialized data and GIS training for teachers, support and mentoring of community college students transferring to UNH, and sponsorship of outreach programs for middle school and high school students. This project provided educational outreach programs, including research experiences for undergraduates and teachers, to 24,202 people. Over 19,000 students were reached through teacher training programs, including 2,537 students underrepresented in STEM.</p> <p>Research snapshots from the Ecosystem &amp; Society project can be viewed here: <a href="https://www.nhepscor.org/news/11">https://www.nhepscor.org/news/11</a>.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/12/2019<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Gardner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405302659_IntegratedAquaticandSoilSensorSystem--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405302659_IntegratedAquaticandSoilSensorSystem--rgov-800width.jpg" title="1.Integrated aquatic and soil sensor system"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405302659_IntegratedAquaticandSoilSensorSystem--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="1.Integrated aquatic and soil sensor system"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">a.The integrated sensor network developed and deployed through NH EPSCoR?s Ecosystem & Society project links aquatic response in headwater streams to conditions in the watersheds they drain.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Illustration by Janice Farmer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Gardner</div> <div class="imageTitle">1.Integrated aquatic and soil sensor system</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405364505_Sensorsmeasuringwatersheddynamics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405364505_Sensorsmeasuringwatersheddynamics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2.Sensors measuring watershed dynamics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405364505_Sensorsmeasuringwatersheddynamics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2.Sensors measuring watershed dynamics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">a.Wil Wollheim and Richard Carey secure an aquatic sensor suite in the Lamprey River in Durham, NH. Using miniaturized, high-tech sensor suites, measurements are made continuously allowing researchers to understand watershed dynamics, including patterns that emerge over time and space.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Photo by Dick Lord</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Gardner</div> <div class="imageTitle">2.Sensors measuring watershed dynamics</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405430052_TeacherVolunteer--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405430052_TeacherVolunteer--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Teacher volunteer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1101245/1101245_10134978_1552405430052_TeacherVolunteer--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Teacher volunteer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">a.Teachers participated in a volunteer water quality network, maintaining sensors and downloading data, in the NH EPSCoR Ecosystem & Society project. Middle school teacher Rebecca Steeves, right, and Plymouth State University student Ashley Hyde check a sensor in the Pemigewassett River.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Photo by Mark Green</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Gardner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Teacher volunteer</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The New Hampshire NSF EPSCoR RII Track-1 award (#1101245), Interactions Among Climate, Land Use, Ecosystem Services, and Society, integrated ecosystem measurements, process-based models and social science to better understand how climate and land cover change affect key terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems across multiple scales. The project?s goals were: 1) To understand how climate variability, climate change and human land use affect the ability of NH landscapes to provide essential aquatic and terrestrial ecosystem services across multiple scales, 2) To build capacity for competitive research in interdisciplinary ecosystem-related natural and social sciences, 3) To strengthen and diversify the STEM workforce pipeline in NH, and 4) To strengthen management and policy decision capacity in NH regarding ecosystems and their services to, and interactions with, society.  Led by the University of New Hampshire, the Ecosystems &amp; Society project engaged researchers and educators from institutions of higher education, formal and informal science education providers, and citizen science networks. Academic partners included Dartmouth College, Plymouth State University, Keene State College, St. Anselm College, Great Bay Community College, and White Mountains Community College.  A new climate dataset was created for New England, dynamically downscaling Earth-system model projections using the Weather Research and Forecasting Model. The resulting high-resolution dataset contains hourly output for the highest resolution domain and is the first climate projections for the region with such high frequency output for a long (55-year) time period. The dataset provides critical inputs for regional impact studies of climate change in such areas as climate extremes, water resources, economic impacts, and other decision-making elements crucial for sound regional planning.    An aquatic sensor network was installed at stream headwater sites, large river sites and at a spatially extensive statewide aquatic network, integrated with a soil sensor system to provide coupled measurements of vegetation, soil conditions, snow cover and headwater stream response. Terrestrial and aquatic ecosystem process models were linked to simulate hydrologic and water quality characteristics related to ecosystem services at regional scales. For the first time, a sensor network was used to estimate whole river network nitrate removal, indicating the potential of sensor networks to improve understanding of water quality controls.   Coupling a terrestrial and aquatic ecosystem model to understand the coupled effects of atmospheric change and land use change as they propagate through terrestrial and into aquatic ecosystems revealed how water quality may potentially change in the future under different scenarios.  Climate scenarios, land use scenarios, and model biogeophysical results were translated into a suite of environmental indicators that represent conditions of the climate, land, and water domains relevant to important ecosystem services and designed to be readily understood by the general public.  Human perceptions and response to ecosystems were measured to understand how decision makers and other residents perceive and value a range of ecosystem services. Researchers developed an integrated ecological-economic model on the tradeoffs between timber harvests, carbon uptake and storage, and surface albedo in the evaluation of forest management strategies. A novel use of deliberative multicriteria decision analysis assessed public attitudes and preferences concerning the ecosystem services generated by the upper Merrimack River watershed.  The NH EPSCoR Data Discovery Center (ddc.unh.edu), established by this project, is a comprehensive data management system, delivering a suite of data ingestion, hosting, query, visualization, and analysis tools directly to the project research teams. In addition, the DDC extends the visibility and utility of the project data sets to stakeholders throughout the state and region.  This project produced 165 publications in peer-reviewed journals. It provided support to 299 individuals, including 52 faculty, 13 post-docs, 17 Ph.D students, 29 M.S. students, 108 undergraduate students, 56 technical staff and 24 other staff. New faculty were installed at two community colleges and two four-year colleges, and faculty from several other colleges were engaged in research and education projects supported by seed funds from this award.  The Ecosystems &amp; Society project sponsored 17 initiatives to provide research or research training experiences such as citizen science networks, specialized data and GIS training for teachers, support and mentoring of community college students transferring to UNH, and sponsorship of outreach programs for middle school and high school students. This project provided educational outreach programs, including research experiences for undergraduates and teachers, to 24,202 people. Over 19,000 students were reached through teacher training programs, including 2,537 students underrepresented in STEM.  Research snapshots from the Ecosystem &amp; Society project can be viewed here: https://www.nhepscor.org/news/11.       Last Modified: 03/12/2019       Submitted by: Kevin H Gardner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
