<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>LSAMP Educational Research Project: Retention of URM Engineering Students through Practice-Oriented Experiential Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>tasha inniss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Northeastern University, partner institution in the Northeast Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (NE-LSAMP) will conduct an engineering educational research study that investigates the hypothesis that participation in experiential education programs, such as formal cooperative education (co-op), internships and research experiences for undergraduates (REUs), supplemented by mentorships, leads to enhanced self-efficacy, augmented learning, and an increased likelihood of retention, particularly among minority students who are historically under-represented in engineering. Each of the five universities in the alliance will participate in the study.  The institutions are:  Northeastern University, University of Massachusetts-Amherst, University of Connecticut, University of Rhode Island and Worcester Polytechnic Institute.  These alliance institutions have formally established research experiences for undergraduates, with only one of the universities having a formal cooperative education program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the reasons for the persisting low percentage of engineering professionals among minorities is their attrition in undergraduate engineering majors. A promising approach to retaining undergraduate minority students is the provision of programs that allow students to gain work experience (referred to as Practice-Oriented Experiential Education or POEE). Such approaches are becoming increasingly relevant in a work culture characterized by the need to continuously reflect and learn from on-going experience. This study will investigate whether POEE is a critical predictor of historically underrepresented students' STEM learning and retention through its impact on self-efficacy.  It will also examine whether an enriched form of POEE (peer mentoring) significantly increases the effect of experiential education on self-efficacy, learning, and retention.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed study will have broader implications for undergraduate engineering programs to have formal support systems in place, as in the case of the NSF LSAMPs. In addition to the contributions to research in the fields of psychology, social cognitive career theory, and experiential education, this project has a number of broader impacts that have national implications.  These national implications are as follows: (1) The research results will provide engineering colleges with data-supported measures of the effectiveness of POEE programs on historically underrepresented minority students. By empirically tracking the effectiveness of these contextual supports, the study will make it possible for engineering colleges to emphasize programs that work. (2) The study will assess the value of formal POEE programs and identify features which can be replicated at other universities, using the methods created through this study. (3) The use of cleaned retention data will create a means for comparison across the five partnering schools, and since one of them represents a significant percentage of engineering cooperative education, the new retention data has the potential to contribute to defining a new parameter. (4) The prominence of the role of self-efficacy in this study will help to determine if it merits inclusion as one of the most critical explanations of academic outcomes, in this case, the outcomes of learning and retention among underrepresented minority engineering undergraduates. (6) This project will seek to build on the newly validated measure of work self-efficacy introduced by Joe Raelin, the Asa Knowles Chair of Practice-Oriented Education in the "Pathways to Self Efficacy and Retention of Women In Undergraduate Engineering" research study currently underway, which could impact future national studies involving learning outcomes from work experience. (7) The model has the potential to become a standard that can be replicated with other populations (such as students with disabilities), with other educational levels (such as graduate studies), or among multiple areas of education beyond engineering (such as the physical sciences).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1102485</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohamad</FirstName>
<LastName>Metghalchi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohamad Metghalchi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>m.metghalchi@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173732973</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000364680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
<LastName>Duggan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claire J Duggan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>c.duggan@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173732036</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Harris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Harris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ri.harris@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173735904</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000573054</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 HUNTINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~98672</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~101327</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Northeastern University , a NE-LSAMP partnered in an engineering educational research study that investigated the hypothesis <em>participation in experiential education programs, such as formal cooperative education (co-op), internships and research experiences for undergraduates (REUs), supplemented by mentorships, leads to enhanced self-efficacy, augmented learning, and an increased likelihood of retention, particularly among minority students who are historically under-represented in engineering.</em></p> <p>All institutional partners established research experiences for undergraduates, with one, Northeastern University having a formal cooperative education program. Institutional partners included the University of Massachusetts Amherst, University of Connecticut, University of Rhode Island and Worcester Polytechnic Institute.</p> <p>Research Questions: The goal of this study was to use survey research methods to isolate those factors that contribute most to the development of; Positive self-efficacy beliefs, learning, and retention of under-represented minority students in undergraduate engineering programs.</p> <p>Accordingly, the study sought to address the following research questions during the course of the two-year project:</p> <p>1.&nbsp;<strong>What is the impact of self-efficacy on academic performance (current GPA) in racial/ethnic groups participating in the study.</strong></p> <p>Findings:adjusting for academic, and work related self-efficacy, <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>students tended to have higher GPAs after an experiential <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>exposure to professional practice regardless of racial/ethnic <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>background.&nbsp; Further, this was not the case with Caucasian <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>students. &nbsp;</p> <p>2.&nbsp;<strong>Does social, academic and cultural support and students&rsquo; perceived socio-economic class have impact on engineering students&rsquo; sense of their own efficacy for studying and working in engineering?</strong></p> <p>Results of the regression suggested that good support from family and friends, as well as having a higher socio-economic family status will more likely coincide with higher levels of academic self-<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>confidence (self-efficacy) for pursuing an engineering major in <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>college.</p> <p>3.&nbsp;<strong>Are students&rsquo; self-efficacy and support impacted similarly by ethnic/racially diversity and experience in professional practice settings.?</strong></p> <p>The significant main effect for diversity seems to be attributable to <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>the Family/Social support score. &nbsp;The&nbsp;diversity group scored higher than the non-diversity group before and after the professional <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>experience. This might suggest that students from diversity backgrounds attribute more to support from family, friends and <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>peers than those from non-diversity backgrounds.</p> <p>Summary</p> <p>According to the 2010 report issued by the National Academies titled &lsquo;Expanding Underrepresented Minority Participation: America&rsquo;s Science and Technology Talent at the Crossroads&rsquo;, the U.S. must involve underrepresented minorities in science and engineering to maintain a globally competitive edge.&nbsp; This recent report essentially builds on an alarm that was sounded five years earlier in the 2005 publication: Rising Above the Gathering Storm by the National Academy of Sciences, National Academy of Engineering, and Institute of Medicine.&nbsp; This has considerable implications for the STEM professions, such as engineering, where minorities make up a disproportionately low percentage of the workforce.&nbsp; As a result of this talent development challenge, c...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Northeastern University , a NE-LSAMP partnered in an engineering educational research study that investigated the hypothesis participation in experiential education programs, such as formal cooperative education (co-op), internships and research experiences for undergraduates (REUs), supplemented by mentorships, leads to enhanced self-efficacy, augmented learning, and an increased likelihood of retention, particularly among minority students who are historically under-represented in engineering.  All institutional partners established research experiences for undergraduates, with one, Northeastern University having a formal cooperative education program. Institutional partners included the University of Massachusetts Amherst, University of Connecticut, University of Rhode Island and Worcester Polytechnic Institute.  Research Questions: The goal of this study was to use survey research methods to isolate those factors that contribute most to the development of; Positive self-efficacy beliefs, learning, and retention of under-represented minority students in undergraduate engineering programs.  Accordingly, the study sought to address the following research questions during the course of the two-year project:  1. What is the impact of self-efficacy on academic performance (current GPA) in racial/ethnic groups participating in the study.  Findings:adjusting for academic, and work related self-efficacy,  students tended to have higher GPAs after an experiential  exposure to professional practice regardless of racial/ethnic  background.  Further, this was not the case with Caucasian  students.    2. Does social, academic and cultural support and studentsÆ perceived socio-economic class have impact on engineering studentsÆ sense of their own efficacy for studying and working in engineering?  Results of the regression suggested that good support from family and friends, as well as having a higher socio-economic family status will more likely coincide with higher levels of academic self- confidence (self-efficacy) for pursuing an engineering major in  college.  3. Are studentsÆ self-efficacy and support impacted similarly by ethnic/racially diversity and experience in professional practice settings.?  The significant main effect for diversity seems to be attributable to  the Family/Social support score.  The diversity group scored higher than the non-diversity group before and after the professional  experience. This might suggest that students from diversity backgrounds attribute more to support from family, friends and  peers than those from non-diversity backgrounds.  Summary  According to the 2010 report issued by the National Academies titled æExpanding Underrepresented Minority Participation: AmericaÆs Science and Technology Talent at the CrossroadsÆ, the U.S. must involve underrepresented minorities in science and engineering to maintain a globally competitive edge.  This recent report essentially builds on an alarm that was sounded five years earlier in the 2005 publication: Rising Above the Gathering Storm by the National Academy of Sciences, National Academy of Engineering, and Institute of Medicine.  This has considerable implications for the STEM professions, such as engineering, where minorities make up a disproportionately low percentage of the workforce.  As a result of this talent development challenge, colleges and universities around the country are placing growing emphasis on programs that allow students to gain work and research experience and are beginning to define success by more than just academic learning.  These programs, referred to in this study as practice-oriented experiential education or POEE, are comprised of  co-op jobs, internships, apprenticeships, undergraduate research and other methods that integrate experience in the world with experience in the classroom.  These approaches are becoming increasingly relevant in a work culture characterized by the need to continuously reflect and learn from ongo...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
