<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NOYCE Principal Investigators Garnering Useful Information on Developing [Project] Effectiveness (NOYCE PI GUIDE)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250347.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250347</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan T Prival</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is identifying and developing the skill sets of Principal Investigators in the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship program to enhance their acquisition of core knowledge in areas relevant to their project's goals, key skills in the nuts and bolts of project management (e.g., managing people, managing funds, and managing operations) and  change leadership (e.g., building and sustaining support among key constituencies, anticipating and adjusting to changing operational conditions, and institutionalizing the project's activities within the core operations of host units).  These skill sets are especially critical for more complex projects. Mentorship is a well established academic strategy for building such sets within faculty. This project seeks to explore whether a many-to-many mentorship system can be effectively implemented using electronic means. The system to be implemented is called the NOYCE Principal Investigators Garnering Useful Instruction in Developing [Project] Effectiveness (NOYCE PI GUIDE). The fundamental assumption is that there are answers to key questions as well as guiding strategies that experienced PIs can share with novice PIs (and potential PIs) to significantly aid their ability to successfully achieve the goals of their projects.  The project is  establishing a web site that features: (a) very short filmed segments and accompanying transcripts introducing fictionalized scenarios derived from interviews conducted with experienced NOYCE PIs, (b) at least 10 short video segments of the experienced NOYCE PIs discussing these two topics, and (c) a moderated electronic community of practice to build peer mentoring networks among would-be, novice and experienced NOYCE PIs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1102114</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
<LastName>Fortenberry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norman L Fortenberry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>N.Fortenberry@asee.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023313500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/15/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Proctor</FirstName>
<LastName>Reid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Proctor P Reid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>preid@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342467</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000089232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Cady</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth T Cady</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ecady@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342064</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 FIFTH STREET NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~250347</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project led to a website that offers support for individuals who have newly-funded NSF Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce) grants or plan to submit proposals to the program. Although these individuals have knowledge and skills related to their research and teaching, they frequently lack experience and skills in both</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; project management, which includes managing people, managing funds, and managing operations, and</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; change management, which includes building and sustaining support among key groups, anticipating and adjusting to changing conditions, and making the project&rsquo;s activities a permanent part of the institution.</p> <p>These skills are especially critical for complex projects, and mentorship is a well-established academic strategy for building skills in less experienced individuals. Typically, mentorship involves one experienced person (the mentor) providing advice to one or more less experienced people (the mentees). However, with a large NSF program involving many new and potential Principal Investigators (PIs), we wanted to determine whether a many-to-many online mentorship system can be effectively implemented. The system is the Noyce Principal Investigators Garnering Useful Instruction in Developing [Project] Effectiveness (Noyce PI GUIDE; <a href="http://govpiguide.org/">http://govpiguide.org/</a>), which provides strategies and knowledge that experienced PIs can share with novice and would-be PIs to significantly aid their ability to successfully achieve the goals of their projects.</p> <p>We worked with Noyce staff to determine what knowledge, skills, and abilities new and prospective PIs need in order to enhance their project management and change leadership skills. Using that list, we interviewed 17 experienced PIs about challenges they had faced and information they wished they had known before starting their projects. We used their answers to produce hypothetical situations that PIs could experience. We then interviewed 9 of the experienced PIs and asked them to answer the following questions about the situations:</p> <ul> <li>In addressing this scenario, what      additional information do you wish you had? </li> <li>Given the scenario, what advice      do you have for the PI?</li> <li>How would you advise the PI to      avoid this situation in the future?</li> </ul> <p>Each answer was split into 1-2 minute segments and posted on the website. Users are able to search by hypothetical situation, by specific question across different scenarios, or by specific PI across all questions. Currently, in addition to the Noyce community, the site includes communities for three other NSF programs. Although new and prospective Noyce PIs would be expected to find the Noyce scenarios the most beneficial, all website users can view any of the videos and join any of the communities. Transcripts of the video segments provide for web site features that are compliant with the Americans with Disabilities act.</p> <p>The website also has the following features:</p> <ul> <li>Support of user-initiated      discussion groups on various topics related to project management and      change leadership.</li> <li>Posted videos accompanied by      transcripts and additional explanatory material.</li> <li>Comment sections on the posted      videos and other resources.</li> <li>Users can create their own groups      based on subjects of interest (e.g., subgroups devoted to [a] new PIs      interacting with experienced PIs, or [b] experienced PIs strategizing on      needed new directions in the overall program).</li> </ul> <p>The ultimate aim of the website is to provide demonstrable value to potential users through the provision of desired information and services. With that in mind, the website could support webinars and RSS feeds. The site users can also create their own resource library ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project led to a website that offers support for individuals who have newly-funded NSF Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce) grants or plan to submit proposals to the program. Although these individuals have knowledge and skills related to their research and teaching, they frequently lack experience and skills in both  1)     project management, which includes managing people, managing funds, and managing operations, and  2)     change management, which includes building and sustaining support among key groups, anticipating and adjusting to changing conditions, and making the projectÆs activities a permanent part of the institution.  These skills are especially critical for complex projects, and mentorship is a well-established academic strategy for building skills in less experienced individuals. Typically, mentorship involves one experienced person (the mentor) providing advice to one or more less experienced people (the mentees). However, with a large NSF program involving many new and potential Principal Investigators (PIs), we wanted to determine whether a many-to-many online mentorship system can be effectively implemented. The system is the Noyce Principal Investigators Garnering Useful Instruction in Developing [Project] Effectiveness (Noyce PI GUIDE; http://govpiguide.org/), which provides strategies and knowledge that experienced PIs can share with novice and would-be PIs to significantly aid their ability to successfully achieve the goals of their projects.  We worked with Noyce staff to determine what knowledge, skills, and abilities new and prospective PIs need in order to enhance their project management and change leadership skills. Using that list, we interviewed 17 experienced PIs about challenges they had faced and information they wished they had known before starting their projects. We used their answers to produce hypothetical situations that PIs could experience. We then interviewed 9 of the experienced PIs and asked them to answer the following questions about the situations:  In addressing this scenario, what      additional information do you wish you had?  Given the scenario, what advice      do you have for the PI? How would you advise the PI to      avoid this situation in the future?   Each answer was split into 1-2 minute segments and posted on the website. Users are able to search by hypothetical situation, by specific question across different scenarios, or by specific PI across all questions. Currently, in addition to the Noyce community, the site includes communities for three other NSF programs. Although new and prospective Noyce PIs would be expected to find the Noyce scenarios the most beneficial, all website users can view any of the videos and join any of the communities. Transcripts of the video segments provide for web site features that are compliant with the Americans with Disabilities act.  The website also has the following features:  Support of user-initiated      discussion groups on various topics related to project management and      change leadership. Posted videos accompanied by      transcripts and additional explanatory material. Comment sections on the posted      videos and other resources. Users can create their own groups      based on subjects of interest (e.g., subgroups devoted to [a] new PIs      interacting with experienced PIs, or [b] experienced PIs strategizing on      needed new directions in the overall program).   The ultimate aim of the website is to provide demonstrable value to potential users through the provision of desired information and services. With that in mind, the website could support webinars and RSS feeds. The site users can also create their own resource library (e.g., documents to share, external web sites, recommendations on consultants, etc.), personalize their home page, chat live with other users (both new and experienced PIs), and share links and bookmarks with other users. Although users are required to log-in, members...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
