<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>134225.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>134225</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julie Palais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Goldberg/1103375&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a postdoctoral fellowship to develop a modeling strategy to help address one of the largest sources of uncertainty regarding future sea-level rise (SLR) over the next several centuries that of the contribution of the West Antarctic ice sheet (WAIS).  Current ice sheet models are ill equipped to reduce this uncertainty because many of the determining factors of its flow are difficult or impossible to observe directly.  In addition the influence of the internal state of the ice is not properly assessed and there is a need to characterize the uncertainty associated with the current state of WAIS, and to improve current data assimilation techniques.  This post-doctoral researcher supported by this award will use a new large-scale thermo-mechanical ice model, capable of modeling WAIS and will incorporate an adjoint to the model using automatic differentiation techniques together with analytic methods. The adjoint will be used to answer questions regarding the relative influence of internal ice temperature and oceanic forcing on WAIS evolution, and to infer time-dependent basal behavior using satellite data (something not currently done).  The host scientist will be Dr. Patrick Heimbach of MIT, whose pioneering work in the generation and use of adjoints in climate modeling will be invaluable. The intellectual merit of the proposed work is the advent of adjoints to time-dependent ice models, which promises improvements in data assimilation and in our understanding of ice sheet dynamics.  The broader impact of the proposed work is quantification of the largest sources of uncertainty of future contributions of land ice to SLR, which could inform policy decisions and guide future fieldwork campaigns.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1103375</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel N Goldberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>9176697304</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000576566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Goldberg                Daniel         N</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085407032</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Goldberg                Daniel         N]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085407032</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5247</Code>
<Text>POST DOC/TRAVEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7754</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY &amp; CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>High Risk/Reward Innovative Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~134225</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The object of this award was to develop an improved methodology for incorporating satellite data into numerical ice sheet models, and apply this methodology to the West Antarctic Ice Sheet. The West Antarctic Ice Sheet is a massive region of ice in Antarctica, and is of importance because the majority rests on a bed that is below sea level, and glaciologists have long argued that this makes it unstable to rapid retreat. We have difficulty representing its dynanics with numerical ice codes, largely due to unknown quantities, such as bed topography and changing slipperiness at its bed, making it difficult to make statements about future behavior. Information about its surface is available from satellites, but often with incomplete temporal and spatial coverage. Methods exist for inferring quantities using "snapshots" of data, but for rapidly changing regions this is not enough. The methodology developed in this project draws on similar methods used in ocean modeling to better understand ocean circulation based on available measurements. Similarly to their approach, a framework has been developed to evaluate the sensitivities of model output to arbitrarily large input datasets, and this aids in the use of time-dependent satellite data to constrain unknown quantities. This work is very new, and while other sophisticated ice sheet models exist, they cannot as easily calculate these sensitivities. The code for the ice model, and its sensitivity framework, is publicly available. The work has been published in the open-access, peer-reviewed journal, The Cryosphere.</p> <p>The work is in its very early stages, but initial tests in idealized circumstances showed promise, and also yielded interesting results: for instance, that the areas under an ice shelf most sensitive to ocean melting are not those places where melting is generall largest; and that it is possible, albeit difficult, to recover information about both basal sliding parameters and basal topography with our model. More recently, the framework has been used to investigate the way that ice shelves have affected the flow within three dynamic West Antarctic glaciers over the last decade.&nbsp;</p> <p>An unrelated and unexpected outcome of the Fellowship was a theoretical investigation into the process of stick-slip on ice streams. Stick-slip is a perplexing phenomenon by which ice motion, thought to be unchanging over decades or centuries, is in certain regions of Antarctica changing its speed dramatically once or twice a day. On these short timescales the ice is thought to deform elastically, like a rubber band. Ice sheet change occurs through a different type of motion, which is more similar to honey or molasses spreading out on a plate (i.e. it does not return to its initial shape). In this study equations were derived which incorporate both types of motion, and applied to a hypothetical ice stream -- a surprising result being that whether stick-slip occurred or not, the time-averaged motion of the ice stream behaved like a purely viscous stream, i.e. one with no elastic component to its flow. The work will hopefully allow scientists to make sense of this perplexing behavior in the context of decadal and centennial ice sheet change. The results have been published in the peer-reviewed Journal of Geophysical Research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2014<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;N&nbsp;Goldberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The object of this award was to develop an improved methodology for incorporating satellite data into numerical ice sheet models, and apply this methodology to the West Antarctic Ice Sheet. The West Antarctic Ice Sheet is a massive region of ice in Antarctica, and is of importance because the majority rests on a bed that is below sea level, and glaciologists have long argued that this makes it unstable to rapid retreat. We have difficulty representing its dynanics with numerical ice codes, largely due to unknown quantities, such as bed topography and changing slipperiness at its bed, making it difficult to make statements about future behavior. Information about its surface is available from satellites, but often with incomplete temporal and spatial coverage. Methods exist for inferring quantities using "snapshots" of data, but for rapidly changing regions this is not enough. The methodology developed in this project draws on similar methods used in ocean modeling to better understand ocean circulation based on available measurements. Similarly to their approach, a framework has been developed to evaluate the sensitivities of model output to arbitrarily large input datasets, and this aids in the use of time-dependent satellite data to constrain unknown quantities. This work is very new, and while other sophisticated ice sheet models exist, they cannot as easily calculate these sensitivities. The code for the ice model, and its sensitivity framework, is publicly available. The work has been published in the open-access, peer-reviewed journal, The Cryosphere.  The work is in its very early stages, but initial tests in idealized circumstances showed promise, and also yielded interesting results: for instance, that the areas under an ice shelf most sensitive to ocean melting are not those places where melting is generall largest; and that it is possible, albeit difficult, to recover information about both basal sliding parameters and basal topography with our model. More recently, the framework has been used to investigate the way that ice shelves have affected the flow within three dynamic West Antarctic glaciers over the last decade.   An unrelated and unexpected outcome of the Fellowship was a theoretical investigation into the process of stick-slip on ice streams. Stick-slip is a perplexing phenomenon by which ice motion, thought to be unchanging over decades or centuries, is in certain regions of Antarctica changing its speed dramatically once or twice a day. On these short timescales the ice is thought to deform elastically, like a rubber band. Ice sheet change occurs through a different type of motion, which is more similar to honey or molasses spreading out on a plate (i.e. it does not return to its initial shape). In this study equations were derived which incorporate both types of motion, and applied to a hypothetical ice stream -- a surprising result being that whether stick-slip occurred or not, the time-averaged motion of the ice stream behaved like a purely viscous stream, i.e. one with no elastic component to its flow. The work will hopefully allow scientists to make sense of this perplexing behavior in the context of decadal and centennial ice sheet change. The results have been published in the peer-reviewed Journal of Geophysical Research.       Last Modified: 08/21/2014       Submitted by: Daniel N Goldberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
