<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Microlensing Theory and Planet Detection: Bridge to the Future</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>339477.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>339477</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will continue operation of the Microlensing Follow Up Network in order to search for and analyze new exoplanets using high-magnification microlensing techniques. The consortium makes use of numerous small-to-moderate size aperture wide-field telescopes to conduct the surveys, as well as larger instruments for quick target-of-opportunity follow-up observations. Data analysis will be used to measure relative planet frequency in the Galactic bulge and disk, constrain models of 3-body planetary systems, and determine orbital information of planets using new mathematical techniques and statistical analysis. As part of the survey they will also obtain and analyze high-resolution spectra of highly magnified dwarf stars in the Galactic bulge in order to measure or put limits on lithium abundances in unevolved stars. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will exploit the advantages that the microlensing technique has over other methods for detecting new planets, such as being more sensitive to planets with lower masses and higher semi-major axes. This will help produce a better understanding of the planetary system distributions in the Galaxy. The dwarf spectra are critical because lithium is a key element in constraining stellar evolution models. The group includes contributions from both professional and amateur astronomers at international locations. Scientific training of the amateur astronomers, and graduate students is also part of the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1103471</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Gould</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Gould</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gould@astronomy.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142921892</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000170192</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernard</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaudi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernard S Gaudi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gaudi@astronomy.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142921914</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000236016</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~104388</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~126823</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~108266</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The most important overall goal of this project was to use microlensing to discover and characterize extrasolar planets that are not accessible to other techniques.&nbsp; Over 6000 planets and strong planetary candidates have been discovered by the radial velocity and transit techniques, compared to fewer than 100 for microlensing.&nbsp; What makes microlensing special is that it can detect extremely faint, or even dark, systems.&nbsp; This is because it detects planets (and their hosts) not from their own light but by their gravitational effects on light coming from a more distant star.&nbsp; This makes microlensing sensitive to very low mass hosts, low mass planets, and very distant systems.<br /><br />We focus here on two of the most exciting discoveries.&nbsp; Both newly discovered systems consist of two low-mass stars with one component of this binary orbited by a roughly Earth-mass planet at roughly 1 AU (distance from Earth to Sun).&nbsp; Before describing more details about these systems, we emphasize that the fact that we found two implies that this type of system (although completely unknown before our work) is likely to be extremely common.&nbsp; It may seem strange that something can be ranked as "common" when there are only two known examples.&nbsp; However, literally one in a million stars gives rise to a microlensing event at all at any given time.&nbsp; Even if each star that generated such a microlensing event had an Earth-mass planet, only about one in 300 would show up in the microlensing event.&nbsp; And even if all had binary companions, only about 1 in 10 would show them.&nbsp; So altogether, about 1 in 3,000,000,000.&nbsp; Given these probabilities, and even accounting for the huge numbers of stars being monitored, two detections is a lot.<br /><br />One system, OGLE-2013-BLG-0341, has two "late-type M dwarfs", i.e., each just over 0.1 solar masses, so just barely able to burn hydrogen (and thus be called a "star").&nbsp; The planet is about 2 Earth-masses and is seen projected just under 1 AU from the less-massive star.&nbsp; The other system, OGLE-2013-BLG-0723, is in some ways even more interesting.&nbsp; The planet is 0.7 Earth-masses, i.e., a bit lighter than Venus.&nbsp; It is orbiting a 0.03 solar mass "star", i.e., actually a brown dwarf.&nbsp; Finally, both objects are orbiting a very low mass star, less than 0.1 solar masses, so just above the 0.075 solar-mass "hydrogen-burning limit".&nbsp; One of the most striking features of this system is that the mass ratio of the planet:host (6.6 x 10^(-5)) is very similar to that of Callisto:Jupiter (5.7 x 10^(-5)) and to Uranus:Sun (4.4 x 10^(-5), while the separations (scaled to host mass) are also very similar (11,13,19)AU/solar-mass.&nbsp; This leads us to conjecture that there is a single formation process that leads to a continuum of outcomes, ranging from planets orbiting stars (like Uranus and the Sun), down to moons orbiting planets (like Callisto and Jupiter), with our new "Venus"/Brown-Dwarf system being a sort of "missing link".<br /><br />Another very remarkable feature of this work is the role of amateur astronomers.&nbsp; Many of the key features of the lightcurve that enabled the discovery of OGLE-2013-BLG-0341 were made from amateur telescopes with apertures in the range 25cm to 40cm, four from New Zealand and one from Australia.&nbsp; The discovery of the binary companion was actually made by an amateur who was searching for holes in the clouds to observe this target.&nbsp; When he found one after a long break, he noticed that the target had gotten brighter by a factor 2 during the intervening hour, and immediately contacted our command center.&nbsp; We then mobilized a massive effort, including both amateurs and professionals, to fully characterize this system.<br /><br />Some of the work of this project concerned preparations for next-generation microlensing.&nbsp; While t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The most important overall goal of this project was to use microlensing to discover and characterize extrasolar planets that are not accessible to other techniques.  Over 6000 planets and strong planetary candidates have been discovered by the radial velocity and transit techniques, compared to fewer than 100 for microlensing.  What makes microlensing special is that it can detect extremely faint, or even dark, systems.  This is because it detects planets (and their hosts) not from their own light but by their gravitational effects on light coming from a more distant star.  This makes microlensing sensitive to very low mass hosts, low mass planets, and very distant systems.  We focus here on two of the most exciting discoveries.  Both newly discovered systems consist of two low-mass stars with one component of this binary orbited by a roughly Earth-mass planet at roughly 1 AU (distance from Earth to Sun).  Before describing more details about these systems, we emphasize that the fact that we found two implies that this type of system (although completely unknown before our work) is likely to be extremely common.  It may seem strange that something can be ranked as "common" when there are only two known examples.  However, literally one in a million stars gives rise to a microlensing event at all at any given time.  Even if each star that generated such a microlensing event had an Earth-mass planet, only about one in 300 would show up in the microlensing event.  And even if all had binary companions, only about 1 in 10 would show them.  So altogether, about 1 in 3,000,000,000.  Given these probabilities, and even accounting for the huge numbers of stars being monitored, two detections is a lot.  One system, OGLE-2013-BLG-0341, has two "late-type M dwarfs", i.e., each just over 0.1 solar masses, so just barely able to burn hydrogen (and thus be called a "star").  The planet is about 2 Earth-masses and is seen projected just under 1 AU from the less-massive star.  The other system, OGLE-2013-BLG-0723, is in some ways even more interesting.  The planet is 0.7 Earth-masses, i.e., a bit lighter than Venus.  It is orbiting a 0.03 solar mass "star", i.e., actually a brown dwarf.  Finally, both objects are orbiting a very low mass star, less than 0.1 solar masses, so just above the 0.075 solar-mass "hydrogen-burning limit".  One of the most striking features of this system is that the mass ratio of the planet:host (6.6 x 10^(-5)) is very similar to that of Callisto:Jupiter (5.7 x 10^(-5)) and to Uranus:Sun (4.4 x 10^(-5), while the separations (scaled to host mass) are also very similar (11,13,19)AU/solar-mass.  This leads us to conjecture that there is a single formation process that leads to a continuum of outcomes, ranging from planets orbiting stars (like Uranus and the Sun), down to moons orbiting planets (like Callisto and Jupiter), with our new "Venus"/Brown-Dwarf system being a sort of "missing link".  Another very remarkable feature of this work is the role of amateur astronomers.  Many of the key features of the lightcurve that enabled the discovery of OGLE-2013-BLG-0341 were made from amateur telescopes with apertures in the range 25cm to 40cm, four from New Zealand and one from Australia.  The discovery of the binary companion was actually made by an amateur who was searching for holes in the clouds to observe this target.  When he found one after a long break, he noticed that the target had gotten brighter by a factor 2 during the intervening hour, and immediately contacted our command center.  We then mobilized a massive effort, including both amateurs and professionals, to fully characterize this system.  Some of the work of this project concerned preparations for next-generation microlensing.  While the work itself was mainly technical in character, the prospects for new microlensing experiments and missions is very bright.  The new Korea Microlensing Telescope Network has just come on line with one 1.6m telescope on e...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
