<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Distribution of Prime Numbers and Related Topics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>134000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>134000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main goal of this project is to refine the recent method of Goldston, Pintz, and Yildirim in several specific problems. The long-term goal is to investigate some of the more difficult questions for which no progress has yet been made. The method of Goldston, Pintz and Yildirim detects primes or almost primes close together by examining these sequences when weighted by certain sieve functions which are large when there are primes in specified configurations.&lt;br/&gt;These sieve functions can be obtained by the Selberg sieve or by an optimization process. Some questions to be examined are to find the smallest prime gap size that can be obtained unconditionally by the method, to determine how the sieve weights behave depending on the number of prime factors a number has, and to examine certain sequences of primes for positive proportion results. The investigator will also continue his work on jumping champions with A. Ledoan, work on error terms in additive prime number theory, and examine applications of higher correlation of zeros of zeta functions to obtaining information on multiplicity and gaps between zeros.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is concerned with prime numbers, which have been studied by mathematicians for thousands of years, and in recent years have found important applications in computer science and cryptography.&lt;br/&gt;Despite the simplicity of how they arise, prime numbers offer some of the most challenging and difficult problems in mathematics, including the Riemann Hypothesis (which is equivalent to the primes having a very regular distribution) and the Goldbach and Twin Prime Conjectures.  The study of these questions has contributed to the development of not just number theory but analysis and algebra. More generally, number theory has applications throughout mathematics and fields that make use of mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1104434</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel A Goldston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>goldston@math.sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4089245125</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000443071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Jose</CityName>
<ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>056820715</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>056820715</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Jose State University]]></Name>
<CityName>san jose</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>951920139</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Washington Square]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~134000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main goal of this project was to refine and develop the GPY method for finding small gaps between primes. The GPY method was introduced in 2005 by Goldston, Pintz, and Yildirim and was successful in proving that there are primes much closer together than the average spacing between primes. The method however fell short of proving that primes will always occur a bounded distant apart. Further the method failed to prove that more than two primes are close together. Despite a number of results and refinements in the years that followed, neither of these goals seemed attainable.</p> <p>In 2013 both of these problems were solved in spectacular fashion. First Yitang Zhang was able to prove that there are infinitely often primes that are a bounded distance apart. This was later refined by a Polymath Project. Later in 2013 Maynard and Tao were able to improve the GPY method directly and obtain improved bounds on the distance between primes and also prove that there exist places where there are lots of primes a bounded distance apart. The PolymathB project found in particular that there are infinitely often primes that are at most 246 apart from each other.&nbsp;</p> <p>These new methods have now been used to solve of a number of old problems on primes, and generated renewed interest in this area. However there still remain limitations that at present block the solutions to famous problems such as the Goldbach Conjecture and the Twin Prime Conjecture.</p> <p>The main objectives of this project were solved by other mathematicians and not the Principal Investigator. Besides following the exciting developments, the PI worked on and solved some secondary problems proposed in the project. With two high school students (in 2014) &nbsp;some results on the best possible formula for the prime pair asymptotic formula were obtained. Earlier with Andrew Ledoan the PI determined the relationship between the most commonly occuring prime gaps and the well-known &nbsp;Hardy-Littlewood conjectures. In 2014 and 2015 the PI worked with a different high school student and separately with an undergraduate student on problems related to the Goldbach conjecture.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goldston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goal of this project was to refine and develop the GPY method for finding small gaps between primes. The GPY method was introduced in 2005 by Goldston, Pintz, and Yildirim and was successful in proving that there are primes much closer together than the average spacing between primes. The method however fell short of proving that primes will always occur a bounded distant apart. Further the method failed to prove that more than two primes are close together. Despite a number of results and refinements in the years that followed, neither of these goals seemed attainable.  In 2013 both of these problems were solved in spectacular fashion. First Yitang Zhang was able to prove that there are infinitely often primes that are a bounded distance apart. This was later refined by a Polymath Project. Later in 2013 Maynard and Tao were able to improve the GPY method directly and obtain improved bounds on the distance between primes and also prove that there exist places where there are lots of primes a bounded distance apart. The PolymathB project found in particular that there are infinitely often primes that are at most 246 apart from each other.   These new methods have now been used to solve of a number of old problems on primes, and generated renewed interest in this area. However there still remain limitations that at present block the solutions to famous problems such as the Goldbach Conjecture and the Twin Prime Conjecture.  The main objectives of this project were solved by other mathematicians and not the Principal Investigator. Besides following the exciting developments, the PI worked on and solved some secondary problems proposed in the project. With two high school students (in 2014)  some results on the best possible formula for the prime pair asymptotic formula were obtained. Earlier with Andrew Ledoan the PI determined the relationship between the most commonly occuring prime gaps and the well-known  Hardy-Littlewood conjectures. In 2014 and 2015 the PI worked with a different high school student and separately with an undergraduate student on problems related to the Goldbach conjecture.              Last Modified: 11/29/2015       Submitted by: Daniel A Goldston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
