<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>First Principles Investigations of Boron Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research that is focused on applying first principles theory and calculations to study, understand, and predict the properties of boron nanostructures. In recent years, boron nanomaterials have been the subject of increasing scientific interest and investigation due to their novel and unusual structural, mechanical, and electronic properties.  These properties differ from those of better-known nanomaterials based on carbon such as graphene, nanoribbons, nanotubes or buckyballs, and may prove robust and useful in device applications.   Elucidating the underlying reasons for the unusual behavior of boron nanosystems furthers understanding of the atomic geometries, unusual bonding schemes, and electronic behaviors that emerge in reduced dimensional systems.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will investigate a range of problems related to the following main topics: (i) the tendency (or lack thereof) of boron atoms deposited on transition metal surfaces to form sheet-like structures; (ii) the stable structures and compositions of boron sheets when metal atoms are incorporated onto them to form metal-borides; (iii) the ramifications of curvature on metal-boride nanotubes in terms of structure and properties to help design materials that naturally form small nanostructures; and (iv) the potential of metal-boride nanosystems for hydrogen storage. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component of this award concentrates on efforts that will disseminate knowledge and interest in computational condensed matter theory and materials physics through mentorship of graduate and undergraduate students. Undergraduate students will continue to be trained and will perform research on nanostructures while learning solid-state and computational physics. The PI will also continue and expand his outreach activities in minority-dominated New Haven local public schools by developing teaching modules in collaboration with high school science teachers. The modules, teaching curricula, and associated kits help in teaching materials science, physics, chemistry, and engineering at a high school level by using electronic devices and media as the delivery vehicles.  These modules will be showcased via workshops organized for high school teachers to help incorporate this material in the classroom and thereby captivate the interest of students who may consider degrees and careers in science or engineering.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research that is focused on studying, understanding, and predicting the properties of very small structures made up of boron atoms that are some one-millionth the size of the human hair. In recent years, such materials have been the subject of increasing scientific interest and investigation due to their novel and unusual structural, mechanical, and electronic properties.  These properties differ from those of better-known materials based on carbon, and may prove robust and useful in various device applications.   Elucidating the underlying reasons for the unusual behavior of boron materials furthers understanding of the atomic geometries, unusual bonding schemes, and electronic behaviors that emerge in systems that are confined along various spatial dimensions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using theoretical and parameter-free computational tools, the PI will investigate a range of problems such as whether boron atoms deposited on transition metal surfaces will form sheet-like structures; the stable structures and compositions of boron sheets when metal atoms are incorporated onto them; and the potential use of metal-boride materials for hydrogen storage. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component of this award concentrates on efforts that will disseminate knowledge and interest in computational condensed matter theory and materials physics through mentorship of graduate and undergraduate students. Undergraduate students will continue to be trained and will perform research on nanostructures while learning solid-state and computational physics. The PI will also continue and expand his outreach activities in minority-dominated New Haven local public schools by developing teaching modules in collaboration with high school science teachers. The modules, teaching curricula, and associated kits help in teaching materials science, physics, chemistry, and engineering at a high school level by using electronic devices and media as the delivery vehicles.  These modules will be showcased via workshops organized for high school teachers to help incorporate this material in the classroom and thereby captivate the interest of students who may consider degrees and careers in science or engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1104974</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sohrab</FirstName>
<LastName>Ismail-Beigi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sohrab Ismail-Beigi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sohrab.ismail-beigi@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034322107</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000203721</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Projects]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has focused on two separate intellectual merit questions related to the physical properties of solid state materials. &nbsp;First, research was undertaken to understand the properties of materials with nanometer scale dimensions made of pure boron as well as boron with added metallic elements, specifically magnesium. &nbsp;The nanoscale types of materials examined included nanotubes as well as flat sheet materials with thicknesses on the scale of atoms: both classes of materials are exemplified by the more well known cases of carbon nanotubes and graphene. &nbsp;Boron based nanomaterials have been the subject of increased interest and investigation due to their novel structural, mechanical, and electronic properties: for example, magnesium boride is a superconducting material with a relatively high transition temperature of 40 Kelvin. &nbsp;Furthermore, boron nanomaterials enlarge the library of nanoscale materials that are accessible and modifiable for potential technological applications. &nbsp;Boron nanomaterials generally show complex bonding patterns and intricate geometric arrangements of their atoms. &nbsp;The project was able to probe and understand key aspects of the properties of nanoscale boron-based materials including: (i) identification of specific metal surfaces on which boron atoms prefer to arrange into atomically thin sheet-like structures, (ii) how the addition of magnesium atoms to boron sheets changes their energetics and structure, (iii) how addition of magnesium to boron sheets leads to a transfer of electrons to the boron component, (iv) how the transfer of electrons in boron nanotubes with attached magnesium can strongly modify the stable diameters of nanotubes that can be created, and (v) more generally, how electron transfer between two nanoscale materials can modify the properties of the joint system in unexpected ways.</p> <p>Second, a novel approach was developed to understand how light interacts with sound waves in solid state materials. &nbsp;When a sound wave propagates in a material, it alternatively compresses and expands the material (since sound is a wave of pressure) which in turn changes the index of refraction of the material. &nbsp;This connection, the photoelastic effect, means light incident on a material can be used to control sound waves propagating inside it and vice versa. &nbsp;Such physical effects can form the basis of new types of optical devices for information processing using light waves. &nbsp;However, from a basic science viewpoint, while one can measure the photoelastic effect experimentally and one can compute its numerical value (the photoelastic coefficient) using modern computational methods, there is a lack of basic physical understanding of what controls the size of this effect in any given material. &nbsp;For example, there is no real predictive method based on a simple physical model that can provide the sign of the photoelastic coefficient much less its precise magnitude (i.e., whether the index of refraction increases upon compression or decreases). &nbsp;The lack of a basic model means that trying to design new materials with improved photoelastic properties is at present based on trial and error. &nbsp;Our work in this project has setup a physical framework for computing the photoelastic effect that directly ties it to how electrons form bonds between the atoms in a material and how those bonds and bonding electrons are distorted upon the arrival of the elastic waves. &nbsp;The approach is from first principles without fudge parameters or simplifying assumptions on the types of bonds or electronic bonding orbitals. &nbsp;To date, the method has been developed from scratch, implemented numerically in software, and thoroughly tested against prior theory and available experiments for semiconductors. &nbsp;The next step is to consider a wider set of materials including metal oxides, various salts, and glass forming materials.</p> <p>To maximize the broader impact of this project, the work on this project has been made available in scientific publications, presented at major national conferences, and displayed at more specialized meetings and workshops for specialists. &nbsp;The research findings are of interest to fundamental and applied scientists who study and fabricate novel materials systems for ultimate technological applications. &nbsp;Separately, presentations and a lecture on materials science were made before interested general public and high school audiences in New Haven, which is a minority-dominated school system, to help them appreciate the importance of nanoscale materials physics and chemistry. &nbsp;In terms of human resource development, one graduate student has performed the bulk of the above research, in the process has been well trained in theoretical physics and materials science, and is now prepared to make novel contributions to the field of materials physics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2016<br>      Modified by: Sohrab&nbsp;Ismail-Beigi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has focused on two separate intellectual merit questions related to the physical properties of solid state materials.  First, research was undertaken to understand the properties of materials with nanometer scale dimensions made of pure boron as well as boron with added metallic elements, specifically magnesium.  The nanoscale types of materials examined included nanotubes as well as flat sheet materials with thicknesses on the scale of atoms: both classes of materials are exemplified by the more well known cases of carbon nanotubes and graphene.  Boron based nanomaterials have been the subject of increased interest and investigation due to their novel structural, mechanical, and electronic properties: for example, magnesium boride is a superconducting material with a relatively high transition temperature of 40 Kelvin.  Furthermore, boron nanomaterials enlarge the library of nanoscale materials that are accessible and modifiable for potential technological applications.  Boron nanomaterials generally show complex bonding patterns and intricate geometric arrangements of their atoms.  The project was able to probe and understand key aspects of the properties of nanoscale boron-based materials including: (i) identification of specific metal surfaces on which boron atoms prefer to arrange into atomically thin sheet-like structures, (ii) how the addition of magnesium atoms to boron sheets changes their energetics and structure, (iii) how addition of magnesium to boron sheets leads to a transfer of electrons to the boron component, (iv) how the transfer of electrons in boron nanotubes with attached magnesium can strongly modify the stable diameters of nanotubes that can be created, and (v) more generally, how electron transfer between two nanoscale materials can modify the properties of the joint system in unexpected ways.  Second, a novel approach was developed to understand how light interacts with sound waves in solid state materials.  When a sound wave propagates in a material, it alternatively compresses and expands the material (since sound is a wave of pressure) which in turn changes the index of refraction of the material.  This connection, the photoelastic effect, means light incident on a material can be used to control sound waves propagating inside it and vice versa.  Such physical effects can form the basis of new types of optical devices for information processing using light waves.  However, from a basic science viewpoint, while one can measure the photoelastic effect experimentally and one can compute its numerical value (the photoelastic coefficient) using modern computational methods, there is a lack of basic physical understanding of what controls the size of this effect in any given material.  For example, there is no real predictive method based on a simple physical model that can provide the sign of the photoelastic coefficient much less its precise magnitude (i.e., whether the index of refraction increases upon compression or decreases).  The lack of a basic model means that trying to design new materials with improved photoelastic properties is at present based on trial and error.  Our work in this project has setup a physical framework for computing the photoelastic effect that directly ties it to how electrons form bonds between the atoms in a material and how those bonds and bonding electrons are distorted upon the arrival of the elastic waves.  The approach is from first principles without fudge parameters or simplifying assumptions on the types of bonds or electronic bonding orbitals.  To date, the method has been developed from scratch, implemented numerically in software, and thoroughly tested against prior theory and available experiments for semiconductors.  The next step is to consider a wider set of materials including metal oxides, various salts, and glass forming materials.  To maximize the broader impact of this project, the work on this project has been made available in scientific publications, presented at major national conferences, and displayed at more specialized meetings and workshops for specialists.  The research findings are of interest to fundamental and applied scientists who study and fabricate novel materials systems for ultimate technological applications.  Separately, presentations and a lecture on materials science were made before interested general public and high school audiences in New Haven, which is a minority-dominated school system, to help them appreciate the importance of nanoscale materials physics and chemistry.  In terms of human resource development, one graduate student has performed the bulk of the above research, in the process has been well trained in theoretical physics and materials science, and is now prepared to make novel contributions to the field of materials physics.          Last Modified: 08/04/2016       Submitted by: Sohrab Ismail-Beigi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
