<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Silica-Derived Nitric Oxide Delivery Vehicles as Anti-Plaque Agents</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research to University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill is to carryout studies in nitric oxide (NO)-releasing silica nanomaterial-scaffolds that reduce dental biofilm formation via localized NO delivery. The rationale for pursuing this work is based on nitric oxide's central role in our body's immune response to pathogens, broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity, and rapid diffusion through biofilms. Silica nanomaterials allow for tunable properties such as NO storage, size and surface charge, and will enable the study of such properties on bactericidal activity and cytotoxicity.  After determining the optimum particle properties for killing planktonic bacteria, the project will study the eradication of established biofilms. The research will establish new knowledge regarding the effects of nanomaterial properties on antibacterial activity. This project is expected in providing graduate and undergraduate students with experiences that interface materials science with microbiology through fundamental, transformative, and discovery research. In addition, this project will take advantage of the clear need for understanding nanoparticle-bacteria dynamics to engage underrepresented populations in science and engineering through the research activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tooth decay due to bacteria plaque biofilms is a prevalent and costly health problem worldwide. Although substantial progress has been made through fluoride treatment of public water supplies and routine dental cleaning, tooth decay remains a significant problem requiring intense treatment.  In 2006, dental care costs amounted to 7.4% of the total healthcare spending in the U.S. alone.  In this proposal, the investigators seek to develop new bactericidal nanomaterials against plaque producing bacteria. This work aims to elucidate how the properties of the nanomaterial (e.g., size, charge, and nitric oxide release kinetics) influence its biocidal activity against plaque producing bacteria. The research is thus critical to the implementation of drug-releasing nanoparticles with maximum therapeutic efficacy. The proposed work will also have significant impact on students. In addition to providing students with research projects that enables training at the interface of material science, chemistry and microbiology, the research will be used to capture the attention of underrepresented populations in science and engineering through specialized research experiences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1104892</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Schoenfisch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark H Schoenfisch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schoenfisch@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9198438714</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~145587</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~149957</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~154456</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through the funded project we defined the most important physical and chemical properties that impact the antibacterial efficacy of macromolecular nitric oxide (NO)-release systems. In addition to synthesizing a diverse repertoire of NO-releasing particles based on size, shape, NO payloads, and exterior functionalities such as charge and hydrophobicity, we evaluated the role of the scaffold properties on antibacterial action. The results from our work suggest that multiple properties govern the antibacterial action of NO, with particle size, shape, and charge/hydrophobicity being equally important as the NO-release kinetics. Furthermore, we observed that certain bacteria, their state (planktonic versus biofilm), and pH played major roles in NO&rsquo;s effectiveness. This knowledge will be of interest to scientists and clinicians alike, particularly those seeking new approaches for eradicating bacteria while avoiding the overuse of antibiotics. While the potential use of NO-release scaffolds for oral care applications (i.e., prevention or treatment of periodontal disease and/or dental caries) is now clearer, other diseases that may benefit from NO-release therapeutics include acne, cystic fibrosis, and chronic wounds. Regardless of the disorder, future work must include rigorous preclinical and clinical testing under conditions common to a given disease.</p> <p>The work carried out also played a significant role in the training of future scientists. In addition to providing both graduate and undergraduate students with interdisciplinary research projects that required the integration of biology, chemistry, and material science, the project was used to capture the attention and interest of underrepresented science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) students. Indeed, the project attracted and helped support Hispanic and Latino students. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;H&nbsp;Schoenfisch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through the funded project we defined the most important physical and chemical properties that impact the antibacterial efficacy of macromolecular nitric oxide (NO)-release systems. In addition to synthesizing a diverse repertoire of NO-releasing particles based on size, shape, NO payloads, and exterior functionalities such as charge and hydrophobicity, we evaluated the role of the scaffold properties on antibacterial action. The results from our work suggest that multiple properties govern the antibacterial action of NO, with particle size, shape, and charge/hydrophobicity being equally important as the NO-release kinetics. Furthermore, we observed that certain bacteria, their state (planktonic versus biofilm), and pH played major roles in NOÆs effectiveness. This knowledge will be of interest to scientists and clinicians alike, particularly those seeking new approaches for eradicating bacteria while avoiding the overuse of antibiotics. While the potential use of NO-release scaffolds for oral care applications (i.e., prevention or treatment of periodontal disease and/or dental caries) is now clearer, other diseases that may benefit from NO-release therapeutics include acne, cystic fibrosis, and chronic wounds. Regardless of the disorder, future work must include rigorous preclinical and clinical testing under conditions common to a given disease.  The work carried out also played a significant role in the training of future scientists. In addition to providing both graduate and undergraduate students with interdisciplinary research projects that required the integration of biology, chemistry, and material science, the project was used to capture the attention and interest of underrepresented science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) students. Indeed, the project attracted and helped support Hispanic and Latino students.            Last Modified: 09/28/2015       Submitted by: Mark H Schoenfisch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
