<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Hybrid Graphene-Ferroelectric Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>419999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>419999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is jointly funded by the Electronic and Photonic Materials (EPM) Program in the Division of Materials Research (DMR) and the Electronics, Photonics, and Magnetic Devices (EPMD) Program in the Division of Electrical, Communications and Cyber Systems (ECCS).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: This research project studies hybrid graphene-ferroelectric materials and devices. The hybrid materials offer promise for combining the strength of the unique two-dimensional Dirac Fermionic electronic structure and high carrier mobility in graphene plus the high functionality in ferroelectric materials. The research is designed to overcome undesirable polarization screening by absorbates on the surface of ferroelectric materials by the use of artificially layered superlattice materials in the form of epitaxial thin films, in which the phase transition temperature and dielectric response of the material can be precisely tailored. The research focuses mainly on two aspects: (1). A ferroelectric material is used to charge dope a graphene sheet in contact with it to a much higher extent than the conventional dielectrics can. Based on the principle of ferroelectric charge doping, atomic force microscopy are used for "on-demand" fabrication of nano-junctions and circuits, allowing definition of sharp potential profiles with arbitrary designs, enabling exploration of the physics of Dirac electron scattering through both scanning probe imaging and electrical transport measurements. (2). A ferroelectric material is used to exert precisely controlled strain on a graphene sheet in particular directions to modify the electronic properties and to study the theoretically predicted gauge field effects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic and applied research issues in an interdisciplinary area that combines physics, materials science and device engineering, with high technological relevance. The unique properties of graphene are exploited in new device structures that utilize both the ferroelectric field effect and piezoelectric strain. Prototype devices studied in the project could form the seed for next-generation electronics such as novel transistors with low-power consumption and high mobility, non-volatile memory devices, and devices based on strained graphene. Graduate students, as well as undergraduate and high-school students, are trained in an interdisciplinary environment and learn thin-film deposition, lithography, atomic force microscopy, and electrical characterization.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1105202</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Dawber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Dawber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matthew.dawber@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316324978</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xu</FirstName>
<LastName>Du</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xu Du</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xu.du@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316328019</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000548113</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1022</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIP ACT-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~419999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research project studies hybrid graphene-ferroelectric devices, aiming to combine the excellent electronic properties of graphene with the high functionality in ferroelectric materials. Over the whole grant period, our work mainly on the following two aspects.</p> <p>&nbsp;(1). We use ferroelectric superlattice as a functional dielectric material to induce strong electric polarization onto graphene. Our approach, utilizing epitaxial ferroelectric superlattice with tunable transition temperature, overcomes the undesirable polarization screening by absorbates on the surface of ferroelectric materials. Based on this approach we successfully demonstrated, for the first time, robust room temperature ferroelectric switching with arbitrary speed in ferroelectric-graphene field effect transistors. A paper is published on this topic (<cite>Nano Lett.</cite>,&nbsp;<strong>2014</strong>,&nbsp;<em>14</em>&nbsp;(9), pp 5437&ndash;5444). Based on this development, we study atomic force microscopy &ldquo;writing&rdquo; of ferroelectric domains in graphene-ferroelectric field effect devices using flexoelectric effect. This on-going work aims for "on-demand" fabrication of nano-junctions and circuits, allowing definition of sharp potential profiles with arbitrary designs, enabling exploration of the physics of Dirac electron scattering through both scanning probe imaging and electrical transport measurements. We expect to yield paper on this topic in the near future. In general, the graphene-ferroelectric superlattice system we developed potentially opens the possibility of novel ferroelectric memories and electronics.</p> <p>&nbsp;(2). We study the impact of strain on the mechanical and electrical properties of graphene and its devices. The original plan was to use ferroelectric/piezoelectric substrates to exert precisely controlled strain on a graphene sheet in particular directions to modify its electronic properties. Due to the limitation in the structural stability of most of the ferroelectric/piezoelectric materials, the technical approach was modified, and flexible plastic substrates are instead used for the purpose of applying strain. We have successfully developed suspended graphene nanoelectromechanical resonators on Polyimide substrate, which allows independent and extensive strain tuning. With these devices, we carried out the first thorough study of the nonlinear dynamics on graphene based nanoelectromechanical resonators. A paper on this topic is under review by Nano Letters. These devices also provide the best platform up-to-date, for studying &ldquo;strain engineering&rdquo; of the electrical properties of graphene and other 2D materials. Currently, we are studying the impact of strain on the corrugation, flexural phonon and gauge field in graphene. A paper on the strain tuning of transport properties in graphene is under preparation. Our achievements open the possibility of tailoring the electrical and mechanical properties of the 2D materials and their devices, using strain.</p> <p>&nbsp;In general, the project addresses basic and applied research issues in an interdisciplinary area that combines physics, materials science and device engineering, with high technological relevance. Through the project, two graduate students, three undergraduate and two high-school students, are trained in an interdisciplinary environment and learn thin-film deposition, lithography, atomic force microscopy, and electrical characterization. In particular, a high school student, Niyati Desai, participated in our research through the Simons Summer Research Program in 2014, working on exploration of a novel superlattice system, BTO/STO, through fabrication and characterization of graphene FET devices on the superlattice. Through her work, Niyati achieved great success in the Siemens competition and became a Siemens FINALIST. She also won the SECOND PLACE IN PHYSICS AND ASTRONOMY in...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research project studies hybrid graphene-ferroelectric devices, aiming to combine the excellent electronic properties of graphene with the high functionality in ferroelectric materials. Over the whole grant period, our work mainly on the following two aspects.   (1). We use ferroelectric superlattice as a functional dielectric material to induce strong electric polarization onto graphene. Our approach, utilizing epitaxial ferroelectric superlattice with tunable transition temperature, overcomes the undesirable polarization screening by absorbates on the surface of ferroelectric materials. Based on this approach we successfully demonstrated, for the first time, robust room temperature ferroelectric switching with arbitrary speed in ferroelectric-graphene field effect transistors. A paper is published on this topic (Nano Lett., 2014, 14 (9), pp 5437&ndash;5444). Based on this development, we study atomic force microscopy "writing" of ferroelectric domains in graphene-ferroelectric field effect devices using flexoelectric effect. This on-going work aims for "on-demand" fabrication of nano-junctions and circuits, allowing definition of sharp potential profiles with arbitrary designs, enabling exploration of the physics of Dirac electron scattering through both scanning probe imaging and electrical transport measurements. We expect to yield paper on this topic in the near future. In general, the graphene-ferroelectric superlattice system we developed potentially opens the possibility of novel ferroelectric memories and electronics.   (2). We study the impact of strain on the mechanical and electrical properties of graphene and its devices. The original plan was to use ferroelectric/piezoelectric substrates to exert precisely controlled strain on a graphene sheet in particular directions to modify its electronic properties. Due to the limitation in the structural stability of most of the ferroelectric/piezoelectric materials, the technical approach was modified, and flexible plastic substrates are instead used for the purpose of applying strain. We have successfully developed suspended graphene nanoelectromechanical resonators on Polyimide substrate, which allows independent and extensive strain tuning. With these devices, we carried out the first thorough study of the nonlinear dynamics on graphene based nanoelectromechanical resonators. A paper on this topic is under review by Nano Letters. These devices also provide the best platform up-to-date, for studying "strain engineering" of the electrical properties of graphene and other 2D materials. Currently, we are studying the impact of strain on the corrugation, flexural phonon and gauge field in graphene. A paper on the strain tuning of transport properties in graphene is under preparation. Our achievements open the possibility of tailoring the electrical and mechanical properties of the 2D materials and their devices, using strain.   In general, the project addresses basic and applied research issues in an interdisciplinary area that combines physics, materials science and device engineering, with high technological relevance. Through the project, two graduate students, three undergraduate and two high-school students, are trained in an interdisciplinary environment and learn thin-film deposition, lithography, atomic force microscopy, and electrical characterization. In particular, a high school student, Niyati Desai, participated in our research through the Simons Summer Research Program in 2014, working on exploration of a novel superlattice system, BTO/STO, through fabrication and characterization of graphene FET devices on the superlattice. Through her work, Niyati achieved great success in the Siemens competition and became a Siemens FINALIST. She also won the SECOND PLACE IN PHYSICS AND ASTRONOMY in the Intel International Science and Engineering Fair             Last Modified: 05/26/2015       Submitted by: Xu Du]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
