<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Degenerate dispersive effects in partial and lattice differential equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>202837.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>202837</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A spatially extended system is said to be dispersive when the speed of propagation of a wave depends upon that wave's frequency. Linear dispersive effects play a fundamental role in the study of a large number of physical scenarios and there has been an explosion of results concerning semi-linear dispersive equations.  Nevertheless there are situations in which the speed of propagation of a wave depends on the wave's frequency as well as its amplitude.  That is to say the mechanism which generates dispersion is nonlinear.  It is the purpose of this project to develop mathematically rigorous theory for such equations when the nonlinear dispersive effects are degenerate (i.e., they vanish very rapidly as the amplitude tends to zero). The degeneracy of the equations allows for the existence of classical solutions which are not smooth and there is substantial numerical and formal evidence that cases arise in which degenerate dispersion leads to catastrophic instability akin to that of a backwards heat equation.  Consequently, one of the principal goals of the project is to develop the existence theory for degenerate dispersive partial differential equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Degenerate dispersive equations arise as models for the dynamics of chains and lattices of hard spheres.  Experimental results demonstrate that such chains exhibit tightly focused pulses which are easily generated and highly tunable. These narrow pulses are expected to find uses in non-destructive testing, shock absorption, remote sensing and medical imaging.  At this time, there is no theoretically rigorous explanation for the stability and robust nature of these pulses. Though there are results concerning similar physical problems where the dispersive effects are not degenerate, they rely strongly on the fact that slow moving pulses are very wide and very small in amplitude.  In the case of hard spheres, the interesting pulse solutions have a fixed width, independent of speed and amplitude and it is not obvious how to extend the known results to this case.  A primary goal of the project is developing mathematical tools for the study of the stability and robustness of such pulses. The inclusion and training of graduate and undergraduate students is an integral part of this project. Among other projects, undergraduate students will be involved into investigation of an important application, models for traffic flow.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1105635</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Wright</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay D Wright</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdoug@math.drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158950981</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225560</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drexel University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158956342</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 10th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DREXEL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drexel University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1505 Race St, 10th Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~139597</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~63240</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Waves which propagate through a solid material or on the surface of the ocean are dispersive, which is to say that the frequency of the wave determine the rate at which it moves. They are also nonlinear, which is to say that changing the ampltude of the wave changes its motion in a complicated way. This project had two main outcomes related to the analysis of such waves.</p> <p>The first was the development of tools to understand how spatial variability in such systems impacts the propagation of the waves. For instance, if a pressue wave moves through a solid material which is a composite of several materials, how does that differ from the case where the material is uniform thoughout the solid? This project showed that (in a certain limiting case) that the waves in the heterogeneous problem can be represented as a piece which is more or less like in the uniform case (with properties determined though a complicated averaging process) plus a high frequency correction (determined by the exact nature of material). Another of this project's results about the impact of spatially varying dispersion on wave propagation is that if the coefficient of dispersion in an equation vanishes then the solution forms shocks at this degenerate point so rapidly that the equation is said to be ill-posed.</p> <p>The second scientific outcome was the development of a new method to describe traveling water waves. Unlike most previous approaches, the new method is flexible enough to describe waves which overturn. This new formulation is suitable both for rigorous analysis and precise numerical computation. &nbsp;Moreover, the method is appropriate for waves in both 2 and 3 spatial dimensions. Using this method, the PI and collaborators provided the first existence proof for periodic traveling vortex sheets in 2D as well as providing an exhaustive list (by means of global bifurcation theory) of limiting cases for such waves. (For instance, waves which encapsulate a bubble, or waves of arbitrarily large amplitude.)</p> <p>Additionally, this project supported an `undergraduate research co-op.' For six months during project, an undergraduate worked as a full time research assistant to the PI. The student learned about the governing equations for wave propagation in heterogeneous solids, devised a numerical method for simulating solutions to such equations and implelemented the methods for a wide variety of physical situations. These results supported and corroborated theoretical results of the PI and are a critical component of the research program. In this way, the project supported the training of a future scientific researcher and advanced the scientific aims of the project simultaneously.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/25/2015<br>      Modified by: Jay&nbsp;D&nbsp;Wright</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Waves which propagate through a solid material or on the surface of the ocean are dispersive, which is to say that the frequency of the wave determine the rate at which it moves. They are also nonlinear, which is to say that changing the ampltude of the wave changes its motion in a complicated way. This project had two main outcomes related to the analysis of such waves.  The first was the development of tools to understand how spatial variability in such systems impacts the propagation of the waves. For instance, if a pressue wave moves through a solid material which is a composite of several materials, how does that differ from the case where the material is uniform thoughout the solid? This project showed that (in a certain limiting case) that the waves in the heterogeneous problem can be represented as a piece which is more or less like in the uniform case (with properties determined though a complicated averaging process) plus a high frequency correction (determined by the exact nature of material). Another of this project's results about the impact of spatially varying dispersion on wave propagation is that if the coefficient of dispersion in an equation vanishes then the solution forms shocks at this degenerate point so rapidly that the equation is said to be ill-posed.  The second scientific outcome was the development of a new method to describe traveling water waves. Unlike most previous approaches, the new method is flexible enough to describe waves which overturn. This new formulation is suitable both for rigorous analysis and precise numerical computation.  Moreover, the method is appropriate for waves in both 2 and 3 spatial dimensions. Using this method, the PI and collaborators provided the first existence proof for periodic traveling vortex sheets in 2D as well as providing an exhaustive list (by means of global bifurcation theory) of limiting cases for such waves. (For instance, waves which encapsulate a bubble, or waves of arbitrarily large amplitude.)  Additionally, this project supported an `undergraduate research co-op.' For six months during project, an undergraduate worked as a full time research assistant to the PI. The student learned about the governing equations for wave propagation in heterogeneous solids, devised a numerical method for simulating solutions to such equations and implelemented the methods for a wide variety of physical situations. These results supported and corroborated theoretical results of the PI and are a critical component of the research program. In this way, the project supported the training of a future scientific researcher and advanced the scientific aims of the project simultaneously.             Last Modified: 11/25/2015       Submitted by: Jay D Wright]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
