<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Dynamical Processes in Semiconductor Nanowires in the Quantum Regime</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>345928.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352178</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Sokol</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Semiconductor nanowires have recently emerged as a new class of materials with significant potential for the advancement of understanding of fundamental physics and for new applications in device physics. This research project will bring together expertise in state-of-the-art semiconductor nanowire growth, in modeling of these structures, and in unique excitation spectroscopies in order to advance the understanding of dynamical properties of semiconductor nanowires whose diameters are in the quantum regime.  This project will: support the design and growth of unique radial and axial nanowire heterostructures; develop new optical tools for measurement of quantum states and their interactions; investigate nanowire heterostructures in the quantum regime utilizing these new tools; employ highly localized electric fields to manipulate and probe the electronic states in the nanowire  heterostructures; carry out both optical and transport measurements; and explore spin dynamics in these nanowire heterostructures.  By designing, growing, and probing nanowire radial and axial heterostructures with length scales from 5 nm - 50 nm, we will have access to the truly quantum regime in these materials.  Both graduate and undergraduate students will be trained in these state-of-the-art techniques, which are an excellent preparation for careers ranging from research and education in academia, to applied development research in the most technologically advanced industries.  The overall goal of this research is to advance the understanding of dynamical processes in semiconductor nanowires in the quantum regime.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Semiconductor nanowires have recently emerged as a new class of materials with significant potential for the advancement of understanding of fundamental physics and for new applications in device physics. The research in this project will bring together expertise in state-of-the-art semiconductor nanowire growth, in modeling of these structures, and in experimental efforts that will advance the understanding of semiconductor nanowires whose diameters are less than 50 nm (1/1000 of the diameter of a human hair), a range where the materials themselves are comparable to the size of the wavelength of electrons. Remarkable phenomena and new technological opportunities are expected when synthetic materials can be designed so as to control the electron wavefunctions.  These states can be probed using both optical and transport measurements by using highly localized electric fields, magnetic fields, and utilizing unique nanowire heterostructures.  This research will be particularly directed towards the effect of spins in these materials where both new physics and new technologies may be enabled.  Graduate and undergraduate students will be trained in state-of-the-art optical and electronic techniques for looking at single nanowires.  Such training is excellent preparation for careers from research and teaching in academia to applied development in the most technologically advanced industries.  The overall goal of this research is to advance the understanding of dynamical processes in semiconductor nanowires in the quantum regime</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1105362</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard E Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>howard.jackson@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135560522</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000120288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leigh</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leigh M Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leigh.smith@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135560457</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000293663</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[51 Goodman Dr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041064767</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041064767</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Cincinnati Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Hall, Suite 530]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7504</Code>
<Text>NSF-INTERNAT COOP IN MATERIALS RES-OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~114497</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120803</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~116878</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div> <p>Semiconductor nanowires have recently emerged as a new class of materials with significant potential for the advancement of understanding of fundamental physics and for new applications in device physics. The research in this project has brought together expertise in state-of-the-art semiconductor nanowire growth, in modeling of these structures, and in experimental efforts that have advances the understanding of semiconductor nanowires whose diameters are less than 50 nm (1/1000 of the diameter of a human hair), a range where the materials themselves are comparable to the size of the wavelength of electrons and where quantum effects become important.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>Remarkable phenomena and new technological opportunities are expected when synthetic materials can be designed so as to control the electron wavefunctions. We have fabricated complex multilayered nanowires where electronic states achieve very strong quantum confinement.&nbsp; These states have been probed using both optical and transport measurements utilizing unique nanowire heterostructures, including investigations of unique radial quantum well tube nanowires.&nbsp; We have observed quantum effects all the way down to the zero-dimensional ultra-small quantum dot regime.&nbsp; Fourteen papers on phenomena in nanowires have been published which provides new information which is essential in the design and construction of new technologies which will utilize these novel nanostructures.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>Graduate and undergraduate students were trained in state-of-the-art optical and electronic techniques in studying single nanowires. Such training is excellent preparation for careers from research and teaching in academia to applied development in the most technologically advanced industries. The graduate and undergraduate students have also been involved in outreach to the public as part of the Cincinnati Museum Center and students from elementary to high schools.&nbsp; The results of this research have advanced the understanding of dynamical processes in semiconductor nanowires in the quantum regime.</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2016<br>      Modified by: Leigh&nbsp;M&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105362/1105362_10135514_1452626273244_emergence-toc-figure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105362/1105362_10135514_1452626273244_emergence-toc-figure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Diagram and Cross Sections of Quantum Well Tube Nanowire"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105362/1105362_10135514_1452626273244_emergence-toc-figure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Diagram and Cross Sections of Quantum Well Tube Nanowire"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Left panel shows a schematic diagram of a core-multishell quantum well tube (QWT) nanowire.  Right panel shows cross-sectional TEM images of an actual QWT.  Middle panel shows a high resolution photoluminescence map of emissions from zero dimensional quantum dots.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ACS Nano Letters</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Leigh&nbsp;M&nbsp;Smith</div> <div class="imageTitle">Diagram and Cross Sections of Quantum Well Tube Nanowire</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Semiconductor nanowires have recently emerged as a new class of materials with significant potential for the advancement of understanding of fundamental physics and for new applications in device physics. The research in this project has brought together expertise in state-of-the-art semiconductor nanowire growth, in modeling of these structures, and in experimental efforts that have advances the understanding of semiconductor nanowires whose diameters are less than 50 nm (1/1000 of the diameter of a human hair), a range where the materials themselves are comparable to the size of the wavelength of electrons and where quantum effects become important.  Intellectual Merit:  Remarkable phenomena and new technological opportunities are expected when synthetic materials can be designed so as to control the electron wavefunctions. We have fabricated complex multilayered nanowires where electronic states achieve very strong quantum confinement.  These states have been probed using both optical and transport measurements utilizing unique nanowire heterostructures, including investigations of unique radial quantum well tube nanowires.  We have observed quantum effects all the way down to the zero-dimensional ultra-small quantum dot regime.  Fourteen papers on phenomena in nanowires have been published which provides new information which is essential in the design and construction of new technologies which will utilize these novel nanostructures.  Broader Impacts:  Graduate and undergraduate students were trained in state-of-the-art optical and electronic techniques in studying single nanowires. Such training is excellent preparation for careers from research and teaching in academia to applied development in the most technologically advanced industries. The graduate and undergraduate students have also been involved in outreach to the public as part of the Cincinnati Museum Center and students from elementary to high schools.  The results of this research have advanced the understanding of dynamical processes in semiconductor nanowires in the quantum regime.        Last Modified: 01/12/2016       Submitted by: Leigh M Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
