<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Understanding Acid-Base Interactions using Interface-Sensitive Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this NSF project is to exploit the interface sensitivity of infrared-visible sum frequency generation spectroscopy (SFG) to measure acid-base interactions at solid-solid interfaces.  An understanding of polar interactions is important in the areas of adhesion, friction, and wetting.  In-situ characterization of acid-base interactions and their role in adhesion of these coatings at the molecular level and under kinetic conditions (for example: during sliding and mechanical contact) pose a formidable challenge to scientists.  The principal investigator (PI), Professor Dhinojwala, proposes to directly probe the acid-base interactions for polymers in contact with inorganic sapphire substrate or sapphire modified with self-assembled monolayers with acidic or basic end groups to understand these interactions at the molecular level.  SFG instrumentation is used to directly monitor the shifts in the vibrational peaks of the acidic and basic groups and correlate them with interaction energies to study exchange kinetics at polymer-solid interface as a function of time, temperature, and composition. This proposal explores the kinetics and thermodynamics of surface segregation driven by acid-base interactions. In addition, this proposal focuses on blends and copolymers to study the role of these interaction energies on the segregation of near solid-solid interfaces and dynamics during sliding and peel-off. The study of interaction energies and its experimental results have important implications in understanding friction and adhesion hysteresis. These interaction energies will be compared with adhesion measurements using the Johnson-Kendall- Roberts (JKR) geometry. In addition to these experiments, the PI will also conduct atomistic molecular dynamics simulations (MD) and quantum calculations to understand the magnitude of the frequency shift and its effect on segregation.  The SFG, MD, and quantum calculations of these experiments will be used in conjunction to understand the influence of surface concentration, steric constraints, and surface roughness on acid-base interactions and the consequences on adhesion energies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fundamental understanding of acid-base interactions helps in predicting the adhesion of polymers to substrates and in developing the next generation of enhanced coatings and adhesives for applications in multiple areas, including, but not limited to, electronics, bio-mineralization, peptide-based surface recognition, nano-composites and solar cells.  This project will support two graduate students who will work together as a group with experts in the areas of surface science, MD simulations, and industrial research. The students working with this broad multidisciplinary group will be provided training to work as a team. Additionally, the graduate students will also have the opportunity to supervise NSF-REU students during the summer.  As a volunteer Director of District 5 Science Day, the PI will continue his outreach to host District Science Day at The University of Akron (UA). The PI has also initiated a mentorship program where he brings together scientists from industries and academia to mentor the science projects. This mentorship program was started in the city of Hudson, Ohio, and the PI plans to make this program available to all schools in District 5. In collaboration with UA's business school and Austen Bio-innovation Institute in Akron, the PI is helpping in developing a multidisciplinary Bio-design class offered to UA students in physical sciences, business, and medicine with a goal of observation or experimental based approach to solve problems. This class will be taught in collaboration with professors from UA's business and medicine schools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1105370</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Dhinojwala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali N Dhinojwala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ali4@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3309726246</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Akron</Name>
<CityName>Akron</CityName>
<ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3309722760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>302 Buchtel Common</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045207552</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF AKRON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045207552</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Akron]]></Name>
<CityName>Akron</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[302 Buchtel Common]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcome (<strong><em><span><span>DMR</span>-1105370 (2011-2016)</span></em></strong>, Understanding Acid-Base Interactions using Interface-Sensitive Spectroscopy</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong><span> The objective of this proposal was to exploit the interface sensitivity of infrared-visible sum frequency generation spectroscopy (<span>SFG</span>) to measure acid-base interactions at solid-solid interfaces.&nbsp; To design coatings that stick to solid surfaces or creating multilayer coatings require a fundamental understanding of the interaction of molecules at interfaces. The focus of this proposal was to understand the formation of acid-base bonds at interfaces and relate it to surface segregation and adhesion. Acid-base interactions play an important in the areas of adhesion, friction, and wetting.&nbsp; In-situ characterization of acid-base interactions and their role in adhesion of these coatings at the molecular level and under kinetic conditions (for example: during sliding and mechanical contact) pose a formidable challenge to scientists.&nbsp; In this grant the PI has designed <span>SFG</span> experiments to study contact of polymer films with an acidic sapphire substrate. They were able to quantify the segregation of more basic groups next to a more acidic sapphire substrate by monitoring the shift in vibration of the surface OH groups. This allowed them to quantify the amount and orientation of these functional groups at the interface. In addition, the PI has developed novel approaches to monitor the changes taking place as a function of humidity, temperature, and during sliding. To improve the understanding of the spectroscopy results, the PI has collaborated with Dr. <span>Tsige</span> to perform molecular dynamics simulations (MD) and quantum calculations to compute <span>SFG</span> spectra for polymer-air interface. These theoretical spectra were compared directly with the experimental results to validate the theoretical models. The validated MD results were then be used to determine important structural differences of polymers as a function of <span>tacticity</span>. This grant has resulted in thirty published papers and filling of eight patent applications.</span></p> <p><strong>Broader Impact:</strong><span> Adhesion is a multi-billion dollar industry and the development of formulations for optimum performance is mostly based on intuition. Even with the advances in the chemistry, our adhesives perform very poorly in wet and humid conditions. They also use toxic additives to improve bonding with substrates. Understanding the bonding mechanism and how it withstands exposure to moisture will help in designing adhesives that are more effective in wet environments. The grant allowed the PI to train four PhD. students in the area of adhesion and surface science (Mike <span>Heiber</span>, Ila Badge, He <span>Zhu</span> and Adrian <span>Defante</span>). As part of the outreach activities, the PI has been organizing District 5 Science Day from last eighteen years (<span>http</span>://www2.<span>uakron</span>.<span>edu</span>/<span>cpspe</span>/<span>wrsd</span>/<span>wrsd</span>.<span>htm</span>). &nbsp;This activity involves around 350 poster presentation from middle and high school students. The best 100 posters are selected for participating at the annual State Fair held in Columbus, Ohio. The PI and his students have mentored undergraduate and high school students. The graduate students gave demonstrations at local schools, metro parks, and also participated as judges during Science Day. The PI has also contributed as a program chair of the adhesion society meeting in 2016; is currently a Vice-Chair for the Gordon conference on adhesion; and co-PI of the new <span>biomimicry</span> center at the University of Akron.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2016<br>      Modified by: Ali&nbsp;N&nbsp;Dhinojwala</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707408547_Science_Day--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707408547_Science_Day--rgov-800width.jpg" title="District 5 Science Day"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707408547_Science_Day--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="District 5 Science Day"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Picture of students and parents attending the award ceremony at the district 5 science day</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Dhinojwala</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ali&nbsp;N&nbsp;Dhinojwala</div> <div class="imageTitle">District 5 Science Day</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707544768_Temperature_Cell--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707544768_Temperature_Cell--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Temperature Cell for SFG"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707544768_Temperature_Cell--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Temperature Cell for SFG"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The heating and cooling cell developed for conducting sum frequency generation experiments</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Dhinojwala</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ali&nbsp;N&nbsp;Dhinojwala</div> <div class="imageTitle">Temperature Cell for SFG</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707705715_Surface_Segregation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707705715_Surface_Segregation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Surface Concentration of PMMA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1105370/1105370_10092112_1476707705715_Surface_Segregation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Surface Concentration of PMMA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The differences in surface concentration of poly(methylmethacrylate) (PMMA) polymer in a thin film containing polystyrene (PS) and PMMA. The concentration at the air interface is enriched with PS and at the sapphire interface with PMMA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ali Dhinojwala</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ali&nbsp;N&nbsp;Dhinojwala</div> <div class="imageTitle">Surface Concentration of PMMA</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcome (DMR-1105370 (2011-2016), Understanding Acid-Base Interactions using Interface-Sensitive Spectroscopy  Intellectual Merit: The objective of this proposal was to exploit the interface sensitivity of infrared-visible sum frequency generation spectroscopy (SFG) to measure acid-base interactions at solid-solid interfaces.  To design coatings that stick to solid surfaces or creating multilayer coatings require a fundamental understanding of the interaction of molecules at interfaces. The focus of this proposal was to understand the formation of acid-base bonds at interfaces and relate it to surface segregation and adhesion. Acid-base interactions play an important in the areas of adhesion, friction, and wetting.  In-situ characterization of acid-base interactions and their role in adhesion of these coatings at the molecular level and under kinetic conditions (for example: during sliding and mechanical contact) pose a formidable challenge to scientists.  In this grant the PI has designed SFG experiments to study contact of polymer films with an acidic sapphire substrate. They were able to quantify the segregation of more basic groups next to a more acidic sapphire substrate by monitoring the shift in vibration of the surface OH groups. This allowed them to quantify the amount and orientation of these functional groups at the interface. In addition, the PI has developed novel approaches to monitor the changes taking place as a function of humidity, temperature, and during sliding. To improve the understanding of the spectroscopy results, the PI has collaborated with Dr. Tsige to perform molecular dynamics simulations (MD) and quantum calculations to compute SFG spectra for polymer-air interface. These theoretical spectra were compared directly with the experimental results to validate the theoretical models. The validated MD results were then be used to determine important structural differences of polymers as a function of tacticity. This grant has resulted in thirty published papers and filling of eight patent applications.  Broader Impact: Adhesion is a multi-billion dollar industry and the development of formulations for optimum performance is mostly based on intuition. Even with the advances in the chemistry, our adhesives perform very poorly in wet and humid conditions. They also use toxic additives to improve bonding with substrates. Understanding the bonding mechanism and how it withstands exposure to moisture will help in designing adhesives that are more effective in wet environments. The grant allowed the PI to train four PhD. students in the area of adhesion and surface science (Mike Heiber, Ila Badge, He Zhu and Adrian Defante). As part of the outreach activities, the PI has been organizing District 5 Science Day from last eighteen years (http://www2.uakron.edu/cpspe/wrsd/wrsd.htm).  This activity involves around 350 poster presentation from middle and high school students. The best 100 posters are selected for participating at the annual State Fair held in Columbus, Ohio. The PI and his students have mentored undergraduate and high school students. The graduate students gave demonstrations at local schools, metro parks, and also participated as judges during Science Day. The PI has also contributed as a program chair of the adhesion society meeting in 2016; is currently a Vice-Chair for the Gordon conference on adhesion; and co-PI of the new biomimicry center at the University of Akron.          Last Modified: 10/17/2016       Submitted by: Ali N Dhinojwala]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
