<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Polymer-Derived In-Situ Metal-Matrix Nanocomposites:  A New Paradigm in Processing, Structure, and Properties of Dispersion Strengthened (copper) Alloys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>460000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>460000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY: A nanoscale dispersion of stable, non-coarsening ceramic particles into a metal matrix is a precondition for metallic composites that resist creep at high homologous temperatures. The goal of this program is to develop the scientific underpinnings for a new method for dispersing fine particles of a ceramic phase into a metal, and understanding how they influence the mechanical properties. In this method the ceramic is introduced into the metal as a polymer, which is then pyrolyzed in-situ to create the nanodispersed ceramic phase. This research program will explore the basic mechanisms for the in-situ conversion of the polymer into the ceramic.  Copper, dispersed with nanoparticles of a polymer-derived ceramic phase constituted from Si-C-N-O, will be employed as the "model" material system for this investigation. The microstructural stability and the creep and creep fracture behavior of the alloy at temperatures approaching 950 °C (about 0.9 of the melting temperature) will be investigated. Fundamental mechanisms that include how the size and spacing, and the structure and bonding at the particle-matrix interface control the climb of dislocations and the nucleation of voids under mechanical loading at high temperatures, will be studied. A key issue is to elucidate how the interfacial bonding influences the threshold stress, the ultimate goal being to achieve a threshold stress that approaches the Orowan upper bound for the escape of dislocations pinned by hard particles. Atomistic modeling isexpected to inform the experimental results.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY: New nanomaterials with unusual properties are often highly complex, both in the way they are made and how they perform. For them to be successfully implemented into next-generation systems, their performance must be underpinned by scientific understanding and models. This research program is dedicated to the science and development of novel high temperature metallic alloys that are potentially important for future engineering systems. Their novelty lies in a polymer route to the creation of a highly stable, nanoscale dispersion of ceramic particles in a metal matrix. The research plan includes intimate international collaborations in Austria and Germany that provide important expertise in atomic scale characterization and modeling. The program has an aggressive plan for dissemination of the scientific outcomes of this research, primarily through International Meetings that are held every two years in Boulder, Colorado.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1105347</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rishi</FirstName>
<LastName>Raj</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rishi Raj</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Rishi.Raj@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034921029</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000102275</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7504</Code>
<Text>NSF-INTERNAT COOP IN MATERIALS RES-OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="NormalEditcourier">In solid state processing the polymer was cross-linked and crushed into powder which was then mechanically milled with copper powder. The polymer, being soft and malleable, was broken down into nano-scale fragments. The volume fraction of the polymer could be increased up to 30 vol% by this method. When the milled powder mixture was hot pressed the polymer converted into a very fine dispersion of ceramic particles. The yield strength of the alloy continued to increase with the volume fraction of the polymer phase, reaching a value of 300 Vickers hardness. The increase in the yield strength with the particle size and spacing could be reasonably well explained by the Orowan stress. The particle size and spacing were determined by transmission electron microscopy. Most remarkably, the yield strength remained unchanged even when the alloy was exposed to 0.9T<sub>M</sub> (950 <sup>o</sup>C) for several hours. The retention of yield strength at high temperatures is attributed to the absence of solubility of the ceramic phase in the metal. (Dispersion strengthened copper alloys prepared by internal oxidation can also show high yield strength but they coarsen at high temperature since the process depends on the diffusivity of oxygen and the solubility of the dopant metal, aluminum or silicon for example, in copper).</p> <p class="NormalEditcourier">The interfacial strength of polymer-derived ceramics on copper has been measured by the periodic cracking technique. The results show a very high interfacial strength, amounting to several GPa. These results have not yet been published.</p> <p class="NormalEditcourier">The liquid metal processing of such <em>in-situ </em>metal alloys is possible when the melting point of the metal is below the temperature where the polymer converts into the ceramic phase (800 &ndash; 1000 <sup>o</sup>C). Magnesium, with a melting point of 650 <sup>o</sup>C was selected for these experiments. Experiments were set up within a glove-box with oxygen levels of less than 1 ppm to prevent oxidation of magnesium. The arrangement had provision for melting the charge, stirring the melt, which created a vortex into which the polymer was injected; remarkably the polymer would be immediately drawn into the melt. The melt was then cast into stainless steel molds (also within the glove box) to make large samples from which several dog-bone samples could be machined for mechanical testing. These test coupons had a gage length of 7.5 cm, and a width of 1 cm, and thickness of a few millimeters. Control samples were prepared from the same magnesium chips but without adding the polymer.</p> <p class="NormalEditcourier">Our research faced a learning curve to understand the nuances of microstructures produced by casting such as growth of dendrites and the segregation of second phases towards the outer perimeters of the grains. While pure Mg showed a clean equiaxed microstructure the castings of the composites showed segregation of the phases introduced by the polymer-additive process around the grains. However, transmission electron microscopy did reveal the retention of nanoscale particles within the grain matrix. Nevertheless tensile tests showed a three to four fold increase in the yield strength, ductility of up to 8%, and an ultimate tensile strength of 180 MPa. The fracture of these specimens remained transgranular, which would be consistent with good interfacial bonding between the magnesium matrix and the dispersed phase. Tensile tests at a strain rate of 10<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>&ndash;1</sup> at 400 <sup>o</sup>C (~0.75 T<sub>M</sub>) showed more than two fold increase in the flow stress relative to pure magnesium. In the alloys the fracture mode transitioned from transgranular to intergranular at high temperature, consistent with the behavior of nearly all structural alloys designed for high temperature applications. Stress rupture experiments, where the time to fracture and the strain rate were measured as a function of stress, applied as a dead-load, gave life times that were three orders of magnitude longer than for pure magnesium. These results, which extended up to 450 <sup>o</sup>C, prove the significance of the <em>in-situ</em> polymer-to-ceramic conversion method for making castings of magnesium which can have lightweight high temperature applications.</p> <p class="NormalEditcourier">A remarkable result with melt processing of magnesium was that the polymer precursor, which is a liquid, could be injected directly into the vortex created by the stirrer in the liquid melt, yielding properties which were similar to those obtained by a two step method where the polymer was first converted into a cross-linking powder and then injected into the melt. The liquid polymer injection method raises the possibility of great technological innovation where the polymer could be &ldquo;blown&rdquo; into the liquid metal to create a very fine dispersion of nanoscale ceramic particles which would yield much higher mechanical properties than those achieved so far.</p> <p class="NormalEditcourier">The results on <em>in-situ </em>castings of magnesium call for interdisciplinary research where casting, chemistry, metallurgy draw synergy in the scientific understanding of this new paradigm for the design and processing of a new genre of high temperature metals.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Rishi&nbsp;Raj</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[In solid state processing the polymer was cross-linked and crushed into powder which was then mechanically milled with copper powder. The polymer, being soft and malleable, was broken down into nano-scale fragments. The volume fraction of the polymer could be increased up to 30 vol% by this method. When the milled powder mixture was hot pressed the polymer converted into a very fine dispersion of ceramic particles. The yield strength of the alloy continued to increase with the volume fraction of the polymer phase, reaching a value of 300 Vickers hardness. The increase in the yield strength with the particle size and spacing could be reasonably well explained by the Orowan stress. The particle size and spacing were determined by transmission electron microscopy. Most remarkably, the yield strength remained unchanged even when the alloy was exposed to 0.9TM (950 oC) for several hours. The retention of yield strength at high temperatures is attributed to the absence of solubility of the ceramic phase in the metal. (Dispersion strengthened copper alloys prepared by internal oxidation can also show high yield strength but they coarsen at high temperature since the process depends on the diffusivity of oxygen and the solubility of the dopant metal, aluminum or silicon for example, in copper). The interfacial strength of polymer-derived ceramics on copper has been measured by the periodic cracking technique. The results show a very high interfacial strength, amounting to several GPa. These results have not yet been published. The liquid metal processing of such in-situ metal alloys is possible when the melting point of the metal is below the temperature where the polymer converts into the ceramic phase (800 &ndash; 1000 oC). Magnesium, with a melting point of 650 oC was selected for these experiments. Experiments were set up within a glove-box with oxygen levels of less than 1 ppm to prevent oxidation of magnesium. The arrangement had provision for melting the charge, stirring the melt, which created a vortex into which the polymer was injected; remarkably the polymer would be immediately drawn into the melt. The melt was then cast into stainless steel molds (also within the glove box) to make large samples from which several dog-bone samples could be machined for mechanical testing. These test coupons had a gage length of 7.5 cm, and a width of 1 cm, and thickness of a few millimeters. Control samples were prepared from the same magnesium chips but without adding the polymer. Our research faced a learning curve to understand the nuances of microstructures produced by casting such as growth of dendrites and the segregation of second phases towards the outer perimeters of the grains. While pure Mg showed a clean equiaxed microstructure the castings of the composites showed segregation of the phases introduced by the polymer-additive process around the grains. However, transmission electron microscopy did reveal the retention of nanoscale particles within the grain matrix. Nevertheless tensile tests showed a three to four fold increase in the yield strength, ductility of up to 8%, and an ultimate tensile strength of 180 MPa. The fracture of these specimens remained transgranular, which would be consistent with good interfacial bonding between the magnesium matrix and the dispersed phase. Tensile tests at a strain rate of 10-2 s&ndash;1 at 400 oC (~0.75 TM) showed more than two fold increase in the flow stress relative to pure magnesium. In the alloys the fracture mode transitioned from transgranular to intergranular at high temperature, consistent with the behavior of nearly all structural alloys designed for high temperature applications. Stress rupture experiments, where the time to fracture and the strain rate were measured as a function of stress, applied as a dead-load, gave life times that were three orders of magnitude longer than for pure magnesium. These results, which extended up to 450 oC, prove the significance of the in-situ polymer-to-ceramic conversion method for making castings of magnesium which can have lightweight high temperature applications. A remarkable result with melt processing of magnesium was that the polymer precursor, which is a liquid, could be injected directly into the vortex created by the stirrer in the liquid melt, yielding properties which were similar to those obtained by a two step method where the polymer was first converted into a cross-linking powder and then injected into the melt. The liquid polymer injection method raises the possibility of great technological innovation where the polymer could be "blown" into the liquid metal to create a very fine dispersion of nanoscale ceramic particles which would yield much higher mechanical properties than those achieved so far. The results on in-situ castings of magnesium call for interdisciplinary research where casting, chemistry, metallurgy draw synergy in the scientific understanding of this new paradigm for the design and processing of a new genre of high temperature metals.           Last Modified: 01/30/2017       Submitted by: Rishi Raj]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
