<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Bayesian methods for structure detection in analysis of object data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Complex data objects such as images, functional data, random sets, shapes, graphs and trees are nowadays commonly used to represent information present in observations. Bayesian methods are well suited for detecting meaningful structures hidden underneath these complex data sets. The structure may come in the form of sparsity, setting many parameter values to a null value like zero, or by making adjacent values equal, thus effectively reducing the number of parameters to handle. This project will provide definitive guidelines for constructing prior distributions on the parameters controlling the distributions of object data, and for computing the resulting posterior distributions in an efficient manner. The main idea of the research is to use an auxiliary stochastic process to control ties in object data. The project connects diverse concepts such as multi-scale modeling, feature sharing, multiple testing, random geometry, machine learning and nonparametric Bayesian paradigm, and synthesizes these different concepts into a powerful approach for analyzing object data. The project also stimulates the development of computing strategies that exploit structural niceties such as conditional conjugacy, thus providing fast and accurate computational approaches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project develops methodologies that will provide a foundation for finding structures in collections of data, with a wide range of applications in astronomy, medical sciences, engineering, finance, and various other fields. The research will help process astronomical images in a more accurate and efficient manner, and thus help identify events in distant supernova remnants and other astronomical bodies.  The research will also have a significant impact in medical imaging, by providing a method of accurate processing of scans of sensitive organs with very little exposure to harmful rays. The project will impact human resource development in the form of graduate student advising. The project will have subprojects that will be suitable topics for undergraduate research projects. Efforts will be made to involve students from under-represented groups to promote diversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1106570</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Subhashis</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghoshal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Subhashis Ghoshal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>subhashis_ghoshal@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195130190</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000381998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2601 Wolf Village Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~49790</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~98717</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~101493</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project deals with data which do not appear in the form of numbers but in more complex forms like images, curves and trees. In order to find structures in such data types, some appropriate tieing mechanisms are introduced. If data show evidence of any structure, the tieing mechanism will pick up those structures wil high chance, making the hidden structure visible after processing. Carefully constructed computational algorithms can carry out the required analysis in real time, making the method very practically usable compared with the previously available methods. The hidden structures found lead to many deeper understanding of the natural process generating the data. For instance, clustering curve data allows identifying certain disease such as epilepsy. Finding boundary of images help determine tumor size very accurately. Denoising of image and background noise removal techniques developed in the project is helful to improve clarity of faint astronomical images.</p> <p>The project led to graduate student advising and funded the research of a student from an underrepresented group. The PI taught an advanced research course which helped many student set their research paths. A conference on the subject matter was recently organized by the PI which enabled local students to interact with experts on the topic.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2015<br>      Modified by: Subhashis&nbsp;Ghoshal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project deals with data which do not appear in the form of numbers but in more complex forms like images, curves and trees. In order to find structures in such data types, some appropriate tieing mechanisms are introduced. If data show evidence of any structure, the tieing mechanism will pick up those structures wil high chance, making the hidden structure visible after processing. Carefully constructed computational algorithms can carry out the required analysis in real time, making the method very practically usable compared with the previously available methods. The hidden structures found lead to many deeper understanding of the natural process generating the data. For instance, clustering curve data allows identifying certain disease such as epilepsy. Finding boundary of images help determine tumor size very accurately. Denoising of image and background noise removal techniques developed in the project is helful to improve clarity of faint astronomical images.  The project led to graduate student advising and funded the research of a student from an underrepresented group. The PI taught an advanced research course which helped many student set their research paths. A conference on the subject matter was recently organized by the PI which enabled local students to interact with experts on the topic.       Last Modified: 08/25/2015       Submitted by: Subhashis Ghoshal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
