<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computational Studies of Nanocrystal Growth</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>480000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports integrated research and education in computational approaches aimed at understanding and quantifying the growth physics of nanocrystals, in particular semiconducting nanowires.  The combination of quantum confinement, superior transport and diverse surface structures have led to the emergence of semiconducting nanowires as materials of choice for next generation nanoelectronic devices and nanoelectromechanical systems. The realization of almost all of the envisioned applications relies on high-yield nanowire synthesis with controlled morphology and composition. The research focuses on classical vapor-liquid-solid growth, wherein a low melting nanoparticle catalyses vapour phase reduction of the gas precursor and also serves as a conduit for essentially one-dimensional mass transfer to the growing nanowire. Fundamental questions remain on aspects related to nanowire growth rate, steady-state diameter and growth orientation selection, in particular for small nanowires with diameters less than a few tens of nanometers. The underlying size dependent effects related to structure, energetics and dynamics of constituent interfaces necessitate a detailed understanding of the growth process that bridges atomic and continuum scales.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will combine computational approaches on atomic and continuum scales to study both equilibrium and non-equilibrium aspects of nanocrystalline growth, focusing on the well-characterized Au-catalyzed silicon nanowire growth system. The atomistically informed multi-physics approach is centered around classical molecular dynamics and suitably tailored Monte-Carlo based techniques, integrated within appropriately designed kinetic Monte-Carlo and phase field simulations. The atomistic computations are aimed at quantifying the energetics and kinetics of the consitutent interfaces, and the equilibrium as well as near-equilibrium structure, composition and morphology of the nanowire/catalyst particle system. The atomistic understanding is transferred to i) a tailored kinetic Monte-Carlo approach, and ii)  phase-field models that allow the PIs to address the growth aspects in their full complexity at the meso- and continuum scales.  It is expected that the insights gained from this research will be applicable to a broad set of technologically relevant nanowire systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research component will be integrated into educational and outreach activities that include i) the summer research discovery program and research internships made available through an NSF-funded interdisciplinary program to promote interest in Mathematics, Physics, Biology, and the sciences among college and high-school students, ii) participation and mentorship within the Materials Research Society chapter at Northeastern University, iii) the development of nanoscale-relevant curricula, iv) design of two capstone projects on nanowire growth and mechanics, v) participation in outreach at local schools and museums in the Boston area and through the Society for Women Engineers at Northeastern University, and vi) integration of related computational efforts within the region via the formation of a New England Network on Computational Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research and educational activities centered on improving our fundamental understanding of the synthesis of technologically relevant materials that have some of their spatial dimensions confined to very small length scales.  A primary focus will be semiconducting "nanowires", which are extended along one direction and have cross-sectional diameters of the order of up to several "nanometers", where a nanometer is one billionth the size of a meter.  Such nanowires are of significant technological interest for next-generation electronic devices, energy systems, as well as systems that integrate electronic and mechanical functionality at the nanometer length scale.  In spite of detailed experimental observations, the mechanisms that govern the formation of nanowires including size, shape, growth orientation and composition remain poorly understood.  Since the realization of almost all of the envisioned applications of nanowires relies on high-yield nanowire synthesis with controlled structure and composition, a detailed theoretical understanding of the growth process at a fundamental level is urgently needed.  In this research program, the PIs will combine various state-of-the-art computational approaches on the atomistic and continuum scales to elucidate basic mechanisms of nanowire formation.  The insight gained from this multi-physics approach is expected to apply to a broad set of technologically relevant elemental and compound materials at the nanoscale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research component will be integrated into educational and outreach activities that include i) the summer research discovery program and research internships made available through an NSF-funded interdisciplinary program to promote interest in Mathematics, Physics, Biology, and the sciences among college and high-school students, ii) participation and mentorship within the Materials Research Society chapter at Northeastern University, iii) the development of nanoscale-relevant curricula, iv) design of two capstone projects on nanowire growth and mechanics, v) participation in outreach at local schools and museums in the Boston area and through the Society for Women Engineers at Northeastern University, and vi) integration of related computational efforts within the region via the formation of a New England Network on Computational Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1106214</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alain</FirstName>
<LastName>Karma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alain S Karma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>a.karma@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173732929</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000215363</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Moneesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Upmanyu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Moneesh Upmanyu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mupmanyu@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173733186</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000321484</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 HUNTINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~320000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The next breakthrough in fast computer chips, highly efficient battery technologies and solar cells may very well be nanoscopic whisker-shaped crystals of silicon packaged like skyscrapers on wafer-scale substrates. An important route for growth of these nanoscale whiskers, or nanowires, involves alloyed droplets. As an example, to grow silicon whiskers, an alloyed droplet of gold and silicon is exposed to a silicon-rich gas, and the droplet catalyzes the formation of silicon nanowire. The nanowire grows with the droplet at its growing tip.&nbsp;&nbsp;The technique was developed decades ago for growing silicon &ldquo;whiskers&rdquo; that used a droplet of liquefied metal to trick vaporized silicon particles into solidifying into whiskers. The synthetic route is now widely used for growing nanowires for variety of technologically important materials.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>The route is attractive as it potentially offers control over both morphology and chemistry during nanowire synthesis. Unfortunately, controlling the size and shape of these 1D &nbsp;morphology and chemistry in these 1D crystals via this technique is challenging because the growth is affected by the surrounding interfaces - the vapor which forms and interface with the droplet surface and also the growing nanowire, and the interface between the liquid droplet and the growing tip of the crystal. Previous models have assumed that the properties of these interface do not change spatially or in time and this continues to handicap our ability to predict orientation and shape selection during growth of these nanocrystals.&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Intellectual merit</em>: In this project, we develop a fundamental understanding of the role of spatial variations in interface energetics and kinetics of VLS route for a classic system, &nbsp;Au-catalyzed growth of silicon nanowires. We employ computational expertise from atomic description of these material systems, to crystal-scale description of the material and the interfaces, and study &nbsp;nucleation and growth in this system. These include all-atom studies of steady-state growth of Si-nanowires to extract the overall growth form, and then extract energetics and kinetics of relevant interfaces (liquid-vapor, solid-vapor, and solid-liquid). &nbsp;We build an integrated approach built around a novel crystal-scale phase field model to make connections with experimental-scale growth and identify key aspects that lead to orientation and shape selection of nanocrystal growth. Our results show that the iquid droplet surface has an ordered structure, that controls the catalytic flux of silicon into the droplet. The growing tip of crystal is faceted with several bevels that follow from crystallography. This shape lowers the barrier for growth.&nbsp;These collection of beveled edges serve the same purpose as the Archimedean spirals that facilitate the growth of macroscale crystals, and that is a key part of the puzzle for large-scale growth of these crystals with prescribed form</p> <p>Our phase field results show that variations in interface energy control the form and extent of these facets, which in terms determine the overall growth, from growth of straight whiskers to kinked whiskers that change orientation. The kinking is also related to the growth rate of various interfaces. Variations in the energy of the solid-vapor interface (i.e. sidewalls) result in effects such as serrated growth, leading to functionally different properties of these periodically rough nanowires. Our methodology of briding atomic-scale with crystal-scale material description has the potential to capture fundamentals of the interplay between structure growth morphology, chemistry (especially dopant control) and properties (mechanical and functional), and is expected to expedite the deployment of nanoscale electronic and mechanical devices based on these nanostructures.</p> <p><em>Broader impact</em>: The results of our studies have broad implications as the focus on fundamental aspects of nanowire growth, as opposed to system specific aspects. The strategy developed here should allow us to develop computational model for VLS study for a wide variety of nanowires, in particular multicomponent semiconducting nanowires such as GaN, GaAs and non-equilibrium doping of pure NWs. The computational strategy is also useful for understanding whisker growth in several other systems, including Li-whisker growth in battery systems. &nbsp;The educational objectives were aimed at integrating the computational techniques with existing courses being taught by the PI and co-PI in their respective department, and including graduate students and postdocs in efforts to integrate research and education. In addition to dissemination efforts via publications, the outreach program was involvement of all proposal personnel (2 PIs, a postdoctoral research associate and 2 graduate students) crystal growth conference held by AACG (American Association for Crystal Growth), including organization of specialized symposia, and within the MRS chapter at NU. &nbsp;A conscious effort was made to improve the participation of the underrepresented student groups, through participation in local schools in Boston.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2017<br>      Modified by: Moneesh&nbsp;Upmanyu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828596725_TOCImage1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828596725_TOCImage1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="faceted growth"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828596725_TOCImage1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="faceted growth"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Summary slide showing the targeted focus of atomic-scale simulations. The growing tip is faceted, which has fundamentally changes the growth form</div> <div class="imageCredit">Moneesh Upmanyu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Moneesh&nbsp;Upmanyu</div> <div class="imageTitle">faceted growth</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828195013_coverArt4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828195013_coverArt4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Growing silicon whisker"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828195013_coverArt4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Growing silicon whisker"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">All-atom studies of a growing silicon whisker. Gold atoms decorate the surface. They serve to catalyze the incorporation of silicon from the vapor phase</div> <div class="imageCredit">Moneesh Upmanyu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Moneesh&nbsp;Upmanyu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Growing silicon whisker</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828354520_coverArt7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828354520_coverArt7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="growing silicon nanowire"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1106214/1106214_10119606_1507828354520_coverArt7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="growing silicon nanowire"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sideview of an Au-catalyzed growing nanowire</div> <div class="imageCredit">Moneesh Upmanyu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Moneesh&nbsp;Upmanyu</div> <div class="imageTitle">growing silicon nanowire</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The next breakthrough in fast computer chips, highly efficient battery technologies and solar cells may very well be nanoscopic whisker-shaped crystals of silicon packaged like skyscrapers on wafer-scale substrates. An important route for growth of these nanoscale whiskers, or nanowires, involves alloyed droplets. As an example, to grow silicon whiskers, an alloyed droplet of gold and silicon is exposed to a silicon-rich gas, and the droplet catalyzes the formation of silicon nanowire. The nanowire grows with the droplet at its growing tip.  The technique was developed decades ago for growing silicon "whiskers" that used a droplet of liquefied metal to trick vaporized silicon particles into solidifying into whiskers. The synthetic route is now widely used for growing nanowires for variety of technologically important materials.   The route is attractive as it potentially offers control over both morphology and chemistry during nanowire synthesis. Unfortunately, controlling the size and shape of these 1D  morphology and chemistry in these 1D crystals via this technique is challenging because the growth is affected by the surrounding interfaces - the vapor which forms and interface with the droplet surface and also the growing nanowire, and the interface between the liquid droplet and the growing tip of the crystal. Previous models have assumed that the properties of these interface do not change spatially or in time and this continues to handicap our ability to predict orientation and shape selection during growth of these nanocrystals.   Intellectual merit: In this project, we develop a fundamental understanding of the role of spatial variations in interface energetics and kinetics of VLS route for a classic system,  Au-catalyzed growth of silicon nanowires. We employ computational expertise from atomic description of these material systems, to crystal-scale description of the material and the interfaces, and study  nucleation and growth in this system. These include all-atom studies of steady-state growth of Si-nanowires to extract the overall growth form, and then extract energetics and kinetics of relevant interfaces (liquid-vapor, solid-vapor, and solid-liquid).  We build an integrated approach built around a novel crystal-scale phase field model to make connections with experimental-scale growth and identify key aspects that lead to orientation and shape selection of nanocrystal growth. Our results show that the iquid droplet surface has an ordered structure, that controls the catalytic flux of silicon into the droplet. The growing tip of crystal is faceted with several bevels that follow from crystallography. This shape lowers the barrier for growth. These collection of beveled edges serve the same purpose as the Archimedean spirals that facilitate the growth of macroscale crystals, and that is a key part of the puzzle for large-scale growth of these crystals with prescribed form  Our phase field results show that variations in interface energy control the form and extent of these facets, which in terms determine the overall growth, from growth of straight whiskers to kinked whiskers that change orientation. The kinking is also related to the growth rate of various interfaces. Variations in the energy of the solid-vapor interface (i.e. sidewalls) result in effects such as serrated growth, leading to functionally different properties of these periodically rough nanowires. Our methodology of briding atomic-scale with crystal-scale material description has the potential to capture fundamentals of the interplay between structure growth morphology, chemistry (especially dopant control) and properties (mechanical and functional), and is expected to expedite the deployment of nanoscale electronic and mechanical devices based on these nanostructures.  Broader impact: The results of our studies have broad implications as the focus on fundamental aspects of nanowire growth, as opposed to system specific aspects. The strategy developed here should allow us to develop computational model for VLS study for a wide variety of nanowires, in particular multicomponent semiconducting nanowires such as GaN, GaAs and non-equilibrium doping of pure NWs. The computational strategy is also useful for understanding whisker growth in several other systems, including Li-whisker growth in battery systems.  The educational objectives were aimed at integrating the computational techniques with existing courses being taught by the PI and co-PI in their respective department, and including graduate students and postdocs in efforts to integrate research and education. In addition to dissemination efforts via publications, the outreach program was involvement of all proposal personnel (2 PIs, a postdoctoral research associate and 2 graduate students) crystal growth conference held by AACG (American Association for Crystal Growth), including organization of specialized symposia, and within the MRS chapter at NU.  A conscious effort was made to improve the participation of the underrepresented student groups, through participation in local schools in Boston.       Last Modified: 10/12/2017       Submitted by: Moneesh Upmanyu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
