<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Combinatorial Statistics and Quantitative Social Choice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>329804.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>329804</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigator studies combinatorial, probabilistic and analytic concepts, theorems and algorithms for analyzing stochastic models coming from social choice theory, from the theory of biological networks and from theoretical computer science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal aims to provide rigorous models answering questions from molecular biology, from the theory of voting and from theoretical computer science. Some of the biologically motivated problems we study include:  Which biological networks can be reconstructed from genetic data? How can they be efficiently reconstructed? &lt;br/&gt;What genealogical relations between individuals can be recovered from their genomes in an efficient manner?  In the theory of voting the questions we address focus on minimizing the ability to manipulate voting and ranking methods and to increase their robustness against voting errors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1106999</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elchanan</FirstName>
<LastName>Mossel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elchanan Mossel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elmos@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172534382</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000429365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7552</Code>
<Text>COFFES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~251812</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~77992</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Combinatorial statistcs studies inference of networks from data. One major outcome of the project is a deep and accurate understanding of inference of large networks consisting of different communities. In particular, we proved a conjecture from physics as to the exact signal to noise ratio needed to detect the existence of different communities. Our work also results in a new algorithm for community detection that is widely applicable for network data. &nbsp;</p> <p>Other work in combinatorial statistics analyzed models of interacting agents on networks and their abilitiy to learn from each others actions. Our work answers long standing open problems from economics regarding "Bayesian Learning" on networks.&nbsp;</p> <p>In a different direction, we developed a number of new tools in the field of mathematical analysis and applied them to derive properties of voting systems. Thus our studuy of the "Gaussian Isoperimetric Problem" allows to establish strong optimality of majority vote in an election between two alternatives. On the other hand, our results that "standard simplices are not most stable" provide a very strong indication that plurality vote is not an optimal voting method in elections involving 3 or more alternatives.&nbsp;</p> <p>Further results in analysis, elaborating on the notion of reverse hyper-contraction, allow to prove very general versions of two of major results in economics regarding voting schemes, i.e., Arrow impossability theorem and the Gibbard-Satterhwaite theorem.&nbsp;</p> <p>All of our work was carried out with collaborators, post-doctoral fellows and graduate students who were partially supported by the grant in their professional development.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2015<br>      Modified by: Elchanan&nbsp;Mossel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Combinatorial statistcs studies inference of networks from data. One major outcome of the project is a deep and accurate understanding of inference of large networks consisting of different communities. In particular, we proved a conjecture from physics as to the exact signal to noise ratio needed to detect the existence of different communities. Our work also results in a new algorithm for community detection that is widely applicable for network data.    Other work in combinatorial statistics analyzed models of interacting agents on networks and their abilitiy to learn from each others actions. Our work answers long standing open problems from economics regarding "Bayesian Learning" on networks.   In a different direction, we developed a number of new tools in the field of mathematical analysis and applied them to derive properties of voting systems. Thus our studuy of the "Gaussian Isoperimetric Problem" allows to establish strong optimality of majority vote in an election between two alternatives. On the other hand, our results that "standard simplices are not most stable" provide a very strong indication that plurality vote is not an optimal voting method in elections involving 3 or more alternatives.   Further results in analysis, elaborating on the notion of reverse hyper-contraction, allow to prove very general versions of two of major results in economics regarding voting schemes, i.e., Arrow impossability theorem and the Gibbard-Satterhwaite theorem.   All of our work was carried out with collaborators, post-doctoral fellows and graduate students who were partially supported by the grant in their professional development.        Last Modified: 10/12/2015       Submitted by: Elchanan Mossel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
