<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Large-scale structure in complex networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>320000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>320000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lora Billings</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigator and his colleagues study the large-scale structure of real-world networks, such as social, biological, and information networks.  Several specific projects will be undertaken.  The first will focus on the classic problem of community detection in networks and the development of compact objective functions for assessing community quality and effective strategies for their optimization.  The methods proposed improve on previous ones in being rigorously motivated, utilizing as much as possible of the information stored in a network, and avoiding some of the pitfalls of previous approaches, such as resolution limits.  A second project will develop methods for general structural inference in networks based on a combination of expectation--maximization (EM) algorithms with Monte Carlo and belief propagation methods.  A particular strength of these approaches is that, because they optimize marginal probabilities, they have the potential to avoid overfitting and offer strategies for solving model selection problems.  Several further projects focus on the extension of these techniques to more complex forms of network structure, including overlapping vertex classes, hierarchical structure, and dependence on general classes of hidden variables.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many systems of scientific interest can be represented as networks, from the Internet to biological networks to social networks.  In the last decade copious amounts of network data have become available in different fields, but in many cases these data are dense and bewildering, presenting a substantial challenge to the user trying to make sense of their structure.  The fundamental question addressed in this research is how we can gain new understanding about physical, biological, and social systems from their network structure.  For instance, the investigator and his collaborators will develop methods for detecting groups of closely interacting nodes in networks, such as cliques of individuals in social networks, or groups of related web sites on the web.  They will also tackle general questions of using network structure to deduce unknown properties of network nodes.  If, for instance, there are several different types of nodes in a network, such as classes of chemicals in a metabolic network in the cell, how can we identify the types from network structure alone, without measuring them directly (which may be difficult or costly)?  The funded research will create a range of mathematical tools that can be applied to problems in this area.  The methods to be developed have a number of possible applications, including new techniques to aid researchers working on biological and social networks, commercial applications in online social networks, and software applications in data visualization and automatic data summarization, among others.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1107796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Newman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Newman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mejn@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347644223</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180261</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7478</Code>
<Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~320000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many scientific and technological systems can be represented as networks: the internet and the world wide web, roads, rail, and airline routes, communications networks, pipelines, biological or biochemical networks, and social networks, including their online incarnations.&nbsp; The work performed under this grant involved the development of new mathematical methods to describe and analyze such networks, and computer algorithms based on this mathematics.&nbsp; In the context of intellectual merits of the research, a particular focus has been on methods for finding communities or modules within networks -- densely connected cliques or groups of nodes within the larger structure.&nbsp; Community finding is a crucial step in understanding the structure of large networks, sometimes with millions of nodes or more, by allowing us to break them down into their component parts which can then be analyzed separately.&nbsp; Under this funding the investigators developed a range of new computational methods for tackling the community finding problem, as well as a greater understanding of when and why these methods do or do not work.&nbsp; One end product has been new computer software that can analyze the structure of large network data sets accurately and rapidly, including data derived from industry, biomedical research, and other sectors.<br /><br />In addition to community structure, the funded work also examined a range of other features of networks including core-periphery divisions between the central and outlying nodes in a network, ranking or hierarchy in networks, so-called percolation properties which quantify a network's resilience to failure or removal of its nodes, and geometric structure in networks whereby the positions of nodes in space can affect their connectivity patterns.&nbsp; The investigators also developed mathematical tools and methods to broaden the range of network data that can be analyzed, particularly focusing on annotated data in which we are told not only the structure of a network but also some information about the characteristics of its nodes, such as the sizes of organisms in a network of species interactions or the locations of neurons in the brain.&nbsp; Another focus has been on methods for the analysis of uncertain network data.&nbsp; For many of the networks studied our knowledge of them is incomplete or may contain inaccurate measurements, and methods developed under this funding allow us to extract useful information even in these cases where the data are imperfect.<br /><br />In addition to the intellectual merits of the research described above, in terms of new mathematics and the development of novel computer methods, the work performed under this funding has substantial benefits to society in the form of potential applications of the methods in a broad range of disciplines in science, medicine, technology, and industry.&nbsp; With the increasing amounts of data gathered online and elsewhere, much of which can be viewed in the form of networks, there is rapidly growing interest in developing and applying network analysis tools to improve our understanding of data sets including biomedical data, online data, and other data from business and industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/26/2016<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Newman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many scientific and technological systems can be represented as networks: the internet and the world wide web, roads, rail, and airline routes, communications networks, pipelines, biological or biochemical networks, and social networks, including their online incarnations.  The work performed under this grant involved the development of new mathematical methods to describe and analyze such networks, and computer algorithms based on this mathematics.  In the context of intellectual merits of the research, a particular focus has been on methods for finding communities or modules within networks -- densely connected cliques or groups of nodes within the larger structure.  Community finding is a crucial step in understanding the structure of large networks, sometimes with millions of nodes or more, by allowing us to break them down into their component parts which can then be analyzed separately.  Under this funding the investigators developed a range of new computational methods for tackling the community finding problem, as well as a greater understanding of when and why these methods do or do not work.  One end product has been new computer software that can analyze the structure of large network data sets accurately and rapidly, including data derived from industry, biomedical research, and other sectors.  In addition to community structure, the funded work also examined a range of other features of networks including core-periphery divisions between the central and outlying nodes in a network, ranking or hierarchy in networks, so-called percolation properties which quantify a network's resilience to failure or removal of its nodes, and geometric structure in networks whereby the positions of nodes in space can affect their connectivity patterns.  The investigators also developed mathematical tools and methods to broaden the range of network data that can be analyzed, particularly focusing on annotated data in which we are told not only the structure of a network but also some information about the characteristics of its nodes, such as the sizes of organisms in a network of species interactions or the locations of neurons in the brain.  Another focus has been on methods for the analysis of uncertain network data.  For many of the networks studied our knowledge of them is incomplete or may contain inaccurate measurements, and methods developed under this funding allow us to extract useful information even in these cases where the data are imperfect.  In addition to the intellectual merits of the research described above, in terms of new mathematics and the development of novel computer methods, the work performed under this funding has substantial benefits to society in the form of potential applications of the methods in a broad range of disciplines in science, medicine, technology, and industry.  With the increasing amounts of data gathered online and elsewhere, much of which can be viewed in the form of networks, there is rapidly growing interest in developing and applying network analysis tools to improve our understanding of data sets including biomedical data, online data, and other data from business and industry.          Last Modified: 08/26/2016       Submitted by: Mark Newman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
