<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Do Holocene Variations In Arctic Sea Ice And Greenland Icebergs Drifting Through Denmark Strait Reflect Natural Cycles?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>432925.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>432925</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William J. Wiseman, Jr.</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Historical observations and theory suggest the importance of the extent and duration of&lt;br/&gt;drift ice on the Climate System through changes in the Hemispheric albedo and the impact of freshwater export from the Arctic Ocean and Greenland Ice Sheet on the Thermohaline Circulation. Funds are provided to develop 50-100 yr resolution records of changes in sea ice export from the Arctic Ocean and iceberg transport from tidewater ice streams of NE Greenland that reach the Denmark Strait and to develop a detailed history of ice-rafted debris (IRD) over the last 12,000 cal yr BP. Denmark Strait is believed to be a critical area for study as it lies at the boundary between the southward export of Polar and Arctic waters and the northwestern limb of the North Atlantic Drift in the form of the Irminger Current. The research will explore a sources-to-sink model along the ENE/E Greenland shelf and across the Denmark Strait using sediment characteristics to document spatial and temporal changes in composition in a series of well-dated, high-resolution cores from either side of the Denmark Strait and along the NE Greenland shelf. This information will be used to infer changes in the transport of sea ice through the Denmark Strait.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the ongoing observations of changing sea ice character in the Arctic, changes in the flux of sea ice into the Greenland-Norwegian Seas and the North Atlantic Ocean, and possible acceleration of ice loss from the Greenland Ice Sheet through iceberg calving, a better understanding of how these processes varied in the past will help inform projections of future climate variations.  This project will develop data sets that contribute to that understanding.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1107942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>Darby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis A Darby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ddarby@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576834701</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 204]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077945947</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Old Dominion University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235290001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5115 Hampton Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~432925</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major outcomes of this project are:</p> <p>1. There is cyclic iceberg production from east Greenland throughout the last 10,000 years. &nbsp;Several cycles are found to be statitically significant; ~200, ~300, 500, and 800 years.</p> <p>2. These cycles are based on precise source determination of the chemical fingerprint of ice-rafted Fe oxide grains in a core on the south Greenland shelf and another on the west Iceland shelf, demonstrating the effectiveness of this provenance tool.</p> <p>3. The cyclic peaks in Fe grains from east Greenland in these cores are approximately double the background levels and multiple sources from Greenland are in sync with each other as well as with peaks of Fe grains from the coastal areas of the Arctic Ocean. &nbsp;This suggests a climatic forcing of these cycles.</p> <p>4. While these increases in ice-rafted detritus from east Greenland might not in themselves amount to more than a few millimeters of sea level rise in a decade, theur coincidence with melting due to global warming in recent decades could add to the already rapid increase in sea level.</p> <p>5. The past sea surface maximum temperature in the south Greenland core was compared to the Fe grain cycles and no correlation is present (R<sup>2</sup>&nbsp;= -0.15). &nbsp;This suggests that increased melting at the core site was not the primary cause of the cycles. &nbsp;</p> <p>There is no obvious climatic variable except solar insolation fluctuations that share similar cycles as found in the two cores for these Fe grains ice-rafted from several sources that are thousands of kilometers apart.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Dennis&nbsp;A&nbsp;Darby</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1107942/1107942_10111085_1475514315313_Fig1DarbyAndrew--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1107942/1107942_10111085_1475514315313_Fig1DarbyAndrew--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Map of source areas and cores studied."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1107942/1107942_10111085_1475514315313_Fig1DarbyAndrew--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Map of source areas and cores studied."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The numbered source areas 42 and 43 on east Greenland are the primary sources for cores 2322 and 2263 from south Greenland and Iceland, respectively.  The circled source areas in the coastal Arctic Ocean are sources that contribute significant numbers of ice-rafted Fe grains in both of these cores.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Darby et al., Cyclic ice-rafted debris from the East Greenland Ice Sheet during the Holocene. in preparation.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dennis&nbsp;A&nbsp;Darby</div> <div class="imageTitle">Map of source areas and cores studied.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1107942/1107942_10111085_1475515049972_Fig2RDarbyJennings--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1107942/1107942_10111085_1475515049972_Fig2RDarbyJennings--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ice-rafted Fe grain numbers in core 2322."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1107942/1107942_10111085_1475515049972_Fig2RDarbyJennings--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ice-rafted Fe grain numbers in core 2322."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The number of ice-rafted Fe grains in core 2322 off southern Greenland are shown for the dominant sources (42=east Greenland, 43 southeast Greenland, and 8 for Banks Island in the Arctic). The coarse fraction  or ice-rafted detritus is show as well.  Trends in all show a decrease around 6ka.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Darby et al., Cyclic ice-rafted debris from the East Greenland Ice Sheet during the Holocene. in prep.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dennis&nbsp;A&nbsp;Darby</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ice-rafted Fe grain numbers in core 2322.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major outcomes of this project are:  1. There is cyclic iceberg production from east Greenland throughout the last 10,000 years.  Several cycles are found to be statitically significant; ~200, ~300, 500, and 800 years.  2. These cycles are based on precise source determination of the chemical fingerprint of ice-rafted Fe oxide grains in a core on the south Greenland shelf and another on the west Iceland shelf, demonstrating the effectiveness of this provenance tool.  3. The cyclic peaks in Fe grains from east Greenland in these cores are approximately double the background levels and multiple sources from Greenland are in sync with each other as well as with peaks of Fe grains from the coastal areas of the Arctic Ocean.  This suggests a climatic forcing of these cycles.  4. While these increases in ice-rafted detritus from east Greenland might not in themselves amount to more than a few millimeters of sea level rise in a decade, theur coincidence with melting due to global warming in recent decades could add to the already rapid increase in sea level.  5. The past sea surface maximum temperature in the south Greenland core was compared to the Fe grain cycles and no correlation is present (R2 = -0.15).  This suggests that increased melting at the core site was not the primary cause of the cycles.    There is no obvious climatic variable except solar insolation fluctuations that share similar cycles as found in the two cores for these Fe grains ice-rafted from several sources that are thousands of kilometers apart.          Last Modified: 10/03/2016       Submitted by: Dennis A Darby]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
