<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Problems of Nonlinear Control</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lora Billings</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The P.I. will study problems in the area of nonlinear control and differential games.  A major focus of the research on differential games will be on Stackelberg solutions in feedback form, and on  Nash equilibrium solutions in infinite time horizon.  Here the main goal is to extend the theory available in linear-quadratic case, studying  more general nonlinear models with robustness properties.   A second main area of research is the control of set-valued evolutions. Models will be considered where the growth of a set can be influenced by a distributed control, or restrained by constructing barriers in real time.  In particular, the P.I. and a collaborator will study in which cases the set can be rendered uniformly bounded for all times, and which are the optimal confinement strategies.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary motivation for the research on differential games  comes from economics. In a typical model that will be considered, the leading player--say, a government, or a central bank--announces its policy in advance, while a subordinate player--say, a private  company--chooses its strategy as a best reply, in order to maximize its own profit.  If the policy to be implemented makes reference to specific parameters that will be observed in the future, such as inflation or unemployment rates, determining the optimal choice for the leading player  leads to challenging mathematical problems.  These will be investigated within the present research.   As a further direction, the study of dynamic blocking problems is motivated by models describing the spatial  spreading of a forest fire, or of a chemical contamination.  The optimal allocation of resources, in the containment effort, poses novel mathematical questions which will also be  addressed by the present project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1108702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Bressan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto Bressan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bressan@math.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651667</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~275000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div>This research was focused on optimal decision problems.&nbsp;Such problems arise in many practical situations, whenever&nbsp;an agent must decide on a best course of action in order to &nbsp;minimize his total cost &nbsp;(or maximize his payoff) over a period of time. As a closely related topic, the PI also studied non-cooperative games,&nbsp;where each player seeks a strategy that maximizes his own payoff&nbsp;in reply to the actions taken by the other players.</div> <p>The first part of the research yielded some new contributions to the basic mathematical theory. &nbsp; In a second stage, the PI developed two specific applications, which will be described here.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><br />I) Shape of the limit order book, in a stock market.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />In mathematical terms, this ``game" models a situation where several competing&nbsp;agents offer for sale various quantities of a&nbsp;given asset, at different prices. An external buyer asks for a random amount X &nbsp;of the asset. This amount will be bought at the lowest available price, as long as this price does not exceed a given upper bound P (see Figure 1).&nbsp;Having observed the prices asked by his competitors, each seller must determine an optimal pricing strategy, maximizing his expected payoff.&nbsp;Clearly, a seller who asks a higher price increases the profit achieved by the sale, but reduces the probability that his asset will actually be sold.&nbsp;&nbsp;If all players adopt optimal strategies, a key question is: what will be the shape of the limit order book? &nbsp;In other words, can one predict how many assets will be offered at the various prices,&nbsp;as a result from the competition among sellers? &nbsp;</p> <p><br />The analysis of this model has shown that the shape of the limit order book depends on three factors:<br />- the total amount of assets put on sale by the various sellers<br />- the maximum price P that the buyer is willing to pay<br />- the probability distribution that the agents assign to the random variable X, i.e. their expectations on the amount that will actually be bought.&nbsp;</p> <p>More general cases have also been studied, where (i) the maximum price P which is acceptable to the buyer is not known a priori, or (ii)<br />sellers have different beliefs. &nbsp;For example, an optimistic seller will&nbsp;expect a large buying order, while a pessimistic seller&nbsp;one will expect a much smaller one.</p> <p>Optimal pricing strategies have been determined &nbsp;by means of explicit formulas, or by computational algorithms. &nbsp;Numerical experiments have also been performed, examining how&nbsp;the sellers may change their strategies over time, until an equilibrium is reached.<br /><br /><br />II) &nbsp;Optimal debt management, in the presence of a bankruptcy risk.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>This project dealt with the common situation where &nbsp;an individual, or a country, need to repay a debt. &nbsp;This was modeled as a game between a borrower and a pool of lenders.&nbsp;The debtor must decide what portion u(t) of his yearly income will be allocated to servicing the debt, at each future time &nbsp;t.&nbsp;<br />A bankruptcy risk is present, which grows with the size of the debt.</p> <p>The main new feature of this model is that the interest rate is decided by the lenders, depending on the probability of losing their investment as a result of bankruptcy. &nbsp;In a way, this reflects the credit rating of the debtor, based on the strategy he follows for the entire future.</p> <p>Unlike standard problems in optimal control, solutions of the dynamical equations can be non-unique. For the same debt repayment plan, &nbsp;if lenders regard their investment as being risky, they will charge a high interest rate. This will push up the chances of bankruptcy making high risk a reality. On the other hand, a widespread belief that the investment is safe will result in a lower int...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This research was focused on optimal decision problems. Such problems arise in many practical situations, whenever an agent must decide on a best course of action in order to  minimize his total cost  (or maximize his payoff) over a period of time. As a closely related topic, the PI also studied non-cooperative games, where each player seeks a strategy that maximizes his own payoff in reply to the actions taken by the other players.  The first part of the research yielded some new contributions to the basic mathematical theory.   In a second stage, the PI developed two specific applications, which will be described here.      I) Shape of the limit order book, in a stock market.    In mathematical terms, this ``game" models a situation where several competing agents offer for sale various quantities of a given asset, at different prices. An external buyer asks for a random amount X  of the asset. This amount will be bought at the lowest available price, as long as this price does not exceed a given upper bound P (see Figure 1). Having observed the prices asked by his competitors, each seller must determine an optimal pricing strategy, maximizing his expected payoff. Clearly, a seller who asks a higher price increases the profit achieved by the sale, but reduces the probability that his asset will actually be sold.  If all players adopt optimal strategies, a key question is: what will be the shape of the limit order book?  In other words, can one predict how many assets will be offered at the various prices, as a result from the competition among sellers?     The analysis of this model has shown that the shape of the limit order book depends on three factors: - the total amount of assets put on sale by the various sellers - the maximum price P that the buyer is willing to pay - the probability distribution that the agents assign to the random variable X, i.e. their expectations on the amount that will actually be bought.   More general cases have also been studied, where (i) the maximum price P which is acceptable to the buyer is not known a priori, or (ii) sellers have different beliefs.  For example, an optimistic seller will expect a large buying order, while a pessimistic seller one will expect a much smaller one.  Optimal pricing strategies have been determined  by means of explicit formulas, or by computational algorithms.  Numerical experiments have also been performed, examining how the sellers may change their strategies over time, until an equilibrium is reached.   II)  Optimal debt management, in the presence of a bankruptcy risk.     This project dealt with the common situation where  an individual, or a country, need to repay a debt.  This was modeled as a game between a borrower and a pool of lenders. The debtor must decide what portion u(t) of his yearly income will be allocated to servicing the debt, at each future time  t.  A bankruptcy risk is present, which grows with the size of the debt.  The main new feature of this model is that the interest rate is decided by the lenders, depending on the probability of losing their investment as a result of bankruptcy.  In a way, this reflects the credit rating of the debtor, based on the strategy he follows for the entire future.  Unlike standard problems in optimal control, solutions of the dynamical equations can be non-unique. For the same debt repayment plan,  if lenders regard their investment as being risky, they will charge a high interest rate. This will push up the chances of bankruptcy making high risk a reality. On the other hand, a widespread belief that the investment is safe will result in a lower interest rate, thus reducing the actual chances of bankruptcy.  On the other hand, thanks to a monotonicity property of the system of differential equations, the analysis has also shown that a unique "minimal" solution can be singled out. This solution is the most advantageous for the borrower, providing a pointwise minimum to the size of his debt.    Assuming th...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
