<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:Synthesis of the Lanthanide metal organic frameworks for thermodynamic analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1108267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hughes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James T Hughes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5104491614</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000575307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hughes                  James          T</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956162826</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hughes                  James          T]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956162826</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~5700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Synthesis of Novel Lanthanide Metal-Organic Frameworks for Thermodynamic Analysis</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>East Asian Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI)</p> <p>June 10<sup>th</sup> &ndash; August 7<sup>th</sup> 2011</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Principle Investigator:<strong> </strong><strong>James T. Hughes</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Peter A. Rock Thermochemistry Laboratory</p> <p>Department of Chemistry</p> <p>University of California at Davis</p> <p>Davis, CA 95616, United States</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><br /></strong></p> <p>Host Advisor:<strong> </strong><strong>Professor Wen-Hua Sun</strong>, FRSC<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Institute of Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Science</p> <p>Beijing, P.R. China</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Background</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Over the six weeks research at the Institute of Chemistry Chinese Academy of Science, in Beijing Peoples Republic of China (ICCAS). Over 100 of solvothermal reactions on two different metal-organic framework (MOF) systems were performed. This resulted in the synthesis of the first isostructural lanthanide MOF series to date. The MOF construction based on combining bidentate organic &ldquo;linker&rdquo; molecules with &ldquo;hub&rdquo; atoms, in this case lanthanide metals. Each hub in these structures contains two lanthanide metal atoms that bind four adjacent linkers creating a 3D array that is analogous to a tinker toy structure. Where sticks and joints combine to form a rigid superstructure yet contains immense void space within the framework. The linker molecules chosen were 1,4 benzene dicarboxylic acid (1,4-BDC) and 3,5-pyridine dicarboxylate (3,5-PYDC)&nbsp;comprised the two MOF systems selected. These organic molecules were combined with the nitrate salts of all the entire lanthanide series with the exception of Promethium.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Understanding the material properties of the lanthanides hybrid material is an important chemical and material science concern. As such materials are analogous to materials found in radioactive storage processes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Synthesis of lanthanide frameworks from 1,4-BDC resulted in an two separate iso-crystalline structure. The first polymorph, which shows the highest crystallinity, uses the atoms Y, and Sm to Lu, to create a rigid 3D framework. The second iso-crystalline phase, spanning the atoms from La to Nd, created a yet to be identified phase. These structural series follows a well known trend of the lanthanide metals as the former framework being constructed of the atoms contained in the <em>yttria</em> subgroup; the latter phase is comprised of atoms found the <em>ceria</em> subgroup. These subgroups are due to similar atomic size of the metal cations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As a result in the interest time, efforts were shifted to scaling up the successful 1,4-BDC based reaction. Making it possible to obtain high quality material required for thermodynamic analysis. I was able to return to UC Davis with plenty of material for proper analysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Cultural and Educational Experiences</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>I made several close friendships with my lab mates during my summer at the ICCAS. My work scheduled followed theirs: Monday to Saturday 8 am to 10 pm, I had the chance to spend at least 80 hours a week working in close proximity with my lab mates. Every Sunday several students and myself would tour Beijing, seeing local sites, eating out and shopping, if nothing else. Overall I was pleased that during my two months in China I never rested, I spent most days with my lab mates. As they worked very hard they spend a lot of time together. I enjoyed these new friendships and cultural immersion my environment presented immensely. Despite working in my home labo...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Synthesis of Novel Lanthanide Metal-Organic Frameworks for Thermodynamic Analysis     East Asian Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI)  June 10th &ndash; August 7th 2011     Principle Investigator: James T. Hughes   Peter A. Rock Thermochemistry Laboratory  Department of Chemistry  University of California at Davis  Davis, CA 95616, United States        Host Advisor: Professor Wen-Hua Sun, FRSC   Institute of Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Science  Beijing, P.R. China     Background   Over the six weeks research at the Institute of Chemistry Chinese Academy of Science, in Beijing Peoples Republic of China (ICCAS). Over 100 of solvothermal reactions on two different metal-organic framework (MOF) systems were performed. This resulted in the synthesis of the first isostructural lanthanide MOF series to date. The MOF construction based on combining bidentate organic "linker" molecules with "hub" atoms, in this case lanthanide metals. Each hub in these structures contains two lanthanide metal atoms that bind four adjacent linkers creating a 3D array that is analogous to a tinker toy structure. Where sticks and joints combine to form a rigid superstructure yet contains immense void space within the framework. The linker molecules chosen were 1,4 benzene dicarboxylic acid (1,4-BDC) and 3,5-pyridine dicarboxylate (3,5-PYDC) comprised the two MOF systems selected. These organic molecules were combined with the nitrate salts of all the entire lanthanide series with the exception of Promethium.     Summary   Understanding the material properties of the lanthanides hybrid material is an important chemical and material science concern. As such materials are analogous to materials found in radioactive storage processes.     Synthesis of lanthanide frameworks from 1,4-BDC resulted in an two separate iso-crystalline structure. The first polymorph, which shows the highest crystallinity, uses the atoms Y, and Sm to Lu, to create a rigid 3D framework. The second iso-crystalline phase, spanning the atoms from La to Nd, created a yet to be identified phase. These structural series follows a well known trend of the lanthanide metals as the former framework being constructed of the atoms contained in the yttria subgroup; the latter phase is comprised of atoms found the ceria subgroup. These subgroups are due to similar atomic size of the metal cations.     As a result in the interest time, efforts were shifted to scaling up the successful 1,4-BDC based reaction. Making it possible to obtain high quality material required for thermodynamic analysis. I was able to return to UC Davis with plenty of material for proper analysis.        Cultural and Educational Experiences   I made several close friendships with my lab mates during my summer at the ICCAS. My work scheduled followed theirs: Monday to Saturday 8 am to 10 pm, I had the chance to spend at least 80 hours a week working in close proximity with my lab mates. Every Sunday several students and myself would tour Beijing, seeing local sites, eating out and shopping, if nothing else. Overall I was pleased that during my two months in China I never rested, I spent most days with my lab mates. As they worked very hard they spend a lot of time together. I enjoyed these new friendships and cultural immersion my environment presented immensely. Despite working in my home laboratory, of which about ~40% originate from Asian countriesÆ, living in Beijing was a totally unique experience that cannot be aptly understood unless one is there. There were so many unique events during my time there, some great, some unpleasant but overall I felt grateful to have the opportunity to observe a day to day life from a different point of view, yet still be productive. I found having an open mind was crucial, as many customs and behaviors are different or can seem strange, as one may expect. Though this does beg the question "what is it that Americans do that is weird?". Seeing a how other humans go through life lets one real...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
