<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: A proposed wastewater biological treatment/recycling unit for island communities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1108578</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Irvine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua L Irvine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8087728957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000576645</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Irvine                  Joshua         L</Name>
<CityName>Waianae</CityName>
<ZipCode>967921826</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Irvine                  Joshua         L]]></Name>
<CityName>Waianae</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>967921826</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~5700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>At the National Science Foundation pre-departure orientation, I fondly recall being asked: &ldquo;Please, introduce yourself: who you are, where you are from, why Taiwan and what are your expectations.&rdquo; I still believe that <a href="http://eng.taiwan.net.tw/" target="_blank">Taiwan</a> chose me--not the other way around.</p> <p>An island shaped like a bean-pod, the People&rsquo;s Republic of China (Taiwan) is more or less 100 miles east of the Republic of China, mainland Asia. The <a href="http://www.nsf.gov/" target="_blank">U.S. National Science Foundation</a> and the <a href="http://web1.nsc.gov.tw/" target="_blank">National Science Council</a> of Taiwan partnered to fund 25 U.S. graduate students for 8-weeks to Taiwan. The intent is to foster international collaborations in science and engineering as well as an orientation to the peoples, society, languages, and cultures of this region. The program is called: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=5284" target="_blank">East Asian and Pacific Summer Institute</a>.</p> <p>By training, I am a student of wastewater engineering from the <a href="http://hawaii.edu/" target="_blank">University of Hawaii at Manoa</a>.</p> <p>One major challenge for island populations is to supply sufficient, usable water to consumers. In particular, Ko Hawaii Pae aina (Hawaiian Islands), Samoa Amelika (American Samoa), Gu&aring;h&aring;n (Guam), Taiwan, the Pacific Islands and other land limited regions will show a growing demand to manage water resources effectively.</p> <p>Continued growth and sustained climate change will have an impact on the availability of freshwater with significant implications to local economy and resources. Recently in 2011, the island of <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-15147043" target="_blank">Tokelau </a>and neighboring Tuvalu have declared states of emergency of &lsquo;severe&rsquo; water shortages.</p> <p>A key challenge to tackle water availability at a community level is to design, develop and implement innovative technological approaches to restore impaired waters to a usable state.</p> <p>One way to augment water scarcity is to extract water from non-traditional sources, most notably seawater and grey-water.</p> <p>Grey-water is the leftover wastewater from daily human water consumption and discharge. The main difference between greywater and sewage water is that greywater contains no fecal materials. There has been much progress in Asia in acceptance and implementation of initiatives in grey-water recycling.</p> <p>All of Taiwan was my research experience. My Host Professor, Dr. C. F. Lin, allowed me to engage with his graduate students from the <a href="http://www.ntu.edu.tw/engv4/" target="_blank">National Taiwan University</a> (NTU) located in the heart of Taipei City. I work alongside them doing terrific research work in integrating membrane and biological treatment systems of grey-water for island communities. Partnering with Dr. Lin&rsquo;s group was a perfect fit because they had the expertise in membrane filter technology. Our lab group at the University of Hawaii at Manoa specializes in biological wastewater treatment where microorganisms are used to metabolize and treat wastewater.</p> <p>At NTU, I tested an in-house treatment process scheme for grey-water recycling by blending each lab group&rsquo;s specialty. Artificial grey-water was prepared daily and fed into the set-up, a two-staged system. The treated water from the first-stage biological unit was fed into the membrane. Water samples were collected and analyzed to determine treatment effectiveness.</p> <p>To have meaningful research results in less than 7-weeks, my study was a proof-of-concept of our designed grey-water recycling system. The summer work has laid the foundation in my skills for a more rigorous, long-term study.</p> <p>Outside of the lab, Dr. Lin introduced me to key indiv...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ At the National Science Foundation pre-departure orientation, I fondly recall being asked: "Please, introduce yourself: who you are, where you are from, why Taiwan and what are your expectations." I still believe that Taiwan chose me--not the other way around.  An island shaped like a bean-pod, the PeopleÆs Republic of China (Taiwan) is more or less 100 miles east of the Republic of China, mainland Asia. The U.S. National Science Foundation and the National Science Council of Taiwan partnered to fund 25 U.S. graduate students for 8-weeks to Taiwan. The intent is to foster international collaborations in science and engineering as well as an orientation to the peoples, society, languages, and cultures of this region. The program is called: East Asian and Pacific Summer Institute.  By training, I am a student of wastewater engineering from the University of Hawaii at Manoa.  One major challenge for island populations is to supply sufficient, usable water to consumers. In particular, Ko Hawaii Pae aina (Hawaiian Islands), Samoa Amelika (American Samoa), Gu&aring;h&aring;n (Guam), Taiwan, the Pacific Islands and other land limited regions will show a growing demand to manage water resources effectively.  Continued growth and sustained climate change will have an impact on the availability of freshwater with significant implications to local economy and resources. Recently in 2011, the island of Tokelau and neighboring Tuvalu have declared states of emergency of æsevereÆ water shortages.  A key challenge to tackle water availability at a community level is to design, develop and implement innovative technological approaches to restore impaired waters to a usable state.  One way to augment water scarcity is to extract water from non-traditional sources, most notably seawater and grey-water.  Grey-water is the leftover wastewater from daily human water consumption and discharge. The main difference between greywater and sewage water is that greywater contains no fecal materials. There has been much progress in Asia in acceptance and implementation of initiatives in grey-water recycling.  All of Taiwan was my research experience. My Host Professor, Dr. C. F. Lin, allowed me to engage with his graduate students from the National Taiwan University (NTU) located in the heart of Taipei City. I work alongside them doing terrific research work in integrating membrane and biological treatment systems of grey-water for island communities. Partnering with Dr. LinÆs group was a perfect fit because they had the expertise in membrane filter technology. Our lab group at the University of Hawaii at Manoa specializes in biological wastewater treatment where microorganisms are used to metabolize and treat wastewater.  At NTU, I tested an in-house treatment process scheme for grey-water recycling by blending each lab groupÆs specialty. Artificial grey-water was prepared daily and fed into the set-up, a two-staged system. The treated water from the first-stage biological unit was fed into the membrane. Water samples were collected and analyzed to determine treatment effectiveness.  To have meaningful research results in less than 7-weeks, my study was a proof-of-concept of our designed grey-water recycling system. The summer work has laid the foundation in my skills for a more rigorous, long-term study.  Outside of the lab, Dr. Lin introduced me to key individuals from academia and government in the water/wastewater resource management field. His graduate students were my guides to the city. The excellent metro system allowed us along with fellow EAPSI participants to explore the many nooks-and-crannies of a vibrant metropolis. LetÆs not forget the æbroke the mouthÆ cuisine&mdash;how we describe delicious food in Hawaii.    I have been fortunate to have work, eat, laugh, and pray in Ilha Formasa, the beautiful island of Taiwan. From this experience, I have a greater insight and glimpse of how life works on another island group far from mine; and aspir...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
