<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Microstructural Design for Enhanced Efficiency in Solid State Energy Conversion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>426000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gary Shiflet</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A collaboration between Texas A&amp;M University and Shanghai Jiao Tong University, China, investigates the microstructural design of magnetic shape memory alloys (MSMAs) tailored for highly efficient energy conversion.  The thermoelastic coupling inherent in these materials provides a route to considerable energy-saving devices based on harvesting of otherwise wasted mechanical work. With the addition of magnetic and electronic couplings, MSMAs as multicaloric materials offer many possibilities for conversion into useful forms of energy. It has also recently been shown that the thermo-elastic process can be harnessed for refrigeration, with large theoretical efficiency gain as compared to current technology. The researchers implement a comprehensive program to study the magneto-thermo-mechanical coupling in MSMAs. The US team collaborates with the Chinese group to fabricate materials with a wide range of controlled microstructures and orientations (single crystals, bi-crystals, controlled texture) and characterize the magneto-thermo-mechanical behavior as a function of processing parameters and microstructural features related to grain size, particle size, volume fraction, morphology, and texture. This is paired with a detailed characterization of the magnetic structure and its coupling to the microstructure. The overall goal is to overcome current material shortcomings, e.g., reduce the transformation hysteresis, increase the toughness, and improve the actuation stress. An important practical target is to achieve inexpensive MSMAs based on controlled solidification and microstructure design, thus providing a highly efficient platform for energy conversion applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research not only advances the fundamental understanding of the multi-functional alloys, but highly efficient MSMAs can potentially revolutionize the field of solid-state cooling. Education benefits include the participation of US students in the international research activities at Shanghai Jiao Tong University, one of the leading materials research universities in China, as well as the establishment of a joint degree program between Texas A&amp;M and Shanghai Jiao Tong universities. The work of the Chinese investigators is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1108396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Ross, Jr.</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph H Ross, Jr.</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhross@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798453842</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ibrahim</FirstName>
<LastName>Karaman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ibrahim Karaman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ikaraman@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798623923</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000310022</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~210000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~146000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>"Materials World Network: Microstructural Design for Enhanced Efficiency in Solid State Energy Conversion" brought together experts from Texas A&amp;M University, Shanghai Jiao-Tong University (China), and Ningbo Institute (China) to develop new alloys and processing techniques for tunable efficient energy conversion devices. The focus is the alloys known as Magnetic Shape Memory Alloys (MSMAs), having a reversible crystal structure change coupled to a change of magnetic state, which can be engineered so that this sudden state change can provide energy or heat needed for next generation solid state cooling or energy recovery devices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Traditional Shape Memory Alloys, sometimes called Memory Metals, can be configured to return to their original shape when heated. When the crystal structure change responsible for this process (termed a martensitic transformation) is made to coincide with a change of magnetic state, the resulting MSMAs can exhibit large magnetic-field induced heating and cooling, known as the magnetocaloric effect (MCE), and an analogous effect induced by physical stress, the elastocaloric effect (ECE). The materials used for MCE are commonly based on rare earth metals, which are expensive and scarce. However the development of effective materials based on MSMA-type alloys holds great promise for developing new practical devices. This project combined the expertise of the Texas A&amp;M University team, led by Profs. Joseph Ross and Ibrahim Karaman, with extensive facilities for characterization, testing, and processing of these materials, with the Shanghai Jiao-Tong University team, led by Prof. Jianguo Li, with unique facilities for the specialized fabrication, for example of aligned polycrystals (containing crystallites with aligned orientations). Fig. 1 shows two of the Texas A&amp;M Ph.D. student team members Nickolaus Bruno and James Monroe explaining project results, while fig. 2 shows Bruno along with Ph.D. student Jing-Han Chen in the laboratory with visiting scientists Baris Emre and Suheyla Yuce, also working on the project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Among the results, work spearheaded by Bruno and his advisor Karaman recently demonstrated that NiCoMnSn-based alloy ribbons not only produce a similar MCE compared to the above-mentioned rare earth compounds, but the operating temperature, refrigeration capacity, and efficiency can be optimized by modifying the microstructure and stoichiometry [N. M. Bruno et al. (2014), Acta Materialia 74, 66]. Fig. 3 shows an optimized process which includes a cyclical application of magnetic field (H, sketched at the bottom along with orientations of magnetic ions within the material). The main graph shows the entropy (vertical, a parameter closely related to the process heat flow) vs. temperature. A crystalline microscructure for this material is also shown in Fig. 4; the material is a thin, optimally annealed ribbon of a nickel-cobalt-manganese-tin alloy. In further work, the SJTU team used directional solidification of NiMnIn alloys to create aligned polycrystals with the ability to exhibit simultaneous mechanical stress and magnetic field induced temperature changes (an MCE + ECE, or "multicaloric" effect; see for example Y. J. Huang et al., to appear in Scripta Materialia). In addition, Jing-Han Chen worked with Bruno along with their advisors Ross and Karaman to lead further investigations into the underlying physical properties leading to the MCE effect in NiMnIn alloys, and a prediction for the relative cooling power leading to new compositions with extremely small thermal hysteresis [an important parameter for ultimate commercialization &ndash; see for example J.-H. Chen et al., J. Appl. Phys. (2014), 116, 203901].</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In related work under this project, James Monroe in his dissertation research supervised by Prof. Karaman recognized that the crystal structure changes...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ "Materials World Network: Microstructural Design for Enhanced Efficiency in Solid State Energy Conversion" brought together experts from Texas A&amp;M University, Shanghai Jiao-Tong University (China), and Ningbo Institute (China) to develop new alloys and processing techniques for tunable efficient energy conversion devices. The focus is the alloys known as Magnetic Shape Memory Alloys (MSMAs), having a reversible crystal structure change coupled to a change of magnetic state, which can be engineered so that this sudden state change can provide energy or heat needed for next generation solid state cooling or energy recovery devices.     Traditional Shape Memory Alloys, sometimes called Memory Metals, can be configured to return to their original shape when heated. When the crystal structure change responsible for this process (termed a martensitic transformation) is made to coincide with a change of magnetic state, the resulting MSMAs can exhibit large magnetic-field induced heating and cooling, known as the magnetocaloric effect (MCE), and an analogous effect induced by physical stress, the elastocaloric effect (ECE). The materials used for MCE are commonly based on rare earth metals, which are expensive and scarce. However the development of effective materials based on MSMA-type alloys holds great promise for developing new practical devices. This project combined the expertise of the Texas A&amp;M University team, led by Profs. Joseph Ross and Ibrahim Karaman, with extensive facilities for characterization, testing, and processing of these materials, with the Shanghai Jiao-Tong University team, led by Prof. Jianguo Li, with unique facilities for the specialized fabrication, for example of aligned polycrystals (containing crystallites with aligned orientations). Fig. 1 shows two of the Texas A&amp;M Ph.D. student team members Nickolaus Bruno and James Monroe explaining project results, while fig. 2 shows Bruno along with Ph.D. student Jing-Han Chen in the laboratory with visiting scientists Baris Emre and Suheyla Yuce, also working on the project.     Among the results, work spearheaded by Bruno and his advisor Karaman recently demonstrated that NiCoMnSn-based alloy ribbons not only produce a similar MCE compared to the above-mentioned rare earth compounds, but the operating temperature, refrigeration capacity, and efficiency can be optimized by modifying the microstructure and stoichiometry [N. M. Bruno et al. (2014), Acta Materialia 74, 66]. Fig. 3 shows an optimized process which includes a cyclical application of magnetic field (H, sketched at the bottom along with orientations of magnetic ions within the material). The main graph shows the entropy (vertical, a parameter closely related to the process heat flow) vs. temperature. A crystalline microscructure for this material is also shown in Fig. 4; the material is a thin, optimally annealed ribbon of a nickel-cobalt-manganese-tin alloy. In further work, the SJTU team used directional solidification of NiMnIn alloys to create aligned polycrystals with the ability to exhibit simultaneous mechanical stress and magnetic field induced temperature changes (an MCE + ECE, or "multicaloric" effect; see for example Y. J. Huang et al., to appear in Scripta Materialia). In addition, Jing-Han Chen worked with Bruno along with their advisors Ross and Karaman to lead further investigations into the underlying physical properties leading to the MCE effect in NiMnIn alloys, and a prediction for the relative cooling power leading to new compositions with extremely small thermal hysteresis [an important parameter for ultimate commercialization &ndash; see for example J.-H. Chen et al., J. Appl. Phys. (2014), 116, 203901].     In related work under this project, James Monroe in his dissertation research supervised by Prof. Karaman recognized that the crystal structure changes determining the MSMA effect may also be tuned to give materials with very low thermal expansion, or a large tune...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
