<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:Growth and Characterization of GdN and SmN Thin Films</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1108305</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>McNulty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James F McNulty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6173202843</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000577122</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>McNulty                 James          F</Name>
<CityName>Brighton</CityName>
<ZipCode>021357004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[McNulty                 James          F]]></Name>
<CityName>Brighton</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021357004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5941</Code>
<Text>NEW ZEALAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~5700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project made some progress in the growth and characterization of the rare-earth nitride series, which are important for the potential applications in magnetic memory devices as well as the pure physical interest in these materials.</p> <p>The project resulted in a further understanding of methods for growing and measuring properties of rare-earth nitride thin films. &nbsp;After characterizing them it was shown that some growth conditions need to be adjusted to produce films of high quality. The difficult conditions necessary for growing these films means that a significant amount of time must be taken to ensure proper conditions. While the success of this part was not high, it is still a valid data point that will help lead to better growth conditions. It was hoped also to create films with properties allowing devices to work at close to room temperature, making for practical device applications.</p> <p>Other samples where successfully grown and have been shown to be high quality. This will allow for simple refinements which can next be used in testing the films for use in applications settings.</p> <p>The project was an overall success due to the exchange of information with the host group, which currently is the leader in the field of studying these materials. The skills and knowledge I learned while working in New Zealand will be extremely useful to my research in the US. The collaboration between was strengthened as well, and future joint work is being planned.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2011<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Mcnulty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project made some progress in the growth and characterization of the rare-earth nitride series, which are important for the potential applications in magnetic memory devices as well as the pure physical interest in these materials.  The project resulted in a further understanding of methods for growing and measuring properties of rare-earth nitride thin films.  After characterizing them it was shown that some growth conditions need to be adjusted to produce films of high quality. The difficult conditions necessary for growing these films means that a significant amount of time must be taken to ensure proper conditions. While the success of this part was not high, it is still a valid data point that will help lead to better growth conditions. It was hoped also to create films with properties allowing devices to work at close to room temperature, making for practical device applications.  Other samples where successfully grown and have been shown to be high quality. This will allow for simple refinements which can next be used in testing the films for use in applications settings.  The project was an overall success due to the exchange of information with the host group, which currently is the leader in the field of studying these materials. The skills and knowledge I learned while working in New Zealand will be extremely useful to my research in the US. The collaboration between was strengthened as well, and future joint work is being planned.          Last Modified: 12/31/2011       Submitted by: James F Mcnulty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
