<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Neutron Star Crusts: Probing the Properties of Dense Matter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>227884.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>227884</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will fund a theoretical effort to model the outer layers of neutron stars.  The principal goals of the research are (1) to generate models of the neutron star inner crust that will handle nuclear reactions with realistic treatment of nuclear composition; (2) to determine how the crust evolves in an accreting environment and to connect observed surface phenomena with the properties of the deep interior; and (3) make predictions about the extent to which the neutron star crust can be deformed in accretion and to compute the expected gravitational wave signals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Neutron stars are the densest objects in the universe and knowledge of neutron star physics is growing rapidly, due to X-ray telescopes, laboratory nuclear experiments, and future gravitational wave detectors such as the Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory. A recent National Academy report, "Connecting Quarks with the Cosmos: Eleven Science Questions for the New Century," identified the nature of matter at exceedingly high density and temperature as one of the eleven critical science questions for the 21st century.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1109176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward F Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebrown@pa.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5178845620</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000269107</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Steiner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew W Steiner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>awsteiner@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052636352</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~75155</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~75249</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~77480</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Neutron stars are the densest objects in the universe and have fascinated theorists and observers since they were first conjectured shortly after the discovery of the neutron. &nbsp;Knowledge of neutron star physics is growing rapidly, due to X-ray telescopes such as <em>Chandra</em> and laboratory nuclear experiments. Indeed, the recent 2010 Decadal Survey, <em>New Worlds, New Horizons</em>, identifies as one of its Frontier questions for Stars and Stellar Evolution, "What controls the mass, radius, and spin of compact stellar remnants?"</p> <p>The outermost kilometer (out of about 10 kilometers or so) of a neutron star, known as its crust, is composed of a mixture of free neutrons, electrons, and "ordinary" nuclei. &nbsp;This crust hides the core of the neutron star from view: to explore the properties of dense matter using observations of neutron stars requires modeling the crust.&nbsp;Over the tenure of this award, the research team has explored how phenomena such as cooling, oscillations, and mergers of neutron stars probe the nature of dense matter.</p> <p>The research team collaborated in the discovery of a new, powerful, coolant in the crusts of neutron stars that accrete matter from an orbiting stellar companion. &nbsp;When matter stripped from the companion accumulates on the surface of the neutron star, pressure increases in the underlying layers. &nbsp;This increase in pressure induces nuclei to capture electrons. For some nuclei, these electron captures can rapidly cycle back-and-forth with electron emissions. &nbsp;With each capture and emission a neutrino is emitted, and this neutrino carries away heat, thereby cooling the neutron star. &nbsp;The research team has begun exploring how this cooling affects energetic explosions on the surface of the neutron star and the observed dimming of the neutron star when the accretion of matter ceases.</p> <p>Some neutron stars are endowed with magnetic field strong enough to "crack" the crust. &nbsp;This cracking is thought to be accompanied by a energetic gamma-ray flare, which has been observed from some of these systems. The research team computed the frequency at which the neutron star crust oscillates and showed how the observed oscillations in these gamma-ray flares could be used to constrain the thickness of the neutron star crust and the degree of entrainment between the nuclei and free neutrons in the crust.</p> <p>Finally, some neutron stars are paired: the two neutron stars orbit about one another. &nbsp;If the neutron stars are sufficiently close, the emission of gravitational radiation&mdash;as predicted by Einstin's theory of gravity&mdash;will cause the orbits to decay, and the neutron stars will eventually merge. &nbsp;The gravitational radiation released in this merger is detectable. &nbsp;The co-PI has computed how the neutron star deforms under the strong tidal field of its companion, and how the amount&nbsp;of&nbsp;deformation&nbsp;depends on the nature of the nuclear interaction. &nbsp;Thus, observations that constrain this deformability&nbsp;can be used to constrain the pressure-density relation of bulk nuclear matter.</p> <p>More broadly, this award has helped to train the next generation of scientists: it supported the doctoral training of a scientist, and the PI has incorporated knowledge gained from this project into graduate courses and undergraduate research projects. &nbsp;The PI's notes on stellar physics have been posted on GitHub as well, so that they can be used by other instructors. Finally, the research team has developed an open-source neutron star cooling code, named 'dStar.' &nbsp;This code is freely available on the code hosting site GitHub, and is being used by observers to interpret observations of neutron stars. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Edward&nbsp;F&nbsp;Brown</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Neutron stars are the densest objects in the universe and have fascinated theorists and observers since they were first conjectured shortly after the discovery of the neutron.  Knowledge of neutron star physics is growing rapidly, due to X-ray telescopes such as Chandra and laboratory nuclear experiments. Indeed, the recent 2010 Decadal Survey, New Worlds, New Horizons, identifies as one of its Frontier questions for Stars and Stellar Evolution, "What controls the mass, radius, and spin of compact stellar remnants?"  The outermost kilometer (out of about 10 kilometers or so) of a neutron star, known as its crust, is composed of a mixture of free neutrons, electrons, and "ordinary" nuclei.  This crust hides the core of the neutron star from view: to explore the properties of dense matter using observations of neutron stars requires modeling the crust. Over the tenure of this award, the research team has explored how phenomena such as cooling, oscillations, and mergers of neutron stars probe the nature of dense matter.  The research team collaborated in the discovery of a new, powerful, coolant in the crusts of neutron stars that accrete matter from an orbiting stellar companion.  When matter stripped from the companion accumulates on the surface of the neutron star, pressure increases in the underlying layers.  This increase in pressure induces nuclei to capture electrons. For some nuclei, these electron captures can rapidly cycle back-and-forth with electron emissions.  With each capture and emission a neutrino is emitted, and this neutrino carries away heat, thereby cooling the neutron star.  The research team has begun exploring how this cooling affects energetic explosions on the surface of the neutron star and the observed dimming of the neutron star when the accretion of matter ceases.  Some neutron stars are endowed with magnetic field strong enough to "crack" the crust.  This cracking is thought to be accompanied by a energetic gamma-ray flare, which has been observed from some of these systems. The research team computed the frequency at which the neutron star crust oscillates and showed how the observed oscillations in these gamma-ray flares could be used to constrain the thickness of the neutron star crust and the degree of entrainment between the nuclei and free neutrons in the crust.  Finally, some neutron stars are paired: the two neutron stars orbit about one another.  If the neutron stars are sufficiently close, the emission of gravitational radiation&mdash;as predicted by Einstin's theory of gravity&mdash;will cause the orbits to decay, and the neutron stars will eventually merge.  The gravitational radiation released in this merger is detectable.  The co-PI has computed how the neutron star deforms under the strong tidal field of its companion, and how the amount of deformation depends on the nature of the nuclear interaction.  Thus, observations that constrain this deformability can be used to constrain the pressure-density relation of bulk nuclear matter.  More broadly, this award has helped to train the next generation of scientists: it supported the doctoral training of a scientist, and the PI has incorporated knowledge gained from this project into graduate courses and undergraduate research projects.  The PI's notes on stellar physics have been posted on GitHub as well, so that they can be used by other instructors. Finally, the research team has developed an open-source neutron star cooling code, named 'dStar.'  This code is freely available on the code hosting site GitHub, and is being used by observers to interpret observations of neutron stars.            Last Modified: 09/28/2015       Submitted by: Edward F Brown]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
