<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Evaluating frequency-dependent selection on Borrelia burgdorferi</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding how pathogen diversity is maintained is the central question of this project. It has been suggested that two mechanisms of natural selection may maintain genetic diversity within the bacterium Borrelia burgdorferi: frequency-dependence and host specialization. Computer simulation modeling, field data collection, and molecular techniques will be integrated to evaluate the evidence for these mechanisms of selection. The first aim of this project is to develop a method for identifying different genotypes of B. burgdorferi from a large number of samples. This method will then be used to monitor wildlife populations naturally infected with this pathogen, for evidence of either selection mechanism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;B. burgdorferi is the bacterium that causes Lyme disease, which has a significant public health impact in the United States. Diversity within this species also relates to human illness, as some types tend to cause more severe disease than others. Understanding how this diversity is maintained may provide insight into the evolution of virulence in this bacterium. The molecular identification method to be developed should be an economical and effective tool for further studies on this pathogen and system. Findings will be disseminated to high school students and the general public, via established relationships between the co-PI and various educators and public outreach programs.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1110472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Durland</FirstName>
<LastName>Fish</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Durland Fish</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>durland.fish@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2037853525</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000209542</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly Tsao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kim.tsao@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2037854689</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000576651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Projects]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="internal-source-marker_0.770529098203656" style="text-indent: 36pt; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 16px; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">The  diversity of genotypes of Borrelia burgdorferi, the bacterium that  causes Lyme disease, provides opportunities to study how and why so many  of these types have persisted. One explanation that is thought to apply  to many pathogens with this array of diversity, such as malaria and  influenza, is frequency-dependent selection. This project has allowed us  to test this explanation as a plausible mechanism for maintaining  Borrelia burgdorferi diversity. This is particularly important because  some genotypes are more likely to cause human disease than others, and a  better understanding of what allows these types to persist in nature  may allow us to better control disease risk.</span></p> <p style="text-indent: 36pt; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 16px; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">We  tested this hypothesis using a combination of field-collected data and  computer simulations. The key comparison in evaluating  frequency-dependent selection was measuring how long infected hosts  could remain infectious, relative to how long they would remain immune  to later infection. Our measurements showed that in this system, this  ratio does not support frequency-dependent selection. The  generalizations regarding relative duration of host immunity and infectiousness are  applicable to other pathogens as well. Depending on how long hosts are  infectious and then retain immunity to a pathogen, we can quantify the  strength of this form of selection on the pathogen, which provides us  with a better understanding of its evolution.</span></p> <p style="text-indent: 36pt; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 16px; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">In  the course of conducting this project, we also developed a relatively  inexpensive method to quickly identify genotypes of Borrelia burgdorferi  from field-collected samples. This process was formerly time-consuming  and cost-prohibitive, limiting the studies that could be performed. This  new method should facilitate future research on this important  pathogen. To promote this method and ease of use, we created analysis  software that is freely available on the co-PI's website. The method  protocol will be submitted to a peer-reviewed journal and, once  published, will also be widely available.</span></p> <p style="text-indent: 36pt; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 16px; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">This  project created research and teaching opportunities for the co-PI, as  well as the early career field assistants who were hired to collect data  for this project. Results were shared with participants in the Young  Scholars program through Yale University's Center for Analytical  Sciences, a program designed to teach biostatistics to local high school  students and expose them to a variety of scientific and analytical  career paths.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2012<br>      Modified by: Kimberly&nbsp;Tsao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The  diversity of genotypes of Borrelia burgdorferi, the bacterium that  causes Lyme disease, provides opportunities to study how and why so many  of these types have persisted. One explanation that is thought to apply  to many pathogens with this array of diversity, such as malaria and  influenza, is frequency-dependent selection. This project has allowed us  to test this explanation as a plausible mechanism for maintaining  Borrelia burgdorferi diversity. This is particularly important because  some genotypes are more likely to cause human disease than others, and a  better understanding of what allows these types to persist in nature  may allow us to better control disease risk. We  tested this hypothesis using a combination of field-collected data and  computer simulations. The key comparison in evaluating  frequency-dependent selection was measuring how long infected hosts  could remain infectious, relative to how long they would remain immune  to later infection. Our measurements showed that in this system, this  ratio does not support frequency-dependent selection. The  generalizations regarding relative duration of host immunity and infectiousness are  applicable to other pathogens as well. Depending on how long hosts are  infectious and then retain immunity to a pathogen, we can quantify the  strength of this form of selection on the pathogen, which provides us  with a better understanding of its evolution. In  the course of conducting this project, we also developed a relatively  inexpensive method to quickly identify genotypes of Borrelia burgdorferi  from field-collected samples. This process was formerly time-consuming  and cost-prohibitive, limiting the studies that could be performed. This  new method should facilitate future research on this important  pathogen. To promote this method and ease of use, we created analysis  software that is freely available on the co-PI's website. The method  protocol will be submitted to a peer-reviewed journal and, once  published, will also be widely available. This  project created research and teaching opportunities for the co-PI, as  well as the early career field assistants who were hired to collect data  for this project. Results were shared with participants in the Young  Scholars program through Yale University's Center for Analytical  Sciences, a program designed to teach biostatistics to local high school  students and expose them to a variety of scientific and analytical  career paths.       Last Modified: 07/10/2012       Submitted by: Kimberly Tsao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
