<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Reciprocal interactions between host behaviors, steroid hormones, and parasites</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Elekonich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>melekoni@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927202</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In human and non-human animals, behavior influences the risk of encountering and becoming infected by parasites. For example, the types of food one eats, places one travels, and risky behaviors one engages in are all important in determining parasite risk. Another important, but less well studied, aspect of the interaction between behavior and parasitism explores how parasites change host behavior after infection. Parasites of people (for example, Toxoplasma gondii) and non-human animals can change the behavior of their hosts, and appear to do so by changing the host's brain chemistry or hormone levels. For example, two trematode parasites infecting California killifish increase the frequency of risky behaviors in the fish, and one of these parasites is associated with changes in the fish's brain chemistry. This study will explore how killifish behavior and hormone levels influence encounter and infection rates with parasites, and how infection changes the fish's behavior and hormone levels. Laboratory behavioral experiments, field experiments in the killifish's natural habitat, and molecular techniques will be used to explore these questions. The researchers predict that less social, more active killifish encounter parasites more often, and that infection changes host levels of androgens, estrogens, and glucocorticoids (types of hormones) and makes the fish more bold, asocial, and active. This project is important because parasites are commonly overlooked in behavioral studies, yet are likely to have very important implications for host behavior and physiology across the animal kingdom. Additionally, the PhD student running this project has a strong history of outreach. She will involve undergraduate and high school students in this project, and this grant will allow her to teach the students molecular techniques for measuring hormone levels, in addition to ecological and behavioral techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1110639</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Sih</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Sih</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>asih@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5308630722</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000130586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Weinersmith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly Weinersmith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>KLSmith@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307547000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000581353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OR/Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~14300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The behaviors that humans and non-human animals engage in influence their risk of becoming infected by parasites. For example, eating certain kinds of foods (like uncooked meats) can make you more likely to get infected by parasites. Additionally, parasites can change the behaviors of their hosts following infection. One way in which behavior changes after infection happens if parasites manipulate the behavior of their hosts to increase the likelihood that the parasite gets transmitted to its next host. Many of us have heard of the "zombie ant", which are infected by a fungus that causes the ant to leave its home, climb up a sapling, and clamp its mouth down around the vein of a leaf on this sapling. In this case, the fungus manipulated the ant to go to a location that was ideal for the growth and reproduction of the fungus, and put the fungus in a place where its offspring would likely encounter more ants that they could infect.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this study, ours goals were to understand how behavior influences infection risk, what behaviors are changed following infection, and whether or not individuals who were already infected were more likely to get infected again in the future. We also wanted to better understand what was happening inside of the host to change behavior following infection. Our study system was a small, abundant fish species known as California killifish (<em>Fundulus parvipinnis</em>) and their brain-infected trematode parasite, <em>Euhaplorchis californiensis. </em>When fish are infected by <em>Euhaplorchis californiensis</em>, they exhibit conspicuous behaviors such as flipping upside down, and these behaviors increase the risk that the fish is eaten by a predatory bird. These weird behaviors benefit the parasite, because birds are the next host in the life cycle for <em>Euhaplorchis californiensis.&nbsp;</em></p> <p>We conducted a series of experiments, and are still in the process of analyzing the large amount of data we collected. A preliminary look at the data suggests that the parasite causes the kilifish to swim up closer to the surface of the water, which may increase the fish's risk of getting infected by more parasites (which hang out near the top of the water) or increase the fish's risk of getting eaten by a bird. Infected fish may also stay closer to an area where they experienced a simulated predator attack. A hormone called cortisol is released by fish when they experience stress, and infected fish show a different cortisol response than do uninfected fish. This change in cortisol response could result in fish responding inappropriately to bird predators, and may be a way through which the parasite increases its likelihood of getting its fish host eaten by a predatory bird. We are doing additional experiments to explore this possibility.&nbsp;</p> <p>These experiments are important because parasites are frequently overlooked in studies on animal behavior, yet interactions with parasites may be very important for determining how animals act. Additionally, these experiments begin to help us understand how parasites manipulate parasite behavior, which is currently a major unanswered question in this field of research.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project contributed to the training of four graduate students and eight undergraduate students. The main graduate student on the project, Kelly Weinersmith, gained experience designing experiments, collecting and analyzing data, writing manuscripts, and mentoring undergraduate students. She mentored two undergraduate students through the process of creating and presenting a poster based on data analyzed by the undergraduate students. All but one of the undergraduate students earned co-authorship on manuscripts arising from this NSF-funded project.&nbsp;</p> <p>Kelly presented her research at an NSF-funded symposium she co-organized with Dr. Zen Faulkes (University of Texas Pan American). The symposiu...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The behaviors that humans and non-human animals engage in influence their risk of becoming infected by parasites. For example, eating certain kinds of foods (like uncooked meats) can make you more likely to get infected by parasites. Additionally, parasites can change the behaviors of their hosts following infection. One way in which behavior changes after infection happens if parasites manipulate the behavior of their hosts to increase the likelihood that the parasite gets transmitted to its next host. Many of us have heard of the "zombie ant", which are infected by a fungus that causes the ant to leave its home, climb up a sapling, and clamp its mouth down around the vein of a leaf on this sapling. In this case, the fungus manipulated the ant to go to a location that was ideal for the growth and reproduction of the fungus, and put the fungus in a place where its offspring would likely encounter more ants that they could infect.   In this study, ours goals were to understand how behavior influences infection risk, what behaviors are changed following infection, and whether or not individuals who were already infected were more likely to get infected again in the future. We also wanted to better understand what was happening inside of the host to change behavior following infection. Our study system was a small, abundant fish species known as California killifish (Fundulus parvipinnis) and their brain-infected trematode parasite, Euhaplorchis californiensis. When fish are infected by Euhaplorchis californiensis, they exhibit conspicuous behaviors such as flipping upside down, and these behaviors increase the risk that the fish is eaten by a predatory bird. These weird behaviors benefit the parasite, because birds are the next host in the life cycle for Euhaplorchis californiensis.   We conducted a series of experiments, and are still in the process of analyzing the large amount of data we collected. A preliminary look at the data suggests that the parasite causes the kilifish to swim up closer to the surface of the water, which may increase the fish's risk of getting infected by more parasites (which hang out near the top of the water) or increase the fish's risk of getting eaten by a bird. Infected fish may also stay closer to an area where they experienced a simulated predator attack. A hormone called cortisol is released by fish when they experience stress, and infected fish show a different cortisol response than do uninfected fish. This change in cortisol response could result in fish responding inappropriately to bird predators, and may be a way through which the parasite increases its likelihood of getting its fish host eaten by a predatory bird. We are doing additional experiments to explore this possibility.   These experiments are important because parasites are frequently overlooked in studies on animal behavior, yet interactions with parasites may be very important for determining how animals act. Additionally, these experiments begin to help us understand how parasites manipulate parasite behavior, which is currently a major unanswered question in this field of research.   This project contributed to the training of four graduate students and eight undergraduate students. The main graduate student on the project, Kelly Weinersmith, gained experience designing experiments, collecting and analyzing data, writing manuscripts, and mentoring undergraduate students. She mentored two undergraduate students through the process of creating and presenting a poster based on data analyzed by the undergraduate students. All but one of the undergraduate students earned co-authorship on manuscripts arising from this NSF-funded project.   Kelly presented her research at an NSF-funded symposium she co-organized with Dr. Zen Faulkes (University of Texas Pan American). The symposium was entitled "Parasite Manipulation of Host Phenotype: Or How to Make a Zombie", occured at the 2014 Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology co...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
