<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theoretical studies of coherent energy transfer in photosynthetic systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evelyn Goldfield</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>egoldfie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Jianshu Cao of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology is supported by an award from the Chemical Theory, Models and Computational Methods program in the Chemistry Division to computationally investigate how efficient and robust coherent energy transfer arises in photosynthesis and how structure-function relations observed in light-harvesting systems can help the design of artificial energy devices. The steps involved in the current project will involve (1) characterizing quantum coherence in light-harvesting systems, (2) using the stochastic wave-function method to realistically explore spatial-temporal correlations in the presence of disorder and noise, and (3) applying optimal design theory to maximizing energy transfer and thus exploring the importance of connectivity and symmetry in donor-acceptor arrays. Understanding the microscopic mechanisms of energy transfer in photosynthetic systems is of larger significance since it is reasonable to expect that coherent transfer within collaborative protein environments may become a pervasive theme in the future. This work will, in addition to providing cutting-edge training for students and postdocs, be incorporated in the MIT curriculum, public-access MIT OpenCourseWare and public lectures on photosynthesis and basic energy sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Photosynthesis in plants starts with the absorption of light by proteins in chlorophyll-containing photosynthetic reaction centers.  The absorbed energy is rapidly transferred elsewhere in the complex protein environment by transfer of electrons to be stored as chemical energy.  A mystery of much interest is how the electron transfer events occur in such a way as to avoid randomizing the energy before storage occurs.  These ultrafast events are increasingly able to be studied by new laser-based experiments, but modeling the proteins by classical ball-and-spring models cannot reproduce the coordinated, or coherent, energy transfer.  Coherence is usually regarded as requiring a description by quantum mechanics, and the PI is therefore developing quantum mechanical approaches to understanding the microscopic mechanisms underlying extremely efficient energy transfer in photosynthesis.  The fact that nature has found a way to establish this collaboration in complicated protein environments raises the hope, to be explored in this project, that we can learn to control and optimize energy transfer efficiency for application in future man-made light-harvesting devices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1112825</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jianshu</FirstName>
<LastName>Cao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jianshu Cao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jianshu@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172531563</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179092</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6881</Code>
<Text>Chem Thry, Mdls &amp; Cmptnl Mthds</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5560</Code>
<Text>ENERGY CONVERSION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7722</Code>
<Text>COMPLEXITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7905</Code>
<Text>MPS SUST ENERGY SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~420000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The focus of my research program supported by the prior NSF funding was the development of theoretical and computational methods to analyze the efficient and robust energy transfer (ET) in the mechanistic study of the pigment-protein complex and in the design of light-harvesting networks. Specifically, my previous research program consisted of three components: (1) prediction of the optimal efficiency and phase modulation in light-harvesting systems, with the goal of characterizing quantum coherence; (2) computer simulations of photosynthetic ET processes using the stochastic wave function method; and (3) application of optimal design theory to explore the connectivity and symmetry of donor-acceptor arrays in order to establish their maximal efficiency and robustness.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Publications Resulting from the Prior NSF Grant</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A total of 56 papers were published over the five years (Sept. 2011-Sept. 2016), including 3 in Physical Review Letters, 1 in PNAS, 4 in JPC Letters, 2 in Scientific Reports, 3 in Nano Letters (collaborations), and 2 in Nature Communications (collaborations). Among these, 40 papers were on the topic of light-harvesting energy transfer, supported solely or jointly by the prior NSF grant. Another 16 papers were published during the five years on the topic of statistical biophysics, which was not supported directly by the prior NSF grant.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Highlights of the Prior Results</strong></p> <p><strong><br /></strong></p> <p>I. Optimal Efficiency of Light-Harvesting Energy Transfer: Robustness and Generality</p> <p>A key component of the previous NSF-funded research was the understanding of optimal energy transfer (ET) in light-harvesting systems. (1) My group is among the first to demonstrate the robustness of optimal energy transfer in the FMO&nbsp; complex and systematically explored its underlying ET mechanism in a series of three papers on the system. (2)&nbsp; In order to unify different physical conditions in light-harvesting systems, we introduced the concept of orthogonal subspace and proposed the generic mechanism of optimal ET. (3) We published three studies to demonstrate that nature engineers not only the basic properties of the constituent molecules but also the superstructure of nanoscale systems to achieve the designed ET properties.</p> <p>II. Quantum Transport in Disordered Systems: Anderson Localization and Thermal Noise</p> <p>Building upon the knowledge learned from photosynthetic systems, we also set out to study the energy transport or charge transport using generic models of organic semiconductors.&nbsp; (1) A characteristic of these organic systems is the competition between static disorder and dynamic noise, which we explored systematically in the context of the Anderson localization.&nbsp; (2) As a result of this competition, charge mobility can be optimized as a function of temperature and was shown to exhibit four distinct scaling relations at different temperature regimes. (3) The critical dependence of the Anderson localization on dimensionality leads to our prediction of the universal scaling of quantum diffusion along a nanotube and its universal transition between the 1D and 2D limits.</p> <p>III. Method Developments: &nbsp;Pushing the Limit of Spatial-Temporal Correlation</p> <p>Perhaps, the most practical outcome from the previous funding period is the development of novel numerical algorithms for simulating large-scale open quantum systems at long times.<ins datetime="2018-05-31T15:38" cite="mailto:Jianshu%20Cao"> </ins>(1) My group has devoted considerable effort to successfully develop a stochastic path integral approach to simulate dissipative quantum dynamics based on wave functions instead of density matrices. &nbsp;(2) To interpret the numerical simulations in light-harvesting systems, we constructed a systematic expansion to map quantum dynamics of energy transfer networks to more intuitive classical kinetics. &nbsp;(3) Based on non-Markovian dynamical maps, we proposed the transfer tensor method (TTM) to process the essential information encoded in the initial stages of the evolution of an open quantum system for the prediction of its trajectory at later stages.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The research is directly motivated by the current energy crisis and can make direct connections to experimental and educational efforts. With the NSF support, I have established collaborations with colleagues at MIT (Moungi Bawendi, Keith Nelson, and the late Robert Silbey), in the States (Graham Fleming and Shaul Mukamel), and in other countries (Jasper Knoester and Martin Plenio). The collaboration with experimental groups and access to their experimental data and images has been crucial for the success of the applications. My educational efforts have been devoted to training students and postdoctoral associates, developing new course materials, and giving public lectures on basic energy research. The new course materials incorporate a set of selected topics relevant to the proposed energy research and will be posted on MIT OpenCourseWare for public access. I continue to present public lectures on the physical principles underlying photosynthetic processes and explain the importance of developing artificial light-harvesting devices. My group has constructed a website to provide our stochastic simulation codes and is developing a user-friendly interface for wide distribution and application of the stochastic methods.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Jianshu&nbsp;Cao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit     The focus of my research program supported by the prior NSF funding was the development of theoretical and computational methods to analyze the efficient and robust energy transfer (ET) in the mechanistic study of the pigment-protein complex and in the design of light-harvesting networks. Specifically, my previous research program consisted of three components: (1) prediction of the optimal efficiency and phase modulation in light-harvesting systems, with the goal of characterizing quantum coherence; (2) computer simulations of photosynthetic ET processes using the stochastic wave function method; and (3) application of optimal design theory to explore the connectivity and symmetry of donor-acceptor arrays in order to establish their maximal efficiency and robustness.     Publications Resulting from the Prior NSF Grant     A total of 56 papers were published over the five years (Sept. 2011-Sept. 2016), including 3 in Physical Review Letters, 1 in PNAS, 4 in JPC Letters, 2 in Scientific Reports, 3 in Nano Letters (collaborations), and 2 in Nature Communications (collaborations). Among these, 40 papers were on the topic of light-harvesting energy transfer, supported solely or jointly by the prior NSF grant. Another 16 papers were published during the five years on the topic of statistical biophysics, which was not supported directly by the prior NSF grant.     Highlights of the Prior Results     I. Optimal Efficiency of Light-Harvesting Energy Transfer: Robustness and Generality  A key component of the previous NSF-funded research was the understanding of optimal energy transfer (ET) in light-harvesting systems. (1) My group is among the first to demonstrate the robustness of optimal energy transfer in the FMO  complex and systematically explored its underlying ET mechanism in a series of three papers on the system. (2)  In order to unify different physical conditions in light-harvesting systems, we introduced the concept of orthogonal subspace and proposed the generic mechanism of optimal ET. (3) We published three studies to demonstrate that nature engineers not only the basic properties of the constituent molecules but also the superstructure of nanoscale systems to achieve the designed ET properties.  II. Quantum Transport in Disordered Systems: Anderson Localization and Thermal Noise  Building upon the knowledge learned from photosynthetic systems, we also set out to study the energy transport or charge transport using generic models of organic semiconductors.  (1) A characteristic of these organic systems is the competition between static disorder and dynamic noise, which we explored systematically in the context of the Anderson localization.  (2) As a result of this competition, charge mobility can be optimized as a function of temperature and was shown to exhibit four distinct scaling relations at different temperature regimes. (3) The critical dependence of the Anderson localization on dimensionality leads to our prediction of the universal scaling of quantum diffusion along a nanotube and its universal transition between the 1D and 2D limits.  III. Method Developments:  Pushing the Limit of Spatial-Temporal Correlation  Perhaps, the most practical outcome from the previous funding period is the development of novel numerical algorithms for simulating large-scale open quantum systems at long times. (1) My group has devoted considerable effort to successfully develop a stochastic path integral approach to simulate dissipative quantum dynamics based on wave functions instead of density matrices.  (2) To interpret the numerical simulations in light-harvesting systems, we constructed a systematic expansion to map quantum dynamics of energy transfer networks to more intuitive classical kinetics.  (3) Based on non-Markovian dynamical maps, we proposed the transfer tensor method (TTM) to process the essential information encoded in the initial stages of the evolution of an open quantum system for the prediction of its trajectory at later stages.     Broader Impact     The research is directly motivated by the current energy crisis and can make direct connections to experimental and educational efforts. With the NSF support, I have established collaborations with colleagues at MIT (Moungi Bawendi, Keith Nelson, and the late Robert Silbey), in the States (Graham Fleming and Shaul Mukamel), and in other countries (Jasper Knoester and Martin Plenio). The collaboration with experimental groups and access to their experimental data and images has been crucial for the success of the applications. My educational efforts have been devoted to training students and postdoctoral associates, developing new course materials, and giving public lectures on basic energy research. The new course materials incorporate a set of selected topics relevant to the proposed energy research and will be posted on MIT OpenCourseWare for public access. I continue to present public lectures on the physical principles underlying photosynthetic processes and explain the importance of developing artificial light-harvesting devices. My group has constructed a website to provide our stochastic simulation codes and is developing a user-friendly interface for wide distribution and application of the stochastic methods.             Last Modified: 05/31/2018       Submitted by: Jianshu Cao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
