<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Non-empirical density functional theory for computational chemistry and materials science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>444000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>444000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evelyn Goldfield</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>egoldfie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Kieron Burke of the University of California, Irvine is supported by an award from the  Chemical Theory, Models and Computational Methods program to carry out research on the development of improvements to density functional theory (DFT). The improvements focus on the development of new functionals including a kinetic energy functional, which would eliminate the need to compute orbitals, and the exchange-correlation functional to improve its reliability and accuracy. Density functional theory has become an essential tool of electronic structure calculations in many fields of chemistry, but there now exist so many empirical functionals that users are often bewildered about which one to choose, and experts regard the theory as highly empirical. The primary objective of this project is to develop an entirely new methodology for developing approximate density functionals by extending the semiclassical approximations on which the original theories were based. The approach uses a simple principle, that of asymptotic exactness as the number of electrons becomes large. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The impact of Burke's work is expected to be broad and to have application in chemistry, materials science, nanoscience, and many other fields. The impact of the work will be further broadened by the development of tutorials and distribution of "DFT in a nutshell", a new and improved version of Burke's "ABCs of DFT" online notes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1112442</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kieron</FirstName>
<LastName>Burke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kieron J Burke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kieron@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498240374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000441023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6881</Code>
<Text>Chem Thry, Mdls &amp; Cmptnl Mthds</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~148000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~296000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project delved into the deep underlying theory behind Density Functional approximations, the most commonly used electronic structure method in physical sciences today. &nbsp; Significant progress was made on understanding the origins of the success of local approximations in the theory, and in some limited cases, finding new approximations that go far beyond those in current use today.</p> <p>Most general advances in the accuracy and reliability of DFT occurred about 20 years ago. &nbsp;The work in this proposal is aimed at creating a framework in which improvements can be made systematically, that are both general and more accurate than those in use today. &nbsp; Ultimate success will mean escaping from the existing patchwork of exact conditions and empirical fits to improve these functionals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Since more than 30,000 papers per year use DFT (a count established during the project), the societal benefits of improvements in the theory cannot be overestimated. &nbsp;</p> <p>Many students (graduate, undergraduate, and even high-school) were exposed t to this field during the course of the work, and many became authors on signficant scientific papers in this area. &nbsp;This exposure will help produce the leaders in this field tomorrow. &nbsp;Also, many public tutorials and short courses on DFT were given within the US and many other countries.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Kieron&nbsp;J&nbsp;Burke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project delved into the deep underlying theory behind Density Functional approximations, the most commonly used electronic structure method in physical sciences today.   Significant progress was made on understanding the origins of the success of local approximations in the theory, and in some limited cases, finding new approximations that go far beyond those in current use today.  Most general advances in the accuracy and reliability of DFT occurred about 20 years ago.  The work in this proposal is aimed at creating a framework in which improvements can be made systematically, that are both general and more accurate than those in use today.   Ultimate success will mean escaping from the existing patchwork of exact conditions and empirical fits to improve these functionals.     Since more than 30,000 papers per year use DFT (a count established during the project), the societal benefits of improvements in the theory cannot be overestimated.    Many students (graduate, undergraduate, and even high-school) were exposed t to this field during the course of the work, and many became authors on signficant scientific papers in this area.  This exposure will help produce the leaders in this field tomorrow.  Also, many public tutorials and short courses on DFT were given within the US and many other countries.       Last Modified: 01/29/2016       Submitted by: Kieron J Burke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
