<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CNH:   The Emergence of Adaptive Governance Arrangements for Tropical Forest Ecosystems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betsy Von Holle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mvonholl@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924974</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research will generate new knowledge on long-standing questions about the origins of adaptive forest governance.  Previous research has established that strong institutional arrangements, i.e., the rule systems that structure human behavior, are needed for effective forest governance outcomes.  But the specific contextual factors that enable strong institutional arrangements to take form remain a puzzle.   This research directly addresses this puzzle by collecting and analyzing new data on how humans interact with their natural environment.  This project will combine new data collection and advanced analytical methods to rigorously test the hypothesis that the emergence of adaptive governance is critically linked to three factors: local ecological knowledge; cultural values and beliefs, and socioeconomic inequalities.  Data will be collected from 56 community-managed tropical forest ecosystems in Bolivia and Uganda and will focus on the measurement of possible causes and consequences of individual and community decision making about access to and use of forest resources. These data will be generated using a variety of data collection methods, including direct measures of forest composition, satellite imagery, studies of forest user behaviors, household surveys, focus group discussions, and interviews with key informants and decision makers.  Data will be analyzed using system-dynamics models, cross-sectional time-series analysis, and qualitative comparative analysis to determine how the interrelated factors of local ecological knowledge, cultural values and beliefs, and socio-economic inequality within resource user groups affect forest conservation outcomes. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This research challenges the conventional wisdom that extrinsic incentives, such as direct payments to forest users, will uniformly lead to increased forest conservation, and will produce information on how forest conservation efforts affect forest users' decisions and behavior in a variety of socioeconomic and cultural settings.  This new knowledge will build a more nuanced view of the potential benefits of a global program to Reduce Emissions from Deforestation and Forest Degradation in Developing Countries.  The research is of immediate practical value as organizations around the world struggle to create policies that promote effective natural resource governance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1114984</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Chazdon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin L Chazdon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robin.chazdon@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8603773878</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314141</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arun</FirstName>
<LastName>Agrawal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arun Agrawal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arunagra@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346475948</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000252461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Krister</FirstName>
<LastName>Andersson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Krister P Andersson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krister.andersson@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037352317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sendzimir</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan P Sendzimir</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sendzim@iiasa.ac.at</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000112370</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>BE: DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project combined long-term data on communities and their forests with cutting-edge experimental methods to test how social and cultural factors like values and inequality affect how people cooperate to manage forests and other complex resources. Key to this project&rsquo;s success was the participation of rural forest-dependent villagers in newly-designed behavioral experiments. These game-like activities simulated forest-harvest decisions to reveal how, when and why people cooperate (or not), questions that would be difficult to answer with traditional tools like direct questionnaires.&nbsp; Also important were system dynamics modeling and simulations which helped to expand the scope and impact of detailed, on-site work.&nbsp; These innovative methods were complemented by traditional social survey techniques to improve our understanding of the interactions between people and forests.&nbsp;</p> <p>The results provide guidance for resource management in many governmental contexts.&nbsp; &nbsp;Farming systems dominated by shifting cultivation show an inherent stability, but only up to a point (Magnuszewski et al 2015), and their participants respond well to incentives that promote communication and community identity (Salk et al., 2016).</p> <p>Decentralized forestry policies, where central governments devolve power and resources to local governments, are becoming more and more popular responses to problems of unsustainable forest use and exploitation (Andersson et al 2015). This project has contributed to new knowledge about the conditions under which decentralization policies stand a better chance of slowing down deforestation rates in developing countries. More specifically, in a recently accepted paper in the Proceedings of the National Academies of Science we find that decentralization can reduce deforestation when local forest user groups actively engage with local government officials in the forest governance process (Wright et al, forthcoming). &nbsp;</p> <p>Payments for Ecosystem Services (PES) programs can be an effective tool in provdiding market-based incentives for sustainable rural resource management. We find that participants may respond better to direct payments than to offers of insurance (Salk et al 2016). The project also contributed with new knowledge about the conditions under which PES programs are more likely to work&mdash;we find that groups that communicate more and enjoy higher levels of trust tend to respond more positively to PES interventions, leading to significantly more forest conservation in such settings (Andersson et al, forthcoming).</p> <p>The most remarkable<span style="text-decoration: underline;"> broader impact</span> of the project was the team&rsquo;s direct involvement with the 12th Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD). While countries&rsquo; reports to the CBD often imply that all credit for conservation success is due to the national government preparing the report, the team proposed methods on how member countries can estimate the conservation contributions of local communities. This proposal led to the unanimous decision to requiring all member countries to make such estimations starting in their 2016 reports. This project contributed to the education and career advancement of numerous participants beyond those named in the proposal.&nbsp; Dozens of field technicians took part in our training regimen to practice and learn new field data collection techniques.&nbsp; These participants included many from under-represented cultural groups and a substantial proportion of women.&nbsp; The team also designed an interactive web-based platform that educators have used to conduct behavioral experiments in the classroom (www.games4sustainability.org).&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has so far produced two peer-reviewed university-press books (Matson et al 2016; Chazdon, 2014) two doctoral dissertations (Ravikumar, 2013; Chan, 2013); and 24 peer-reviewed journal articles (Agrawal, 2014; Alston et al., 2013; Andersson and Chan, 2014; Andersson et al 2014; Andersson et al 2014b; Andersson et al., 2016; Andersson et al fortcoming; Andersson, 2013; Benson Wahlen, 2014; Chazdon et al., 2014; Chazdon, 2013a; Chazdon 2013b; Chazdon, and Arroyo, 2013; Cook, et al Forthcoming; Magnuszewski, et al 2015; Messier et al 2014; Persha and Andersson, 2014; Ravikumar et al., 2013; Salk et al 2013; Salk et al., 2014; Salk et al., 2016; Van Laerhoven and Andersson 2013; Wright and Andersson, 2013; Wright and Jaramillo 2015; Wright et al., Forthcoming).</p> <p>Full list of reference for these and other citations are available in the project&rsquo;s FINAL REPORT.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Krister&nbsp;P&nbsp;Andersson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project combined long-term data on communities and their forests with cutting-edge experimental methods to test how social and cultural factors like values and inequality affect how people cooperate to manage forests and other complex resources. Key to this project?s success was the participation of rural forest-dependent villagers in newly-designed behavioral experiments. These game-like activities simulated forest-harvest decisions to reveal how, when and why people cooperate (or not), questions that would be difficult to answer with traditional tools like direct questionnaires.  Also important were system dynamics modeling and simulations which helped to expand the scope and impact of detailed, on-site work.  These innovative methods were complemented by traditional social survey techniques to improve our understanding of the interactions between people and forests.   The results provide guidance for resource management in many governmental contexts.   Farming systems dominated by shifting cultivation show an inherent stability, but only up to a point (Magnuszewski et al 2015), and their participants respond well to incentives that promote communication and community identity (Salk et al., 2016).  Decentralized forestry policies, where central governments devolve power and resources to local governments, are becoming more and more popular responses to problems of unsustainable forest use and exploitation (Andersson et al 2015). This project has contributed to new knowledge about the conditions under which decentralization policies stand a better chance of slowing down deforestation rates in developing countries. More specifically, in a recently accepted paper in the Proceedings of the National Academies of Science we find that decentralization can reduce deforestation when local forest user groups actively engage with local government officials in the forest governance process (Wright et al, forthcoming).    Payments for Ecosystem Services (PES) programs can be an effective tool in provdiding market-based incentives for sustainable rural resource management. We find that participants may respond better to direct payments than to offers of insurance (Salk et al 2016). The project also contributed with new knowledge about the conditions under which PES programs are more likely to work&mdash;we find that groups that communicate more and enjoy higher levels of trust tend to respond more positively to PES interventions, leading to significantly more forest conservation in such settings (Andersson et al, forthcoming).  The most remarkable broader impact of the project was the team?s direct involvement with the 12th Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD). While countries? reports to the CBD often imply that all credit for conservation success is due to the national government preparing the report, the team proposed methods on how member countries can estimate the conservation contributions of local communities. This proposal led to the unanimous decision to requiring all member countries to make such estimations starting in their 2016 reports. This project contributed to the education and career advancement of numerous participants beyond those named in the proposal.  Dozens of field technicians took part in our training regimen to practice and learn new field data collection techniques.  These participants included many from under-represented cultural groups and a substantial proportion of women.  The team also designed an interactive web-based platform that educators have used to conduct behavioral experiments in the classroom (www.games4sustainability.org).   The project has so far produced two peer-reviewed university-press books (Matson et al 2016; Chazdon, 2014) two doctoral dissertations (Ravikumar, 2013; Chan, 2013); and 24 peer-reviewed journal articles (Agrawal, 2014; Alston et al., 2013; Andersson and Chan, 2014; Andersson et al 2014; Andersson et al 2014b; Andersson et al., 2016; Andersson et al fortcoming; Andersson, 2013; Benson Wahlen, 2014; Chazdon et al., 2014; Chazdon, 2013a; Chazdon 2013b; Chazdon, and Arroyo, 2013; Cook, et al Forthcoming; Magnuszewski, et al 2015; Messier et al 2014; Persha and Andersson, 2014; Ravikumar et al., 2013; Salk et al 2013; Salk et al., 2014; Salk et al., 2016; Van Laerhoven and Andersson 2013; Wright and Andersson, 2013; Wright and Jaramillo 2015; Wright et al., Forthcoming).  Full list of reference for these and other citations are available in the project?s FINAL REPORT.           Last Modified: 11/29/2016       Submitted by: Krister P Andersson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
