<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>III: Small: RUI: Improving Data Quality and Data Mining Using Noisy Micro-Outsourcing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>260628.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>355628</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Machine learning currently offers one of the most cost-effective approaches to building predictive models (e.g., classifiers for categorizing the millions of messages, news articles, and blogs that are generated every day). However, the effective use of machine learning methods in such settings is limited by the availability of a training corpus (i.e., a representative set of instances that have been labeled with the correponding categories).  In domains where labeled data are scarce or expensive to acquire, there is an urgent need for cost-effective approaches to selectively acquiring labels for data samples used to train predictive models using machine learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project explores novel techniques that take advantage of the low cost of micro-outsourcing using systems such as Amazon's mechanical Turk, to engage a large number of workers from around the world for acquiring the labels of instances to be used to construct the training corpus. There is currently little understanding of how to utilize the multiple noisy labels obtained using micro-outsourcing. There is a need for advanced techniques for taking advantage of the low cost of micro-outsourcing in order to improve data quality and the quality of models built from the available data. It explores novel approaches for utilizing multiple labels given to an instance by different labelers. It also extends active learning techniques for active selection of samples to be labeled to take into account the multi-sets of labels that have been already obtained from a pool of labelers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advances in techniques for active selection of data instances to be labeled in a micro-outsourcing setting can significantly improve the quality of data used to build predictive models in a broad range of applications, including gene annotation, image annotation, text classification, sentiment analysis, and recommender systems, where unlabeled data are plentiful yet labeled data are sparse. The project will provide research opportunities for students at University of Central Arkansas, a primarily undergraduate institution and help expand the STEM pipeline. Additional information about the project can be found at: http://sun0.cs.uca.edu/~ssheng/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1115417</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor S Sheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>victor.sheng@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8068348971</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572595</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Central Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>Conway</CityName>
<ZipCode>720350001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5014505061</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Donaghey Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006562250</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL ARKANSAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006562250</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>Conway</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>720350001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Donaghey Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9232</Code>
<Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~174942</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~101686</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~31000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project explored novel techniques that take advantage of the low cost of micro-outsourcing using systems such as Amazon's mechanical Turk, to engage a large number of workers from around the world for acquiring the labels of instances to be used to construct the training corpus. The technical focuses of the project are to develop repeated labeling strategies (related to active learning) to take advantage of the low cost of crowdsourcing to acquire labels for selected data points.</p> <p>Specially, we designed novel strategies for utilizing repeated noisy labels to improve the performance of supervised learning. The strategies we designed are labeling quality agnostic strategies for real world applications. We investigate how close these labeling quality agnostic strategies are to a labeling quality gnostic strategy. We also examined the impact of example labeling difficulty on existing selective repeated-labeling strategies.</p> <p>Because non-expert labelers lack expertise and dedication, and have strong personal preference, they may have bias when labeling. This causes Imbalanced Multiple Noisy Labeling. Our research results show that the imbalanced multiple noisy labeling is a general trend and becomes more serious if the related true underlying class distribution is imbalanced. &nbsp;We investigated the performance of the state-of-art ground truth inference algorithms and found this is a challenge issue for all of them. Therefore, we proposed several novel ground truth inference algorithms to take the imbalanced issue into consideration. Our experimental results show they do improve the integrated label quality.</p> <p>After the imbalanced labeling phenomena is discovered in the crowd-sourcing environment, we think this phenomenon will directly impact the existing active learning strategies, since the existing active learning strategies do not consider this. With this direction, we design three novel active learning strategies to actively acquire labels from the crowd-sourcing environment. The three novel strategies integrate the imbalanced ground truth inference into their iterative acquisition procedure. According to our experimental results, they perform much better when the multiple noisy labeling is imbalanced, and do not perform worse when the multiple noisy labeling is balanced.</p> <p>Besides, we also try to estimate the uncertainty of the integrated label directly, taking advantage of the estimation of the labeler quality distribution just computed. With the direct uncertainty estimation, we developed a novel repeated strategy NLU&mdash;which does not make the non-adversarial assumption, and instead takes into consideration the prior class distribution during the uncertainty estimation. Our experiments demonstrate that it improves the performance of the corresponding strategies. Similarly, we combined the score of NLU with the score of MU, to create the New Label and Model Uncertainty (NLMU) method. &nbsp;</p> <p>We further empirically studied the performance of existing EM-based consensus algorithms and found all of the state-of-the-art algorithms ignore the potential bias characteristics of datasets and perform badly although they model the complexity of the systems. To address the issue of handling biased labeling, we proposed a novel consensus algorithm, namely adaptive weighted majority voting (AWMV), based on the statistical difference between the labeling qualities of the two classes.</p> <p>To facilitate the research on mining the wisdom of crowds, we develop a novel software package named Crowd Environment and its Knowledge Analysis (CEKA), with the help from our undergraduate students. The main contribution of CEKA lies on three aspects. (1) It provides comprehensive functions, which not only includes a great number of ground truth inference algorithms with a uniform easy-to-use programming interface but also includes a lot of well-designed functions for the management of crowdsourced data. (2) It is seamlessly compatible with the famous machine learning tool WEKA, which facilitates the combination of the previous inference and the subsequent model learning procedures. (3) It is written in Java and completely open source. Therefore, many new ideas and methods, such as noise correction for crowdsourcing, are easily embedded in. The project CEKA is available at: <a href="http://ceka.sourceforge.net/">http://ceka.sourceforge.net/</a>.</p> <p>The findings have impact on research areas such as visual recognition, natural language processing, and sentiment analysis. Under the support of this project, seven master&rsquo;s students graduated. This project also attracted 16 undergraduate students to participate and conduct research on data mining and machine learning. Seven of them finished their undergraduate education with honor theses. Five students were from underrepresented groups, including four female students and an African student. A new graduate course, Advanced Data Mining, was developed.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Victor&nbsp;S&nbsp;Sheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project explored novel techniques that take advantage of the low cost of micro-outsourcing using systems such as Amazon's mechanical Turk, to engage a large number of workers from around the world for acquiring the labels of instances to be used to construct the training corpus. The technical focuses of the project are to develop repeated labeling strategies (related to active learning) to take advantage of the low cost of crowdsourcing to acquire labels for selected data points.  Specially, we designed novel strategies for utilizing repeated noisy labels to improve the performance of supervised learning. The strategies we designed are labeling quality agnostic strategies for real world applications. We investigate how close these labeling quality agnostic strategies are to a labeling quality gnostic strategy. We also examined the impact of example labeling difficulty on existing selective repeated-labeling strategies.  Because non-expert labelers lack expertise and dedication, and have strong personal preference, they may have bias when labeling. This causes Imbalanced Multiple Noisy Labeling. Our research results show that the imbalanced multiple noisy labeling is a general trend and becomes more serious if the related true underlying class distribution is imbalanced.  We investigated the performance of the state-of-art ground truth inference algorithms and found this is a challenge issue for all of them. Therefore, we proposed several novel ground truth inference algorithms to take the imbalanced issue into consideration. Our experimental results show they do improve the integrated label quality.  After the imbalanced labeling phenomena is discovered in the crowd-sourcing environment, we think this phenomenon will directly impact the existing active learning strategies, since the existing active learning strategies do not consider this. With this direction, we design three novel active learning strategies to actively acquire labels from the crowd-sourcing environment. The three novel strategies integrate the imbalanced ground truth inference into their iterative acquisition procedure. According to our experimental results, they perform much better when the multiple noisy labeling is imbalanced, and do not perform worse when the multiple noisy labeling is balanced.  Besides, we also try to estimate the uncertainty of the integrated label directly, taking advantage of the estimation of the labeler quality distribution just computed. With the direct uncertainty estimation, we developed a novel repeated strategy NLU&mdash;which does not make the non-adversarial assumption, and instead takes into consideration the prior class distribution during the uncertainty estimation. Our experiments demonstrate that it improves the performance of the corresponding strategies. Similarly, we combined the score of NLU with the score of MU, to create the New Label and Model Uncertainty (NLMU) method.    We further empirically studied the performance of existing EM-based consensus algorithms and found all of the state-of-the-art algorithms ignore the potential bias characteristics of datasets and perform badly although they model the complexity of the systems. To address the issue of handling biased labeling, we proposed a novel consensus algorithm, namely adaptive weighted majority voting (AWMV), based on the statistical difference between the labeling qualities of the two classes.  To facilitate the research on mining the wisdom of crowds, we develop a novel software package named Crowd Environment and its Knowledge Analysis (CEKA), with the help from our undergraduate students. The main contribution of CEKA lies on three aspects. (1) It provides comprehensive functions, which not only includes a great number of ground truth inference algorithms with a uniform easy-to-use programming interface but also includes a lot of well-designed functions for the management of crowdsourced data. (2) It is seamlessly compatible with the famous machine learning tool WEKA, which facilitates the combination of the previous inference and the subsequent model learning procedures. (3) It is written in Java and completely open source. Therefore, many new ideas and methods, such as noise correction for crowdsourcing, are easily embedded in. The project CEKA is available at: http://ceka.sourceforge.net/.  The findings have impact on research areas such as visual recognition, natural language processing, and sentiment analysis. Under the support of this project, seven master’s students graduated. This project also attracted 16 undergraduate students to participate and conduct research on data mining and machine learning. Seven of them finished their undergraduate education with honor theses. Five students were from underrepresented groups, including four female students and an African student. A new graduate course, Advanced Data Mining, was developed.       Last Modified: 11/28/2019       Submitted by: Victor S Sheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
