<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Small: New and Improved Algorithms for Minimization and Subspace Tracking</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rahul Shah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Gram--Schmidt orthogonal factorization algorithm and the Golub--Kahan--Lanczos (GKL) bidiagonal reduction algorithm produce two fundamental factorizations for numerical linear algebra. Enhancements to these algorithm provide the foundation for the ``New and Improved Algorithms for Minimization and Subspace Tracking'' that are the subject of this proposal. These are both orthogonal factorization algorithms designed to produce bases for subspaces of interest and, for both algorithms, stability analyses are necessary to consider what is necessary to keep these bases orthogonal. The algorithms are also adapted to be based upon matrix--matrix operations, thereby making them implementable using the level-3 BLAS and sparse BLAS routine necessary to make them efficient on modern architectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Based upon the  new Gram--Schmidt and GKL procedures, regularized least squares and algorithms for tracking the leading principal subspace of a matrix are developed. Using discrete cosine and fast Fourier transform&lt;br/&gt;based preconditioners developed by the PI and collaborators in a previous NSF project, a regularized least squares algorithm is extended into a Newton--based regularized total least squares algorithm that is well suited to image deblurring problems.&lt;br/&gt;                                                                           &lt;br/&gt;The research on the block Gram--Schmidt and GKL bidiagonalization algorithms advance the scientific community's  knowledge of how to develop efficient software in modern computing environments for two fundamental algorithms in numerical linear algebra, a core field that straddles computational science and applied mathematics. The Gram--Schmidt algorithms are important in the development of iterative methods for the solution of large systems of linear equations arising in a long list of scientific and engineering disciplines. The GKL  bidiagonal reduction algorithm and subspace tracking work is useful in the numerous applications of dimension reduction within statistics, most notably web search algorithms.  Bidiagonal reduction is also a key component in the solution of the Netflix problem--the problem of identifying which films a customer would enjoy watching among a very large sample based upon a smaller sample of films which he/she has already rated. The image deblurring algorithms are important in the reconstruction of high-resolution images. These images, similar to those produced by high-resolution television, are expensive to transmit. The total least squares research develops an algorithm that would be useful in recovering a high-resolution image from cheaper-to-transmit lower resolution images.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1115704</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jesse</FirstName>
<LastName>Barlow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jesse L Barlow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barlow@cse.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148631705</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000406670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7933</Code>
<Text>NUM, SYMBOL, &amp; ALGEBRA COMPUT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~350000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit.</p> <p><br />The research followed two related tracks.</p> <p>In the first track, the project concerned the solution of total least squares problems that arise in image deblurring.This work, with a Ph.D. student and the help of one undergraduate honors student, &nbsp;resulted in two algorithms that &nbsp;are as efficient as anything in the current literature. The project also considered an update strategy for principal components.</p> <p><br />The second track concerned related fundamental issues in computational linear algebra: (1) on how maintainence of orthogonality in the Golub-Kahan-Lanczos (GKL) singular value algorithm is reflected in how the algorithm behaves in practice; (2) with Ivan Slapnicar and Nevena Jacovcevic-Stor, the PI did work that enhanced our understanding of the eigenvalues of symmetric arrow matrices--these arise in proper implementation of the GKL algorithm and several applications in physics; (3) &nbsp;with Alicja Smoktunowicz, the PI developed a block Gram-Schmidt algorithm that fits into two contexts in the first track--this work in important in the implementation of popular algorithms for very large linear systems such as GMRES.<br /><br />Broader Educational Impact.</p> <p><br />The educational impacts were the training of one Ph.D. student and postdoc, Dr. Geunseop Lee. Informally attached to thework of the project was one undergraduate honors student. The PI also introduced a course on numerical image processing at Penn State.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Broader Scientific Impact.</p> <p>The broader scientific impact of the research has been disseminated through research papers. The &nbsp;total least squares algorithms were developed with a high resolution image reconstruction &nbsp;problem in mind and this has potential impact in high definition television. The principal component update work was applied to the improvement of a classic object tracking algorithm.&nbsp;The GKL singular value work has applications in the broad spectrum of scientific fields that use principal components and the new Gram-Schmidt algorithms are important in the development of update algorithms for principal component approximations. The arrow matrix eigenvalue problem is useful in solving total least squares problems, in developing methods for symmetric tridiagonal eigenvalue problems, in Lanczos eigenvalue and singular value algorithms, and several problems in physics including &nbsp;radiationless transitions in isolated molecules, oscillators vibrationally coupled with a Fermi liquid, and quantum optics.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Jesse&nbsp;L&nbsp;Barlow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit.   The research followed two related tracks.  In the first track, the project concerned the solution of total least squares problems that arise in image deblurring.This work, with a Ph.D. student and the help of one undergraduate honors student,  resulted in two algorithms that  are as efficient as anything in the current literature. The project also considered an update strategy for principal components.   The second track concerned related fundamental issues in computational linear algebra: (1) on how maintainence of orthogonality in the Golub-Kahan-Lanczos (GKL) singular value algorithm is reflected in how the algorithm behaves in practice; (2) with Ivan Slapnicar and Nevena Jacovcevic-Stor, the PI did work that enhanced our understanding of the eigenvalues of symmetric arrow matrices--these arise in proper implementation of the GKL algorithm and several applications in physics; (3)  with Alicja Smoktunowicz, the PI developed a block Gram-Schmidt algorithm that fits into two contexts in the first track--this work in important in the implementation of popular algorithms for very large linear systems such as GMRES.  Broader Educational Impact.   The educational impacts were the training of one Ph.D. student and postdoc, Dr. Geunseop Lee. Informally attached to thework of the project was one undergraduate honors student. The PI also introduced a course on numerical image processing at Penn State.    Broader Scientific Impact.  The broader scientific impact of the research has been disseminated through research papers. The  total least squares algorithms were developed with a high resolution image reconstruction  problem in mind and this has potential impact in high definition television. The principal component update work was applied to the improvement of a classic object tracking algorithm. The GKL singular value work has applications in the broad spectrum of scientific fields that use principal components and the new Gram-Schmidt algorithms are important in the development of update algorithms for principal component approximations. The arrow matrix eigenvalue problem is useful in solving total least squares problems, in developing methods for symmetric tridiagonal eigenvalue problems, in Lanczos eigenvalue and singular value algorithms, and several problems in physics including  radiationless transitions in isolated molecules, oscillators vibrationally coupled with a Fermi liquid, and quantum optics.           Last Modified: 09/01/2015       Submitted by: Jesse L Barlow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
