<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Digitization TCN Collaborative Research: North American Lichens and Bryophytes: Sensitive Indicators of Environmental Quality and Change</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>292066.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>292066</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lichens and bryophytes share biological traits that make them some of the most sensitive indicators of environmental change. The goal of this project is to provide high quality data to address how species distributions change as a result of major environmental events across time and space. Specifically, this project will digitize the label information (the what, when, where and by whom collected) and images for approximately 2.3 million biological specimens curated in North American lichen and bryophyte herbaria. These collections represent well over 90% of all specimens collected in Canada, the United States and Mexico and held by over 60 US non-governmental institutions. New, on-line digitization techniques will be made publically available at at http://symbiota.org/nalichens/ and http://symbiota.org/bryophytes/, and will allow interested members of the public to be involved and learn about biodiversity alongside the professionals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Availability of nearly the entire North American bryophyte and lichen collections on-line will greatly accelerate knowledge and evaluation of the biodiversity of these organisms by fostering collaborations between professionals and the general public. Additionally, models developed from these digitized data will aid future mapping projections of large scale species distributions and identification of biodiversity hotspots as prime candidates for protection. These endeavors will help to elucidate regions where changes are imminent and likely to have substantial impact, as well as to facilitate proactive initiatives to alleviate such changes. This award is made as part of the National Resource for Digitization of Biological Collections through the Advancing Digitization of Biological Collections program and all data resulting from this award will be available through the national resource.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1115001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>A. Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Shaw</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>A. Jonathan Shaw</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shaw@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196607344</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196637</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francois</FirstName>
<LastName>Lutzoni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francois M Lutzoni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>flutzoni@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196607261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000254445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St, Suite 710]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>Digitization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>DIGITIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~292066</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this multi-institutional project was to database specimen records for bryophytes (mosses, liverworts, hornworts) and lichens, and make them publically searchable on the Bryophyte and Lichen Portals (<a href="http://bryophyteportal.org/">http://bryophyteportal.org/</a>; <a href="http://lichenportal.org/)">http://lichenportal.org/)</a>.&nbsp; &nbsp;More than 60 educational and research institutions collaborated on this project, with leadership from staff at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. The goal of the project was to database approximately 2.3 million specimen records to document the floras of North America, including Mexico, Puerto Rico, and Hawaii. Available data include taxonomic identifications, collection localities, and habitat information for each specimen.&nbsp; The data were gathered by directly transcribing information into the databases or by photographing specimen labels and then utilizing Optical Character Recognition (OCR) and Natural Language Processing (NLP) to populate the databases. The Duke University herbarium contains large collections of both bryophytes and lichens.&nbsp; Duke staff were responsible for databasing all North American specimens in the Duke herbarium.&nbsp; In addition, Duke staff were responsible for capturing data from five smaller herbaria in the eastern United States. These included collections in Binghamton University (NY), Towson University (MD), the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill (NC), the University of Richmond (VA), and the University of Tennessee (TN).&nbsp; Estimates prior to initiation of the project were a total of some 261,000 specimen records. By completion of the project, the Bryophyte and Lichen Portals contained over 400,000 records from these institutions.&nbsp; The database also includes over 200 plant images contributed by the Duke team.&nbsp; In addition, the project supported training of undergraduates, graduate students, and post-doctoral associates in herbarium curation and biodiversity informatics. Information gathered during the course of this project is critically important to a wide range of scientists including ecologists and biodiversity infomaticians, as well as governmental and nongovernmental conservation agencies.&nbsp; Members of the broader public interested in natural history and biodiversity also frequently access our digitally available resources. The Bryophyte and Lichen Portals include modules to encourage public participation, with links to additional sources of biodiversity data.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2016<br>      Modified by: A. Jonathan&nbsp;Shaw</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this multi-institutional project was to database specimen records for bryophytes (mosses, liverworts, hornworts) and lichens, and make them publically searchable on the Bryophyte and Lichen Portals (http://bryophyteportal.org/; http://lichenportal.org/).   More than 60 educational and research institutions collaborated on this project, with leadership from staff at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. The goal of the project was to database approximately 2.3 million specimen records to document the floras of North America, including Mexico, Puerto Rico, and Hawaii. Available data include taxonomic identifications, collection localities, and habitat information for each specimen.  The data were gathered by directly transcribing information into the databases or by photographing specimen labels and then utilizing Optical Character Recognition (OCR) and Natural Language Processing (NLP) to populate the databases. The Duke University herbarium contains large collections of both bryophytes and lichens.  Duke staff were responsible for databasing all North American specimens in the Duke herbarium.  In addition, Duke staff were responsible for capturing data from five smaller herbaria in the eastern United States. These included collections in Binghamton University (NY), Towson University (MD), the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill (NC), the University of Richmond (VA), and the University of Tennessee (TN).  Estimates prior to initiation of the project were a total of some 261,000 specimen records. By completion of the project, the Bryophyte and Lichen Portals contained over 400,000 records from these institutions.  The database also includes over 200 plant images contributed by the Duke team.  In addition, the project supported training of undergraduates, graduate students, and post-doctoral associates in herbarium curation and biodiversity informatics. Information gathered during the course of this project is critically important to a wide range of scientists including ecologists and biodiversity infomaticians, as well as governmental and nongovernmental conservation agencies.  Members of the broader public interested in natural history and biodiversity also frequently access our digitally available resources. The Bryophyte and Lichen Portals include modules to encourage public participation, with links to additional sources of biodiversity data.       Last Modified: 10/27/2016       Submitted by: A. Jonathan Shaw]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
