<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHB: Small: Machine Learning Models for Blood Glucose Prediction in Diabetes Management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>349999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>389999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to develop machine learning models that leverage underutilized data and account for individual patient differences to improve diabetes management. Diabetes is a chronic disease, which must be treated and managed over a lifetime. In type 1 diabetes, the pancreas does not produce insulin, an essential hormone needed to convert food into energy. The disease is treated with insulin and managed by monitoring and controlling blood glucose levels. Good blood glucose control is key to avoiding serious diabetic complications, but achieving and maintaining good blood glucose control is difficult. Patients are highly individual in their responses to treatment and to life events that affect blood glucose levels. Large volumes of blood glucose data are collected automatically, but automated analysis is lacking. Patients do not always know when problems are impending; problems occurring while patients are asleep are especially dangerous.  Machine learning models that predict blood glucose levels would enable or facilitate new applications of direct benefit to patients, including: alerts to immediately notify patients of impending problems; decision support systems recommending actions to prevent problems; and educational simulations showing the effects of different treatment choices or lifestyle options on blood glucose levels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The task of blood glucose prediction is approached as a time series forecasting problem. Blood glucose is predicted based on a patient's prior blood glucose levels, insulin data, meal data, exercise data, sleep patterns and work schedules. Batch and incremental time series regression models, including support vector machines and neural networks, are being investigated. To account for individual patient differences, separate models are trained for each patient. However, transfer learning may enable data from multiple patients to aid in building models for patients with limited historical data. Models are sought that are robust in the face of imperfect data, including missing life events, inaccurately recorded life events, and noisy glucose sensors. Disjoint sets of training and testing data extracted from non-overlapping time intervals are used to build models that are compared against baselines such as autoregressive integrated moving average models. Standard metrics for comparing models, such as root mean square error and coefficient of determination, will be supplemented with domain dependent measures of goodness, including the Clarke error grid.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work aims to improve the overall health and wellbeing of the nearly two million Americans with type 1 diabetes. Predicting blood glucose problems in advance gives patients time to take steps to prevent the predicted problems from occurring. This improves blood glucose control, which is known to reduce the risk of serious diabetic complications, including blindness, amputations, kidney disease, strokes, heart attacks, and death from severe hypoglycemia. In addition, this research project forms the cornerstone of a new Smart Health and Wellbeing Laboratory at Ohio University. This new laboratory is designed to promote further interdisciplinary research among computer scientists and health care professionals as well as to attract more women to careers in computer science. Additional information about the project and the laboratory is available at http://oucsace.cs.ohiou.edu/~marling/shb.html.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1117489</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Marling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cynthia R Marling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marling@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405931246</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000278414</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Razvan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bunescu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Razvan C Bunescu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rbunescu@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000515843</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwartz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank L Schwartz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schwartf@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405932857</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000576924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio University</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio University]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[108 CUTLER HL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~349999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~22000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~18000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>People with type 1 diabetes must continually monitor their blood glucose levels, trying to keep them as close to normal as possible.&nbsp; When blood glucose levels get too high, the risk of long-term diabetic complications increases.&nbsp; When they get too low, patients may experience immediate problems, including weakness, dizziness, nausea, shaking and sweating.&nbsp; If left untreated, low blood glucose levels can lead to seizures, coma, and even death.&nbsp; The goal of this research has been to predict blood glucose levels 30 and 60 minutes into the future, so that patients would be able to anticipate problems and take actions to prevent them. <br /><br />We have trained machine learning models to predict blood glucose levels in individuals with type 1 diabetes on insulin pump therapy.&nbsp; The models base their predictions on past blood glucose levels, insulin dosages, meals, and other events that occur in the everyday life of a patient.&nbsp; Data for the models comes from the patient's medical devices (insulin pump and continuous glucose monitoring system) and from self-reported life events.&nbsp; This data is pre-processed to obtain relevant features using physiological models of blood glucose behavior. Our best model to date makes predictions that are comparable to those of physicians who specialize in diabetes management.&nbsp; This is the first time that a machine learning model, using features derived from a physiological model, has been able to perform competitively with diabetes experts at this task.&nbsp; Once this milestone was achieved, we investigated how data from sensors in fitness trackers (heart rate, galvanic skin response, and skin temperature) could be used to improve blood glucose level prediction.&nbsp; We built data visualization software to consolidate and display the many different types of data that can impact blood glucose levels.&nbsp; While all of our models and software are experimental in nature, the Technology Transfer Office at Ohio University is exploring opportunities to scale up the technology and make it available to physicians and patients. <br /><br />As part of this project, the SmartHealth Lab was established at Ohio University to promote further research into how advanced computing technologies can be leveraged to improve health and wellbeing.&nbsp; The research conducted on blood glucose level prediction in the  SmartHealth Lab to date has shed light on additional promising  technologies that will be explored in future research.&nbsp; Finally, as part of NSF's Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program, three undergraduate students had the opportunity to conduct research in this new lab.&nbsp; <br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Cynthia&nbsp;R&nbsp;Marling</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1117489/1117489_10119461_1471534047531_prediction-plot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1117489/1117489_10119461_1471534047531_prediction-plot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Blood Glucose Level Prediction"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1117489/1117489_10119461_1471534047531_prediction-plot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Blood Glucose Level Prediction"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Knowing when blood glucose levels will be too high or too low allows patients to act to prevent these problems.  Blood glucose levels are predicted 30 and 60 minutes into the future.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Cynthia R Marling</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cynthia&nbsp;R&nbsp;Marling</div> <div class="imageTitle">Blood Glucose Level Prediction</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1117489/1117489_10119461_1471534891181_AI-team--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1117489/1117489_10119461_1471534891181_AI-team--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The SmartHealth Lab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1117489/1117489_10119461_1471534891181_AI-team--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The SmartHealth Lab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SmartHealth Lab members stand in front of a display of their new data visualization software.  The SmartHealth Lab was created as part of this project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Cynthia R Marling</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cynthia&nbsp;R&nbsp;Marling</div> <div class="imageTitle">The SmartHealth Lab</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ People with type 1 diabetes must continually monitor their blood glucose levels, trying to keep them as close to normal as possible.  When blood glucose levels get too high, the risk of long-term diabetic complications increases.  When they get too low, patients may experience immediate problems, including weakness, dizziness, nausea, shaking and sweating.  If left untreated, low blood glucose levels can lead to seizures, coma, and even death.  The goal of this research has been to predict blood glucose levels 30 and 60 minutes into the future, so that patients would be able to anticipate problems and take actions to prevent them.   We have trained machine learning models to predict blood glucose levels in individuals with type 1 diabetes on insulin pump therapy.  The models base their predictions on past blood glucose levels, insulin dosages, meals, and other events that occur in the everyday life of a patient.  Data for the models comes from the patient's medical devices (insulin pump and continuous glucose monitoring system) and from self-reported life events.  This data is pre-processed to obtain relevant features using physiological models of blood glucose behavior. Our best model to date makes predictions that are comparable to those of physicians who specialize in diabetes management.  This is the first time that a machine learning model, using features derived from a physiological model, has been able to perform competitively with diabetes experts at this task.  Once this milestone was achieved, we investigated how data from sensors in fitness trackers (heart rate, galvanic skin response, and skin temperature) could be used to improve blood glucose level prediction.  We built data visualization software to consolidate and display the many different types of data that can impact blood glucose levels.  While all of our models and software are experimental in nature, the Technology Transfer Office at Ohio University is exploring opportunities to scale up the technology and make it available to physicians and patients.   As part of this project, the SmartHealth Lab was established at Ohio University to promote further research into how advanced computing technologies can be leveraged to improve health and wellbeing.  The research conducted on blood glucose level prediction in the  SmartHealth Lab to date has shed light on additional promising  technologies that will be explored in future research.  Finally, as part of NSF's Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program, three undergraduate students had the opportunity to conduct research in this new lab.           Last Modified: 08/19/2016       Submitted by: Cynthia R Marling]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
