<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS:  Small:  Inducing and Exploiting Spectrum Predictability via Traffic Shaping and Mobility for Cognitive Communication in White Space</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>429864.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>429864</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Spectrum opportunities in white space hinge heavily on the traffic patterns of the licensed users (PUs), and vary across space, time, and frequency. Making a paradigm shift,  this project advocates to leverage traffic shaping and mobility patterns of PUs for  inducing predictable structures of spectrum holes in the spatio-temporal domain, which in turn enables more efficient spectrum access by cognitive radio users. With such a common thread, this project will 1) study joint traffic shaping and network coding for PUs, as a spectrum shaper, to induce predictive structures in spectrum holes; 2) investigate SUs? cognitive transmissions via adaptive file fragmentation and predetermined file fragmentation that can match the characteristics of spectrum opportunities discovered on the fly; and 3) explore cognitive routing via exploiting PU-mobility predictability.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Efficient spectrum usage will facilitate a wide variety of scientific and engineering applications and result in a significant impact on the society at large. This research will open a new direction for spectrum shaping that induces predictable structures of spectrum opportunities, which can then be exploited by SUs for effective cognitive communications. The findings will advance the state-of-the-art of cognitive radio networking and spur a new line of thinking.  Another major task of this project is to integrate research with educational activities. In particular, the PIs will continue to involve under-represented and minority students in research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1117462</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Junshan</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Junshan Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>junshan.zhang@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807277389</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yanchao</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yanchao Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yczhang@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807270039</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000495163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ORSPA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~429864</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Spectrum opportunities in white space hinge heavily on the traffic patterns of the licensed users (PUs), and vary across space, time, and frequency. Making a paradigm shift,&nbsp; this project advocates to leverage traffic shaping and mobility patterns of PUs for inducing predictable structures of spectrum holes in the spatio-temporal domain, which in turn enables more efficient spectrum access by cognitive radio users.</p> <p>Under this common theme, research findings can be summarized &nbsp;as follows: 1) Opportunistic spectrum scheduling is devised based on jointly exploiting channel correlation and PU traffic memory, by<span>&nbsp;formulating the problem as a partially observable Markov decision process</span>; 2)&nbsp;<span>greedy approximation algorithms are devised based on j</span>oint sensing and subband Allocation for spectrum profiling; 3) &nbsp;crowdsourced spectrum misuse detection, named&nbsp;<span>SpecGuard, is investigated &nbsp;by embedding and detecting a spectrum permit at the physical layer; 4)</span>&nbsp;<span>SafeDSA, a</span>PHY-based approach, is devised for authenticating secondary users in dynamic spectrum systems,&nbsp;</p> <p>Efficient spectrum usage will facilitate a wide variety of scientific and engineering applications and result in a significant impact on the society at large. These research findings will open a new direction for spectrum shaping that induces predictable structures of spectrum opportunities, Another major accomplishment of this project is to integrate research with educational activities and train graduate students for workforce in wireless industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2015<br>      Modified by: Junshan&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Spectrum opportunities in white space hinge heavily on the traffic patterns of the licensed users (PUs), and vary across space, time, and frequency. Making a paradigm shift,  this project advocates to leverage traffic shaping and mobility patterns of PUs for inducing predictable structures of spectrum holes in the spatio-temporal domain, which in turn enables more efficient spectrum access by cognitive radio users.  Under this common theme, research findings can be summarized  as follows: 1) Opportunistic spectrum scheduling is devised based on jointly exploiting channel correlation and PU traffic memory, by formulating the problem as a partially observable Markov decision process; 2) greedy approximation algorithms are devised based on joint sensing and subband Allocation for spectrum profiling; 3)  crowdsourced spectrum misuse detection, named SpecGuard, is investigated  by embedding and detecting a spectrum permit at the physical layer; 4) SafeDSA, aPHY-based approach, is devised for authenticating secondary users in dynamic spectrum systems,   Efficient spectrum usage will facilitate a wide variety of scientific and engineering applications and result in a significant impact on the society at large. These research findings will open a new direction for spectrum shaping that induces predictable structures of spectrum opportunities, Another major accomplishment of this project is to integrate research with educational activities and train graduate students for workforce in wireless industry.          Last Modified: 08/31/2015       Submitted by: Junshan Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
