<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Small: Applied Algorithims: Tech Transfer from the Algorithims Toolbox II</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tracy Kimbrel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkimbrel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927924</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the past decades, the field of algorithms has developed a toolbox of theoretical techniques that let computer systems to do more with less---to solve harder problems more quickly, using less memory, less communication with other computers, and less of a human user's assistance.  One measure of algorithms' research success has been the large number of implemented systems whose designs have been impacted by contributions from the algorithms community.  There are many more such successes waiting in the wings for individuals or groups who can draw the connection between an existing algorithmic technique and an existing applied problem.  Often, the biggest challenge is recognizing the connection between the practitioner's problem statement and the proper algorithmic solution techniques.  This research addresses the process of ``technology transfer'' from the algorithmic toolbox to other computer science domains.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator is working closely with practitioners in various areas of computer science to identify computational problems whose efficient solution would advance their research agendas, dig through the theory toolbox to find techniques that, properly adapted, can be used to efficiently solve those problems, and assist in such adaptation.  Domains being addressed include natural language processing, detection of influence pathways in biological networks, traffic route planning that accounts for uncertain delays, network coding for efficient use of communication bandwidth, and efficient use of crowdsourced computation.  But rather than being driven by a particular problem domain, the investigator is interested in the overall process for applying theoretical work in algorithms to problems in the practical domain, and is always seeking new applied problems that can benefit from this approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful completion of the proposed work will contribute advancement to many different branches of computer science.  The contributions to other branches of computer science will, in turn, allow them to achieve their goals of broad impact on society.  The investigator also hopes to increase the general sense of connection between theoreticians and practitioners, yielding increased collaborations and successful applications of algorithms to theory beyond those made directly during this project.  The project will contribute to research training by continuing to employ large numbers of students with attention given to gender diversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1117381</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Karger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David R Karger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>karger@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172586167</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7926</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aimed to apply techniques from the theoretical analysis of algorithms to problems arising in practice.&nbsp; It succeeded on a number of fronts.&nbsp;</p> <p>We made several advances in the domain of crowdsourcing, a new field that explores the way the Web enables massive crowds to works together on massive tasks such as classifying images, captioning video, constructing large information databases, or making recommendations.&nbsp; We applied mathematical methods to improve the way crowdsourcing systems (such as Amazon's mechanical turk) assign workers to tasks (to provide rapid high quality responses) and identify and correct the inevitable errors/wrong answers that crop up when large numbers of people are working on a large problem.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also made further advances in the area of network coding, a relatively new technique for broadcasting information to large numbers of recipients that makes more efficient use of available network bandwidth.&nbsp;&nbsp; Our techniques reduce the amount of (costly) network that needs to be deployed in order to provide a certain level of service or, conversely, allow better service to be achieved for a given amount of network capacity.</p> <p>Finally, we've made important advances in the study of network reliability.&nbsp; This domain is concerned with assessing the chance of networks becomming disconnected due to random component failure. Our work significantly simplifies and speeds up procedures for determining network reliability, and thus provide tools to help network designers assess the quality of their networks and ensure that they can provide the desired level of service.</p> <p>In all three cases, our work advanced knowledge (Intellectual Merit) by developing new algorithms and theories for these problems, which may find further use in other related problems.&nbsp; At the same time, all three lines of work offer the potential for advancement of society (Broader Impact) as they provide improved techniques for solving a variety of problems that people encounter in their work.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;R&nbsp;Karger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aimed to apply techniques from the theoretical analysis of algorithms to problems arising in practice.  It succeeded on a number of fronts.   We made several advances in the domain of crowdsourcing, a new field that explores the way the Web enables massive crowds to works together on massive tasks such as classifying images, captioning video, constructing large information databases, or making recommendations.  We applied mathematical methods to improve the way crowdsourcing systems (such as Amazon's mechanical turk) assign workers to tasks (to provide rapid high quality responses) and identify and correct the inevitable errors/wrong answers that crop up when large numbers of people are working on a large problem.   We also made further advances in the area of network coding, a relatively new technique for broadcasting information to large numbers of recipients that makes more efficient use of available network bandwidth.   Our techniques reduce the amount of (costly) network that needs to be deployed in order to provide a certain level of service or, conversely, allow better service to be achieved for a given amount of network capacity.  Finally, we've made important advances in the study of network reliability.  This domain is concerned with assessing the chance of networks becomming disconnected due to random component failure. Our work significantly simplifies and speeds up procedures for determining network reliability, and thus provide tools to help network designers assess the quality of their networks and ensure that they can provide the desired level of service.  In all three cases, our work advanced knowledge (Intellectual Merit) by developing new algorithms and theories for these problems, which may find further use in other related problems.  At the same time, all three lines of work offer the potential for advancement of society (Broader Impact) as they provide improved techniques for solving a variety of problems that people encounter in their work.       Last Modified: 12/01/2016       Submitted by: David R Karger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
