<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: Small:  Adaptive Network Coding for Wireless Relay Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>416603.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>416603</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Network coding has demonstrated to be very effective in increasing wireless network capacity and reliability. However, the benefits of network coding are only applicable in networks consisting of reliable and trustworthy nodes. Non-negligible network coding (NC) noise and network pollution can cause substantial performance decrease. There is a cogent need for adaptive network coding schemes that can optimize network level throughput by exploiting NC noise and NC pollution. This research develops efficient adaptive model that can provide optimal network level throughput by designing of adaptive network coding schemes, pollution detection model, and joint treatment of coding and dynamic routing. The overall objective is threefold. First, it develops adaptive characteristic model and efficient estimation on the NC noise and NC pollution. Based on this, novel on-the-fly adaptive network coding schemes are developed. Second, this research develops theoretical characterization and effective pollution detection and immunization schemes in relay networks through source privacy protection. Third, this research establishes the mathematical structure for the wireless relay node, and designs cost function for optimal throughput computation. Based on this, provably optimal algorithms with polynomial time complexity are developed under the given pollution constraint and security requirement. In addition, this project also includes a significant education component aimed at integrating frontier research with undergraduate and graduate curricula.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1117831</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tongtong</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tongtong Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tongli@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173557688</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000353453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jian Ren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>renjian@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173534379</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000351707</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~416603</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Network coding (NC) is being viewed as a new communication paradigm that can greatly improve the throughout of the existing networks. &nbsp;However, the salient advantages of network coding are only possible when the network nodes are reliable and trustworthy. To prevent the network pollution propagation and retain the benefits of NC, this research focuses on pollution detection and pollution correction techniques. Our research results can be summarized as follows:</p> <p><br />1. We designed schemes to detect network pollution in the exact node where the pollution occurred. &nbsp;Network coding provides a design tradeoff between network throughput and computation. Unfortunately, the computational operation makes the diagram vulnerable to pollution attacks, which can dramatically reduce the network throughput. In this research, we developed schemes that can detect the pollutions to be detected at exactly where they occurred before propagation to the subsequent nodes. This approach can optimize the capacity and likelihood for the pollution to be cancelled to retain the benefits of NC.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />2. We developed adaptive network coding schemes to optimize network level throughput. &nbsp;This is achieved through a combination of optimal coding scheme design, network topology and dynamic relay selection strategy. &nbsp;While optimizing the network throughput under pollution attacks and malicious attacks, this design can also improved the network performance and communication privacy.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Jian&nbsp;Ren</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Network coding (NC) is being viewed as a new communication paradigm that can greatly improve the throughout of the existing networks.  However, the salient advantages of network coding are only possible when the network nodes are reliable and trustworthy. To prevent the network pollution propagation and retain the benefits of NC, this research focuses on pollution detection and pollution correction techniques. Our research results can be summarized as follows:   1. We designed schemes to detect network pollution in the exact node where the pollution occurred.  Network coding provides a design tradeoff between network throughput and computation. Unfortunately, the computational operation makes the diagram vulnerable to pollution attacks, which can dramatically reduce the network throughput. In this research, we developed schemes that can detect the pollutions to be detected at exactly where they occurred before propagation to the subsequent nodes. This approach can optimize the capacity and likelihood for the pollution to be cancelled to retain the benefits of NC.    2. We developed adaptive network coding schemes to optimize network level throughput.  This is achieved through a combination of optimal coding scheme design, network topology and dynamic relay selection strategy.  While optimizing the network throughput under pollution attacks and malicious attacks, this design can also improved the network performance and communication privacy.           Last Modified: 10/03/2016       Submitted by: Jian Ren]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
