<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Great Earthquakes, Megathrust Phenomenology and Continental Dynamics in the Southern Andes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>720000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>720000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dennis Geist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dgeist@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924361</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The overall goal of the project is to understand the processes that created and now drive evolution of the modern Andes.  In order to do that, we must understand the spatial and temporal variability of stresses generated in the upper plate by coupling at the plate interface and by viscous drag of the asthenosphere.  Specifically,  the project will focus on the 2010 Mw 8.8 Maule earthquake in Chile, the earthquake cycle along the Nazca-South America plate interface, orogenesis of the Andean system, and its relationship to crustal deformation and mantle flow.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is structured around two main themes:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;? How does megathrust  phenomenology influence or control the architecture, from forearc to backarc, of the Andean orogeny? &lt;br/&gt;? How do geological materials, shallow structure and slab/mantle dynamics influence or control the behavior and evolution of the megathrust? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI group will use GPS and INSAR to examine post-seismic transients and combine these with co-seismic data. They will combine many sources of GPS data (German - GFZ and US groups) that have been collected from 1993 to present over the entire orogen in an effort to develop a synoptic model. This includes data from 33 cGPS stations installed in Chile with NSF-RAPID funds immediately following the Maule earthquake.  The regional extent of new analysis will include the rupture zone from the 1960 Mw 9.5 earthquake, which still shows post-seismic transient deformation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Among the important geodynamic processes that the project will address are (1) time-variable deformation in the aftermath of a great subduction-zone earthquake; (2) improved models of plate interface rheology and their implications for plate boundary earthquake cycles; and (3) interaction between plate boundary and intraplate deformation over time-scales from decadal to geological. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to GPS and InSAR observation of surface deformation, the project brings to bear a number of state-of-the-art observational and modeling approaches;  earthquake location and source mechanism determination; geological and geochemical constraints on uplift and erosion rates; inversion for geometric and rheological parameters associated with the plate interface; and large-scale geodynamic modeling. The investigator team is highly qualified to take on these activities, and has a strong track record in previous work in the area. They have developed a strong set of collaborations, both in-country and with other international researchers working in the area.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1118239</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gurnis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Gurnis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gurnis@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956979</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000094280</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Simons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Simons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>simons@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956984</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000450622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean-Philippe</FirstName>
<LastName>Avouac</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean-Philippe Avouac</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>avouac@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956073</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487423</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/28/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1581</Code>
<Text>CONTINENTAL DYNAMICS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~340000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~380000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project explored the dynamics of subduction plate boundaries, specifically the South America / Nazca plate boundary across time scales that spanned those of individual large earthquakes and the month/years immediately following the earthquake all the way to the million year time scale of large scale plate motions. &nbsp;More specifically, we focussed on the magnitude &gt; 8 earthquakes in 2010 and 2014 that ruptured the plate interface and induced considerable postseismic deformation and showed how the coseismic and postseismic fault slip mosaic the fault. &nbsp;</p> <p>We also improved our methods of making the fundemental space geodetic measurement from which we can infer the behavior of the major faults. &nbsp;These improvements focussed on the use of atmospheric models to reduce the impact of temporal and spatial variations in atmsopheric water content on the accuracy of measurements of ground deformation.&nbsp;</p> <p>In terms of longer time scale processes, we developed the essential components of a modeling framework to use the history of plate motion to improve our understanding of the mechanical nature of the earth's interior. &nbsp;We then used these tools to explore the mechanical properties of different subduction zones, comparing those that are seismogenic to those that are relatively aseismic. &nbsp;</p> <p>All of these research efforts are developing and expanding our abilities to exploit large scale computational resources to answer fundemental scientific questions in Earth sciences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Simons</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project explored the dynamics of subduction plate boundaries, specifically the South America / Nazca plate boundary across time scales that spanned those of individual large earthquakes and the month/years immediately following the earthquake all the way to the million year time scale of large scale plate motions.  More specifically, we focussed on the magnitude &gt; 8 earthquakes in 2010 and 2014 that ruptured the plate interface and induced considerable postseismic deformation and showed how the coseismic and postseismic fault slip mosaic the fault.    We also improved our methods of making the fundemental space geodetic measurement from which we can infer the behavior of the major faults.  These improvements focussed on the use of atmospheric models to reduce the impact of temporal and spatial variations in atmsopheric water content on the accuracy of measurements of ground deformation.   In terms of longer time scale processes, we developed the essential components of a modeling framework to use the history of plate motion to improve our understanding of the mechanical nature of the earth's interior.  We then used these tools to explore the mechanical properties of different subduction zones, comparing those that are seismogenic to those that are relatively aseismic.    All of these research efforts are developing and expanding our abilities to exploit large scale computational resources to answer fundemental scientific questions in Earth sciences.       Last Modified: 11/23/2016       Submitted by: Mark Simons]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
