<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Teacher Education: Learning the Practice of Statistics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>396415.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>396415</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fsloane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This exploratory project is to enhance the ability of teachers to provide high quality STEM education for all students by developing research-based materials that enable teachers to facilitate students' progress toward statistical understanding.  The exploratory project has two phases. The first phase will focus on modeling student learning of difficult statistical concepts by constructing and developing a set of student learning progressions.  Informed by the first phase, the second phase will focus on developing, implementing, supporting, and pilot testing instructional materials for teachers aimed at increasing knowledge and effective practice of statistical concepts. Formative and summative assessments will be used to evaluate (a) the materials, (b) the participant activities and experiences with the materials, and (c) the implementation process. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Both Common Core State Standards for Mathematics and National Council of Teachers of Mathematics standards clearly recommend the emphasis of statistics education in K-12 schools.  In recent years, researchers have started to explore issues related to statistics education in Grades K-8, but little work has been done at the high school level.  This exploratory project addresses a critical need in mathematics education and fills an important gap in teacher education related to high school statistics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1119016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Haddock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John R Haddock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhaddock@memphis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9016782482</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000299203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/28/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Bargagliotti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna E Bargagliotti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Anna.Bargagliotti@lmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3103384582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489477</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Celia</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Celia Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>croussea@memphis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9016785759</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000525930</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Conley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark W Conley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mwconley@memphis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9016782365</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000549412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Loyola Marymount University</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900452659</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3103384599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One LMU Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[University Hall, Ste 3000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>43</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA43</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072946239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOYOLA MARYMOUNT UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072946239</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Memphis]]></Name>
<CityName>Memphis</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>381523370</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Administration 315]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~396415</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aims to&nbsp;<em>develop</em><em>&nbsp;</em>innovative curricular materials to enhance the ability of high-school teachers to foster students&rsquo; statistical learning. These materials are useful for teacher preparation institutions, school districts, professional development programs, and individuals interested in furthering their own statistical knowledge. All materials are geared towards helping high-school teachers implement the&nbsp;<em>Common Core Standards</em>&nbsp;for statistics as well as closely align with the learning goals outlined in the&nbsp;<em>Guidelines for Assessment and Instruction in Statistics Education: A Pre-K&ndash;12 Curriculum Framework</em>&nbsp;(GAISE) report.</p> <p>The&nbsp;<em>goal</em><em>&nbsp;</em>of Project-SET is to address the challenge of enhancing the ability of teachers to provide high quality STEM education for all students by developing a model of research-based practices that enable teachers to facilitate students&rsquo; progress toward statistical understanding.</p> <p>The project impact and intellectual merit can be summarized by the following points:</p> <ol> <li>The project gathered evidence to support the idea that teacher learning trajectories can offer an effective way to structure professional development.</li> <li>The project uncovered that teachers struggle with statistical concepts in the Common Core State Standards. In particular, the use of simulations is an important technique emphasized in the standards with which teachers struggle. The project found that teachers are not familiar with and not accustomed to using simulations. </li> <li>The project focused extensive efforts on disseminating the results thus trying to make an impact on teacher education of statistics. This directly influences and provides guidance for statistical professional development for teachers.</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2015<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;E&nbsp;Bargagliotti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aims to develop innovative curricular materials to enhance the ability of high-school teachers to foster studentsÆ statistical learning. These materials are useful for teacher preparation institutions, school districts, professional development programs, and individuals interested in furthering their own statistical knowledge. All materials are geared towards helping high-school teachers implement the Common Core Standards for statistics as well as closely align with the learning goals outlined in the Guidelines for Assessment and Instruction in Statistics Education: A Pre-K&ndash;12 Curriculum Framework (GAISE) report.  The goal of Project-SET is to address the challenge of enhancing the ability of teachers to provide high quality STEM education for all students by developing a model of research-based practices that enable teachers to facilitate studentsÆ progress toward statistical understanding.  The project impact and intellectual merit can be summarized by the following points:  The project gathered evidence to support the idea that teacher learning trajectories can offer an effective way to structure professional development. The project uncovered that teachers struggle with statistical concepts in the Common Core State Standards. In particular, the use of simulations is an important technique emphasized in the standards with which teachers struggle. The project found that teachers are not familiar with and not accustomed to using simulations.  The project focused extensive efforts on disseminating the results thus trying to make an impact on teacher education of statistics. This directly influences and provides guidance for statistical professional development for teachers.           Last Modified: 12/14/2015       Submitted by: Anna E Bargagliotti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
