<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Southern Amazonian birds and their symbionts: Biodiversity and endemicity of parasites from the most diverse avifauna on Earth</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>263700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project involves several parasitologists from the USA, Brazil, Bulgaria, and Ukraine that will collaborate to survey, study, describe, and archive parasites associated with birds in five geographically isolated regions (areas of endemism) of southern Amazonian Brazil.  The research will involve collection and deposition of museum specimens for research and will use both physical characteristics and genetic data from both the birds and their parasites to describe this poorly known segment of biological diversity in the world's richest ecosystem.  At over 6.5 million km2, Amazonia is estimated to harbor more than one tenth of the world's species. Brazilian Amazonia harbors the most diverse bird fauna on earth (~1300 species), yet the parasite fauna of Amazonian birds is almost completely unstudied.  Parasites are incredibly diverse and make up 30-70% of life on earth.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has a number of important societal benefits. First, this work fosters international collaboration between US and Brazilian researchers and students, who will travel between these institutions to teach, learn, work, and collaborate to further the understanding of birds and their parasites.  Training of a diverse pool (including underrepresented groups) of US and Brazilian graduate and undergraduate students will augment the diminishing pool of expertise working on understudied parasite groups.  This study also will have long-term value because parasites are known to have important consequences on the health, behavior, demography, and evolution of their hosts (including humans and other animals).  Parasites are known to cause or spread disease among and between hosts.  Thus, through modern approaches to gathering and archiving the material collected, this study will employ cutting edge research to make substantial lasting contributions to our knowledge of the diversity, distribution, and evolutionary history, of avian parasites in Amazonia, and therefore will have important human and wildlife health implications far into the future.  Lastly, this research is a novel collaborative effort to gather data needed to conserve the biodiversity of the Amazon, the richest fauna on earth.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1120734</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vasyl</FirstName>
<LastName>Tkach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vasyl V Tkach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vasyl.tkach@und.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7017774675</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000403494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Dakota Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Grand Forks</CityName>
<ZipCode>582027306</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7017774151</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>264 Centennial Dr Stop 7306</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>102280781</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH DAKOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>102280781</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Dakota Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Grand Forks</CityName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<ZipCode>582027306</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[264 Centennial Dr Stop 7306]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>At over 6.5 million km2, Amazonia is estimated to harbor more than one tenth of the world&rsquo;s species. Amazonia has the most diverse bird fauna on earth yet the parasite fauna of Amazonian birds was very little studied. Considering that parasites are extremely diverse and make up 30-70% of life on earth, this was a substantial gap in knowledge. This international collaboration provided an opportunity to document these groups of organisms and build collections and capacity to understand their diversity through research now and into the future.</p> <p>During the project, PIs, students, and collaborators conducted five joint expeditions in southern Amazonian Brazil and Peru to collect birds and their parasites to study and characterize the biodiversity of parasites and other symbiotic organisms living on and in birds from one of the most biodiverse regions of the world.&nbsp; Brazilian collaborators and postdocs independently collected additional material that was also available for the joint research outcomes of the project.&nbsp; In total, 22 papers authored by the PIs and student trainees have been published and several more are submitted and in preparation. Among these research outcomes are research papers describing 3 new bird species and 17 new multicellular parasite species. Blood sporozoan (&rdquo;avian malaria&rdquo;) dataset amassed during the project contained more than 300 new genetic lineages of these protists. Materials from the project have been also used in a variety of ecological, biogeographical and phylogenetic studies. Project participants published protocols for comprehensive examination of birds for parasites as well as a new, optimized protocols for screening bird blood and tissue samples for sporozoans using a combination of real time and nested polymerase chain reactions.</p> <p>Numerous broader impacts have come out of the project as well.&nbsp; Students were active participants at all stages of this work. At the University of North Dakota alone the project has directly benefitted the training of 4 graduate students, 8 undergraduate students, and 4 high school students. All students have been trained in numerous classical and modern parasitological techniques. Several of them presented the results of this work at scientific meetings and/or published in peer reviewed journals. PI Tkach also trained several visiting researchers and students from universities in the United States, Brazil and Venezuela. During the project, hundreds of UND undergraduate students learned about these parasites and the project in PI Tkach&rsquo;s classes. A significant number of students and 4 postdocs were involved in the project in collaborating institutions. Thousands of data rich bird and parasite specimens have been deposited in the collections at the Field Museum, Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University, Museu Goeldi, and Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de S&atilde;o Paulo. An educational website for public engagement is on the http://expeditions.fieldmuseum.org/ site, and a web application has been developed to manage parasite biodiversity survey data (ParaSite: www.parasite.fieldmuseum.org). At the 2013 American Ornithologists Union Meeting, PIs Weckstein and Tkach taught a workshop on methods for collecting and studying bird parasites. PI Tkach has given presentations to academic audiences at 6 universities in Brazil (2015) and Peru (2016) and offered 2 workshops in two different universities in Peru.</p> <p>Lastly, this research project fostered and significantly broadened the international collaborative web of researchers for all project participants.&nbsp; For example, at the initiation of the project we did not have a collaborating Brazilian endoparasitologist.&nbsp; However, our work down in Brazil provided opportunities for an additional Brazilian faculty/postdoc collaborators and students to join research expeditions and participate in collaborative research projects. We anticipate that these new collaborations will provide exciting opportunities for future collaborative projects.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Vasyl&nbsp;V&nbsp;Tkach</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1120734/1120734_10099209_1509475884946_Figurefinal--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1120734/1120734_10099209_1509475884946_Figurefinal--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1120734/1120734_10099209_1509475884946_Figurefinal--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A. Royal flycatcher Onychorhynchus coronatus. B.Chestnut woodpecker Celeus elegans. C. Josh Engel recording bird songs. D. Vasyl Tkach training students in Peru. E. Nematode Subulura travassosi. F. New digenean species Mosesia ovalis. G. New species and genus of digeneans, family Renschtrematidae.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Vasyl Tkach</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Vasyl&nbsp;V&nbsp;Tkach</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ At over 6.5 million km2, Amazonia is estimated to harbor more than one tenth of the world?s species. Amazonia has the most diverse bird fauna on earth yet the parasite fauna of Amazonian birds was very little studied. Considering that parasites are extremely diverse and make up 30-70% of life on earth, this was a substantial gap in knowledge. This international collaboration provided an opportunity to document these groups of organisms and build collections and capacity to understand their diversity through research now and into the future.  During the project, PIs, students, and collaborators conducted five joint expeditions in southern Amazonian Brazil and Peru to collect birds and their parasites to study and characterize the biodiversity of parasites and other symbiotic organisms living on and in birds from one of the most biodiverse regions of the world.  Brazilian collaborators and postdocs independently collected additional material that was also available for the joint research outcomes of the project.  In total, 22 papers authored by the PIs and student trainees have been published and several more are submitted and in preparation. Among these research outcomes are research papers describing 3 new bird species and 17 new multicellular parasite species. Blood sporozoan ("avian malaria") dataset amassed during the project contained more than 300 new genetic lineages of these protists. Materials from the project have been also used in a variety of ecological, biogeographical and phylogenetic studies. Project participants published protocols for comprehensive examination of birds for parasites as well as a new, optimized protocols for screening bird blood and tissue samples for sporozoans using a combination of real time and nested polymerase chain reactions.  Numerous broader impacts have come out of the project as well.  Students were active participants at all stages of this work. At the University of North Dakota alone the project has directly benefitted the training of 4 graduate students, 8 undergraduate students, and 4 high school students. All students have been trained in numerous classical and modern parasitological techniques. Several of them presented the results of this work at scientific meetings and/or published in peer reviewed journals. PI Tkach also trained several visiting researchers and students from universities in the United States, Brazil and Venezuela. During the project, hundreds of UND undergraduate students learned about these parasites and the project in PI Tkach?s classes. A significant number of students and 4 postdocs were involved in the project in collaborating institutions. Thousands of data rich bird and parasite specimens have been deposited in the collections at the Field Museum, Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University, Museu Goeldi, and Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de S&atilde;o Paulo. An educational website for public engagement is on the http://expeditions.fieldmuseum.org/ site, and a web application has been developed to manage parasite biodiversity survey data (ParaSite: www.parasite.fieldmuseum.org). At the 2013 American Ornithologists Union Meeting, PIs Weckstein and Tkach taught a workshop on methods for collecting and studying bird parasites. PI Tkach has given presentations to academic audiences at 6 universities in Brazil (2015) and Peru (2016) and offered 2 workshops in two different universities in Peru.  Lastly, this research project fostered and significantly broadened the international collaborative web of researchers for all project participants.  For example, at the initiation of the project we did not have a collaborating Brazilian endoparasitologist.  However, our work down in Brazil provided opportunities for an additional Brazilian faculty/postdoc collaborators and students to join research expeditions and participate in collaborative research projects. We anticipate that these new collaborations will provide exciting opportunities for future collaborative projects.       Last Modified: 10/31/2017       Submitted by: Vasyl V Tkach]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
