<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Phylogeography in Madagascar - Using ants to test hypotheses of biotic diversification in a model continent</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>325399.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>331679</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The tropical regions of the world house a disproportionately high amount of the world's biodiversity. Though the reasons for this are not well understood, a number of hypotheses have sought to explain these high rates of speciation; most focusing on the well-studied biota of the Neotropics. The goal of this research project is to better understand biotic diversification in the tropics by focusing on Madagascar, a natural laboratory for such work. Due to its isolation, Madagascar is well suited to explore how organisms diverge and persist in fragmented habitats without the confounding influence of migration to or from adjacent areas. The researchers will study speciation of ants, which as a group, are younger than the island itself. Thus all 700+ species known from Madagascar are derived from transoceanic colonists, whose speciation and diversification on the island has left a genetic signature of these processes in their descendants. By employing molecular data and genomic methods the scientists will explore the history and the factors influencing the diversification of Malagasy ants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This high diversity in Madagascar, the comprehensive sampling of the endemic ants, and the availability of newly developed, low-cost DNA sequencing technologies will allow this study to test recent advances in methods of ecological niche modeling, delimiting species, and inferring relationships. These data also will allow rigorous testing of existing hypotheses of biotic diversification and examination of whether temporal and ecological commonalities exist in patterns observed among taxa. This will be one of the broadest assessments of tropical diversification to date and will greatly enhance understanding of 1) the biological history of Madagascar, 2) the role of landscape features and environmental change on biological diversification, and 3) the extent to which modeling methods can contribute to the delimitation of distinct species.  The project will train graduate and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1121080</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brice</FirstName>
<LastName>Noonan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brice P Noonan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bnoonan@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6629156705</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000484295</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Mississippi</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6629157482</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 BARR HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 1848]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>067713560</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSISSIPPI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067713560</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Mississippi]]></Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 BARR HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~325399</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research project explored the patterns of ant biodiversity and evolution on the island of Madagascar. Though our understanding of the geological history of this incredible island is relatively well established, the factors that led to the remarkable level of biological diversity and endemism (spcies found only on Madagascar) remain a mystery.</p> <p>By utilizing the enormous collection of Malagasy ants at the California Academy of Science we were able to apply cutting-edge molecular techniques to the exploration of the evolutionary history of an incredibly diverse (more than 2,000 species!) radiation of a keystone group (one critically important for ecosystem function). Ants are particularly suitable for such a project as they represent an ancient lineage for which many 'living fossils' remain on Madagascar and they have a wide variety of life histories (wet vs. dry habitat, winged vs. wingless).</p> <p>Our findings touched on a number of aspects of ant evolution, perhaps the most surprising of these was our ability to resolve the ant tree of life with some surprising refinements to previously reported hypotheses. The exploration of genetic patterns within lineages provided remarkable insight into what is clearly a diverse biota whose species numbers have been vastly underestimated. This diversity appears to be highly correlated with life-history strategies and will greatly inform our approach to disentangeling the evolutionary history of the tropics and the process of prioritizing areas for conservation efforts.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/07/2017<br>      Modified by: Brice&nbsp;P&nbsp;Noonan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research project explored the patterns of ant biodiversity and evolution on the island of Madagascar. Though our understanding of the geological history of this incredible island is relatively well established, the factors that led to the remarkable level of biological diversity and endemism (spcies found only on Madagascar) remain a mystery.  By utilizing the enormous collection of Malagasy ants at the California Academy of Science we were able to apply cutting-edge molecular techniques to the exploration of the evolutionary history of an incredibly diverse (more than 2,000 species!) radiation of a keystone group (one critically important for ecosystem function). Ants are particularly suitable for such a project as they represent an ancient lineage for which many 'living fossils' remain on Madagascar and they have a wide variety of life histories (wet vs. dry habitat, winged vs. wingless).  Our findings touched on a number of aspects of ant evolution, perhaps the most surprising of these was our ability to resolve the ant tree of life with some surprising refinements to previously reported hypotheses. The exploration of genetic patterns within lineages provided remarkable insight into what is clearly a diverse biota whose species numbers have been vastly underestimated. This diversity appears to be highly correlated with life-history strategies and will greatly inform our approach to disentangeling the evolutionary history of the tropics and the process of prioritizing areas for conservation efforts.        Last Modified: 03/07/2017       Submitted by: Brice P Noonan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
