<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Molecular and functional analysis of virulence factors from L. heterotoma, a generalist parasite of Drosophila</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499270.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>505270</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>rollie clem</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Parasitic wasps are a large class of insects, whose success depends on venom factors and virus-like particles (VLPs). VLPs, produced by the wasps themselves have an obligatory relationship with their wasps. The focus of the project is to understand how L. heterotoma, a generalist parasitic wasp that infects Drosophila hosts across the genus, succeeds in nature. When introduced into Drosophila larvae, venom factors and VLPs of L. heterotoma wipe out the host?s immune system and the immune pathways remain' off'. In fact, VLPs enter the host's body cavity and destroy the fly's immature and mature blood cells. Blood cells carry out and coordinate immune functions of the fly host.&lt;br/&gt;D. melanogaster is by far the best-characterized insect and one of the most intensively-studied organisms. The investigators will utilize Drosophila genetics to explore why these generalist wasps succeed on a wide range of Drosophila species globally. By combining molecular and computational methods, the investigators will identify the cDNA clones corresponding to VLP proteins and inhibitory factors from L. heterotoma venom. They will compare the structures of these L. heterotoma molecules from venom of other, related wasp species. Using transgenic and genetic methods, they will analyze the inhibitory function of each protein in the fly's immune response. These studies will reveal how insect hosts and their parasites adapt to each other and shape the evolution of their community. In addition, because immune signaling in all insects is conserved, discoveries from this project can be used to restrict the spread of other insect species that compromise human health or destroy plants.&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide ample training opportunities for middle and high school students. Strains and assays will be used in lab-based Genetics courses of the Biology curriculum at CCNY. The cDNA sequence data will be used to develop bioinformatics projects for CCNY students. Sequences of L. heterotoma cDNAs will be deposited in NCBI and will be available to researchers worldwide.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1121817</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shubha</FirstName>
<LastName>Govind</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shubha Govind</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sgovind@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126508476</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000313709</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Convent Ave at 138th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>SYMBIOSIS DEF &amp; SELF RECOG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~499270</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An obligate parasite is an organism that depends completely on another organism to survive. A large group of wasps called parasitoid wasps or parasitic wasps are obligate parasites of other insects and are extremely successful in nature. Female parasitic wasps lay eggs in the body of their hosts, where they develop into adults by consuming host tissues, ultimately killing them. Adult female and male wasps are free-living and mate to initiate a new generation of wasps. In many parts of the world, parasitic wasps are used to control insect pests that threaten agricultural crops. Applications of parasitic wasps can substitute for insecticides, reduce dangerous chemical usages, and make the environment safer for livestock and humans.</p> <p>Some parasitic wasps (called specialist parasites) grow on a small range of hosts whereas others (called generalist parasites) can attack and succeed on many different host species. We focus on small specialist/generalist parasitic wasps of the genus <em>Leptopilina</em>. These wasps parasitize larvae of <em>Drosophila melanogaster</em> and its relatives. One such relative is the spotted-wing <em>Drosophila</em> (<em>D. suzukii</em>), commonly known as the spotted-wing <em>Drosophila </em>(SWD). This SWD fruit fly species is a major invasive pest of soft fruits around the world and scientists are searching for efficient ways of containing these pests including using parasitic wasps of <em>Drosophila </em>to kill them.</p> <p><em>L. heterotoma</em> attacks and succeeds on a wide host range of <em>Drosophila </em>spp. whereas a close relative, <em>L. boulardi</em>, is more selective and succeeds only on flies of the melanogaster group. Both <em>L. heterotoma </em>and <em>L. boulardi </em>are extremely successful on <em>D. melanogaster</em>, a well-characterized model organism for human disease and agriculture research. <em>L. heterotoma</em> venom kills blood cells, or hemocytes, of the fly host, strongly suppressing host defenses. In contrast, <em>L. boulardi</em> attack leads to activation of the immune system although the venom suppresses (but does not kill) host hemocytes. Thus, the reasons why both wasps succeed on <em>D. melanogaster</em> are different. We hypothesized that this difference in how the venom of each wasp interacts with the host hemocytes may in part be responsible for their host range.</p> <p>The venom of both wasp species is packed with microscopic structures dubbed virus-like particles or VLPs. VLPs of both species are star shaped but are distinguishable morphologically. In this project, we examined the composition of <em>L. heterotoma</em> VLPs and tracked the presence/absence of <em>L. heterotoma</em> VLP proteins in <em>L. boulardi</em>. This comparative approach identified several unique proteins in <em>L. heterotoma</em> VLPs. We are characterizing the structures and functions of these proteins in various <em>ex vivo</em> and <em>in vivo</em> assays to understand their mode of action in larval hemocytes. Toward this goal, we are taking advantage of transgenic methods and well-characterized genetic fly strains to study how the cell biology of host hemocytes affected by VLP proteins. Insights drawn from these studies will be relevant to our general understanding of the evolution of generalist <em>versus </em>specialist host-parasite relationships. Because of extensive molecular conservation in the core NF-&kappa;B signaling components in insects, it is likely that inhibitory strategies identified here are experimentally transferrable to other insect species to restrict the spread of disease vectors or plant pests. We will learn if venom factors of <em>Leptopilina </em>wasps are effective against pests such as SWD. Molecular information of VLPs is also providing insights into the nature and origin of the VLPs.</p> <p>This project was conducted in collaboration with proteomics experts, bioinformaticians, genome biologists, and yeast and <em>Drosophila</em> geneticists. Our combined efforts provided rich training opportunities to numerous undergraduates at City College and Brooklyn College, graduate students at the CUNY Graduate Center, and one post-doctoral fellow at CCNY.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Shubha&nbsp;Govind</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1121817/1121817_10122912_1475512233590_SEM3copy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1121817/1121817_10122912_1475512233590_SEM3copy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SEM of L. heterotoma VLP"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1121817/1121817_10122912_1475512233590_SEM3copy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SEM of L. heterotoma VLP"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A virus-like particle purified from the venom of parasitic wasp, Leptopilina heterotoma. Notice the presence of spikes emerging from a central core. These spikes mediate interactions of the VLP with host hemocytes. In the NSF-funded project, we have characterized the proteins of these VLPs.</div> <div class="imageCredit">http://jgv.microbiologyresearch.org/content/journal/jgv/10.1099/vir.0.81474-0</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shubha&nbsp;Govind</div> <div class="imageTitle">SEM of L. heterotoma VLP</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An obligate parasite is an organism that depends completely on another organism to survive. A large group of wasps called parasitoid wasps or parasitic wasps are obligate parasites of other insects and are extremely successful in nature. Female parasitic wasps lay eggs in the body of their hosts, where they develop into adults by consuming host tissues, ultimately killing them. Adult female and male wasps are free-living and mate to initiate a new generation of wasps. In many parts of the world, parasitic wasps are used to control insect pests that threaten agricultural crops. Applications of parasitic wasps can substitute for insecticides, reduce dangerous chemical usages, and make the environment safer for livestock and humans.  Some parasitic wasps (called specialist parasites) grow on a small range of hosts whereas others (called generalist parasites) can attack and succeed on many different host species. We focus on small specialist/generalist parasitic wasps of the genus Leptopilina. These wasps parasitize larvae of Drosophila melanogaster and its relatives. One such relative is the spotted-wing Drosophila (D. suzukii), commonly known as the spotted-wing Drosophila (SWD). This SWD fruit fly species is a major invasive pest of soft fruits around the world and scientists are searching for efficient ways of containing these pests including using parasitic wasps of Drosophila to kill them.  L. heterotoma attacks and succeeds on a wide host range of Drosophila spp. whereas a close relative, L. boulardi, is more selective and succeeds only on flies of the melanogaster group. Both L. heterotoma and L. boulardi are extremely successful on D. melanogaster, a well-characterized model organism for human disease and agriculture research. L. heterotoma venom kills blood cells, or hemocytes, of the fly host, strongly suppressing host defenses. In contrast, L. boulardi attack leads to activation of the immune system although the venom suppresses (but does not kill) host hemocytes. Thus, the reasons why both wasps succeed on D. melanogaster are different. We hypothesized that this difference in how the venom of each wasp interacts with the host hemocytes may in part be responsible for their host range.  The venom of both wasp species is packed with microscopic structures dubbed virus-like particles or VLPs. VLPs of both species are star shaped but are distinguishable morphologically. In this project, we examined the composition of L. heterotoma VLPs and tracked the presence/absence of L. heterotoma VLP proteins in L. boulardi. This comparative approach identified several unique proteins in L. heterotoma VLPs. We are characterizing the structures and functions of these proteins in various ex vivo and in vivo assays to understand their mode of action in larval hemocytes. Toward this goal, we are taking advantage of transgenic methods and well-characterized genetic fly strains to study how the cell biology of host hemocytes affected by VLP proteins. Insights drawn from these studies will be relevant to our general understanding of the evolution of generalist versus specialist host-parasite relationships. Because of extensive molecular conservation in the core NF-&kappa;B signaling components in insects, it is likely that inhibitory strategies identified here are experimentally transferrable to other insect species to restrict the spread of disease vectors or plant pests. We will learn if venom factors of Leptopilina wasps are effective against pests such as SWD. Molecular information of VLPs is also providing insights into the nature and origin of the VLPs.  This project was conducted in collaboration with proteomics experts, bioinformaticians, genome biologists, and yeast and Drosophila geneticists. Our combined efforts provided rich training opportunities to numerous undergraduates at City College and Brooklyn College, graduate students at the CUNY Graduate Center, and one post-doctoral fellow at CCNY.       Last Modified: 10/03/2016       Submitted by: Shubha Govind]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
