<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Research to Shape Instruction and Placement in Algebra and Precalculus</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>524487.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>524487</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>srichard@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924657</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is developing a new research-based instrument for placement of students in algebra and precalculus and disseminating documented descriptions and sample items of this new instrument. The work is based on earlier research and testing that produced a Calculus Concepts Readiness test (CCR) and a companion Precalculus Concepts Assessment (PCA). In particular, researchers considered students' conceptual understanding of key concepts required for success in subsequent mathematics courses, in future careers, and as informed citizens. The purpose of this follow-on development and dissemination effort is twofold: i) to influence and improve college mathematics placement tests and ii) to inform and shape instructional practice in algebra and precalculus courses. The intellectual merit of this project rests in its recognition that while there is an adequate research base to inform more effective instructional practice, teachers at all levels lack ready access to assessment tools that reinforce teaching for improving students' deep conceptual understanding. Indeed, most placement tests currently in use focus on procedural fluency, thus reinforcing traditional instructional approaches. The new placement test becomes part of a coherent suite of instruments that serve to improve teaching and learning throughout the entire algebra-precalculus-calculus pathway. The project is exerting its broader impacts in several ways. Firstly, the reasoning and conceptual taxonomies of the new instrument, as well as sample items to illustrate the conceptual reasoning coverage, are being made publicly available and used throughout the dissemination phase of the project to inform professional development efforts not only for college and university faculty teaching lower-division mathematics courses, but also for K-12 teachers. Secondly, the project is being led by the Mathematical Association of America (MAA), the largest professional organization in the world with a focus on undergraduate mathematics. The organization's online and print publications, and sessions at national and regional meetings provide diverse and far-reaching channels for dissemination. In addition, existing relationships with other national organizations seeking to raise the quality of mathematics instruction gives the MAA a unique opportunity to develop, pilot, and rigorously document the reliability and validity of placement tests. Finally, the results of this project are contributing to improved articulation between secondary and post-secondary mathematics and informing pre-service and in-service teacher education in mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1122965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caren</FirstName>
<LastName>Diefenderfer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Caren L Diefenderfer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cdiefenderfer@hollins.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5403626595</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219054</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernard</FirstName>
<LastName>Madison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernard L Madison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmadison@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795753351</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000345096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marilyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marilyn Carlson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marilyn.carlson@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809656168</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396469</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Pearson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J Michael Pearson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pearson@maa.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023875200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481659</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/10/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Ensley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Ensley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>deensley@ship.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7174771406</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000351480</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Braddy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda Braddy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>linda.braddy@tccd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8175156686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365160</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/25/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lloyd</FirstName>
<LastName>Douglas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lloyd E Douglas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ledougl2@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039814058</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000520200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/11/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mathematical Association of America</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200361358</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023875200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1529 18th St NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072662992</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MATHEMATICAL ASSOCIATION OF AMERICA, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072662992</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mathematical Association of America]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200361358</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1529 18th St NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7511</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 2 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~524487</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <em>Using Research to Shape Instruction and Placement in Precalculus and Algebra</em> (URSIP) project team developed and disseminated two assessment instruments, the<em> Calculus Concept Readiness</em> (CCR) and the <em>Algebra, Precalculus Concept Readiness</em> (APCR). The instruments have been disseminated to mathematics faculty and graduate students through national workshops, mini-courses at national conferences, and published articles. The broad taxonomies that guided the development of these instruments describe the specific reasoning abilities, understandings, and skills that research has revealed to be foundational for learning calculus. The data from administering APCR and CCR provides a valid and reliable measure of student reasoning and learning of the specific concepts and content described in the taxonomies. This data also identifies specific strengths and weaknesses in student learning, providing useful formative data for adapting precalculus level curriculum and instruction to be more effective in preparing students for calculus. The impact of the URSIP project is a dramatic increase in the number of students who are prepared to learn and succeed in calculus, leading to more students successfully completing STEM degrees.</p> <p>The research findings from the URSIP project revealed that precalculus courses are more meaningful and effective when precalculus instructors are more knowledgeable of the process of learning and understanding precalculus concepts. The URSIP workshops and mini-courses engaged faculty in activities to improve their knowledge of what is involved in acquiring the critical reasoning abilities, understandings, and skills that precalculus level courses should be developing in students. As mathematics instructors become more knowledgeable of what is involved in understanding and learning key ideas of precalculus level instruction, they are better equipped to interpret and use the APCR and CCR, and other formative data to inform and adapt their precalculus level curriculum and instruction.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Marilyn&nbsp;Carlson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Using Research to Shape Instruction and Placement in Precalculus and Algebra (URSIP) project team developed and disseminated two assessment instruments, the Calculus Concept Readiness (CCR) and the Algebra, Precalculus Concept Readiness (APCR). The instruments have been disseminated to mathematics faculty and graduate students through national workshops, mini-courses at national conferences, and published articles. The broad taxonomies that guided the development of these instruments describe the specific reasoning abilities, understandings, and skills that research has revealed to be foundational for learning calculus. The data from administering APCR and CCR provides a valid and reliable measure of student reasoning and learning of the specific concepts and content described in the taxonomies. This data also identifies specific strengths and weaknesses in student learning, providing useful formative data for adapting precalculus level curriculum and instruction to be more effective in preparing students for calculus. The impact of the URSIP project is a dramatic increase in the number of students who are prepared to learn and succeed in calculus, leading to more students successfully completing STEM degrees.  The research findings from the URSIP project revealed that precalculus courses are more meaningful and effective when precalculus instructors are more knowledgeable of the process of learning and understanding precalculus concepts. The URSIP workshops and mini-courses engaged faculty in activities to improve their knowledge of what is involved in acquiring the critical reasoning abilities, understandings, and skills that precalculus level courses should be developing in students. As mathematics instructors become more knowledgeable of what is involved in understanding and learning key ideas of precalculus level instruction, they are better equipped to interpret and use the APCR and CCR, and other formative data to inform and adapt their precalculus level curriculum and instruction.              Last Modified: 12/15/2017       Submitted by: Marilyn Carlson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
