<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>VOSS: Virtual organizations in action: Understanding socio-technical systems through changes in structure and technology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399896.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399896</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajiv Ramnath</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Virtual organizations are groups of individuals whose members and resources may be distributed geographically and structurally, yet who function as a coherent unit through the use of collaborative technology. In the context of business, virtual organizations offer the promise of growth and innovation through flexible and fluid structures, yet employees face the challenge of managing coordination costs as a result of the dynamic and evolving work. New collaborative technologies, such as those that facilitate communication and knowledge sharing as well as social media and task integration capabilities, offer coordination benefits that could counter, and possibly exceed, the coordination costs that arise from working in virtual organizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through qualitative interviews of individuals and an online survey of working groups, this project will: (a) define and measure features of organization structure, collaborative technology, and workflow outcomes in a range of structures (including virtual organization structures) within a business organization adopting a new and emergent organizational structure, (b) describe the consequences (positive and negative) of different organization structures and collaborative technologies in terms of their impact on workflow outcomes, and (c) create a public web-based resource that can be used by the organizational and technology communities to better understand the kinds of structures and technologies that affect workflow outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research on the intersection of virtual organization structures and collaborative technology is still in its infancy. Data collected from this unique empirical setting will provide critical insight into how new structures and new technologies influence each other as well as workflow outcomes. In addition to furthering scientific understanding of virtual organizations, a potentially transformative outcome of this research is facilitating understanding of virtual organizations for science, education, healthcare, and other types of organizations. Moreover, study results can be incorporated into the design and testing of collaborative technology, which could contribute to new advances in tools to support distributed work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1122286</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathon</FirstName>
<LastName>Cummings</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathon Cummings</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jonathon.cummings@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196607756</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483837</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tony</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Driscoll</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tony O'Driscoll</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tony.odriscoll@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196843030</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000528108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St, Suite 710]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7642</Code>
<Text>VIRTUAL ORGANIZATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7953</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL-COMPUTATIONAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7642</Code>
<Text>VIRTUAL ORGANIZATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7953</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL-COMPUTATIONAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~399896</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Virtual Organizations as Socio-Technical Systems (VOSS) project examined the life cycle of an enterprise social media system in a large, global corporation. The system allowed employees to create virtual communities, post messages to groups, and share files. We were particularly interested in (1) how characteristics of system users (e.g., company tenure, US vs non-US, employee status) differed from system non-users as well as how frequent users differed from infrequent users, (2) how the use of the system for collaboration in public virtual communities (open to anyone in company) differed from collaboration in private virtual communities (by invitation only), and (3) how use of the system diffused throughout the company over its life cycle (e.g., rate of adoption as a function of reporting supervisor, organizational unit, and geographic location). The corporation provided a merged dataset (without names, IDs, or contact information of employees) which combined system usage data (over 1.5 million records) with human resource data (background information on over 100,000 employees). The system usage and HR data were supplemented by qualitative interviews with employees in the company to better understand the barriers to system adoption as well as the opportunities the system provided for collaboration.<br /><br />The results of this project could impact scholarship in the areas of organization science, information systems, and social networks. For example, system users were more likely to be in the company longer, were more likely to be from the US (rather than outside the US), and were more likely to be full-time employees (rather than contractors) -- people who were more core to the US-based international. Interview data also suggested that competing tools (e.g., email, cloud storage, web conferencing) were a key barrier to system use, as employees had many alternative ways to collaborate with co-workers. Furthermore, employees created significantly more private virtual communities than public virtual communities, and our interviews revealed that employees preferred private groups for sharing knowledge about ongoing tasks and work-in-progress, while employees preferred public groups for making documents or general knowledge available to the entire corporation. Finally, adoption of the system was heavily influenced by reporting supervisor, organizational unit, and geographic location, indicating that the formal structure of the firm played a important role in determining the rate of adoption. Several presentations and working papers describe the results of the project in more detail.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Jonathon&nbsp;Cummings</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Virtual Organizations as Socio-Technical Systems (VOSS) project examined the life cycle of an enterprise social media system in a large, global corporation. The system allowed employees to create virtual communities, post messages to groups, and share files. We were particularly interested in (1) how characteristics of system users (e.g., company tenure, US vs non-US, employee status) differed from system non-users as well as how frequent users differed from infrequent users, (2) how the use of the system for collaboration in public virtual communities (open to anyone in company) differed from collaboration in private virtual communities (by invitation only), and (3) how use of the system diffused throughout the company over its life cycle (e.g., rate of adoption as a function of reporting supervisor, organizational unit, and geographic location). The corporation provided a merged dataset (without names, IDs, or contact information of employees) which combined system usage data (over 1.5 million records) with human resource data (background information on over 100,000 employees). The system usage and HR data were supplemented by qualitative interviews with employees in the company to better understand the barriers to system adoption as well as the opportunities the system provided for collaboration.  The results of this project could impact scholarship in the areas of organization science, information systems, and social networks. For example, system users were more likely to be in the company longer, were more likely to be from the US (rather than outside the US), and were more likely to be full-time employees (rather than contractors) -- people who were more core to the US-based international. Interview data also suggested that competing tools (e.g., email, cloud storage, web conferencing) were a key barrier to system use, as employees had many alternative ways to collaborate with co-workers. Furthermore, employees created significantly more private virtual communities than public virtual communities, and our interviews revealed that employees preferred private groups for sharing knowledge about ongoing tasks and work-in-progress, while employees preferred public groups for making documents or general knowledge available to the entire corporation. Finally, adoption of the system was heavily influenced by reporting supervisor, organizational unit, and geographic location, indicating that the formal structure of the firm played a important role in determining the rate of adoption. Several presentations and working papers describe the results of the project in more detail.       Last Modified: 11/30/2015       Submitted by: Jonathon Cummings]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
