<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Generating a Community for Undergraduate Research Through the Use of Comparative Microbial Genomics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>477223.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>477223</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Terry S. Woodin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Through faculty workshops and an open source website, called Genome Solver, covering both effective teaching approaches and the use of biogenomics and genomics tools for undergraduate research, the project is creating a framework for faculty development that impacts student learning and has the potential to add to our general knowledge about the human microbiome.  It is a collaboration between a number of entities, the PI and her group in the Department of Biology at Georgetown, a group at Simmons College, the Georgetown Center for New Designs in Learning (the developer of the Global Solver [http://globalsolver.org] upon which Genome Solver is based) and the J. Craig Venter Institute (the site of the faculty workshops and developer of the genomic tools).  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:  The project is timely in its materials and its approach to making those materials available.  It is helping faculty keep their courses current with new developments in the literature and in approaches to teaching.  In addition it is encouraging use of student laboratories as a place for groups of students, faculty, and bioinformatics experts to collaborate in research on important topics in the genetics of microbes affecting human health and behavior. Ongoing research in these student laboratories has the potential for being deposited in GenBank and prepared for publication in refereed journals.  Examples of the tools students are learning to use include BLAST, ClustalW, and hidden Markov model approaches for protein domains.  Students start out with a computer-based analysis of genomic data and then use this information to generate hypotheses that are then tested by wet lab experiments to investigate an aspect of microbial physiology stemming from that analysis.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:  Genome Solver is creating an online community where students and experts across different institutions can come together to discuss science and curricular ideas.  Faculty from minority serving institutions are part of the workshop recruitment and team and advisory board to insure that this work will benefit a diversity of institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts toward Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1123016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosenwald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne G Rosenwald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rosenwaa@georgetown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2026875997</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Roecklein-Canfield</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Roecklein-Canfield</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jennifer.canfield@simmons.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6177382000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000237311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramana</FirstName>
<LastName>Madupu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramana Madupu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rmadupu@jcvi.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3017957871</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242174</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Russell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet Russell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsr49@georgetown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2026250100</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508275</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgetown University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200571789</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2026250100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>37th &amp; O St N W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049515844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGETOWN UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049515844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgetown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200571789</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[37th &amp; O St N W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7511</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 2 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7972</Code>
<Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~477223</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;The Genome Solver Project: &nbsp;Bioinformatics Training for Undergraduate Faculty and Their Students</p> <p>With the increases in ability to sequence DNA from humans down to the microbes that live in and on them, the DNA sequence databases are bursting.&nbsp; These data are rich resources for practicing scientists but also for undergraduate students and their instructors.&nbsp; With this in mind we initially developed the Genome Solver Project (GSP), to take advantage of the data resulting from the Human Microbiome Project (HMP), which was designed to investigate the different ecological niches in and on the human body by identifying the microorganisms that live in different places (skin, mouth, intestinal tract, etc.).&nbsp; These data are freely available at public sites that can be accessed by anyone.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Investigating the DNA sequence data from the microbes identified in the HMP is relatively straightforward because the only equipment required is a computer with an Internet connection since analysis tools are available over the web.&nbsp; However, because this discipline, called &ldquo;bioinformatics&rdquo; which combines biology and computer science is relatively new, many undergraduate faculty feel the need for some training.&nbsp; As part of the GSP, we developed bioinformatics training workshops for faculty for the necessary professional development, in collaboration with colleagues at the J. Craig Venter Institute. In these two-day workshops, we talked about where to acquire the DNA sequence data, how to analyze it using relatively easy tools, and how to incorporate this information into specific classes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, we developed a website (<a href="http://genomesolver.org">http://genomesolver.org</a>) to share information about the Human Microbiome Project and other microbes in the news, curriculum modules, &ldquo;how-to&rdquo; manuals for reminders about how to use the analysis tools, and best practices for pedagogy.&nbsp; This website serves as a community of practice because we found in surveys of the participants that many faculty feel isolated at their home institutions in efforts to engage in bioinformatics and research and curriculum development.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In all, through the Genome Solver Project, we have trained more than 120 faculty members, many from community colleges or minority-serving institutions.&nbsp; The website has more than 350 registered participants, both faculty and students.&nbsp; We are currently in the process of expanding Genome Solver through development of a community science project for faculty and their students.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;G&nbsp;Rosenwald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1123016/1123016_10114939_1440953637627_gslogo-print--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1123016/1123016_10114939_1440953637627_gslogo-print--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Genome Solver"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1123016/1123016_10114939_1440953637627_gslogo-print--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Genome Solver"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image represents the data available for study through the Human Microbiome Project, the data sources tapped for the Genome Solver Project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Secor</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Genome Solver Project:  Bioinformatics Training for Undergraduate Faculty and Their Students  With the increases in ability to sequence DNA from humans down to the microbes that live in and on them, the DNA sequence databases are bursting.  These data are rich resources for practicing scientists but also for undergraduate students and their instructors.  With this in mind we initially developed the Genome Solver Project (GSP), to take advantage of the data resulting from the Human Microbiome Project (HMP), which was designed to investigate the different ecological niches in and on the human body by identifying the microorganisms that live in different places (skin, mouth, intestinal tract, etc.).  These data are freely available at public sites that can be accessed by anyone.        Investigating the DNA sequence data from the microbes identified in the HMP is relatively straightforward because the only equipment required is a computer with an Internet connection since analysis tools are available over the web.  However, because this discipline, called "bioinformatics" which combines biology and computer science is relatively new, many undergraduate faculty feel the need for some training.  As part of the GSP, we developed bioinformatics training workshops for faculty for the necessary professional development, in collaboration with colleagues at the J. Craig Venter Institute. In these two-day workshops, we talked about where to acquire the DNA sequence data, how to analyze it using relatively easy tools, and how to incorporate this information into specific classes.      In addition, we developed a website (http://genomesolver.org) to share information about the Human Microbiome Project and other microbes in the news, curriculum modules, "how-to" manuals for reminders about how to use the analysis tools, and best practices for pedagogy.  This website serves as a community of practice because we found in surveys of the participants that many faculty feel isolated at their home institutions in efforts to engage in bioinformatics and research and curriculum development.      In all, through the Genome Solver Project, we have trained more than 120 faculty members, many from community colleges or minority-serving institutions.  The website has more than 350 registered participants, both faculty and students.  We are currently in the process of expanding Genome Solver through development of a community science project for faculty and their students.             Last Modified: 08/30/2015       Submitted by: Anne G Rosenwald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
