<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Robot Hoedown &amp; Rodeo at SIGCSE 2011</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6283.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6283</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Suzanne C. Fitzgerald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The SIGCSE Robot Hoedown and Rodeo provides computer science faculty, teachers, and graduate students the opportunity to program a variety of robot platforms used in education. Though a significant minority of computer science educators has used robots, most computer science educators have never had the opportunity to experiment with one.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advances in consumer electronics and robotics have created several platforms which are sufficiently affordable to move to the "personal robot" model in which each student has his or her own robot for the duration of a class. There is recent evidence that students in courses with personal robots show greater motivation to complete assignments in the course and that these courses have better retention rates.  This workshop primarily focuses on these relatively newer and more affordable platforms.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This robotics workshop is part of SIGCSE 2011, the flagship conference for the Association for Computing Machinery?s Special Interest Group on Computer Science Education which attracts roughly 1200 attendees each year. The workshop provides conference attendees who have never programmed a robot before the opportunity to do so and offers those who already have programmed a robot the chance to work with alternative platforms.  The creative results of programmed robotic dance movements and robot-specific programming challenges are publicly demonstrated throughout the conference.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1123550</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Kay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Ms</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer S Kay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kay@rowan.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8562564593</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000215882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tom</FirstName>
<LastName>Lauwers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tom B Lauwers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tlauwers@birdbraintechnologies.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122165833</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rowan University</Name>
<CityName>Glassboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>080281701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8562564057</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[201 Mullica Hill Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>139203145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROWAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>139203145</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rowan University]]></Name>
<CityName>Dallas</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>752014005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sheraton Dallas, 400 N Olive St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~6283</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong><span id="internal-source-marker_0.5635244369026041" style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong></span><br /><br /><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">The  key goal of this project was to give educators a new way to engage K-12  &amp; College students in Computer Science, so as to foster the  workforce that will be needed to make transformative breakthroughs in  the future. The Robot Hoedown and Rodeo was a three day event taking  place at SIGCSE 2011, the premier conference for computer science educators. The purpose of the event was to introduce robot programming to  the nearly 1200 educators attending the conference, and to raise  awareness amongst participants of how robots could be used in their  classrooms. Despite evidence that robots can be used as educational  tools to excite and motivate students, only a minority of educators at  SIGCSE had ever programmed a robot, and even fewer participants had  tried using them in their classrooms. Our project provided educators  with:</span></p> <ul> <li><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"> The opportunity to borrow and program one or more of over 75 robots  representing five of the most popular educational robotics platforms.</span></li> <li><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Free downloads of a dozen robot-programming software environments.</span></li> <li><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Access to knowledgeable Teaching Assistants who could help them get started with programming.</span></li> <li><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Numerous sample assignments.</span></li> <li><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Expert-led introductions to the robot platforms and their educational  possibilities through a number of demonstrations and exhibits held  throughout the three day conference.</span></li> </ul> <p><br /><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Broader Impact</span></strong></span><br /><br /><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Conference attendees who completed an exit survey were generally favorable of the </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: normal; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">event,  and the majority of those who programmed a robot &nbsp;reported that t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  The  key goal of this project was to give educators a new way to engage K-12  &amp; College students in Computer Science, so as to foster the  workforce that will be needed to make transformative breakthroughs in  the future. The Robot Hoedown and Rodeo was a three day event taking  place at SIGCSE 2011, the premier conference for computer science educators. The purpose of the event was to introduce robot programming to  the nearly 1200 educators attending the conference, and to raise  awareness amongst participants of how robots could be used in their  classrooms. Despite evidence that robots can be used as educational  tools to excite and motivate students, only a minority of educators at  SIGCSE had ever programmed a robot, and even fewer participants had  tried using them in their classrooms. Our project provided educators  with:   The opportunity to borrow and program one or more of over 75 robots  representing five of the most popular educational robotics platforms. Free downloads of a dozen robot-programming software environments. Access to knowledgeable Teaching Assistants who could help them get started with programming. Numerous sample assignments. Expert-led introductions to the robot platforms and their educational  possibilities through a number of demonstrations and exhibits held  throughout the three day conference.    Broader Impact  Conference attendees who completed an exit survey were generally favorable of the event,  and the majority of those who programmed a robot  reported that they  would be more likely to use robots in their classrooms in the future.  Thus the event may lead to improved educational opportunities for a number of Computer Science students. The event also generated  significant educational material in the form of tutorials and sample  projects that are now freely available to educators and students on the  web. Finally, as a consequence of the event the PIs produced a document  targeted at computer science educators that provides an introduction to  and overview of robot hardware platforms and software options currently  available for educational robotics.       Last Modified: 09/27/2011       Submitted by: Jennifer S Kay]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
