<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Explaining the Rarity of Click Sounds as consonants in the Languages of the World</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>184249.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>196449</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmaling@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928046</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project seeks to explain the rarity of clicks as consonants in the languages of the world. In most consonants, the source of sound is generated on air coming from the lungs as speakers breathe out. The source of sound is separate from the filtering action of the tongue and lips. The separation of the source of sound from the filter underlies current theories of speech production, and is assumed in all computer generated models of speech. However, in some speech sounds, the separation of the source of sound from the filtering action of the vocal tract is less clear.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For example, for sounds like 'h' that are made in the throat, the source of sound is changed due to the proximity of the tongue constriction to the vocal folds. In click consonants, speakers produce sound by creating a cavity between two parts of the tongue and the palate. The sound is generated by creating a vacuum between the tongue and the palate, which allows air to flow into the vacuum, and is simultaneously filtered by the tongue's shape and position. This project will consist of careful analyses of these complex speech gestures and their resulting sounds. The research team will collect high frame-rate ultrasound data of the tongue during click production. The ultrasound method yields an image of the tongue every 8 thousandths of a second, which is aligned with the audio signal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The volume of the cavity formed between the tongue and the palate in the production of click consonants will be measured and correlated with the frequency of the sound waves that are produced. These and other analyses will be used to support Dr. Miller's petition to the International Phonetic Association to add two newly documented click sounds to the International Phonetic Alphabet. The results of this project will also contribute to computer speech generation by providing valuable data for future models that can handle source-filter interactions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1123634</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda L Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>miller.5592@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142929752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7395</Code>
<Text>NAMIBIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~184249</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~800</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~11400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The intellectual merit of this project is that it has provided an explanation for why click consonants are so rare as contrastive sounds cross-linguistically (G&uuml;ldemann and Stoneking 2008), but so common as other types of speech markers. &nbsp;For example, click consonants are quite common in English as discourse markers. Miller has described the interactions between the production of the source of the airstream, and the filtering mechanism that determines the places of articulation involved in clicks, using Source Filter Theory (Fant 1960). Source Filter Theory is the overarching theory that underlies all speech recognition and synthesis methods. The source-filter interactions found in the production of clicks, make clicks among the most articulatorily complex sounds in the languages of the world, and lead to their cross-linguistic rarity. Tongue dorsum retraction, tongue root retraction, and tongue center lowering all contribute to the production of the source of air using the lingual airstream mechanism. These articulatory movements also contribute to the filtering of air, and interact with the tongue front raising gestures of following high front vowels. The rarefaction gestures make clicks difficult to incorporate into the jaw opening gestures of the CV syllable (Kohler 1997). The palatal click has been shown to involve a raised, bunched tongue posture, with a uvulo-pharyngeal dorsal constriction. The dental and alveolar clicks have been shown to involve uvular dorsal constrictions, and the alveolar clicks have been shown to involve an additional tongue root retraction gesture that carries over into the following vowel. The tongue root retraction that is part of the rarefaction gesture of the alveolar clicks retracts and lowers following front vowels, and is the basis of the co-occurrence restrictions that are found between alveolar clicks and front vowels. Results of this project also show that the palatal click has two different variants that occur preceding front vs. back vowels. A fricated variant of the palatal click occurs before front vowels, and a non-fricated variant occurs before back vowels. This type of variation in the palatal click consonant shows that clicks vary in different speech contexts just as all other consonants do.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this project are that clicks are extremely difficult to produce, but that they are similar to other consonants found in the languages of the world in that the tongue postures in the clicks set up to interact with approaching tongue postures in following vowels. Thus, this research shows that click consonants follow universal consonant-vowel coarticulation patterns seen in human languages. Since clicks occur in English as discourse markers, the understanding of click production and acoustics will improve natural language applications of speech recognition and synthesis. Further broader impacts are that the investigation of consonant-vowel coarticulation following the methodology developed in this project will be useful for a better understanding of the articulatory to acoustic mapping of all speech sounds, which will help improve speech synthesis and speech recognition systems for all languages. Further, the lingual ultrasound methodology developed in this project will be useful for the investigation of speech disorders where clicks are sometimes produced, such as Velo Cardial Facial Syndrome and the speech of congenitally deaf children that have had cochlear implants. The insights the methods will bring to speech problems found in individuals with these speech and hearing disorders will improve the lives of people with these disorders by providing insights into how to best improve assistive hearing devices to aid such people, and how to best help these people produce more intelligible speech.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Amanda&nbsp;L&nbsp;Miller</p>...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit of this project is that it has provided an explanation for why click consonants are so rare as contrastive sounds cross-linguistically (G&uuml;ldemann and Stoneking 2008), but so common as other types of speech markers.  For example, click consonants are quite common in English as discourse markers. Miller has described the interactions between the production of the source of the airstream, and the filtering mechanism that determines the places of articulation involved in clicks, using Source Filter Theory (Fant 1960). Source Filter Theory is the overarching theory that underlies all speech recognition and synthesis methods. The source-filter interactions found in the production of clicks, make clicks among the most articulatorily complex sounds in the languages of the world, and lead to their cross-linguistic rarity. Tongue dorsum retraction, tongue root retraction, and tongue center lowering all contribute to the production of the source of air using the lingual airstream mechanism. These articulatory movements also contribute to the filtering of air, and interact with the tongue front raising gestures of following high front vowels. The rarefaction gestures make clicks difficult to incorporate into the jaw opening gestures of the CV syllable (Kohler 1997). The palatal click has been shown to involve a raised, bunched tongue posture, with a uvulo-pharyngeal dorsal constriction. The dental and alveolar clicks have been shown to involve uvular dorsal constrictions, and the alveolar clicks have been shown to involve an additional tongue root retraction gesture that carries over into the following vowel. The tongue root retraction that is part of the rarefaction gesture of the alveolar clicks retracts and lowers following front vowels, and is the basis of the co-occurrence restrictions that are found between alveolar clicks and front vowels. Results of this project also show that the palatal click has two different variants that occur preceding front vs. back vowels. A fricated variant of the palatal click occurs before front vowels, and a non-fricated variant occurs before back vowels. This type of variation in the palatal click consonant shows that clicks vary in different speech contexts just as all other consonants do.  The broader impacts of this project are that clicks are extremely difficult to produce, but that they are similar to other consonants found in the languages of the world in that the tongue postures in the clicks set up to interact with approaching tongue postures in following vowels. Thus, this research shows that click consonants follow universal consonant-vowel coarticulation patterns seen in human languages. Since clicks occur in English as discourse markers, the understanding of click production and acoustics will improve natural language applications of speech recognition and synthesis. Further broader impacts are that the investigation of consonant-vowel coarticulation following the methodology developed in this project will be useful for a better understanding of the articulatory to acoustic mapping of all speech sounds, which will help improve speech synthesis and speech recognition systems for all languages. Further, the lingual ultrasound methodology developed in this project will be useful for the investigation of speech disorders where clicks are sometimes produced, such as Velo Cardial Facial Syndrome and the speech of congenitally deaf children that have had cochlear implants. The insights the methods will bring to speech problems found in individuals with these speech and hearing disorders will improve the lives of people with these disorders by providing insights into how to best improve assistive hearing devices to aid such people, and how to best help these people produce more intelligible speech.       Last Modified: 05/01/2016       Submitted by: Amanda L Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
