<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: International Collaboration in Chemistry: Formation Mechanisms of Iodinated Disinfection By-Products from X-Ray Contrast Media</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>216464.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>216464</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Environmental Chemical Sciences (ECS) program of the Division of Chemistry will support the international collaboration in chemistry research program of Prof. Stephen Duirk of the University of Akron, Prof. Michael Plewa of the University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Dr. Susan Richardson of USEPA, and Dr. Thomas Ternes of the Federal Institute of Hydrology in Koblenz, Germany. The collaborative team of investigators and their students will employ advanced measurement methods to elucidate the formation mechanisms of highly toxic iodo-disinfentant by products (iodo-DBPs) from the reaction of drinking water disinfectants with iodinated X-ray contrast media (ICM). ICM have never been investigated as precursors to DBPs in drinking water treatment, despite the fact that they are widely used and are found at high levels in surface waters. The US researchers will identify low molecular weight iodo-DBPs formed during the reaction of chlorinated oxidants with ICM and their TPs, and German researchers will identify high molecular weight reaction products. The toxicity (mammalian cell genotoxicity and cytotoxicity) of the reaction product mixtures and of individual iodo-DBPs identified will also be measured to determine which ICM, and their microbial transformation products (TPs), and reaction conditions give rise to toxic by-products. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As clean water sources are contaminated with anthropogenic chemicals from wastewater inputs, it is important to understand how these contaminants can be chemically transformed during drinking water treatment resulting in the formation of toxic transformation products. Understanding contaminant transformation pathways will ultimately result in minimizing or eliminating the formation of highly toxic DBPs in drinking water, which could potentially impact the millions of people worldwide who consume disinfected drinking water. The study will provide an excellent educational opportunity for undergraduate and graduate students to carry out an environmental chemical science project of great societal importance in international collaborative settings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This international collaborative research project is supported jointly by NSF and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (German Research Foundation) (DFG).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1124844</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Plewa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Plewa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mplewa@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173333614</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8008</Code>
<Text>Intl Collabrtn in Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9156</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9189</Code>
<Text>WATER RESOURCES/COASTAL &amp; MARINE ENVIRON</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~71906</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~69008</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~75550</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Drinking water disinfection was an outstanding public health achievement of the 20<sup>th</sup> century. It significantly reduced acute waterborne diseases.&nbsp; However, an unintended consequence of water disinfection was the generation of disinfection by-products (DBPs) that are formed by the interaction between the disinfectant and organic matter, bromide and iodide present in source waters. DBPs are toxic and have been associated with certain human cancers and adverse pregnancy outcomes. Different DBPs were shown to be cytotoxic, neurotoxic, teratogenic, mutagenic, genotoxic, and carcinogenic in a series of biological assays. Although over 600 DBPs have been chemically identified we discovered that the broad class of iodine-containing DBPs (I-DBPs) was the most toxic group of DBPs. This collaborative research project demonstrated that when certain iodinated X-ray-contrast media (ICM) pharmaceuticals are present in source waters, I-DBPs are generated after the disinfection process for drinking water. We demonstrated that among a group of ICMs, iopamidol generated the highest levels of mammalian cell cytotoxicity and genotoxicity as well as the production of I-DBPs. We defined the spectra of chemical iodinated DBPs generated after iopamidol plus source waters were disinfected by chlorine or chloramines. A major achievement of this project was the resolution of a degradation pathway of iopamidol. The analytical chemistry section of this project demonstrated two major classes of by-products were formed after disinfection of source water containing iopamidol. These classes were high molecular weight iopamidol transformation products and low molecular weight I-DBPs formed from the released I? from the iopamidol. &nbsp;We isolated the five most prevalent high molecular weight transformation products and conducted detailed biological analyses. The high molecular weight agents showed limited levels of mammalian cell cytotoxicity and no genotoxic damage while the low molecular weight I-DBPs were cytotoxic and induced genomic DNA damage in mammalian cells. Thus it is the low molecular weight I-DBPs that are responsible for the generation of enhanced toxicity after iopamidol and source waters were disinfected. These data demonstrate that widely used pharmaceutical contaminants in source waters can lead to drinking water disinfection by-products that may have adverse consequences for the environment and the public health.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/12/2016<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;J&nbsp;Plewa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Drinking water disinfection was an outstanding public health achievement of the 20th century. It significantly reduced acute waterborne diseases.  However, an unintended consequence of water disinfection was the generation of disinfection by-products (DBPs) that are formed by the interaction between the disinfectant and organic matter, bromide and iodide present in source waters. DBPs are toxic and have been associated with certain human cancers and adverse pregnancy outcomes. Different DBPs were shown to be cytotoxic, neurotoxic, teratogenic, mutagenic, genotoxic, and carcinogenic in a series of biological assays. Although over 600 DBPs have been chemically identified we discovered that the broad class of iodine-containing DBPs (I-DBPs) was the most toxic group of DBPs. This collaborative research project demonstrated that when certain iodinated X-ray-contrast media (ICM) pharmaceuticals are present in source waters, I-DBPs are generated after the disinfection process for drinking water. We demonstrated that among a group of ICMs, iopamidol generated the highest levels of mammalian cell cytotoxicity and genotoxicity as well as the production of I-DBPs. We defined the spectra of chemical iodinated DBPs generated after iopamidol plus source waters were disinfected by chlorine or chloramines. A major achievement of this project was the resolution of a degradation pathway of iopamidol. The analytical chemistry section of this project demonstrated two major classes of by-products were formed after disinfection of source water containing iopamidol. These classes were high molecular weight iopamidol transformation products and low molecular weight I-DBPs formed from the released I? from the iopamidol.  We isolated the five most prevalent high molecular weight transformation products and conducted detailed biological analyses. The high molecular weight agents showed limited levels of mammalian cell cytotoxicity and no genotoxic damage while the low molecular weight I-DBPs were cytotoxic and induced genomic DNA damage in mammalian cells. Thus it is the low molecular weight I-DBPs that are responsible for the generation of enhanced toxicity after iopamidol and source waters were disinfected. These data demonstrate that widely used pharmaceutical contaminants in source waters can lead to drinking water disinfection by-products that may have adverse consequences for the environment and the public health.          Last Modified: 09/12/2016       Submitted by: Michael J Plewa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
