<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Defining controls on incisional avulsions in alluvial basins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>171083.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171083</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlawrenc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collaborative Research: Defining controls on incisional avulsions in alluvial basins&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;River avulsion occurs when water is diverted out of a river and creates a new channel on the surrounding floodplain. The associated flooding can be catastrophic for people living along rivers, but hazard mitigation is difficult because models cannot predict the timing, location, or style of river avulsion.  Incisional avulsion occurs when a new river channel is established through erosion rather than deposition, and, although it is common in some river systems, this avulsion style is particularly poorly understood. The goal of this study is to define the sedimentologic and hydrodynamic conditions associated with incisional avulsions. Using combined modeling and field approaches the PIs will evaluate how characteristics such as floodplain topography, slope, ground cover, and overbank deposition control avulsion styles and test the hypothesis that incisional avulsions occur in steep fluvial systems with topographically rough, unvegetated, well-drained floodplains that lack abundant overbank suspended-sediment supply. Modeling work will be conducted with Delft3D, a physics-based numerical model that solves the equations for water flow and sediment transport, and field-data collection will focus on ancient strata where channel and floodplain characteristics can be measured for large numbers of paleoavulsion deposits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results from this project will help improve prediction of avulsion flood hazards and will enhance understanding of the relationships between channel avulsion and floodplain erosion and deposition. Avulsion is also a primary control on the distribution of fluvial hydrocarbon, groundwater, and CO2-storage reservoirs. Better understanding of avulsion processes gained through this research will aid subsurface predictions of reservoir quality and location. Broader impacts of this work also include development of a self-paced, web-based education module about rivers and avulsions. In collaboration with the Geoscience Outreach Foundation the PIs will design a Rivers from Above curriculum comprising guided tours of rivers and avulsions using Google Earth and Google Maps. Rivers from Above will focus on river forms and patterns, river avulsion, and avulsion impacts on society. The PIs will work with the outreach offices at Penn State and Boston College to develop, pilot test, and evaluate module activities in Pittsburgh- and Boston-area schools, targeting underserved communities in each region. Finally, this proposal will also support the education and training of several graduate and undergraduate students and the early careers of two junior faculty members.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1124167</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Hajek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Hajek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hajek@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148674418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000555947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~171083</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="float-left">Rivers sometimes jump their banks and relocate to new pathways. This process, called river avulsion, is important because it distributes nutrients to farms and floodplains, poses significant and hard-to-predict flooding risks to communities living near rivers, and controls the distribution and quality of hydrocarbon and water resources buried in ancient river deposits. The goal of this project was to determine what characteristics of channels and floodplains control river avulsion style both today and in Earth&rsquo;s past. In particular we wanted to understand why some rivers avulse by eroding into their floodplains rather than by building new channels through deposition because this difference is significant for predicting avulsion patterns, flood risks, and the connectedness of buried river deposits.</p> <p>By studying what controls river avulsion style in ancient river deposits, in modern rivers, and with numerical models, we have been able to demonstrate that the type of sediment carried by a river, floodplain drainage, and floodplain topography are key factors that determine avulsion style. Results from this research show that the relationship between channels and floodplains is complex and that floodplain conditions can have a significant influence on river behavior. The scaling relationship established during this project (that describes or predicts how commonly a river is likely to avulse by incision or progradation; Hajek and Edmonds, 2014) is novel and provides a new basis for comparing relative rates and scales of these processes even in ancient deposits.</p> <p class="clear">This project serves as an important example of how the stratigraphic record can bolster studies of geomorphology and surface processes. By successfully combining geomorphological and stratigraphic perspectives on Earth surface processes, the results of this project impact both civil engineering and river management along with how the petroleum industry can predict the connectivity of subsurface reservoirs. This project demonstrates the potential for integrated hypothesis testing across modern and ancient systems in future work.</p> <p>This project supported undergraduate and gradate students and results from this research have been incorporated into secondary school, undergraduate, and graduate curricula. The multi-disciplinary aspects of this project provided a important framework for STEM and geoscience workforce development. Digital outcrop datasets collected during this study are publically available for other research and teaching projects. Results from this research are detailed in peer-reviewed publications, were included in presentations at international meetings, and comprise portions of multiple graduate and undergraduate theses.</p> <p>Improved understanding of river avulsion that resulted from this study will enhance our ability to predict avulsion-related flooding hazards in rivers worldwide, support sustainable river management, and advance development of subsurface energy and water resources.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Elizabeth&nbsp;A&nbsp;Hajek</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1124167/1124167_10136469_1483160273110_NSFreportFinal_summaryfig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1124167/1124167_10136469_1483160273110_NSFreportFinal_summaryfig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Controls on river avulsion style"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1124167/1124167_10136469_1483160273110_NSFreportFinal_summaryfig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Controls on river avulsion style"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Incisional and progradational avulsions are end-member styles associated with floodplains that are either prone to deposit or erode. (Based on Hajek and Edmonds, 2014)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Elizabeth Hajek</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elizabeth&nbsp;A&nbsp;Hajek</div> <div class="imageTitle">Controls on river avulsion style</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Rivers sometimes jump their banks and relocate to new pathways. This process, called river avulsion, is important because it distributes nutrients to farms and floodplains, poses significant and hard-to-predict flooding risks to communities living near rivers, and controls the distribution and quality of hydrocarbon and water resources buried in ancient river deposits. The goal of this project was to determine what characteristics of channels and floodplains control river avulsion style both today and in Earth?s past. In particular we wanted to understand why some rivers avulse by eroding into their floodplains rather than by building new channels through deposition because this difference is significant for predicting avulsion patterns, flood risks, and the connectedness of buried river deposits.  By studying what controls river avulsion style in ancient river deposits, in modern rivers, and with numerical models, we have been able to demonstrate that the type of sediment carried by a river, floodplain drainage, and floodplain topography are key factors that determine avulsion style. Results from this research show that the relationship between channels and floodplains is complex and that floodplain conditions can have a significant influence on river behavior. The scaling relationship established during this project (that describes or predicts how commonly a river is likely to avulse by incision or progradation; Hajek and Edmonds, 2014) is novel and provides a new basis for comparing relative rates and scales of these processes even in ancient deposits. This project serves as an important example of how the stratigraphic record can bolster studies of geomorphology and surface processes. By successfully combining geomorphological and stratigraphic perspectives on Earth surface processes, the results of this project impact both civil engineering and river management along with how the petroleum industry can predict the connectivity of subsurface reservoirs. This project demonstrates the potential for integrated hypothesis testing across modern and ancient systems in future work.  This project supported undergraduate and gradate students and results from this research have been incorporated into secondary school, undergraduate, and graduate curricula. The multi-disciplinary aspects of this project provided a important framework for STEM and geoscience workforce development. Digital outcrop datasets collected during this study are publically available for other research and teaching projects. Results from this research are detailed in peer-reviewed publications, were included in presentations at international meetings, and comprise portions of multiple graduate and undergraduate theses.  Improved understanding of river avulsion that resulted from this study will enhance our ability to predict avulsion-related flooding hazards in rivers worldwide, support sustainable river management, and advance development of subsurface energy and water resources.       Last Modified: 12/31/2016       Submitted by: Elizabeth A Hajek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
