<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CDI-Type II: First-Principles Based Control of Multi-Scale Meta-Material Assembly Processes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>406401.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406401</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The assembly of colloidal nano- or micro-particles into perfectly ordered periodic structures provides a basis for manufacturing photonic band gap materials and other multi-scale meta-materials with unique electric, magnetic, and optical properties.  Although proof-of-concept materials have been made in laboratories to verify their amazing properties, no existing process is yet sufficiently controllable, scalable, and robust for high-throughput manufacturing to enable commercial applications.  The fundamental limitation to assembling colloidal components into ordered structures is the complex interplay of thermal motion, interparticle interactions, and external fields that lead to defect-rich and often arrested states.  We propose a new approach to the meta-material assembly problem that combines expertise from four separate scientific fields that traditionally have had minimal interaction.  Mathematical models of the colloidal systems, represented as free energy landscapes (FELs) in a few key variables that characterize the state of the assembly process, will be constructed using data from advanced microscopic imaging and analysis tools.  The FELs will in turn be used as input to rigorous process control algorithms, developed for stochastic processes, that will navigate the landscapes to yield defect-free products. This strategy will be demonstrated and refined on prototype lab-scale reactors, using real-time digital microscopic imaging as the sensor and programmable particle-particle interaction potentials &amp; electric fields as the actuators, to produce meta-materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of broader impact, successful development of fundamental tools for large-scale assembly of defect-free colloidal crystals has the potential to produce revolutionary technologies (e.g. optical computing, energy harvesting, sub-diffraction limit imaging, invisibility cloaking) not unlike the creation of single crystal silicon to enable integrated circuits and modern computing. No existing processes today are capable of producing such materials at a commercial scale despite 25 years of trial-and-error efforts. A strategy of rigorous real-time control using quantitatively accurate process models, like that proposed here, is required. The education and outreach activities will incorporate integrate concepts from modeling, control, simulations, and experiments, including rich visual data from colloid experiments (e.g. images, videos) and physics-based simulations (e.g. renderings, animations) to provide intuitive education/training for students at all levels.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1125188</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Ford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daveford@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795754951</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000188788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7751</Code>
<Text>CDI TYPE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7721</Code>
<Text>FROM DATA TO KNOWLEDGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7722</Code>
<Text>COMPLEXITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7752</Code>
<Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~406401</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Meta-materials are synthetic materials composed of small objects arranged in a regular pattern &ndash; like a crystalline solid, but made of small particles rather than atoms. Meta-materials have unique electric, magnetic, and optical properties because of their perfectly ordered structures that repeat on a length scale similar to that of electromagnetic radiation. There is currently no way to manufacture meta-materials at a large scale with an acceptably low number of defects. This project developed experimental and modeling tools to enable the assembly of colloidal particles (solid particles of size 1 nanometer to 1 micron, dispersed in liquid) into perfectly ordered periodic structures. The approach was based on obtaining dynamical models of colloidal assembly from optical microscopy and computer simulations, which were then used in rigorous process control algorithms to navigate complex stochastic assembly processes to yield defect-free structures. The intellectual merit of this proposal was in the development of integrated methods and models to engineer pathways towards low-defect nano- and micro- structured materials. The broader impacts of this project included the training of students in new ways to measure and manipulate synthetic and natural materials that are of utmost importance to nano-science and technology, and therefore of great potential importance to future technologies that aim to manipulate interactions, dynamics, structure, and emergent properties in synthetic material systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2015<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Ford</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1125188/1125188_10129709_1449002561241_OutcomesFigure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1125188/1125188_10129709_1449002561241_OutcomesFigure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Overview"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1125188/1125188_10129709_1449002561241_OutcomesFigure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Overview"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The directed assembly of colloidal particles into structured objects requires four major elements: sensing, modeling, actuation, and control.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael A. Bevan, David M. Ford, Martha A. Grover, Benjamin Shapiro</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Ford</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Overview</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Meta-materials are synthetic materials composed of small objects arranged in a regular pattern &ndash; like a crystalline solid, but made of small particles rather than atoms. Meta-materials have unique electric, magnetic, and optical properties because of their perfectly ordered structures that repeat on a length scale similar to that of electromagnetic radiation. There is currently no way to manufacture meta-materials at a large scale with an acceptably low number of defects. This project developed experimental and modeling tools to enable the assembly of colloidal particles (solid particles of size 1 nanometer to 1 micron, dispersed in liquid) into perfectly ordered periodic structures. The approach was based on obtaining dynamical models of colloidal assembly from optical microscopy and computer simulations, which were then used in rigorous process control algorithms to navigate complex stochastic assembly processes to yield defect-free structures. The intellectual merit of this proposal was in the development of integrated methods and models to engineer pathways towards low-defect nano- and micro- structured materials. The broader impacts of this project included the training of students in new ways to measure and manipulate synthetic and natural materials that are of utmost importance to nano-science and technology, and therefore of great potential importance to future technologies that aim to manipulate interactions, dynamics, structure, and emergent properties in synthetic material systems.          Last Modified: 12/01/2015       Submitted by: David M Ford]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
