<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference on GEOMETRIC STRUCTURES IN MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15390.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15390</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The purpose of the conference is to bring together physicists and mathematicians working in related areas of differential geometry, geometric analysis and theoretical physics. The main focus will be on special geometric structures and their applications in differential and algebraic geometry, theoretical physics and string theory.  The conference is structured  around invited talks, poster session and informal discussions.&lt;br/&gt;NSF funds will be used to support the participation of US researchers in the international conference on Geometric Structures in Mathematical Physics, Golden Sands, Bulgaria, September 19 - September 26, 2011.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mathematics has always been a fundamental subject. The conference will provide an important opportunity for Americans researchers to meet their partners from around the world. The conference gives a unique opportunity for sharing of ideas between researchers of many EU and US scientists. Specific topics will be determined by the invited speakers who are all internationally recognized experts. These topics are all active and central areas of geometry and mathematical physics.  The conference aims at presenting and developing further the latest achievements in the subject. About 70% of the requested total funding will be used for covering the traveling expenses of US participants without additional NSF support who are from under-represented groups, post-doctoral associates, and junior faculty.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1127129</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dimiter</FirstName>
<LastName>Vassilev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dimiter N Vassilev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vassilev@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052772136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238702</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868853094</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~15390</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The funding was used to support the travel of US participants to two international conferences: <em>Geometric Structures in Mathematical Physics 2011</em>(Golden Sands, Bulgaria, September 19-26, 2011) and <em>Differential Geometry Days In <span><span>honour</span></span> of Luis A. <span><span>Cordero</span></span> </em>(Santiago <span><span>de</span></span> <span><span>Compostela</span></span>, Spain, June 27-29, 2012).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The conferences brought together physicists and mathematicians working in related areas of differential geometry, geometric analysis and theoretical physics. The main focus was on special geometric structures and their applications in geometry, theoretical physics and string theory. The format was invited talks, poster sessions and informal discussions. There were more than fourty&nbsp; talks and&nbsp; posters covering topics on the latest achievements in the subjects.&nbsp; The conference participants included a number of graduate students and young researchers. All participants were able to work on existing or create new collaborative projects.</p> <div class="WordSection1"> <p><strong>Plenary Talks</strong></p> </div> <pre><em>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Ilka Agricola (Philipps-University Marburg, Germany), <em>Dirac operators with torsion</em></pre> <pre><em>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Adrian Andrada (Universidad Nacional de Cordoba, Argentina), <em>Flat complex connections with torsion of type (1,1)</em></pre> <pre><em>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Vestislav Apostolov (UQAM, Montreal, Canada), <em>Ambitoric 4-manifolds<strong> </strong></em></pre> <pre><em>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Florin Belgun (University of Hamburg, Germany), <em>A generalization of Gallot's theorem</em></pre> <pre><em>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Charles Boyer (University of New Mexico, USA), <em>Extremal Sasakian Geometry</em></pre> <pre><em>6.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Christofer Braun (University of Leicester, UK), <em>Quantum homotopy algebras</em></pre> <pre><em>7.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Letizia Brunetti (University of Bari, Italy), <em>A new Osserman condition in Lorentz S-manifolds</em></pre> <pre><em>8.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>David Calderbank (University of Bath, UK), <em>Extremal metrics and the ambitoric geometry of convex quadrilaterals</em></pre> <pre><em>9.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Vicente Cortes (University of Hamburg, Germany), <em>From cubic polynomials to complete quaternionic K&auml;hler manifolds</em></pre> <pre><em>10.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Johann Davidov (IMI BAS and Higher School of Civil Engineering, Bulgaria), <em>Para-hyperhermitian structures on complex surfaces</em></pre> <pre><em>11.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Isabel Dotti (Universidad Nacional de Cordoba, Argentina), <em>The Killing Yano equation on Lie groups</em></pre> <pre><em>12.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Maciej Dunajski (University of Cambridge, UK), <em>How to recognise a conformally K&auml;hler metric</em></pre> <pre><em>13.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Anna Fino (Universita di Torino, Italy), <em>An analog of selfduality in dimension nine</em></pre> <pre><em>14.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Thomas Friedrich (Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany), <em>Exotic geometries in special small dimensions</em></pre> <pre><em>15.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Sergey Galkin (IPMU, Tokyo, Japan), <em>Generalized K3 automorphisms</em></pre> <pre><em>16.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Paul Gauduchon (Ecole Polytechniquie, Paris, France), <em>Non-existence of almost complex structures on quaternion-K&auml;hler</em> <em>manifolds of positive type</em></pre> <pre><em>17.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Moritz Hoegner (University of Cambridge, UK), <em>Octonionic Instantons</em></pre> <pre><em>18.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Dmitry Kaledin (Steklov Math Institute, Moscow, Russia), <em>Cyclic K-theory</em></pre> <pre><em>19.&nbsp;&nbsp; </em>Ljudmila Kamenova (Stony Brook, USA), <em>Recent devel...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The funding was used to support the travel of US participants to two international conferences: Geometric Structures in Mathematical Physics 2011(Golden Sands, Bulgaria, September 19-26, 2011) and Differential Geometry Days In honour of Luis A. Cordero (Santiago de Compostela, Spain, June 27-29, 2012).    The conferences brought together physicists and mathematicians working in related areas of differential geometry, geometric analysis and theoretical physics. The main focus was on special geometric structures and their applications in geometry, theoretical physics and string theory. The format was invited talks, poster sessions and informal discussions. There were more than fourty  talks and  posters covering topics on the latest achievements in the subjects.  The conference participants included a number of graduate students and young researchers. All participants were able to work on existing or create new collaborative projects.   Plenary Talks  1.      Ilka Agricola (Philipps-University Marburg, Germany), Dirac operators with torsion 2.      Adrian Andrada (Universidad Nacional de Cordoba, Argentina), Flat complex connections with torsion of type (1,1) 3.      Vestislav Apostolov (UQAM, Montreal, Canada), Ambitoric 4-manifolds  4.      Florin Belgun (University of Hamburg, Germany), A generalization of Gallot's theorem 5.      Charles Boyer (University of New Mexico, USA), Extremal Sasakian Geometry 6.      Christofer Braun (University of Leicester, UK), Quantum homotopy algebras 7.      Letizia Brunetti (University of Bari, Italy), A new Osserman condition in Lorentz S-manifolds 8.      David Calderbank (University of Bath, UK), Extremal metrics and the ambitoric geometry of convex quadrilaterals 9.      Vicente Cortes (University of Hamburg, Germany), From cubic polynomials to complete quaternionic K&auml;hler manifolds 10.   Johann Davidov (IMI BAS and Higher School of Civil Engineering, Bulgaria), Para-hyperhermitian structures on complex surfaces 11.   Isabel Dotti (Universidad Nacional de Cordoba, Argentina), The Killing Yano equation on Lie groups 12.   Maciej Dunajski (University of Cambridge, UK), How to recognise a conformally K&auml;hler metric 13.   Anna Fino (Universita di Torino, Italy), An analog of selfduality in dimension nine 14.   Thomas Friedrich (Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany), Exotic geometries in special small dimensions 15.   Sergey Galkin (IPMU, Tokyo, Japan), Generalized K3 automorphisms 16.   Paul Gauduchon (Ecole Polytechniquie, Paris, France), Non-existence of almost complex structures on quaternion-K&auml;hler manifolds of positive type 17.   Moritz Hoegner (University of Cambridge, UK), Octonionic Instantons 18.   Dmitry Kaledin (Steklov Math Institute, Moscow, Russia), Cyclic K-theory 19.   Ljudmila Kamenova (Stony Brook, USA), Recent developments in hyper-K&auml;hler geometry 20.   Ludmil Katzarkov (University of Miami, USA &amp; University of Vienna), Wallcrossings and generations 21.   Alexei Kovalev (University of Cambridge, UK), New examples of compact and asymptotically cylindrical G2 manifolds 22.   Ignacio Lujan Fernandez (Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain), Reduction of Homogeneous structure 23.   Mancho Manev (Plovdiv University, Bulgaria), Natural connection with totally skew-symmetric torsion on almost contact manifolds with B-metric 24.   Velichka Milousheva ((IMI BAS and Higher School of Civil Engineering, Bulgaria), An invariant theory of marginally trapped surfaces in the four-dimensional Minkowski space 25.   Marian Ioan Munteanu (Al.I.Cuza University of Iasi, Romania), On the geometry of PR-warped products in para-K&auml;hler manifolds  26.   Tony Pantev (University of Pennsilvania, USA), Constructions of generalized monopoles 27.   George Papadopoulos (King's College London, UK), String special geometry 28.   Yat-Sun Poon (UC Riverside, USA), Deformation of Generalized Complex Manifolds 29.   Victor Przyjalkowski (Steklov Math Institute, Moscow, Russia), La...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
