<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI:  Optically Functional Surfaces for Photonic Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>394256.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>394256</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this GOALI program is to demonstrate optically functional surfaces by (i) employment of a deposition technique that allows for tailorable refractive indices and by (ii) lithographically structuring of refractive-index-controlled surfaces. The benefits resulting from such optically functional surfaces will be demonstrated in photo-voltaic solar cells and light-emitting diodes. The program is a collaborative effort with Magnolia Solar Company, a company committed to conduct joint research in optically-functional-surface technology and commercializing it for photo-voltaic applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In optical sciences, the refractive index of a medium is the most fundamental quantity and it is desirable to control both the (i) refractive index profile as well as (ii) the surface geometry (structure). The intellectual merit of the proposed project lies in the demonstration of a new class of optically functional surfaces, and in the employment of these surfaces in photo-voltaic solar cells and light-emitting diodes. Due to the fundamental nature of the refractive index, tailorable-refractive-index films are anticipated to be transformative with far-reaching impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational goals are (i) training and furthering of the intellectual growth of graduate students, (ii) raising the interest of undergraduate students particularly of domestic students and involvement of these students in leading-edge research, (iii) allowing students to work side-by-side with engineers from our partner company, and (iv) increasing participation of disadvantaged and underrepresented groups. The new research direction, including the application of new optical materials to devices, provides a great opportunity for students to be educated and trained in an exciting field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1127731</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Plawsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel L Plawsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plawsky@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182766049</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000321213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>E.</FirstName>
<LastName>Schubert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>E. F Schubert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>EFSchubert@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182768775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000202462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/31/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
<LastName>Welser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roger E Welser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>RWelser@QMEnergyInc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4015565644</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000549322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/20/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Madis</FirstName>
<LastName>Raukas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Madis Raukas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>madis.raukas@sylvania.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9787501506</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000645428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Eighth Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~394256</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>YAG:Ce phosphors are widely used in LEDs to help produce white light. The photoluminescent YAG:Ce phosphors are capable of absorbing blue light and down-converting it into yellow light. White light is thus obtained by mixing the remaining blue light and the down-converted yellow light. Powder-based YAG:Ce phosphors are commonly used but they exhibit disadvantages such as high scattering loss and heat accumulation. YAG:Ce ceramic phosphor plates (CPPs) were developed as a new type of phosphor for applications requiring high luminance and prolonged lifetime. However, YAG:Ce CPPs bring new challenges. First, YAG:Ce CPPs suffer high surface reflection losses due to the noticeable refractive index difference between the YAG:Ce (n = 1.82~1.85) and the air (n = 1), so that about 15.6% of the incident light is lost due to the index mismatch. Second, the emission from activators inside the YAG:Ce CPPs is omnidirectional, rather than in a desired, concentrated emission pattern. Therefore, optical structures that could address these two challenges are of great interest. A nanospiral-structured graded-index anti-reflection coating was fabricated in this work on the surface of YAG:Ce and has been demonstrated to effectively enhance the normal-direction transmission of YAG:Ce. &nbsp;Near theoretical performance was achieved using TiO2 and SiO2 materials.</p> <p>An optical model based on the film growth mechanism was developed for simulating the effect of coating morphology on its optical response, and also for evaluating the adverse factors, such as scattering and absorption, that deteriorate the anti-reflection coating&rsquo;s performance. the model was shown to be in excellent agreement with the data and explained why spiral and zig-zag structures are preferred over straight nanorod formulations.</p> <p>The work led to the development of two new structures and their fabrication is ongoing. The first structure is a graded-index anti-reflection grating that would offer enhanced transmission over a spatially uniform coating. &nbsp;The second structure is more exiting, a zero-index photonic crystal, made entirely from dielectric materials and would enable further spatial and frequency control of light.</p> <p>In addition, several offshoots of the work were promising. &nbsp;We developed nanostructured coatings for photoctalaysis that include gold nanoparticles deposited directly atop the nanostructures to for a periodic gold/TiO2 array sandwich. &nbsp;This offered the ability to shift the absorption frequency of the TiO2 into the visible region of the spectrum leading to enhanced performance. &nbsp;We were also able to simulate and theorteically describe the process for forming the gold nanoparticles and the realtionship between the gold layer thickness, the nanorod density, and the subsequent ability to form the gold nanospheres. &nbsp;Finally, we developed a thermal interface material consisting of a block copolymer matrix with an interpenetrating gold network. &nbsp;The system offers promise for making enhanced coatings to reject heat in microelectronic and photonic devices.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2016<br>      Modified by: Joel&nbsp;L&nbsp;Plawsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1127731/1127731_10121025_1472589162122_Photo1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1127731/1127731_10121025_1472589162122_Photo1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Antireflection Coating"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1127731/1127731_10121025_1472589162122_Photo1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Antireflection Coating"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM images of an optimized antireflection coating formed from 6 layers of TiO2 followed by 5 layers of SiO2.</div> <div class="imageCredit">S. Liu & J.L. Plawsky</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joel&nbsp;L&nbsp;Plawsky</div> <div class="imageTitle">Antireflection Coating</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1127731/1127731_10121025_1472590011579_Photo2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1127731/1127731_10121025_1472590011579_Photo2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Thermal Interface Material"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1127731/1127731_10121025_1472590011579_Photo2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Thermal Interface Material"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM images of gold, nanorod assemblies in patterned polystyrene/polymethymethacrylate block copolymer thin films after rapid thermal annealing at 180 °C for 1, 2, 4, 8 min (a-d), and 200 °C (for 1, 2, 4 min (e-g), respectively.</div> <div class="imageCredit">F.Lai & J.L. Plawsky</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joel&nbsp;L&nbsp;Plawsky</div> <div class="imageTitle">Thermal Interface Material</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ YAG:Ce phosphors are widely used in LEDs to help produce white light. The photoluminescent YAG:Ce phosphors are capable of absorbing blue light and down-converting it into yellow light. White light is thus obtained by mixing the remaining blue light and the down-converted yellow light. Powder-based YAG:Ce phosphors are commonly used but they exhibit disadvantages such as high scattering loss and heat accumulation. YAG:Ce ceramic phosphor plates (CPPs) were developed as a new type of phosphor for applications requiring high luminance and prolonged lifetime. However, YAG:Ce CPPs bring new challenges. First, YAG:Ce CPPs suffer high surface reflection losses due to the noticeable refractive index difference between the YAG:Ce (n = 1.82~1.85) and the air (n = 1), so that about 15.6% of the incident light is lost due to the index mismatch. Second, the emission from activators inside the YAG:Ce CPPs is omnidirectional, rather than in a desired, concentrated emission pattern. Therefore, optical structures that could address these two challenges are of great interest. A nanospiral-structured graded-index anti-reflection coating was fabricated in this work on the surface of YAG:Ce and has been demonstrated to effectively enhance the normal-direction transmission of YAG:Ce.  Near theoretical performance was achieved using TiO2 and SiO2 materials.  An optical model based on the film growth mechanism was developed for simulating the effect of coating morphology on its optical response, and also for evaluating the adverse factors, such as scattering and absorption, that deteriorate the anti-reflection coating?s performance. the model was shown to be in excellent agreement with the data and explained why spiral and zig-zag structures are preferred over straight nanorod formulations.  The work led to the development of two new structures and their fabrication is ongoing. The first structure is a graded-index anti-reflection grating that would offer enhanced transmission over a spatially uniform coating.  The second structure is more exiting, a zero-index photonic crystal, made entirely from dielectric materials and would enable further spatial and frequency control of light.  In addition, several offshoots of the work were promising.  We developed nanostructured coatings for photoctalaysis that include gold nanoparticles deposited directly atop the nanostructures to for a periodic gold/TiO2 array sandwich.  This offered the ability to shift the absorption frequency of the TiO2 into the visible region of the spectrum leading to enhanced performance.  We were also able to simulate and theorteically describe the process for forming the gold nanoparticles and the realtionship between the gold layer thickness, the nanorod density, and the subsequent ability to form the gold nanospheres.  Finally, we developed a thermal interface material consisting of a block copolymer matrix with an interpenetrating gold network.  The system offers promise for making enhanced coatings to reject heat in microelectronic and photonic devices.        Last Modified: 10/17/2016       Submitted by: Joel L Plawsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
