<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>QMHP: Multiscale Analysis of Coupled Electrical, Mechanical Systems at Nanoscale</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>352842.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352842</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is exploit unique electrical and mechanical properties of materials at the nanoscale to develop novel sensors, energy-conversion devices and integrated systems with unprecedented sensitivity, efficiency and functionality. The approach is to develop advanced computational tools to seamlessly integrate electrical and mechanical physical phenomena ranging from the quantum to the chip-scale, and to employ these computational tools to not only understand fundamental aspects of coupled electrical and mechanical phenomena but also to enable rapid computational prototyping of a variety of devices and systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposed research focuses on the development of fundamentally new multiscale approaches where physical theories accounting for quantum effects, nanoscopic electrical and mechanical behavior, and material in homogeneities will be developed. The multiscale computational tools will provide unique physical insights into electrical and mechanical properties and their coupling and enable development of innovative electrically-actuated nanoelectromechanical sensors, devices and systems. The proposed multiscale approaches have the potential to be many orders of magnitude faster than existing quantum and atomistic approaches for design of coupled electromechanical systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposed research on the development of novel nanoelectromechanical systems has the potential to revolutionize sensor, computer, energy and health care sectors there by creating new industry, economy and impacting the common person in the society. Proposed research will educate graduate and undergraduate students in the interdisciplinary area of computational nanotechnology. Educational modules focusing on fundamentals of nanoelectromechanical systems and multiscale computational methods will be developed and made available on the web.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1127480</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>N</FirstName>
<LastName>Aluru</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>N R Aluru</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aluru@utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2177226292</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148273</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Beckman Institute for Advanced Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618012325</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[405 N. Mathews Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102E</Code>
<Text>Quantum/high perform algorithm</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~114760</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~117586</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~120496</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Summary of Some of the Key Accomplishments<strong>:</strong></p> <ol> </ol> <p>1) We investigated coupled electrical and mechanical/chemical properties of graphene by performing quantum simulations based on density functional theory. In particular, we investigated adsorption of two gas molecules, 1,2-dichlorobenzene(DCB) and dimethyl methyphosphonate (DMMP), on graphene. Quantum calculations indicated that these molecules do not change the electronic properties (in particular the density of states) of pristine graphene. However, when graphene is p-doped, there is a significant effect of each gas molecule on electronic properties of graphene. In particular, DCP introduces holes in the valence band and DMMP introduces electrons in the conduction band. These studies not only provided fundamental insights into adsorption of gas molecules on graphene, but also enable sensing of a variety of gas molecules using graphene.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>2) Many electronic and mechanical applications of graphene rely on graphene deposited over some substrate. We performed extensive molecular dynamics simulations to investigate the mechanical properties of a silicon nanofilm covered with a defective graphene. Our results showed that graphene not only enhances the mechanical properties of a silicon nanofilm but also unifies the mechanical properties of the ultrathin silicon nanofilms among different crystal orientations. We observed that the Young's modulus and critical stress of the silicon nanofilm along four crystal orientations covered with graphene decrease as the thickness of the silicon nanofilm increases. In addition, we also studied the effects of monoatomic vacancies and Stone&ndash;Wales (SW) defects with various concentrations on the mechanical properties of a silicon nanofilm covered with defective graphene. Our results showed that Young's modulus reduces linearly for monoatomic vacancies and a relatively smaller dependence is observed on SW defects, while the critical stress is more sensitive to the presence of both types of defects. These results demonstrated the significance of graphene in enhancing the mechanical properties of the silicon nanofilm.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>3) By performing detailed atomistic simulations, we investigated the mechanical properties of cross-linked polymers. Crosslinking can fundamentally change the mechanical properties of a linear glassy polymer. It has been experimentally observed that when lightly crosslinked, poly(methylmethacrylate) (PMMA) has a characteristically more ductile response to mechanical loading than does linear PMMA despite having a higher glass transition temperature. We performed molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to investigate conformational and energetic differences between linear PMMA and lightly crosslinked PMMA under shear deformation. As consistent with experiments, crosslinked PMMA is found to have a reduced yield stress relative to linear PMMA. Using the probing capabilities of our explicit atom MD approach, we observed that while the crosslinks have a minimal direct energy contribution to the total system, they can alter how the main chains conform to macroscopic loading. In crosslinked PMMA, the backbone aligns more with the direction of external loading, thereby reducing the force applied to (and associated deformation of) the polymer bonds.</p> <p>4) We developed a better understanding of the attractive force that arises from quantum fluctuations (generally referred to as Casimir effects). The fundamental mechanisms underlying quantum fluctuations have been actively investigated through various theoretical and experimental approaches. However, the effect of the force on micro/nanoelectromechanical (M/NEM) devices has not been fully understood yet, especially in the transition region involving gaps ranging from 10 nm to 1 micron, due to the complexity of the force. During the last year, we numerically calculated the...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary of Some of the Key Accomplishments:    1) We investigated coupled electrical and mechanical/chemical properties of graphene by performing quantum simulations based on density functional theory. In particular, we investigated adsorption of two gas molecules, 1,2-dichlorobenzene(DCB) and dimethyl methyphosphonate (DMMP), on graphene. Quantum calculations indicated that these molecules do not change the electronic properties (in particular the density of states) of pristine graphene. However, when graphene is p-doped, there is a significant effect of each gas molecule on electronic properties of graphene. In particular, DCP introduces holes in the valence band and DMMP introduces electrons in the conduction band. These studies not only provided fundamental insights into adsorption of gas molecules on graphene, but also enable sensing of a variety of gas molecules using graphene.    2) Many electronic and mechanical applications of graphene rely on graphene deposited over some substrate. We performed extensive molecular dynamics simulations to investigate the mechanical properties of a silicon nanofilm covered with a defective graphene. Our results showed that graphene not only enhances the mechanical properties of a silicon nanofilm but also unifies the mechanical properties of the ultrathin silicon nanofilms among different crystal orientations. We observed that the Young's modulus and critical stress of the silicon nanofilm along four crystal orientations covered with graphene decrease as the thickness of the silicon nanofilm increases. In addition, we also studied the effects of monoatomic vacancies and Stone&ndash;Wales (SW) defects with various concentrations on the mechanical properties of a silicon nanofilm covered with defective graphene. Our results showed that Young's modulus reduces linearly for monoatomic vacancies and a relatively smaller dependence is observed on SW defects, while the critical stress is more sensitive to the presence of both types of defects. These results demonstrated the significance of graphene in enhancing the mechanical properties of the silicon nanofilm.    3) By performing detailed atomistic simulations, we investigated the mechanical properties of cross-linked polymers. Crosslinking can fundamentally change the mechanical properties of a linear glassy polymer. It has been experimentally observed that when lightly crosslinked, poly(methylmethacrylate) (PMMA) has a characteristically more ductile response to mechanical loading than does linear PMMA despite having a higher glass transition temperature. We performed molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to investigate conformational and energetic differences between linear PMMA and lightly crosslinked PMMA under shear deformation. As consistent with experiments, crosslinked PMMA is found to have a reduced yield stress relative to linear PMMA. Using the probing capabilities of our explicit atom MD approach, we observed that while the crosslinks have a minimal direct energy contribution to the total system, they can alter how the main chains conform to macroscopic loading. In crosslinked PMMA, the backbone aligns more with the direction of external loading, thereby reducing the force applied to (and associated deformation of) the polymer bonds.  4) We developed a better understanding of the attractive force that arises from quantum fluctuations (generally referred to as Casimir effects). The fundamental mechanisms underlying quantum fluctuations have been actively investigated through various theoretical and experimental approaches. However, the effect of the force on micro/nanoelectromechanical (M/NEM) devices has not been fully understood yet, especially in the transition region involving gaps ranging from 10 nm to 1 micron, due to the complexity of the force. During the last year, we numerically calculated the Casimir effects in M/NEM devices by using the Lifshitz formula, the general expression for the Casimir effects. Our results show ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
