<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Rapid Assessment of Antibiotic Resistance by Mass Measurement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499861.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>956807</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project proposes to develop a "close-to-care" instrument that can assess antibiotic susceptibility of infection-causing bacteria in less than one hour.  MEMS-fabricated sensors and integrated fluidics will measure the mass and growth rate of a small number of bacteria in-vitro with a resolution near 1 femtogram.  By exposing the bacteria to a panel of antibiotics while monitoring growth rate, an infection's susceptibility profile will be determined very rapidly.  Using this information, doctors will be able to select targeted antibiotic treatment much faster than is possible using conventional methods that require incubation and take 24 hours or longer - a crucial time savings.  The platform will be validated on multiple E. coli strains that have a range of susceptibility, in both saline and healthy urine matrices.  To demonstrate clinical value, the results will be compared to conventional methods.  Additional tests will be performed on clinical isolates of E. coli  and K. pneumoniae that cause urinary tract infections, and on MRSA (methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will be to improve medical outcomes of infection and to facilitate antibiotic stewardship.  The rapidly expanding prevalence of resistant bacteria, combined with a decline in the discovery of new antibiotics, pose one of today's most dire health threats.  More than 100,000 people die of infections each year in the U.S., behind only cancer and heart disease.  There is unanimous consensus among infectious disease experts that rapid diagnostics to identify resistance are crucial for administering targeted antibiotic therapy, leading to better outcomes, and for minimizing the spread of resistant strains.  The test to be developed here directly addresses these needs.  The project targets UTI (urinary tract infections) that are responsible for the majority of hospital-acquired infections; and MRSA (methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus) that kills more than 20,000 Americans every year.  The platform will be configured for "close-to-care" use in microbiology labs found in most hospitals, and capture a significant fraction of the $500M U.S. market for susceptibility testing equipment and reagents.  The platform also will address nearer-term markets in antibiotic discovery and laboratory research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1127393</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ken</FirstName>
<LastName>Babcock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ken L Babcock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ken@affinitybio.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8054550181</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000073285</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Affinity Biosensors</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931173108</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8054550181</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75D Robin Hill Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>802576830</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AFFINITY BIOSENSORS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Affinity Biosensors]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931173108</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75D Robin Hill RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~499861</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~456946</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h1>Intellectual Merits&nbsp;</h1> <p>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project produced a benchtop instrument that can automatically assess antibiotic susceptibility of infection-causing bacteria in just a few hours. At the heart of the instrument is a microfluidic sensor, called a microchannel resonator, that can detect microbes and even weigh them individually.&nbsp;&nbsp;The instrument profiles the contents of a bacteria culture in a few seconds by determining the bacteria concentration (#/ml) and the microbe mass profiles.&nbsp;&nbsp;By monitoring the growth rate of multiple cultures exposed to a number of antibiotics, the instrument can quickly determine which antibiotics will stifle microbe growth and successfully eliminate a patient&rsquo;s infection.&nbsp;&nbsp;Using this information, doctors will be able to select targeted antibiotic treatment much faster than is possible using conventional methods that take 24 hours or longer &ndash; a crucial time savings.&nbsp;&nbsp;The instrument has been tested successfully on multiple species of bacteria, including those taken from clinical blood and urine samples, and can produce antibiotic susceptibility results for a panel of 14 antibiotics.&nbsp;&nbsp;It will soon enter clinical trials to validate its use in diagnosing blood stream infection.</p> <h1>Broader Impacts</h1> <p>Speed is critical when diagnosing blood stream infection and sepsis.&nbsp;&nbsp;For every hour that a patient forgoes correct antibiotic treatment, the chance of death increases 8%.&nbsp;&nbsp;The instrument produced in this project will reduce the time needed to prescribe a targeted antibiotic from days to a few hours, and so will have a significant impact on patient outcomes.&nbsp;&nbsp;The open format of the instrument will also enable it to address other acute bacterial infections such as hospital-acquired urinary tract infections and meningitis. In addition to aiding treatment of individual patients, rapid diagnostics help prevent the spread of highly resistant strains of bacteria, one of today&rsquo;s most dire health threats.&nbsp;&nbsp;More than 100,000 people die of infections each year in the U.S., behind only cancer and heart disease, and the number is growing due to the emergence of &ldquo;superbugs,&rdquo; bacteria that resist treatment by multiple antibiotics, even the most advanced ones.&nbsp;&nbsp;The rapid diagnostic feedback provided by this instrument will help slow the spread of resistant strains by guaranteeing that the administered antibiotic will successfully eliminate an infection.&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>&nbsp;</em></p> <h1>Key Words</h1> <p>Bacteria, antibiotic, antibiotic susceptibility, antibiotic resistance, microchannel resonator</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Ken&nbsp;L&nbsp;Babcock</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Intellectual Merits   This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project produced a benchtop instrument that can automatically assess antibiotic susceptibility of infection-causing bacteria in just a few hours. At the heart of the instrument is a microfluidic sensor, called a microchannel resonator, that can detect microbes and even weigh them individually.  The instrument profiles the contents of a bacteria culture in a few seconds by determining the bacteria concentration (#/ml) and the microbe mass profiles.  By monitoring the growth rate of multiple cultures exposed to a number of antibiotics, the instrument can quickly determine which antibiotics will stifle microbe growth and successfully eliminate a patient?s infection.  Using this information, doctors will be able to select targeted antibiotic treatment much faster than is possible using conventional methods that take 24 hours or longer &ndash; a crucial time savings.  The instrument has been tested successfully on multiple species of bacteria, including those taken from clinical blood and urine samples, and can produce antibiotic susceptibility results for a panel of 14 antibiotics.  It will soon enter clinical trials to validate its use in diagnosing blood stream infection. Broader Impacts  Speed is critical when diagnosing blood stream infection and sepsis.  For every hour that a patient forgoes correct antibiotic treatment, the chance of death increases 8%.  The instrument produced in this project will reduce the time needed to prescribe a targeted antibiotic from days to a few hours, and so will have a significant impact on patient outcomes.  The open format of the instrument will also enable it to address other acute bacterial infections such as hospital-acquired urinary tract infections and meningitis. In addition to aiding treatment of individual patients, rapid diagnostics help prevent the spread of highly resistant strains of bacteria, one of today?s most dire health threats.  More than 100,000 people die of infections each year in the U.S., behind only cancer and heart disease, and the number is growing due to the emergence of "superbugs," bacteria that resist treatment by multiple antibiotics, even the most advanced ones.  The rapid diagnostic feedback provided by this instrument will help slow the spread of resistant strains by guaranteeing that the administered antibiotic will successfully eliminate an infection.    Key Words  Bacteria, antibiotic, antibiotic susceptibility, antibiotic resistance, microchannel resonator          Last Modified: 09/13/2018       Submitted by: Ken L Babcock]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
