<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Genetic and Histological Dissection of Phenotypic Variation in Quantitative Resistance to Maize Diseases</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3977771.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3977771</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne W. Sylvester</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asylvest@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927168</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Randall J. Wisser (University of Delaware - Newark)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Co-PIs: Kirk Czymmek (University of Delaware - Newark), Rebecca J. Nelson (Cornell University), Gary Payne (North Carolina State University), Nick Lauter (USDA-ARS/Iowa State University) and Alicia Carriquiry (Iowa State University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Other Senior Personnel/Faculty Associates: Peter J. Balint-Kurti and James B. Holland (USDA-ARS/North Carolina State University) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the causes of phenotypic variation in the plant defense response is one of the most important challenges faced by plant biologists. It is known that genetics plays a major role. However, this genetic variation is typically expressed on a quantitative scale that has made it difficult to pin down the genes and unravel the mechanisms underlying defense. Recent advances in plant research have substantially increased knowledge of the genetic architecture (i.e., information about how the genetic code produces phenotypic variation) of plant defense.  However, in order to make this knowledge actionable, genetic observations must be mechanistically understood at other biological levels such as the cellular and molecular levels. In this project, a comprehensive analysis of maize quantitative defense will refine the understanding of its genetic architecture and identify genes involved in phenotypic variation for disease resistance. Furthermore, large-scale genetic resources and modernized computational tools will be used to link genetic architecture to mechanisms responsible for host defense. This project aims to achieve a more holistic understanding of the biological basis of plant defense so that novel long-term solutions for disease control can be envisaged.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project are several-fold. First, the project will contribute to the development of sustainable approaches to crop protection. The project's contributions to understanding the mechanisms that underlie variation in plant-pathogen interactions will inform the design of resistant germplasm. This is important in reducing losses of yield and quality for US maize, but is even more critical for protecting the food security of smallholder farmers in developing countries, where losses due to maize diseases are proportionally greater. Second, project insights will be distilled and conveyed to a large and diverse group of citizens in an effective and entertaining way through partnership with the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences. This partnership will improve science teacher competency in plant sciences; strengthen education about plant genomics and biology for seventh grade students by giving them hands-on experiences in state-of-the-art labs; and to offer a lecture series to the general public to increase science literacy. The museum is the highest attended in NC with over 650,000 annual visitors of varied ages, educational and socio- economic backgrounds. Third, scientific capacity building will be an integral part of the research conducted across the four institutions involved in this project. Undergraduates, including those from underrepresented groups in science, will be exposed to both field and laboratory studies and mentored by project leaders and post-doctoral scholars. Graduate and post-doctoral scholars will receive supplemental training through specialized workshops and co-investigating laboratory visits. Exchanges between laboratories will allow these researchers to acquire new skills and strengthen their development in collaborative and integrative research. A dedicated project website will act as a public awareness showcase for the project and access as a portal to available data and resources generated by the project along with information about the deposition of data into resource-appropriate public repositories (such as GenBank, GEO, MaizeGDB, and Panzea) from which project data can be accessed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1127076</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Payne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary A Payne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gary_payne@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195156994</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250070</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kirk</FirstName>
<LastName>Czymmek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kirk J Czymmek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kczymmek@danforthcenter.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3145871261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/12/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Nelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca J Nelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rjn7@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072546499</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nick</FirstName>
<LastName>Lauter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nick Lauter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nickl@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152948260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
<LastName>Wisser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Randall Wisser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rjw@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028311356</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000534792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Caplan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Caplan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jcaplan@UDel.Edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028312136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000569055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1499972</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1824533</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~653266</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-02f628af-c9cf-a5ca-d52f-58132b7c56c2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Diseases caused by plant pathogens are one of the most important factors limiting agricultural productivity. Plants have different types of natural defenses, one of which, called quantitative disease resistance (QDR), is known for its durability &ndash; meaning that the resistance is effective over long periods of time and across large areas of land in which a crop is cultivated. Understanding how QDR is durable would open new avenues for sustainably mitigating diseases of crops. However, the complex nature of QDR has been a tremendous barrier to unravelling the mechanisms that underlie this type of resistance.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Focusing on two diseases of maize (corn), Northern leaf blight and Southern leaf blight, caused by different fungal pathogens, our team set out to begin acquiring a more holistic understanding of the biological basis of QDR so that novel, long-term solutions for disease control can be envisaged.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Through the development and use of germplasm resources, genetic and computational methods and tools, and a novel platform for investigating plant-pathogen interactions at the cellular level, this project shed new light on the biology of QDR while innovating scientific techniques for future studies on QDR.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Large-scale genetic mapping studies and applications of new statistical methods refined the roadmap linking genes in the maize genome to variation in QDR. Independent functional tests for some of these genes, using mutant genetic stocks and genetic transformation, helped to validate their role in QDR. Activities aimed at sequencing QDR-associated sections of the maize genome generated broadly useful tools for genetics and genomics research. This also provided new leads about the causal basis for QDR at one particular region of the genome that has been strongly associated with resistance to Northern leaf blight. Exemplifying the culmination of these and other project activities including bioimaging (described below), a maize gene encoding caffeoyl-CoA O-methyltransferase, associated with the strengthening of plant cell walls, was found to confer QDR to multiple diseases, including Northern and Southern leaf blight. Taken together, our team&rsquo;s efforts led to the discovery of different genes in the maize genome with unique functions underlying QDR, substantiating our hypothesis that an array of mechanisms or complexity per se may explain durability.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Infectious fungal pathogens form microscopic cellular networks inside of their host tissue, but QDR has been historically examined macroscopically as symptoms (lesions) on the 2D surface of the tissue, such as maize leaves in the case of Northern and Southern leaf blight. As another component of the project, interdisciplinary activities bridging genetics, pathology, microscopy, and computer science provided the first-ever glimpses into 3D microscopic maize-fungal interactions across continuous, millimeter (macroscopic) areas of host leaf tissue. This allowed multiple whole infection networks of the fungal pathogens within the host tissue to be examined in 3D. We learned that the different pathogens have either restricted (Northern leaf blight) or unrestricted (Southern leaf blight) means of gaining entry into the host tissue. For Southern leaf blight, at least one mechanism of QDR was found to occur post-infection, limiting expansion of infection networks within the host tissue. More generally, our work on 3D image data revealed a critical gap in methods to comparatively analyze and interpret 3D data on biological specimens. This will be an important frontier for the plant scientific community, which, in the emergent era of &ldquo;phenomics&rdquo; (high-throughput phenotyping), continues to amass similar data at different spatial scales.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In terms of personnel, this project supported the education and training of 11 undergraduate students, 16 graduate students, 9 postdoctoral associates, and 22 technicians or other professionals. Project leaders also collaborated with staff at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences to implement learning activities linked to the project. This helped the museum establish new exhibits and teaching toolkits that reached over 1500 students and teachers ranging from high school to elementary school levels.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Taken together, while helping to educate the next generation of scientists and contribute to public education, this project generated critical scientific resources, methods, and knowledge that set the stage for continued research on QDR and enable new thinking on the development of disease resistant varieties in maize and other crops. Continued research into plant disease resistance can lead to long-term solutions for crop protection that ensure a stable and secure food supply.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2018<br>      Modified by: Randall&nbsp;Wisser</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Diseases caused by plant pathogens are one of the most important factors limiting agricultural productivity. Plants have different types of natural defenses, one of which, called quantitative disease resistance (QDR), is known for its durability &ndash; meaning that the resistance is effective over long periods of time and across large areas of land in which a crop is cultivated. Understanding how QDR is durable would open new avenues for sustainably mitigating diseases of crops. However, the complex nature of QDR has been a tremendous barrier to unravelling the mechanisms that underlie this type of resistance. Focusing on two diseases of maize (corn), Northern leaf blight and Southern leaf blight, caused by different fungal pathogens, our team set out to begin acquiring a more holistic understanding of the biological basis of QDR so that novel, long-term solutions for disease control can be envisaged. Through the development and use of germplasm resources, genetic and computational methods and tools, and a novel platform for investigating plant-pathogen interactions at the cellular level, this project shed new light on the biology of QDR while innovating scientific techniques for future studies on QDR. Large-scale genetic mapping studies and applications of new statistical methods refined the roadmap linking genes in the maize genome to variation in QDR. Independent functional tests for some of these genes, using mutant genetic stocks and genetic transformation, helped to validate their role in QDR. Activities aimed at sequencing QDR-associated sections of the maize genome generated broadly useful tools for genetics and genomics research. This also provided new leads about the causal basis for QDR at one particular region of the genome that has been strongly associated with resistance to Northern leaf blight. Exemplifying the culmination of these and other project activities including bioimaging (described below), a maize gene encoding caffeoyl-CoA O-methyltransferase, associated with the strengthening of plant cell walls, was found to confer QDR to multiple diseases, including Northern and Southern leaf blight. Taken together, our team?s efforts led to the discovery of different genes in the maize genome with unique functions underlying QDR, substantiating our hypothesis that an array of mechanisms or complexity per se may explain durability. Infectious fungal pathogens form microscopic cellular networks inside of their host tissue, but QDR has been historically examined macroscopically as symptoms (lesions) on the 2D surface of the tissue, such as maize leaves in the case of Northern and Southern leaf blight. As another component of the project, interdisciplinary activities bridging genetics, pathology, microscopy, and computer science provided the first-ever glimpses into 3D microscopic maize-fungal interactions across continuous, millimeter (macroscopic) areas of host leaf tissue. This allowed multiple whole infection networks of the fungal pathogens within the host tissue to be examined in 3D. We learned that the different pathogens have either restricted (Northern leaf blight) or unrestricted (Southern leaf blight) means of gaining entry into the host tissue. For Southern leaf blight, at least one mechanism of QDR was found to occur post-infection, limiting expansion of infection networks within the host tissue. More generally, our work on 3D image data revealed a critical gap in methods to comparatively analyze and interpret 3D data on biological specimens. This will be an important frontier for the plant scientific community, which, in the emergent era of "phenomics" (high-throughput phenotyping), continues to amass similar data at different spatial scales. In terms of personnel, this project supported the education and training of 11 undergraduate students, 16 graduate students, 9 postdoctoral associates, and 22 technicians or other professionals. Project leaders also collaborated with staff at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences to implement learning activities linked to the project. This helped the museum establish new exhibits and teaching toolkits that reached over 1500 students and teachers ranging from high school to elementary school levels. Taken together, while helping to educate the next generation of scientists and contribute to public education, this project generated critical scientific resources, methods, and knowledge that set the stage for continued research on QDR and enable new thinking on the development of disease resistant varieties in maize and other crops. Continued research into plant disease resistance can lead to long-term solutions for crop protection that ensure a stable and secure food supply.               Last Modified: 02/24/2018       Submitted by: Randall Wisser]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
