<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Energy Efficient COD Removal and De-nitrification for Re-circulating Aquaculture Facilities with a Combined Bio-electrochemical Process</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1207998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will optimize and pilot test a novel, energy-positive approach to de-nitrification for the global aquaculture industry. Recirculating aquaculture systems suffer from high wastewater treatment costs. Leveraging recent advances in bio-electrochemical systems, Cambrian's de-nitrification technology is capable of simultaneously treating chemical oxygen demand (COD) at end of pipe and nitrates in culture tank water while generating electricity directly. Phase I R&amp;D demonstrated the existence of exo-electrogenic microorganisms in aquaculture wastewater. A flow through reactor consistently treated nitrate to below EPA drinking water concentrations (10mg/L) while removing an average of 65% of end-of-pipe COD and generating over 96 Amps/m3. An economic analysis demonstrated potential operating savings of over 70%, and significant bio-security benefits, versus competing systems. Phase II R&amp;D will focus on optimizing treatment rates and reactor parameters with partner firms, and piloting a scaled reactor at an Aquaculture farm.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research are to introduce technologies and strategies that solve water and energy problems for the recirculating aquaculture industry. With the collapse of fisheries globally, the aquaculture industry is poised to fill an important gap in our food production. However, recirculating systems in particular are under pressure to limit environmental harm caused by water intensity and pollution. Bio-electrochemical systems represent a novel approach to turn waste resources into energy, thereby increasing farmer?s bottom line and resolving the tension between economics and sustainability. Future research can broaden applications to other industries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1127435</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Silver</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew R Silver</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>silver@cambrianinnovation.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173071755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000083644</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/26/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhen</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhen Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zhuang@cambrianinnovation.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173071755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000593728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cambrian Innovation Inc</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>022102347</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173071755</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>27 Drydock Avenue 2nd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>784797412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAMBRIAN INNOVATION INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784797412</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Intact Labs LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021434213</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>168E</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR/ERC Collab (SECO)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~508000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~599999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~99999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>NSF Phase II SBIR Final Report</strong></p> <p><strong>Reporting Period: </strong><strong>10/01/2011 </strong><strong>&ndash; 05/31/2018</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;Energy Efficient COD Removal and Denitrification for Recirculating Aquaculture Facilities with a Combined Bioelectrochemical Process</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Principal Investigator: <strong>Dr. Zhen Huang</strong></p> <p>Project Manager: <strong>Dr.</strong> <strong>Prakash Balan</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>NSF Phase II Award: &nbsp;<strong>1127435</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <h2>1. Public Summary</h2> <p><span style="color: #158155; font-size: 22px;">1.1&nbsp;&nbsp; Technical Merits</span></p> <p>Cambrian has developed a concept for applying AquaVolt technology to remove nitrogen from the effluent of wastewater treatment systems in industrial and municipal operations. The technology focuses&nbsp;on ion-exchange-based denitrification in modular form membranes to improve nitrogen management in anaerobic systems. Discharges from industrial facilities, especially wastewater treatment facilities, for example in wineries, breweries and dairies and municipal wastewater treatment plants, with little to no treatment for nitrogen are a significant source of nitrogen nutrients to surface waters throughout the country. Setting permit limits and treating the wastewater to meet these limits can substantially reduce nitrogen loading from these facilities, protecting local and downstream water quality.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This Phase II SBIR project focused on the development of this technology as a novel polishing solution for wineries to enable water reuse as irrigation water. The focus of the project was to identify key operational parameters to optimize nitrate flux transfer via an anion exchange membrane, develop novel membrane modules and system process, and demonstrate the technology at larger scale. Cambrian Innovation&rsquo;s proprietary design and application of AquaVolt offers enhanced nitrogen removal to meet regulatory while providing additional benefits as follows: (i) <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Capability to achieve vineyard irrigation water quality standard for reuse:</span> (ii) <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Economic System with low capital and operational costs;</span> (iii) <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Modular design.</span> Overall, the project was successful in establishing solutions to operational constraints, and the technology is now ready for commercial deployment.</p> <p><span style="color: #158155; font-size: 22px;">1.2&nbsp;&nbsp; Broader Impacts/ Commercial Potential</span></p> <p>The application of AquaVolt technology has the potential to provide an economical method to reduce nitrogen discharge from industrial and municipal wastewater treatment systems. Equipment and process design for an integrated process and bench scale testing was completed to demonstrate this conceptual application of AquaVolt technology. This application could provide a nearer term opportunity for commercial introduction of AquaVolt technology compared to residential on-site wastewater treatment application because the potential users of this technology are already under considerable regulatory pressure to reduce nitrogen discharge, are better funded industrial and municipal operations that can more readily afford the required investment compared to individual homeowners and the existence of a more efficient path to market through established technology licensors and system suppliers.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The target entry market for AquaVolt technology will be winery effluent polishing (COD and nitrogen removal) where the polished effluent can be used for vineyard irrigation. It was reported that 32,585 gallons water is needed for irrigation per ton grapes in northern California. Assuming one ton grape makes 780 bottles of wine, it corresponds to a total number of 150,000 million gallons of irrigation water is required in California only given US produced 825 million gallons of wine in 2015 and California produced an average of 90 percent of total U.S. wine production. Today&rsquo;s forward-thinking wineries are actively seeking the cost savings from the reuse of treated wastewater for irrigation. However, most of the wineries treated effluent can&rsquo;t meet the irrigation water quality standards. One of the most important &ldquo;out of compliance&rdquo; parameter is nitrogen. Sensitive crops may be affected by nitrogen concentrations above 5 mg/l. Grapes are sensitive and may continue to grow late into the season at the expense of fruit production. Yields are often reduced and grapes may be late in maturing and have a lower sugar content. Experience in Libya indicated that almost no fruiting occurred in grapes when an irrigation water containing &gt;50 mg/l of N was used continuously.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Upon successful demonstration, AquaVolt will not only be offered as a turn?key water and wastewater treatment solution available for installation directly by the facility operator but will also be marketed as a key component to larger water treatment systems and skid-mounted systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2018<br>      Modified by: Zhen&nbsp;Huang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF Phase II SBIR Final Report  Reporting Period: 10/01/2011 &ndash; 05/31/2018      Energy Efficient COD Removal and Denitrification for Recirculating Aquaculture Facilities with a Combined Bioelectrochemical Process     Principal Investigator: Dr. Zhen Huang  Project Manager: Dr. Prakash Balan   NSF Phase II Award:  1127435    1. Public Summary  1.1   Technical Merits  Cambrian has developed a concept for applying AquaVolt technology to remove nitrogen from the effluent of wastewater treatment systems in industrial and municipal operations. The technology focuses on ion-exchange-based denitrification in modular form membranes to improve nitrogen management in anaerobic systems. Discharges from industrial facilities, especially wastewater treatment facilities, for example in wineries, breweries and dairies and municipal wastewater treatment plants, with little to no treatment for nitrogen are a significant source of nitrogen nutrients to surface waters throughout the country. Setting permit limits and treating the wastewater to meet these limits can substantially reduce nitrogen loading from these facilities, protecting local and downstream water quality.      This Phase II SBIR project focused on the development of this technology as a novel polishing solution for wineries to enable water reuse as irrigation water. The focus of the project was to identify key operational parameters to optimize nitrate flux transfer via an anion exchange membrane, develop novel membrane modules and system process, and demonstrate the technology at larger scale. Cambrian Innovation?s proprietary design and application of AquaVolt offers enhanced nitrogen removal to meet regulatory while providing additional benefits as follows: (i) Capability to achieve vineyard irrigation water quality standard for reuse: (ii) Economic System with low capital and operational costs; (iii) Modular design. Overall, the project was successful in establishing solutions to operational constraints, and the technology is now ready for commercial deployment.  1.2   Broader Impacts/ Commercial Potential  The application of AquaVolt technology has the potential to provide an economical method to reduce nitrogen discharge from industrial and municipal wastewater treatment systems. Equipment and process design for an integrated process and bench scale testing was completed to demonstrate this conceptual application of AquaVolt technology. This application could provide a nearer term opportunity for commercial introduction of AquaVolt technology compared to residential on-site wastewater treatment application because the potential users of this technology are already under considerable regulatory pressure to reduce nitrogen discharge, are better funded industrial and municipal operations that can more readily afford the required investment compared to individual homeowners and the existence of a more efficient path to market through established technology licensors and system suppliers.      The target entry market for AquaVolt technology will be winery effluent polishing (COD and nitrogen removal) where the polished effluent can be used for vineyard irrigation. It was reported that 32,585 gallons water is needed for irrigation per ton grapes in northern California. Assuming one ton grape makes 780 bottles of wine, it corresponds to a total number of 150,000 million gallons of irrigation water is required in California only given US produced 825 million gallons of wine in 2015 and California produced an average of 90 percent of total U.S. wine production. Today?s forward-thinking wineries are actively seeking the cost savings from the reuse of treated wastewater for irrigation. However, most of the wineries treated effluent can?t meet the irrigation water quality standards. One of the most important "out of compliance" parameter is nitrogen. Sensitive crops may be affected by nitrogen concentrations above 5 mg/l. Grapes are sensitive and may continue to grow late into the season at the expense of fruit production. Yields are often reduced and grapes may be late in maturing and have a lower sugar content. Experience in Libya indicated that almost no fruiting occurred in grapes when an irrigation water containing &gt;50 mg/l of N was used continuously.      Upon successful demonstration, AquaVolt will not only be offered as a turn?key water and wastewater treatment solution available for installation directly by the facility operator but will also be marketed as a key component to larger water treatment systems and skid-mounted systems.          Last Modified: 08/08/2018       Submitted by: Zhen Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
