<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of a Tender-Energy Microspectroscopy and Imaging User Facility for Earth Sciences at NSLS and NSLS-II</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225620.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225620</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will create a new, unique synchrotron-based user facility to examine geologic materials at the micron scale with a focused X-ray beam tuned specifically for lighter elements Na through Ti.  This facility is designed and optimized for "tender" (1-8 keV energy) X-ray micro-spectroscopy and imaging applications for Earth Science research, and will complement existing and highly productive "hard" X-ray facilities operating above about 4.5 keV.  It will extend to lower energies the X-ray fluorescence (XRF) and X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) capabilities typical of hard X-ray microprobes, as element-specific non-invasive probes of elemental distribution and local physical and electronic structures and states in crystalline and non-crystalline materials.  In addition, it will offer advanced capabilities for microbeam extended X-ray absorption spectroscopy (EXAFS) for determination of more detailed local structure around the selected element.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will be undertaken by adding new micro-focusing capabilities at an established and proven macro-focused (~1mm spot size) tender-energy XAS beamline at X15B of the National Synchrotron Light Source (NSLS) at Brookhaven National Laboratory, and will subsequently transition to the new Tender Energy Spectroscopy (TES) beamline under development at NSLS-II.  Its key attributes will be the distinct 1 to 8 keV energy range, user-tunable spot size from about 50 microns to 1 micron, high flux and stability optimized for high-quality and extended XAS, options for both XRF and XAS mapping with rapid scanning, and a helium glove-box sample environment.  Performance will improve when transferred to NSLS-II, a state-of-the-art new Synchrotron designed for high brightness applications.  These new capabilities are critical for advancing our knowledge of geochemical and biogeochemical processes, in particular those involving lighter elements, and will be openly available for use through the NSLS General User program.  Specific applications targeted include the mineral-water interface, nutrients and contaminants, carbonates, paleoclimate, redox processes, high-pressure mineralogy; and health effects of Earth materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1128957</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Reeder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard J Reeder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rjreeder@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316327932</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304673</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Schoonen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin A Schoonen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>martin.schoonen@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316328007</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emma</FirstName>
<LastName>Rasbury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emma T Rasbury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>troy.rasbury@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316321488</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000348193</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Northrup</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Northrup</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paul.northrup@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316329949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000558942</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117942100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~225620</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The purpose of this proposal was to develop a new Synchrotron user facility for microbeam X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) and quantitative X-ray fluorescence (XRF) imaging, at the National Synchrotron Light Source (NSLS) and NSLS-II. It included design, purchase of components, and construction of the microprobe endstation and controls; initial development, commissioning, and application at NSLS Beamline X15B, and subsequent transition to the new TES (Tender-Energy Spatially Resolved X-ray Absorption Spectroscopy) beamline at NSLS-II. This facility is optimized for the &ldquo;tender&rdquo; energy range of 1-5 keV, reaching up to 8 keV. Thus it uniquely covers the K absorption edges of critical elements Mg, Al, Si, P, S, Cl, and Ca, and can reach up to Co.&nbsp; It is designed to provide a stable, high-flux<br />microbeam focus, user-tunable from ~50 to ~1 microns, achieved using two-stage achromatic focusing. Existing beamline optics collimate, monochromate, and macro-focus the X-ray beam to ~1 mm at a secondary source aperture (SSA). Beam from the SSA is then re-focused by a pair of mirrors in KB geometry to the microbeam scale. Size of the microbeam is tunable, at the expense of flux, by adjusting the size of the SSA as a virtual source.&nbsp; Unique aspects of this microprobe are a) its energy range particularly in a non-vacuum (helium) environment, and b) its optimization for energy scanning including full XAS at microbeam spatial resolution.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; At NSLS Beamline X15B, we installed the microprobe endstation sample chamber, KB microfocusing optics, X-ray fluorescence detectors, optical microscope, and sample stage. The first focused microbeam was achieved, and we subsequently tested and commissioned the instrument and its control system, and developed and beta-tested basic data-acquisition software.&nbsp; This included fast on-the-fly scanning of both the sample stage and the monochromator. &nbsp;Initial measurements were made by the PI and Co-Is, on a variety of geologic materials.&nbsp; In addition, a number of General Users were accommodated with user beamtime.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; At NSLS-II, the developed instruments and components were moved to, modified to match, and integrated into, the NSLS-II TES beamline at port 8-BM, all in partnership with the NSLS-II Facility.&nbsp; The new TES Microprobe is now open for User access though the NSLS-II User Program.&nbsp; See the NSLS-II web page at <a href="redir.aspx?C=C2-OKzIAfstI6gGxp34Lina9S33XJIY2Xd9kucdNFCnOEh7mxtXTCA..&amp;URL=https%3a%2f%2fwww.bnl.gov%2fps%2fuserguide%2fproposals.php" target="_blank">https://www.bnl.gov/ps/userguide/proposals.php</a>&nbsp;for details.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;Northrup</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       The purpose of this proposal was to develop a new Synchrotron user facility for microbeam X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) and quantitative X-ray fluorescence (XRF) imaging, at the National Synchrotron Light Source (NSLS) and NSLS-II. It included design, purchase of components, and construction of the microprobe endstation and controls; initial development, commissioning, and application at NSLS Beamline X15B, and subsequent transition to the new TES (Tender-Energy Spatially Resolved X-ray Absorption Spectroscopy) beamline at NSLS-II. This facility is optimized for the "tender" energy range of 1-5 keV, reaching up to 8 keV. Thus it uniquely covers the K absorption edges of critical elements Mg, Al, Si, P, S, Cl, and Ca, and can reach up to Co.  It is designed to provide a stable, high-flux microbeam focus, user-tunable from ~50 to ~1 microns, achieved using two-stage achromatic focusing. Existing beamline optics collimate, monochromate, and macro-focus the X-ray beam to ~1 mm at a secondary source aperture (SSA). Beam from the SSA is then re-focused by a pair of mirrors in KB geometry to the microbeam scale. Size of the microbeam is tunable, at the expense of flux, by adjusting the size of the SSA as a virtual source.  Unique aspects of this microprobe are a) its energy range particularly in a non-vacuum (helium) environment, and b) its optimization for energy scanning including full XAS at microbeam spatial resolution.        At NSLS Beamline X15B, we installed the microprobe endstation sample chamber, KB microfocusing optics, X-ray fluorescence detectors, optical microscope, and sample stage. The first focused microbeam was achieved, and we subsequently tested and commissioned the instrument and its control system, and developed and beta-tested basic data-acquisition software.  This included fast on-the-fly scanning of both the sample stage and the monochromator.  Initial measurements were made by the PI and Co-Is, on a variety of geologic materials.  In addition, a number of General Users were accommodated with user beamtime.       At NSLS-II, the developed instruments and components were moved to, modified to match, and integrated into, the NSLS-II TES beamline at port 8-BM, all in partnership with the NSLS-II Facility.  The new TES Microprobe is now open for User access though the NSLS-II User Program.  See the NSLS-II web page at https://www.bnl.gov/ps/userguide/proposals.php for details.        Last Modified: 09/05/2016       Submitted by: Paul Northrup]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
