<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nanowire FET Sensors with Intrinsic Sensitivity Improvement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objectives&lt;br/&gt;As a contending point-of-care (POC) diagnostic platform component technology, semiconductor nanowire field-effect transistor (FET) sensors permit visual-label-free and real-time electronic detections of numerous biomolecules with high sensitivity and great specificity. The limit of detection (LOD) and quantification (LOQ), however, needs to be improved before their POC diagnostic platform deployment.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research exploits the fundamental scientific principles and engineering measures to maximize the intrinsic detection sensitivity. The project will hypothesize, develop, and thoroughly characterize a transformative amplifying nanowire FET sensor structure. The research goal is to improve the detection sensitivity, LOD, and LOQ by 1-2 orders over the conventional nanowire FET sensors. Although detection of biomolecules in liquid environment is aimed as the research driver, the same amplifying sensor structure can be readily adopted for numerous other applications. Finally, a dynamically tunable and highly sensitive sensor device technology and architecture can be envisaged for deployments in disease diagnostics and health monitoring, defense and homeland security, and pharmaceutical discovery.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research and education activities will help nurture and educate future engineers and scientists in the areas of nanoelectronics and biosensing. Research experiences for underrepresented, women, and international students with integrated diversity will be created in the project. The research results will be broadly disseminated to enhance scientific and technological understanding. The outreach activities to high school, industry, and general scientific community will stimulate awareness and interests in these sectors. Finally, these sectors will in turn contribute to the advancement of the field of nanoelectronic biosensing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1128673</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chi On</FirstName>
<LastName>Chui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chi On Chui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chui@ee.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102674786</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000073973</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951594</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>As a contending point-of-care (POC) diagnostic platform component technology, semiconductor nanowire field-effect transistor (FET) sensors permit visual-label-free and real-time electronic detections of numerous biomolecules with high sensitivity and great specificity. The limit of detection (LOD) and quantification (LOQ), however, needs to be improved before their POC diagnostic platform deployment. The project aims to hypothesize, develop, and thoroughly characterize a transformative amplifying nanowire FET (nwFET) sensor structure.</p> <p>The research team has proposed and demonstrated a transformative integrated electronic amplification concept that can boost the detection sensitivity and output current. The team has implemented such concept by cascading two nwFETs to form a T-shape integrated amplifying nwFET biosensors, with the bottom vertical and top horizontal nwFETs being the transducer and amplifier respectively. The team has fabricated the T-nwFET biosensor prototypes, which is deployable in future all-electronic point-of-care (PoC) systems, and characterized their sensitivity in key biomolecules detection. The team has demonstrated a ~1,000 times lower LLOD compared to the clinical standard, called the enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) in quantitating analytes in biologically relevant solutions such as serum.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The project&rsquo;s research and education activities have nurtures and educated future engineers and scientists in the areas of nanoelectronics and biosensing. Graduate student researchers have gained opportunities to learn fundamental FET biosensor physics, nanofabrication skill in the cleanroom, electronic device characterization, and biosensing analytical approaches. The results have been and continued to be disseminated in multidisciplinary conferences and workshops, published in archival journals, and others. The project PI and student researchers have also made open presentations of the research results at the department&rsquo;s Annual Research Review and the UCLA Engineering Tech Forum, which impacts a broad audience of science and engineering policymakers, industrial partners, and members of the education community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Chi On&nbsp;Chui</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1128673/1128673_10118356_1440976514242_T-nwFET--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1128673/1128673_10118356_1440976514242_T-nwFET--rgov-800width.jpg" title="T-nanowire Biosensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1128673/1128673_10118356_1440976514242_T-nwFET--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="T-nanowire Biosensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prototype of the novel amplifying T-nanowire field-effect transistor (FET) biosensors with 3 orders of magnitude lower limit of detection compared to the state of the art</div> <div class="imageCredit">UCLA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chi On&nbsp;Chui</div> <div class="imageTitle">T-nanowire Biosensor</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  As a contending point-of-care (POC) diagnostic platform component technology, semiconductor nanowire field-effect transistor (FET) sensors permit visual-label-free and real-time electronic detections of numerous biomolecules with high sensitivity and great specificity. The limit of detection (LOD) and quantification (LOQ), however, needs to be improved before their POC diagnostic platform deployment. The project aims to hypothesize, develop, and thoroughly characterize a transformative amplifying nanowire FET (nwFET) sensor structure.  The research team has proposed and demonstrated a transformative integrated electronic amplification concept that can boost the detection sensitivity and output current. The team has implemented such concept by cascading two nwFETs to form a T-shape integrated amplifying nwFET biosensors, with the bottom vertical and top horizontal nwFETs being the transducer and amplifier respectively. The team has fabricated the T-nwFET biosensor prototypes, which is deployable in future all-electronic point-of-care (PoC) systems, and characterized their sensitivity in key biomolecules detection. The team has demonstrated a ~1,000 times lower LLOD compared to the clinical standard, called the enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) in quantitating analytes in biologically relevant solutions such as serum.     Broader Impacts  The projectÆs research and education activities have nurtures and educated future engineers and scientists in the areas of nanoelectronics and biosensing. Graduate student researchers have gained opportunities to learn fundamental FET biosensor physics, nanofabrication skill in the cleanroom, electronic device characterization, and biosensing analytical approaches. The results have been and continued to be disseminated in multidisciplinary conferences and workshops, published in archival journals, and others. The project PI and student researchers have also made open presentations of the research results at the departmentÆs Annual Research Review and the UCLA Engineering Tech Forum, which impacts a broad audience of science and engineering policymakers, industrial partners, and members of the education community.       Last Modified: 08/30/2015       Submitted by: Chi On Chui]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
