<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Assessing the Effect of Contextual Exercises on Student Adoption of Expert CAD Modeling Techniques</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>113047.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>113047</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This engineering education research project seeks to understand how experts model engineered products and system in computer aided design (CAD).  By drawing from expertise from industry that both design and uses CAD tools, the project will investigate how to teach students CAD skills that can readily transfer between CAD platforms, thus helping create a more effective engineering workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project stems from the fact that computer aided design is a fundamental skill in many engineering disciplines, where students are expected to become CAD experts.  The project also engages students from a predominately minority institution in order to make sure the findings can be broadly applied across a wide spectrum of engineering programs.  This project overlaps with NSF's strategic goals of transforming the frontiers through preparation of an engineering workforce with new capabilities and expertise.  Additionally NSF's goal of innovating for society is enabled by supporting the development of innovative learning systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1129411</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaobo</FirstName>
<LastName>Peng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaobo Peng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xipeng@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362619959</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396107</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Prairie View A &amp; M University</Name>
<CityName>Prairie View</CityName>
<ZipCode>774460519</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9362611689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 519</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MS 1230]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRAIRIE VIEW A&amp;M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Prairie View A & M University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>774460667</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~113047</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Computer-aided design (CAD) tools are critical in the modern engineering workforce. This work has examined how to use the expertise of practicing engineers and exercises better aimed at teaching students how to model in CAD to improve CAD education. As part of this work, a survey that was designed to measure the adaptive nature of expertise was distributed to over 600 participants that ranged from college freshmen to practicing engineers. The sample population came from a major research university, a minority serving institution, and the technical personnel at three Fortune 500 companies. These survey responses served as a base line level of adaptive expertise.</p> <p>Practicing engineers at two of the participating companies were asked to model a component in a CAD program that they were not familiar with. They were interviewed before and after the modeling exercise. Their screens were also recorded as they modeled and the actual CAD models were analyzed to see how engineers created the necessary geometry. These video recordings were watched and the times used for particular activities were tabulated. The interview results were assessed for various attributes of adaptive expertise. These industry data were then compared to that of students that had been taking a course in CAD modeling. Figures 1 and 2 show the time usage differences and model attribute differences, respectively. The results from these activities were broadly in agreement with the data from existing expertise literature; namely, experts spend more time planning and use more complex solutions than novices. This is true even though the experts in this case had very little experience with the software that they were using. These results highlight the need to focus on skills that are more strategic in nature, those related to planning how to model something, as opposed to those that are related to the actual modeling process (which buttons to click).</p> <p>Another aspect of this work was an examination of the role of contextual or learner-centered exercises on CAD modeling performance. Typically, students are asked to model stylized components that do not resemble any actual products when learning to use CAD. As part of this project, some students were given the opportunity to bring in objects that they used in their daily lives to model during the class. The results of these students were compared to those of the students that modeled the typical stylized components. Examples of traditional stylized and contextual components are shown in Figures 3 and 4, respectively. While the introduction of contextual exercises did not improve student modeling performance as measured by a laboratory practical, those students that participated in contextual modeling exercises did display higher levels of adaptive expertise as evidenced by interview analysis results. These results show the benefits of allowing students to move away from stylized examples and towards more &ldquo;real&rdquo; components.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2015<br>      Modified by: Xiaobo&nbsp;Peng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1129411/1129411_10137082_1444061551384_Fig.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1129411/1129411_10137082_1444061551384_Fig.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. Time Usage Data"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1129411/1129411_10137082_1444061551384_Fig.1--rgov-66x4...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Computer-aided design (CAD) tools are critical in the modern engineering workforce. This work has examined how to use the expertise of practicing engineers and exercises better aimed at teaching students how to model in CAD to improve CAD education. As part of this work, a survey that was designed to measure the adaptive nature of expertise was distributed to over 600 participants that ranged from college freshmen to practicing engineers. The sample population came from a major research university, a minority serving institution, and the technical personnel at three Fortune 500 companies. These survey responses served as a base line level of adaptive expertise.  Practicing engineers at two of the participating companies were asked to model a component in a CAD program that they were not familiar with. They were interviewed before and after the modeling exercise. Their screens were also recorded as they modeled and the actual CAD models were analyzed to see how engineers created the necessary geometry. These video recordings were watched and the times used for particular activities were tabulated. The interview results were assessed for various attributes of adaptive expertise. These industry data were then compared to that of students that had been taking a course in CAD modeling. Figures 1 and 2 show the time usage differences and model attribute differences, respectively. The results from these activities were broadly in agreement with the data from existing expertise literature; namely, experts spend more time planning and use more complex solutions than novices. This is true even though the experts in this case had very little experience with the software that they were using. These results highlight the need to focus on skills that are more strategic in nature, those related to planning how to model something, as opposed to those that are related to the actual modeling process (which buttons to click).  Another aspect of this work was an examination of the role of contextual or learner-centered exercises on CAD modeling performance. Typically, students are asked to model stylized components that do not resemble any actual products when learning to use CAD. As part of this project, some students were given the opportunity to bring in objects that they used in their daily lives to model during the class. The results of these students were compared to those of the students that modeled the typical stylized components. Examples of traditional stylized and contextual components are shown in Figures 3 and 4, respectively. While the introduction of contextual exercises did not improve student modeling performance as measured by a laboratory practical, those students that participated in contextual modeling exercises did display higher levels of adaptive expertise as evidenced by interview analysis results. These results show the benefits of allowing students to move away from stylized examples and towards more "real" components.       Last Modified: 10/05/2015       Submitted by: Xiaobo Peng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
