<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Conference on Interdisciplinary Applied and Computational Mathematics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed International Conference on Interdisciplinary Applied and Computational Mathematics is a five-day conference to be held June 17-21, 2011 at Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China. This conference will bring together leading researchers in the world to discuss recent advances on Multiscale, Multiphysics, and Stochastic Modeling, Analysis and Computation of Direct, Inverse, and Imaging Problems and Applications. The conference focuses on three related topics. The first is the development of multi-scale, multiphysics modeling, analysis, and computation techniques that are critically important for the simulation and design of nano materials and fabrications. The second is the integration of inverse problem techniques with imaging analysis methods for important physical processes that arise in nondestructive testing, optical imaging, near-field microscopy, and nano/bio imaging.  The third is the uncertainty quantification of the large scale problems focusing on imaging and inverse problems in random media as well as numerical solutions of stochastic partial differential equations. There will be about three plenary speakers each day, giving 1-hour talks. While the plenary speakers are predominantly from a mathematical background, many of the local speakers will be form an experimental background. Also there will be three introductory talks which lay out the nature of the challenges in each area, and a forward looking session at the end of the conference. A poster session will be available to graduate students and postdocs for advertising their research results. The NSF fund will be used to support US-based scientists (mostly junior researchers) for attending the conference and exchanging new ideas in various application areas.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent innovative developments of the multi-scale, multi-physics modeling and computational methods, inverse problem methods, and imaging techniques are applicable to describe many other physical processes and will have impact on the modeling and computation of the models in computational biology, multi-scale modeling of materials science, nano technology, and imaging science. Advances in these fields will greatly contribute to the development nano technologies for solar energy harvesting, medical imaging and therapeutics. Many physical systems, devices and processes of importance to science and engineering are not very well understood and controlled due to uncertainty in physical models and their parameters, multi-scale material properties, the operating environment, or measurement. While numerical simulations offer a viable alternative for critical decision making, simulation uncertainties from physical, analytical, or numerical errors must be characterized and managed. General and efficient mathematical models and novel computational algorithms must be developed for modeling multi-scale, multi-physics processes with appropriate control of uncertainty. The understanding of the role of stochastic effects on the direct, inverse, and imaging problems will have broad impact on the advancement of these key areas of scientific study. By combining these areas into a focused conference, and interspersing theoretical, applied, and computational talks, we hope to promote a cross-fertilization between scientists with various disciplinary backgrounds. By outlining the potential impact that theoretical tools can have on the most salient issues of our day, the workshop will influence and invigorate the educational efforts at the institutions of the speakers and workshop participants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1129181</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Di</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Di Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richardl@math.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173538143</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~38000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="759" height="84"> <tbody> <tr> <td colspan="2" width="759"> <p><span style="color: #990066; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;"> <strong>International Conferences on Interdisciplinary Applied and     Computational Mathematics</strong></span></p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="588"> <p><strong> <span style="color: #990000; font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif; font-size: xx-small;"> </span></strong></p> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <p><strong><span style="color: #990000;"><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">1st conf., 17-21 June, 2011 </span></span></span></strong></p> <p><strong><span style="color: #990000;"><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">2nd conf., 19-22, June, 2013</span></span></span></strong><br /><span class="STYLE2"><strong><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif; font-size: xx-small;">&nbsp;</span></strong><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif; font-size: xx-small;"><strong>&nbsp;</strong></span></span><strong><span style="color: #990066;"><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;"><br /></span></span></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #990000;"><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">Sir Run Run Shaw Science Building<br />Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China</span></span></span></strong></p> </td> <td width="171"> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5" width="760"> <tbody> <tr> <td><!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-size: small;">http://www.math.zju.edu.cn/ICACM/ICIACM/</span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-size: small;">http://www.math.zju.edu.cn/ICACM/ICACM201306/index.htm<br /></span></p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> <div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: medium;">The international      conference will focus on mathematical and computational      challenges for Multiscale, Multiphysics, and Stochastic      Modeling, Analysis and Computation of Direct, Inverse, and      Imaging Problems and Applications. </span></p> </div> <div> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: medium;">The overall technical      emphasis consists of three components: </span></p> </div> <div> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: medium;">(1) multi-physics,      multi-scale modeling and computation; </span></p> </div> <div> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: medium;">(2) computational aspects      of inverse and imaging problems; </span></p> </div> <div> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: medium;">(3) uncertainty  quantification.      These are inter-related and will provide a basis for developing PDE  models, novel mathematics and computational methods, and      effective algorithms especially for systems in which      uncertainties are inherent in their models and/or numerical      solutions. </span></p> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <p><span style="font-size: small;">Detials: </span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">The international conference will focus on mathematical and computational challenges for Multiscale, Multiphysics, and Stochastic Modeling, Analysis and Computation of Direct, Inverse, and Imaging Problems and Applications. Novel computational methods and mathematical modeling tools will be presented to address fundament...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      International Conferences on Interdisciplinary Applied and     Computational Mathematics             1st conf., 17-21 June, 2011   2nd conf., 19-22, June, 2013    Sir Run Run Shaw Science Building Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China              http://www.math.zju.edu.cn/ICACM/ICIACM/ http://www.math.zju.edu.cn/ICACM/ICACM201306/index.htm           The international      conference will focus on mathematical and computational      challenges for Multiscale, Multiphysics, and Stochastic      Modeling, Analysis and Computation of Direct, Inverse, and      Imaging Problems and Applications.     The overall technical      emphasis consists of three components:     (1) multi-physics,      multi-scale modeling and computation;     (2) computational aspects      of inverse and imaging problems;     (3) uncertainty  quantification.      These are inter-related and will provide a basis for developing PDE  models, novel mathematics and computational methods, and      effective algorithms especially for systems in which      uncertainties are inherent in their models and/or numerical      solutions.    Detials:   The international conference will focus on mathematical and computational challenges for Multiscale, Multiphysics, and Stochastic Modeling, Analysis and Computation of Direct, Inverse, and Imaging Problems and Applications. Novel computational methods and mathematical modeling tools will be presented to address fundamental issues with impacts on critical scientific and industrial applications. Our overall technical emphasis consists of three components: (1) multi-physics, multi-scale modeling and computation; (2) computational aspects of inverse and imaging problems; and (3) uncertainty quantification. Even though each of the three components is fundamental and has its own novelty, they are inter-related and will provide a basis for developing PDE models, novel mathematics and computational methods, and effective algorithms especially for systems in which uncertainties are inherent in their models and/or numerical solutions.  Many physical systems, devices and processes of importance are not very well understood and controlled due to uncertainty in physical models and their parameters, multi-scale material properties, the operating environment, or measurement. While numerical simulations offer a viable alternative for critical decision making, simulation uncertainties from physical, analytical, or numerical errors must be characterized and managed. General and efficient mathematical models and novel computational algorithms must be developed for modeling multi-scale, multiphysics processes with appropriate control of uncertainty, as well as for large scale inverse and imaging problems that arise for examples in nondestructive evaluation and material characterization/design of multi-scale and random media.  Critical issues on multi-scale and multiphysics simulations as well as multi-scale stochastic inverse problems to the effective high-fidelity predictive tools will be discussed in the conference. The innovative developments of the multi-scale, multi-physics modeling and computational methods, inverse problem methods, and imaging techniques are applicable to describe many other physical processes and will have impact on the modeling and computation of the models in computational biology, multi-scale modeling of materials science, nano technology, and imaging science. These developments call for the involvement of mathematicians to resolve complex problems in modeling, analysis and computation. A major challenge is the development of mathematical theories and computational methods for bridging the different spatial and temporal scales and dealing with the stochastic nature of the systems. The purpose of this conference is to bring active researchers in the world refocus their current endeavors and stimulate progress in these directions. Particularly the conference will highlight applications to diverse cutting-edge scien...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
