<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Stable isotope tracers of the subsurface biosphere and its geochemical effects in oceanic ridge flank basement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>211999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>211999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Barbara Ransom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bransom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927792</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A vast subsurface biosphere exists beneath the seafloor, but there is little understanding of exactly how microbes affect chemical exchange between seawater and oceanic basement, or how this affects global geochemical budgets. Recent research shows that microbes have an active role in altering the volcanic rocks on the seafloor, and new isotope techniques have been developed that can tell the temperatures at which the alteration has taken place. This research uses the stable isotopes of sulfur and oxygen in altered seafloor mafic lavas sampled by NSF-funded Ocean Drilling Program to (1) trace the distribution of the subsurface biosphere in the oceanic basement, (2) understand how microbial processes affect chemical and isotope exchange between seawater and the crust, and (3) determine the influence of microbial processes on geochemical cycling in the oceans. This is the first study of its kind, and as such is potentially transformative in terms of its ability to inform us about life in the deep biosphere. Research will involve the sulfur contents and isotopes in rocks from cool fluid downwelling sites along the flanks of mid-ocean ridges. The oxygen isotope compositions of phosphate adsorbed to iron-oxyhydroxides from warm and cool sites will also be analyzed to examine the effects of in-situ biological activity and estimate the temperature at which microbial metabolic processes are occurring, giving an idea of the depth in the ocean crust to which life extends. The broader impacts of the work include support of an African American female researcher and the training of undergraduates and a postdoc in state-of-the-art stable isotope techniques. Minority high school students in the New Haven CT area will also be engaged in the laboratory research. In addition, public outreach associated with the project will be carried out by the Peabody Museum in New Haven and the University of Michigan Nano-Rocks summer high school camp. The work will incorporate research results into courses and support analytical facilities at both institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1129631</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Alt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey C Alt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jalt@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347648380</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000320461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1100 N. University]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6899</Code>
<Text>OCE-Ocean Sciences Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~211999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The purpose of this project is to use geochemical tracers to test for the effects of microbial activity in volcanic basement of the oceanic crust. Previous work has shown that sulfate reduction by microbes is an important process in basement buried by sediment and which remains at warm temperatures of 50-100?C. &nbsp;A major goal of the current work was to understand the role of microbial sulfate reduction in cold (near 0?C) volcanic basement, which makes up the vast majority of oceanic crust. &nbsp;Analyses of three cold ridge flank basement sections indicate that such basement can lose more sulfur through oxidation than in warm flank basement sections, but that cold flank basement can also retain or even gain more sulfur than warm flank basement. An interesting new outcome is that high seawater/rock ratios can lead to oxidation of rocks and loss of sulfur along flow pathways, as expected, but the high fluid fluxes that maintain cold temperatures in basement also supply more abundant sulfate, leading to fixation of greater amounts of sulfur as sulfide in the reducing host rocks, farther from the fluid flow pathways. Another new result is that microbial activity (sulfate reduction) is an important factor in controlling chemical exchange of other elements between seawater and basement, specifically thallium is incorporated into sulfide minerals, so uptake of thallium by the basement is controlled by microbial activity. This is significant because thallium in basalts has been used as a tracer of seawater to calculate global fluxes of heat and fluid in submarine hydrothermal systems. More generally, these results confirm previous and current results for sulfur that show that microbial activity can be quantitatively important in seawater-crustal chemical and isotopic exchange. Major controls on microbial sulfate reduction in volcanic oceanic basement include the abundance of fractures, the timing of fracturing, and lithology (pillowed basalts versus sheet flows). Results from the present study further our understanding of sulfur geochemistry and microbial sulfate reduction in oceanic basement, and support previous estimates of the global importance of input of microbially derived sulfur into altered oceanic basalt.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/25/2014<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;C&nbsp;Alt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             The purpose of this project is to use geochemical tracers to test for the effects of microbial activity in volcanic basement of the oceanic crust. Previous work has shown that sulfate reduction by microbes is an important process in basement buried by sediment and which remains at warm temperatures of 50-100?C.  A major goal of the current work was to understand the role of microbial sulfate reduction in cold (near 0?C) volcanic basement, which makes up the vast majority of oceanic crust.  Analyses of three cold ridge flank basement sections indicate that such basement can lose more sulfur through oxidation than in warm flank basement sections, but that cold flank basement can also retain or even gain more sulfur than warm flank basement. An interesting new outcome is that high seawater/rock ratios can lead to oxidation of rocks and loss of sulfur along flow pathways, as expected, but the high fluid fluxes that maintain cold temperatures in basement also supply more abundant sulfate, leading to fixation of greater amounts of sulfur as sulfide in the reducing host rocks, farther from the fluid flow pathways. Another new result is that microbial activity (sulfate reduction) is an important factor in controlling chemical exchange of other elements between seawater and basement, specifically thallium is incorporated into sulfide minerals, so uptake of thallium by the basement is controlled by microbial activity. This is significant because thallium in basalts has been used as a tracer of seawater to calculate global fluxes of heat and fluid in submarine hydrothermal systems. More generally, these results confirm previous and current results for sulfur that show that microbial activity can be quantitatively important in seawater-crustal chemical and isotopic exchange. Major controls on microbial sulfate reduction in volcanic oceanic basement include the abundance of fractures, the timing of fracturing, and lithology (pillowed basalts versus sheet flows). Results from the present study further our understanding of sulfur geochemistry and microbial sulfate reduction in oceanic basement, and support previous estimates of the global importance of input of microbially derived sulfur into altered oceanic basalt.       Last Modified: 11/25/2014       Submitted by: Jeffrey C Alt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
