<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Post-seismic response updip of the Chilean megathrust earthquake of February 27, 2010</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>312672.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>312672</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Among the hazards that arise from large earthquakes are the direct effects of great earthquakes, as evidenced by last year?s devastating earthquake off Japan, and local and distant effects of tsunamis. Though they pose enormous risks to life and property in highly populated areas, neither of these phenomena is as yet well understood. The recent great earthquake in Chile did not generate a large tsunami, probably because the rupture produce a surface break at the seafloor. Available evidence suggests that slip did not occur at depths shallower than about 30 km down-dip from the trench. Accordingly, the proponents of this project infer that the outer accretionary wedge that lies along the Chile coast above the rupture zone behaves as a poro-elastic medium that will adjust over time to the new stress regime caused by the earthquake. The aim of the proposal is to observe the effects of this transient adjustment, by deploying a focused array of ocean bottom seismographs equipped with flow meters. The principal broader impact of this effort is considerably improved understanding of megathrust earthquakes and tsunamis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1130013</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Trehu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne M Trehu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trehu@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417372655</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973315503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~312672</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The February 27, 2010, M8.8 earthquake offshore south central Chile was the 5<sup>th</sup> largest earthquake since seismologists have been able to assess earthquake magnitudes.&nbsp; It occurred on the segment of the Peru/Chile subduction zone north of the segment that ruptured in the great Chilean earthquake of 1960, which was the largest instrumentally recorded earthquake.&nbsp; One unusual aspect of this earthquake is that the ocean-crossing tsunami it generated was smaller than expected, although it did have devastating effects along the coast of Chile.&nbsp; Because of the frictional properties of sediments that form the outer accretionary wedge, slip during large subduction zone earthquakes may be arrested before the plate boundary fault reaches the surface at the trench.&nbsp; The primary objective of this project, informally known as ChilePEPPER for Project Exploring Prism Post-Earthquake Response, was to determine how the outer accretionary wedge was responding to the change in stress resulting from slip at greater depth on the fault. A better understanding of how the outer wedge responds to slip down-dip during earthquakes, and how the scientific community can &ldquo;read&rdquo; the earthquake history written in the geologic structure of the outer wedge, can inform earthquake and tsunami hazard evaluations for subduction zones around the globe.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We expected to observe seafloor uplift, &ldquo;slow&rdquo; earthquakes (i.e. earthquakes in which the slip is slower than usual but still fast enough to generate seismic waves), seismic tremor (narrow-band, emergent seismic signals that are distinct from the broadband, sharp signals generated by earthquake), and fluid expulsion through the seafloor as fluids in the pore space between sediment grains flowed in response to stress.&nbsp; To measure these phenomena, we installed 10 temporary seismometers provided by the US Ocean Bottom Seismometer Instrument Pool (OBSIP), funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF) and operated by the Incorporated Research Institutions for Seismology (IRIS).&nbsp; In addition to seismometers, the instruments were equipped with absolute pressure gauges and pore fluid meters. The instruments were deployed in May 2012 in a small array up-dip from the patch of greatest slip during the earthquake.&nbsp; The OBSs were recovered in March 2013.&nbsp; In 2012, we also acquired a grid of high-resolution seismic reflection lines to image subsurface structure of the accretionary wedge and swath bathymetric data, including a profile across the continental margin that was coincident with profiles acquired before the earthquake in 2008 and in 2011, to detect possible changes in the depth of the seafloor.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We were able to locate 575 local earthquakes that occurred within and near the seismic array, most of which were not located by land-based seismic networks, and we developed an empirical magnitude scale for comparison with the land-based network locations. Most of the seismicity was located near the boundary between the accreted wedge and the harder rock of continental crust that forms the backstop to the wedge, on the plate boundary, or in the subducting oceanic plate.&nbsp; Very few events were located within the wedge; nor did we detect any slow earthquakes, tremor or diffuse fluid flow in or out of the seafloor. &nbsp;Through careful statistical analysis of the spatially coincident swath bathymetry profile, we were also able to lower the detection threshold for bathymetric differencing and detected ~5 m of uplift of the seafloor between 2008 and 2012 which we attribute to uplift during the earthquake.&nbsp; Our data also provided new data for evaluating the interaction between sediment transport down steep canyons incised into the margin and transport along the base of the margin along the trench, which contributes to understanding the sedimentary architecture of trench deposits.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>From the seismicity and bathymetric change results, we conclude that the accretionary wedge beneath our array slipped along with the rest of the upper plate forearc during the 2010 earthquake.&nbsp; Slip-to-the-trench, however, was probably local or the tsunami would have been larger. Combined with our observations of abrupt changes in the folding and faulting structure of the outer accretionary wedge, we conclude that along-strike changes in how the outer wedge responds to earthquakes that originate at greater depth recur for multiple seismic cycles and that structures that can be imaged with seismic reflection data can inform models for anticipating deformation patterns in future earthquakes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Students and faculty from the US (4), China (1), and Chile (5) participated in the 2012 cruise; in 2013, one US and one Chilean student participated. Two US students and 2 Chilean students presented results from the survey at international conferences and in peer-reviewed publications.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;M&nbsp;Trehu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The February 27, 2010, M8.8 earthquake offshore south central Chile was the 5th largest earthquake since seismologists have been able to assess earthquake magnitudes.  It occurred on the segment of the Peru/Chile subduction zone north of the segment that ruptured in the great Chilean earthquake of 1960, which was the largest instrumentally recorded earthquake.  One unusual aspect of this earthquake is that the ocean-crossing tsunami it generated was smaller than expected, although it did have devastating effects along the coast of Chile.  Because of the frictional properties of sediments that form the outer accretionary wedge, slip during large subduction zone earthquakes may be arrested before the plate boundary fault reaches the surface at the trench.  The primary objective of this project, informally known as ChilePEPPER for Project Exploring Prism Post-Earthquake Response, was to determine how the outer accretionary wedge was responding to the change in stress resulting from slip at greater depth on the fault. A better understanding of how the outer wedge responds to slip down-dip during earthquakes, and how the scientific community can "read" the earthquake history written in the geologic structure of the outer wedge, can inform earthquake and tsunami hazard evaluations for subduction zones around the globe.                 We expected to observe seafloor uplift, "slow" earthquakes (i.e. earthquakes in which the slip is slower than usual but still fast enough to generate seismic waves), seismic tremor (narrow-band, emergent seismic signals that are distinct from the broadband, sharp signals generated by earthquake), and fluid expulsion through the seafloor as fluids in the pore space between sediment grains flowed in response to stress.  To measure these phenomena, we installed 10 temporary seismometers provided by the US Ocean Bottom Seismometer Instrument Pool (OBSIP), funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF) and operated by the Incorporated Research Institutions for Seismology (IRIS).  In addition to seismometers, the instruments were equipped with absolute pressure gauges and pore fluid meters. The instruments were deployed in May 2012 in a small array up-dip from the patch of greatest slip during the earthquake.  The OBSs were recovered in March 2013.  In 2012, we also acquired a grid of high-resolution seismic reflection lines to image subsurface structure of the accretionary wedge and swath bathymetric data, including a profile across the continental margin that was coincident with profiles acquired before the earthquake in 2008 and in 2011, to detect possible changes in the depth of the seafloor.     We were able to locate 575 local earthquakes that occurred within and near the seismic array, most of which were not located by land-based seismic networks, and we developed an empirical magnitude scale for comparison with the land-based network locations. Most of the seismicity was located near the boundary between the accreted wedge and the harder rock of continental crust that forms the backstop to the wedge, on the plate boundary, or in the subducting oceanic plate.  Very few events were located within the wedge; nor did we detect any slow earthquakes, tremor or diffuse fluid flow in or out of the seafloor.  Through careful statistical analysis of the spatially coincident swath bathymetry profile, we were also able to lower the detection threshold for bathymetric differencing and detected ~5 m of uplift of the seafloor between 2008 and 2012 which we attribute to uplift during the earthquake.  Our data also provided new data for evaluating the interaction between sediment transport down steep canyons incised into the margin and transport along the base of the margin along the trench, which contributes to understanding the sedimentary architecture of trench deposits.     From the seismicity and bathymetric change results, we conclude that the accretionary wedge beneath our array slipped along with the rest of the upper plate forearc during the 2010 earthquake.  Slip-to-the-trench, however, was probably local or the tsunami would have been larger. Combined with our observations of abrupt changes in the folding and faulting structure of the outer accretionary wedge, we conclude that along-strike changes in how the outer wedge responds to earthquakes that originate at greater depth recur for multiple seismic cycles and that structures that can be imaged with seismic reflection data can inform models for anticipating deformation patterns in future earthquakes.      Students and faculty from the US (4), China (1), and Chile (5) participated in the 2012 cruise; in 2013, one US and one Chilean student participated. Two US students and 2 Chilean students presented results from the survey at international conferences and in peer-reviewed publications.           Last Modified: 01/30/2017       Submitted by: Anne M Trehu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
