<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Understanding the Role of Picocyanobacteria in the Marine Silicate Cycle</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>259697.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>259697</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>INTELECTUAL MERIT: The investigators will follow-up on their discovery of significant accumulation of silicon by marine picocyanobacteria of the genus Synechococcus to assess the contribution of these organisms to the cycling of biogenic silica in the ocean. Oceanographers have long assumed that diatoms are the dominant marine organisms controlling the cycling of silica in the ocean. Recently, however, single-cell analyses of picocyanobacterial cells from field samples surprisingly revealed the presence of substantial amounts of silicon within Synechococcus. The contribution of Synechococcus to biogenic silica often rivaled that of living diatoms in the two systems examined. Moreover, size fractionation of biogenic silica indicates that up to 25% of biogenic silica can exist in the picoplanktonic size fraction. Given that picocyanobacteria dominate phytoplankton biomass and primary production over much of the world?s ocean, these findings raise significant questions about the factors controlling the marine silica cycle globally, as well as the proper interpretation of biogenic silica measurements, Si: N ratios in particulate matter, and ratios of silicate and nitrate depletion. It also suggests that picocyanobacterial populations may be subject to previously unknown constraints on their productivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will have both laboratory and field components. Because cellular Si varies substantially among the field-collected samples and laboratory strains so far analyzed, the laboratory component will document variability in Si uptake and cellular Si concentrations, while determining what role physiological and phylogenetic factors play in this variability.  The investigators will use strains of Synechococcus for which there are already genome sequences. Laboratory experiments will 1) use 32Si radiotracer uptake experiments to assess the degree of variability in Si content and Si uptake kinetics among strains of Synechococcus acclimated to different levels of silicate, 2) characterize the intracellular distribution and chemistry of silicon within cells using fractionation techniques, density centrifugation, electron microscopy and x-ray absorption spectroscopy, and 3) use bioinformatic analyses of published genomes to determine whether uptake of Si can be predicted based on phylogenetic relationships, to identify candidate genes involved in cyanobacterial Si metabolism, and to develop probes for community structure that can be related to cellular Si content. Field work at the Bermuda Atlantic Time Series (BATS) site will assess the contribution of Synechococcus and diatoms to total biogenic silica in surface waters at times of the year when the former are typically dominant. Field measurements will include size fractionation of biogenic silica biomass and Si uptake, and synchrotron-based x-ray fluorescence microscopy, and the phylogenetic composition of the Synechococcus assemblage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACTS: This project has the potential to drive a major paradigm shift in our understanding of the marine silicon cycle. In addition, one PhD student will be trained at Stony Brook. Each PI will provide research experience to a number of undergraduates working on original research projects for credit, as a part of an REU program or as the basis for undergraduate theses. Stony Brook research programs for undergraduates are supported with summer research money from the Undergraduate Research and Creative Activities (URECA) program, and draw on its very diverse student body. The investigators will also engage promising high school level students through several residential programs that the PIs have been a part of in the past. These include the BLOOM program at Bigelow and the Simons Summer Research Fellowship Program at Stony Brook. The PI has continuing relationship with a regional high school (Brentwood) with a high proportion of underrepresented minorities. PI Twining is involved in the Café Scientifique program at Bigelow. Baines will engage in similar outreach through the Center for Science and Mathematics Education (CESAME) sponsored Open Science Nights. Finally, PI Baines will cooperate with CESAMEs teacher education programs, with the aim of incorporating biological oceanography into K-12 curricula. PIs Krause and Brzezinski will incorporate aspects of phytoplankton ecology into UCSB's Oceans to Classroom Program that brings marine research at UCSB to life for over 18,000 K-12 students each year.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1131139</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Baines</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen B Baines</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbaines@ms.cc.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316321092</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000194320</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jackie</FirstName>
<LastName>Collier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jackie L Collier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jackie.collier@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316328696</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365903</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117945245</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Nicolls Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9117</Code>
<Text>MARINE BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~259697</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sequestration of atmospheric carbon in the ocean is intimately tied to the fate of silicon. This element is required for the growth diatoms, tiny single celled plants whose dense silica skeletons cause them to sink to deep waters, taking with them carbon and associated nutrients they accumulated near the surface. However, it has recently been shown that tiny photosynthetic bacteria, the picocyanobacteria, also accumulate silicon. Because these organisms are so tiny, they are less likely to sink. Nonetheless, material budgets suggest that a nontrivial amount of the carbon sinking to deep waters from the surface must be in the form of picocyanobacteria. &nbsp;The presence of Si inside these cells, if it increases the density of aggregates that include them, could be one reason for this apparent paradox.</p> <p>To determine the maximum potential contribution of the picocyanobacterium,&nbsp;<em>Synechococcus</em>, to the oceanic silicon cycle, we studied a region where they are among the major contributors to biomass and primary production. We measured inventories of Si in cyanobacteria and diatom cells, estimated from cell abundance and single cell measurements of cellular Si made using Synchrotron X-ray Fluorescence microscopy (SXRF). We found that picocyanobacteria and diatoms have very different impacts on the Si cycle. &nbsp;On average, about half of the biogenic Si in the picocyanobacterial size fraction is in living cells, whereas most of the Si in the diatom fraction is in non-living detritus. &nbsp;This suggests that Si is rapidly recycled back to the dissolved phase from picocyanobacteria, possibly by protozoan grazers, while the Si detritus produced by diatoms persists for much longer in the environment, allowing it to accumulate. &nbsp;As a consequence, the amount of biogenic Si in the bacterial size fraction is only 16% of total biogenic Si even though specific Si uptake rates in that fraction are similar to that in the diatom fraction. &nbsp;The amount of biogenic Si in the picocyanobacterial size fraction is also relatively constant across sites and times, possibly due to relatively constant productivity and control of populations by protozoan predators and viruses. &nbsp;The uptake of Si and biogenic Si for the diatom size fraction is much more variable by comparison.</p> <p>What is less clear is the mechanism and possible fitness value of Si uptake by the picocyanobacteria. &nbsp;Si uptake by <em>Synechococcus </em>varied with concentration of dissolved silicon in a complex manner, suggesting at least two mechanisms of uptake into or onto the cell. &nbsp;<span>We also observed substantial variability in Si uptake among six cultured strains of&nbsp;</span><em>Synechococcus</em><span>.&nbsp;<span>However, when we looked at the genomes for <em>Synechococcus </em>generally we found few genes that could clearly be described as Si-related, and no correlation between the presence of those genes and Si uptake by the strains. &nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-size: 12px;">There is also some indication from our experiments that Si might be leaking into the cell incidentally via a phosphate channel, as occurs in some land plants. However, once again, there is no apparent correlation between the presence of various types of phosphate uptake genes and Si uptake. &nbsp;In the field, picocyanobacterial community structure at the clade level was not correlated with rates of Si uptake rates or biogenic Si in the cyanobacterial fraction. &nbsp;The very wide variation in cellular Si even with a single culture suggests either substantial plasticity or polymorphism at the substrain level that would not be detected by these approaches.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;">This uncertainty extends to the form of silica within <em>Synechococcus </em>cells. Freeze fracturing cells caused much of the Si to become dissolved, suggesting that much of the Si is not in the form of solid mineral silica. &nbsp;We used x-ray absorbance near edge structure spectroscopy (XANES) to probe cyanobacterial strains grown under different levels of Si. &nbsp;The XANES spectra clearly indicate differences between the form of Si in <em>Synechococcus</em>&nbsp;and that in diatoms, with the former exhibiting more features associated with crystalline forms or discontinuities between different mineral forms of Si. &nbsp;A much more complete library of Si mineral forms is needed to more fully interpret these spectra. &nbsp;Resolving these issues in the future could affect whether picocyanobacteria are possibly useful models for studying biological silicification so as to improve efficiency of silicon chip production methods.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;">In addition to these findings, the funding will result in at least 9 publications, and there have been 8 presentations at major scientific meetings. &nbsp;Three graduate students, three undergrads and two post-docs were involved in the research at Stony Brook.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/26/2016<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;B&nbsp;Baines</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sequestration of atmospheric carbon in the ocean is intimately tied to the fate of silicon. This element is required for the growth diatoms, tiny single celled plants whose dense silica skeletons cause them to sink to deep waters, taking with them carbon and associated nutrients they accumulated near the surface. However, it has recently been shown that tiny photosynthetic bacteria, the picocyanobacteria, also accumulate silicon. Because these organisms are so tiny, they are less likely to sink. Nonetheless, material budgets suggest that a nontrivial amount of the carbon sinking to deep waters from the surface must be in the form of picocyanobacteria.  The presence of Si inside these cells, if it increases the density of aggregates that include them, could be one reason for this apparent paradox.  To determine the maximum potential contribution of the picocyanobacterium, Synechococcus, to the oceanic silicon cycle, we studied a region where they are among the major contributors to biomass and primary production. We measured inventories of Si in cyanobacteria and diatom cells, estimated from cell abundance and single cell measurements of cellular Si made using Synchrotron X-ray Fluorescence microscopy (SXRF). We found that picocyanobacteria and diatoms have very different impacts on the Si cycle.  On average, about half of the biogenic Si in the picocyanobacterial size fraction is in living cells, whereas most of the Si in the diatom fraction is in non-living detritus.  This suggests that Si is rapidly recycled back to the dissolved phase from picocyanobacteria, possibly by protozoan grazers, while the Si detritus produced by diatoms persists for much longer in the environment, allowing it to accumulate.  As a consequence, the amount of biogenic Si in the bacterial size fraction is only 16% of total biogenic Si even though specific Si uptake rates in that fraction are similar to that in the diatom fraction.  The amount of biogenic Si in the picocyanobacterial size fraction is also relatively constant across sites and times, possibly due to relatively constant productivity and control of populations by protozoan predators and viruses.  The uptake of Si and biogenic Si for the diatom size fraction is much more variable by comparison.  What is less clear is the mechanism and possible fitness value of Si uptake by the picocyanobacteria.  Si uptake by Synechococcus varied with concentration of dissolved silicon in a complex manner, suggesting at least two mechanisms of uptake into or onto the cell.  We also observed substantial variability in Si uptake among six cultured strains of Synechococcus. However, when we looked at the genomes for Synechococcus generally we found few genes that could clearly be described as Si-related, and no correlation between the presence of those genes and Si uptake by the strains.  There is also some indication from our experiments that Si might be leaking into the cell incidentally via a phosphate channel, as occurs in some land plants. However, once again, there is no apparent correlation between the presence of various types of phosphate uptake genes and Si uptake.  In the field, picocyanobacterial community structure at the clade level was not correlated with rates of Si uptake rates or biogenic Si in the cyanobacterial fraction.  The very wide variation in cellular Si even with a single culture suggests either substantial plasticity or polymorphism at the substrain level that would not be detected by these approaches.  This uncertainty extends to the form of silica within Synechococcus cells. Freeze fracturing cells caused much of the Si to become dissolved, suggesting that much of the Si is not in the form of solid mineral silica.  We used x-ray absorbance near edge structure spectroscopy (XANES) to probe cyanobacterial strains grown under different levels of Si.  The XANES spectra clearly indicate differences between the form of Si in Synechococcus and that in diatoms, with the former exhibiting more features associated with crystalline forms or discontinuities between different mineral forms of Si.  A much more complete library of Si mineral forms is needed to more fully interpret these spectra.  Resolving these issues in the future could affect whether picocyanobacteria are possibly useful models for studying biological silicification so as to improve efficiency of silicon chip production methods.  In addition to these findings, the funding will result in at least 9 publications, and there have been 8 presentations at major scientific meetings.  Three graduate students, three undergrads and two post-docs were involved in the research at Stony Brook.       Last Modified: 08/26/2016       Submitted by: Stephen B Baines]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
