<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  From Warnings to Evacuation in Hurricanes: a Holistic Investigation using an Interdisciplinary Approach</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>371378.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>371378</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin Dillon-Merrill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rdillonm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Hurricane evacuation is a complex process driven by human decision-making under uncertainty and governed by social, technical, spatial, and temporal constraints.  This project takes a holistic approach to modeling the process by integrating behavioral modeling of household decision making with methodologies based on emerging concepts in network science, stochastic modeling and agent based simulation. Data will be collected through scientific telephone surveys developed using qualitative methods and integrated into a temporal GIS framework including 2010 Census demographic data, spatial risk zones, and transportation route information. Communication and assimilation of evacuation warnings will be modeled using emerging complex network approaches including social contagion on random networks. The resulting impact of warning propagation on risk perception will be an input to household agent-based evacuation decision models that will incorporate social and temporal constraints. Evacuation trips thus generated (including timing, potential routes/destinations) will then be analyzed and evaluated using stochastic optimization models incorporating nontraditional objectives such as evacuation to safety and determine optimal routes, departure time, and safe destinations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The importance of this project is that it will integrate social science and engineering to model a process in which social and technical aspects cannot each be studied in isolation.  This interconnection is faced by forecasters and emergency managers as much as by researchers in multiple disciplines.  As such it should open new paths in cross-disciplinary research and teaching applied to problems that are both complex and of consequence to society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1131503</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Satish</FirstName>
<LastName>Ukkusuri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Satish Ukkusuri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sukkusur@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654942296</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~371378</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Hurricane Sandy produced a disastrous storm surge in coastal areas of New York and New Jersey with property damage of nearly $50 billion (the second-costliest since 1900) and 72 fatalities occurring in the mid-Atlantic and northeastern United States. Hurricane evacuation is a complex dynamic process that includes several interrelated steps to complete and this process is governed by important factors such as hurricane trajectory and warning system, household locations and types, individual characteristics and others. In this study, we developed various advances to understand how warning information can be communicated to the public based on real world data collection of social networks from Hurricane Sandy.&nbsp;</p> <p>This study explored the social network influence on evacuation behavior by using ego-centric social network data obtained from Hurricane Sandy and by taking into account the nested structure of the data i.e. friends or close contacts (alters) being nested within an individual (ego). In this regard, this study develops a multinomial multilevel model of evacuation decision outcome at the dyadic (ego-alter tie) level by using Hierarchical Generalized Linear Modeling (HGLM) technique to investigate the effects of relational or tie attributes in addition to individuals' own socio-demographic characteristics. Model estimation results suggest that factors that define a social tie (frequency of contact, discussion topic and geographic proximity) significantly influence the association of evacuation decision between an individual and his social partner. In addition, individuals' (both ego and alter) own socio-demographics such as age, marital status, previous evacuation experience, evacuation order from emergency officials, household's type, size, location and proximity to a water body also affect the decision to evacuate.</p> <p>At the individual-level evacuation decision making process during Hurricane Sandy is analyzed by using a random parameters logit-based modeling approach in order to explore the role of social and information networks in addition to individual and household characteristics. Random parameters capture heterogeneous individualized responses among the population that account for the limitations of traditional evacuation behavior models that have used a constant parameters assumption for variables influencing the decision to evacuate. In the survey, individuals' ego-centric social network information were obtained by using the Personal Network Research Design (PNRD) approach. Estimation results from the logit model suggest that the reliability of different types of information sources such as radio, television, social media and internet significantly influence the evacuation decision making. Social network parameters such as network size, homophily, heterogeneity, length of relationship, etc. also play a vital role in determining whether an individual finally decides to evacuate. Additional factors related to individual (age, marital status, evacuation order and experience) and household (location, size, type, proximity to water body) characteristics are also found to be important predictors consistent with previous findings. These findigs are significant to highlight how the results can be communicated effectively to various communities so that households can make effective decisions during evacuation orders.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Satish&nbsp;Ukkusuri</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Hurricane Sandy produced a disastrous storm surge in coastal areas of New York and New Jersey with property damage of nearly $50 billion (the second-costliest since 1900) and 72 fatalities occurring in the mid-Atlantic and northeastern United States. Hurricane evacuation is a complex dynamic process that includes several interrelated steps to complete and this process is governed by important factors such as hurricane trajectory and warning system, household locations and types, individual characteristics and others. In this study, we developed various advances to understand how warning information can be communicated to the public based on real world data collection of social networks from Hurricane Sandy.   This study explored the social network influence on evacuation behavior by using ego-centric social network data obtained from Hurricane Sandy and by taking into account the nested structure of the data i.e. friends or close contacts (alters) being nested within an individual (ego). In this regard, this study develops a multinomial multilevel model of evacuation decision outcome at the dyadic (ego-alter tie) level by using Hierarchical Generalized Linear Modeling (HGLM) technique to investigate the effects of relational or tie attributes in addition to individuals' own socio-demographic characteristics. Model estimation results suggest that factors that define a social tie (frequency of contact, discussion topic and geographic proximity) significantly influence the association of evacuation decision between an individual and his social partner. In addition, individuals' (both ego and alter) own socio-demographics such as age, marital status, previous evacuation experience, evacuation order from emergency officials, household's type, size, location and proximity to a water body also affect the decision to evacuate.  At the individual-level evacuation decision making process during Hurricane Sandy is analyzed by using a random parameters logit-based modeling approach in order to explore the role of social and information networks in addition to individual and household characteristics. Random parameters capture heterogeneous individualized responses among the population that account for the limitations of traditional evacuation behavior models that have used a constant parameters assumption for variables influencing the decision to evacuate. In the survey, individuals' ego-centric social network information were obtained by using the Personal Network Research Design (PNRD) approach. Estimation results from the logit model suggest that the reliability of different types of information sources such as radio, television, social media and internet significantly influence the evacuation decision making. Social network parameters such as network size, homophily, heterogeneity, length of relationship, etc. also play a vital role in determining whether an individual finally decides to evacuate. Additional factors related to individual (age, marital status, evacuation order and experience) and household (location, size, type, proximity to water body) characteristics are also found to be important predictors consistent with previous findings. These findigs are significant to highlight how the results can be communicated effectively to various communities so that households can make effective decisions during evacuation orders.          Last Modified: 12/21/2017       Submitted by: Satish Ukkusuri]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
