<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Accurate and Efficient Surrogate Modeling Applied to Computational Mechanics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>106123.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>106123</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Siegmund</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this EArly-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project is to apply High Dimensional Model Representation (HDMR) technique to construct highly accurate and efficient surrogate computational mechanics models. Advanced computational mechanics simulations typically deal with very large scale models that are extremely time consuming. HDMR technique uses systemic sampling procedure relating outputs of the original physical model to its inputs to produce highly accurate and computationally cheap equivalent models. These low order surrogate models are expected to dramatically reduce the cost of very large scale simulations while maintaining the accuracy of the original models. The proposed methodology is extendable to other fields of engineering besides computational mechanics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research has the potential to transform current state of modeling philosophy and simulation capability in computational mechanics, and enable very large scale simulations at a reasonable cost. Simulations hitherto intractable due to very high computational burden can be performed efficiently with the proposed methodology. Additionally, it will provide new avenues in the development of accurate yet efficient simulation methods. Educational objectives will focus on (1) training graduate as well as undergraduate students in the area of surrogate modeling, and (2) developing new course materials for the existing courses on computational mechanics. The research being at the confluence of diverse areas of science and engineering such as mechanics, statistics and computational methods, will provide rich educational and research experiences for undergraduate and graduate students in state-of-the-art computational modeling and simulation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1132364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Spandan</FirstName>
<LastName>Maiti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Spandan Maiti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>spm54@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873442</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311639</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/03/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Club]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1630</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~106123</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this Early-concept Grant for Exploratory Research  (EAGER) project was to apply High Dimensional Model Representation (HDMR)  technique to construct highly accurate and efficient surrogate  computational mechanics models. Advanced computational mechanics  simulations typically deal with very large scale models that are  extremely time consuming. HDMR technique is a systemic sampling  procedure relating outputs of the original physical model to its inputs  to produce highly accurate and computationally cheap equivalent models.  These low order surrogate models are expected to dramatically reduce the  cost of very large scale simulations while maintaining the accuracy of  the original models. A chief benefit of the developed methodology is that it treats the actual physical model as a black box, and thus is readily extendable to other  fields of engineering besides computational mechanics.    This research  has the potential to transform current state of modeling philosophy and  simulation capability in computational mechanics, and enable very large  scale simulations at a reasonable cost. Simulations hitherto intractable  due to very high computational burden can be performed efficiently with  the proposed methodology. Additionally, it will provide new avenues in  the development of accurate yet efficient simulation methods.  Educational objective of the project focused on (1) training one graduate in the general area of computational mechanics, and particularly the area of surrogate modeling, and (2)  developing simulation software for undergraduate education. This software was used to demonstrate to the students mechanical response of complex materials&nbsp; in real time. The research being at the confluence of diverse  areas of science and engineering such as mechanics, statistics and  computational methods,&nbsp; provided rich educational and research  experiences for undergraduate and graduate students in state-of-the-art  computational modeling and simulation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2013<br>      Modified by: Spandan&nbsp;Maiti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this Early-concept Grant for Exploratory Research  (EAGER) project was to apply High Dimensional Model Representation (HDMR)  technique to construct highly accurate and efficient surrogate  computational mechanics models. Advanced computational mechanics  simulations typically deal with very large scale models that are  extremely time consuming. HDMR technique is a systemic sampling  procedure relating outputs of the original physical model to its inputs  to produce highly accurate and computationally cheap equivalent models.  These low order surrogate models are expected to dramatically reduce the  cost of very large scale simulations while maintaining the accuracy of  the original models. A chief benefit of the developed methodology is that it treats the actual physical model as a black box, and thus is readily extendable to other  fields of engineering besides computational mechanics.    This research  has the potential to transform current state of modeling philosophy and  simulation capability in computational mechanics, and enable very large  scale simulations at a reasonable cost. Simulations hitherto intractable  due to very high computational burden can be performed efficiently with  the proposed methodology. Additionally, it will provide new avenues in  the development of accurate yet efficient simulation methods.  Educational objective of the project focused on (1) training one graduate in the general area of computational mechanics, and particularly the area of surrogate modeling, and (2)  developing simulation software for undergraduate education. This software was used to demonstrate to the students mechanical response of complex materials  in real time. The research being at the confluence of diverse  areas of science and engineering such as mechanics, statistics and  computational methods,  provided rich educational and research  experiences for undergraduate and graduate students in state-of-the-art  computational modeling and simulation.       Last Modified: 10/31/2013       Submitted by: Spandan Maiti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
