<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Understanding and Optimizing A Supercritical Fluid Process for Recycling of Printed Circuit Boards</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>119941.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>119941</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927066</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1133770 (Dai). Widespread use of electronic equipment and shortening of product life cycles have created the challenging task of dealing with the ever-increasing quantity of obsolete electronic equipment. The huge amount of electronic waste (E-waste) generated each year and the lack of established methodologies capable of handling the increasing volumes of E-waste pose a severe environmental threat. Among the challenges to successful electronic equipment recycling, printed circuit board (PCB, primary components in every type of electronic product) recycling is recognized as one of the most difficult problems because of the complex construction and complicated materials composition of PCBs. The current PCB recycling industry uses traditional metallurgical technologies in which the fiber reinforced polymer matrix materials are incinerated. Although great effort has been made in the traditional metallurgical technologies for increasing the recycling efficiency for the end-of-life electronic products, the PCB recycling industry still faces the problems of poor environmental performance and limited economic returns.  Recently, under an EAGER grant, the PIs of this award demonstrated proof-of-concept preliminary work for developing a novel supercritical fluid (SCF) CO2-based PCB recycling process at relatively low/medium temperatures and pressures. The exploratory experiments demonstrated that PCBs are delaminated with metals and glass fiber maintain their original form, making it possible to increase recovery rates not only for precious metals but also for non-metal materials. Such a process opens a new dimension for recycling of PCB and provides the possibility of satisfying economical and environmental demands. In the current project, the research team will systematically investigate the delamination mechanism of the bonding materials in PCBs under supercritical fluid processes and seek to understand structure/process relationships. Although literature documents the application of supercritical fluids in polymer synthesis and processing, there is limited existing work on revealing the performance of polymeric materials in supercritical fluids. In addition, the research team will optimize the SCF process by implementing process conditions based on the mechanism study and systematically evaluate process performance. Finally, the team will model and validate the recycling process for scale-up in terms of cost, energy, and environmental impact.   The team will collaborate with industrial collaborators to promote transferring fundamental research to practical application. In addition, research and education will be integrated throughout the entire project duration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1133770</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lenore</FirstName>
<LastName>Dai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lenore Dai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lenore.dai@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809654112</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8020</Code>
<Text>Green Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~58899</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~61042</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Widespread use of electronic equipments and shortening of product life cycles have created the challenging task of dealing with the ever-increasing quantity of obsolete electronic equipments. The huge amount of electronic wastes (E-wastes) generated each year and the lack of established methodologies capable of handling the increasing volumes of the E-wastes pose a severe environmental threat. Among the challenges to successful electronic equipment recycling, printed circuit board (PCB, primary components in every type of electronic product) recycling is recognized as one of the most difficult problems because of their complex construction and complicated materials composition.&nbsp;The current PCB recycling industry usestraditional metallurgical technologies in which the fiber reinforced polymer matrix materials areincinerated. Although great effort has been made in the traditional metallurgical technologies forincreasing the recycling efficiency for the end-of-life electronic products, the PCB recyclingindustry still faces the problems of poor environmental performance and limited economicreturns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Recently, we have demonstrated the proof-of-concept preliminary work of developing a novel supercritical fluid (SCF) carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) based PCB recycling process at low/medium temperatures and pressures. This project has provided a systematic fundamental study of structure/property/process condition of the supercritical fluid process. &nbsp;The research shows that a small amount of water or sodium carbonate optimize the recycling process. A better fundamental understanding has been developed on the supercritical fluid process to recycle PCBs, which leads process optimization. The fundamental knowledge on structure/property/process relationships also contributes to polymer degradation and aging in general under a supercritical fluid condition.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The research has resulted in one refereed journal publication and several conference/symposium presentations. &nbsp;Two PhD students and one undergraduate at Arizona State University are trained and partially supported by this grant. &nbsp;One of the PhD students defended her thesis and is currently working at Intel.&nbsp; The other PhD student is scheduled to defend on June 19, 2015. The undergraduate student received a NSF Graduate Fellowship and is currently pursing her PhD in Chemical Engineering at the University of Illinois.&nbsp; The project has also been presented to the freshmen courses and various outreach actives such as see@asu, SEMTE Open House and Engineering Open House.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/08/2015<br>      Modified by: Lenore&nbsp;Dai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Widespread use of electronic equipments and shortening of product life cycles have created the challenging task of dealing with the ever-increasing quantity of obsolete electronic equipments. The huge amount of electronic wastes (E-wastes) generated each year and the lack of established methodologies capable of handling the increasing volumes of the E-wastes pose a severe environmental threat. Among the challenges to successful electronic equipment recycling, printed circuit board (PCB, primary components in every type of electronic product) recycling is recognized as one of the most difficult problems because of their complex construction and complicated materials composition. The current PCB recycling industry usestraditional metallurgical technologies in which the fiber reinforced polymer matrix materials areincinerated. Although great effort has been made in the traditional metallurgical technologies forincreasing the recycling efficiency for the end-of-life electronic products, the PCB recyclingindustry still faces the problems of poor environmental performance and limited economicreturns.     Recently, we have demonstrated the proof-of-concept preliminary work of developing a novel supercritical fluid (SCF) carbon dioxide (CO2) based PCB recycling process at low/medium temperatures and pressures. This project has provided a systematic fundamental study of structure/property/process condition of the supercritical fluid process.  The research shows that a small amount of water or sodium carbonate optimize the recycling process. A better fundamental understanding has been developed on the supercritical fluid process to recycle PCBs, which leads process optimization. The fundamental knowledge on structure/property/process relationships also contributes to polymer degradation and aging in general under a supercritical fluid condition.      The research has resulted in one refereed journal publication and several conference/symposium presentations.  Two PhD students and one undergraduate at Arizona State University are trained and partially supported by this grant.  One of the PhD students defended her thesis and is currently working at Intel.  The other PhD student is scheduled to defend on June 19, 2015. The undergraduate student received a NSF Graduate Fellowship and is currently pursing her PhD in Chemical Engineering at the University of Illinois.  The project has also been presented to the freshmen courses and various outreach actives such as see@asu, SEMTE Open House and Engineering Open House.          Last Modified: 06/08/2015       Submitted by: Lenore Dai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
