<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC for Next Generation Photovoltaics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>305000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1196827</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dmitri Perkins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dperkins@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>I/UCRC for Next Generation Photovoltaics &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1134849 University of Texas at Austin (UT-A); Brian Korgel &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Texas, Austin (UT-A) will become a new site in the existing Industry/ University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) for Next Generation Photovoltaics. The I/UCRC for Next Generation Photovoltaics began officially on March 1, 2010, with Colorado State University (CSU) as the only site (and the lead) in the Center. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center for Next Generation Photovoltaics focuses on the creation of innovative new strategies to low-cost photovoltaic devices by developing novel precursors, materials, and formulations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The biggest long-term challenge facing the photovoltaics (PVs) industry is the development of a low-cost, scalable and reliable manufacturing approach to produce solar cells that are cost competitive with fossil fuels. This requires new PVs with efficiencies higher than 20% that are suitable for use for 20 years in the field and can be manufactured at very low cost. This I/UCRC site will target the development of multijunction thin film PVs that are very cheap to make but can achieve very high efficiencies. New materials, precursors, formulations and processes will be developed. This research is at the frontier of materials science and engineering, chemistry, chemical engineering, physics and electrical engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A solution to decrease PV costs significantly would lead to widespread adoption of solar cell technology and a decrease in the world's reliance on non-renewable energy resources. The research problem is also an excellent training arena for future scientists and engineers, as it is highly interdisciplinary and provides a training environment for students. The I/UCRC efforts will also be interfaced with educational programs at CSU and UT-A focused on green technology. The industrial partnerships in the I/UCRC are also vital to the success of the program, and have the potential to catalyze significant economic growth. The proposed site will have a team of faculty and students that is diverse in gender, race and ethnicity and will always strive to increase the diversity of participants in the program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1134849</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Korgel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian A Korgel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>korgel@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124715633</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448003</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787137726</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N211</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N212</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N644</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O122</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O181</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>170E</Code>
<Text>Interagency Agreements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8036</Code>
<Text>Advanced Electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8041</Code>
<Text>Fabrications and Processing Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8808</Code>
<Text>Veterans Research Supplements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~61000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~140050</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~355498</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~444548</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~195731</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During Phase I, the Next Generation Photovoltaics I/UCRC has consisted of two research sites at The University of Texas at Austin (UT Austin) and Colorado State University (CSU). Through this partnership--working in close collaboration with industry--new strategies have been developed to lower the cost of power generated by solar cells. For instance, key technologies have been created within the I/UCRC research program and translated into industry for commercial use by PV module producers, including world-class device efficiencies, plasma processing systems for large area substrates, electroluminescence testing tools that have been placed on PV manufacturing lines, computational simulation methods for complex manufacturing hardware, an algorithm that utilizes advanced process control for optimized production scheduling, and new nanocrystal ink chemistry utilized in industry for high-throughput roll-to-roll PV device manufacturing. Even during extremely volatile times for the PV industry, the I/UCRC has seen significant growth. The Center engaged 9 faculty from the two institutions in the research program, and helped train 40 students at all levels, including (18) BS, (3) MS, (15) PhD, and (4) post-doctoral, in the field of PV research. Since 2012, the Center has generated 10 invention disclosures for its members, resulting in four patent applications (1 issued) and two license agreements. The I/UCRC for Next Generation Photovoltaics has also enabled the formation of three startup companies, one of which was founded by a PhD student trained in the I/UCRC. Going forward, our Center will continue to focus on the research and development needs of the PV industry, which have been evolving rapidly to include not only PV device materials, manufacturing and design, but also a variety of "soft cost" issues such as balance of systems, device maintenance and operation, deployment, policy and education. To help address these emerging areas, new research sites at Texas A&amp;M University (TAMU) and the Colorado School of Mines are being created.</p> <p>The research program during the Phase I of the Center has led to a variety of important scientific and technical breakthroughs, many of which have been adopted by the PV industry. Going forward, the Center iscontinuing to expand its holistic research agenda to address all aspectsof the PV industry, including balance of systems (BOS), maintenance &amp; operation (M&amp;O), deployment strategies, policy and education. The organizational structure of the I/UCRC enables an ideal proving ground for cutting edge research of interest to the multifaceted PV industry. The I/UCRC will continue to enable key discoveries in the area of PV research and more broadly, global energy sustainability and security.</p> <p>The Center provides a unique educational opportunity for students, young scholars and faculty researchers, by encouraging interaction and communication across disciplines and between academic researchers and industry partners. The industrial partnerships within the I/UCRC can also catalyze economic growth and development. The Center is furthermore dedicated to creating a diverse and highly trained workforce for the coming years of the PV industry, creating the next generation of industry leaders and pioneers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;A&nbsp;Korgel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During Phase I, the Next Generation Photovoltaics I/UCRC has consisted of two research sites at The University of Texas at Austin (UT Austin) and Colorado State University (CSU). Through this partnership--working in close collaboration with industry--new strategies have been developed to lower the cost of power generated by solar cells. For instance, key technologies have been created within the I/UCRC research program and translated into industry for commercial use by PV module producers, including world-class device efficiencies, plasma processing systems for large area substrates, electroluminescence testing tools that have been placed on PV manufacturing lines, computational simulation methods for complex manufacturing hardware, an algorithm that utilizes advanced process control for optimized production scheduling, and new nanocrystal ink chemistry utilized in industry for high-throughput roll-to-roll PV device manufacturing. Even during extremely volatile times for the PV industry, the I/UCRC has seen significant growth. The Center engaged 9 faculty from the two institutions in the research program, and helped train 40 students at all levels, including (18) BS, (3) MS, (15) PhD, and (4) post-doctoral, in the field of PV research. Since 2012, the Center has generated 10 invention disclosures for its members, resulting in four patent applications (1 issued) and two license agreements. The I/UCRC for Next Generation Photovoltaics has also enabled the formation of three startup companies, one of which was founded by a PhD student trained in the I/UCRC. Going forward, our Center will continue to focus on the research and development needs of the PV industry, which have been evolving rapidly to include not only PV device materials, manufacturing and design, but also a variety of "soft cost" issues such as balance of systems, device maintenance and operation, deployment, policy and education. To help address these emerging areas, new research sites at Texas A&amp;M University (TAMU) and the Colorado School of Mines are being created.  The research program during the Phase I of the Center has led to a variety of important scientific and technical breakthroughs, many of which have been adopted by the PV industry. Going forward, the Center iscontinuing to expand its holistic research agenda to address all aspectsof the PV industry, including balance of systems (BOS), maintenance &amp; operation (M&amp;O), deployment strategies, policy and education. The organizational structure of the I/UCRC enables an ideal proving ground for cutting edge research of interest to the multifaceted PV industry. The I/UCRC will continue to enable key discoveries in the area of PV research and more broadly, global energy sustainability and security.  The Center provides a unique educational opportunity for students, young scholars and faculty researchers, by encouraging interaction and communication across disciplines and between academic researchers and industry partners. The industrial partnerships within the I/UCRC can also catalyze economic growth and development. The Center is furthermore dedicated to creating a diverse and highly trained workforce for the coming years of the PV industry, creating the next generation of industry leaders and pioneers.       Last Modified: 07/15/2016       Submitted by: Brian A Korgel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
