<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Modeling Effective Research Ethics Education in Graduate International Collaborations:  A Learning Outcomes Approach</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397985.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdudka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Council of Graduate Schools (CGS) proposes a collaborative, three-year education project to coordinate, develop, and evaluate research ethics education programs that respond to research integrity issues that arise in international collaborations in science and engineering (S&amp;E). The project addresses two specific national needs: the preparation of S&amp;E researchers at U.S. institutions to face the ethical challenges of international research collaborations, and the need for effective methods of assessing and improving the preparation of U.S. graduate students to conduct collaborative research in an international context. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Council of Graduate Schools will address these needs through the following activities: (1) convene an international, interdisciplinary team of experts in research ethics education, S&amp;E collaboration, and learning assessment together with graduate education leaders to identify core research ethics skills needed in graduate international collaborations; (2) publish a framework paper and a preliminary learning outcomes rubric for graduate international collaborations; (3) develop and issue a request for proposals for pilot projects that develop and assess research ethics education programs in existing international collaborations; (4) convene an external selection committee to nominate five institutions to receive awards of $24,000 each to develop pilot projects in the development of coordinated research ethics curricula; (5) begin to assess curricular and institutional innovations in this area and develop an infrastructure for ongoing common assessment of their impact over time through a multi-tiered assessment strategy; (6) develop CGS electronic resources to feature project outcomes from the five pilot projects, including a Learning Outcomes Repository; (7) synthesize project results in CGS hardcopy and electronic publications that will reach nearly every U.S. university in S&amp;E graduate education; and (8) further disseminate best practices and findings through technical workshops and sessions at national and international meetings on research ethics and/or international collaboration.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1135345</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Sowell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert S Sowell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rsowell@cgs.nche.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022233791</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000354894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Denecke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Denecke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ddenecke@cgs.nche.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022233791</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380131</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Kent</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia D Kent</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkent@cgs.nche.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2024613874</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599867</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Council of Graduate Schools</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200361146</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2022233791</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 Dupont Circle NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 230]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094100393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COUNCIL OF GRADUATE SCHOOLS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Council of Graduate Schools]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200361173</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Dupont Circle NW Suite 230]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7491</Code>
<Text>ETHICS EDU FOR SCI &amp; ENG PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7491</Code>
<Text>ETHICS EDU FOR SCI &amp; ENG PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~397985</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through the Modeling Effective Research Ethics Education in Graduate International Collaborations project, the Council of Graduate Schools (CGS) successfully: (1) convened an international, interdisciplinary advisory committee of researchers, experts, and university leaders in international research collaborations to identify and define specific curricular content areas, activities, and unmet needs in STEM graduate education, (2) created a rubric for use in the creation of graduate student learning outcomes intended to inform graduate education programming and resources, (3) authored a framework paper that outlined specific gaps in current graduate research ethics curricula for preparing students to succeed as future faculty and as researchers working in international research networks and the global research enterprise, (4) analyzed information, collected through CGS-created assessment tools, about (a) existing institutional and disciplined based resources and activities, and (b) graduate student awareness of and participation in resources and activities, and (5) created an online repository to resources and activities developed by CGS and collected from the four participating institutions (Emory University, Northern Arizona University, the University of Oklahoma, and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Participating institutions used the CGS-developed <strong>learning outcomes</strong> rubric as prompts in the creation of graduate student learning outcomes for each of three broad content areas (cultural context, research practices, and ethical frameworks) and to address different aspects of learning (e.g., knowledge, skills, and attitudes) identified with input from the project advisory committee. These outcomes were identified and communicated in a way so as to have general applicability across STEM disciplines while at the same time prompting the development of new research ethics educational opportunities where gaps currently exist. These outcomes and the project results generally, will enable current and future graduate students to receive earlier and more comprehensive training on the issues specific to international collaborations.&nbsp; The emphasis on research ethics training was expanded in existing orientation activities, program requirements, and research ethics requirements at participating universities to include international collaboration issues and was used as a foundation in the creation of case studies, new resources, and activities. The involvement of faculty in the development, refinement, and use of learning outcomes provided them with an opportunity to both increase their engagement with the issues and improve the way in which they mentor and train students for international research and collaborations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>All institutions reported the prior existence of general research ethics education programming, resources, and activities.&nbsp; However through two CGS-developed surveys, this grant project enabled these institutions to identify gaps in the provision of research ethics education specific to international collaborations through the completion of an <strong>inventory of their existing resources</strong> and collection <strong>information about their students&rsquo; use and awareness of those resources</strong>. Participating institutions yielded usable responses from 3,860 graduate students.&nbsp; The majority of those students (63%) were enrolled in a STEM major, and of those in STEM, nearly half reported being in the Engineering (33%) and Biological and Agricultural Sciences (18%) fields. Using these data for formative purposes and programmatic improvement, participating institutions created new resources, training materials, and websites to connect both faculty and students with the information needed to address resource gaps and increase awareness.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At the conc...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through the Modeling Effective Research Ethics Education in Graduate International Collaborations project, the Council of Graduate Schools (CGS) successfully: (1) convened an international, interdisciplinary advisory committee of researchers, experts, and university leaders in international research collaborations to identify and define specific curricular content areas, activities, and unmet needs in STEM graduate education, (2) created a rubric for use in the creation of graduate student learning outcomes intended to inform graduate education programming and resources, (3) authored a framework paper that outlined specific gaps in current graduate research ethics curricula for preparing students to succeed as future faculty and as researchers working in international research networks and the global research enterprise, (4) analyzed information, collected through CGS-created assessment tools, about (a) existing institutional and disciplined based resources and activities, and (b) graduate student awareness of and participation in resources and activities, and (5) created an online repository to resources and activities developed by CGS and collected from the four participating institutions (Emory University, Northern Arizona University, the University of Oklahoma, and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University).     Participating institutions used the CGS-developed learning outcomes rubric as prompts in the creation of graduate student learning outcomes for each of three broad content areas (cultural context, research practices, and ethical frameworks) and to address different aspects of learning (e.g., knowledge, skills, and attitudes) identified with input from the project advisory committee. These outcomes were identified and communicated in a way so as to have general applicability across STEM disciplines while at the same time prompting the development of new research ethics educational opportunities where gaps currently exist. These outcomes and the project results generally, will enable current and future graduate students to receive earlier and more comprehensive training on the issues specific to international collaborations.  The emphasis on research ethics training was expanded in existing orientation activities, program requirements, and research ethics requirements at participating universities to include international collaboration issues and was used as a foundation in the creation of case studies, new resources, and activities. The involvement of faculty in the development, refinement, and use of learning outcomes provided them with an opportunity to both increase their engagement with the issues and improve the way in which they mentor and train students for international research and collaborations.     All institutions reported the prior existence of general research ethics education programming, resources, and activities.  However through two CGS-developed surveys, this grant project enabled these institutions to identify gaps in the provision of research ethics education specific to international collaborations through the completion of an inventory of their existing resources and collection information about their studentsÆ use and awareness of those resources. Participating institutions yielded usable responses from 3,860 graduate students.  The majority of those students (63%) were enrolled in a STEM major, and of those in STEM, nearly half reported being in the Engineering (33%) and Biological and Agricultural Sciences (18%) fields. Using these data for formative purposes and programmatic improvement, participating institutions created new resources, training materials, and websites to connect both faculty and students with the information needed to address resource gaps and increase awareness.     At the conclusion of the project, CGS created an online repository with project-related resources for both public and student use. This resource will continue to be actively disseminate to CGS mem...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
