<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Oklahoma PDE and Applied Math Workshops</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>28266.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>28266</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative award provides support for participants in two applied mathematics meetings at Oklahoma State University and the University of Oklahoma during the 2011-2012 and 2012-2013 academic years, respectively:&lt;br/&gt;(1) a workshop on recent progress in partial differential equations of fluid mechanics, with emphasis on modeling of geophysical fluids, to be held at Oklahoma State University on November 12-13, 2011;&lt;br/&gt;(2) a workshop on applied mathematics, to be held at the University of Oklahoma in October, 2012.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each meeting features invited lectures by leading researchers on topics of current research interest in applied partial differential equations and applied mathematics in general. The events bring together scholars currently making important contributions, early career mathematicians, and students working in the field. The conference encourages and financially supports participation by students, recent Ph.D. recipients, and members of groups underrepresented in mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conference web site: http://www.math.okstate.edu/ok_pde_workshop</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1135402</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jiahong</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jiahong Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jiahong@math.okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4057445788</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297974</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>740780001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[401 Math Science]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~28266</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The award for the project "Collaborative Research: Oklahoma PDE and Applied Math Workshops" supported the travels of participants to attend "The Third Oklahoma Partial Differential Equations Workshop" held at Oklahoma State University, November 12-13 (Saturday-Sunday), 2011.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Partial differential equations (PDEs) are fundamental tools in understanding many fluid phenomena ranging from small scale blood flows to large-scale geophysical flows and have played pivotal roles in many practical applications involving fluid flows. In the last few years, these PDEs have gained renewed interests and significant progress has been made. One goal of this conference has been to broadly disseminate these recent advances in a timely fashion.</p> <p><br />This workshop brought together leading experts and researchers on the focused PDEs from several countries. In addition, more than twenty-five young mathematicians (graduate students and recent Ph.D's) from Oklahoma and surrounding states participated in this workshop with ten of them given the opportunities to present their research. It is worth mentioning that a very high proportion of this workshop participants are from under-represented groups.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />During this two-day workshop, senior experts as well as junior researchers presented their state-of-the-art research and involved in active direct communications and discussions. Extensive collaborations have been initiated and these combined efforts are certain to generate new ideas and strategies, which may lead to the resolution of several outstanding open problems on the focused PDES.</p> <p><br />This conference also provided an excellent opportunity for training and mentoring students and recent Ph.D.'s. Twenty-five junior mathematicians &nbsp;attended this conference with many of them given the opportunities to present their researches. They communicated extensively with the leading experts of their fields and built social and collaborative networks with other participants.&nbsp;<span>&nbsp;The connections and bonds will benefit them throughout the rest of their careers.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><br />This conference was reported in Oklahoma State University Communications.This helps to raise the public awareness of mathematics and promote mathematical research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2014<br>      Modified by: Jiahong&nbsp;Wu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The award for the project "Collaborative Research: Oklahoma PDE and Applied Math Workshops" supported the travels of participants to attend "The Third Oklahoma Partial Differential Equations Workshop" held at Oklahoma State University, November 12-13 (Saturday-Sunday), 2011.    Partial differential equations (PDEs) are fundamental tools in understanding many fluid phenomena ranging from small scale blood flows to large-scale geophysical flows and have played pivotal roles in many practical applications involving fluid flows. In the last few years, these PDEs have gained renewed interests and significant progress has been made. One goal of this conference has been to broadly disseminate these recent advances in a timely fashion.   This workshop brought together leading experts and researchers on the focused PDEs from several countries. In addition, more than twenty-five young mathematicians (graduate students and recent Ph.D's) from Oklahoma and surrounding states participated in this workshop with ten of them given the opportunities to present their research. It is worth mentioning that a very high proportion of this workshop participants are from under-represented groups.    During this two-day workshop, senior experts as well as junior researchers presented their state-of-the-art research and involved in active direct communications and discussions. Extensive collaborations have been initiated and these combined efforts are certain to generate new ideas and strategies, which may lead to the resolution of several outstanding open problems on the focused PDES.   This conference also provided an excellent opportunity for training and mentoring students and recent Ph.D.'s. Twenty-five junior mathematicians  attended this conference with many of them given the opportunities to present their researches. They communicated extensively with the leading experts of their fields and built social and collaborative networks with other participants.  The connections and bonds will benefit them throughout the rest of their careers.    This conference was reported in Oklahoma State University Communications.This helps to raise the public awareness of mathematics and promote mathematical research.       Last Modified: 08/28/2014       Submitted by: Jiahong Wu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
