<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FESD Type I: A Delta Dynamics Collaboratory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4800000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4800002</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlawrenc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>River deltas represent a major Earth-surface system with societal need. Low-lying, ecologically productive, and inhabited by millions of people, deltas also lie directly in the path of a confluence of ongoing changes: nutrient overloading from agriculture; accelerated subsidence and sea-level rise; effects of land use and navigation; and changing hydrology and sediment supply. The overall objective of this proposal is to develop tested, high-resolution, quantitative models incorporating morphodynamics, ecology, and stratigraphy to predict river delta dynamics over engineering to geologic time-scales, and to specifically address questions of system dynamics, resiliency, and sustainability. We will do this by establishing the Delta Dynamics Collaboratory (DDC) for multi-investigator, interdisciplinary investigations of river delta sedimentary and ecologic dynamics. The lead institution for DDC will be the University of Texas, Austin, currently the center of delta prediction efforts for the National Center for Earth-surface Dynamics (NCED). The collaboratory will comprise two main work centers: a field observatory and a virtual modeling center, together with supporting experimental facilities. The observatory will be at Wax Lake Delta, a manageably small (140 km2), actively growing delta about 100 km west of the main Mississippi Delta birdsfoot. The main observational goal will be to create a network of self-activating sensors to monitor delta behavior during major events (storms, river floods) that will complement an intensive survey program to measure ecosystem properties and relate them to high-resolution topography, bathymetry, and flow fields. The virtual modeling center will be hosted by the Community Surface Dynamics Modeling System (CSDMS) at University of Colorado, where it can contribute to an evolving library of modules for computation and visualization of geomorphic and sedimentary systems, including access to many of the existing delta models. These two centers will be supported by experimental programs at the universities of Minnesota, Illinois, and Texas, and computational programs at Penn State, Boston College, Louisiana-Lafayette, Minnesota, Illinois, and Texas. &lt;br/&gt;Given the challenges, and the fact that no predictive ecogeomorphic model for deltas currently exists, there is certainly a risk that we are not as close to creating one as we think. But the return is enormous, not only providing tools that will be used by coastal scientists and managers worldwide, but also potentially providing the scientific basis for dramatically reshaping the US Gulf coast, creating hundreds of km2 of productive new wetlands and helping to protect New Orleans against future storms. The DDC also will include an innovative educational program through collaboration with the UT-Austin, Jackson School of Geosciences GeoFORCE Texas program, the nation's largest college preparatory program for Earth sciences. At present, 93% of GeoFORCE multi-year participating minority students have gone on to college. DDC will partner with GeoFORCE by providing web-based classroom and lab materials for its high-school Earth sciences program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1135427</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Mohrig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Mohrig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mohrig@jsg.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124712282</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/26/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Duke-Sylvester</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott M Duke-Sylvester</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smd3729@louisiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3374826203</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000584678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8016</Code>
<Text>Front in Earth Sys Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~3020001</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1780001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project developed numerical models predicting the behavior of river deltas over engineering to geologic time-scales in order to address questions of system dynamics, resiliency, and sustainability for these important coastal systems. These models have direct impacts on society as over 500 million people live on or near deltas and a significant fraction of our transportation infrastructure is focused in these coastal zones. Accurate prediction of the growth and/or retreat of deltas under different environmental scenarios required building numerical models that integrated hydrology with sediment transport and ecology. In particular, we focused on the development of a plant community model that was fully integrated with the land-building model. The integration of the vegetation and hydrology models involves a two-way exchange of information. The vegetation model needed to provide the hydrology model with information about the spatial distribution of plant species and the spatial distribution of plant stems. The hydrology model needs to inform the vegetation model about the physical characteristics of the environment that are important for the growth, persistence and senescence of plants. We established a monitoring network at Wax Lake Delta (WLD), south-central Louisiana, to collect the plant, water, solids, and solutes data necessary to guide and test our developing numerical codes.</p> <p>Measurements at WLD documented how delta wetlands and their sedimentary deposits can be harnessed to scrub excess dissolved nutrients from river water and to sequester excess carbon from the environment. This understanding required new measurements that for the first time fully defined the transport of water, solids, and solutes both out of and back into delta channels. These observed exchanges between the channels and adjacent wetlands guided the development of a next generation of delta-system models and required developing an information theory approach to defining the couplings between deltaic state variables. The scales and significance of couplings between water level, water and sediment discharge, wind, tides, and temperature have been quantified at WLD, and work now focusses on determining how hydrological connectivity affects nutrient dynamics.</p> <p>Collecting field measurements is expensive and in many cases not possible so we carried out the necessary studies at WLD to confirm how UAVSAR and AirSWOT, airplane-based radar instruments flown by NASA, can be used to generate delta-wide measurements of water-surface velocity, shallow delta-front bathymetry, and water surface elevation. These data hold great promise in (1) providing a strong test for all types of numerical models estimating delta flow fields, and (2) further characterizing exchanges of water, solids, and solutes between distributary channels and island-top wetlands. Our scientific results that are particularly relevant to land building are available to be used by engineers and communities focused on resource management in coastal environs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;Mohrig</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project developed numerical models predicting the behavior of river deltas over engineering to geologic time-scales in order to address questions of system dynamics, resiliency, and sustainability for these important coastal systems. These models have direct impacts on society as over 500 million people live on or near deltas and a significant fraction of our transportation infrastructure is focused in these coastal zones. Accurate prediction of the growth and/or retreat of deltas under different environmental scenarios required building numerical models that integrated hydrology with sediment transport and ecology. In particular, we focused on the development of a plant community model that was fully integrated with the land-building model. The integration of the vegetation and hydrology models involves a two-way exchange of information. The vegetation model needed to provide the hydrology model with information about the spatial distribution of plant species and the spatial distribution of plant stems. The hydrology model needs to inform the vegetation model about the physical characteristics of the environment that are important for the growth, persistence and senescence of plants. We established a monitoring network at Wax Lake Delta (WLD), south-central Louisiana, to collect the plant, water, solids, and solutes data necessary to guide and test our developing numerical codes.  Measurements at WLD documented how delta wetlands and their sedimentary deposits can be harnessed to scrub excess dissolved nutrients from river water and to sequester excess carbon from the environment. This understanding required new measurements that for the first time fully defined the transport of water, solids, and solutes both out of and back into delta channels. These observed exchanges between the channels and adjacent wetlands guided the development of a next generation of delta-system models and required developing an information theory approach to defining the couplings between deltaic state variables. The scales and significance of couplings between water level, water and sediment discharge, wind, tides, and temperature have been quantified at WLD, and work now focusses on determining how hydrological connectivity affects nutrient dynamics.  Collecting field measurements is expensive and in many cases not possible so we carried out the necessary studies at WLD to confirm how UAVSAR and AirSWOT, airplane-based radar instruments flown by NASA, can be used to generate delta-wide measurements of water-surface velocity, shallow delta-front bathymetry, and water surface elevation. These data hold great promise in (1) providing a strong test for all types of numerical models estimating delta flow fields, and (2) further characterizing exchanges of water, solids, and solutes between distributary channels and island-top wetlands. Our scientific results that are particularly relevant to land building are available to be used by engineers and communities focused on resource management in coastal environs.          Last Modified: 04/30/2019       Submitted by: David Mohrig]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
