<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Low-latitude Ionosphere and the Development of Forecasting Techniques Using the Low-latitude Ionosphere Sensor Network (LISN) Distributed Observatory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>950000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1050557</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth S. Lieberman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will continue operating the Low-latitude Ionosphere Sensor Network (LISN) and utilize its regional measurements to investigate the day-to-day variability and formation of structures and dynamics in the low-latitude ionosphere. LISN is a distributed observatory composed of GPS receivers, flux gate magnetometers, and Vertical Incidence Pulsed Ionospheric Radar (VIPIR) ionosondes installed principally in the western half of South America. The work carried out under this grant will collect, store, and disseminate real-time ionospheric observables - a nowcast - and to conduct dedicated campaigns and investigations leading toward developing a predictive capability - a forecast - of the electrodynamics and stability of the low- latitude ionosphere over South America.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1135675</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cesar</FirstName>
<LastName>Valladares</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cesar E Valladares</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cev160230@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728835349</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000370110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5926</Code>
<Text>LATIN AMERICA, SDC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~650000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~40558</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~59999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goals of this project were to operate a distributed observatory in South America to investigate the upper layers of the atmosphere, between 100 and 600 km altitude, assess the day-to-day variability and follow the formation of medium and large-scale structures.&nbsp; Funding made it possible to deploy two small radars in the countries of Argentina and Bolivia to study how structures form and evolve in the high altitude atmosphere.&nbsp; The project included a Web site designed to collect, store, and disseminate real-time observables to members of the scientific community and to the general public.&nbsp; This new type of remote observations and concurrent reporting is called the nowcasting of the upper atmosphere.</p> <p>The following projects were investigated: the study of disturbances that develop at 300 km altitude associated with the tropical storm Irene, perturbations in the total electron content due to the existence of solar magnetic storms, the formation of structures that are conjugate and map following the magnetic field of the Earth from the Caribbean region to the southern part of Brazil in South America, the interaction of large-scale perturbations near the magnetic equator, and the formation of disturbances above 200 kilometers due to the 15 February 2013 Chelyabinsk meteor explosion.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Cesar&nbsp;E&nbsp;Valladares</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this project were to operate a distributed observatory in South America to investigate the upper layers of the atmosphere, between 100 and 600 km altitude, assess the day-to-day variability and follow the formation of medium and large-scale structures.  Funding made it possible to deploy two small radars in the countries of Argentina and Bolivia to study how structures form and evolve in the high altitude atmosphere.  The project included a Web site designed to collect, store, and disseminate real-time observables to members of the scientific community and to the general public.  This new type of remote observations and concurrent reporting is called the nowcasting of the upper atmosphere.  The following projects were investigated: the study of disturbances that develop at 300 km altitude associated with the tropical storm Irene, perturbations in the total electron content due to the existence of solar magnetic storms, the formation of structures that are conjugate and map following the magnetic field of the Earth from the Caribbean region to the southern part of Brazil in South America, the interaction of large-scale perturbations near the magnetic equator, and the formation of disturbances above 200 kilometers due to the 15 February 2013 Chelyabinsk meteor explosion.          Last Modified: 12/29/2016       Submitted by: Cesar E Valladares]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
