<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Noyce/MSTI Teacher Fellows Master Teacher Fellows Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1814088.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1814088</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Kim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924458</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Robert Noyce/ Mathematics and Science Teacher Institute (MSTI) at Xavier University of Louisiana goals are to: (1) educate and train Master Teacher Fellows (MTF) to achieve National Board for Professional Teaching Certification in mathematics or science and (2) introduce Teacher Fellows (TF) to the field of mathematics /science education and support their efforts in the high-needs school districts in New Orleans area.  Partners include New Orleans Parish School Districts, ExxonMobil Foundation, the local Audubon Zoo and Aquarium, National Science Teachers Association' and National Mathematics Teachers Association.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;MSTI is recruiting and supporting 10 STEM professionals and/or recent STEM graduates as Teacher Fellows to enroll in the MAT Program and receive licensure and recruiting a cohort of 10 Master Teaching Fellows to participate in professional development seminars with the collaborative partners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:  Noyce/MSTI is increasing the pool of STEM teachers in New Orleans by working with the collaborative partners to provide training and support and giving direct, supervised, organized teaching experiences to both TF and MTF cohorts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:  This proposal is increasing the number of STEM teachers in the high-need New Orleans area.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1136425</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sindhu</FirstName>
<LastName>Unnithan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sindhu S Unnithan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sunnitha@xula.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5045205306</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000359353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bilyeu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryan Bilyeu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbilyeu@xula.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5045205414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000368816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rosalind</FirstName>
<LastName>Hale</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rosalind P Hale</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhale@xula.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5045207536</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557934</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/25/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Renee</FirstName>
<LastName>Akbar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Renee Akbar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rvakbar@xula.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5045207538</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713475</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Xavier University of Louisiana</Name>
<CityName>new orleans</CityName>
<ZipCode>701251098</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5045205440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>#1 Drexel Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020857876</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>XAVIER UNIVERSITY OF LOUISIANA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020857876</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Xavier University of Louisiana]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701251056</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Drexel Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7908</Code>
<Text>Teaching &amp; Mstr Tchng Fellows</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~392502</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~415186</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~329808</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~336212</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~340380</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Noyce/MSTI Scholarship Program at Xavier University of Louisiana&nbsp;received funding from NSF between 2012 and 2017 to increasse the number and quality of minority teachers of mathematics and science classrooms in an urban city in a southeastern state.&nbsp; Each year reported continuous improvement of program effectiveness, and outcome attainment. The outcomes of this project were improving content knowledge, developing effective instructional strategies, and&nbsp; working with schools and districts to develop school-based coaching.</p> <p>Twenty educators were recruited and selected to particpate in the two-tiered&nbsp;model to produce highly-qualified teachers&nbsp;for high -&nbsp;needs school settings. To&nbsp;enhance content-knowledge and develop effective instructional activities, particpants particpated in a number of professional development activities with a focus on reflective teaching practices.&nbsp; These were provided by the National Board of Professional Standards, Workshop Way and a variety of sessions attended by particpants at regional conferences, such as&nbsp;the Louisiana Council of Teachers of Mathematics and the Lousiana Science Teacher Association.&nbsp;</p> <p>The first tier of the model consisted of ten secondary mathematics and science teachers known a the Master Teacher Fellows Program (MTF).&nbsp; The goal for this cohort was to become nationally board certified. National certification is a recognition that the participant met the highest standards&nbsp;of effective teaching.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition to attending the professional development activities above, The Master Fellows also particpated in the National Board of Professional Standards program and its Take One program, which focuses on mathematics and science instruction.&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the course of the grant,&nbsp;&nbsp;one Fellow attained national certification.&nbsp; The other particpants&nbsp;retook&nbsp;the exam, but their&nbsp;scores were&nbsp;impacted by a change in the test and a change in the cutoff score. In addition, the districts in which these educators were employed, did not have the funds for the customary merit pay set aside for nationally certified teachers.&nbsp; Particpants had little to no incentive to retake the exam&nbsp;a third time, even though they continued to fully particpate in the professional development activities.&nbsp; At the close of the program, two particpants retook the exam and are awaiting the results.</p> <p>The second tier of the model was the Teaching Fellows program (TF). Ten educators were recruited mainly from HBCUs to become mathematics and science teachers in an urban city in a southeastern state. Each Teacher Fellow enrolled in a Master of Arts in Teaching program at a univeristy&nbsp;with a&nbsp;teacher preparation program that emphasized inquiry, collaboration, and experimentation. In addition to coursework, particpants attended seminars, and engaged in activities and projects focused on identifying, developing, and integrating effective teaching practices that&nbsp;positively impact students enrolled in high - needs schools.&nbsp; All of the Teaching Fellows earned a Master of Arts in Teaching degree.&nbsp; Additionally, each Fellow passed all parts of the Praxis Teacher Licensure Exam,&nbsp;which made them eligible for state certification.</p> <p>A unique component of the project was the engagement and participation of education and STEM faculty.&nbsp; Under the guidance of the National Board consultant, faculty formed teams to observe and provide space and time for reflective and intentional feedback designed to improve teh participant's&nbsp;instructional practice.&nbsp; This model of collaborative school-based coaching supported teachers in the assessment and analysis of instruction based on best practices.</p> <p>Each team observed Master Teacher Fellows and Teacher Fellows at least twice a semester. To support the current observations conducted by the district while maintaining the integrity of the NOYCE/MSTI Scholarship program, the Reformed Teaching Observation Protocol (RTOP) instrument was selected. This&nbsp; instrument was chosen because it provides a standardized means for detecting the degree to which classroom-instruction uses student-centered, engaged learnng practices, known as reformed teaching. On a 5 point Likert scale (0, no evidence of reform - 4, strong evidence of reform, 97% of the Fellows scored a 3, indicating a significant paradigm shift from&nbsp;teacher-centered lecture-driven practices to instructional practices that are student-centered and activity-based&nbsp;and include multiple opportunities for student collaborations on projects and other learning activities.</p> <p>To conclude, the NOYCE/MSTI Scholarship Program achieved its outcomes of enhancing content-knowledge and improving teaching practices through innovative professional development activities that focused on student-centered, activity - based learning environments.&nbsp; The faculty teams modeled collaborative school-based coaching that helped to provide reflective and intentional feedback&nbsp;to improve classroom&nbsp;practices.&nbsp; An unintended outcome involved university faculty who self-reported a shift in their approach to teaching university students as a result of particpating in this program.&nbsp;&nbsp;They too&nbsp; moved away&nbsp;from lecture to an approach that involved inquiry-based collaborations and student-centered instructional practices.&nbsp;&nbsp;The two-tiered model was designed to fill a critical shortage of high quality mathematics and science teachers in high&nbsp;- needs schools. Utilizing this model, a cohort of twenty mathematics and science teachers were retained by providing support structures that strengthen&nbsp;instructional practice and enhanced content-knowledge.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Renee&nbsp;Akbar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Noyce/MSTI Scholarship Program at Xavier University of Louisiana received funding from NSF between 2012 and 2017 to increasse the number and quality of minority teachers of mathematics and science classrooms in an urban city in a southeastern state.  Each year reported continuous improvement of program effectiveness, and outcome attainment. The outcomes of this project were improving content knowledge, developing effective instructional strategies, and  working with schools and districts to develop school-based coaching.  Twenty educators were recruited and selected to particpate in the two-tiered model to produce highly-qualified teachers for high - needs school settings. To enhance content-knowledge and develop effective instructional activities, particpants particpated in a number of professional development activities with a focus on reflective teaching practices.  These were provided by the National Board of Professional Standards, Workshop Way and a variety of sessions attended by particpants at regional conferences, such as the Louisiana Council of Teachers of Mathematics and the Lousiana Science Teacher Association.   The first tier of the model consisted of ten secondary mathematics and science teachers known a the Master Teacher Fellows Program (MTF).  The goal for this cohort was to become nationally board certified. National certification is a recognition that the participant met the highest standards of effective teaching.  In addition to attending the professional development activities above, The Master Fellows also particpated in the National Board of Professional Standards program and its Take One program, which focuses on mathematics and science instruction.   Over the course of the grant,  one Fellow attained national certification.  The other particpants retook the exam, but their scores were impacted by a change in the test and a change in the cutoff score. In addition, the districts in which these educators were employed, did not have the funds for the customary merit pay set aside for nationally certified teachers.  Particpants had little to no incentive to retake the exam a third time, even though they continued to fully particpate in the professional development activities.  At the close of the program, two particpants retook the exam and are awaiting the results.  The second tier of the model was the Teaching Fellows program (TF). Ten educators were recruited mainly from HBCUs to become mathematics and science teachers in an urban city in a southeastern state. Each Teacher Fellow enrolled in a Master of Arts in Teaching program at a univeristy with a teacher preparation program that emphasized inquiry, collaboration, and experimentation. In addition to coursework, particpants attended seminars, and engaged in activities and projects focused on identifying, developing, and integrating effective teaching practices that positively impact students enrolled in high - needs schools.  All of the Teaching Fellows earned a Master of Arts in Teaching degree.  Additionally, each Fellow passed all parts of the Praxis Teacher Licensure Exam, which made them eligible for state certification.  A unique component of the project was the engagement and participation of education and STEM faculty.  Under the guidance of the National Board consultant, faculty formed teams to observe and provide space and time for reflective and intentional feedback designed to improve teh participant's instructional practice.  This model of collaborative school-based coaching supported teachers in the assessment and analysis of instruction based on best practices.  Each team observed Master Teacher Fellows and Teacher Fellows at least twice a semester. To support the current observations conducted by the district while maintaining the integrity of the NOYCE/MSTI Scholarship program, the Reformed Teaching Observation Protocol (RTOP) instrument was selected. This  instrument was chosen because it provides a standardized means for detecting the degree to which classroom-instruction uses student-centered, engaged learnng practices, known as reformed teaching. On a 5 point Likert scale (0, no evidence of reform - 4, strong evidence of reform, 97% of the Fellows scored a 3, indicating a significant paradigm shift from teacher-centered lecture-driven practices to instructional practices that are student-centered and activity-based and include multiple opportunities for student collaborations on projects and other learning activities.  To conclude, the NOYCE/MSTI Scholarship Program achieved its outcomes of enhancing content-knowledge and improving teaching practices through innovative professional development activities that focused on student-centered, activity - based learning environments.  The faculty teams modeled collaborative school-based coaching that helped to provide reflective and intentional feedback to improve classroom practices.  An unintended outcome involved university faculty who self-reported a shift in their approach to teaching university students as a result of particpating in this program.  They too  moved away from lecture to an approach that involved inquiry-based collaborations and student-centered instructional practices.  The two-tiered model was designed to fill a critical shortage of high quality mathematics and science teachers in high - needs schools. Utilizing this model, a cohort of twenty mathematics and science teachers were retained by providing support structures that strengthen instructional practice and enhanced content-knowledge.                            Last Modified: 08/06/2018       Submitted by: Renee Akbar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
