<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Adelphi University Science Education Advancement (SEA) Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Turley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Adelphi University Science Education Advancement (SEA) Noyce Scholarship Program is providing scholarships to 26 students majoring in the sciences as they prepare to enter a science teaching career in a high-need public school. This program includes: 1) two field-based marine science courses that explore marine environments of Long Island, 2) a three-week internship with Nassau Board Of Cooperative Education Services Summer Marine Biology (BOCES), 3) a strong mentoring/induction program pairing scholars with an accomplished teacher-mentor from high-need partner schools, 4) mentorship by a National Board of Professional Teaching Standards (NBPTS) certified teacher, and 5) assessments using the NBPTS Take One! program. The scope of educational reach of the partners in this project, Adelphi University and Nassau BOCES, makes this project an important contribution to the much needed effort to increase the quality and quantity of highly-qualified science teachers. The project's focus on 1) using marine sciences as a vehicle for the teaching and learning of all science disciplines and 2) preparing teachers to use marine environments in their own curriculum holds significant promise for the improvement of science education in a region spanning from New York City to the far reaches of Long Island, a region comprising some of the most important yet over-used coastal environments found along the Atlantic seaboard.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1136380</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beth</FirstName>
<LastName>Christensen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beth Christensen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christensenb@rowan.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8562565251</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000194394</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tracy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hogan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tracy Hogan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hogan@adelphi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5168774019</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589168</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Adelphi University</Name>
<CityName>Garden City</CityName>
<ZipCode>115304299</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5162948700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>South Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065972838</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADELPHI UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065972838</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ADELPHI UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>GARDEN CITY</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>115304299</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ONE SOUTH AVENUE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">Title: Adelphi University Science Education Advancement (SEA) Program/Robert Noyce Scholarship Program, PI: T. Hogan, Co-PI: B. Christensen</p> <p dir="ltr">Intellectual Merit. To date, program objectives have been met with 26 Scholars that have graduated with their MA, passed all certification exams and been awarded New York State certification in grades 7-12 Chemistry, Biology, Physics or Earth Science education. Data Table 1 highlights important statistics of scholars across cohorts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">*Includes one Scholar that graduated May 2018.</p> <p dir="ltr">Broader Impacts. The Adelphi SEA program successfully recruited and prepared 26 new teachers across all four science disciplines. Over 80% of the candidates were drawn from underrepresented groups including females and nonwhite males. 100% of our candidates that completed the program have, are currently, or will begin to fulfill the scholarship requirements by teaching two years in a high-needs school on Long Island, in New York City or beyond. Our final candidate (chemistry) will begin teaching this coming school year (2018-2019) in New York City.</p> <p dir="ltr">Overall Outcomes of Phase I: Adelphi Science Education Advancement/NSF Noyce Program</p> <p dir="ltr">There were five overarching goals to guide all efforts of this program. Each goal is defined below along with supporting evidence to indicate the degree of success in meeting the goal.</p> <p dir="ltr">Objective 1: The program will provide recruitment and scholarship support to secondary science teachers with attention to underrepresented groups within those populations.</p> <p dir="ltr">Due to the success in recruiting STEM professionals for the MA track, the Phase I program recruited 29 candidates (3 more than the proposed 26 Scholars). Of the 29, 26 Scholars ultimately completed the program. Three Scholars partially completed the program but left due to financial and family hardships. Beginning with Cohort 3, we increased the scholarship from partial ($22,500) to full scholarship ($37,000) to provide more incentive for STEM professionals to enroll in the program. Overall, we found much greater success in recruiting graduate STEM career changers for the one year preparation program as compared to our undergraduate/graduate five-year program candidates. Across all cohorts, over 80 percent of the Scholars enrolled in the program were either women or non-white men.</p> <p dir="ltr">Objective 2: Develop effective mentor-scholar partnership coupled with supervision and support by University faculty to ensure Scholars receive appropriate opportunities and support for guided practice in teaching.</p> <p dir="ltr">Effective mentoring is an important part of the teacher preparation process and a prominent part of the Adelphi University Noyce/SEA Program. Partnerships were established with secondary schools on Long Island and New York City, and each scholar was paired with an accomplished teacher mentor at each clinical practice site. Based on evaluation of focus group data, findings revealed that Scholars considered their student teaching experience, via guidance from accomplished teacher mentors, as having the most impact on their teacher preparation.</p> <p dir="ltr">Objective 3: Engage in rigorous coursework embedded in field and clinical settings to allow for integration of pedagogy and maximum coherence among theory, research and practice.</p> <p dir="ltr">Overall, through surveys and focus groups, findings suggested that the Adelphi Noyce Program was successful in developing a comprehensive and coherent course of study preparing Scholars for science instruction that motivates and engages students. The Scholars generally found their coursework thought-provoking, challenging, enjoyable and useful. In evaluating the benefits of their coursework, they highly valued the courses that they perceived had the most direct utility such as student teaching and lesson planning. They valued field experiences and internships and incorporated these experiences in their instruction when opportunities arose.</p> <p dir="ltr">Objective 4: Provide evidence-based teaching and learning in formal and informal environments.</p> <p dir="ltr">All 26 Scholars obtained satisfactory grades and completed the program with an exit GPA of 3.76 to 4.00, with an average GPA of 3.89. 100% of Scholars successfully completed all New York State Certification exams, suggesting that the Adelphi Noyce Program is providing Scholars with evidence-based teaching and learning experiences.</p> <p dir="ltr">Objective 5: Promote candidate retention and continued development of accomplished teaching for each scholar.</p> <p dir="ltr">The Adelphi SEA program has been effective at retaining their Scholars and placing them in high-needs schools. Across the past four (of six) cohorts, 19 of the Scholars have fulfilled the scholarship agreement requirements. For the 2018-2019 school year, 14 scholars continue to teach science to students in grades 7-12 after their two years of mandatory service to the profession (75% retention rate). &nbsp;</p> <div>&nbsp;</div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Tracy&nbsp;Hogan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Title: Adelphi University Science Education Advancement (SEA) Program/Robert Noyce Scholarship Program, PI: T. Hogan, Co-PI: B. Christensen Intellectual Merit. To date, program objectives have been met with 26 Scholars that have graduated with their MA, passed all certification exams and been awarded New York State certification in grades 7-12 Chemistry, Biology, Physics or Earth Science education. Data Table 1 highlights important statistics of scholars across cohorts.    *Includes one Scholar that graduated May 2018. Broader Impacts. The Adelphi SEA program successfully recruited and prepared 26 new teachers across all four science disciplines. Over 80% of the candidates were drawn from underrepresented groups including females and nonwhite males. 100% of our candidates that completed the program have, are currently, or will begin to fulfill the scholarship requirements by teaching two years in a high-needs school on Long Island, in New York City or beyond. Our final candidate (chemistry) will begin teaching this coming school year (2018-2019) in New York City. Overall Outcomes of Phase I: Adelphi Science Education Advancement/NSF Noyce Program There were five overarching goals to guide all efforts of this program. Each goal is defined below along with supporting evidence to indicate the degree of success in meeting the goal. Objective 1: The program will provide recruitment and scholarship support to secondary science teachers with attention to underrepresented groups within those populations. Due to the success in recruiting STEM professionals for the MA track, the Phase I program recruited 29 candidates (3 more than the proposed 26 Scholars). Of the 29, 26 Scholars ultimately completed the program. Three Scholars partially completed the program but left due to financial and family hardships. Beginning with Cohort 3, we increased the scholarship from partial ($22,500) to full scholarship ($37,000) to provide more incentive for STEM professionals to enroll in the program. Overall, we found much greater success in recruiting graduate STEM career changers for the one year preparation program as compared to our undergraduate/graduate five-year program candidates. Across all cohorts, over 80 percent of the Scholars enrolled in the program were either women or non-white men. Objective 2: Develop effective mentor-scholar partnership coupled with supervision and support by University faculty to ensure Scholars receive appropriate opportunities and support for guided practice in teaching. Effective mentoring is an important part of the teacher preparation process and a prominent part of the Adelphi University Noyce/SEA Program. Partnerships were established with secondary schools on Long Island and New York City, and each scholar was paired with an accomplished teacher mentor at each clinical practice site. Based on evaluation of focus group data, findings revealed that Scholars considered their student teaching experience, via guidance from accomplished teacher mentors, as having the most impact on their teacher preparation. Objective 3: Engage in rigorous coursework embedded in field and clinical settings to allow for integration of pedagogy and maximum coherence among theory, research and practice. Overall, through surveys and focus groups, findings suggested that the Adelphi Noyce Program was successful in developing a comprehensive and coherent course of study preparing Scholars for science instruction that motivates and engages students. The Scholars generally found their coursework thought-provoking, challenging, enjoyable and useful. In evaluating the benefits of their coursework, they highly valued the courses that they perceived had the most direct utility such as student teaching and lesson planning. They valued field experiences and internships and incorporated these experiences in their instruction when opportunities arose. Objective 4: Provide evidence-based teaching and learning in formal and informal environments. All 26 Scholars obtained satisfactory grades and completed the program with an exit GPA of 3.76 to 4.00, with an average GPA of 3.89. 100% of Scholars successfully completed all New York State Certification exams, suggesting that the Adelphi Noyce Program is providing Scholars with evidence-based teaching and learning experiences. Objective 5: Promote candidate retention and continued development of accomplished teaching for each scholar. The Adelphi SEA program has been effective at retaining their Scholars and placing them in high-needs schools. Across the past four (of six) cohorts, 19 of the Scholars have fulfilled the scholarship agreement requirements. For the 2018-2019 school year, 14 scholars continue to teach science to students in grades 7-12 after their two years of mandatory service to the profession (75% retention rate).                 Last Modified: 10/01/2018       Submitted by: Tracy Hogan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
