<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GSE/RES: Impact of Single-Sex Public Educational Environments on Mathematics and Science Classroom Environment, Student Academic Performance, and Student Self-Concept</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>524667.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>524667</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jolene Jesse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjesse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: Clemson University will investigate the classroom environment of Single-Sex Public Education (SSPE) mathematics and science classes in middle grades and the impact of these classes on students' academic achievement and academic self-concept. The central hypothesis is that SSPE settings increase girls' academic self-concept, but the teacher is a larger influence than whether the class is SSPE or coeducational (COED) on academic rigor and discourse in the classroom. There are three specific aims for the proposed research: (1) Analyze and compare the academic rigor and classroom discourse of SSPE and COED classes, (2) Analyze and compare academic performance of SSPE students and COED students in middle grades mathematics and science, and (3) Analyze and compare academic self-concept of SSPE and COED students in middle grades mathematics and science. The project will analyze videoed lesson sessions of SSPE and COED mathematics and science middle grades classes for academic rigor and for classroom discourse; analyze student performance on the state-mandated annual standardized assessment, the Palmetto Assessment of State Standards (PASS) exam in mathematics and science; and assess student identities and attitudes about mathematics and science through a survey instrument.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: An improved understanding of SSPE mathematics and science middle grades classrooms and their relationship to academic achievement and academic self-concept will inform key stakeholders as they make decisions about student participation in SSPE settings. The principles of diversity and broadening opportunities for and participation of underrepresented groups are central to the proposed research. Each aspect of the research, from the objectives to the specific aims to the research plan to the expected outcomes, revolves around the relationship of girls to mathematics and science teaching and learning. The proposed research also enhances networks and partnerships by fostering collaborations with several K-12 school districts and schools across the state of South Carolina that are participating in single-sex mathematics and science classrooms in the middle grades. Dissemination of the research will include national presentations and publications, as well as sharing the findings with participating schools and districts at local faculty meetings and professional development in-service meetings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1136248</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Bridges</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William C Bridges</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wbrdgs@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8656563012</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000253533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stacy</FirstName>
<LastName>Che</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stacy M Che</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sche@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646562036</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Brackett Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1544</Code>
<Text>RES ON GENDER IN SCI &amp; ENGINE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~524667</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project contributed to our understandings of single-sex education in mathematics and science middle grades classrooms in public schools in the U.S. Because, at the time of this project's onset, little was known about such educational settings, the project research team spent 3 years of the project in data collection. This extensive period of data collection resulted in a databse of 353 video classroom sessions of mathematics and science teachers in all girls, all boys, and coeducational classrooms. These lesson sessions have been analyzed for academic rigor, and a subset have been analyzed for classroom discourse. Further, more than 900 student academic self-concept surveys have been completed and analyzed over the life of the project. Finally, academic performance data for thousands of students were collected and analyzed for relationships between student math/science performance and class type (all girls, all boys, coed).&nbsp;</p> <p>Findings from the research activities stemming from this project indicate that academic rigor is consistent across classtype, that student academic self-concept is consistent across classtype, and that student academic performance is consistent across classtype. Our discourse analysis reveals, however, that classroom discourse has the potential to vary, for a given teacher, across classtype and that single-sex classes could pose a space for teachers to enact traditional gendered norms and expectations through momentary but influential utterances during class.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/12/2016<br>      Modified by: Stacy&nbsp;M&nbsp;Che</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project contributed to our understandings of single-sex education in mathematics and science middle grades classrooms in public schools in the U.S. Because, at the time of this project's onset, little was known about such educational settings, the project research team spent 3 years of the project in data collection. This extensive period of data collection resulted in a databse of 353 video classroom sessions of mathematics and science teachers in all girls, all boys, and coeducational classrooms. These lesson sessions have been analyzed for academic rigor, and a subset have been analyzed for classroom discourse. Further, more than 900 student academic self-concept surveys have been completed and analyzed over the life of the project. Finally, academic performance data for thousands of students were collected and analyzed for relationships between student math/science performance and class type (all girls, all boys, coed).   Findings from the research activities stemming from this project indicate that academic rigor is consistent across classtype, that student academic self-concept is consistent across classtype, and that student academic performance is consistent across classtype. Our discourse analysis reveals, however, that classroom discourse has the potential to vary, for a given teacher, across classtype and that single-sex classes could pose a space for teachers to enact traditional gendered norms and expectations through momentary but influential utterances during class.       Last Modified: 02/12/2016       Submitted by: Stacy M Che]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
