<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Coupling of Gas-Phase Radical Oxidation Chemistry and Organic-Aerosol Formation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>661375</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Through laboratory experiments this project will probe complex interactions between gas-phase organic oxidation chemistry and the evolution of organic particulate matter (PM) making use of advanced instruments including (1) a Chemical Ionization Mass Spectrometer (CIMS) designed for flexible, highly sensitive measurement of critical radicals as well as gas-phase organic compounds including organic acids and peroxides and (2) a High-Resolution Time of Flight Aerosol Mass Spectrometer (HR-AMS) to measure the size-dependent non-refractory fraction of particle composition between 50 and 700 nanometer size, explicitly resolving carbon, hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen in the particles. A portion of the experiments will be "traditional" secondary organic aerosol (SOA) formation from such systems as alpha-pinene plus ozone, but with measurement of peroxides and other reactive oxygen species under a range of conditions. The larger share of experiments will be carried out with several carefully selected sequences of organic precursors designed to model later-generation oxidation products of traditional SOA experiments. Specifically, SOA formation will be initiated from precursors at selected points in a 2-dimensional (2D) space combining volatility and carbon oxidation state to test whether organic aerosol mass yields and properties vary systematically based on location in this space. If SOA properties do organize in this space, that will confirm the utility of this 2D representation as a dramatic simplification for model representations of SOA behavior, and the results of this research will provide essential parameters required to implement this 2D framework in models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Organic aerosols are significant players in both climate and particulate matter health effects. In each case their contributions are among the most uncertain. Consequently, the results of this project will significantly enhance understanding of particulate matter health effects and aerosol-cloud interactions influencing climate. This will inform evolving policy in both areas. The research will be carried out by a postdoctoral associate, a graduate student, and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1136479</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neil</FirstName>
<LastName>Donahue</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Neil M Donahue</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nmd@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122684415</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5950</Code>
<Text>SWITZERLAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~61375</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research by scientists at Carnegie Mellon University (CMU) focused on the role oxidation chemistry plays in the evolution of organic particulate matter in the atmosphere. &nbsp;The research evolved along two related fronts, one at CMU and one in a consortium at CERN in Geneva.</p> <p>Reserach conducted at CMU focused on experiments addressing the oxidation pathways of specific molecules selected as model systems for oxidation chemistry at various stages ("generations") of atmospheric processing and also development of a versitile modeling framework called the "two-dimensaional volatility basis set" (2D-VBS). &nbsp;The experiments focused on oxidation products of alpha-pinene, a well-studied natural hydrocarbon emitted by trees. &nbsp;alpha-Pinene itself is known to be a strong source of secondary organic aerosol (SOA), which consists of organic material that can condense onto particles, but only 10-20% of the oxidation products condense to form SOA at first. The research question was how efficient oxidation of the 80-90% of gas-phase products might be in forming SOA. &nbsp;Experiments showed that both pinonaldehyde (one of the most volatile products) and pinanediol (one of the least volatile gas-phase products) could produce SOA, and that the less volatile product made SOA more efficiently. &nbsp;These results and others served as constraints for continued development of the 2D-VBS, including incorporation into the Community Air Quality Model (CMAQ), focusing on air quality in Eastern China. &nbsp;Understanding how oxidation (aging) of organic aerosol influences its properties, including the health effects of fine particles, is a major challenge in particulate matter health effects research.</p> <p><br />The second research front took place as part of the CLOUD consortium at CERN, which focuses on chemistry and physics leading to new-particle formation in the atmosphere. &nbsp;The CMU team members have been especially focused on the role of organic oxidation products in new-particle formation, including many of the same species addressed in the work at CMU described above. &nbsp;A succession of experiments at CLOUD showed first that sulfuric acid production (by sulfur dioxide oxidation) could lead to new-particle formation rates consistent with atmospheric observations in the presence of a strong base such as dimethyl amine. &nbsp;Subsequent experiments showed that oxidized organic compounds could play a similar stabilizing role, and characteristic patterns observed with mass spectrometers in the CLOUD experiments closely resembled similar observations in boreal forests. &nbsp;Finally, experiments with alpha-pinene oxidation alone revealed that alpha-pinene oxidation products could lead to new-particle formation without assistance from sulfuric acid, suggesting pathways for new-particle formation in the pre-industrial atmosphere. &nbsp;This work is laying the foundation for a much more detailed understanding of how total particle number has changed throughout the atmosphere between pre-industrial times and the present day. &nbsp;Uncertainty in how particle concentrations have changed over that period constitutes one of the leading uncertainties in climate forcing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2015<br>      Modified by: Neil&nbsp;M&nbsp;Donahue</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research by scientists at Carnegie Mellon University (CMU) focused on the role oxidation chemistry plays in the evolution of organic particulate matter in the atmosphere.  The research evolved along two related fronts, one at CMU and one in a consortium at CERN in Geneva.  Reserach conducted at CMU focused on experiments addressing the oxidation pathways of specific molecules selected as model systems for oxidation chemistry at various stages ("generations") of atmospheric processing and also development of a versitile modeling framework called the "two-dimensaional volatility basis set" (2D-VBS).  The experiments focused on oxidation products of alpha-pinene, a well-studied natural hydrocarbon emitted by trees.  alpha-Pinene itself is known to be a strong source of secondary organic aerosol (SOA), which consists of organic material that can condense onto particles, but only 10-20% of the oxidation products condense to form SOA at first. The research question was how efficient oxidation of the 80-90% of gas-phase products might be in forming SOA.  Experiments showed that both pinonaldehyde (one of the most volatile products) and pinanediol (one of the least volatile gas-phase products) could produce SOA, and that the less volatile product made SOA more efficiently.  These results and others served as constraints for continued development of the 2D-VBS, including incorporation into the Community Air Quality Model (CMAQ), focusing on air quality in Eastern China.  Understanding how oxidation (aging) of organic aerosol influences its properties, including the health effects of fine particles, is a major challenge in particulate matter health effects research.   The second research front took place as part of the CLOUD consortium at CERN, which focuses on chemistry and physics leading to new-particle formation in the atmosphere.  The CMU team members have been especially focused on the role of organic oxidation products in new-particle formation, including many of the same species addressed in the work at CMU described above.  A succession of experiments at CLOUD showed first that sulfuric acid production (by sulfur dioxide oxidation) could lead to new-particle formation rates consistent with atmospheric observations in the presence of a strong base such as dimethyl amine.  Subsequent experiments showed that oxidized organic compounds could play a similar stabilizing role, and characteristic patterns observed with mass spectrometers in the CLOUD experiments closely resembled similar observations in boreal forests.  Finally, experiments with alpha-pinene oxidation alone revealed that alpha-pinene oxidation products could lead to new-particle formation without assistance from sulfuric acid, suggesting pathways for new-particle formation in the pre-industrial atmosphere.  This work is laying the foundation for a much more detailed understanding of how total particle number has changed throughout the atmosphere between pre-industrial times and the present day.  Uncertainty in how particle concentrations have changed over that period constitutes one of the leading uncertainties in climate forcing.       Last Modified: 11/09/2015       Submitted by: Neil M Donahue]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
