<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EFRI-MIKS: Microfluidic-Based Screening of Multi-Kingdom Microbial Communication Molecules</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1999998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1999998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kerstin Mukerji</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmukerji@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925390</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This NSF award by the Office of Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation supports work to enable the creation of novel platforms and animal models allowing new insight in complex multi-kingdom interactions. Significant progress has been made to decode the small molecule signals developed by all organisims to respond to, and survive in, their environments. However, evolutionary programs have ensured that other organisms mimic or highjack these communication signals in a defensive or symbiotic maneuver, exponentially increasing the scope and complexity of this chemical language. The outcome of these inter-kingdom signals can determine the behavior, survival, virulence or gene expression of all participating organisms. Because of&lt;br/&gt;the disparity in the methods and platforms used and available to study each organisms as well as the complexity of the signaling involved, progress in discovering these interactions is slow. Here we bring together expertise from four scientific disciplines; chemistry, biomedical engineering, immunology and&lt;br/&gt;microbiology; to present disruptive methodologies to capture this language. Focusing on fungal secondary metabolites (SM) as the communication molecules, we demonstrate the enabling features and high-throughput power of novel microdevices in both hypothesis driven and discovery-based science. Our overarching goal is to create broadly applicable microscaled methods to unlock the secret language of cell-to-cell communication in intra- and inter-kingdom interactions. A key component of this award is to prime students at the highschool level to the broad implications on human health, food safety and the environment of these multi-kingdom interactions, through the creation of an interactive, hands-on, lab course, in which students will be sensitized to aspects of micro-engineering, fungal genetics and molecular biology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1136903</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Keller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy P Keller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>npkeller@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082629795</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213432</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Beebe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David J Beebe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>djbeebe@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082622260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000338284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Clay</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Clay Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>clayw@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3234421670</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000371655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Huttenlocher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Huttenlocher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huttenlocher@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082654642</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000310967</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1999998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>All environments are composed of a complex and shifting microbiome that communicates largely through chemical signaling.&nbsp; Perhaps the most understood example involves quorum signaling systems between bacteria, and more recently fungi, yet even these systems represent but one microbial communication process.&nbsp;&nbsp; Difficulties in fully assessing this vast communication network can be attributed to both lack of user-friendly technologies and inability to identify and characterize microbial signaling molecules.&nbsp; Here we brought together expertise from four scientific disciplines &ndash; chemistry, biomedical engineering, immunology and medical microbiology - to address the poorly understood role of multicellular and inter-kingdom signaling interactions.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong> This research has led to novel insights into cross-kingdom signal communication signals using our novel microscale and zebrafish platforms to identify previously unknown chemical microbial signatures impacting immune cell functioning.&nbsp; These include our findings that fungal and bacterial metabolites can alter immune cell responses, that co-culture of fungi and bacteria alter each others development as well as their interaction with host immune responses and that microscale technologies allow for characterization of molecules not easily detectable by macroscale technologies.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact. </strong>One of the strengths of our studies was that they involved interdisciplinary approaches encompassing fields of chemistry, biomedical engineering, immunology and medical microbiology. Combined, the four labs provided not only significant cross-discipline training opportunities for post-gradate, graduate and undergraduate students in all labs but also education opportunities for high school students. &nbsp;Results from our studies were presented at local, national and international meetings and published in both scientific and public oriented journals.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Nancy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Keller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ All environments are composed of a complex and shifting microbiome that communicates largely through chemical signaling.  Perhaps the most understood example involves quorum signaling systems between bacteria, and more recently fungi, yet even these systems represent but one microbial communication process.   Difficulties in fully assessing this vast communication network can be attributed to both lack of user-friendly technologies and inability to identify and characterize microbial signaling molecules.  Here we brought together expertise from four scientific disciplines &ndash; chemistry, biomedical engineering, immunology and medical microbiology - to address the poorly understood role of multicellular and inter-kingdom signaling interactions.   Intellectual Merit. This research has led to novel insights into cross-kingdom signal communication signals using our novel microscale and zebrafish platforms to identify previously unknown chemical microbial signatures impacting immune cell functioning.  These include our findings that fungal and bacterial metabolites can alter immune cell responses, that co-culture of fungi and bacteria alter each others development as well as their interaction with host immune responses and that microscale technologies allow for characterization of molecules not easily detectable by macroscale technologies.  Broader Impact. One of the strengths of our studies was that they involved interdisciplinary approaches encompassing fields of chemistry, biomedical engineering, immunology and medical microbiology. Combined, the four labs provided not only significant cross-discipline training opportunities for post-gradate, graduate and undergraduate students in all labs but also education opportunities for high school students.  Results from our studies were presented at local, national and international meetings and published in both scientific and public oriented journals.       Last Modified: 10/31/2016       Submitted by: Nancy P Keller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
