<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation Award:Secure measurement-based IP geolocation for Cloud Auditing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199755.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>238835</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Tennessee State University's Research Initiation Award entitled - Secure measurement-based IP Geolocation for Cloud Auditing - will enhance the cyber security research program at the university by investigating novel security problems in cloud auditing.  The educational goal involves the integration of cloud auditing research in select undergraduate courses. Cloud computing is one of the most enticing technologies due to its scalable, flexible, and cost-efficient access to computing resources. However, the increased concentration of business data and computing power scales security risks as well. One of the recent security concerns is attributed to the lack of sufficient transparency in the operations of the cloud provider, leading to difficulties in cloud auditing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates a critical network mapping and measurement (NMM) technique, Secure IP Geolocation, to facilitate reliable cloud auditing. The overarching goal is to develop a methodology based on machine learning that will determine the geolocations of the cloud nodes containing user data with higher reliability, robustness and sensitivity than the current state-of-the art measurement-based IP geolocation techniques. Three separate but synergistic research goals are proposed: 1) develop a machine learning based approach to estimate the hop distances between arbitrary host pairs in complex network topologies that is accurate, scalable, timely, and does not require a significant measurement infrastructure;  2) develop a single node classifier using delay measurements and hop distances based on machine learning to detect forged latency results by adversarial clients in a cloud network; and  3) develop a fusion classifier which is scalable and independent of the network latency levels by training to pool latency and hop count data from multiple target nodes, allowing sufficient number of training examples at any latency level.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1137466</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sachin</FirstName>
<LastName>Shetty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sachin Shetty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sshetty@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6152431453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502750</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tennessee State University</Name>
<CityName>nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372091561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6159637631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3500 John A. Merritt Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>108814179</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TENNESSEE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>878135631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tennessee State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372091561</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3500 John A. Merritt Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~199755</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~39080</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The RIA has made a significant impact on the cloud security research efforts at Tennessee State University (TSU). To the best of our knowledge, the team presented the first security risk comparison for commercial cloud providers at ACM CCGRID 2013. The project team has published research results in &nbsp;over 25 conference, journals, workshop proceedings and one book. The RIA has helped the PI develop research capability in the area of cloud security at TSU. The award has helped establish the PI as an expert in the area of cloud system and mobile security. The award has also helped enhance the research expertise of &nbsp;undergraduate students in cyber security.</p> <p>The students have won awards at university's research symposium, Tennessee Board of Regents Academy of Science meetings and NSF Emerging Research Network conference. Air Force Research Laboratory (AFRL) at Rome, NY was the collaborator and during the project lifetime, PI and six undergraduate students interned at AFRL during Summer 2011-Summer 2013. The summer internship and visiting faculty research experience has been incredibly valuable for the PI and the students. The PI and students were exposed to several cyber security research and development initiatives at AFRL. These experiences were instrumental in enhancing the quality of the research projects.&nbsp;</p> <p>The research results have been integrated in undergraduate courses in computer networking, network security, distributed systems and computer architeture and operating systems. The project has also helped establish TSU's first cloud data center for cyber security research and education. Laboratory experiments utilizing the cloud data center resources have been incorporated in the undergraduate courses. The RIA research results have been instrumental in the PI securing external funds from DHS, DOD, DOE, and Boeing. TSU is a partnering member in three centers of excellence funded by DOD, DHS and DOE.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2015<br>      Modified by: Sachin&nbsp;Shetty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1137466/1137466_10118882_1443360759550_IMG_9250--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1137466/1137466_10118882_1443360759550_IMG_9250--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CybersecurityResearchTeam"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1137466/1137466_10118882_1443360759550_IMG_9250--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CybersecurityResearchTeam"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tennessee State University's Cyber Security Research Team</div> <div class="imageCredit">TSU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sachin&nbsp;Shetty</div> <div class="imageTitle">CybersecurityResearchTeam</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The RIA has made a significant impact on the cloud security research efforts at Tennessee State University (TSU). To the best of our knowledge, the team presented the first security risk comparison for commercial cloud providers at ACM CCGRID 2013. The project team has published research results in  over 25 conference, journals, workshop proceedings and one book. The RIA has helped the PI develop research capability in the area of cloud security at TSU. The award has helped establish the PI as an expert in the area of cloud system and mobile security. The award has also helped enhance the research expertise of  undergraduate students in cyber security.  The students have won awards at university's research symposium, Tennessee Board of Regents Academy of Science meetings and NSF Emerging Research Network conference. Air Force Research Laboratory (AFRL) at Rome, NY was the collaborator and during the project lifetime, PI and six undergraduate students interned at AFRL during Summer 2011-Summer 2013. The summer internship and visiting faculty research experience has been incredibly valuable for the PI and the students. The PI and students were exposed to several cyber security research and development initiatives at AFRL. These experiences were instrumental in enhancing the quality of the research projects.   The research results have been integrated in undergraduate courses in computer networking, network security, distributed systems and computer architeture and operating systems. The project has also helped establish TSU's first cloud data center for cyber security research and education. Laboratory experiments utilizing the cloud data center resources have been incorporated in the undergraduate courses. The RIA research results have been instrumental in the PI securing external funds from DHS, DOD, DOE, and Boeing. TSU is a partnering member in three centers of excellence funded by DOD, DHS and DOE.             Last Modified: 09/27/2015       Submitted by: Sachin Shetty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
