<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion: Enhancing Undergraduate Programs in Environmental Science and Sustainability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298421.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298421</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of the District of Columbia (UDC) will conduct a Targeted Infusion Project entitled - Enhancing Undergraduate Programs in Environmental Science and Sustainability. This project will enable UDC to improve the quality and scope of the undergraduate environmental sciences and sustainability programs. In this project, three comprehensive core strategies that include seven project activities will be developed and implemented.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first strategy includes updating the undergraduate curriculum and course contents by creating and integrating new modules, by enabling interactive online course for mobile delivery, and by including data mining and infusing sustainability into all courses. The second strategy focuses on the development of a hands-on multidisciplinary summer-bridge program designed for high school students in Washington DC to boost their interest and to increase enrollment in UDC's undergraduate programs in environmental science and engineering. The third strategy is to develop two team-oriented experiential and problem-based learning multidisciplinary courses - sustainability and urban water quality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ultimate goal is to increase the participation of underrepresented minority students in undergraduate STEM education, especially in the environmental sciences and sustainability programs. The short term goals of this project include: increased program quality by incorporating lab and field experiments, increased enrollment and retention in the undergraduate environmental sciences programs, and preparation of students for graduate school and the workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1137529</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lily</FirstName>
<LastName>Liang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lily R Liang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>LLiang@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022745086</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494451</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pradeep</FirstName>
<LastName>Behera</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pradeep K Behera</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbehera@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022746186</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000495113</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suzan</FirstName>
<LastName>Harkness</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suzan Harkness</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sharkness@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022745072</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tolessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Deksissa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tolessa Deksissa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tdeksissa@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022745273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546503</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of the District of Columbia</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200081122</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2022746260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4200 Connecticut Ave NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038994133</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>137460275</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of the District of Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200081122</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4200 Connecticut Ave. NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~298421</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A competitive global economy depends on workers with science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) skills. &nbsp;The Environmental sciences and sustainability program at the University of the District of Columbia (UDC) is part of the STEM education that is keen to build STEM skills such as systems thinking and problem solving. &nbsp;The previous curriculum of the program was unable to meet this goal and ineffective in attracting and preparing underrepresented minority students. &nbsp;Thus, it was necessary to update the program content and education experience to attract and prepare senior high school students and incoming freshmen in STEM.</p> <p>In this work, we revised the curriculum and introduced three innovative undergraduate courses. &nbsp;The 1<sup>st</sup> course was a hands-on and team-taught interdisciplinary summer bridge course in environment and sustainability. &nbsp;The main objective of this course was to attract and prepare underrepresented minority students in STEM programs based on an inquiry and problem solving approach. &nbsp;This innovative approach includes the scientific method, engineering design, mobile technology, cloud computing, and a capstone group project with laboratory and field studies. &nbsp;Based on three years of data, the average perceived student learning goals in application of sciences and technology was improved by 20%. &nbsp;Ninety percent of the students have expressed interest in majoring STEM programs. &nbsp;This demonstrates that engaging students with the diverse learning activities integrated with advanced sciences and technologies helps students demonstrate excellency in systems thinking and problem solving skills.&nbsp;</p> <p>The second course was designed to infuse environmental sciences and sustainability concepts across the curriculum. &nbsp;On this team taught course, environmental studies and sustainability concepts were integrated with the liberal education course, such as discovery civic. . Our research finding showed that integration of sustainability concept with the discovery civic course significantly improved students&rsquo; systems thinking and problem solving skills. &nbsp;Based on pre and post survey questions, the result shows that students system thinking and problem solving skill improved by about 80%. &nbsp;The sustainability concept improved holistic system thinking of students and their ability to make connections, whereas learning the concept of civic engagement encouraged students to apply their knowledge towards sustainable solutions. &nbsp;We also developed a module to infuse sustainability concept in civil engineering courses. &nbsp;Thus, infusing sustainability concept across curriculum can enhance students systems thinking and problem solving skills.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The third course was designed to prepare students in data analysis and interpretation to manage urban water quality. &nbsp;About 87% of students demonstrated good analytical skills. &nbsp;By integrating laboratory experiences with data mining techniques, this course has enhanced student&rsquo;s ability to analyze large data. &nbsp;The course improved student&rsquo;s ability to apply data mining by 67% in describing complex integrated urban wastewater subsystem interactions. &nbsp;The course also helped students the ability to apply best management practices in addressing urban stormwater management issues. Integration of data mining with the water quality course was innovative and has enhanced the ability of students to analyze large data and create new knowledge to analyze problems.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also reviewed and updated the course sequence environmental science and sustainability program and developed a new curriculum map. &nbsp;This updated curriculum improved students learning experience. Students who participated in the project activities of the updated curriculum expressed interest to pursue their graduate s...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A competitive global economy depends on workers with science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) skills.  The Environmental sciences and sustainability program at the University of the District of Columbia (UDC) is part of the STEM education that is keen to build STEM skills such as systems thinking and problem solving.  The previous curriculum of the program was unable to meet this goal and ineffective in attracting and preparing underrepresented minority students.  Thus, it was necessary to update the program content and education experience to attract and prepare senior high school students and incoming freshmen in STEM.  In this work, we revised the curriculum and introduced three innovative undergraduate courses.  The 1st course was a hands-on and team-taught interdisciplinary summer bridge course in environment and sustainability.  The main objective of this course was to attract and prepare underrepresented minority students in STEM programs based on an inquiry and problem solving approach.  This innovative approach includes the scientific method, engineering design, mobile technology, cloud computing, and a capstone group project with laboratory and field studies.  Based on three years of data, the average perceived student learning goals in application of sciences and technology was improved by 20%.  Ninety percent of the students have expressed interest in majoring STEM programs.  This demonstrates that engaging students with the diverse learning activities integrated with advanced sciences and technologies helps students demonstrate excellency in systems thinking and problem solving skills.   The second course was designed to infuse environmental sciences and sustainability concepts across the curriculum.  On this team taught course, environmental studies and sustainability concepts were integrated with the liberal education course, such as discovery civic. . Our research finding showed that integration of sustainability concept with the discovery civic course significantly improved studentsÆ systems thinking and problem solving skills.  Based on pre and post survey questions, the result shows that students system thinking and problem solving skill improved by about 80%.  The sustainability concept improved holistic system thinking of students and their ability to make connections, whereas learning the concept of civic engagement encouraged students to apply their knowledge towards sustainable solutions.  We also developed a module to infuse sustainability concept in civil engineering courses.  Thus, infusing sustainability concept across curriculum can enhance students systems thinking and problem solving skills.     The third course was designed to prepare students in data analysis and interpretation to manage urban water quality.  About 87% of students demonstrated good analytical skills.  By integrating laboratory experiences with data mining techniques, this course has enhanced studentÆs ability to analyze large data.  The course improved studentÆs ability to apply data mining by 67% in describing complex integrated urban wastewater subsystem interactions.  The course also helped students the ability to apply best management practices in addressing urban stormwater management issues. Integration of data mining with the water quality course was innovative and has enhanced the ability of students to analyze large data and create new knowledge to analyze problems.   We also reviewed and updated the course sequence environmental science and sustainability program and developed a new curriculum map.  This updated curriculum improved students learning experience. Students who participated in the project activities of the updated curriculum expressed interest to pursue their graduate study in STEM fields, such as the existing Professional Science MasterÆs program in water resources management at UDC.  Currently, five students have joined the PSM program.     Furthermore, several graduate and undergraduate studen...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
