<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Reducing Uncertainty in Heterotrophic Respiration: Linking Continental Experiments, Analytical Modeling, and Shared Data Sets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>82506.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>85006</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Blood</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eblood@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924349</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Determining the terrestrial carbon balance (how much carbon a landscape is gaining or losing) requires correctly estimating the difference between inputs and outputs.  Scientific knowledge of the output side is relatively weak, however; in particular,  the limited understanding of what is termed heterotrophic respiration (RH), the carbon respired by microbes from soil and decaying organic material, limits our predictive ability. This raises an unsettling question, one that is the focus, and underlying intellectual merit, of this exploratory project: can continental-scale carbon be balanced if the underlying science understanding is unbalanced? To address this problem, funds are provided to host a community assessment on understanding, constraining, and predicting large-scale RH carbon fluxes, bringing together scientists with a wide range of specialties, nationalities, and expertise. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will benefit from, and take advantage of, a number of converging trends in carbon cycle science: innovative new continental-scale experiments; the sophistication of analytical methods linking individual measurements with continental- to global-scale analyses; and the increasing use of tools to collaborate, document, and analyze shared data sets. To maximize the impact of this workshop, the Awardee will live-stream the proceedings online; post all presentations; write a white paper that outlines the major limitations to understanding continental-scale RH, and offers possible solutions; develop manuscript(s) that address workshop topics, focusing on implications for large-scale science; hold follow-up sessions at national meetings; and encourage participants to use this as a springboard in advancing fundamental scientific research in Macrosystems Biology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1137178</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Harmon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark E Harmon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Mark.Harmon@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417378455</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000098258</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Bond-Lamberty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Bond-Lamberty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bondlamberty@pnnl.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5093717608</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000521371</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rodrigo</FirstName>
<LastName>Vargas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rodrigo Vargas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rvargas@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028311386</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000590435</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973312140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~85006</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examined the current status of research on heterotrophic respiration, the process by which organic matter is broken down into its parts (such as carbon dioxide) and developed a community perspective on how this science can be advanced in the future.&nbsp; Two workshops&nbsp;involving invited scientists were held and&nbsp;draft&nbsp;manuscripts describing the conclusions were developed.&nbsp; In addition a workshop report was created.&nbsp;</p> <p>The manuscripts consider four areas that the future science of heterotrophic repiration should examine:</p> <p>1. This process is highly variable in space and new breakthroughs are most likely when this is acknowledged and used to gain insights. This is in contrast to the current practice of averaging and homogenizing which is likely to hide as much as it reveals.</p> <p>2. The models needed to predict this process will vary in terms of their detail and extent they are used (very local to the globe). A better way needs to be found to link these models so they are compariable and support each other. One proposed mechanism is to agree upon the processes that are to be included in all heterotrophic respiration models and to find suitable ways to either expand or collapse them depending on the models objectives.</p> <p>3. While heterotrophic respiration is often viewed as only the release of carbon dioxide, this limited view misses many important relationships to other forms of respiration that produce methane, the relationship to mineral nutrients being released by this process, and the subsequent uptake of these elements in new growth.&nbsp; It is therefore important for ecological scientists to expand their perspectives if ecosystem behavior is to be understood and predicted.</p> <p>4. Currently there&nbsp;is no functional classification to predict heterotrophic respiration rates, behaviors, or controls.&nbsp; This is in contrast to other aspects of ecology, which have plant and ecosystem functional types. To aid in the creation of new experiments, observations, and modeling related to heterotrophic respiration, it would very helpful for scientists to develop a&nbsp;Decomposition Functional Type that would characterize differences in the efficiency of breaking down organic matter, the dominant organisms responsible for this process, the types of organic matter being broken down, the end product of the breakdown process (carbon dioxide versus methane) and the way these systems respond to changes in the environment.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/20/2015<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;E&nbsp;Harmon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examined the current status of research on heterotrophic respiration, the process by which organic matter is broken down into its parts (such as carbon dioxide) and developed a community perspective on how this science can be advanced in the future.  Two workshops involving invited scientists were held and draft manuscripts describing the conclusions were developed.  In addition a workshop report was created.   The manuscripts consider four areas that the future science of heterotrophic repiration should examine:  1. This process is highly variable in space and new breakthroughs are most likely when this is acknowledged and used to gain insights. This is in contrast to the current practice of averaging and homogenizing which is likely to hide as much as it reveals.  2. The models needed to predict this process will vary in terms of their detail and extent they are used (very local to the globe). A better way needs to be found to link these models so they are compariable and support each other. One proposed mechanism is to agree upon the processes that are to be included in all heterotrophic respiration models and to find suitable ways to either expand or collapse them depending on the models objectives.  3. While heterotrophic respiration is often viewed as only the release of carbon dioxide, this limited view misses many important relationships to other forms of respiration that produce methane, the relationship to mineral nutrients being released by this process, and the subsequent uptake of these elements in new growth.  It is therefore important for ecological scientists to expand their perspectives if ecosystem behavior is to be understood and predicted.  4. Currently there is no functional classification to predict heterotrophic respiration rates, behaviors, or controls.  This is in contrast to other aspects of ecology, which have plant and ecosystem functional types. To aid in the creation of new experiments, observations, and modeling related to heterotrophic respiration, it would very helpful for scientists to develop a Decomposition Functional Type that would characterize differences in the efficiency of breaking down organic matter, the dominant organisms responsible for this process, the types of organic matter being broken down, the end product of the breakdown process (carbon dioxide versus methane) and the way these systems respond to changes in the environment.                 Last Modified: 09/20/2015       Submitted by: Mark E Harmon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
