<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building Excellence and Access through Research (BEAR)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1748712.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1748712</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cheyney Universitys implementation project entitled - Building Excellence and Access through Research (BEAR) - has the goal to increase the recruitment, retention, and graduation of Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) students, as well as increase their admission rate to STEM graduate programs or to the STEM workforce. This goal will be attained through three interrelated activities: curriculum development and instrumentation, faculty development, and student development.  The project is based on the lessons learned from the previous HBCU-UP implementation project, interventions and strategies adapted from best practices described in the literature, formative and outcome-based evaluation results, and the overall mission and priorities of the University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The expected project outcomes include: increased STEM student graduation rates; increased use of technology in teaching and research by STEM faculty; strengthened relationships and partnerships with other academic institutions and industry partners; increased faculty participation in research, grant writing and other scholarly activities; enhanced quality of undergraduate research experiences; and increased numbers of students going to graduate school.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1137523</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adedoyin</FirstName>
<LastName>Adeyiga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adedoyin M Adeyiga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aadeyiga@cheyney.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6103992531</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241821</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Banks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan Banks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ivan.Banks@cheyney.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2153992000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000561235</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cheyney University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Cheyney</CityName>
<ZipCode>193190000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2153992282</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Cheyney &amp; Creek Roads</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>103802310</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHEYNEY UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003027539</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cheyney University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Cheyney</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>193190200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1837 University Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~659428</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~358164</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~362418</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~368702</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Curriculum Core Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The computer science program has been recently revised to provide the following tracks: Human Computer Interactions, Cyber Security, and Computer Information Systems.&nbsp; This has added more options to our computer science program.&nbsp; Although, overall institutional enrollment has declined significantly in the last two years due to reduced state funding, overall STEM enrollment has doubled the last four years.&nbsp; This fall semester, Cheyney University welcomed its largest freshman class (&gt;250 students) in over five years, with significant gain in Biology and Computer Science.</p> <p>Newly developed and approved courses includes, Nursing Chemistry (SCH 205), Online Nursing Chemistry, and Online General Chemistry I and II (SCH 111 and 112).&nbsp; We anticipate that Organic Chemistry, some basic Math courses and General Biology I and II&nbsp;online courses will follow soon.</p> <p>We also approved an Advanced Spectroscopy course (SCH 460) and a Forensic Chemistry course (SCH 470) that is pending university approval.&nbsp; Both courses are designed to introduce students to emerging science areas that will give students more options, should they decide to enter the STEM workforce in these areas.&nbsp; The courses are also designed to provide basic introduction to these areas, should students decide to embark in graduate studies.</p> <p>We developed a state-of-the-art library with brand new computers, equipped with STEM software to accommodate STEM students&rsquo; needs and also&nbsp;help with instruction.</p> <p>We hired several students as peer tutors and also hired a professional tutor to help struggling students and increase persistent rates.&nbsp; The professional tutor worked with students after hour to accommodate students whose course loads prohibits them from seeking tutoring during the day.</p> <p>We incorporated the use of technology into gatekeeper courses, especially, General Chemistry, General Physics, General Biology and Pre-Calculus.&nbsp; Students are able to do inquiry based experiments in&nbsp;General and Organic Chemistry courses&nbsp;with Vernier products;&nbsp;efforts that we hope to continue with additional funding and spread to other science courses. Math students use ALEKS, which has helped tremendously with students struggling with basic and introductory math courses.</p> <p>We incorporated online homework modules through Sapling Learning, Webassign and MasteringChemistry and Physics.&nbsp; Through this effort, we hope to reduce failure and attrition rates in these gatekeeper courses.&nbsp; All the aforementioned modules blended well with our Desire-2-Learn (D2L) course management system.</p> <p><strong>Student Core</strong></p> <p>The NSF BEAR project participated in the three open house events held by the institution (March 2017, May 2017 and July 2017) to recruit potential scholars for the program and also increase our overall enrollment for the STEM areas.&nbsp; Dr. Frank Pogue (Interim President of Cheyney University) renewed our articulation agreement with Community College of Philadelphia (CCP) in February 2016 to help increase enrollment.&nbsp; The effort paid dividend with over 250 students matriculating this fall.</p> <p>Recruitment into the NSF Scholar&rsquo;s program ended last fall due to project&rsquo;s end date of August 31, 2017.</p> <p>The NSF BEAR program held its annual Research Day on December 3, 2016.&nbsp; The program brought together all students who participated in summer research programs to present their work.&nbsp; There were over 50 participants and 16 presenters.&nbsp; The event (held yearly) has been a confidence booster for students prior to attending local and national conferences.</p> <p>The NSF BEAR program held a total 8 seminars,&nbsp;sponsored by the department.&nbsp; The event brought to campus scientists and recruiters, and served as means to introducing students and faculty to current research topics and vital networking with potential graduate recruiters.</p> <p>In all, five (5) students conducted summer research on campus and fourteen (14) received external paid summer research internships this past year.&nbsp; Also, Cheyney students attended and presented at various conferences, including but not limited to the Undergraduate Research Day at the Capitol in Harrisburg, PA (April 6, 2017), 17th Annual AMP conference in Philadelphia (October 15, 2016), and the Annual Day of Research Discovery 2017 at Drexel University (May 4, 2017)</p> <p>In addition, several Cheyney seniors took advantage of the GRE and MCAT preparation courses, offered free of charge by our Keystone Honors Academy.&nbsp; The aforementioned student- engagement activities resulted in six (6) of our May 2017 graduates heading to graduate school,&nbsp;four (4) heading to health professional school and two (2) securing employment and entering the STEM workforce.</p> <p><strong>Faculty Core</strong></p> <p>This past year, Cheyney's STEM faculty attended a total of twelve (12) seminars and workshops, presented two (2) research papers at conferences and received two (2) additional funding from five (5) submissions to various agencies</p> <p>Funding from all sources aforementioned (Keystone, CUCCIES, LSAMP, Rural PA and HBCU-UP) provided necessary support for both faculty and students.&nbsp; Through aforementioned collaborations, one (1) STEM faculty worked off campus with four (4) students this summer at Brookhaven National Laboratory.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2017<br>      Modified by: Adedoyin&nbsp;M&nbsp;Adeyiga</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Curriculum Core Outcomes  The computer science program has been recently revised to provide the following tracks: Human Computer Interactions, Cyber Security, and Computer Information Systems.  This has added more options to our computer science program.  Although, overall institutional enrollment has declined significantly in the last two years due to reduced state funding, overall STEM enrollment has doubled the last four years.  This fall semester, Cheyney University welcomed its largest freshman class (&gt;250 students) in over five years, with significant gain in Biology and Computer Science.  Newly developed and approved courses includes, Nursing Chemistry (SCH 205), Online Nursing Chemistry, and Online General Chemistry I and II (SCH 111 and 112).  We anticipate that Organic Chemistry, some basic Math courses and General Biology I and II online courses will follow soon.  We also approved an Advanced Spectroscopy course (SCH 460) and a Forensic Chemistry course (SCH 470) that is pending university approval.  Both courses are designed to introduce students to emerging science areas that will give students more options, should they decide to enter the STEM workforce in these areas.  The courses are also designed to provide basic introduction to these areas, should students decide to embark in graduate studies.  We developed a state-of-the-art library with brand new computers, equipped with STEM software to accommodate STEM students? needs and also help with instruction.  We hired several students as peer tutors and also hired a professional tutor to help struggling students and increase persistent rates.  The professional tutor worked with students after hour to accommodate students whose course loads prohibits them from seeking tutoring during the day.  We incorporated the use of technology into gatekeeper courses, especially, General Chemistry, General Physics, General Biology and Pre-Calculus.  Students are able to do inquiry based experiments in General and Organic Chemistry courses with Vernier products; efforts that we hope to continue with additional funding and spread to other science courses. Math students use ALEKS, which has helped tremendously with students struggling with basic and introductory math courses.  We incorporated online homework modules through Sapling Learning, Webassign and MasteringChemistry and Physics.  Through this effort, we hope to reduce failure and attrition rates in these gatekeeper courses.  All the aforementioned modules blended well with our Desire-2-Learn (D2L) course management system.  Student Core  The NSF BEAR project participated in the three open house events held by the institution (March 2017, May 2017 and July 2017) to recruit potential scholars for the program and also increase our overall enrollment for the STEM areas.  Dr. Frank Pogue (Interim President of Cheyney University) renewed our articulation agreement with Community College of Philadelphia (CCP) in February 2016 to help increase enrollment.  The effort paid dividend with over 250 students matriculating this fall.  Recruitment into the NSF Scholar?s program ended last fall due to project?s end date of August 31, 2017.  The NSF BEAR program held its annual Research Day on December 3, 2016.  The program brought together all students who participated in summer research programs to present their work.  There were over 50 participants and 16 presenters.  The event (held yearly) has been a confidence booster for students prior to attending local and national conferences.  The NSF BEAR program held a total 8 seminars, sponsored by the department.  The event brought to campus scientists and recruiters, and served as means to introducing students and faculty to current research topics and vital networking with potential graduate recruiters.  In all, five (5) students conducted summer research on campus and fourteen (14) received external paid summer research internships this past year.  Also, Cheyney students attended and presented at various conferences, including but not limited to the Undergraduate Research Day at the Capitol in Harrisburg, PA (April 6, 2017), 17th Annual AMP conference in Philadelphia (October 15, 2016), and the Annual Day of Research Discovery 2017 at Drexel University (May 4, 2017)  In addition, several Cheyney seniors took advantage of the GRE and MCAT preparation courses, offered free of charge by our Keystone Honors Academy.  The aforementioned student- engagement activities resulted in six (6) of our May 2017 graduates heading to graduate school, four (4) heading to health professional school and two (2) securing employment and entering the STEM workforce.  Faculty Core  This past year, Cheyney's STEM faculty attended a total of twelve (12) seminars and workshops, presented two (2) research papers at conferences and received two (2) additional funding from five (5) submissions to various agencies  Funding from all sources aforementioned (Keystone, CUCCIES, LSAMP, Rural PA and HBCU-UP) provided necessary support for both faculty and students.  Through aforementioned collaborations, one (1) STEM faculty worked off campus with four (4) students this summer at Brookhaven National Laboratory.             Last Modified: 09/23/2017       Submitted by: Adedoyin M Adeyiga]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
