<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NUE: Nanotechnology EXposure for Undergraduate Students (NANO-NEXUS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Nanotechnology Undergraduate Education (NUE) in Engineering program entitled, "NUE: Nanotechnology EXposure for Undergraduate Students (NUE-NEXUS)", at Stevens Institute of Technology under the direction of Dr. Eui-Hyeok Yang, seeks to create a nexus between nanotechnology and undergraduate engineering education at Stevens to expand understanding of nanotechnology and its applications to a broad undergraduate engineering student population. In this program, two new nanotechnology courses, NANO 300: Introduction to Nanoscale Science and Engineering and NANO 325: Introduction to Nanofabrication and Characterization, will provide a means to educate a broad student population in nanotechnology. The new courses are dual-purpose, educating the broader engineering student population in nanoscience and nanotechnology while serving as the foundation for those undergraduate students choosing to pursue the undergraduate nanotechnology research track. Since the research track will serve to increase the pipeline of students aiming for graduate programs, documented success will provide a replicable paradigm for others looking to promote undergraduate research as a foundation for future graduate studies.  Integrated within the proposed program are dissemination of nanotechnology educational materials to benefit the engineering education community interested in incorporating nanotechnology into engineering curricula and in bringing appropriate, engaging nanotechnology materials and modular elements to K-12 and community college domains. These proposed elements extend the efforts of the existing interdisciplinary Nanotechnology Graduate Program to the undergraduate level, and are tightly aligned with Stevens' institutional vision of creating a world-class research and education thrust in nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1138244</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheppard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith G Sheppard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ksheppar@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012165260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000202413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Besser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ronald S Besser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rbesser@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012165257</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449337</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Fisher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank T Fisher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ffisher@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012168913</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000205059</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eui-Hyeok</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eui-Hyeok Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eui-hyeok.yang@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012165574</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000071689</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chang-Hwan</FirstName>
<LastName>Choi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chang-Hwan Choi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cchoi@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012165579</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000073797</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stevens Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>HOBOKEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2012168762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CASTLE POINT ON HUDSON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064271570</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>STEVENS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064271570</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stevens Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Hoboken</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7219</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY UNDERGRAD EDUCA</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>113E</Code>
<Text>ENG CURRICULUMN DEVELOPMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7219</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY UNDERGRAD EDUCA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>While developing countries such as India and China are producing unprecedented numbers of engineers and scientists, US undergraduate enrollment in engineering continues to decline at an alarming rate, and there is increasing concern that there may be insufficient number of students in the engineering pipeline to support the workforce of tomorrow. At the same time, the last decade has witnessed phenomenal growth and research investment in nanotechnology, which appears poised to provide the growth engine for technology development for decades to come. Together these conditions indicate a significant demand for scientists and engineers prepared with the nanotechnology literacy necessary to drive innovations across many diverse technology sectors in order to maintain the leadership position of the United States in these fields.</p> <p>We therefore developed a program to introduce nanotechnology to a broad undergraduate engineering student population through two new courses. These two new courses introduce contemporary themes of nanotechnology within the undergraduate engineering curriculum:</p> <p><em>NANO 200: Introduction to Nanoscale Science and Engineering</em> is designed to be a sophomore-level class that fulfills an open Science Elective. The course introduces sophomore-level undergraduate students to the fundamental principles behind nanotechnology and nanomaterials, as well as to applications of nanotechnology. The role of solid state physics and chemistry in nanotech is emphasized. Principles of nanoscale tools such as surface probe and atomic force microscopy, nanolithography, and special topics such as molecular electronics are also covered. By the end of the course, students understand the principles of the fabrication, characterization and manipulation of nanoscale materials, systems, and devices and how they can be exploited for new applications. The main focus of the course is to understand the fundamental challenges and limitations involved in designing and demonstrating micro and nano devices and systems. Core courses such as Chemistry 1 and Physics 1 in the standard undergraduate engineering curriculum are prerequisites for this course. While the primary audience is sophomore-level students who wish to use the course as a Science Elective, undergraduate science and engineering students may also enroll in the course later in their studies to satisfy General Elective requirements for their respective degrees.</p> <p><em>NANO 325: Introduction to Nanodevices and Systems Fabrication and Characterization</em> is designed to be a junior-level course that would satisfy one of the three General Elective course requirements in our undergraduate engineering programs. This course provides a hands-on experience for junior-level undergraduate students in nanofabrication and characterization. It discusses the grand challenges of nanofabrication and showcases examples of specific applications of nanotechnology in electronics, photonics, chemistry, biology, medicine, defense, and energy. Building upon the material covered in the NANO 200 course, which serves as a prerequisite, NANO 325 focuses on the development of prototype devices/systems (e.g. relatively simple sensors or actuators) in order for students to understand the full sequence/spectrum of development of nanodevices and systems, e.g. from brainstorming ideas and concept design through fabrication, integration, and characterization.</p> <p>For the research-track we specifically incorporated support and mentoring mechanisms that have been proven in the literature to optimize the effectiveness of these experiences. Through these dual mechanisms we seek to promote nanotechnology literacy within our general undergraduate engineering student body while simultaneously setting the foundation for a nanotechnology-based research track that will facilitate a pipeline of students pursuing nanotechnology as a career i...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ While developing countries such as India and China are producing unprecedented numbers of engineers and scientists, US undergraduate enrollment in engineering continues to decline at an alarming rate, and there is increasing concern that there may be insufficient number of students in the engineering pipeline to support the workforce of tomorrow. At the same time, the last decade has witnessed phenomenal growth and research investment in nanotechnology, which appears poised to provide the growth engine for technology development for decades to come. Together these conditions indicate a significant demand for scientists and engineers prepared with the nanotechnology literacy necessary to drive innovations across many diverse technology sectors in order to maintain the leadership position of the United States in these fields.  We therefore developed a program to introduce nanotechnology to a broad undergraduate engineering student population through two new courses. These two new courses introduce contemporary themes of nanotechnology within the undergraduate engineering curriculum:  NANO 200: Introduction to Nanoscale Science and Engineering is designed to be a sophomore-level class that fulfills an open Science Elective. The course introduces sophomore-level undergraduate students to the fundamental principles behind nanotechnology and nanomaterials, as well as to applications of nanotechnology. The role of solid state physics and chemistry in nanotech is emphasized. Principles of nanoscale tools such as surface probe and atomic force microscopy, nanolithography, and special topics such as molecular electronics are also covered. By the end of the course, students understand the principles of the fabrication, characterization and manipulation of nanoscale materials, systems, and devices and how they can be exploited for new applications. The main focus of the course is to understand the fundamental challenges and limitations involved in designing and demonstrating micro and nano devices and systems. Core courses such as Chemistry 1 and Physics 1 in the standard undergraduate engineering curriculum are prerequisites for this course. While the primary audience is sophomore-level students who wish to use the course as a Science Elective, undergraduate science and engineering students may also enroll in the course later in their studies to satisfy General Elective requirements for their respective degrees.  NANO 325: Introduction to Nanodevices and Systems Fabrication and Characterization is designed to be a junior-level course that would satisfy one of the three General Elective course requirements in our undergraduate engineering programs. This course provides a hands-on experience for junior-level undergraduate students in nanofabrication and characterization. It discusses the grand challenges of nanofabrication and showcases examples of specific applications of nanotechnology in electronics, photonics, chemistry, biology, medicine, defense, and energy. Building upon the material covered in the NANO 200 course, which serves as a prerequisite, NANO 325 focuses on the development of prototype devices/systems (e.g. relatively simple sensors or actuators) in order for students to understand the full sequence/spectrum of development of nanodevices and systems, e.g. from brainstorming ideas and concept design through fabrication, integration, and characterization.  For the research-track we specifically incorporated support and mentoring mechanisms that have been proven in the literature to optimize the effectiveness of these experiences. Through these dual mechanisms we seek to promote nanotechnology literacy within our general undergraduate engineering student body while simultaneously setting the foundation for a nanotechnology-based research track that will facilitate a pipeline of students pursuing nanotechnology as a career including through graduate-level education.          Last Modified: 01/09/2016       Submitted by: Eui-Hy...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
