<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integrating Science Into Afterschool: A Three-Dimensional Approach To Engaging Underserved Populations In Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>993705.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>993705</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Haury</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Integrating Science into Afterschool, an ITEST Strategies project, builds upon prior NSF-funded work to develop a three-dimensional (3-D) strategy for engaging underserved youth, families, and afterschool facilitators in year-round science learning and exposure to careers in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). The project leverages community partnerships in urban Philadelphia, including The Franklin Institute, public sector entities and community organizations, to deliver the STEM education experience in the multiple access points of afterschool, home, and community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Integrating Science targets elementary aged students (grades 3-5) and their families, and aims to strategically network a diverse set of stakeholders to develop, implement, and study: 1) science project-based learning (PBL) units in community-based afterschool programs for elementary-age children, 2) thematically-linked home-based activities designed to engage family members in science explorations in the comfort of their home, and 3) family science events focused on building career linkages that will be hosted by both the community-based organizations hosting afterschool programs as well as the museum. Integrating Science into Afterschool will serve a total of 60 staff, 450 students in grades 3-5 and 450 families in urban Philadelphia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Additionally, Integrating Science will build the capacity of science educators in nontraditional learning environments, cultivate parent support for STEM, and provide a better understanding of the ways in which communities can increase awareness of and access to science learning and STEM careers. Integrating Science has the potential to sustain and expand this proof-of-concept model through existing partners regionally, statewide, and nationwide. Long-term outcomes include using this 3-D model to address important questions within the field including how afterschool programs impact children's sense of identity in science, how parents can be encouraged and supported to become advocates of science and of science career pathways for their children, and identifying ways in which underrepresented groups come to understand, value, and promote STEM content and careers. Evaluation of the project will include the use of comparison groups and valid, normed surveys to understand the impact on students, families and afterschool facilitators.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1138911</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dale</FirstName>
<LastName>McCreedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dale McCreedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmccreedy@explorethedc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6158902300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213479</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Franklin Institute Science Museum</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191031115</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2154481121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>222 North 20th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001741859</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FRANKLIN INSTITUTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Franklin Institute Science Museum]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191031194</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[222 NOrth 20th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~300535</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~341908</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~351262</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Integrating Science Into Afterschool: A Three-Dimensional Approach To Engaging Underserved Populations In Science, or STEM 3D, was&nbsp;a five year project led by The Franklin Institute. The project was created with three major goals: to (1) increase youth engagement in hands-on, inquiry based, science projects; (2) cultivate intergenerational/parental support for science learning; and (3) evaluate the effectiveness of this 3-D (afterschool, home, and community) approach in engaging children, families, afterschool facilitators, and community-based organizations in science learning and the promotion of science learning and STEM professions.</p> <p>Three cohorts of out-of-school time (OST) facilitators integrated informal, project-based, STEM activities into their programs at nearly 50 sites. Through working with OST facilitators to incorporate career exposure and exploration into STEM activities and to develop family-oriented STEM activities, Franklin Institute staff created lasting impacts on under-resourced communities across Philadelphia. A total of 1,200 children in upper elementary grades participated in these collaboratively developed activities at their afterschool and summer camp sites, and dozens more led activities for other students and families though Philadelphia Science Festival events.</p> <p>The STEM 3D initiative was framed by the argument that the integration of STEM learning across three dimensions (afterschool, home, and community) is essential to build positive science identities and create viable STEM pathways for Philadelphia children who would otherwise be disconnected from the city&rsquo;s STEM-rich institutions and opportunities. The successes of this initiative indicate the value of an approach that crosses over various dimensions of children&rsquo;s lives.&nbsp; Students who participated in STEM 3D reported feeling significantly more interested in science as a result of their time in the program. Adult facilitators who participated in STEM 3D professional development reported a change in their approach to leading activities, using an open-ended, collaborative problem solving approach instead of a more didactic technique. These participants also noticed an increase in the depth and breath of their STEM content knowledge.</p> <p>The STEM 3D initiative demonstrates that crisscrossing the boundaries of informal learning sites can be highly productive, but it is not a straightforward process for adults positioned in different roles. Within STEM 3D, new approaches to museum-OST relationships were created, as were new approaches to OST-family relationships.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Dale&nbsp;Mccreedy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Integrating Science Into Afterschool: A Three-Dimensional Approach To Engaging Underserved Populations In Science, or STEM 3D, was a five year project led by The Franklin Institute. The project was created with three major goals: to (1) increase youth engagement in hands-on, inquiry based, science projects; (2) cultivate intergenerational/parental support for science learning; and (3) evaluate the effectiveness of this 3-D (afterschool, home, and community) approach in engaging children, families, afterschool facilitators, and community-based organizations in science learning and the promotion of science learning and STEM professions.  Three cohorts of out-of-school time (OST) facilitators integrated informal, project-based, STEM activities into their programs at nearly 50 sites. Through working with OST facilitators to incorporate career exposure and exploration into STEM activities and to develop family-oriented STEM activities, Franklin Institute staff created lasting impacts on under-resourced communities across Philadelphia. A total of 1,200 children in upper elementary grades participated in these collaboratively developed activities at their afterschool and summer camp sites, and dozens more led activities for other students and families though Philadelphia Science Festival events.  The STEM 3D initiative was framed by the argument that the integration of STEM learning across three dimensions (afterschool, home, and community) is essential to build positive science identities and create viable STEM pathways for Philadelphia children who would otherwise be disconnected from the city?s STEM-rich institutions and opportunities. The successes of this initiative indicate the value of an approach that crosses over various dimensions of children?s lives.  Students who participated in STEM 3D reported feeling significantly more interested in science as a result of their time in the program. Adult facilitators who participated in STEM 3D professional development reported a change in their approach to leading activities, using an open-ended, collaborative problem solving approach instead of a more didactic technique. These participants also noticed an increase in the depth and breath of their STEM content knowledge.  The STEM 3D initiative demonstrates that crisscrossing the boundaries of informal learning sites can be highly productive, but it is not a straightforward process for adults positioned in different roles. Within STEM 3D, new approaches to museum-OST relationships were created, as were new approaches to OST-family relationships.          Last Modified: 09/28/2017       Submitted by: Dale Mccreedy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
