<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Timing, Extent, and Spatial Progression of Neogene Displacement Transfer, Southern Walker Lane, Western Great Basin</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>145926.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>145926</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030103</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Fountain</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Northwesterly displacement of the Sierra Nevada with respect to the Great Basin in the western US Cordillera has been ongoing for the last 12 to 15 Ma.  This motion is accommodated by a complicated and incompletely understood belt of deformation along the western margin of the Great Basin that links major, misaligned strike-slip faults in eastern California and western Nevada.  Based on previous research and our preliminary work, we have identified that the deformed belt underlies a region of nearly 15,000 km2 and contains large tectonic blocks that both translate toward the northwest as the crust is pulled apart and also undergo vertical-axis rotations of 20° to 90°.  In this project, we will provide a better understanding of the dimensions of the tectonic blocks, how far they have moved laterally, to what degree they experienced vertical-axis rotation, and the spatial-temporal pattern of deformation.  Much of the western borderland of North America and many parts of other continents around the world reside in similar tectonic settings and record comparable histories of deformation.  This study will provide the opportunity to better understand how and to what degree the translation and rotation of large crustal blocks is accommodated as the continental crust is fragmented in response to the relative movement of lithospheric plates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Crustal response to displacement transfer in structural stepovers linking misaligned segments of large-magnitude transcurrent faults is accommodated by components of translational and rotational displacement and strain and results in complex three-dimensional arrays of structures.  The mechanisms by which rotational and translational strain are accommodated either by rigid-blocks and/or by distributed strain and to what degree the translational and rotational processes are coupled in space-time are poorly understood.  In this study, we integrate detailed and regional geologic mapping with thermochronologic, structural, and paleomagnetic analysis to unravel the history of transcurrent structures separating the Sierra Nevada and central Great Basin.  The objective of the work is to characterize transcurrent and high-angle normal fault displacement, estimate slip on low-angle detachment faults, and assess the relation between translational deformation and differential rotation.  Our research results will provide the needed detailed understanding of the spatial and temporal pattern of deformation and supply the constraints to differentiate between coeval and serial translational and rotational deformation histories within the stepover system and provide the means to assess whether or to what degree rotation is accommodated by rigid-body motion or distributed strain processes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1139177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Geissman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John W Geissman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>geissman@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052649319</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 W. Campbell Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~145926</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was a collaborative effort that involved field geologic mapping, investigation of important structural features (i.e. faults), numerical age determinations of key volcanic deposits, studies of the magnetic remanence (paleomagnetism) of key volcanic deposits, gravitational field studies to determine basin geometry, and studies of the low temperature cooling history of selected rocks to better understand the tectonic evolution of the west-central Great Basin.&nbsp; &nbsp;Notably, the western part of the Great Basin, east of the Sierra Nevada, presently is a diffuse zone of overall weakness in western North America, where some 20 to 25 percent of the general interaction between the Pacific Ocean tectonic plate and the North American tectonic plate is being accommodated.&nbsp;&nbsp; A growing number of studies have concluded that this diffuse zone of deformation between the two plates has evolved quickly over the past ~20 million years (time interval referred to as the Neogene), and that the style of deformation has changed considerably over this time interval.&nbsp; Because the region has strong seismic risk potential and has been the general site of young volcanism of different styles (e.g., Mammoth Lakes area), determining a more complete Neogene history of the area is warranted.&nbsp;&nbsp; The area is characterized by two major right-lateral sense fault systems (the Furnace Creek/Fish Lake Valley and the Central Walker Lane) that parallel the eastern margin of the Sierra Nevada and are offset (to the east) by some 50+ kilometers at the southern end of the Walker Lane.&nbsp; We hypothesized that displacement transfer between the fault systems was accommodated by low-angle normal (detachment) faults dipping to the northwest, vertical axis rotation of generally a clockwise sense (as determined by paleomagnetic data), and by motion along a complex array of younger high-angle faults. &nbsp;Our work demonstrates that a major detachment system, likely responsible for the initiation of the regionally extensive displacement transfer system, underlies exposures of Proterozoic, Paleozoic, Mesozoic, and Neogene sedimentary, plutonic, and volcanic rocks in the Gold Mountain area of the southern Walker Lane.&nbsp; This informally named Gold Mountain detachment is considered to be the breakaway part of a regionally extensive structure that stretches north over 80 km to exposure of the low-angle structure in the Silver Peak &ndash; Lone Mountain area.&nbsp; &nbsp;Thus, key objectives of this project have been to determine whether slip on detachment faults and vertical axis rotation was coeval or sequentially developed, and to document whether displacement transfer followed a systematic spatial and temporal progression from south to north or if all structures were active concurrently.</p> <p>Our collection for paleomagnetic study includes over 400 sampling sites, with typically 7-14 independently oriented samples.&nbsp; The paleomagnetic data obtained from ignimbrites of mid-Neogene age and younger units in our study area are directly compared with results from the same units exposed to the east and southeast (e.g., Nevada Test Site).&nbsp; Using the area immediately south of Gold Mountain as an example of key results, a well-exposed section of the Ammonia Tanks Member of the Timber Mountain Tuff nonconformably overlies Mesozoic granitoids and Paleozoic metasedimentary rocks.&nbsp; The section dips some 40 degrees southeast and field observations lead us to infer that the contact between the volcanic rocks and older rocks is depositional.&nbsp; The paleomagnetic data from these rocks are interpreted to indicate that the general sampling locality has experienced some 50 degrees of clockwise rotation.&nbsp; Farther to the north, near the Gold Point ghost town, the inferred magnitude of rotation in deposits of the Timber Mountain Tuff remains clockwise in sense, but variable in magnitude.&nbsp; &nbsp;Data from the younger &nbsp;Stonewall Flat Tuff, in the western part of Slate Ridge, where the tuff is in depositional contact with Mesozoic granitic rocks, indicate that the tuff, and thus underlying basement rocks, have not experienced appreciable vertical axis rotation since about 7.6 Ma.&nbsp; This relation appears to be the common to most areas where the Stonewall Flat Tuff has been sampled.</p> <p>In terms of Broader Impacts, the paleomagnetic study of these rocks served as a principal component of the dissertation of Dr. Jacob Jackson, who is now employed at ExxonMobil.&nbsp; &nbsp;Mr. Tom Fitter, who was in the fast track MS program at UTD, studied the anisotropy of magnetic susceptibility of the ignimbrite deposits that were the targeted rocks for most of the collection and has been employed at Pioneer Natural Resources since completing his MS.&nbsp; &nbsp;Ms. Ranyah Kharwat, also in the MS program at UTD, is studying the anisotropy of remanence (anhysteretic remanent magnetization, saturation isothermal remanent magnetization) of selected ignimbrite sites obtained in our study, as well as ignimbrites from the Jemez Mountains, to better understand how magnetic anisotropy fabrics are controlled by ignimbrite textures, compositions, and crystal content. She will graduate in Fall, 2016. &nbsp;A total of six UTD undergraduate students were employed as part-time laboratory assistants to help with several aspects of the research.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2016<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;W&nbsp;Geissman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was a collaborative effort that involved field geologic mapping, investigation of important structural features (i.e. faults), numerical age determinations of key volcanic deposits, studies of the magnetic remanence (paleomagnetism) of key volcanic deposits, gravitational field studies to determine basin geometry, and studies of the low temperature cooling history of selected rocks to better understand the tectonic evolution of the west-central Great Basin.   Notably, the western part of the Great Basin, east of the Sierra Nevada, presently is a diffuse zone of overall weakness in western North America, where some 20 to 25 percent of the general interaction between the Pacific Ocean tectonic plate and the North American tectonic plate is being accommodated.   A growing number of studies have concluded that this diffuse zone of deformation between the two plates has evolved quickly over the past ~20 million years (time interval referred to as the Neogene), and that the style of deformation has changed considerably over this time interval.  Because the region has strong seismic risk potential and has been the general site of young volcanism of different styles (e.g., Mammoth Lakes area), determining a more complete Neogene history of the area is warranted.   The area is characterized by two major right-lateral sense fault systems (the Furnace Creek/Fish Lake Valley and the Central Walker Lane) that parallel the eastern margin of the Sierra Nevada and are offset (to the east) by some 50+ kilometers at the southern end of the Walker Lane.  We hypothesized that displacement transfer between the fault systems was accommodated by low-angle normal (detachment) faults dipping to the northwest, vertical axis rotation of generally a clockwise sense (as determined by paleomagnetic data), and by motion along a complex array of younger high-angle faults.  Our work demonstrates that a major detachment system, likely responsible for the initiation of the regionally extensive displacement transfer system, underlies exposures of Proterozoic, Paleozoic, Mesozoic, and Neogene sedimentary, plutonic, and volcanic rocks in the Gold Mountain area of the southern Walker Lane.  This informally named Gold Mountain detachment is considered to be the breakaway part of a regionally extensive structure that stretches north over 80 km to exposure of the low-angle structure in the Silver Peak &ndash; Lone Mountain area.   Thus, key objectives of this project have been to determine whether slip on detachment faults and vertical axis rotation was coeval or sequentially developed, and to document whether displacement transfer followed a systematic spatial and temporal progression from south to north or if all structures were active concurrently.  Our collection for paleomagnetic study includes over 400 sampling sites, with typically 7-14 independently oriented samples.  The paleomagnetic data obtained from ignimbrites of mid-Neogene age and younger units in our study area are directly compared with results from the same units exposed to the east and southeast (e.g., Nevada Test Site).  Using the area immediately south of Gold Mountain as an example of key results, a well-exposed section of the Ammonia Tanks Member of the Timber Mountain Tuff nonconformably overlies Mesozoic granitoids and Paleozoic metasedimentary rocks.  The section dips some 40 degrees southeast and field observations lead us to infer that the contact between the volcanic rocks and older rocks is depositional.  The paleomagnetic data from these rocks are interpreted to indicate that the general sampling locality has experienced some 50 degrees of clockwise rotation.  Farther to the north, near the Gold Point ghost town, the inferred magnitude of rotation in deposits of the Timber Mountain Tuff remains clockwise in sense, but variable in magnitude.   Data from the younger  Stonewall Flat Tuff, in the western part of Slate Ridge, where the tuff is in depositional contact with Mesozoic granitic rocks, indicate that the tuff, and thus underlying basement rocks, have not experienced appreciable vertical axis rotation since about 7.6 Ma.  This relation appears to be the common to most areas where the Stonewall Flat Tuff has been sampled.  In terms of Broader Impacts, the paleomagnetic study of these rocks served as a principal component of the dissertation of Dr. Jacob Jackson, who is now employed at ExxonMobil.   Mr. Tom Fitter, who was in the fast track MS program at UTD, studied the anisotropy of magnetic susceptibility of the ignimbrite deposits that were the targeted rocks for most of the collection and has been employed at Pioneer Natural Resources since completing his MS.   Ms. Ranyah Kharwat, also in the MS program at UTD, is studying the anisotropy of remanence (anhysteretic remanent magnetization, saturation isothermal remanent magnetization) of selected ignimbrite sites obtained in our study, as well as ignimbrites from the Jemez Mountains, to better understand how magnetic anisotropy fabrics are controlled by ignimbrite textures, compositions, and crystal content. She will graduate in Fall, 2016.  A total of six UTD undergraduate students were employed as part-time laboratory assistants to help with several aspects of the research.           Last Modified: 10/31/2016       Submitted by: John W Geissman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
