<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Astronomy with CARMA</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1607547.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1749947</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Combined Array for Research in Millimeter Astronomy (CARMA) was formed from the merger of three telescope arrays supported by the Division of Astronomical Science's University Radio Observatories (URO) Program: Caltech's Owens Valley Radio Observatory (OVRO) array  of six 10.4-meter-diameter telescopes, the Berkeley Illinois Maryland Association (BIMA) array of nine 6.1-meter-diameter telescopes, and the University of Chicago's Sunyaev-Zeldovitch Array of eight 3.5-meter-diameter telescopes. CARMA currently achieves resolutions as high as 0.2 arcseconds at a wavelength of 1mm and, due to its heterogeneous combination of telescope diameters, provides excellent imaging over a wide range of angular scales.  Science enabled by CARMA covers a broad range of astronomical topics, including star formation and molecular clouds, studies of external galaxies, and the investigation of solar system objects. CARMA is a pathfinder for the Atacama Large Millimeter Array (ALMA) and a pipeline for training experts in the field of millimeter interferometry to take full advantage of ALMA's capabilities for US astronomy.   Users outside the CARMA collaboration receive 30% of all observing time.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1140019</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Leitch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik M Leitch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eml@astro.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8187933973</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230522</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Kravtsov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrey V Kravtsov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrey@oddjob.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737024249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000493432</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlstrom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E Carlstrom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jc@kicp.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7738340269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000163167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gladders</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael D Gladders</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gladders@oddjob.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7738340392</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489473</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5801 South Ellis Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1211</Code>
<Text>UNIV RADIO FACILITIES PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1257</Code>
<Text>MID-SCALE INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~525434</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1082113</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~142400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Combined Array for Millimeter Astronomy (CARMA) was located at Cedar Flat, near White Mountain in California. There were eight 3.5 m, nine 6 m, and six 10 m telescopes operating together to make high fidelity images of astronomical objects at wavelengths from 1 cm to 1 mm.&nbsp; The array was built and operated by a collaboration of scientists from the University of Chicago, Caltech, UC Berkeley, UCIC and UMD. CARMA was used to conduct cutting-edge astrophysical research&nbsp; for a broad range of science: from the formation of stars to the formation of galaxies and creation of structure in the early universe.&nbsp; An additional primary goal of CARMA was training the next generation of radio astronomers and instrumentalists and many of the NSF supported scientists and staff at the ALMA array in Chile were trained when graduate students or postdocs with CARMA.</p> <p>The primary science goal of the U.Chicago researchers was to use CARMA to image the spectral distortion in the radiation (light) of the cosmic microwave background caused by its interaction with the hot gas associated with galaxy clusters.&nbsp; The cosmic microwave background is the fossil light from the big bang, which has been traveling to us for nearly 14 billion years. Galaxy clusters are the largest objects that the universe has produced, with masses exceeding a thousand trillion times the mass of our sun. About 80% of this tremendous mass is dark matter, while most of the cluster's ordinary matter is contained in hot 100 million degree gas &ldquo;atmosphere&rdquo; in which the galaxies are immersed.&nbsp; The galaxies (not shown here in the figure) account for only a small fraction of the mass, although they are the only component visible at optical wavelengths. The hot gas interacts with the cosmic microwave background causing a small distortion, which appears as a shadow at cm-wavelengths, known as the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect.&nbsp;</p> <p>CARMA&rsquo;s extremely sensitive cm-wave receivers combined with its ability to pack the telescopes in very close to each other, allowed us to be able to make detailed images of the extended (a million light years across) and very low brightness Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect, actually a low brightness &ldquo;shadow&rdquo; against the smooth cosmic microwave background. This data allows us to investigate the details of the galaxy cluster in a unique and complementary way to that done at other wavelengths. The figure shows a CARMA 23 telescope array imaging of the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect for the massive galaxy cluster MS0735. The CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich imaging (green in the figure) reveals the total energy and distribution of the hot gas. In addition the figure also shows the x-ray emission of the hot gas (Chandra X-ray data in blue), which is sensitive to the density of the gas, as well as the bright radio emission (VLA radio emission in red), which traces the very high energy jets of gas driven from a black hole in the central galaxy (much too small to be imaged). Understanding the structure of these most massive objects requires such multiwavelength observations and enables fundamental tests of the evolution of the universe.&nbsp; The CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich measurements as well as the X-ray imaging (Chandra) show large bubbles in the otherwise smoothly distributed hot atmosphere. The lack x-ray emission indicates low density gas, but the empty bubbles in the Sunyaev-Zel&rsquo;dovich imaging, indicates that the gas must be extremely hot, billions of degrees or more likely that the bubbles are supported by relativistic protons, placing constraints on mechanisms for which the jets from the central black hole are able to heat the intracluster gas.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;E&nbsp;Carlstrom</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1140019/1140019_10214444_1514512024380_CARMA_23--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1140019/1140019_10214444_1514512024380_CARMA_23--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Combined Array for Millimeter Astronomy (CARMA)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1140019/1140019_10214444_1514512024380_CARMA_23--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Combined Array for Millimeter Astronomy (CARMA)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The CARMA 23-telescope heterogeneous interferometric array at Cedar Flat, near White Mountain in California. There were eight 3.5 m, nine 6 m, and six 10 m telescopes operating over three selectable bands (1 cm, 3 mm, and 1.3 mm) and configurable into arrays with baselines spanning 4.5 m to 2 km.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CARMA Collaboration</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;E&nbsp;Carlstrom</div> <div class="imageTitle">Combined Array for Millimeter Astronomy (CARMA)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1140019/1140019_10214444_1514511517713_MS0735_composite--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1140019/1140019_10214444_1514511517713_MS0735_composite--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect imaging."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1140019/1140019_10214444_1514511517713_MS0735_composite--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect imaging."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Composite image of massive cluster of galaxies MS0735. The black hole at its center produces radio jets (VLA red) that inflate bubbles in the X-ray emitting intracluster medium (Chandra blue), which also scatters the light of the cosmic microwave background causing a shadow in sky (CARMA SZ green).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zubair Abdulla</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;E&nbsp;Carlstrom</div> <div class="imageTitle">CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect imaging.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Combined Array for Millimeter Astronomy (CARMA) was located at Cedar Flat, near White Mountain in California. There were eight 3.5 m, nine 6 m, and six 10 m telescopes operating together to make high fidelity images of astronomical objects at wavelengths from 1 cm to 1 mm.  The array was built and operated by a collaboration of scientists from the University of Chicago, Caltech, UC Berkeley, UCIC and UMD. CARMA was used to conduct cutting-edge astrophysical research  for a broad range of science: from the formation of stars to the formation of galaxies and creation of structure in the early universe.  An additional primary goal of CARMA was training the next generation of radio astronomers and instrumentalists and many of the NSF supported scientists and staff at the ALMA array in Chile were trained when graduate students or postdocs with CARMA.  The primary science goal of the U.Chicago researchers was to use CARMA to image the spectral distortion in the radiation (light) of the cosmic microwave background caused by its interaction with the hot gas associated with galaxy clusters.  The cosmic microwave background is the fossil light from the big bang, which has been traveling to us for nearly 14 billion years. Galaxy clusters are the largest objects that the universe has produced, with masses exceeding a thousand trillion times the mass of our sun. About 80% of this tremendous mass is dark matter, while most of the cluster's ordinary matter is contained in hot 100 million degree gas "atmosphere" in which the galaxies are immersed.  The galaxies (not shown here in the figure) account for only a small fraction of the mass, although they are the only component visible at optical wavelengths. The hot gas interacts with the cosmic microwave background causing a small distortion, which appears as a shadow at cm-wavelengths, known as the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect.   CARMA?s extremely sensitive cm-wave receivers combined with its ability to pack the telescopes in very close to each other, allowed us to be able to make detailed images of the extended (a million light years across) and very low brightness Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect, actually a low brightness "shadow" against the smooth cosmic microwave background. This data allows us to investigate the details of the galaxy cluster in a unique and complementary way to that done at other wavelengths. The figure shows a CARMA 23 telescope array imaging of the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect for the massive galaxy cluster MS0735. The CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich imaging (green in the figure) reveals the total energy and distribution of the hot gas. In addition the figure also shows the x-ray emission of the hot gas (Chandra X-ray data in blue), which is sensitive to the density of the gas, as well as the bright radio emission (VLA radio emission in red), which traces the very high energy jets of gas driven from a black hole in the central galaxy (much too small to be imaged). Understanding the structure of these most massive objects requires such multiwavelength observations and enables fundamental tests of the evolution of the universe.  The CARMA Sunyaev-Zel'dovich measurements as well as the X-ray imaging (Chandra) show large bubbles in the otherwise smoothly distributed hot atmosphere. The lack x-ray emission indicates low density gas, but the empty bubbles in the Sunyaev-Zel?dovich imaging, indicates that the gas must be extremely hot, billions of degrees or more likely that the bubbles are supported by relativistic protons, placing constraints on mechanisms for which the jets from the central black hole are able to heat the intracluster gas.           Last Modified: 12/28/2017       Submitted by: John E Carlstrom]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
