<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RCN-SEES: Finding Common Ground: Developing Sustainable Networks of Women Scientists for Addressing Issues of Environmental Hazards</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>296405.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>438151</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajiv Ramnath</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mitigating the impact of natural environmental hazards and climate change is a major challenge. Reducing &lt;br/&gt;societal vulnerability goes beyond understanding seismographic and meteorological data and must integrate the human, economic and social influences on risk assessment, hazard preparedness and disaster response. To increase the intellectual capacity to anticipate and mitigate the effects of environmental hazards, this project will develop a multidisciplinary research network to increase the number of women (an underrepresented group) in environmental hazards scholarship.  This international effort will couple practitioners in the fields of geosciences, atmospheric science, economics and other social sciences in the U.S, with those in Latin America and the Caribbean, two areas that are particularly vulnerable to the risks posed by natural hazards due to their rapid urbanization, poorly engineered construction, inadequate infrastructure, poverty and other factors.  Through engaging research workshops and the use of collaborative cybertools, we will (1) create an international network of women with common research interests in environmental hazards; (2) use this network to build intellectual leadership capacity in this area through activities that broaden knowledge of the scientific and social science research on environmental hazards, and (3) promote network growth and assess its impact on participants. The network will facilitate the exchange of research ideas, build strong multi-disciplinary research teams, create networking relationships and broaden the knowledge base of participants in both the human and geological sciences (i.e. risk assessment, management and preparedness and socio-economic and political factors associated with environmental hazards). Workshops will lay the foundation for the longer-term cyber enabled network that will facilitate and enhance the research activities of the participants and sustain cross-disciplinary dialogue. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the factors (including the cyber enabled activities) that are most effective in developing and maintaining distributed, interdisciplinary, international research networks will inform other scholarly communities and improve the effectiveness of social networks in technical fields. Broadening the participation of women in science, technology, engineering and math is central to increasing national competitiveness and addressing environmental hazards issues that have significant implications for our society. The network is designed to increase the numbers, retention and leadership of women researchers, students, postdocs in the field, to educate them in multidisciplinary aspects of environmental hazard research and to engage them in activities that provide outreach to citizens in at-risk communities where environmental hazards are among the major causes of death and disease, particularly for women and young  children, and women play a key role in preparing for and mitigating disasters. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will have an enormous impact on a wide range of environmental hazards posed by meteorological phenomena, such as hurricanes, storms, droughts and floods; and geophysical activity, such as earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, landslides, mudslides, and tsunamis. It will improve our disaster preparedness, enhance hazard mitigation efforts, and provide for much more effective hazard response.  Engaging a diverse participant pool through well-designed team-building activities will result in strong collaborative research and an enduring network of scholars that will make a lasting contribution to the field of hazards and sustainability science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1140205</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R</FirstName>
<LastName>Macdonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>R H Macdonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhmacd@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572212443</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Geraldine</FirstName>
<LastName>Richmond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Geraldine L Richmond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richmond@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413464635</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000410417</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>Stockard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean Stockard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000434769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katharine</FirstName>
<LastName>Cashman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katharine V Cashman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cashman@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413464323</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000109340</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079289626</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049793995</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon Eugene]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974030001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7642</Code>
<Text>VIRTUAL ORGANIZATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7642</Code>
<Text>VIRTUAL ORGANIZATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~427701</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~10450</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Scientists for Addressing Issues of Environmental Hazards</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><em>The focus of this project has been the development of a multidisciplinary research-based network to increase the intellectual capacity to anticipate and mitigate the effects of environmental hazards. </em>This international effort coupled practitioners in the fields of geosciences, atmospheric science, economics and other social sciences in the U.S, with those in Latin America and the Caribbean. The motivation for partnering with neighbors to the south stems from cross-cultural concerns about hazards posed by meteorological phenomena, such as hurricanes, storms, droughts and floods; and geophysical activity, such as earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, landslides, mudslides, and tsunamis.&nbsp; The emphasis has been on maximizing the participation of women because of their under representation in fields that are central to mitigating environmental hazards. The project goals have been to: (1) create a network of women in the U.S., Latin America and Caribbean with common research interests in environmental hazards; (2) to use this network to build intellectual leadership capacity in this area through activities that broaden knowledge in the scientific, economic and social science research around the topic of environmental hazards, and (3) to maintain and grow this network by employing established methods that promote network development, and examine its growth and impact on participants.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We accomplished these goals and objectives by holding a series of four research-based workshops in Santiago, Chile (2012), Buenos Aires, Argentina (2013), Montego Bay, Jamaica (2014) and San Francisco, CA (2015) for the 45 women researchers to facilitate the exchange of research ideas, build networking relationships and broaden the knowledge base of participants in areas beyond the geosciences (i.e. risk assessment, management and preparedness and socio-economic and political factors associated with environmental hazards).&nbsp; We maximized participation by all interested workshop participants in the programs and network through coordinated activities with the American Geophysical Union and related professional organizations, women in geoscience groups and student groups, and assessing the quality and progress of the networking activities and their short and long term impact on the careers of participants using social science research methods.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/19/2017<br>      Modified by: Geraldine&nbsp;L&nbsp;Richmond</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Scientists for Addressing Issues of Environmental Hazards     The focus of this project has been the development of a multidisciplinary research-based network to increase the intellectual capacity to anticipate and mitigate the effects of environmental hazards. This international effort coupled practitioners in the fields of geosciences, atmospheric science, economics and other social sciences in the U.S, with those in Latin America and the Caribbean. The motivation for partnering with neighbors to the south stems from cross-cultural concerns about hazards posed by meteorological phenomena, such as hurricanes, storms, droughts and floods; and geophysical activity, such as earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, landslides, mudslides, and tsunamis.  The emphasis has been on maximizing the participation of women because of their under representation in fields that are central to mitigating environmental hazards. The project goals have been to: (1) create a network of women in the U.S., Latin America and Caribbean with common research interests in environmental hazards; (2) to use this network to build intellectual leadership capacity in this area through activities that broaden knowledge in the scientific, economic and social science research around the topic of environmental hazards, and (3) to maintain and grow this network by employing established methods that promote network development, and examine its growth and impact on participants.     We accomplished these goals and objectives by holding a series of four research-based workshops in Santiago, Chile (2012), Buenos Aires, Argentina (2013), Montego Bay, Jamaica (2014) and San Francisco, CA (2015) for the 45 women researchers to facilitate the exchange of research ideas, build networking relationships and broaden the knowledge base of participants in areas beyond the geosciences (i.e. risk assessment, management and preparedness and socio-economic and political factors associated with environmental hazards).  We maximized participation by all interested workshop participants in the programs and network through coordinated activities with the American Geophysical Union and related professional organizations, women in geoscience groups and student groups, and assessing the quality and progress of the networking activities and their short and long term impact on the careers of participants using social science research methods.                      Last Modified: 01/19/2017       Submitted by: Geraldine L Richmond]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
