<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Enhancing Intrinsic Motivation in Core Engineering Courses</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gul Kremer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is redesigning a sophomore-level electrical and computer engineering course to increase students' intrinsic motivation for learning technical engineering content. Motivation research has found that students learn more when the content is linked to their career goals and when they can make some decisions about their own learning. This project is offering students different options for projects which will help them learn the required course content.  The investigators are collecting evaluation data which relates students' motivation to their learning of key engineering concepts in digital logic and computer organization. Student learning and motivation in this new course are also being compared to a control group in a traditional engineering course on the same topic. Graduate teaching assistants and engineering faculty members are being trained to teach motivation-based engineering courses in other topics as well.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1140554</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Loui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Loui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>loui@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332595</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000474751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David E Goldberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>deg@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173330897</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332366</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Geoffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Herman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Geoffrey L Herman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>glherman@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8473098699</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000592249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In a typical undergraduate engineering program, students are required to take several core courses in the engineering sciences: statics, dynamics, thermodynamics, electric circuits, etc. Because the content of these mandatory courses may seem unrelated to students&rsquo; ultimate goals, students usually experience low levels of motivation and engagement, leading to decreased learning and disinterest in engineering. In this project, we developed a method for redesigning the teaching methods of these courses based on the motivational theory Self-Determination Theory. By surveying and interviewing students, we showed that we enhanced students&rsquo; intrinsic motivation to learn in core engineering courses, by giving students some responsibility for choosing what they learn and how they demonstrate their learning. Using standardized assessment tools, we demonstrated that by focusing on improving students' motivation to learn, we were able to not only improve students' motivation but also their learning of core concepts and skills.</p> <p>Simultaneously, the project sought to address the broad challenge of developing innovative teaching methods that will be used by typical engineering professors. Professors frequently complain that the time required to learn and use innovative teaching methods is prohibitive and insufficiently rewarded. Our innovative course design method was structured so that it requires little training and no additional time from professors to implement beyond their traditional teaching methods. We have shown that faculty are quite ready to use teaching methods that can improve students' motivation and learning when the time costs of implementing these teaching methods is sufficiently low.</p> <p>Our project has culminated in the creation of a low-cost, intrinsic motivation course design method that is being used by several engineering professors and hundreds of graduate teaching assistants across the country. At the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 12 engineering professors are already using our course design method in their courses, impacting thousands of students per year. The training of graduate research assistants in methods for improving students' motivation to learn provides opportunities to impact increasingly more schools and students as the project grows. This rapid adoption of an innovative teaching method is rare, demonstrating that using engineering principles of designing innovations for the targeted users can lead to rapid adoption and use of those innovations.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Geoffrey&nbsp;L&nbsp;Herman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In a typical undergraduate engineering program, students are required to take several core courses in the engineering sciences: statics, dynamics, thermodynamics, electric circuits, etc. Because the content of these mandatory courses may seem unrelated to studentsÆ ultimate goals, students usually experience low levels of motivation and engagement, leading to decreased learning and disinterest in engineering. In this project, we developed a method for redesigning the teaching methods of these courses based on the motivational theory Self-Determination Theory. By surveying and interviewing students, we showed that we enhanced studentsÆ intrinsic motivation to learn in core engineering courses, by giving students some responsibility for choosing what they learn and how they demonstrate their learning. Using standardized assessment tools, we demonstrated that by focusing on improving students' motivation to learn, we were able to not only improve students' motivation but also their learning of core concepts and skills.  Simultaneously, the project sought to address the broad challenge of developing innovative teaching methods that will be used by typical engineering professors. Professors frequently complain that the time required to learn and use innovative teaching methods is prohibitive and insufficiently rewarded. Our innovative course design method was structured so that it requires little training and no additional time from professors to implement beyond their traditional teaching methods. We have shown that faculty are quite ready to use teaching methods that can improve students' motivation and learning when the time costs of implementing these teaching methods is sufficiently low.  Our project has culminated in the creation of a low-cost, intrinsic motivation course design method that is being used by several engineering professors and hundreds of graduate teaching assistants across the country. At the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 12 engineering professors are already using our course design method in their courses, impacting thousands of students per year. The training of graduate research assistants in methods for improving students' motivation to learn provides opportunities to impact increasingly more schools and students as the project grows. This rapid adoption of an innovative teaching method is rare, demonstrating that using engineering principles of designing innovations for the targeted users can lead to rapid adoption and use of those innovations.        Last Modified: 09/28/2015       Submitted by: Geoffrey L Herman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
