<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Connecting the historic 2011 Mississippi River flood to marsh sedimentation on the Delta</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49982.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49982</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Cutler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pcutler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924961</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project aims to determine the impact of a geologically significant flood event on coastal sedimentation patterns and rates.  Determining transport pathways will enable researchers from University of Pennsylvania, University of Mississippi, and the U.S. Geological Survey to connect the dots between river dynamics, coastal dynamics, and marsh maintenance.  Two contrasting river plumes will be studied?-that of the Mississippi River itself, which is expected to disperse sediment into the Gulf and not contribute greatly to wetland development because of its narrow, focused jet, and that of the Atchafalaya River, which is expected to spread diffusely across the landscape and be more prone to deposit sediment to nourish wetlands. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will make use of satellite data, physical sampling, and numerical modeling.  Measurement approaches are (1) analysis of satellite data on sea surface temperature, color, and height; (2) collection of sediment samples at the outlet of the Mississippi River using a boat survey with acoustic dopplar, surface sediment samples, and bed grab samples, and (3) measurement of marshland sediment accretion rates once the floodwaters begin to subside.  New theory recently developed by two of the PIs for estimating mixing rates and sedimentation patterns in coastal Louisiana resulting from the flood will be captured in a model.  The results of the model will be compared with measured plume dynamics off the Mississippi River, and sampled marsh sediments from the shelf bottom and marsh surfaces along the Mississippi and Atchafalaya Rivers, to enhance understanding of how the Mississippi Delta functions as a sediment dispersal system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is consensus that protecting and expanding coastal marshes is vital for coastal Louisiana but much less agreement on how to do it.  Scientific understanding of marsh building needs to be bolstered before it can inform this debate. This project seizes a unique opportunity to examine constrasting modes of sediment dynamics in two plumes from the historic 2011 Mississippi floods, and aims to enhance the scientific basis for delta restoration that will become increasingly important in the years to come.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1140269</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>McKee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen L McKee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>karen_mckee@usgs.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3182668662</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481994</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Horton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin P Horton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bphorton@marine.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8989323430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000182524</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Jerolmack</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas J Jerolmack</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sediment@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2157462823</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leonardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Macelloni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leonardo Macelloni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leonardo.macelloni@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2286887099</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000593379</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
<LastName>Lutken</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carol Lutken</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>clutken@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6629155598</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000593380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~49982</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">Coastal wetlands on the Mississippi Delta are deteriorating in part because levees and control structures starve them of sediment, and prevent the river from changing course to form a new delta. There is a consensus that protecting and expanding coastal wetlands is vital for residents and ecosystems of the Mississippi River Delta, and that harnessing natural processes of wetland building using the Mississippi River and its sediments is an essential component of restoration plans. The only portion of the Delta where significant expansion of coastal wetland is presently occurring is at the mouth of the Atchafalaya River, where a higher sediment concentration and lower river current speed allow sediment deposition. The recently released Draft 2012 Coastal Master Plan proposes river diversions and channel realignment to divert sediment and freshwater from the Mississippi and Atchafalaya Rivers into adjacent basins with the goal of reconnecting the river to the delta wetlands. The successful design and implementation of such measures requires a solid understanding of diverted sediment movement and deposition, especially during flood events when the potential sediment load is greatest.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">The MR flood of Spring 2011 was one of the largest on record, and provided a unique opportunity to examine the routing and deposition of Mississippi and Atchafalaya River sediments into delta wetlands. Flood waters at the Old River Control Structure &ndash; the location where the Mississippi River splits into the Atchafalaya and Mississippi channels &ndash; crested for the period of 14-31 May 2011. To relieve pressure on levees along the downstream portion of the MR in Baton Rouge and New Orleans, the Morganza Spillway was opened on 14 May 2011 for the first time in almost 40 years. This diverted water to the west into the Atchafalaya Basin, flooding the swamps and marshes along the entire length of the Atchafalaya River &ndash; simulating a kind of &ldquo;natural&rdquo; flood that used to occur often before levees were emplaced.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">We tracked the movement and deposition of river sediment during the flood using a combination of satellite data, a boat survey of the currents emanating from the mouth of the Mississippi, and a helicopter survey sampling deposited flood sediment across most of coastal Louisiana. We show that the focused, high-momentum jet from the leveed Mississippi delivered sediment far offshore, where it was unable to contribute to significant marsh sedimentation. In contrast, the plume from the &ldquo;naturally flooded&rdquo; Atchafalaya Basin was more diffuse with diverted water inundating a large area, and sediment was trapped within the coastal current. Sediment deposition was greatest in the marshes of the Atchafalaya Basin, intermediate and more localized around the mouth of the Mississippi River, and least in the basins that are farthest away from both river outlets. Our findings show how floods actually contribute sediment to maintain and build coastal marshes, and also how human-built control structures influence deposition patterns and potentially threaten the sustainability of fragile marshes. This understanding will useful for the design of proposed artificial diversions, in order to protect vulnerable areas such as New Orleans.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/20/2012<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;J&nbsp;Jerolmack</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <d...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coastal wetlands on the Mississippi Delta are deteriorating in part because levees and control structures starve them of sediment, and prevent the river from changing course to form a new delta. There is a consensus that protecting and expanding coastal wetlands is vital for residents and ecosystems of the Mississippi River Delta, and that harnessing natural processes of wetland building using the Mississippi River and its sediments is an essential component of restoration plans. The only portion of the Delta where significant expansion of coastal wetland is presently occurring is at the mouth of the Atchafalaya River, where a higher sediment concentration and lower river current speed allow sediment deposition. The recently released Draft 2012 Coastal Master Plan proposes river diversions and channel realignment to divert sediment and freshwater from the Mississippi and Atchafalaya Rivers into adjacent basins with the goal of reconnecting the river to the delta wetlands. The successful design and implementation of such measures requires a solid understanding of diverted sediment movement and deposition, especially during flood events when the potential sediment load is greatest.   The MR flood of Spring 2011 was one of the largest on record, and provided a unique opportunity to examine the routing and deposition of Mississippi and Atchafalaya River sediments into delta wetlands. Flood waters at the Old River Control Structure &ndash; the location where the Mississippi River splits into the Atchafalaya and Mississippi channels &ndash; crested for the period of 14-31 May 2011. To relieve pressure on levees along the downstream portion of the MR in Baton Rouge and New Orleans, the Morganza Spillway was opened on 14 May 2011 for the first time in almost 40 years. This diverted water to the west into the Atchafalaya Basin, flooding the swamps and marshes along the entire length of the Atchafalaya River &ndash; simulating a kind of "natural" flood that used to occur often before levees were emplaced.   We tracked the movement and deposition of river sediment during the flood using a combination of satellite data, a boat survey of the currents emanating from the mouth of the Mississippi, and a helicopter survey sampling deposited flood sediment across most of coastal Louisiana. We show that the focused, high-momentum jet from the leveed Mississippi delivered sediment far offshore, where it was unable to contribute to significant marsh sedimentation. In contrast, the plume from the "naturally flooded" Atchafalaya Basin was more diffuse with diverted water inundating a large area, and sediment was trapped within the coastal current. Sediment deposition was greatest in the marshes of the Atchafalaya Basin, intermediate and more localized around the mouth of the Mississippi River, and least in the basins that are farthest away from both river outlets. Our findings show how floods actually contribute sediment to maintain and build coastal marshes, and also how human-built control structures influence deposition patterns and potentially threaten the sustainability of fragile marshes. This understanding will useful for the design of proposed artificial diversions, in order to protect vulnerable areas such as New Orleans.       Last Modified: 06/20/2012       Submitted by: Douglas J Jerolmack]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
