<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TUES: Use of Video Production to Promote Collaborative Learning and Higher Level Cognitive Understanding in an Introductory Life Science Curriculum</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>181173.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>181173</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Sullivan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project students at UCLA are selected to enroll in a series of 3 seminar-style classes, one in each quarter, supplementary to their Introductory Life Science lecture and discussion course. In the classes, teams of students learn to produce short documentary videos on topics of societal interest in evolutionary biology, which they have researched in the literature and through conversations with experts on the UCLA faculty.  Their improvement in high-level cognitive mastery compared to a matched control group is expected to increase their academic success and foster their retention in life science majors. Students are chosen from among those identified as underrepresented in STEM disciplines and who have experienced life challenges. Such students are particularly susceptible to abandoning STEM majors, so success in this program has a broad impact. In addition, the video products, developed collaboratively and with the help of graduate-student facilitators from theater, film, and television backgrounds, are shown to UCLA students majoring in other disciplines and to middle-school students. This project thus has an unusually broad impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1140951</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Barber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul H Barber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paulbarber@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3107945349</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485022</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951606</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[621 Charles E Young Drive South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~181173</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ineffective and uninspiring introductory courses&nbsp;in science, math, and engineering have played a detrimental role in the loss of undergraduate STEM majors. Across the board, about 40% of undergraduates who intend on getting a STEM degree actually receive a STEM degree&ndash; and for women and underrepresented minorities (URM), the retention rates are even lower. &nbsp;To bridge the excitement gap, improve student learning, and to increase persistence, especially of URM students in STEM majors, we developed a 10-week life science course at UCLA, called &ldquo;Communicating Science&rdquo;.&nbsp;We recruited incoming freshmen from underrepresented minorities and/or from underserved backgrounds (e.g. low income, underperforming high schools, first-generation college student, etc.) and have declared an undergraduate major in the Division of Life Sciences.&nbsp;The course was designed for students to work collaboratively in small groups with the help of instructors and graduate students&nbsp;from&nbsp;UCLA&rsquo;s Department of Theater Film and Television&nbsp;to understand and convey cutting-edge science to a general audience through the production of short (3-5 minute) documentary videos about life science research at UCLA. Students work together to learn about the research that&rsquo;s happening on campus, interview research professors, learn how they became research scientists, and to understand the concepts relevant to the research they do. Through the process of asking questions out of genuine curiosity, and synthesizing information so they can illustrate it and explain it to their peers, students see science in context, and make important connections that could help them develop a deeper conceptual understanding of science and could help them envision future careers in science and/or science education. The course also teaches skills in collaboration, communication, and video-literacy&ndash; important skills that are becoming more and more valuable to science.&nbsp;Research&nbsp;shows that inclusive classroom environments&mdash;ones that cultivate creativity, collaboration, and active learning while providing computational challenges and intellectual rigor&mdash;are essential to retain the most talented students and preserve student diversity in science courses.&nbsp;</p> <p>Assessment of the course, indicates that students felt that their communication skills improved with students in their groups and with faculty, as well as increased abilities to communicate scientific concepts. Through a qualitative analysis of open-ended responses, nearly all students reported that through creating their videos and watching those of their peers, the repeated opportunities to see evolution in differing contexts, helped to deepen their understanding of evolution, including its importance and impact across a diversity of science disciplines<em>.&nbsp;</em>Nearly all students found the process of interviewing Life Sciences faculty for their videos to be the most meaningful experience &nbsp;in the course. In particular, students reported that these student-faculty interactions helped eliminate their preconceived notions of science faculty (e.g. being unapproachable, intimidating, or inaccessible).&nbsp;</p> <p>The most notable result of our study was a remarkable increase in student commitment to pursuing degrees and careers in science. Although less than 40% of STEM students nationwide complete their STEM degrees, more than 80% of our students, have remained committed to being a science major. What makes this result more remarkable is that nearly 85% of our students were URM students, and more than 60% are first-generation college students. The persistence rate of students who participated in our course is four times higher than the national average, more than twice the average of URM students at UCLA, and even exceeds the 70% persistence rate of Caucasian and Asian students at UCLA.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;A selection of videos can be viewed at&nbsp;<a href="https://cs.eeb.ucla.edu/">https://cs.eeb.ucla.edu/</a>. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;H&nbsp;Barber</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ineffective and uninspiring introductory courses in science, math, and engineering have played a detrimental role in the loss of undergraduate STEM majors. Across the board, about 40% of undergraduates who intend on getting a STEM degree actually receive a STEM degree&ndash; and for women and underrepresented minorities (URM), the retention rates are even lower.  To bridge the excitement gap, improve student learning, and to increase persistence, especially of URM students in STEM majors, we developed a 10-week life science course at UCLA, called "Communicating Science". We recruited incoming freshmen from underrepresented minorities and/or from underserved backgrounds (e.g. low income, underperforming high schools, first-generation college student, etc.) and have declared an undergraduate major in the Division of Life Sciences. The course was designed for students to work collaboratively in small groups with the help of instructors and graduate students from UCLA?s Department of Theater Film and Television to understand and convey cutting-edge science to a general audience through the production of short (3-5 minute) documentary videos about life science research at UCLA. Students work together to learn about the research that?s happening on campus, interview research professors, learn how they became research scientists, and to understand the concepts relevant to the research they do. Through the process of asking questions out of genuine curiosity, and synthesizing information so they can illustrate it and explain it to their peers, students see science in context, and make important connections that could help them develop a deeper conceptual understanding of science and could help them envision future careers in science and/or science education. The course also teaches skills in collaboration, communication, and video-literacy&ndash; important skills that are becoming more and more valuable to science. Research shows that inclusive classroom environments&mdash;ones that cultivate creativity, collaboration, and active learning while providing computational challenges and intellectual rigor&mdash;are essential to retain the most talented students and preserve student diversity in science courses.   Assessment of the course, indicates that students felt that their communication skills improved with students in their groups and with faculty, as well as increased abilities to communicate scientific concepts. Through a qualitative analysis of open-ended responses, nearly all students reported that through creating their videos and watching those of their peers, the repeated opportunities to see evolution in differing contexts, helped to deepen their understanding of evolution, including its importance and impact across a diversity of science disciplines. Nearly all students found the process of interviewing Life Sciences faculty for their videos to be the most meaningful experience  in the course. In particular, students reported that these student-faculty interactions helped eliminate their preconceived notions of science faculty (e.g. being unapproachable, intimidating, or inaccessible).   The most notable result of our study was a remarkable increase in student commitment to pursuing degrees and careers in science. Although less than 40% of STEM students nationwide complete their STEM degrees, more than 80% of our students, have remained committed to being a science major. What makes this result more remarkable is that nearly 85% of our students were URM students, and more than 60% are first-generation college students. The persistence rate of students who participated in our course is four times higher than the national average, more than twice the average of URM students at UCLA, and even exceeds the 70% persistence rate of Caucasian and Asian students at UCLA.    A selection of videos can be viewed at https://cs.eeb.ucla.edu/.             Last Modified: 09/13/2016       Submitted by: Paul H Barber]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
