<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integration and Assessment of an Inquiry-Based Laboratory Within Three Different Educational Settings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>207494.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207494</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Virginia Carter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vccarter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924651</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is implementing an inquiry-based biology laboratory module and determining whether it is effective and transferable across diverse educational environments. The module is composed of a series of experiments and exercises that navigate students through a UV-mutagenesis screen in search of an understanding for how cells monitor their genomic integrity. The module is being implemented within three different educational environments: 1) an introductory-level biology course at a public, primarily undergraduate university (PUI) with less selective admission criteria, 2) the equivalent (i.e. transferable) introductory-level biology course at a community college, and 3) the curriculum of a mathematics and science secondary teacher training program. Assessments that measure learning gains, student perception and course completion rates are being conducted in all three settings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is enhancing the research and education infrastructure of a public PUI, a community college, and a mathematics and science secondary teacher training program through the acquisition of equipment and the development of new skills. Scientist-teacher partnerships are developing, and these partnerships allow community college faculty and prospective secondary mathematics and science teachers to engage in scientific inquiry. The PUI faculty are developing a better understanding for the needs of community college transfer students and building relationships with the future local high school mathematics and science teachers. All course materials and findings are accessible and freely available via a website and the BEN portal, while research findings are being presented at national conferences and published in science education and research journals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts toward Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1140120</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Wolkow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas D Wolkow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>twolkow@uccs.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7192623663</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000233861</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Hines</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa M Hines</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lhines@uccs.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7192553192</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470077</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Colorado Springs</Name>
<CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
<ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7192553153</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1420, Austin Bluffs Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186192829</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Colorado Springs]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7972</Code>
<Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~207494</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Early research experiences must be made available to all undergraduate students, including those at two-year institutions who account for nearly half of America's college students.&nbsp; While there is evidence indicating the Course-Based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs) correlate with student gains in knowledge and enjoyment in two-year institutions, very few have successfully implemented them.&nbsp; To identify the specific barriers that preclude two-year instituions from CURE-based curricular reform, we implemented a seven-week research experience entitled Soakin' Up the Rays with <em>S. pombe&nbsp;</em>(SUR)&nbsp;into the curriculum of equivalent introductory biology courses at a two-year institution (Pikes Peak Community College, Colorado Springs, CO) and a four-year institution (University of Colorado Colorado Springs) within the same geographic region.&nbsp; In the SUR CURE, students perform a yeast UV-mutagenesis screen, isolate DNA damage response (DDR) mutants and assign them to sensor, transducer or effector branches of this signal transduction pathway (Figure 1).&nbsp; In doing so, students may discover mutations in early DDR processes that advance understanding of this important tumor-suppressor pathway.</p> <p>Using a randomized study design, we evaluated this CURE with respect to both knowledge gains and student perception.&nbsp; We found that the two-yer and four-year student populations had dramatically different impressions of the experience.&nbsp; Students at the four-year instituion enjoyed the CURE significantly more than the traditional labs.&nbsp; However, students at the two-year institution enjoyed the traditional labs significnatly more, even though the CURE successfully produced targeted learning gains.&nbsp; Course evaluations and surveys administered to the two-year instructors, students and support staff reflected that the major barrier precluding success was the need for additional training during implementation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Several revisions&nbsp;were made to address the identified barriers.&nbsp; For example, we added more detailed soluations and commentary to instructor lecture slides and manuals for both students and instructors.&nbsp; A preparatory lab session was alsso developed and incorporated prior to Lab 1 of the module to allow students to leanr basic lab skills and operate equipment, and additional microscopy training sessions were provided to instructors.&nbsp; Specifically, laboratory support coordinators attended a training workshop and were provided with preparative technique videos and worksheets containing pre-programmed calculations to facilitate accurate media and reagent preparation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Using the revised implementation startegy containing these modifications, we re-evaluated the experience at another campus of the same two-year institution with a differnet group of instructors and support staff.&nbsp; This time, the results reflecte what was observed with the four-year student population.&nbsp; The students enjoyed the research experience significantly more than the traditional labs.</p> <p>The goal of attaining widespread adoption of research experiences in STEM education is contingent upon addressing barriers unique to the environments of different educational settings.&nbsp; Here, we demonstrate that the integration of a successful research experience in a two-year institution can be accomplished with a comprehensive training strategy targeting instructors, lab coordinators/staff, and students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/17/2015<br>      Modified by: Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hines</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Early research experiences must be made available to all undergraduate students, including those at two-year institutions who account for nearly half of America's college students.  While there is evidence indicating the Course-Based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs) correlate with student gains in knowledge and enjoyment in two-year institutions, very few have successfully implemented them.  To identify the specific barriers that preclude two-year instituions from CURE-based curricular reform, we implemented a seven-week research experience entitled Soakin' Up the Rays with S. pombe (SUR) into the curriculum of equivalent introductory biology courses at a two-year institution (Pikes Peak Community College, Colorado Springs, CO) and a four-year institution (University of Colorado Colorado Springs) within the same geographic region.  In the SUR CURE, students perform a yeast UV-mutagenesis screen, isolate DNA damage response (DDR) mutants and assign them to sensor, transducer or effector branches of this signal transduction pathway (Figure 1).  In doing so, students may discover mutations in early DDR processes that advance understanding of this important tumor-suppressor pathway.  Using a randomized study design, we evaluated this CURE with respect to both knowledge gains and student perception.  We found that the two-yer and four-year student populations had dramatically different impressions of the experience.  Students at the four-year instituion enjoyed the CURE significantly more than the traditional labs.  However, students at the two-year institution enjoyed the traditional labs significnatly more, even though the CURE successfully produced targeted learning gains.  Course evaluations and surveys administered to the two-year instructors, students and support staff reflected that the major barrier precluding success was the need for additional training during implementation.   Several revisions were made to address the identified barriers.  For example, we added more detailed soluations and commentary to instructor lecture slides and manuals for both students and instructors.  A preparatory lab session was alsso developed and incorporated prior to Lab 1 of the module to allow students to leanr basic lab skills and operate equipment, and additional microscopy training sessions were provided to instructors.  Specifically, laboratory support coordinators attended a training workshop and were provided with preparative technique videos and worksheets containing pre-programmed calculations to facilitate accurate media and reagent preparation.   Using the revised implementation startegy containing these modifications, we re-evaluated the experience at another campus of the same two-year institution with a differnet group of instructors and support staff.  This time, the results reflecte what was observed with the four-year student population.  The students enjoyed the research experience significantly more than the traditional labs.  The goal of attaining widespread adoption of research experiences in STEM education is contingent upon addressing barriers unique to the environments of different educational settings.  Here, we demonstrate that the integration of a successful research experience in a two-year institution can be accomplished with a comprehensive training strategy targeting instructors, lab coordinators/staff, and students.           Last Modified: 06/17/2015       Submitted by: Lisa M Hines]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
