<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Antarctic Meteorological Research Center</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>198781.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>238537</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This two year renewal effort has two community directed aims: 1) continued collection, quality control and distribution of the Antarctic AWS network meteorological data sets; and 2) the continued production of Antarctic composite infrared satellite imagery.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By making the AWS networked data readily available to a wide, even global,  community of researchers and observational forecasters, the AMRC archive provides a necessary and useful compilation. On the value of this activity alone, the broader impacts of these activities continues to be a prime reason for continuing the records activities in one form or another. A legacy of the University of Wisconsin efforts in this arena enables continuity of the data collection and archival efforts. Outreach activities to the (Wisconsin) public and efforts to engage (Wisconsin) K-12 school children and their teachers will also be continued.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1141908</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Keller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda M Keller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lmkeller@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082652209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000281703</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Lazzara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew A Lazzara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mattl@ssec.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082620436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SSEC, University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1225 West Dayton Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5407</Code>
<Text>Polar Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5407</Code>
<Text>POLAR CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~198781</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~39756</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Antarctic Meteorological Research Center (AMRC) has focused on the generation and stewardship of Antarctic meteorological data sets along with providing expertise to the community. Over the many years the AMRC has been in existence, this goal has been met via:</p> <ul> <li>archiving over 40 Terabytes of meteorological data;</li> <li> providing specialized data requests to hundreds of researchers, artists, educators, and others from the general public; and </li> <li>generating an unparalleled satellite composite imagery series over the Antarctic and southern ocean. </li> </ul> <p>One of AMRC's signature highlights is its generation of the unique Antarctic composite satellite imagery over the Antarctic and adjacent Southern Ocean. This project specifically worked on and completed the following tasks:</p> <ul> <li>Improvements in resolution (from 5 km to 4 km) (See Figures), </li> <li>New compositing methodology implemented (with a peer-reviewed paper published on that methodology)</li> <li>Additional spectral channels formally created, distributed, and archived</li> </ul> <p>The AMRC has evolved as the primary steward of all United States Antarctic Program (USAP) staffed stations, field camp, and ship based meteorological observations. This task involves data collection, archive and distribution. Additionally, the AMRC has a collected other standard meteorological observations from around the Antarctic and adjacent land areas in the Southern Hemisphere (see Table).&nbsp; This collection historically includes global numerical model output over the Antarctic and Southern Ocean/Hemisphere, also collected throughout the project.</p> <p>In the final supplemental year of the project, effort was placed into making two specific datasets more available to the commumity.&nbsp; The Antarctic satellite composites have been converted into other data formats commonly used in the science community.&nbsp; Additionally, the Antarctic Automatic Weather Station (AWS) observation dataset has been made available over the web via a database interface.&nbsp; This allows for standard queries and additional output data formats.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;A&nbsp;Lazzara</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1141908/1141908_10213017_1448686845185_SAMPLE-IR--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1141908/1141908_10213017_1448686845185_SAMPLE-IR--rgov-800width.jpg" title="A Sample 4 km Infrared Antarctic Composite Image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1141908/1141908_10213017_1448686845185_SAMPLE-IR--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="A Sample 4 km Infrared Antarctic Composite Image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A sample infrared Antarctic composite image at 4 kilometer resolution.</div> <div class="imageCredit">(Display Courtesy of Matthew Lazzara)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;A&nbsp;Lazzara</div> <div class="imageTitle">A Sample 4 km Infrared Antarctic Composite Image</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1141908/1141908_10213017_1448675397349_AMRC_Data_Table1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1141908/1141908_10213017_1448675397349_AMRC_Data_Table1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AMRC Antarctic Meteorological Data Archive"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1141908/11...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Antarctic Meteorological Research Center (AMRC) has focused on the generation and stewardship of Antarctic meteorological data sets along with providing expertise to the community. Over the many years the AMRC has been in existence, this goal has been met via:  archiving over 40 Terabytes of meteorological data;  providing specialized data requests to hundreds of researchers, artists, educators, and others from the general public; and  generating an unparalleled satellite composite imagery series over the Antarctic and southern ocean.    One of AMRC's signature highlights is its generation of the unique Antarctic composite satellite imagery over the Antarctic and adjacent Southern Ocean. This project specifically worked on and completed the following tasks:  Improvements in resolution (from 5 km to 4 km) (See Figures),  New compositing methodology implemented (with a peer-reviewed paper published on that methodology) Additional spectral channels formally created, distributed, and archived   The AMRC has evolved as the primary steward of all United States Antarctic Program (USAP) staffed stations, field camp, and ship based meteorological observations. This task involves data collection, archive and distribution. Additionally, the AMRC has a collected other standard meteorological observations from around the Antarctic and adjacent land areas in the Southern Hemisphere (see Table).  This collection historically includes global numerical model output over the Antarctic and Southern Ocean/Hemisphere, also collected throughout the project.  In the final supplemental year of the project, effort was placed into making two specific datasets more available to the commumity.  The Antarctic satellite composites have been converted into other data formats commonly used in the science community.  Additionally, the Antarctic Automatic Weather Station (AWS) observation dataset has been made available over the web via a database interface.  This allows for standard queries and additional output data formats.       Last Modified: 11/30/2015       Submitted by: Matthew A Lazzara]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
