<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integrating Biomechanical Engineering Research and Design and a Co-operative Education Curriculum</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199196.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199196</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yvette Weatherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a partnership among industry, the local community, and Drexel University with the goal to design and implement a Biomechanical Engineering curriculum that enables students to translate research results into commercially viable products. Building on the successes of the Gateway Coalition and the VaNTH Engineering Research Center, the project begins at the junior level, carries through to graduation and incorporates problem-based learning, cooperative education and entrepreneurial training. Faculty researchers, through the partnership, are assisting students as they learn to turn research results into products. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project goal is being met by modifying existing junior level courses into a problem-based format, integrating cooperative education into the curriculum, and using Biomechanical Engineering faculty expertise to deliver the innovative classroom techniques. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project evaluation is assessing benefits to students, faculty and co-op partners and consists of short and long term data collection and analysis. New understanding generated in the program will be widely disseminated and tested at local schools consisting of Lehigh University, Worcester Polytechnic Institute, Rochester Polytechnic Institute and Olin College.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1141186</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sunwei@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158955810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000215409</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongseok</FirstName>
<LastName>Noh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hongseok Noh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mosesnoh@coe.drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158952273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000302227</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Morss Clyne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alisa Morss Clyne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aclyne@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014059806</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000199792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Tangorra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Tangorra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlt66@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158952296</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drexel University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158956342</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 10th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DREXEL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drexel University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191042875</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~199196</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project was to determine how implementing a problem-based learning approach in a biomechanics course could help students achieve better results in their cooperative education jobs and their design projects. We re-designed a current course to be taught entirely in a problem-based learning format. The students learned how to design medical devices,&nbsp;create a mechanical lung assessment tool, tissue engineer a&nbsp;new lung, create an HIV point-of-care device, and build jumping artificial legs. We&nbsp;then followed these students through their co-op and design experiences to determine how they benefited from the problem-based learning course. Ih the broader community, we introduced problem-based learning and active learning approaches to students and professors at Drexel University. We also created and led a workshop to teach problem-based learning and active&nbsp;learning approaches to&nbsp;the biomechanics community through the Summer Biomechanics, Bioengineering, and Biotransport Conference (SB3C). The problems we created, along with problems collected from professors around the country, were made available to biomechanics educators.</p> <p>The intellectual merit outcomes of this project are:</p> <p>- problem-based learning courses are particularly popular with students in co-op programs, due to their focus on hands-on, real world learning</p> <p>- students reported improved understanding of how to apply biomechanics in their jobs and design projects</p> <p>- professors are interested in applying problem-based learning to their courses, as long as they are provided with the necessary tools</p> <p>The broader impacts outcomes of this project are:</p> <p>- a stronger problem based learning and active learning community in biomechanics education</p> <p>- new resources to help professors implement problem-based learning in biomechanics</p> <p>- a stronger biomechanics curriculum and problem-based learning knowledge base at Drexel University</p> <p>Overall, this project demonstrated that problem-based learning is an effective approach in biomechanics education. The critical step is to disseminate information so that more educators can easily implement these techniques in their classrooms.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/21/2015<br>      Modified by: Alisa&nbsp;Morss Clyne</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project was to determine how implementing a problem-based learning approach in a biomechanics course could help students achieve better results in their cooperative education jobs and their design projects. We re-designed a current course to be taught entirely in a problem-based learning format. The students learned how to design medical devices, create a mechanical lung assessment tool, tissue engineer a new lung, create an HIV point-of-care device, and build jumping artificial legs. We then followed these students through their co-op and design experiences to determine how they benefited from the problem-based learning course. Ih the broader community, we introduced problem-based learning and active learning approaches to students and professors at Drexel University. We also created and led a workshop to teach problem-based learning and active learning approaches to the biomechanics community through the Summer Biomechanics, Bioengineering, and Biotransport Conference (SB3C). The problems we created, along with problems collected from professors around the country, were made available to biomechanics educators.  The intellectual merit outcomes of this project are:  - problem-based learning courses are particularly popular with students in co-op programs, due to their focus on hands-on, real world learning  - students reported improved understanding of how to apply biomechanics in their jobs and design projects  - professors are interested in applying problem-based learning to their courses, as long as they are provided with the necessary tools  The broader impacts outcomes of this project are:  - a stronger problem based learning and active learning community in biomechanics education  - new resources to help professors implement problem-based learning in biomechanics  - a stronger biomechanics curriculum and problem-based learning knowledge base at Drexel University  Overall, this project demonstrated that problem-based learning is an effective approach in biomechanics education. The critical step is to disseminate information so that more educators can easily implement these techniques in their classrooms.       Last Modified: 10/21/2015       Submitted by: Alisa Morss Clyne]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
