<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Testing genotype-hormone associations in circumpolar ancestral and descendant populations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna M. Kerttula</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is an EAGER proposal to establish the foundation for subsequent research on the environmental, behavioral, and genetic determinants of reproductive hormone levels in indigenous arctic women. There is strong scientific evidence that concentrations of the steroid hormones investigated in this project influence the capacity to conceive and are significant risk factors for several diseases (e.g., breast and other cancers, cardiovascular disease), yet very little is known about the variation of these hormones among pre-menopausal women in the arctic. This EAGER project is an experimental project designed to evaluate whether genetic variation at specific loci contribute to hormonal variation in circumpolar ancestral (Central Asian) and descendant (indigenous South American) populations. The researchers expect this project to provide 1) validated field, laboratory and statistical approaches to hormone concentrations in women, and 2) valuable and novel data for the anticipated future study of circumpolar populations. In addition, the PI will be actively involved in community outreach in Alaska, Canada, and Greenland in order to inform indigenous communities of the findings from the EAGER research and solicit community interest and collaboration in a broader circumpolar study. This project is potentially transformative in both the scientific potential to define a specific genome related to steroid hormones and in the broader impacts of creating a community collaborative project that has the potential to gain deeper insight into fatal diseases affecting these communities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1142201</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Demas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory E Demas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gdemas@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128560158</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213207</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Vitzthum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia J Vitzthum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vitzthum@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128569065</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000060950</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Nephew</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth P Nephew</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>knephew@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128559445</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537701</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Renbarger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamie L Renbarger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jarenbar@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128550516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000587407</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474021847</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~99994</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The core goal of this research project is to understand the contributions of genetic, behavioral and environmental factors to variation in human fertility and health. Individual differences in fertility are partly dependent upon a woman's reproductive hormone levels during her menstrual cycle.&nbsp; These steroidal hormones are also known to be significant risk factors for several diseases including breast cancer and cardiovascular disease. Yet we know very little about the genetic, behavioral and environmental causes of individual differences in these hormone levels.</p> <p>To address this gap in knowledge we measured the concentrations of steroidal hormones and also determined genotypes in women from different populations (Bolivian Aymara, former East and West Germany, and Central Asia). The specific characteristics of each of these population made them particularly suitable choices for this study. Contemporary Germany is very similar to the U.S. but had been divided for about 40 years into two separate countries with different lifestyles.&nbsp; Thus Germany is both a good model for understanding hormonal variation in the U.S. population, and also allows a comparison of the effects of the different lifestyles on hormone concentrations in these genetically comparable German samples. Likewise, the Bolivian Aymara and Central Asian populations are genetically similar because of their shared ancestry with circumpolar populations, but their different lifestyles and environments are likely to influence hormone concentrations.</p> <p>We used advanced technologies to measure these hormonal and genotypic biomarkers.&nbsp; These techniques included LCMS (liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry), a highly sensitive and specific &nbsp;approach that can determine the urinary concentrations of multiple hormones simultaneously, thus saving cost and time compared to measuring each hormone individually. Genotypes for a set of 250,000 SNPs (single nucleotide polymorphism) were determined with the HumanExome BeadChip, a technique that requires high quality DNA. &nbsp;With extensive testing, we developed an optimal protocol for the extraction from saliva samples of the necessary volumes of high quality DNA.</p> <p>We identified a significant SNP, exm562556 (rs34068461), associated with variation in fertility (fertility highest in GG genotype than in GT genotype which was higher than TT genotype). This variant is in a gene that encodes a protein thought to be involved in centrosomal or ciliary functions. Mutations in this gene also cause Leber congenital amaurosis type V, a syndrome including congenital blindness.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this project included training and professional development for two post-doctoral scholars and development of new collaborations between the Departments of Chemistry and Anthropology at Indiana University, Bloomington (IUB), and between IUB and the School of Medicine (IUPUI in Indianapolis). We have also strengthened ties between IU and German colleagues, who assisted us in transferring their LCMS protocol to IUB. We continue to improve this protocol to make it faster, less costly and more widely available.</p> <p>This project has also provided valuable technological tools for a new multi-season investigation, now underway, of &nbsp;the effects of extremes in light exposure on steroid hormone concentrations.&nbsp; Shift workers are at higher risk for several diseases including certain cancers associated with high steroid hormone levels. One cause of this higher risk may be greater light exposure during the night, which may increase steroid hormone production and may also negatively impact immune functioning. The new project is the first study to concurrently measure hormone levels and immune functioning in humans during two conditions of extremely long exposure to light (the Arctic summer) and extremely short exposure to light (the Arctic winter). &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Virginia&nbsp;J&nbsp;Vitzthum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The core goal of this research project is to understand the contributions of genetic, behavioral and environmental factors to variation in human fertility and health. Individual differences in fertility are partly dependent upon a woman's reproductive hormone levels during her menstrual cycle.  These steroidal hormones are also known to be significant risk factors for several diseases including breast cancer and cardiovascular disease. Yet we know very little about the genetic, behavioral and environmental causes of individual differences in these hormone levels.  To address this gap in knowledge we measured the concentrations of steroidal hormones and also determined genotypes in women from different populations (Bolivian Aymara, former East and West Germany, and Central Asia). The specific characteristics of each of these population made them particularly suitable choices for this study. Contemporary Germany is very similar to the U.S. but had been divided for about 40 years into two separate countries with different lifestyles.  Thus Germany is both a good model for understanding hormonal variation in the U.S. population, and also allows a comparison of the effects of the different lifestyles on hormone concentrations in these genetically comparable German samples. Likewise, the Bolivian Aymara and Central Asian populations are genetically similar because of their shared ancestry with circumpolar populations, but their different lifestyles and environments are likely to influence hormone concentrations.  We used advanced technologies to measure these hormonal and genotypic biomarkers.  These techniques included LCMS (liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry), a highly sensitive and specific  approach that can determine the urinary concentrations of multiple hormones simultaneously, thus saving cost and time compared to measuring each hormone individually. Genotypes for a set of 250,000 SNPs (single nucleotide polymorphism) were determined with the HumanExome BeadChip, a technique that requires high quality DNA.  With extensive testing, we developed an optimal protocol for the extraction from saliva samples of the necessary volumes of high quality DNA.  We identified a significant SNP, exm562556 (rs34068461), associated with variation in fertility (fertility highest in GG genotype than in GT genotype which was higher than TT genotype). This variant is in a gene that encodes a protein thought to be involved in centrosomal or ciliary functions. Mutations in this gene also cause Leber congenital amaurosis type V, a syndrome including congenital blindness.  The broader impacts of this project included training and professional development for two post-doctoral scholars and development of new collaborations between the Departments of Chemistry and Anthropology at Indiana University, Bloomington (IUB), and between IUB and the School of Medicine (IUPUI in Indianapolis). We have also strengthened ties between IU and German colleagues, who assisted us in transferring their LCMS protocol to IUB. We continue to improve this protocol to make it faster, less costly and more widely available.  This project has also provided valuable technological tools for a new multi-season investigation, now underway, of  the effects of extremes in light exposure on steroid hormone concentrations.  Shift workers are at higher risk for several diseases including certain cancers associated with high steroid hormone levels. One cause of this higher risk may be greater light exposure during the night, which may increase steroid hormone production and may also negatively impact immune functioning. The new project is the first study to concurrently measure hormone levels and immune functioning in humans during two conditions of extremely long exposure to light (the Arctic summer) and extremely short exposure to light (the Arctic winter).         Last Modified: 01/28/2017       Submitted by: Virginia J Vitzthum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
