<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Extended Life Implantable Biosensor Platform</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/20/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>88036.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>88036</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Massood Tabib-Azar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objective:&lt;br/&gt;The objective is to develop a microfabricated biosensing platform based on Glucose Binding Protein (GBP) that continuously and reliably measures glucose levels in the hypoglycemic, normal, and hyperglycemic range.  The platform will consist of three components: a glucose-sensing array based on the electrochemical detection of glucose using the model enzyme glucose oxidase (GOx), an independent power supply, and a telemetry system.  The performance of this biosensing array will be compared with that of the well-established GOx glucose biosensor.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The project has significance beyond blood glucose monitoring, since identical miniaturized biosensing platforms can be utilized for other applications with a wide range of other biosensors.  In addition, multiple sensors selective to a series of analytes can be incorporated in different reservoirs within a single device, allowing the measurement of multiple analytes.  Moreover, this platform can be utilized as a responsive drug delivery system.  Such a system integrates reservoirs loaded with miniature sensors with drug-containing reservoirs.  Finally, the proposed platforms should result in enabling technologies that will find applications in individualized medicine.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;The work will involve students at both, the graduate and undergraduate levels.  Such work will foster interdisciplinary interactions and will provide the students with the necessary skills and knowledge for the design and development of novel biotechnologies.  The investigators plan to broadly disseminate the results of this work and raise the awareness of the general public in diabetes research, biosensing, hybrid systems, and device miniaturization.  This will be accomplished through participation in workshops and outreach programs.  The newly developed technologies will be highlighted in bioengineering courses.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1142376</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sylvia</FirstName>
<LastName>Daunert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sylvia Daunert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sdaunert@med.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3052434005</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Miami School of Medicine</Name>
<CityName>Coral Gables</CityName>
<ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052780918</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004146619</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami School of Medicine]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331016129</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>099E</Code>
<Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~30719</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~57317</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">During this grant funding period we progressed toward the development of glucose sensors with extended service lives and altered activity making them suitable for detection in all the glucose ranges, including the hypoglycemic, normal, and hyperglycemic glucose levels. We first developed and optimized a glucose sensor for the integration in an implantable device. The sensor was based on the immobilization of an acrylamide-based hydrogel containing glucose oxidase on a gold/polypyrrole (Au/PPy) flap which covered a microliter-volume vial. .&nbsp; The ability of the immobilized hydrogel to monitor small changes in glucose was investigated. The sensor was able to monitor changes in glucose concentration throughout the physiological range.The extended life of the sensor was addressed by implementing an array of hydrogel microsensors covered in individual microvials and as one sensor will begin to fail a fresh could be put into action. The feasilbility of this design was then proved by the reproducibility between microsensors on different flaps. A variety of different Au/PPy flap designs were also investigated.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">We investigated methods to not only enhance the lifetime of the device as a whole but also to enhance the lifetime and activity of individual sensor. To that end, we designed and developed new glucose recognition proteins (GRPs) by truncating the full length glucose/galactose binding protein from <em>E. coli</em> glucose galactose binding protein (GBP), and by globally incorporating unnatural amino acids with the structure of GRPs. Three truncated fragments of GBP (tGRP1, tGRP2, and tGRP3) were engineered based on a rational design to maintain the glucose binding ability as well as the ability to undergo conformational change on binding to glucose. The three different proteins were expressed in <em>E. coli</em> and chemically modified via site-selective labeling of a unique Cys residue with a fluorescent probe, namely 7-diethylamino-3-((((2-maleimidyl)ethyl)amino)carbonyl) coumarin (MDCC) to determine the glucose binding ability. Since tGRP3, the smallest truncated fragment of GBP had most of the amino acids removed required to be functional and therefore it lacked any glucose binding activity. However, tGRP1 and tGRP2 were able to respond to changes in glucose which was reflected by the quenching in the fluorescence emission from the MDCC-labeled tGRPs on binding to glucose It was found that as the protein was increasingly truncated, the apparent K<sub>D&shy;</sub> observed was increased, thus decreasing its affinity for glucose. Therefore, truncating GBP allowed for the modulation of the binding constant, which in turn, facilitated the utilization of GBP for the development of glucose biosensor for detection in physiological ranges. Furthermore, the alteration of protein sequence by global incorporation of unnatural amino acids in full length GBP and its truncated fragments (tGRP1 and tGRP2) was investigated as a tool to alter activity and thermal stability of these proteins. Fluorinated tryptophan (5-fluorotryptophan, FW) and leucine (5,5,5-trifluoroleucine, FL) were incorporated in the GRPs using a media-shift method wherein the bacteria is first grown in a medium enriched with all 20 amino acids, and then transferred to a medium lacking the 20<sup>th</sup> amino acid, which is then replaced by its unnatural analogue. By utilizing this method we were able to replace all the natural tryptophans or leucines by their unnatural analogues in GBP which was confirmed by LC-ESI-MS-MS. Glucose binding activity was maintained in the unnatural proteins. It was observed that the incorporation of FLs resulted in a higher increase in K<sub>D</sub>s as compared to those with FWs which can be attributed to the greater number of leucines than tryptophans in proteins. Thermal stability of the unnatural amino acid incor...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[During this grant funding period we progressed toward the development of glucose sensors with extended service lives and altered activity making them suitable for detection in all the glucose ranges, including the hypoglycemic, normal, and hyperglycemic glucose levels. We first developed and optimized a glucose sensor for the integration in an implantable device. The sensor was based on the immobilization of an acrylamide-based hydrogel containing glucose oxidase on a gold/polypyrrole (Au/PPy) flap which covered a microliter-volume vial. .  The ability of the immobilized hydrogel to monitor small changes in glucose was investigated. The sensor was able to monitor changes in glucose concentration throughout the physiological range.The extended life of the sensor was addressed by implementing an array of hydrogel microsensors covered in individual microvials and as one sensor will begin to fail a fresh could be put into action. The feasilbility of this design was then proved by the reproducibility between microsensors on different flaps. A variety of different Au/PPy flap designs were also investigated. We investigated methods to not only enhance the lifetime of the device as a whole but also to enhance the lifetime and activity of individual sensor. To that end, we designed and developed new glucose recognition proteins (GRPs) by truncating the full length glucose/galactose binding protein from E. coli glucose galactose binding protein (GBP), and by globally incorporating unnatural amino acids with the structure of GRPs. Three truncated fragments of GBP (tGRP1, tGRP2, and tGRP3) were engineered based on a rational design to maintain the glucose binding ability as well as the ability to undergo conformational change on binding to glucose. The three different proteins were expressed in E. coli and chemically modified via site-selective labeling of a unique Cys residue with a fluorescent probe, namely 7-diethylamino-3-((((2-maleimidyl)ethyl)amino)carbonyl) coumarin (MDCC) to determine the glucose binding ability. Since tGRP3, the smallest truncated fragment of GBP had most of the amino acids removed required to be functional and therefore it lacked any glucose binding activity. However, tGRP1 and tGRP2 were able to respond to changes in glucose which was reflected by the quenching in the fluorescence emission from the MDCC-labeled tGRPs on binding to glucose It was found that as the protein was increasingly truncated, the apparent KD&shy; observed was increased, thus decreasing its affinity for glucose. Therefore, truncating GBP allowed for the modulation of the binding constant, which in turn, facilitated the utilization of GBP for the development of glucose biosensor for detection in physiological ranges. Furthermore, the alteration of protein sequence by global incorporation of unnatural amino acids in full length GBP and its truncated fragments (tGRP1 and tGRP2) was investigated as a tool to alter activity and thermal stability of these proteins. Fluorinated tryptophan (5-fluorotryptophan, FW) and leucine (5,5,5-trifluoroleucine, FL) were incorporated in the GRPs using a media-shift method wherein the bacteria is first grown in a medium enriched with all 20 amino acids, and then transferred to a medium lacking the 20th amino acid, which is then replaced by its unnatural analogue. By utilizing this method we were able to replace all the natural tryptophans or leucines by their unnatural analogues in GBP which was confirmed by LC-ESI-MS-MS. Glucose binding activity was maintained in the unnatural proteins. It was observed that the incorporation of FLs resulted in a higher increase in KDs as compared to those with FWs which can be attributed to the greater number of leucines than tryptophans in proteins. Thermal stability of the unnatural amino acid incorporated GRPs (uGRPs) was investigated by circular dichroism. Incorporation of FW and FL into both tGRPs resulted in enhanced thermal stability when compared to the full length GB...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
