<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Developing an Antarctic Tephra Database for Interdisciplinary Paleoclimate Research (AntT)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>365095.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>365095</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mstiegli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924354</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many key questions in climate research (e.g. relative timing of climate events in different geographic areas, climate-forcing mechanisms, natural threshold levels in the climate system) are dependent on accurate reconstructions of the temporal and spatial distribution of past rapid climate change events in continental, atmospheric, marine and polar realms. This collaborative interdisciplinary research project aims to consolidate, into a single user-friendly database, information about volcanic products detected in Antarctica. By consolidating information about volcanic sources, and physical and geochemical characteristics of volcanic products, this systematic data collection approach will improve the ability of researchers to identify volcanic ash, or tephra, from specific volcanic eruptions that may be spread over large areas in a geologically instantaneous amount of time. Development of this database will assist in the identification and cross-correlation of time intervals in various paleoclimate archives that contain volcanic layers from often unknown sources. The AntT project relies on a cyberinfrastructure framework developed in house through NSF funded CDI-Type I: CiiWork for data assimilation, interpretation and open distribution model. In addition to collection and integration of existing information about volcanic products, this project will focus on filling the information gaps about unique physico-chemical characteristics of very fine (&lt;3 micrometer) volcanic particles  (cryptotephra) that are present in Antarctic ice cores. This component of research will involve improving analytical methodology for detecting cryptotephra layers in ice, and will train a new generation of scientists to apply an array of modern state?of?the-art instrumentation available to the project team. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The recognized importance of tephra in establishing a chronological framework for volcanic and sedimentary successions has already resulted in the development of robust regional tephrochronological frameworks (e.g. Europe, Kamchatka, New Zealand, Western North America). The AntT project will provide this framework for Antarctic tephrochronology, as needed for precise correlation records between Antarctic ice cores  (e.g. WAIS Divide, RICE, ITASE) and global paleoclimate archives. The results of AntT will be of particular significance to climatologists, paleoclimatologists, atmospheric chemists, geochemists, climate modelers, solar-terrestrial physicists, environmental statisticians, and policy makers for designing solutions to mitigate or cope with likely future impacts of climate change events on modern society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1142007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Yates</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin G Yates</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yates@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812154</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000171936</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrei</FirstName>
<LastName>Kurbatov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrei V Kurbatov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akurbatov@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812840</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162139</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerbi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher C Gerbi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christopher.gerbi@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812153</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186875787</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071750426</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>Orono</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5292</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5407</Code>
<Text>Polar Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~365095</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A collaborative effort between the University of Maine (UM) and New Mexico Tech (NMT) resulted in the development of new cyberinfrastructure framework designed to greatly simplify access to volcanological data sets collected in Antarctica and adjacent areas. An easy-to-use, open source, publicly available web based platform mimics typical research workflow required to characterize and correlate volcanic products preserved in Antarctic paleoclimate archives with the specific source volcanic eruption. The project was also focused on broadening the number of records, stored in the system, from major prehistorical tropical and regional volcanic eruptions. After a major redesign of methodology for extraction and geochemical analyses, a new protocol that greatly improves capturing of ultra fine (~5 &mu;m) volcanic ash (cryptotephra) particles from ice cores has been developed. The new sampling technique lead to the discovery of previously undetected in ice cores volcanic products from several major historical and prehistorical volcanic eruptions from Antarctica, New Zealand, South America and Indonesia.</p> <p>Improved detection and parametrization of cryptotephra in Antarctic ice cores and simplified access to all relevant information via the AntT web site will result in better parametrization of the impacts of prehistorical volcanic eruptions in climate models, improve global history of Earth's volcanism, and contribute to improving volcanic hazards mitigation from super eruptions of the past.</p> <p>The intergrated project educational component included training a new generation of scientists to work in an interdisciplinary research setting while acquiring new skills ranging from cutting edge use of geochemical instrumentation, material science methods, glaciology, paleoclimatology and computer science. This project provided support for five graduate students (one Ph.D. student, Nels Iverson, at NMT, partial support to UM computer science Ph.D. student Mark Royer and three MS students: Donna Kalteyer, Sarah Wheatley, Laura Hartman) and several undergraduate students at UM.&nbsp;&nbsp; The broader impact component of this project was continuous efforts of the PIs in fostering and promoting international cooperation in the tephra-in-ice community.&nbsp; Kurbatov and Dunbar have been collaborating with European and US tephra researchers for a number of years, sharing data and working collaboratively on tephra preparation techniques and correlations. These activities have led to several long-term initiatives to foster future information science and technology driven advances in the field of volcanology.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Andrei&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kurbatov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A collaborative effort between the University of Maine (UM) and New Mexico Tech (NMT) resulted in the development of new cyberinfrastructure framework designed to greatly simplify access to volcanological data sets collected in Antarctica and adjacent areas. An easy-to-use, open source, publicly available web based platform mimics typical research workflow required to characterize and correlate volcanic products preserved in Antarctic paleoclimate archives with the specific source volcanic eruption. The project was also focused on broadening the number of records, stored in the system, from major prehistorical tropical and regional volcanic eruptions. After a major redesign of methodology for extraction and geochemical analyses, a new protocol that greatly improves capturing of ultra fine (~5 &mu;m) volcanic ash (cryptotephra) particles from ice cores has been developed. The new sampling technique lead to the discovery of previously undetected in ice cores volcanic products from several major historical and prehistorical volcanic eruptions from Antarctica, New Zealand, South America and Indonesia.  Improved detection and parametrization of cryptotephra in Antarctic ice cores and simplified access to all relevant information via the AntT web site will result in better parametrization of the impacts of prehistorical volcanic eruptions in climate models, improve global history of Earth's volcanism, and contribute to improving volcanic hazards mitigation from super eruptions of the past.  The intergrated project educational component included training a new generation of scientists to work in an interdisciplinary research setting while acquiring new skills ranging from cutting edge use of geochemical instrumentation, material science methods, glaciology, paleoclimatology and computer science. This project provided support for five graduate students (one Ph.D. student, Nels Iverson, at NMT, partial support to UM computer science Ph.D. student Mark Royer and three MS students: Donna Kalteyer, Sarah Wheatley, Laura Hartman) and several undergraduate students at UM.   The broader impact component of this project was continuous efforts of the PIs in fostering and promoting international cooperation in the tephra-in-ice community.  Kurbatov and Dunbar have been collaborating with European and US tephra researchers for a number of years, sharing data and working collaboratively on tephra preparation techniques and correlations. These activities have led to several long-term initiatives to foster future information science and technology driven advances in the field of volcanology.       Last Modified: 10/04/2017       Submitted by: Andrei V Kurbatov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
