<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Targeted Nanoparticle Delivery Agent for Treatment of Adult Leukemia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149848.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>164848</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to explore the application of a targeted nanodelivery system for both treatment and efficacy monitoring in patients with adult leukemia. Unlike solid tumors, for which surgery, radiation, and conventional treatments are an option, leukemias are cancers of the blood, which have very poor prognosis due to the fact that they are disseminated diseases from inception. In this project, the targeted and drug-filled nanoparticle will be optimized for effective tumor killing in cell culture, followed by validation using established in-vivo methods for adult leukemia in a mouse model.  It is expected that this targeted nanodelivery system will increase the therapeutic window and minimize systemic therapy related toxicity, demonstrating the superior margin of safety compared to the standard methods for treatment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impact of this project will be the potential to provide a technology that is capable of delivering a wide array of drug molecules (hydrophilic and hydrophobic) or drug cocktails using multiple tissue targeting ligands. The specific focus of this project is adult acute leukemia for which there is currently no curative treatment, and the adult survival rate is only 30%.  Highly robust, customizable, stable, and easy to manufacture, this particle delivery system is anticipated to make a major impact on the treatment of adult leukemia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1143342</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Nagy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon O Nagy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jon.nagy@nagyconsult.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4065868420</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553465</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/16/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NanoValent Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<ZipCode>597184012</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4065868420</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>910 Technology BLVD STE G</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>788166986</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NANOVALENT PHARMACEUTICALS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NanoValent Pharmaceuticals, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597186850</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[910 Technology Blvd STE G]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~164848</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><!--   @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1791491579 18 0 131231 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1791491579 18 0 131231 0;}   p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  mso-bidi-font-size:10.0pt;  font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-no-proof:yes;} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-size:10.0pt;  mso-ansi-font-size:10.0pt;  mso-bidi-font-size:10.0pt;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-fareast-language:JA;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.25in 1.0in 1.25in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --></p> <!--   @font-face  {font-family:Arial;  panose-1:2 11 6 4 2 2 2 2 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536859905 -1073711037 9 0 511 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1791491579 18 0 131231 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1107305727 0 0 415 0;}   p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  mso-bidi-font-size:10.0pt;  font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-no-proof:yes;} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-size:10.0pt;  mso-ansi-font-size:10.0pt;  mso-bidi-font-size:10.0pt;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-fareast-language:JA;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.25in 1.0in 1.25in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --> <p class="MsoNormal" style="mso-pagination: none; mso-layout-grid-align: none; text-autospace: none;"><span style="font-size: 11.0pt; font-family: Arial; mso-fareast-language: JA; mso-no-proof: no;">This NSF Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project entitled, &ldquo;Targeted Nanoparticle Delivery Agent for Treatment of Adult Leukemia,&rdquo; awarded to NanoValent Pharmaceuticals, Inc. has demonstrated proof of principle that proprietary, targeted nanoparticles are capable of carrying conventional cancer drugs to tumor cells. While therapeutic nanoparticles have been introduced into clinical practice (Abraxane<sup>TM</sup> and Doxil<sup>TM</sup>) and others are in development, none to our knowledge have been developed that show tumor target specificity (as opposed to increased affinity). We are endeavoring to show that targeted delivery of cancer therapy can improve therapeutic response while minimizing the toxic effects on healthy tissue, for virtually any cancer treatment. The innovation of this approach was demonstrated by dramatically reducing the tumor burden in a mouse injected with human leukemia cells. The ability to demonstrate this objective is both highly significant and transformative, as most efforts to date have shown drawbacks in the targeting of nanoparticles or delivery of therapeutic content. Throu...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This NSF Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project entitled, "Targeted Nanoparticle Delivery Agent for Treatment of Adult Leukemia," awarded to NanoValent Pharmaceuticals, Inc. has demonstrated proof of principle that proprietary, targeted nanoparticles are capable of carrying conventional cancer drugs to tumor cells. While therapeutic nanoparticles have been introduced into clinical practice (AbraxaneTM and DoxilTM) and others are in development, none to our knowledge have been developed that show tumor target specificity (as opposed to increased affinity). We are endeavoring to show that targeted delivery of cancer therapy can improve therapeutic response while minimizing the toxic effects on healthy tissue, for virtually any cancer treatment. The innovation of this approach was demonstrated by dramatically reducing the tumor burden in a mouse injected with human leukemia cells. The ability to demonstrate this objective is both highly significant and transformative, as most efforts to date have shown drawbacks in the targeting of nanoparticles or delivery of therapeutic content. Through this study, the field of knowledge with respect to cancer treatment by nanoscopic-sized particles has been significantly advanced. This project supports the NSF objectives of furthering research in bioengineering, with treatment-related goals, by applying engineering principles to problems in medicine. Completion of this phase of the project allows NanoValent to advance closer to completing preclinical studies in anticipation of human clinical testing, requiring investigational new drug (IND) status for this material with the FDA.    The broader societal implication of realizing a new, effective treatment for adult leukemia is tremendous.  Within the U.S. alone, there are an estimated 274,930 people living with leukemia. In 2011, it is estimated that 44,600 people (25,320 men and 19,280 women) were diagnosed with leukemia, including 10 times as many adults as children and adolescents, with the median age at diagnosis being 66 years. Also in 2011, 21,780 of those already afflicted with leukemia were expected to die from the disease. The American Cancer Society projects even higher figures for 2012, estimating that 47,150 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with leukemia and that approximately 23,540 patients will die from it.  As off target toxicity is driving the level of drug that a leukemia patient can receive, the fatality rate will be dramatically reduced if more drug substance can be delivered to the tumor with concomitant avoidance of toxicity to normal tissues. The nanoparticle technology described here is well positioned to advance the drug delivery field on a scientific level by demonstrating efficient delivery of therapeutics to leukemia cells. Combined with tumor delivery this technology could facilitate highly effective, æpersonalizedÆ cancer therapy that is not currently possible with routine systemic therapy.        Last Modified: 04/16/2013       Submitted by: Jon O Nagy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
