<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Improved Characterization and Prediction of Antarctic Weather and Climate Though Utilization of CONCORDIASI Data Set</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>273473.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>273473</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Based on a successful multidisciplinary and international (Fr-US) CONCORDIASI campaign, an evaluation of high resolution weather simulations using AMPS (Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System) code will be made by comparing modeled and observed data. The extensive CONCORDIASI observation set will allow unprecedented comparison of the regional performance of the model outputs over Antarctica and the Southern Ocean.  Approximately 640 dropsondes were deployed from some 13 balloon flights during a 7 week period in 2010. The dropsondes yield in-situ profiles of wind, temperature, pressure  and humidity through the Antarctic atmosphere. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In turn the performance of the model may serve as diagnostic for a number of key meteorological phenomena in the Antarctic, including atmospheric circulation and dynamics, and the ability to determine momentum balance, moisture and radiation over the continent during austral summertime. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Educational goals include graduate student training and involvement, and potentially enhanced operational skill of forecast models such as AMPS, used operationally in the USAP program</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1143790</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Parsons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David B Parsons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dparsons@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4053258565</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000190499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Cavallo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Cavallo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cavallo@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065500829</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000554501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Five Partners Place, Suite 3100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>848348348</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046862181</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oklahoma Norman Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Norman</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730195300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 David L. Boren Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5112</Code>
<Text>ANT Earth Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~273473</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Projections of changes in weather and climate in Antarctica is critical for the economy, society and environmental conditions of the world. For example, if the Antarctic ice sheet melted, sea levels are estimated to rise by about 60 m (about 200 feet). In-situ measurements are sparse in Antarctica, so our project undertook a complex field campaign with long duration balloons that deployed sensors to provide the first dense network of observations of the atmosphere over the continent of Antarctica and the surrounding ice sheet. The average time of these balloon flights was 69 days. The sensors deployed from these balloons were called dropsondes that measure temperature, humidity, winds and pressure in a manner similar to the observations deployed from aircraft into hurricanes.These measurements were used to discover new aspects of the atmospheric conditions, such as conditions near the surface of the sea ice surrounding the continent and surprisingly warm with weak temperature inverstions. This finding has impications for the prediction of sea ice.</p> <p>The project also worked to find deficiences in weather and climate models utilized to predict conditions in this region. One broader impacts of this work will be to reduce model errors and improve forecasts of conditions over this region. An important aspect of this work was to propose a change in how the AMPS (Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System) model used by the NSF community is initialized. Since this model is utilized for logistical operations to and from the ice sheet, improvements in this model will increase public safety and efficiency. Improved forecasts can reduce costs through decreasing the number of flights that are turned back due to weather. Each flight costs between $100,000 and $150,000.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;B&nbsp;Parsons</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Projections of changes in weather and climate in Antarctica is critical for the economy, society and environmental conditions of the world. For example, if the Antarctic ice sheet melted, sea levels are estimated to rise by about 60 m (about 200 feet). In-situ measurements are sparse in Antarctica, so our project undertook a complex field campaign with long duration balloons that deployed sensors to provide the first dense network of observations of the atmosphere over the continent of Antarctica and the surrounding ice sheet. The average time of these balloon flights was 69 days. The sensors deployed from these balloons were called dropsondes that measure temperature, humidity, winds and pressure in a manner similar to the observations deployed from aircraft into hurricanes.These measurements were used to discover new aspects of the atmospheric conditions, such as conditions near the surface of the sea ice surrounding the continent and surprisingly warm with weak temperature inverstions. This finding has impications for the prediction of sea ice.  The project also worked to find deficiences in weather and climate models utilized to predict conditions in this region. One broader impacts of this work will be to reduce model errors and improve forecasts of conditions over this region. An important aspect of this work was to propose a change in how the AMPS (Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System) model used by the NSF community is initialized. Since this model is utilized for logistical operations to and from the ice sheet, improvements in this model will increase public safety and efficiency. Improved forecasts can reduce costs through decreasing the number of flights that are turned back due to weather. Each flight costs between $100,000 and $150,000.       Last Modified: 01/17/2018       Submitted by: David B Parsons]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
