<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PC3: Collaborative Research: Wireless Sensor Networks for Protecting Wildlife and Humans</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>178209.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>262212</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harriet Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a collaborative project between Ohio State University, Cornell University, The Indian Institute of Science - Bangalore, the Wildlife Institute of India, and the Indian Institute of Information Technology - Allahabad.  The dramatic dwindling of forests and concomitant escalation in human-wildlife conflicts are resulting in broad environmental impact, including large economic and social costs, increasing human deaths in areas used by large mammals, and animal population decline. This project enables a baseline operational wireless sensor network system for protection of animals, humans, and the forest.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The forest setting involves complex scenes demanding the discrimination of several targets of interest in a highly cluttered setting as well as discrimination of their intent and behaviors. Activity patterns evolve in a naturally adversarial environment. The system architecture being developed integrates in a transformative way a suitably rich set of sensing modalities with intent inferencing, learning, optimization, and deployment techniques, to monitor a diverse set of targets. Mature system components are to be deployed in Panna, a tiger reserve in central India, in close cooperation with domain experts and forestry management. The project is a collaboration between researchers in the US and India who are substantially involved in complementary aspects of wildlife related research. A subsequent protection-centric effort in the US is envisioned that builds upon the lessons learned by this effort.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful realization of system components and a baseline system would lead to an assessment of the potential benefits of using wireless sensor networks for protection related to forests and potential transition into production use. Over time, this will help establish credible early-warning systems, and monitoring protocols for animal use of human areas and human use of forest areas that can support recovery efforts.  This project is part of the Pervasive Communications and Computing Collaboration (PC3) initiative.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1143685</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anish</FirstName>
<LastName>Arora</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anish K Arora</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anish@cse.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142648771</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000378457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2015 Neil Av]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~178209</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~84003</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project designed and developed wireless sensor network (WSN) technology for an early warning system in national parks that protects flagship animal species and neighboring human settlers--the former from poachers/hostile intruders and the latter from animal excursion incidents.&nbsp; </span></p> <p><span>The technology was deployed in the summer of 2014 in Panna Tiger Reserve, in Madhya Pradesh, India, in cooperation with our Indian partners as well as other stakeholders.&nbsp; Two types of Virtual Fences, based on arrays of micropower radar sensors and on fiber optical cables, were tested successfully.&nbsp; Detection and classification reports of animals and humans from these Virtual Fences were sent in near real time over a long-lived, multi-hop wireless network to a Forest Ranger station.&nbsp; </span></p> <p><span>The success of this deployment led to the adoption of OSU&rsquo;s radar Virtual Fence and wireless mesh network in a rhino park in South Africa, with support from the World Wildlife Fund and Google Impact.&nbsp; (Rhino poaching is in a crisis state in South Africa.) OSU has also been asked to plan a tiger reserve deployment in Pench Tiger Reserve in India in late 2016.</span></p> <p><span>From a basis science perspective, the project advanced the robustness of classification and wireless networking, which is important given the complex clutter and dynamic environment encountered in the forest setting.&nbsp; Methods for making data driven learning of low power algorithms robust to diverse environments were developed, published, and demonstrated in the context of human-animal classification with the radar, people counting with the radar, and multi-hop relay network deployment.&nbsp; </span></p> <p><span>Other outcomes of interest include: We organized three interdisciplinary workshops (in Panna, India in December 2011, Phitsanulok, Thailand in December 2012, and Dehradun, India in December 2014) that brought together federal and state level governmental agencies, non-governmental organizations, domain scientists, technologists, and students) on WSN technologies for forest protection. &nbsp;Also, as part of our collaboration with Cornell University, we mentored a postdoc student who has since become a faculty member in a premier computer science program.&nbsp; We graduated a doctoral student whose dissertation was primary on the robust classification work studied in this effort.&nbsp; The Ph.D. dissertation of a current student will also derive largely from the research conducted in this effort. We shared this work with distinguished and student attendees of Science Conclaves organized at the Indian Institute of Information Technology, Allahabad, India in 2013 and 2014.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Anish&nbsp;K&nbsp;Arora</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project designed and developed wireless sensor network (WSN) technology for an early warning system in national parks that protects flagship animal species and neighboring human settlers--the former from poachers/hostile intruders and the latter from animal excursion incidents.    The technology was deployed in the summer of 2014 in Panna Tiger Reserve, in Madhya Pradesh, India, in cooperation with our Indian partners as well as other stakeholders.  Two types of Virtual Fences, based on arrays of micropower radar sensors and on fiber optical cables, were tested successfully.  Detection and classification reports of animals and humans from these Virtual Fences were sent in near real time over a long-lived, multi-hop wireless network to a Forest Ranger station.    The success of this deployment led to the adoption of OSUÆs radar Virtual Fence and wireless mesh network in a rhino park in South Africa, with support from the World Wildlife Fund and Google Impact.  (Rhino poaching is in a crisis state in South Africa.) OSU has also been asked to plan a tiger reserve deployment in Pench Tiger Reserve in India in late 2016.  From a basis science perspective, the project advanced the robustness of classification and wireless networking, which is important given the complex clutter and dynamic environment encountered in the forest setting.  Methods for making data driven learning of low power algorithms robust to diverse environments were developed, published, and demonstrated in the context of human-animal classification with the radar, people counting with the radar, and multi-hop relay network deployment.    Other outcomes of interest include: We organized three interdisciplinary workshops (in Panna, India in December 2011, Phitsanulok, Thailand in December 2012, and Dehradun, India in December 2014) that brought together federal and state level governmental agencies, non-governmental organizations, domain scientists, technologists, and students) on WSN technologies for forest protection.  Also, as part of our collaboration with Cornell University, we mentored a postdoc student who has since become a faculty member in a premier computer science program.  We graduated a doctoral student whose dissertation was primary on the robust classification work studied in this effort.  The Ph.D. dissertation of a current student will also derive largely from the research conducted in this effort. We shared this work with distinguished and student attendees of Science Conclaves organized at the Indian Institute of Information Technology, Allahabad, India in 2013 and 2014.       Last Modified: 03/16/2016       Submitted by: Anish K Arora]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
