<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>OPUS: Ecology and Complexity of the Coffee Farm</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>170000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Much of the world's land is now used for agriculture and the interactions between agricultural and natural systems is increasingly important to sustaining both.  For example, natural systems provide organisms that pollinate and control pests on crops, and farms can support a diversity of native species that co-exist with agriculture.   However, this mutual benefit depends strongly on how farms are managed: highly intensive agriculture may not be sustainable, whereas less intensive methods may, in the long run, yield more.  Coffee farms are a model system in which to study how farms can be managed to be ecologically sustainable, and this project will support a synthesis of two decades of study by two of the world?s leading researchers on biodiversity, ecosystem function, and complex interactions between organisms in coffee plantations in Central America.  The main scientific result will be a book on the agroecology of coffee aimed at students and also informative to more senior scientists and managers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project for improving agriculture and maintaining the environment are manifest.  The researchers will further enhance these impacts by posting illustrated guides on a website for easy access, and collaborating with a Mexican colleague to produce educational, interactive, simulation models to help farmers, students, and other stake holders to understand agroecosystems using coffee plantations as a model.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1144923</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivette</FirstName>
<LastName>Perfecto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivette Perfecto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>perfecto@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641433</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000479266</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7565</Code>
<Text>OPUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>My research for the past 20 years has been concentrated on the intersection between biodiversity and agricultural landscapes, in particular those dominated by coffee production in Mesoamerica. With the OPUS grant I, along with my colleague John Vandermeer, wrote and published a book that provides a synthesis of what we have learned over this period about ecological theory using coffee as a model system.&nbsp; We used a dialectical/complexity approach to synthesize the wealth of information that has been generated by us, our students and other researchers focusing on complex ecological interactions at various scales. During the synthesis process we examined issues of historicity, interconnections, heterogeneity, and integration of levels to generate a new understanding of ecological complexity within agricultural landscapes. With this book project we tried to provide a new lens for the study of agricultural systems that focus on biodiversity and complexity and to inspire a new cadre of students to embrace complexity when studying agroecosystems. The book is now being translated into Spanish since there has been great interest among Latin American coffee researchers and ecologists interested in ecological complexity. The book is available in printed form as well as electronically.</p> <p>In addition to the book we also published a review paper in the Annual Reviews of Ecology, Evolution and Systematics.</p> <p>Another important outcome of the project was a board game, <em>Azteca Chess</em>, based on a network of ecological interactions unveiled during our studies of the ecology of the coffee agroecosystem. <em>Azteca Chess&rsquo;</em> aim is engaging farmers, students, and the general public in a fun way to learn about ecological complexity. In collaboration with Dr. Luis Garcia Barrios, from ECOSUR, Mexico, we develop this highly graphic, fun and pedagogic interactive game and conducted numerous workshop/tournaments with the participation of close to a 100 farmers and 50 students from Latin America and the U.S.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Ivette&nbsp;Perfecto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ My research for the past 20 years has been concentrated on the intersection between biodiversity and agricultural landscapes, in particular those dominated by coffee production in Mesoamerica. With the OPUS grant I, along with my colleague John Vandermeer, wrote and published a book that provides a synthesis of what we have learned over this period about ecological theory using coffee as a model system.  We used a dialectical/complexity approach to synthesize the wealth of information that has been generated by us, our students and other researchers focusing on complex ecological interactions at various scales. During the synthesis process we examined issues of historicity, interconnections, heterogeneity, and integration of levels to generate a new understanding of ecological complexity within agricultural landscapes. With this book project we tried to provide a new lens for the study of agricultural systems that focus on biodiversity and complexity and to inspire a new cadre of students to embrace complexity when studying agroecosystems. The book is now being translated into Spanish since there has been great interest among Latin American coffee researchers and ecologists interested in ecological complexity. The book is available in printed form as well as electronically.  In addition to the book we also published a review paper in the Annual Reviews of Ecology, Evolution and Systematics.  Another important outcome of the project was a board game, Azteca Chess, based on a network of ecological interactions unveiled during our studies of the ecology of the coffee agroecosystem. Azteca ChessÆ aim is engaging farmers, students, and the general public in a fun way to learn about ecological complexity. In collaboration with Dr. Luis Garcia Barrios, from ECOSUR, Mexico, we develop this highly graphic, fun and pedagogic interactive game and conducted numerous workshop/tournaments with the participation of close to a 100 farmers and 50 students from Latin America and the U.S.       Last Modified: 02/14/2016       Submitted by: Ivette Perfecto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
