<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IGERT:  Solar Utilization Network (SUN)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3006642.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3006642</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010103</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship (IGERT) award focuses on the energy transition from the current fossil-fuel-based economy to one where solar energy harvested by means of photovoltaics, solar-thermal, and photosynthesis-driven bioenergy approaches will become a keystone in global human energy use. Scalability, efficiency and economy of these three technical solar energy conversion approaches, along with societal components such as sustainability policy and responsible energy use, will all be necessary for success. This program supports the interdisciplinary training of diverse student cohorts in multiple solar energy conversion areas at different scales, integrated with a policy and social understanding, thus educating the next generation of citizen-scientists, innovative thinkers and enlightened policy makers who can guide society toward a sustainable energy future.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:  In order to further enhance inclusion of students from all backgrounds, the SUN IGERT project will leverage agreements with schools and programs with significant enrollment of underrepresented groups, particularly Hispanics and Native Americans, to lower barriers for underrepresented minorities. Effective mentoring and use-inspired, application-oriented, integrative research projects will enhance retention in the program. This program will also provide the groundwork for a novel Energy Ph.D. program. Successes from our program can be emulated and adapted at other institutions nationally and globally, thus catalyzing the training of a much larger group of students who can shepherd society to a new, sustainable energy future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IGERT is an NSF-wide program intended to meet the challenges of educating U.S. Ph.D. scientists and engineers with the interdisciplinary background, deep knowledge in a chosen discipline, and the technical, professional, and personal skills needed for the career demands of the future. The program is intended to establish new models for graduate education and training in a fertile environment for collaborative research that transcends traditional disciplinary boundaries, and to engage students in understanding the processes by which research is translated to innovations for societal benefit.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1144616</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ana</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ana L Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ana.moore@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809652953</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000372073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Willem</FirstName>
<LastName>Vermaas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Willem F Vermaas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wim@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809656250</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315697</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Guston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David H Guston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.guston@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807278787</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000195728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jenefer</FirstName>
<LastName>Husman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jenefer E Husman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhusman@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413469564</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000392620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cesar</FirstName>
<LastName>Torres</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cesar I Torres</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cit@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807279689</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567174</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1335</Code>
<Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1997</Code>
<Text>NSF Research Traineeship (NRT)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1335</Code>
<Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~480479</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~682564</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~893649</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~949950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The IGERT-SUN program focused on educating the next generation of leaders who will need to seamlessly navigate a very transdisciplinary field in order to guide society toward a solar-based, sustainable energy future. &nbsp;An important, lasting outcome of the program was the establishment of an interdisciplinary Sustainable Energy PhD program at Arizona State University (ASU) that is designed to train doctoral students to see beyond disciplinary boundaries and to learn to work at the interface of science, engineering and public policy.&nbsp; Patterned after the interdisciplinary curriculum developed during the first four years of IGERT-SUN, the Doctor of Philosophy in Sustainable Energy program was officially launched in November 2016. &nbsp;The new program is a hallmark of the intellectual merit of the IGERT-SUN program.&nbsp; As indicated on the Sustainable Energy program's website, <a href="https://schoolofsustainability.asu.edu/degrees/doctor-philosophy-sustainable-energy/">https://schoolofsustainability.asu.edu/degrees/doctor-philosophy-sustainable-energy/</a>, students in the program "will conduct collaborative cross-disciplinary research integrating energy science with societal and policy insights."&nbsp; Graduates of the new Sustainable Energy PhD program will be uniquely poised to take on leadership roles in industry, government and academic institutions to transition society from a fossil fuel-based economy toward a sustainable energy future.</p> <p>An important aspect of interdisciplinary studies in the IGERT-SUN program was learning to design collaborative projects that addressed both cultural and disciplinary diversity. &nbsp;Students were asked to develop such projects as part of the IGERT-SUN course work and were encouraged to advance their ideas via the Competitive Innovation Incentive Fund (CIIF) portion of the program. &nbsp;In total the program sponsored six CIIF projects involving a total of 13 IGERT-SUN trainees and three independent collaborators. &nbsp;The CIIF projects exemplify the broader impacts of the IGERT-SUN program, and three of these projects are briefly mentioned here.&nbsp; First, in the WaterE project, IGERT-SUN trainees worked with the community of Mompos, Colombia to address water quality issues. They built a prototype solar-powered system to teach local students about water filtration and water quality, performed water testing and conducted surveys to evaluate energy access, water quality and perceptions on quality of life.&nbsp;</p> <p>In a second CIIF project trainees focused on helping to bring a sustainable waste management strategy to the rural community of Sittee River, Belize. &nbsp;In collaboration with the local community, they built an anaerobic digester to turn waste to biogas and taught classes at the local school on the basics of the engineering process to engage students in the project.&nbsp; Working with young women of color in Belize, the trainees, who were among the 25% of underrepresented minority students supported by the IGERT-SUN program, were inspired to start BioGals, an organization to empower women of color in the United States to conduct their research abroad, which in turn could inspire women of color abroad to pursue STEM fields. BioGals officially gained non-profit status on October 24, 2018 and reaches a larger audience through their website, <a href="https://www.biogals.com/">https://www.biogals.com/</a>, where interested students can find an application to join the team.</p> <p>Finally, in another CIIF project IGERT-SUN students collaborated with Sustainable Energy PhD students to address the energy needs of a hurricane-ravaged community center in Puerto Rico.&nbsp; The team worked closely with stakeholders in Puerto Rico to design a patent-pending retractable photovoltaic solar system that could be safely stowed in advance of a hurricane, allowing for a quick resumption of power following a storm. &nbsp;The system was successfully installed in July 2019.&nbsp; These three very diverse CIIF projects illustrate the power of collaboration across disciplines to impact real-world challenges.&nbsp;</p> <p>All IGERT-SUN trainees also had the opportunity to participate in one of two summer experiences: the Netherlands experience, which <strong>exposed trainees to two diverse solar energy research programs at Wageningen University and at the Technical University of Delft, and the Washington experience,</strong><strong> </strong>which was focused on government and science policy development and communicating complex technical information to a broader community.<strong>&nbsp; </strong>These experiences were designed to: 1) develop the students' ability to place research projects into a broader and more global perspective, and 2) develop the students' ability to effectively communicate the importance of their research. &nbsp;Students gained both direct and indirect value from these experiences and an overwhelming majority of participating students provided positive feedback to program evaluators and rated it very useful or better.</p> <p>In total the IGERT-SUN program supported 27 trainees across 11 STEM disciplines generating 51 journal articles in refereed publications, one non-refereed publication, seven book chapters, two patent applications, 26 conference publications and 140 conference presentations.&nbsp; Of the 12 trainees who have completed their schooling, two hold academic faculty positions, two hold post-doctoral fellowships, one is a research associate at a national laboratory, one works in an analytical laboratory, five work in various energy/sustainability-related industries and one works as a policy analyst.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Willem&nbsp;F&nbsp;Vermaas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The IGERT-SUN program focused on educating the next generation of leaders who will need to seamlessly navigate a very transdisciplinary field in order to guide society toward a solar-based, sustainable energy future.  An important, lasting outcome of the program was the establishment of an interdisciplinary Sustainable Energy PhD program at Arizona State University (ASU) that is designed to train doctoral students to see beyond disciplinary boundaries and to learn to work at the interface of science, engineering and public policy.  Patterned after the interdisciplinary curriculum developed during the first four years of IGERT-SUN, the Doctor of Philosophy in Sustainable Energy program was officially launched in November 2016.  The new program is a hallmark of the intellectual merit of the IGERT-SUN program.  As indicated on the Sustainable Energy program's website, https://schoolofsustainability.asu.edu/degrees/doctor-philosophy-sustainable-energy/, students in the program "will conduct collaborative cross-disciplinary research integrating energy science with societal and policy insights."  Graduates of the new Sustainable Energy PhD program will be uniquely poised to take on leadership roles in industry, government and academic institutions to transition society from a fossil fuel-based economy toward a sustainable energy future.  An important aspect of interdisciplinary studies in the IGERT-SUN program was learning to design collaborative projects that addressed both cultural and disciplinary diversity.  Students were asked to develop such projects as part of the IGERT-SUN course work and were encouraged to advance their ideas via the Competitive Innovation Incentive Fund (CIIF) portion of the program.  In total the program sponsored six CIIF projects involving a total of 13 IGERT-SUN trainees and three independent collaborators.  The CIIF projects exemplify the broader impacts of the IGERT-SUN program, and three of these projects are briefly mentioned here.  First, in the WaterE project, IGERT-SUN trainees worked with the community of Mompos, Colombia to address water quality issues. They built a prototype solar-powered system to teach local students about water filtration and water quality, performed water testing and conducted surveys to evaluate energy access, water quality and perceptions on quality of life.   In a second CIIF project trainees focused on helping to bring a sustainable waste management strategy to the rural community of Sittee River, Belize.  In collaboration with the local community, they built an anaerobic digester to turn waste to biogas and taught classes at the local school on the basics of the engineering process to engage students in the project.  Working with young women of color in Belize, the trainees, who were among the 25% of underrepresented minority students supported by the IGERT-SUN program, were inspired to start BioGals, an organization to empower women of color in the United States to conduct their research abroad, which in turn could inspire women of color abroad to pursue STEM fields. BioGals officially gained non-profit status on October 24, 2018 and reaches a larger audience through their website, https://www.biogals.com/, where interested students can find an application to join the team.  Finally, in another CIIF project IGERT-SUN students collaborated with Sustainable Energy PhD students to address the energy needs of a hurricane-ravaged community center in Puerto Rico.  The team worked closely with stakeholders in Puerto Rico to design a patent-pending retractable photovoltaic solar system that could be safely stowed in advance of a hurricane, allowing for a quick resumption of power following a storm.  The system was successfully installed in July 2019.  These three very diverse CIIF projects illustrate the power of collaboration across disciplines to impact real-world challenges.   All IGERT-SUN trainees also had the opportunity to participate in one of two summer experiences: the Netherlands experience, which exposed trainees to two diverse solar energy research programs at Wageningen University and at the Technical University of Delft, and the Washington experience, which was focused on government and science policy development and communicating complex technical information to a broader community.  These experiences were designed to: 1) develop the students' ability to place research projects into a broader and more global perspective, and 2) develop the students' ability to effectively communicate the importance of their research.  Students gained both direct and indirect value from these experiences and an overwhelming majority of participating students provided positive feedback to program evaluators and rated it very useful or better.  In total the IGERT-SUN program supported 27 trainees across 11 STEM disciplines generating 51 journal articles in refereed publications, one non-refereed publication, seven book chapters, two patent applications, 26 conference publications and 140 conference presentations.  Of the 12 trainees who have completed their schooling, two hold academic faculty positions, two hold post-doctoral fellowships, one is a research associate at a national laboratory, one works in an analytical laboratory, five work in various energy/sustainability-related industries and one works as a policy analyst.       Last Modified: 08/13/2019       Submitted by: Willem F Vermaas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
