<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IGERT: Soft Material Robotics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1491646.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2709035</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010103</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>IGERT: Soft Material Robotics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship (IGERT) award creates an interdisciplinary graduate program to  develop advances in the field of soft robotics. These machines, inspired by animals, will be capable of complex tasks that are difficult to achieve with conventional robots, suitable for close interactions with humans, and able to work in environmentally sensitive locations. The research will cross traditional disciplinary boundaries, employing novel biomaterials, exploiting cellular processes and tissue engineering methods, and using control strategies derived from evolutionary principles ? approaches that are comparatively rare in conventional robotics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The development of this new technology provides an exciting opportunity to train inventive and entrepreneurial future science and engineering leaders. IGERT trainees will train in multiple disciplines, including materials science, neuromechanics, mechanical control systems, computer science, artificial intelligence and product design. Novel collaborative training approaches include the formation of mentorship teams and an innovative problem solving-based model of education. IGERT trainees will exploit bioengineering approaches to machine design, fabricate and control new robotic devices to address a wide range of current medical, social and environmental challenges. For example, soft robots could be developed for internal medical diagnosis and delivery of therapeutics, or for search and rescue operations and bioremediation. The international partners, leaders in the emerging field of soft robots, will help trainees form collaborations and affiliations across the world. These students will bridge emerging areas of biology and engineering to create revolutionary new technologies including robots for human assistance and environmentally-friendly biodegradable robots. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IGERT is an NSF-wide program intended to meet the challenges of educating U.S. Ph.D. scientists and engineers with the interdisciplinary background, deep knowledge in a chosen discipline, and the technical, professional, and personal skills needed for the career demands of the future. The program is intended to establish new models for graduate education and training in a fertile environment for collaborative research that transcends traditional disciplinary boundaries, and to engage students in understanding the processes by which research is translated to innovations for societal benefit.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1144591</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Trimmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry A Trimmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barry.trimmer@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273924</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103223</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaplan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David L Kaplan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.kaplan@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273251</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162550</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021554237</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 Boston Av]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1335</Code>
<Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1997</Code>
<Text>NSF Research Traineeship (NRT)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8062</Code>
<Text>IGERT Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8063</Code>
<Text>IGERT Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8064</Code>
<Text>IGERT Materials Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1335</Code>
<Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1073597</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1157091</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~78347</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>IGERT: Soft Material Robotics&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 2012 - 2018. Tufts University</p> <p>The overall aim of this program was to build an interdisciplinary research and graduate education center for the new field of Soft Material Robotics. The program featured novel approaches to collaborative training. Its core science and engineering goal was to develop robust, adaptable, mobile machines that are impossible to achieve with conventional robots. This includes devices that are entirely soft, biocompatible and biodegradable.</p> <p>In terms of <strong><em>broader impacts</em></strong> and the development of human resources, the program involved 29 graduate student trainees: 11 have received their PhDs, 4 completed masters research and 12 are continuing work on their PhD theses. Students were enrolled in the Schools of Engineering and Arts and Sciences from the departments of Biology, Mechanical Engineering, Electrical and Computer Engineering, Civil and Environmental Engineering, Biomedical Engineering, Chemical and Biological Engineering and Computer Science and were co-mentored by professors in these different departments. During the funded period, faculty and students disseminated their IGERT-related work in 11 books or book chapters, 146 conference presentations or seminars and 110 peer reviewed publications and more are currently in process.</p> <p>New students attended an interdisciplinary "Boot Camp" and most took part in an Innovation Challenge training course. There were opportunities for extended, International Research Experiences and students visited labs and workshops in Italy, Switzerland, Japan and the United Kingdom. Students also participated in international conferences in Australia, Uruguay, Canada, France, Portugal, and Finland. Soft robotics continues to be an active field of research at Tufts University with the recent appointment of new tenure-track faculty members working at the forefront of the design and control of novel deformable machines.</p> <p>In addition to these broader training achievements the program initiated several major research directions of significant <strong><em>intellectual merit</em></strong> that are ongoing. This includes the design, fabrication and testing of a non-pneumatic, electrically-actuated crawling robot. This device was constructed primarily from compressible foam that allows it to change its size and shape dramatically. It has been used to explore different strategies for controlling soft robot locomotion and incorporates design concepts derived from studying animal movements. We expect to develop this prototype into a cheap and durable machine for searching and surveying in complex three-dimensional environments.</p> <p>In addition to addressing problems in mechanical control, students in the IGERT program explored methods for transmitting large amounts of sensory data efficiently. To mitigate some of the constraints that soft bodied robots place on conventional wiring, time-mode multipliers were included within the sensor circuitry allowing for both computation and conversion to be performed on the sensor platform. Additional work in this area introduced a novel and computationally efficient visual saliency algorithm for performing neurotrophic attention-based data reduction.</p> <p>Faculty and students are continuing related research in soft animal neuromechanics to improve our understanding of locomotion control. This includes recording how the nervous system coordinates muscle activity during climbing, crawling and rapid defensive behavior. Progress is also being made in understanding how sensory information contributes to movement adaptation in natural environments. Results from this work are being used to guide all aspects of soft robot design, fabrication and control.</p> <p>Another ongoing research area is the development of materials, tissues and microstructures for biomedical and robotic applications. IGERT students worked on engineered tendon-derived materials for nerve regeneration and muscle driven bio actuators. They also studied how fibrous biomaterials can be used to control the mechanical properties of swimming robots. A new research direction has been initiated to explore how tissue engineering with invertebrate cells can be exploited to grow sustainable, biodegradable, and ethically responsible, living robots.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Barry&nbsp;A&nbsp;Trimmer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1144591/1144591_10177121_1560886217179_FinalGraphic2019--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1144591/1144591_10177121_1560886217179_FinalGraphic2019--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Activities and Products: Soft Material Robotics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1144591/1144591_10177121_1560886217179_FinalGraphic2019--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Activities and Products: Soft Material Robotics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IGERT: Soft Material Robotics - An interdisciplinary PhD training program at Tufts University 2012 - 2018.Surrounding photos of student training and research activities are some of the devices and projects developed in the program. Clockwise from top middle: 1) SquMaBot - an untethered terrestrial</div> <div class="imageCredit">Barry A Trimmer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Barry&nbsp;A&nbsp;Trimmer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Activities and Products: Soft Material Robotics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ IGERT: Soft Material Robotics     2012 - 2018. Tufts University  The overall aim of this program was to build an interdisciplinary research and graduate education center for the new field of Soft Material Robotics. The program featured novel approaches to collaborative training. Its core science and engineering goal was to develop robust, adaptable, mobile machines that are impossible to achieve with conventional robots. This includes devices that are entirely soft, biocompatible and biodegradable.  In terms of broader impacts and the development of human resources, the program involved 29 graduate student trainees: 11 have received their PhDs, 4 completed masters research and 12 are continuing work on their PhD theses. Students were enrolled in the Schools of Engineering and Arts and Sciences from the departments of Biology, Mechanical Engineering, Electrical and Computer Engineering, Civil and Environmental Engineering, Biomedical Engineering, Chemical and Biological Engineering and Computer Science and were co-mentored by professors in these different departments. During the funded period, faculty and students disseminated their IGERT-related work in 11 books or book chapters, 146 conference presentations or seminars and 110 peer reviewed publications and more are currently in process.  New students attended an interdisciplinary "Boot Camp" and most took part in an Innovation Challenge training course. There were opportunities for extended, International Research Experiences and students visited labs and workshops in Italy, Switzerland, Japan and the United Kingdom. Students also participated in international conferences in Australia, Uruguay, Canada, France, Portugal, and Finland. Soft robotics continues to be an active field of research at Tufts University with the recent appointment of new tenure-track faculty members working at the forefront of the design and control of novel deformable machines.  In addition to these broader training achievements the program initiated several major research directions of significant intellectual merit that are ongoing. This includes the design, fabrication and testing of a non-pneumatic, electrically-actuated crawling robot. This device was constructed primarily from compressible foam that allows it to change its size and shape dramatically. It has been used to explore different strategies for controlling soft robot locomotion and incorporates design concepts derived from studying animal movements. We expect to develop this prototype into a cheap and durable machine for searching and surveying in complex three-dimensional environments.  In addition to addressing problems in mechanical control, students in the IGERT program explored methods for transmitting large amounts of sensory data efficiently. To mitigate some of the constraints that soft bodied robots place on conventional wiring, time-mode multipliers were included within the sensor circuitry allowing for both computation and conversion to be performed on the sensor platform. Additional work in this area introduced a novel and computationally efficient visual saliency algorithm for performing neurotrophic attention-based data reduction.  Faculty and students are continuing related research in soft animal neuromechanics to improve our understanding of locomotion control. This includes recording how the nervous system coordinates muscle activity during climbing, crawling and rapid defensive behavior. Progress is also being made in understanding how sensory information contributes to movement adaptation in natural environments. Results from this work are being used to guide all aspects of soft robot design, fabrication and control.  Another ongoing research area is the development of materials, tissues and microstructures for biomedical and robotic applications. IGERT students worked on engineered tendon-derived materials for nerve regeneration and muscle driven bio actuators. They also studied how fibrous biomaterials can be used to control the mechanical properties of swimming robots. A new research direction has been initiated to explore how tissue engineering with invertebrate cells can be exploited to grow sustainable, biodegradable, and ethically responsible, living robots.          Last Modified: 06/18/2019       Submitted by: Barry A Trimmer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
