<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Iridescent Color Signals in Context: Interactions among Behavior, Perception, Function, and Light Environment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjawor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927887</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The visual signals of many animals include iridescent colors which have the unique property of changing dramatically in brightness and hue when the viewer position changes relative to the reflecting surface.  Understanding the production and perception of these directional color signals in nature is a more complex problem than for non-directional colors.  This study will explore a beautifully iridescent and common butterfly, the Pipevine Swallowtail.  This butterfly has large iridescent areas on the lower wing surface that signal this species distastefulness to potential predators, and also on the upper wing surfaces (males only) which is used by females in mate choice. Experiments and observations in the field, lab and a large butterfly enclosure at a botanical garden will evaluate the relative positions and movements of sender and intended receivers, the perceptual capabilities of intended receivers, and the available illumination in nature.  This will be done separately for each wing surface with careful attention to the function of each signal and the context in which it is viewed by intended receivers - females for the upper wing surface and predators for the lower wing surface.  Behavioral experiments will explore the implications for the directionality of iridescence for signal detection and effectiveness.  Overall this study has the potential to transform our views of how iridescent color signals in animals in various contexts are actually viewed and used in nature.  In addition to the intellectual merits, the broader impacts of the proposed research include providing research training experiences for undergraduate and graduate students, especially for groups underrepresented in the sciences, stimulating the interest of a broad audience through publication in technical journals and popular literature, and outreach activities using established web sites (http://rutowski.lab.asu.edu and http://askabiologist.asu.edu/) and local public natural history organizations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1145654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Rutowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ronald L Rutowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>r.rutowski@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809654369</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000439672</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852874501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~390000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many animals are brightly colored and some elements of bright coloration are iridescent.&nbsp; This means their appearance changes with the angle from which they are viewed, that is, they are directional.&nbsp; Over 100 years ago it was suggested that this directionality might make it difficult for animals to use iridescent colors as signals because they may often not be visible to intended receivers.&nbsp; Proposed general solutions to this problem include the signaler moving into a position during an interaction that ensures that the signal is visible to the intended receiver.&nbsp; We have examined these ideas and expectations using the Pipevine Swallowtail butterfly in which there are iridescent components to both their warning coloration on the lower hindwing surfasce and the sexual signals of the male's upper hindwing.&nbsp;</p> <p>As for our studies of the male's iridescent sexual signal we began by describing in details the behavior of males in courtship relative to the female using measurements from slow motion video.&nbsp; A courting male repeatedly swoops up in front of a flying female from behind and below her.&nbsp; Using the information gathered about how the male moved during a swoop we examined how the upper surface of the male&rsquo;s hindwings would appear to the female during this maneuver outdoors under natural sunlight and skylight.&nbsp; Our results show that the structure of the swoop ensures that the female will see the male&rsquo;s blue iridescence no matter how his swoop is oriented relative to the sun.&nbsp;&nbsp; We attempted experiments to evaluate if the flashiness of the iridescence during a swoop makes it any more attractive to females but the results were inconclusive.&nbsp; Our main conclusion is that the behavior of males has evolved to enhance the transmission of their iridescent sexual signal to the female.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have also shown that quality of the male's coloration is heritable and correlated with the quantity of nutritious materials he is likely to pass to females during copulation.&nbsp; These characteristics suggest that the color signal is likely to contain information of value to females in mate selection. &nbsp;</p> <p>We studied the warning coloration on the lower hindwing surface in this species in a series of carefully designed experiments with wild and domesticated bird predators exploring their recognition and learning of the warning signal of the Pipevine Swallowtail.&nbsp; We first revealed that the iridescent blue component of the coloration of the ventral hindwing of the Pipevine Swallowtail contributes to their learned recognition as warning signals in nature, but their role is likely to depend on the context and species of predator attacking.&nbsp; When considering the consequences of changes in both hue and brightness of iridescent colors that predators might see when approaching these animals, we found that variation in these color properties during training did not decrease their effectiveness as warning signals.&nbsp; We also found that within the likely variation seen by predators, constantly brighter signals were more effective than less bright signals, and constantly blue-violet signals were more readily learned than blue-green by domestic chickens.&nbsp; Our main conclusion is that in spite of its directionality the iridescent blue contributes to the effectiveness of the warning signal especially under relatively low light conditions.&nbsp; This was further supported from inferences about how the blue and orange patches would appear to birds at dawn and dusk when they are most likely to be foraging.&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, these results suggest that the directionality of iridescent signals can in some cases lead to behavioral adaptations that enhance signal transmission but in other cases the brightness of iridescent signals makes them visible to receivers from a variety of vantage points, even under dim light conditions without direct sunlight.&nbsp; This was a novel and unanticipated result that suggests that iridescent color signals in nature may work effectively in a broader range of light environments than previously thought.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project served as a rich opportunity for training future scientists especially graduate and undergraduate students from a variety of groups underrepresented in the sciences.&nbsp; We have also produced new techniques and approaches for the study of iridescent coloration, and stimulated public interest in animal coloration and butterflies.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Ronald&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rutowski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1145654/1145654_10169408_1481909055112_Pipevineswallowtailmale--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1145654/1145654_10169408_1481909055112_Pipevineswallowtailmale--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Male of the Pipevine Swallowtail"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1145654/1145654_10169408_1481909055112_Pipevineswallowtailmale--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Male of the Pipevine Swallowtail"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Males have a brilliant blue iridescent reflection on their upper wing surfaces, especially the hindwing surfaces.  This blue coloration is a sexual signal that can contains information about the males genes and his ability to invest in his offspring.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ron Rutowski</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ronald&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rutowski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Male of the Pipevine Swallowtail</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1145654/1145654_10169408_1481909359766_Pipevineswallowtailmatingpair--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1145654/1145654_10169408_1481909359766_Pipevineswallowtailmatingpair--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mating pair of Pipevine Swallowtails"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1145654/1145654_10169408_1481909359766_Pipevineswallowtailmatingpair--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mating pair of Pipevine Swallowtails"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The males and females of the Pipevine Swallowtail have a similar coloration on their lower wing surface.  This coloration is a warning signals that announces to predators that they are distasteful.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ron Rutowski</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ronald&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rutowski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mating pair of Pipevine Swallowtails</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many animals are brightly colored and some elements of bright coloration are iridescent.  This means their appearance changes with the angle from which they are viewed, that is, they are directional.  Over 100 years ago it was suggested that this directionality might make it difficult for animals to use iridescent colors as signals because they may often not be visible to intended receivers.  Proposed general solutions to this problem include the signaler moving into a position during an interaction that ensures that the signal is visible to the intended receiver.  We have examined these ideas and expectations using the Pipevine Swallowtail butterfly in which there are iridescent components to both their warning coloration on the lower hindwing surfasce and the sexual signals of the male's upper hindwing.   As for our studies of the male's iridescent sexual signal we began by describing in details the behavior of males in courtship relative to the female using measurements from slow motion video.  A courting male repeatedly swoops up in front of a flying female from behind and below her.  Using the information gathered about how the male moved during a swoop we examined how the upper surface of the male?s hindwings would appear to the female during this maneuver outdoors under natural sunlight and skylight.  Our results show that the structure of the swoop ensures that the female will see the male?s blue iridescence no matter how his swoop is oriented relative to the sun.   We attempted experiments to evaluate if the flashiness of the iridescence during a swoop makes it any more attractive to females but the results were inconclusive.  Our main conclusion is that the behavior of males has evolved to enhance the transmission of their iridescent sexual signal to the female.   We have also shown that quality of the male's coloration is heritable and correlated with the quantity of nutritious materials he is likely to pass to females during copulation.  These characteristics suggest that the color signal is likely to contain information of value to females in mate selection.    We studied the warning coloration on the lower hindwing surface in this species in a series of carefully designed experiments with wild and domesticated bird predators exploring their recognition and learning of the warning signal of the Pipevine Swallowtail.  We first revealed that the iridescent blue component of the coloration of the ventral hindwing of the Pipevine Swallowtail contributes to their learned recognition as warning signals in nature, but their role is likely to depend on the context and species of predator attacking.  When considering the consequences of changes in both hue and brightness of iridescent colors that predators might see when approaching these animals, we found that variation in these color properties during training did not decrease their effectiveness as warning signals.  We also found that within the likely variation seen by predators, constantly brighter signals were more effective than less bright signals, and constantly blue-violet signals were more readily learned than blue-green by domestic chickens.  Our main conclusion is that in spite of its directionality the iridescent blue contributes to the effectiveness of the warning signal especially under relatively low light conditions.  This was further supported from inferences about how the blue and orange patches would appear to birds at dawn and dusk when they are most likely to be foraging.   Overall, these results suggest that the directionality of iridescent signals can in some cases lead to behavioral adaptations that enhance signal transmission but in other cases the brightness of iridescent signals makes them visible to receivers from a variety of vantage points, even under dim light conditions without direct sunlight.  This was a novel and unanticipated result that suggests that iridescent color signals in nature may work effectively in a broader range of light environments than previously thought.   This project served as a rich opportunity for training future scientists especially graduate and undergraduate students from a variety of groups underrepresented in the sciences.  We have also produced new techniques and approaches for the study of iridescent coloration, and stimulated public interest in animal coloration and butterflies.           Last Modified: 12/16/2016       Submitted by: Ronald L Rutowski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
