<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Biological Inventory of the Amphibians and Reptiles of Laos</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>376860.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>402000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Little is known about the amphibians (frogs, salamanders, and caecilians) and reptiles (turtles, lizards, and snakes) of the Southeast Asian country of Laos. Laos has been plagued by war, instability and isolation from the West, and this has led to a long gap in wildlife research. An improved political situation has made new fieldwork possible, and Laos is now known to contain a high diversity of amphibians and reptile species, many of which occur only there. New country records and entirely new species to science are being rapidly discovered in Laos. Low capacity and poor infrastructure impedes such research by in-country scientists. This three-year project will undertake surveys of amphibians and reptiles, and their parasites, at nine priority field sites across Laos. The work will be undertaken collaboratively between U.S. and Lao biodiversity scientists in partnership with a U.S. non-governmental wildlife conservation organization.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Knowledge of which species occur where is fundamental to global biodiversity conservation. Many species of amphibians and reptiles in Laos are at risk of extinction, primarily due to habitat destruction. This project will provide essential information on the biology of amphibians and reptiles in Laos to conservation managers, the international scientific community, and the U.S. public via museum exhibits. A U.S. postdoctoral scholar and Lao graduate students and scientists will receive extensive training in field research and museum science to ensure project impact on the next generation of biodiversity scientists and stewards.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1145922</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Stuart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryan L Stuart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bryan.stuart@naturalsciences.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9197078861</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Friends of the North Carolina State Museum of Natural Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276011029</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9197079847</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11 West Jones Stree</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>615733656</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FRIENDS OF THE NORTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State Museum of Natural Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276011029</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11 West Jones Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY SURVEYS &amp; INVENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9232</Code>
<Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~376860</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~25140</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Very little has been known on the amphibians and reptiles of the Southeast Asian country of Laos. This is primarily due to a lack of field sampling of amphibians and reptiles in Laos, and historically a lack of national scientists in the country with expertise in these organisms. The goal of this project was to describe which species of amphibians and reptiles occur where in Laos, as learned through new fieldwork conducted throughout the country and study of the resulting scientific specimens and their DNA sequence data. At the same time, this highly collaborative project supported the development of in-country scientists, students, and natural history collection.&nbsp;</p> <p>The grant supported a total of nine field trips by the PI to sample amphibians and reptiles throughout Laos, as well as numerous additional field trips by collaborating Lao scientists and students. Over 2,000 specimens were collected that were associated with a broad spectrum of data to maximize their scientific utility, including detailed habitat data, DNA and RNA samples, advertisement calls of frogs, high-resolution photographs, blood parasite and amphibian chytrid fungus samples, and natural history observations. These specimens were shared between the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences (NCSM) and a newly developed natural history collection at the National University of Laos. Those deposited at NCSM have been fully incorporated into the museum's research collections, and are being made known to scientists, biodiversity conservation managers, and the public through the museum's online collection database. To date, these specimens have been used by the collaborative team in support of over a dozen scientific publications, a book chapter, three Lao M.Sc. theses (one completed, two in progress) and one Lao Ph.D. dissertation (completed). Hundreds of specimens and associated tissue samples that were obtained on the project have also been loaned for study to researchers at other institutions. The research resulting from these specimens has filled a large geographic gap in knowledge of amphibians and reptiles in mainland Southeast Asia. These data will support new analyses to understand the patterns and processes that have generated high biodiversity in mainland Southeast Asia, and allow for a synthesis of the species that occur in Laos.</p> <p>The grant provided direct training in biodiversity science to five Lao female scientists (four M.Sc. and/or Ph.D. students and one university faculty member), two U.S. female scientists (postdoctoral scholars at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences), one U.S. community college faculty member, one U.S. undergraduate student, and ten U.S. community college students. This training included field herpetology methods, laboratory methods, taxonomic study of specimens, analyzing and published results, and giving scientific presentations. Three of the trainees (both U.S. postdoctoral scholars and one Lao Ph.D student) successfully obtained faculty and/or museum curator positions following this experience. The project also improved the natural history collection in the Department of Biology, National University of Laos, through provision of specimens, curatorial supplies, and curatorial training. The project findings have been shared with the U.S. public through radio interviews, online blogs, newspaper articles, and&nbsp;presentations to visitors at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Bryan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stuart</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Very little has been known on the amphibians and reptiles of the Southeast Asian country of Laos. This is primarily due to a lack of field sampling of amphibians and reptiles in Laos, and historically a lack of national scientists in the country with expertise in these organisms. The goal of this project was to describe which species of amphibians and reptiles occur where in Laos, as learned through new fieldwork conducted throughout the country and study of the resulting scientific specimens and their DNA sequence data. At the same time, this highly collaborative project supported the development of in-country scientists, students, and natural history collection.   The grant supported a total of nine field trips by the PI to sample amphibians and reptiles throughout Laos, as well as numerous additional field trips by collaborating Lao scientists and students. Over 2,000 specimens were collected that were associated with a broad spectrum of data to maximize their scientific utility, including detailed habitat data, DNA and RNA samples, advertisement calls of frogs, high-resolution photographs, blood parasite and amphibian chytrid fungus samples, and natural history observations. These specimens were shared between the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences (NCSM) and a newly developed natural history collection at the National University of Laos. Those deposited at NCSM have been fully incorporated into the museum's research collections, and are being made known to scientists, biodiversity conservation managers, and the public through the museum's online collection database. To date, these specimens have been used by the collaborative team in support of over a dozen scientific publications, a book chapter, three Lao M.Sc. theses (one completed, two in progress) and one Lao Ph.D. dissertation (completed). Hundreds of specimens and associated tissue samples that were obtained on the project have also been loaned for study to researchers at other institutions. The research resulting from these specimens has filled a large geographic gap in knowledge of amphibians and reptiles in mainland Southeast Asia. These data will support new analyses to understand the patterns and processes that have generated high biodiversity in mainland Southeast Asia, and allow for a synthesis of the species that occur in Laos.  The grant provided direct training in biodiversity science to five Lao female scientists (four M.Sc. and/or Ph.D. students and one university faculty member), two U.S. female scientists (postdoctoral scholars at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences), one U.S. community college faculty member, one U.S. undergraduate student, and ten U.S. community college students. This training included field herpetology methods, laboratory methods, taxonomic study of specimens, analyzing and published results, and giving scientific presentations. Three of the trainees (both U.S. postdoctoral scholars and one Lao Ph.D student) successfully obtained faculty and/or museum curator positions following this experience. The project also improved the natural history collection in the Department of Biology, National University of Laos, through provision of specimens, curatorial supplies, and curatorial training. The project findings have been shared with the U.S. public through radio interviews, online blogs, newspaper articles, and presentations to visitors at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences.             Last Modified: 06/07/2016       Submitted by: Bryan L Stuart]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
