<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  ABI Development:  Building A Community Resource for Neuroscientists</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99317.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99317</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Maglia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of California-San Diego and Yale University are awarded collaborative grants to develop a Neuroscience Gateway (NSG) that will facilitate access and use of high performance computing (HPC) resources by neuroscientists. Computational modeling of cells and networks has become an essential part of neuroscience research, and investigators are using models to address problems of ever increasing complexity, e.g. large scale network models and optimization or exploration of high dimensional parameter spaces. The NSG will catalyze such research by lowering or eliminating the administrative and technical barriers that currently make it difficult for investigators to use HPC resources. It will offer computer time to neuroscience users through an administratively and technologically streamlined process with a simple web portal-based environment for uploading models, specifying HPC job parameters, querying running job status and receiving job completion notices, and retrieving and storing output data. The URL of the NSG portal is http://www.nsgportal.org. It will also provide a community forum for neuroscientists to collaborate and share data. The NSG architecture will transparently distribute user jobs to appropriate HPC resources provided by NSF supercomputer centers. The NSG team will collaborate with developers of neural simulation software to optimally install, test, and benchmark these applications on HPC machines, and allow developers to test new versions before release. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will have a transformative impact by enabling access by members of the computational neuroscience community to HPC resources for research and instruction involving compute-intensive simulations (typically large neural networks). Many of these investigators and students would otherwise find it very difficult, if not impossible, to implement and study models that press or exceed the storage and speed capabilities that are under their direct control. Computational modeling offers opportunities for students and researchers at institutions with limited resources for wet lab or experimental infrastructure to participate in leading edge science. Projects such as this, which facilitate access to HPC resources, democratize participation in science by mitigating the financial barriers to research infrastructure. The NSG will enable students and researchers, who lack access to HPC resources and are thus at a significant disadvantage compared to very few who have it, by removing the barriers for progress for many including historically underrepresented groups. The PIs of this project will target the promotion of the NSG to underrepresented minority scientists and minority serving institutions through active participation in summer training academies and a network of previously mentored female and minority students, some now employed at minority serving institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1146830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Carnevale</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas T Carnevale</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ted.carnevale@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034947381</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463013</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University School of Medicine, Dept Neurobiology]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065103218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[330 Cedar Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~99317</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We developed the Neuroscience Gateway (NSG) to catalyze progress in neuroscience research by addressing neuroscientists' growing need to use high performance computing resources (HPC). Computational modeling of biological neurons and networks (brain circuits) has become an essential part of research on how the brain works. However, advances in experimental and theoretical neuroscience are increasingly raising questions which require modeling projects that exceed the power of what is available to most neuroscientists in their own labs or research institutions. More powerful high performance computing (HPC) resources do exist and have been used for many years by researchers in the physical sciences, but technical and administrative barriers had prevented most neuroscientists from being able to access them. The NSG simplifies access to HPC resources by reducing or eliminating those barriers. It does this by streamlining the process of signing up for an account and getting computer time, and providing users a simple, browser-based interface that makes it easy for them to upload their models, run simulations, and get back results. The response to NSG has been very enthusiastic, and NSG users have already begun publishing the results of studies that would have taken much longer or been impractical without it. Looking forward, we have already begun to work on new projects that leverage NSG's strengths by linking it to other neuroscience modeling resources so that they too can more easily access HPC.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Nicholas&nbsp;T&nbsp;Carnevale</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We developed the Neuroscience Gateway (NSG) to catalyze progress in neuroscience research by addressing neuroscientists' growing need to use high performance computing resources (HPC). Computational modeling of biological neurons and networks (brain circuits) has become an essential part of research on how the brain works. However, advances in experimental and theoretical neuroscience are increasingly raising questions which require modeling projects that exceed the power of what is available to most neuroscientists in their own labs or research institutions. More powerful high performance computing (HPC) resources do exist and have been used for many years by researchers in the physical sciences, but technical and administrative barriers had prevented most neuroscientists from being able to access them. The NSG simplifies access to HPC resources by reducing or eliminating those barriers. It does this by streamlining the process of signing up for an account and getting computer time, and providing users a simple, browser-based interface that makes it easy for them to upload their models, run simulations, and get back results. The response to NSG has been very enthusiastic, and NSG users have already begun publishing the results of studies that would have taken much longer or been impractical without it. Looking forward, we have already begun to work on new projects that leverage NSG's strengths by linking it to other neuroscience modeling resources so that they too can more easily access HPC.       Last Modified: 08/28/2015       Submitted by: Nicholas T Carnevale]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
