<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Searching for Photospheric Causes of Small-Scale Chromospheric Activity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397757.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ilia Roussev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>iroussev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927436</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research team will use the New Solar Telescope (NST) of the Big Bear Solar Observatory (BBSO) to investigate the origins of solar chromospheric features, such as spicules, "rapid blue shifted events," and so-called "anemone jets," as well as the tiny intergranular jets recently discovered by BBSO staff using the NST. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In particular, this team will constrain the driving mechanisms of chromospheric upflows by analyzing high resolution NST and spacecraft observations of coronal holes and "quiet Sun" areas. They will study chromospheric jet properties (such as velocities, association with the solar magnetic field, and time evolution), as well as chromospheric response to solar photospheric dynamics. The research team will also organize several joint observational and data analysis campaigns involving NST and selected spacecraft for capturing the details of solar surface phenomena with unprecedented clarity, revealing the dynamics of small scale magnetic fields in the Sun's photosphere and chromosphere. This team expects their analysis to provide new insight into coronal heating and related processes in the lower solar atmosphere, as well as to advance our understanding of solar wind acceleration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team members will provide their new NST data to the wider solar community and perform specific solar observations upon request from outside researchers. They note that recent high quality NST imagery has already generated significant interest among the general public (for example, making the list of National Geographic's "Best Space Pictures of 2010") and they anticipate that this form of outreach will continue.  This research activity will also support the further education and professional growth of a graduate student.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1146896</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vasyl</FirstName>
<LastName>Yurchyshyn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vasyl Yurchyshyn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vasyl.yurchyshyn@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9098665791</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486899</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenda</FirstName>
<LastName>Cao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenda Cao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wenda.cao@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9735965301</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000495002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Heights</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075162990</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW JERSEY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075162990</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Jersey Institute of Technology/Big Bear Solar Obs.]]></Name>
<CityName>Big Bear City</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>923149672</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[40386 N. Shore Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1523</Code>
<Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~131071</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~131048</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~135638</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p { margin-bottom: 0.08in; }a:link {  } --> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Nimbus Roman No9 L,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">The research performed with the NSF funded project advanced our knowledge and understanding of small-scale solar phenomena. First, our data analysis supported the idea that the recently discovered spicules of type II are driven by emergence of new magnetic fields and with their subsequent reconnection with the overlying (canopy) magnetic fields. Further research showed that such magnetic reconnection can be driven by advection of emerging fields toward the large field concentrations. Second, analyzing the high-resolution images of the sunspot's umbra we were able to resolve and to describe in details a new phenomena &ndash; umbral jets, which are cool jet-like oscillating structures seen in the chromosphere of an umbra. The spikes tend to occur above the darkest parts of the umbra where magnetic fields are strongest. The spikes exhibit up and down oscillatory motions and their spectral evolution suggests that they might be driven by upward propagating shocks generated by photospheric oscillations. </span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Nimbus Roman No9 L,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">We also reported that even large, repeatedly occurring jets were also found to be driven by the continuous injection of magnetic twist before and during the series of flares. We conclude that this continuous emergence of twisted magnetic flux played an important role in producing successive flares,  transferring energy from the photosphere into the corona and and developing a series of blowout jets. Similar picture is observed on even larger spatial and temporal scales. The study of a X1.6 flare showed that it was directly triggered by a flux emergence that occurred inside a &delta;-sunspot. The emergence lead to localized reconnection, which in turn triggered a chain of flares/reconnections that ended high in the heliosphere forming a global post-eruption arcade that spanned the entire AR.</span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Nimbus Roman No9 L,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">Intellectual merit: We study demonstrated that all jetting activity, regardless of the spatial scale may be driven by the same physical mechanism: emergence of twisted magnetic fields with subsequent reconnections with the preexisting magnetic structures. In other words, the magnetic energy generated by the subsurface convective flows is injected into the solar atmosphere and released from the Sun by series of reconnection events of various spatial and temporal scales. </span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-family: Nimbus Roman No9 L,serif;"><span style="font-size: x-small;">The broad impact: An graduate student was supported by the NSF funding who contributed significantly to the project. He finished his PhD thesis and will be defending it at the end of March 2016.<span style="color: #000000;">&nbsp; Since the NST&rsquo;s first light, and especially, since the first images taken with the adaptive optics system, many schools, magazines, and popular science websites expressed their interest in our data. Bringing our data before the public will help to understand the world and will let </span>teachers and students use state-of-the-art data in classroom work. Here at Big Bear Solar Observatory we partnered with the local Astronomical Society which helps us in organizing public tours and lectures.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Vasyl&nbsp;Yurchyshyn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research performed with the NSF funded project advanced our knowledge and understanding of small-scale solar phenomena. First, our data analysis supported the idea that the recently discovered spicules of type II are driven by emergence of new magnetic fields and with their subsequent reconnection with the overlying (canopy) magnetic fields. Further research showed that such magnetic reconnection can be driven by advection of emerging fields toward the large field concentrations. Second, analyzing the high-resolution images of the sunspot's umbra we were able to resolve and to describe in details a new phenomena &ndash; umbral jets, which are cool jet-like oscillating structures seen in the chromosphere of an umbra. The spikes tend to occur above the darkest parts of the umbra where magnetic fields are strongest. The spikes exhibit up and down oscillatory motions and their spectral evolution suggests that they might be driven by upward propagating shocks generated by photospheric oscillations.    We also reported that even large, repeatedly occurring jets were also found to be driven by the continuous injection of magnetic twist before and during the series of flares. We conclude that this continuous emergence of twisted magnetic flux played an important role in producing successive flares,  transferring energy from the photosphere into the corona and and developing a series of blowout jets. Similar picture is observed on even larger spatial and temporal scales. The study of a X1.6 flare showed that it was directly triggered by a flux emergence that occurred inside a &delta;-sunspot. The emergence lead to localized reconnection, which in turn triggered a chain of flares/reconnections that ended high in the heliosphere forming a global post-eruption arcade that spanned the entire AR.   Intellectual merit: We study demonstrated that all jetting activity, regardless of the spatial scale may be driven by the same physical mechanism: emergence of twisted magnetic fields with subsequent reconnections with the preexisting magnetic structures. In other words, the magnetic energy generated by the subsurface convective flows is injected into the solar atmosphere and released from the Sun by series of reconnection events of various spatial and temporal scales.     The broad impact: An graduate student was supported by the NSF funding who contributed significantly to the project. He finished his PhD thesis and will be defending it at the end of March 2016.  Since the NSTÆs first light, and especially, since the first images taken with the adaptive optics system, many schools, magazines, and popular science websites expressed their interest in our data. Bringing our data before the public will help to understand the world and will let teachers and students use state-of-the-art data in classroom work. Here at Big Bear Solar Observatory we partnered with the local Astronomical Society which helps us in organizing public tours and lectures.       Last Modified: 03/01/2016       Submitted by: Vasyl Yurchyshyn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
