<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH:  Genomic consequences of recent and ancient allopolyploidy:  a continuum of ages in Tragopogon (Asteraceae)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>336390.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>361890</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Much of what is known about the evolutionary fate of genes following genome doubling (polyploidy) is based on several crops that are thousands of years old and synthetic polyploids that are only several generations old. This project will investigate the very surprising finding that homeologous genes are lost rapidly after polyploidization, rather than being silenced or other regulatory changes. They want to know if there are general rules about which genes or larger pieces of genomes are preferentially lost. This is important because previous findings were from synthetic polyploids and recent natural polyploids (&lt;100 years). The plant genus Tragopogon (goatsbeard, in the sunflower family) provides a unique opportunity to investigate changes that occur following polyploidy in nature across a range of ages. Tragopogon contains diploids, natural polyploids that are only 60-80 years old, synthetic polyploids, and older Eurasian polyploids. This study will investigate an older (0.8 -2.8 million years ago, mya) natural polyploid for comparison with the recently formed polyploids; it also extends to an ancient polyploidy event (&gt;30 mya) early in the history of the sunflower family. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Genome doubling (polyploidy) has generated much of the diversity of life. All vertebrates and flowering plants experienced at least one episode of ancient polyploidy, and many crops are polyploids. Hence, elucidating the consequences of polyploidy will enhance our understanding of the diversification of life and provide fundamental knowledge about crop genomes. Results will provide important insights into the processes that generated much of life and most crops. In addition, the project will train undergraduate and graduate students, and a post-doctoral scholar, as well as including outreach activities to the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1146065</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Soltis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas E Soltis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dsoltis@botany.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523921721</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pamela</FirstName>
<LastName>Soltis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pamela S Soltis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>psoltis@flmnh.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522731964</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000391654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Barbazuk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William B Barbazuk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbarbazuk@botany.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522738624</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326117800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~336390</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~12500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~13000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We investigated the changes that occur over time following genome doubling (polyploidy). &nbsp;Polyploidy is a crucial process to understand--all our crops are polyploid as are flowering plants and many ferns and even vertebrates. Using cutting edge genomic approaches we extended our genomic and cytogenetic investigations from F1 hybrids, synthetics, and young polyploids &lt;80 years old (<em>T. mirus </em>and <em>T. miscellus</em>) to an older allopolyploid (<em>T. castellanus</em>) and its diploid parents. We were &nbsp;also able to extend to an ancient polyploidy event that corresponds with the origin of Asteraceae over 30 mya.</p> <p>We found that the genomic changes in the older polyploid (gene loss and expression changes) closely reflects what is ongoing in the young polyploids. The same genes appear to show expression changes and loss. We also found that the amount of gene loss and expression change in T. castellanus closely mirrored the values reported for T. mirus and T. miscellus. We have also conducted additional genomic analyses of the young polyploids so we can include a larger number of genes for a more comprehensive comparison. Significantly, it does appear that there are genomic rules in Compositae. The events that are ongoing in the young polyploids are reflective of the changes seen that are fixed in the older poylploids.&nbsp; In other words, genomic changes that occur in deep time may be predicted in just a few generations.&nbsp; But the rules for Compositae may not apply to other lineages&mdash;e.g., Poaceae or Fabaceae.&nbsp; Polyploidy appears to be a very complex phenomenon&mdash;there may be different rules for different lineages.&nbsp; Thus, our results have very broad implications and we have reviewed these broader impacts (D Soltis et al. 2016 a,b; P. Soltis et al.2016a,b).</p> <p>We also documented three independent origins of the older polyploid T. castellanus&mdash;two of the origins showed additive karyotypes of the parents&mdash;but the third origin did show karyotypic change&mdash;and the population was fixed for those changes, which appear to involve both compensated aneuploidy and translocations.&nbsp; These chromosomal changes are just what is seen ongoing in some plants of the young polyploids&nbsp; (T. mirus and T. miscellus).&nbsp; So again, the chromosomal changes that are ongoing in a few generations in the young polyploids are predictive of what may happen (but fixed) in populations of an older polyploid.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2016<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;E&nbsp;Soltis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We investigated the changes that occur over time following genome doubling (polyploidy).  Polyploidy is a crucial process to understand--all our crops are polyploid as are flowering plants and many ferns and even vertebrates. Using cutting edge genomic approaches we extended our genomic and cytogenetic investigations from F1 hybrids, synthetics, and young polyploids &lt;80 years old (T. mirus and T. miscellus) to an older allopolyploid (T. castellanus) and its diploid parents. We were  also able to extend to an ancient polyploidy event that corresponds with the origin of Asteraceae over 30 mya.  We found that the genomic changes in the older polyploid (gene loss and expression changes) closely reflects what is ongoing in the young polyploids. The same genes appear to show expression changes and loss. We also found that the amount of gene loss and expression change in T. castellanus closely mirrored the values reported for T. mirus and T. miscellus. We have also conducted additional genomic analyses of the young polyploids so we can include a larger number of genes for a more comprehensive comparison. Significantly, it does appear that there are genomic rules in Compositae. The events that are ongoing in the young polyploids are reflective of the changes seen that are fixed in the older poylploids.  In other words, genomic changes that occur in deep time may be predicted in just a few generations.  But the rules for Compositae may not apply to other lineages&mdash;e.g., Poaceae or Fabaceae.  Polyploidy appears to be a very complex phenomenon&mdash;there may be different rules for different lineages.  Thus, our results have very broad implications and we have reviewed these broader impacts (D Soltis et al. 2016 a,b; P. Soltis et al.2016a,b).  We also documented three independent origins of the older polyploid T. castellanus&mdash;two of the origins showed additive karyotypes of the parents&mdash;but the third origin did show karyotypic change&mdash;and the population was fixed for those changes, which appear to involve both compensated aneuploidy and translocations.  These chromosomal changes are just what is seen ongoing in some plants of the young polyploids  (T. mirus and T. miscellus).  So again, the chromosomal changes that are ongoing in a few generations in the young polyploids are predictive of what may happen (but fixed) in populations of an older polyploid.           Last Modified: 09/27/2016       Submitted by: Douglas E Soltis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
