<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Elucidating the roles of natural selection and mate discrimination in the evolution of reproductive isolation in a polymorphic amphibian</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>439983.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>459616</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project addresses two key questions in the field of evolutionary biology for the highly polymorphic strawberry dart frog (Dendrobates pumilio): (1) what are the barriers to gene exchange between new diverging species and (2) what are the relative contributions of natural selection and mate discrimination in the formation of those barriers? The diversity of color-patterns exhibited by these frogs appears to have evolved recently and rapidly in response to natural selection. Experiments will be conducted to test for differences in survival and mating success among differently colored frogs that result from differences in predation and female mating preferences. By integrating insights from ecological and behavioral experiments, this work will systematically assess the relative contributions of a suite of potential barriers to reproduction, providing empirical support for theory regarding the mechanisms of speciation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The processes that lead to the formation of new species are central to the maintenance of biodiversity.  This project aims to improve our understanding of how new species arise in nature, and will permit an exciting comparison to well-studied groups of animals, like Heliconius butterflies and African Rift Lake Cichlids.  The project will also provide international educational and research opportunities for a postdoctoral researcher, graduate students, and undergraduates. The development of outreach programs to engage students and community members in Panama and Louisiana in learning about evolution is also an important component of this work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1146370</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Corinne</FirstName>
<LastName>Richards-Zawacki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Corinne Richards-Zawacki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cori.zawacki@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126240447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000329157</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701185665</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6823 St. Charles Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~446726</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~6250</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6640</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aimed to answer two key questions in the field of evolutionary biology for the amazingly variable strawberry poison frog (<em>Oophaga pumilio</em>).&nbsp; In and around the young Bocas del Toro Archipelago of Panama this species exhibits a variety of color morphs and the goal of our project was to understand: (1) to what extent has reproductive isolation has evolved between these lineages? and (2) what are roles of natural versus sexual selection in that process?&nbsp; To do this we used a natural transition zone between red and blue color morphs where red, blue and intermediately colored (brown) individuals can be found.</p> <p>While we predicted, based on aposematism theory, that natural selection due to predation would reduce the fitness of color morphs that are rare, dull (i.e., not an obvious warning color), or outside their native range, we found no evidence that a frog's color influences the likelihood of attack either by natural predators or a model predator.&nbsp; Interestingly, we found the lowest attack rate in the area where frogs are variable in color, suggesting that a reduction in the risk of predation may have relaxed natural selection on coloration, perhaps allowing for color to diversify in response to other agents of selection (e.g., sexual selection). We also predicted that sexual selection due to color-assortative female mating preferences would generate behavioral reproductive isolation among color morphs.&nbsp; While we found evidence for color-assortative courtship in red and blue populations, in the transition zone, where frogs are either red, blue or intermediate in color, females showed a consistent preference for courtship with red males rather than a preference for their own color in a mate.&nbsp; This suggests that while color-assortative mating may pose a barrier to reproduction for frogs that stray outside their native range, when two morphs come into contact, these assortative preferences may not persist.&nbsp; As a result, we concluded that unless other reproductive barriers evolve, the progression of these color morphs to speciation is unlikely.</p> <p>Postdoctoral, PhD and undergraduate level researchers were trained in association with this project. The results of this project have been disseminated broadly through scientific publications, outreach events in Panama and New Orleans, Louisiana, and through the creation of educational modules for teaching evolution at the undergraduate level.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Corinne&nbsp;Richards-Zawacki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aimed to answer two key questions in the field of evolutionary biology for the amazingly variable strawberry poison frog (Oophaga pumilio).  In and around the young Bocas del Toro Archipelago of Panama this species exhibits a variety of color morphs and the goal of our project was to understand: (1) to what extent has reproductive isolation has evolved between these lineages? and (2) what are roles of natural versus sexual selection in that process?  To do this we used a natural transition zone between red and blue color morphs where red, blue and intermediately colored (brown) individuals can be found.  While we predicted, based on aposematism theory, that natural selection due to predation would reduce the fitness of color morphs that are rare, dull (i.e., not an obvious warning color), or outside their native range, we found no evidence that a frog's color influences the likelihood of attack either by natural predators or a model predator.  Interestingly, we found the lowest attack rate in the area where frogs are variable in color, suggesting that a reduction in the risk of predation may have relaxed natural selection on coloration, perhaps allowing for color to diversify in response to other agents of selection (e.g., sexual selection). We also predicted that sexual selection due to color-assortative female mating preferences would generate behavioral reproductive isolation among color morphs.  While we found evidence for color-assortative courtship in red and blue populations, in the transition zone, where frogs are either red, blue or intermediate in color, females showed a consistent preference for courtship with red males rather than a preference for their own color in a mate.  This suggests that while color-assortative mating may pose a barrier to reproduction for frogs that stray outside their native range, when two morphs come into contact, these assortative preferences may not persist.  As a result, we concluded that unless other reproductive barriers evolve, the progression of these color morphs to speciation is unlikely.  Postdoctoral, PhD and undergraduate level researchers were trained in association with this project. The results of this project have been disseminated broadly through scientific publications, outreach events in Panama and New Orleans, Louisiana, and through the creation of educational modules for teaching evolution at the undergraduate level.       Last Modified: 06/23/2016       Submitted by: Corinne Richards-Zawacki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
