<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Functional implications of stress-evoked changes in epigenetic mechanisms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edda Thiels</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ethiels@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928167</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Prolonged or repeated stress leads to allostatic overload that mediates various cellular changes in the hippocampus, the area of the brain important for learning and memory.  These changes result in reduced hippocampus function and deficits in learning and memory. Chronic stress-mediated memory deficits in humans and animals are well documented. Less is known about the molecular mechanisms underlying adverse effects that cause reduced hippocampus function in response to chronic stress. It is becoming increasingly evident that dynamic changes to the histones, the proteins that DNA is coiled around, are molecular mechanisms important for the physiological reaction to environmental stressors. Deciphering information encoded in histone modifications in the hippocampus in response to chronic stress is critical for understanding the molecular mechanisms of regulation of memory by stress. This project will identify novel histone changes that are modulated in response to chronic stress and negatively impact hippocampus function. Furthermore, the project is designed to investigate the effects on memory as the functional output of these modifications. By studying epigenetic changes and the mechanisms of these changes, these studies will define a novel common point of convergence as a mechanism to control transcription of genes that are regulated by stress and involved in learning and memory. Such information will fill the gap connecting histone modifications in the hippocampus to memory impairments caused by chronic stress. Students working in this lab will gain valuable research experience at the undergraduate, masters, and doctoral levels. These students participate in experiment planning, performance and analysis, as well as manuscript preparation and presentation at national and international meetings. Training provided by the research in this proposal is particularly important for science education in Louisiana, which is currently designated as an NSF EPSCOR state.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1146853</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Schrader</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura A Schrader</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schrader@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5048623139</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000301050</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701185665</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1096</Code>
<Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~375000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goals of this project were to determine the effects of activation of a particular enzyme, called SIRT1, in the hippocampus during chronic stress. SIRT1 has several known effects in cells, including modulation of chromatin, which affects gene transcription. We found that SIRT1 was activated in the hippocampus of male rats exposed to chronic stress. Furthermore, we found that this hyperactivation of SIRT1 mediated some of the molecular and behavioral effects of chronic stress. For example, behaviorally, chronic stress impairs object location memory and causes anhedonia, or reduced ability to feel pleasure. SIRT1 inhibition during chronic stress recovered object location memory and reduced anhedonia. In addition, we observed that SIRT1 inhibition reversed some of the  molecular effects that we observed in the hippocampus. Several of these  molecules are important for learning and memory.&nbsp; Together, these results suggest that SIRT1 activation is a basic mechanism mediating some of these behavioral effects that we observed.</p> <p>We have also begun investigating sex differences in the behavioral and molecular response to chronic stress. Interestingly, many of the molecular changes that occur in the hippocampus in response to stress are not affected in female hippocampus. In addition, the behavioral effects, specifically impaired memory, is not observed.&nbsp; This suggests that alternative pathways may be activated in the hippocampus of females, that allow females to respond differently to the stress. These pathways and the role of sex hormones in these responses will be further investigated in future projects.</p> <p>In addition, we further investigated the effects of pre-treatment with chronic stress on the acute stress response. Importantly, chronic stress blocked some of the molecular effects, including changes in the chromatin caused by acute stress. This suggests that in some cases, chronic stress may enhance adaptation of the brain to a traumatic acute stress.&nbsp; These effects will be further investigated in future projects.</p> <p>Dr. Schrader has trained 5 graduate students and multiple undergraduates in her laboratory working on this project. These students have presented various results from this project at various local and national meetings.&nbsp; In addition, Dr. Schrader and several of the students participated in K-12 as well as adult outreach sessions during the duration of this project. These include activties planned by the local Society for Neuroscience chapter for the annual Brain Awareness Week.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;A&nbsp;Schrader</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this project were to determine the effects of activation of a particular enzyme, called SIRT1, in the hippocampus during chronic stress. SIRT1 has several known effects in cells, including modulation of chromatin, which affects gene transcription. We found that SIRT1 was activated in the hippocampus of male rats exposed to chronic stress. Furthermore, we found that this hyperactivation of SIRT1 mediated some of the molecular and behavioral effects of chronic stress. For example, behaviorally, chronic stress impairs object location memory and causes anhedonia, or reduced ability to feel pleasure. SIRT1 inhibition during chronic stress recovered object location memory and reduced anhedonia. In addition, we observed that SIRT1 inhibition reversed some of the  molecular effects that we observed in the hippocampus. Several of these  molecules are important for learning and memory.  Together, these results suggest that SIRT1 activation is a basic mechanism mediating some of these behavioral effects that we observed.  We have also begun investigating sex differences in the behavioral and molecular response to chronic stress. Interestingly, many of the molecular changes that occur in the hippocampus in response to stress are not affected in female hippocampus. In addition, the behavioral effects, specifically impaired memory, is not observed.  This suggests that alternative pathways may be activated in the hippocampus of females, that allow females to respond differently to the stress. These pathways and the role of sex hormones in these responses will be further investigated in future projects.  In addition, we further investigated the effects of pre-treatment with chronic stress on the acute stress response. Importantly, chronic stress blocked some of the molecular effects, including changes in the chromatin caused by acute stress. This suggests that in some cases, chronic stress may enhance adaptation of the brain to a traumatic acute stress.  These effects will be further investigated in future projects.  Dr. Schrader has trained 5 graduate students and multiple undergraduates in her laboratory working on this project. These students have presented various results from this project at various local and national meetings.  In addition, Dr. Schrader and several of the students participated in K-12 as well as adult outreach sessions during the duration of this project. These include activties planned by the local Society for Neuroscience chapter for the annual Brain Awareness Week.          Last Modified: 07/28/2015       Submitted by: Laura A Schrader]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
