<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:   Scientific Computing for a New Generation of Ecologists</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>599244.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>599244</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ecology is about to face the data deluge that other biological disciplines have already experienced. With ecological data increasing rapidly in quality and size, new methods are needed to extract the most relevant biological information from massive data-sets. The objective of this project is to develop new mathematical, computational and statistical tools for the analysis of three ecological problems. First, when a species goes extinct, the impact reverberates through the ecological network, possibly causing the extinction of other species. A new method to predict such "secondary extinctions" will be developed. Second, the number and size of published ecological networks is increasing rapidly, making it possible to answer one of the oldest questions in ecology: how many species traits (e.g., body size, swimming speed, metabolic rate) does one need to measure to predict whether two species will interact? A new computational method, coupled with a large dataset will attempt to answer this question. Knowing which are the critical traits determining the possibility of interactions could find application in the study of invasive species. Third, the spatial structure of ecosystems mediates many ecological processes. A new method will be developed to measure the impact of spatial heterogeneity on the structure of ecological networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development of these new tools require sophisticated methods, which are not typically included in the curriculum of biologists. The educational goal of the project is to train ecologists in the computational methods that will be needed to advance the discipline in the decades to come. Graduate students will learn how to automate the analysis of biological data, distribute computation over large computer clusters, organize data into relational databases, program in different languages, collaborate on data, code and manuscripts, automatically managing versions and conflicts, and pick the right tool for each task.  Outreach activities will be provided through lectures and media interviews and with activities carried out in collaboration with local elementary schools and the Museum of Science and Industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1148867</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefano</FirstName>
<LastName>Allesina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefano Allesina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sallesina@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737021988</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000500865</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1101 E. 57th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8750</Code>
<Text>Bio &amp; Comp Shared Princ (BCSP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~599244</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The educational side of the project focused on improving computational skills of biologists. To this end, a new class ("Introduction to Scientific Computing for Biologists") was developed, taught at the University of Chicago and in abbreviated form around the world, priviledging institutions serving minority students and researchers from developing countries. The book "Computing Skills for Biologists" (Allesina and Wilmes, 2019) was based on the material prepared for this project.</p> <p>The research focus of the project has been on the interplay between ecological network structure and the dynamics occurring on these networks. A number of publications produced under this project used methods borrowed from the mathematics of random matrices to establish expectations for the stability of large ecological networks, filling a gap in the theory---most results in ecological theory examine the case of only a handful of interacting species.</p> <p>The project also characterized the dimensionality of published ecological networks (how many traits does one need to measure, in order to predict whether two species will interact?) and the structure of food webs and pollination networks. New methods were developed to analyze ecological networks in which different types of interaction between species (e.g., predation, facilitation, competition) are pooled together.</p> <p>Results questioned previous knowledge of ecological dynamics, including: the relationship between intra- and inter-specific interactions and their effect on stability; the need of intra-specific competition to stabilize large food webs; the role of higher-order interactions (i.e., those involving more than two species) in maintaining biodiversity.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Stefano&nbsp;Allesina</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The educational side of the project focused on improving computational skills of biologists. To this end, a new class ("Introduction to Scientific Computing for Biologists") was developed, taught at the University of Chicago and in abbreviated form around the world, priviledging institutions serving minority students and researchers from developing countries. The book "Computing Skills for Biologists" (Allesina and Wilmes, 2019) was based on the material prepared for this project.  The research focus of the project has been on the interplay between ecological network structure and the dynamics occurring on these networks. A number of publications produced under this project used methods borrowed from the mathematics of random matrices to establish expectations for the stability of large ecological networks, filling a gap in the theory---most results in ecological theory examine the case of only a handful of interacting species.  The project also characterized the dimensionality of published ecological networks (how many traits does one need to measure, in order to predict whether two species will interact?) and the structure of food webs and pollination networks. New methods were developed to analyze ecological networks in which different types of interaction between species (e.g., predation, facilitation, competition) are pooled together.  Results questioned previous knowledge of ecological dynamics, including: the relationship between intra- and inter-specific interactions and their effect on stability; the need of intra-specific competition to stabilize large food webs; the role of higher-order interactions (i.e., those involving more than two species) in maintaining biodiversity.       Last Modified: 09/12/2018       Submitted by: Stefano Allesina]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
