<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Natural solar cells and their geochemical implications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>140776.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>140776</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030205</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hailiang Dong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical description:&lt;br/&gt;The role of photoelectrochemical processes in Earth?s early history is not well understood.  Many common oxide and sulfide minerals are photoactive and capable of driving natural photoredox processes.  The proposal discusses several major events in Earth history, such as banded iron formations and the rise of oxygen, to which such photochemically active minerals might have contributed.  The project focuses in particular on a new concept in natural photoelectrochemistry: coupled-mineral systems.&lt;br/&gt;In solar energy research, there is a great deal of interest in photochemical water splitting ? the formation of O2 and H2 using sunlight and water.  Such processes are usually quite inefficient, but engineered ?tandem cells? have been constructed in which two semiconductors, each absorbing a different light wavelength, greatly improve the efficiency of the overall photocatalytic process.  The photochemical current densities that we measured in initial experiments with hematite-pyrite tandem cell (which can be expected to form in nature as the simple consequence of incipient pyrite oxidation) are surprisingly comparable to the deposition rates of iron in banded iron formations and the rate of water loss from Mars over time.  The time seems ripe, therefore, to study a few likely naturally-occurring mineral tandem cell systems in order to quantify the extent to which mineral-based photochemistry might have driven important early-Earth and planetary processes.&lt;br/&gt;We propose to investigate the behavior and properties of such natural photo-electrochemical cells.  We intend to understand the rates at which water can be oxidized and hydrogen produced, the rates at which other common aqueous solutes can be oxidized or reduced, the mineral properties needed for such processes, assess a small set of mineral systems that could have been important on early Earth, and investigate the effects of variable pO2, light intensity, pH, temperature, and both aqueous and solid compositions on the overall photoelectrochemical process.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical explanation:&lt;br/&gt;While the role of semiconducting minerals in natural processes of the Earth is of geological interest, the fundamental properties of mineral semiconductors as photocatalysts are probably of greatest significance in the development of solar energy technology.  If a solar photocatalytic system can be developed that produces fuels (chemically stored energy) reasonably efficiently, such technology ? if it is to truly impact the global energy picture in the long run ? must be constructed of Earth-abundant materials.  Iron and manganese oxides and sulfides are common, whereas there is simply not enough platinum on Earth to be used as electrodes/catalyst for such systems.  From the point of view of medium- to long-term energy security (not to mention climate change), such fuel-generating technologies as described in this proposal need to be better studied, improved, and implemented.  The PI has experience both in fundamental geochemistry research as well as with scientists working on solar energy, and the improved understanding of the tandem-cell mineral systems in this proposal has applications equally in geochemistry and solar energy technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1148494</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Eggleston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrick M Eggleston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ceggleston@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3073401671</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000374412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Department 3355]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~140776</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Photosynthesis by plants is not the only way in which solar energy is utilized in the natural environment. We know that sunlight drives free radical production and ozone production in the stratosphere and elsewhere in the atmosphere. We know that there are many light-driven reactions involving iron and manganese in natural waters. In this study, we show that a number of natural mineral systems are photoactive. The natural process in which sulfide minerals like pyrite &ndash; fool&rsquo;s gold &ndash; &ldquo;rust&rdquo; in air to form an oxidized outer layer is also one in which the natural equivalent of a photoelectrochemical &ldquo;tandem cell&rdquo; (two semiconducting materials, one layered on top of the other) such that the outer layer absorbs short wavelength,&nbsp; high energy light and transmits longer wavelength, lower energy light to the underlying mineral that is more able to absorb it. These mineral systems are shown to produce oxygen under illumination, confirming the process of water splitting (other work also confirms the production of hydrogen as well). In other words, these natural mineral systems act as natural solar cells to accomplish useful chemistry at the Earth&rsquo;s surface. During the study, we became interested in desert varnish &ndash; thin rock coatings - because these coatings are always associated with a population of bacteria.&nbsp; Our study strongly suggests that the minerals in the desert varnish absorb sunlight and produce compounds that can be utilized by resident bacteria as an energy source. This is important because it suggests that prior to the evolution of modern oxygenic photosynthesis, life could have supported itself based on the energy absorbed and converted into useful chemical compounds by natural semiconducting minerals. More generally, this study helps us understand that our geologic environment &ndash; think about a vista in the desert southwest of the U.S. with red rocks, rock varnish, and so forth &ndash; is not inert or inactive but instead an active and ongoing chemical agent akin to a widely dispersed solar energy collection system that supports bacterial life and affects our chemical environment, the breakdown of organic pollutants, and so forth. Similar processes likely take place on Mars and created the oxidized &ldquo;rusted&rdquo; surface environment on Mars despite the lack of oxygen in Mars&rsquo; atmosphere.&nbsp; On Earth, these findings also allow us to start speculating about the origins of biological oxygenic photosynthesis; photosystem II has at its core reaction center a manganese oxygen cluster, and photosystem I has as a reaction center an iron-sulfur cluster. In a way, biological photosynthesis may still depend in part on &ldquo;bits&rdquo; of mineral that biology still utilizes to generate chemical energy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/25/2015<br>      Modified by: Carrick&nbsp;M&nbsp;Eggleston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Photosynthesis by plants is not the only way in which solar energy is utilized in the natural environment. We know that sunlight drives free radical production and ozone production in the stratosphere and elsewhere in the atmosphere. We know that there are many light-driven reactions involving iron and manganese in natural waters. In this study, we show that a number of natural mineral systems are photoactive. The natural process in which sulfide minerals like pyrite &ndash; foolÆs gold &ndash; "rust" in air to form an oxidized outer layer is also one in which the natural equivalent of a photoelectrochemical "tandem cell" (two semiconducting materials, one layered on top of the other) such that the outer layer absorbs short wavelength,  high energy light and transmits longer wavelength, lower energy light to the underlying mineral that is more able to absorb it. These mineral systems are shown to produce oxygen under illumination, confirming the process of water splitting (other work also confirms the production of hydrogen as well). In other words, these natural mineral systems act as natural solar cells to accomplish useful chemistry at the EarthÆs surface. During the study, we became interested in desert varnish &ndash; thin rock coatings - because these coatings are always associated with a population of bacteria.  Our study strongly suggests that the minerals in the desert varnish absorb sunlight and produce compounds that can be utilized by resident bacteria as an energy source. This is important because it suggests that prior to the evolution of modern oxygenic photosynthesis, life could have supported itself based on the energy absorbed and converted into useful chemical compounds by natural semiconducting minerals. More generally, this study helps us understand that our geologic environment &ndash; think about a vista in the desert southwest of the U.S. with red rocks, rock varnish, and so forth &ndash; is not inert or inactive but instead an active and ongoing chemical agent akin to a widely dispersed solar energy collection system that supports bacterial life and affects our chemical environment, the breakdown of organic pollutants, and so forth. Similar processes likely take place on Mars and created the oxidized "rusted" surface environment on Mars despite the lack of oxygen in MarsÆ atmosphere.  On Earth, these findings also allow us to start speculating about the origins of biological oxygenic photosynthesis; photosystem II has at its core reaction center a manganese oxygen cluster, and photosystem I has as a reaction center an iron-sulfur cluster. In a way, biological photosynthesis may still depend in part on "bits" of mineral that biology still utilizes to generate chemical energy.       Last Modified: 11/25/2015       Submitted by: Carrick M Eggleston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
