<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:   Establishement and Maintenance of an Environmentally-Acquired Symbiosis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>800000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>818252</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Purnima Bhanot</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most animals, including humans, have specific associations with beneficial bacteria that facilitate digestion or provide defense against harmful pathogens and parasites. While some animals pass these bacteria directly from mother to offspring, ensuring acquisition, other animals  are born bacteria-free and then must acquire these beneficial partners from the environment. Little is understood about the process by which organisms establish and maintain these specialized associations in the face of encountering millions of diverse environmental microbes. Here, researchers use the relationship between broad-headed bugs and Burkholderia bacteria to study the ecological, immunological and evolutionary forces that shape host-microbe specialization. The project will couple environmental sampling, molecular approaches and experimentation to explore what benefits the bacteria provide to the host, what bacterial genes facilitate establishment within the host, and how the host responds to the introduction of alternative bacteria. This comprehensive approach will provide insight into how both host and microbial properties shape the establishment and maintenance of animal-bacteria associations. The project will train undergraduate and graduate students as well as one postdoctoral fellow. The researchers will also work with visual arts and biology instructors at both the undergraduate and middle-school levels to bring science into the art classroom, facilitating exploration of how art can be used to expose students to science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1149829</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerardo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicole Gerardo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nicole.gerardo@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4045743228</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506503</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1599-001-1BA]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMORY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303221064</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1510 Clifton Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9103</Code>
<Text>CLB-Career</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~178252</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong> Many animals, including humans, form intimate associations with beneficial microbes. These microbes can aid digestion, provision their hosts with nutrients or provide protection against disease. While some associations are complex, involving an array of microbial partners that form a community within and on their hosts, many insects form specialized associations with only one or a few species of bacteria. In some of these insect systems, both the insects and their bacteria can be readily cultured and maintained in the laboratory, facilitating a wide array of research approaches to study how these associations are maintained and why these associations are maintained.</p> <p>Here, we focused on associations of several true bug species with bacteria in the genus <em>Burkholderia.</em> We demonstrated that four species found living in the same environment (<em>Alydus tomentosus, Al. calcaratus</em>, <em>Al. conspersus</em> and <em>Megalotomus quinquespinosus</em>), all store <em>Burkholderia </em>spp. bacteria in specialized crypts in their gut. These bacteria are readily acquired from the environment each generation, and associations are not species specific; the bugs select from and establish associations with bacteria from the same bacterial pool. <em>Burkholderia </em>association decreases development time and increases survival of these bugs, highlighting their importance for host fitness. The specificity in association with <em>Burkholderia</em> rather than other bacteria appears to be driven, in part, by differential immune responses towards <em>Burkholderia </em>and other bacteria.</p> <p>Following on this work, we began to focus our research on another true bug species (and agricultural crop pest), Anasa tristis. We demonstrated that these insects too store <em>Burkholderia</em> in specialized gut crypts. Experimental infection of <em>A. tristis</em> with some strains indicate that the bacteria significantly increase survival and decrease development time of their hosts, and furthermore, can alter the ability of the insects to maintain association with a bacterial plant pathogen that they vector to squash plants. However, these influences on hosts are specific to the <em>Burkholderia</em> strain with which the bugs are inoculated; some strains provide fewer benefits than others.</p> <p>Despite the importance of these associations for <em>A. tristis</em>, the bacteria are not passed from mother to offspring, as is the case in many insect systems, but are instead acquired from the environment. Environmental acquisition is facilitated by shedding of bacteria through feces and by inoculation of plants by older individuals. Uninfected individuals then pick up the bacteria by feeding on the plants. Such indirect transmission may minimize costs associated with direct maternal transmission.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts. </strong>Visuals arts is increasingly used as a method to communicate science to the public. Such an interdisciplinary approach is speculated to facilitate science communication to audiences that may not be familiar with or regularly exposed to science. Here, we established several programs to integrate the arts and sciences. Over several years, we worked with undergraduate ceramics classes to explore topics in symbiosis, mutualism and the microbial world through ceramics. Students were exposed to study systems, different microbial growth forms, life under the microscope and important microbes in our world. They created pieces incorporating the concepts, patterns and shapes to which they were exposed. These collaborations culminated in a public exhibit at Emory University and a permanent display at a local community garden. In an advanced ceramics class, we paired the student artists with scientists on campus. These students met with the scientists and learned about their research. They then created pieces in response to that work. These initial artist-scientist pairings formed the basis of a new model for engagement of the arts and scientists at Emory University. Working with students, we helped found Science.Art.Wonder (S.A.W), an organization dedicated to utilizing the visual arts to teach and explore science. Through collaborations, this organization was also chartered at Georgia Tech University. In its inaugural year, S.A.W paired over 100 artists from the universities and from the community with scientists and engineers. The resulting works were displayed at several events at the Atlanta Science Festival.</p> <p>In addition, we developed a program, MYcrobes.org, to expose the public to the microbial community around them. At Atlanta Science Festival events and in school classrooms, we cultured bacteria and fungi from people's bodies and from environmental surfaces onto Petri dishes. Microbial growth of these dishes was then photographed daily, and the photos were archived on a website where participants could then go look at their microbes grow and change over time. To date, we have cultured microbes with thousands of community members in the greater Atlanta area.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Nicole&nbsp;Gerardo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit. Many animals, including humans, form intimate associations with beneficial microbes. These microbes can aid digestion, provision their hosts with nutrients or provide protection against disease. While some associations are complex, involving an array of microbial partners that form a community within and on their hosts, many insects form specialized associations with only one or a few species of bacteria. In some of these insect systems, both the insects and their bacteria can be readily cultured and maintained in the laboratory, facilitating a wide array of research approaches to study how these associations are maintained and why these associations are maintained.  Here, we focused on associations of several true bug species with bacteria in the genus Burkholderia. We demonstrated that four species found living in the same environment (Alydus tomentosus, Al. calcaratus, Al. conspersus and Megalotomus quinquespinosus), all store Burkholderia spp. bacteria in specialized crypts in their gut. These bacteria are readily acquired from the environment each generation, and associations are not species specific; the bugs select from and establish associations with bacteria from the same bacterial pool. Burkholderia association decreases development time and increases survival of these bugs, highlighting their importance for host fitness. The specificity in association with Burkholderia rather than other bacteria appears to be driven, in part, by differential immune responses towards Burkholderia and other bacteria.  Following on this work, we began to focus our research on another true bug species (and agricultural crop pest), Anasa tristis. We demonstrated that these insects too store Burkholderia in specialized gut crypts. Experimental infection of A. tristis with some strains indicate that the bacteria significantly increase survival and decrease development time of their hosts, and furthermore, can alter the ability of the insects to maintain association with a bacterial plant pathogen that they vector to squash plants. However, these influences on hosts are specific to the Burkholderia strain with which the bugs are inoculated; some strains provide fewer benefits than others.  Despite the importance of these associations for A. tristis, the bacteria are not passed from mother to offspring, as is the case in many insect systems, but are instead acquired from the environment. Environmental acquisition is facilitated by shedding of bacteria through feces and by inoculation of plants by older individuals. Uninfected individuals then pick up the bacteria by feeding on the plants. Such indirect transmission may minimize costs associated with direct maternal transmission.     Broader Impacts. Visuals arts is increasingly used as a method to communicate science to the public. Such an interdisciplinary approach is speculated to facilitate science communication to audiences that may not be familiar with or regularly exposed to science. Here, we established several programs to integrate the arts and sciences. Over several years, we worked with undergraduate ceramics classes to explore topics in symbiosis, mutualism and the microbial world through ceramics. Students were exposed to study systems, different microbial growth forms, life under the microscope and important microbes in our world. They created pieces incorporating the concepts, patterns and shapes to which they were exposed. These collaborations culminated in a public exhibit at Emory University and a permanent display at a local community garden. In an advanced ceramics class, we paired the student artists with scientists on campus. These students met with the scientists and learned about their research. They then created pieces in response to that work. These initial artist-scientist pairings formed the basis of a new model for engagement of the arts and scientists at Emory University. Working with students, we helped found Science.Art.Wonder (S.A.W), an organization dedicated to utilizing the visual arts to teach and explore science. Through collaborations, this organization was also chartered at Georgia Tech University. In its inaugural year, S.A.W paired over 100 artists from the universities and from the community with scientists and engineers. The resulting works were displayed at several events at the Atlanta Science Festival.  In addition, we developed a program, MYcrobes.org, to expose the public to the microbial community around them. At Atlanta Science Festival events and in school classrooms, we cultured bacteria and fungi from people's bodies and from environmental surfaces onto Petri dishes. Microbial growth of these dishes was then photographed daily, and the photos were archived on a website where participants could then go look at their microbes grow and change over time. To date, we have cultured microbes with thousands of community members in the greater Atlanta area.          Last Modified: 10/31/2018       Submitted by: Nicole Gerardo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
