<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Quantifying the flux and isotope effects associated with sulfur-bearing intermediate species within dissimilatory sulfate reduction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>284763.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>445554</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030205</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebarrera@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927780</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The story of Earth's history is locked within marine sediments, with the stable isotopes of sulfur providing much of this information and timeline.  Despite this utility, what controls the behavior of these isotopes is incompletely understood.  The goal of this CAREER award is to systematically evaluate how sulfur isotopes are fractionated when growing on different soluble sulfur compounds.  In the same fashion that humans breathe oxygen, these organisms can grow on sulfate, sulfite, thiosulfate and trithionate; these are the targeted substrates.  This work will thus develop a framework whereby specific fractionations will be linked to particular metabolic processes.  In essence, this is a 'fingerprinting' process.  At the core of this research is the team-based STEM model where local high school students will work closely with undergraduates from a suite of colleges in New England to conduct all the experimental work outlined above.  This will bring young scientists along on the path of designing research questions, performing lab-based experiments, processing data and working with particular instruments, and finally relating these results to the published literature.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1149555</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David T Johnston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnston@eps.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174965024</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1350 Masschusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~204556</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~80557</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~80234</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~80207</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The sedimentary sulfur isotope record is a prime target for reconstructing Earth&rsquo;s early biogeochemical activity and oxidant (seawater sulfate and atmospheric oxygen) budgets, and benefits from a pervasive geological record in both shale and carbonate. This means that there is a catalog of ancient biological activity that, if calibrated properly (the goal of this work), could unlock the story of Earth&rsquo;s biological change an innovation.&nbsp; At the heart of this &lsquo;calibration&rsquo; is a microbial metabolism that breathes sulfate (in the same way that we breathe oxygen).&nbsp; The work undertaken through this CAREER award worked to understand how this metabolic process fractionates isotopes &ndash; isotopes are just different flavors of an element, like sulfur.&nbsp; We systematically broke the metabolic process down into its constituent steps, measured the &lsquo;isotope effect&rsquo; at each step, and in the final efforts of this award, put all these pieces back together to offer a quantitative and robust framework for interpreting sulfur isotope records.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this work come both in the form of public outreach and professional development.&nbsp; For the former, we created a cartoon &ndash; freely available on the Johnston lab website &ndash; outlining the core targets and outcomes of this work.&nbsp; Further, and in terms of professional development, aspects of this work have been far reaching.&nbsp; Most notably is the training of a large number of students and post docs, including Cecilia Sanders (now at Caltech), Kalina Grabb (now at WHOI), Margaret Powell (current Harvard student) and Emma Bertran (PhD at Princeton). Over the course of the project, these students were mentored by former PhD student William Leavitt, former postdoc Alex Bradley and PI Johnston.&nbsp; These collaborations resulted in the publication of 7 papers on this subject.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;T&nbsp;Johnston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The sedimentary sulfur isotope record is a prime target for reconstructing Earth’s early biogeochemical activity and oxidant (seawater sulfate and atmospheric oxygen) budgets, and benefits from a pervasive geological record in both shale and carbonate. This means that there is a catalog of ancient biological activity that, if calibrated properly (the goal of this work), could unlock the story of Earth’s biological change an innovation.  At the heart of this ‘calibration’ is a microbial metabolism that breathes sulfate (in the same way that we breathe oxygen).  The work undertaken through this CAREER award worked to understand how this metabolic process fractionates isotopes &ndash; isotopes are just different flavors of an element, like sulfur.  We systematically broke the metabolic process down into its constituent steps, measured the ‘isotope effect’ at each step, and in the final efforts of this award, put all these pieces back together to offer a quantitative and robust framework for interpreting sulfur isotope records.     The broader impacts of this work come both in the form of public outreach and professional development.  For the former, we created a cartoon &ndash; freely available on the Johnston lab website &ndash; outlining the core targets and outcomes of this work.  Further, and in terms of professional development, aspects of this work have been far reaching.  Most notably is the training of a large number of students and post docs, including Cecilia Sanders (now at Caltech), Kalina Grabb (now at WHOI), Margaret Powell (current Harvard student) and Emma Bertran (PhD at Princeton). Over the course of the project, these students were mentored by former PhD student William Leavitt, former postdoc Alex Bradley and PI Johnston.  These collaborations resulted in the publication of 7 papers on this subject.          Last Modified: 01/29/2020       Submitted by: David T Johnston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
