<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Photoelectrochemical Investigation of Thin Film Hematite Solar Cells</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>527731.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>527731</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Hamann of the Department of Chemistry at Michigan State University will investigate the photo-catalytic oxidation of water using hematite electrodes.  A series of highly-controlled and systematic investigations on thin film hematite electrodes, including studying contacting electrolytes, the electrode interface and bulk material modifications, will be carried out.  A combination of electrochemical, photoelectrochemical, spectroscopic and microscopic measurements will be employed to characterize the new configurations of hematite photo-catalysts.  Also to be explored are strategies of increasing the light absorption of the optimized thin films including creating highly ordered nanostructures via atomic layer deposition and incorporating plasmonic nanoparticles. The broader impacts involve training undergraduate students and graduate student researchers and developing an experimental module on solar energy conversion using hematite electrodes for area high schools.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research outlines several approaches to substantially improve the energy conversion efficiency of hematite solar cells.  A breakthrough resulted from this research will have significant impact on the realization of truly cost-effective solar energy conversion and storage; this would benefit society tremendously by contributing to our energy independence and the mitigation of carbon emissions.  In addition, the interdisciplinary nature of the proposed work is expected to impact diverse fields, including materials chemistry, electrochemistry, and catalysis.  The research further involves several teaching points which will be integrated into educational activities at all levels, including the efforts to involve groups generally underrepresented in science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1150378</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas W Hamann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hamann@chemistry.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173531072</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000512964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241322</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[409 Chemistry Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>046E</Code>
<Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~147731</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project focused on the possibility of using iron oxide (hematite) electrodes to harness sunlight and convert water into hydrogen and oxygen. Hematite suffers from a low efficiency of getting charge carriers &ndash; specifically holes &ndash; created by light absorption to the electrode surface to carry out the desired water oxidation reaction. One question we initially addressed was whether it is possible to overcome this drawback by changing the dimensions of the electrode to minimize the distance photogenerated holes need to travel in order to reach the surface (i.e. nanostructuring). In order to accomplish this goal, we advanced the use of atomic layer deposition, ALD, to grow highly controlled, reproducible thin films with variable thicknesses as an ideal nanostructure model system.<a title="Klahr, 2011 #124" href="file:///C:/Work%20Files/Grants/2011%20NSF%20CAREER/Project%20Outcomes%20Report.docx#_ENREF_20"></a> Combining photo-electrochemical results with optical measurements indicated an optimal thickness for a hematite electrode of only ~20 nm. Nanostructuring alone does not completely overcome the limitations of hematite films, therefore doping/alloying strategies were also pursued. This ultimately allowed us to develop thin film electrodes which exhibited very high internal quantum yields.</p> <p>While the combination of nanostructuring and doping/allowing may be able to overcome the short hole collection length, holes that reach the electrode/electrolyte interface must still be collected efficiently via water oxidation. Electrochemical impedance spectroscopy, EIS, measurements for different conditions of voltage, light intensity and electrolyte pH were performed to investigate the main steps involved in water oxidation on hematite electrodes. Comparison of the behavior of hematite with and without fast hole scavengers present allowed for isolation of the water oxidation reaction. The strong correlation between charging of a surface state with the charge transfer resistance and the photocurrent onset provided strong evidence of the accumulation of holes in surface states at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface, which are responsible for water oxidation. This accumulation of holes at the surface was correlated with a change in the absorption spectrum of hematite electrodes during water oxidation by <em>in-situ</em> photo-induced spectroelectrochemistry measurements. In addition, we showed the first example of <em>operando</em> infrared spectroscopy measurements of water oxidation intermediate species on a semiconductor surface. From these combined results, a mechanism of water oxidation on the hematite electrode surface was proposed where charging the surface state actually corresponds to the generation of a high valent iron oxo (Fe=O) species resulting from the first step in the water oxidation reaction. This represents a major advance in fundamental understanding of photocatalytic reactions of semiconductor surfaces.</p> <p>In order to overcome the kinetic competition of water oxidation vs. recombination of surface states involved in water oxidation, the addition of water oxidation catalysts to the hematite electrode surface was investigated. We found that under illumination, porous cobalt phosphate catalysts can efficiently collect and store photo-generated holes from the hematite electrode. This improved charge separation reduces surface state recombination which results in increased water oxidation efficiency. In other work, a single ALD cycle was employed to deposit cobalt oxide catalysts which resulted in the first demonstration of catalytic activity (accelerating the rate of water oxidation rather than reduced recombination) from a surface species on hematite.</p> <p>As a result of the above work, we have now established a detailed understanding of photocatalytic water splitting with hematite. Recent and ongoing efforts aims at expanding this effort to other earth abundant metal oxide materials, such as copper tungstate, as well as metal nitrides, such as tantalum nitride. The goal is to gain a broader, more general understanding of photo-induced water splitting on semiconductor surfaces. In addition, we are expanding our investigations of the electron-transfer dynamics that occur at the semiconductor (e.g. hematite or copper tungstate) catalyst interface.</p> <p>We have therefore made substantial progress in achieving this project goals of answering basic science questions relevant to photocatalytic water splitting with an earth abundant oxide materials. In addition to the scientific advances, several graduate students &ndash; including underrepresented students &ndash; were supported by this project and received extensive training in material synthesis, characterization, electrochemistry, spectroscopy, solar energy conversion and catalysis. These students were also able to attend several national meetings and give poster and oral presentations on their work. The PI developed and teaches a graduate course on the physics and chemistry of solar energy conversion to more generally train graduate students in energy and materials sciences. The PI also lectures to an undergraduate class on green chemistry (for non-science majors) where the results of this project, in very basic terms, are presented to a diverse group of underrepresented students. The PI gave many invited talks at national and international conferences related to materials and solar fuels research, and was the organizer of an international solar fuels meeting, and participated in numerous outreach activities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;W&nbsp;Hamann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project focused on the possibility of using iron oxide (hematite) electrodes to harness sunlight and convert water into hydrogen and oxygen. Hematite suffers from a low efficiency of getting charge carriers &ndash; specifically holes &ndash; created by light absorption to the electrode surface to carry out the desired water oxidation reaction. One question we initially addressed was whether it is possible to overcome this drawback by changing the dimensions of the electrode to minimize the distance photogenerated holes need to travel in order to reach the surface (i.e. nanostructuring). In order to accomplish this goal, we advanced the use of atomic layer deposition, ALD, to grow highly controlled, reproducible thin films with variable thicknesses as an ideal nanostructure model system. Combining photo-electrochemical results with optical measurements indicated an optimal thickness for a hematite electrode of only ~20 nm. Nanostructuring alone does not completely overcome the limitations of hematite films, therefore doping/alloying strategies were also pursued. This ultimately allowed us to develop thin film electrodes which exhibited very high internal quantum yields.  While the combination of nanostructuring and doping/allowing may be able to overcome the short hole collection length, holes that reach the electrode/electrolyte interface must still be collected efficiently via water oxidation. Electrochemical impedance spectroscopy, EIS, measurements for different conditions of voltage, light intensity and electrolyte pH were performed to investigate the main steps involved in water oxidation on hematite electrodes. Comparison of the behavior of hematite with and without fast hole scavengers present allowed for isolation of the water oxidation reaction. The strong correlation between charging of a surface state with the charge transfer resistance and the photocurrent onset provided strong evidence of the accumulation of holes in surface states at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface, which are responsible for water oxidation. This accumulation of holes at the surface was correlated with a change in the absorption spectrum of hematite electrodes during water oxidation by in-situ photo-induced spectroelectrochemistry measurements. In addition, we showed the first example of operando infrared spectroscopy measurements of water oxidation intermediate species on a semiconductor surface. From these combined results, a mechanism of water oxidation on the hematite electrode surface was proposed where charging the surface state actually corresponds to the generation of a high valent iron oxo (Fe=O) species resulting from the first step in the water oxidation reaction. This represents a major advance in fundamental understanding of photocatalytic reactions of semiconductor surfaces.  In order to overcome the kinetic competition of water oxidation vs. recombination of surface states involved in water oxidation, the addition of water oxidation catalysts to the hematite electrode surface was investigated. We found that under illumination, porous cobalt phosphate catalysts can efficiently collect and store photo-generated holes from the hematite electrode. This improved charge separation reduces surface state recombination which results in increased water oxidation efficiency. In other work, a single ALD cycle was employed to deposit cobalt oxide catalysts which resulted in the first demonstration of catalytic activity (accelerating the rate of water oxidation rather than reduced recombination) from a surface species on hematite.  As a result of the above work, we have now established a detailed understanding of photocatalytic water splitting with hematite. Recent and ongoing efforts aims at expanding this effort to other earth abundant metal oxide materials, such as copper tungstate, as well as metal nitrides, such as tantalum nitride. The goal is to gain a broader, more general understanding of photo-induced water splitting on semiconductor surfaces. In addition, we are expanding our investigations of the electron-transfer dynamics that occur at the semiconductor (e.g. hematite or copper tungstate) catalyst interface.  We have therefore made substantial progress in achieving this project goals of answering basic science questions relevant to photocatalytic water splitting with an earth abundant oxide materials. In addition to the scientific advances, several graduate students &ndash; including underrepresented students &ndash; were supported by this project and received extensive training in material synthesis, characterization, electrochemistry, spectroscopy, solar energy conversion and catalysis. These students were also able to attend several national meetings and give poster and oral presentations on their work. The PI developed and teaches a graduate course on the physics and chemistry of solar energy conversion to more generally train graduate students in energy and materials sciences. The PI also lectures to an undergraduate class on green chemistry (for non-science majors) where the results of this project, in very basic terms, are presented to a diverse group of underrepresented students. The PI gave many invited talks at national and international conferences related to materials and solar fuels research, and was the organizer of an international solar fuels meeting, and participated in numerous outreach activities.          Last Modified: 05/02/2017       Submitted by: Thomas W Hamann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
