<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Innovations in Microscale Plasticity and Failure Mechanics to Enable  Microforming Processes, with Bending and Hydroforming as Paradigms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>433000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) grant aims at enhancing the understanding of deformation and failure of microtubes (diameter &lt; 1mm) with few (&lt;10) grains through the thickness. Such components abound in microelectronic, microfluidic and biomedical applications. Their mechanical behavior is dominated by the limited number of through-thickness grains, which renders the continuum approximation unsuitable. In this research, stainless steel 304 and CuZn 30 brass microtubes will be inflated under internal pressure and axial load and taken to failure, using a testing machine to be created for this purpose. These experimental findings will then help establish a microstructurally-informed, crystal plasticity constitutive model, with the aid of the research partner in South Korea. Finite element simulations of the experiments will be coupled with this material model to capture the deformation and failures observed. Subsequently, two micromanufacturing processes (microtube bending and hydroforming) will be examined using a combination of experiments and analysis. A microtube bending device will be created for the purposes of this project, while an existing apparatus in Cologne, Germany, will be used for the microtube hydroforming experiments. The performance of the numerical and constitutive models established above will be examined in light of these experiments and will be improved as needed, to capture the failures observed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will contribute to the scientific understanding of grain-dominated deformation and failure of materials. It will enable the broader implementation of microtube bending and hydroforming in innovative microelectronic, microfluidic and biomedical products, benefiting the American industry. The award will also provide two graduate students with the opportunity to perform research for a total of 18-24 months in Germany and South Korea, preparing them well for the globalization of research and industry. Lastly, training and integrating minorities will result in a more diverse, fair and internationally competitive workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1150523</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioannis</FirstName>
<LastName>Korkolis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ioannis Korkolis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>korkolis.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142477874</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544754</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>111089470</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY SYSTEM OF NEW HAMPSHIRE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001765866</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Hampshire]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>038242619</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Kingsbury Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1467</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project investigated the fundamental science behind microforming processes, i.e., deformation processes where one or more of the external dimensions of the component that is being made are comparable to the grain size of the metal. Metals are composed of atoms arranged in periodic lattices. Due to the way that a metal solidifies from the melt, multiple lattices start to grow simultaneously, so that in the end the metal is seen to be composed of many distinct crystals or grains (each crystal/grain having a specific orientation of its atomic lattice in space). The grains are strongly anisotropic, i.e., their properties and behavior depend on the orientation. Since a typical polycrystalline metal is composed of millions of grains, what is observed at the macroscale is a statistical average of the behavior of each grain. On the other hand, when the dimensions of the component are comparable to the grain size, that averaging is not valid and the overall behavior is governed by that of individual grains. An example of this is deformation-induced surface roughening, that oftentimes limits the deformation during microforming. This prevents the creation of complex shapes and ultimately increases the cost of biomedical, microelectronic and other devices.</p> <p>The project evolved along two parallel paths: creation of custom experimental testing equipment, and modeling of the behaviors observed using crystal plasticity. On the equipment front, two machines for microforming have been created: one is an apparatus for combined axial force and internal pressure loading of microtubes (Ripley and Korkolis, 2015). To the best of our knowledge, this is the only machine of its size in the world. It has been used to probe the behavior of stainless steel microtubes for biomedical applications (also see Ripley, 2015). The second is a custom apparatus for pure bending of microtubes. Both machines can be used with Digital Image Correlation and Infrared Thermography.</p> <p>On the modeling front, this award supported perhaps the only research on deformation-induced surface roughening where there is a 1-to-1 correlation between the specimen used for testing, and the finite element model. In other words, the microstructure of the specimen was reconstructed from 2 scans of its top and bottom surfaces. A special procedure for interpolating these images in 3D was devised. The procedure is general enough so that it can be used for a much larger family of 3D reconstructions from 2D scans, i.e., from partial data sets, and beyond only metal microstructures. It has enough merit to have been published separately in a peer-reviewed journal (Knysh et al, 2019). For this research, an exact model of the specimen used for the experiments was reconstructed, and the deformation-induced roughening was predicted. The model was further exercised to reveal correlations between microstructure and roughening (Knysh et al, submitted). In parallel to this effort, novel techniques for determining the inelastic heat fraction (Knysh and Korkolis, 2015) and the post-necking hardening response (Knysh and Korkolis, 2017) were proposed. Both of these are of very general applicability in mechanics of materials.</p> <p>The project lead to an extensive training of human capital: 3 graduate students, which resulted in 1 PhD and 2 MS theses; 6 REU students, including 1 female and 1 African-American; 5 undergraduates in 3 senior design projects, including 1 African-American. It has also involved 1 visiting professor from Univ. of Tokyo and 1 undergraduate student from Tokyo Metropolitan University (Japan). The project has also lead to international collaborations in Japan and S. Korea, including a research visit by the PhD student for 3 months in Tokyo. Lastly, the project has involved a U.S. start-up company, Psylotech, Inc.</p> <p>The research on the fundamental science behind microforming processes applicable to biomedical and microelectronic components is expected to benefit society at-large, by allowing more imaginative designs to be implemented, and a more rational process design. In addition, by shedding further light to the interrelation between surface roughening and microstructure, it can enable alloy and process design across the spectrum of manufacturing industry, enhancing the competitiveness of US manufacturing.</p> <p>REFERENCES</p> <p>P.W. Ripley and Y.P. Korkolis, "Multiaxial Deformation Apparatus for Testing of Microtubes Under Combined Axial-Force and Internal-Pressure", Experimental Mechanics, 56 (2016), 273-286</p> <p>P.W. Ripley, &ldquo;Development of biaxial loading apparatus for testing of microtubes under axial force and internal pressure and experiments on 304L stainless steel microtubes&rdquo;, MS Thesis, Univ. of New Hampshire, 2014.</p> <p>P. Knysh, K. Sasaki, T. Furushima, M. Knezevic, Y.P. Korkolis, &ldquo;A shape interpolation procedure: Application to creating explicit grain structure models based on partial data sets&rdquo;, Computational Materials Science, 167 (2019), 42-51</p> <p>P. Knysh and Y.P. Korkolis, &ldquo;Determination of the fraction of plastic work converted into heat in metals&rdquo;, Mechanics of Materials, 86 (2015), 71-80</p> <p>P. Knysh and Y.P. Korkolis, &ldquo;Identification of the post-necking hardening response of rate-and temperature-dependent metals&rdquo;, International Journal of Solids and Structures, 115 (2017), 149-160</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Ioannis&nbsp;Korkolis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigated the fundamental science behind microforming processes, i.e., deformation processes where one or more of the external dimensions of the component that is being made are comparable to the grain size of the metal. Metals are composed of atoms arranged in periodic lattices. Due to the way that a metal solidifies from the melt, multiple lattices start to grow simultaneously, so that in the end the metal is seen to be composed of many distinct crystals or grains (each crystal/grain having a specific orientation of its atomic lattice in space). The grains are strongly anisotropic, i.e., their properties and behavior depend on the orientation. Since a typical polycrystalline metal is composed of millions of grains, what is observed at the macroscale is a statistical average of the behavior of each grain. On the other hand, when the dimensions of the component are comparable to the grain size, that averaging is not valid and the overall behavior is governed by that of individual grains. An example of this is deformation-induced surface roughening, that oftentimes limits the deformation during microforming. This prevents the creation of complex shapes and ultimately increases the cost of biomedical, microelectronic and other devices.  The project evolved along two parallel paths: creation of custom experimental testing equipment, and modeling of the behaviors observed using crystal plasticity. On the equipment front, two machines for microforming have been created: one is an apparatus for combined axial force and internal pressure loading of microtubes (Ripley and Korkolis, 2015). To the best of our knowledge, this is the only machine of its size in the world. It has been used to probe the behavior of stainless steel microtubes for biomedical applications (also see Ripley, 2015). The second is a custom apparatus for pure bending of microtubes. Both machines can be used with Digital Image Correlation and Infrared Thermography.  On the modeling front, this award supported perhaps the only research on deformation-induced surface roughening where there is a 1-to-1 correlation between the specimen used for testing, and the finite element model. In other words, the microstructure of the specimen was reconstructed from 2 scans of its top and bottom surfaces. A special procedure for interpolating these images in 3D was devised. The procedure is general enough so that it can be used for a much larger family of 3D reconstructions from 2D scans, i.e., from partial data sets, and beyond only metal microstructures. It has enough merit to have been published separately in a peer-reviewed journal (Knysh et al, 2019). For this research, an exact model of the specimen used for the experiments was reconstructed, and the deformation-induced roughening was predicted. The model was further exercised to reveal correlations between microstructure and roughening (Knysh et al, submitted). In parallel to this effort, novel techniques for determining the inelastic heat fraction (Knysh and Korkolis, 2015) and the post-necking hardening response (Knysh and Korkolis, 2017) were proposed. Both of these are of very general applicability in mechanics of materials.  The project lead to an extensive training of human capital: 3 graduate students, which resulted in 1 PhD and 2 MS theses; 6 REU students, including 1 female and 1 African-American; 5 undergraduates in 3 senior design projects, including 1 African-American. It has also involved 1 visiting professor from Univ. of Tokyo and 1 undergraduate student from Tokyo Metropolitan University (Japan). The project has also lead to international collaborations in Japan and S. Korea, including a research visit by the PhD student for 3 months in Tokyo. Lastly, the project has involved a U.S. start-up company, Psylotech, Inc.  The research on the fundamental science behind microforming processes applicable to biomedical and microelectronic components is expected to benefit society at-large, by allowing more imaginative designs to be implemented, and a more rational process design. In addition, by shedding further light to the interrelation between surface roughening and microstructure, it can enable alloy and process design across the spectrum of manufacturing industry, enhancing the competitiveness of US manufacturing.  REFERENCES  P.W. Ripley and Y.P. Korkolis, "Multiaxial Deformation Apparatus for Testing of Microtubes Under Combined Axial-Force and Internal-Pressure", Experimental Mechanics, 56 (2016), 273-286  P.W. Ripley, "Development of biaxial loading apparatus for testing of microtubes under axial force and internal pressure and experiments on 304L stainless steel microtubes", MS Thesis, Univ. of New Hampshire, 2014.  P. Knysh, K. Sasaki, T. Furushima, M. Knezevic, Y.P. Korkolis, "A shape interpolation procedure: Application to creating explicit grain structure models based on partial data sets", Computational Materials Science, 167 (2019), 42-51  P. Knysh and Y.P. Korkolis, "Determination of the fraction of plastic work converted into heat in metals", Mechanics of Materials, 86 (2015), 71-80  P. Knysh and Y.P. Korkolis, "Identification of the post-necking hardening response of rate-and temperature-dependent metals", International Journal of Solids and Structures, 115 (2017), 149-160       Last Modified: 07/08/2019       Submitted by: Ioannis Korkolis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
