<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Exploiting Quantum Optoelectronic Properties of Dirac Quasiparticles in Graphene</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>**** TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate and enhance understanding of the quantum electronic and optoelectronic phenomena of graphene - a system with two-dimensional Dirac cone dispersion. Graphene has unique electronic and symmetry properties distinct from other 2D electronic systems, such as the chiral massless dispersion of low energy electrons in single-layer graphene, the tunable effective mass and bandgap in bilayer graphene, and unusual quantum Hall effects with large Landau level spacing at moderate magnetic fields. The integration of ultrafast pump-probe spectroscopy with electrical transport will lead to the investigation of the electronic properties of such systems while benefiting from advanced nano-optical spectroscopy techniques. This proposal comprises investigations of both spatial and temporal dynamics of non-equilibrium excitations with and without magnetic fields, the photovoltaic Hall effect with circularly polarized light, Berry-phase related valley Hall effects, broken-symmetry states, and photocurrent generation in the quantum Hall regime. A fundamental understanding of this technologically important material may lead to new applications including high-speed and low power-consumption electronics, broadband communication, new sensing technologies, and photovoltaics. This multidisciplinary research program provides an excellent platform for undergraduate and graduate students to learn physics, device engineering, and materials science, and for post-doctoral researchers to gain professional experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;As silicon technology faces fundamental limits, breakthroughs in electronics are likely to rely on other materials which allow the exploitation of features and concepts not available in the silicon/oxide system. One promising system is graphene, a single layer of graphite. What sets graphene apart from conventional semiconductors is that the electrons in the graphene behave like photons, traveling with an effective speed just 300 times smaller than the speed of light. This unique feature gives graphene superior physical properties for potential new electronic applications. This project will exploit the novel electronic and optical properties of graphene through a combination of material synthesis, device fabrication, and optoelectronic measurements. In particularly, electron dynamics will be probed by ultrafast laser pulses with a pulse width 13 orders of magnitude smaller than one second. The obtained physical understanding of this technologically important material may lead to high-speed and low power-consumption electronics, broadband communication, new sensing technologies, and photovoltaics. The proposed multidisciplinary research program provides an excellent platform for undergraduate and graduate students to learn physics, device engineering, and materials science, and for post-doctoral researchers to gain professional experience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1150719</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaodong Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xuxd@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065438444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000580398</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/03/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951560</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Standard">The recent emergence of 2D layered materials offers a new material platform for exploring science and technology. In this project, we combine rigorous nanoscale device fabrication and optoelectronic measurements to investigate the fundamental optoelectronic properties of Dirac quantum materials, such as graphene and atomically-thin transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs).</p> <p class="Standard">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Standard">In graphene, we studied a number of device structures. (1) Simple monolayer graphene transistor. We discovered a photo-Nernst effect, which drives photocurrent uniformly along the free edges of graphene in the presence of perpendicular magnetic field. This &ldquo;photo-Nernst&rdquo; current provides an unambiguous demonstration of the Shockley-Ramo nature of long-range photocurrent generation in a gapless material. (2) Bilayer graphene with a dual gate structure. We demonstrate enhanced hot-carrier response by opening a bandgap in originally gapless bilayer graphene. (3) Graphene on hexagonal boron nitride with a moir&eacute; superlattice potential. We demonstrate the generation and collection of multiple hot-carriers upon the absorption of one photon, promising for highly efficient and flexible graphene optoelectronics.</p> <p class="Standard">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Standard">Atomically thin TMDs offer the first type of solid state system for optical control of valley pseudospin, which is one type of electronic degrees of freedom for encoding information. In monolayer TMD, we demonstrated both optical initialization of valley pseudospin in a particular state and optical creation of quantum coherence between two states. In bilayer TMDs, we demonstrate electrically switching on and off the valley pseudospin states, a prototype of valleytronics.</p> <p class="Standard">&nbsp;</p> <p>Our study of the fundamental device properties of Dirac materials shows the promise of these new quantum materials for electronic and photonic applications. This program also provided an educational platform for 4 PhD students, over 10 undergraduate students, and one postdoc. A number of out-reach programs and new classes have been developed during the project for further enhancing broader impacts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Xiaodong&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The recent emergence of 2D layered materials offers a new material platform for exploring science and technology. In this project, we combine rigorous nanoscale device fabrication and optoelectronic measurements to investigate the fundamental optoelectronic properties of Dirac quantum materials, such as graphene and atomically-thin transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs).   In graphene, we studied a number of device structures. (1) Simple monolayer graphene transistor. We discovered a photo-Nernst effect, which drives photocurrent uniformly along the free edges of graphene in the presence of perpendicular magnetic field. This "photo-Nernst" current provides an unambiguous demonstration of the Shockley-Ramo nature of long-range photocurrent generation in a gapless material. (2) Bilayer graphene with a dual gate structure. We demonstrate enhanced hot-carrier response by opening a bandgap in originally gapless bilayer graphene. (3) Graphene on hexagonal boron nitride with a moir&eacute; superlattice potential. We demonstrate the generation and collection of multiple hot-carriers upon the absorption of one photon, promising for highly efficient and flexible graphene optoelectronics.   Atomically thin TMDs offer the first type of solid state system for optical control of valley pseudospin, which is one type of electronic degrees of freedom for encoding information. In monolayer TMD, we demonstrated both optical initialization of valley pseudospin in a particular state and optical creation of quantum coherence between two states. In bilayer TMDs, we demonstrate electrically switching on and off the valley pseudospin states, a prototype of valleytronics.    Our study of the fundamental device properties of Dirac materials shows the promise of these new quantum materials for electronic and photonic applications. This program also provided an educational platform for 4 PhD students, over 10 undergraduate students, and one postdoc. A number of out-reach programs and new classes have been developed during the project for further enhancing broader impacts.           Last Modified: 01/15/2017       Submitted by: Xiaodong Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
