<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PECASE: Widely tunable monolithic THz waveguides, lasers, and arrays</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404800</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proposal ECCS 1150071&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective&lt;br/&gt;The research objective of this proposal is the investigation and development of widely and continuously tunable terahertz quantum-cascade lasers and other active devices based upon monolithic and voltage tunable metamaterial waveguides. These waveguides are based on the transmission-line metamaterial concept in which the dispersion relation is tuned by electrical control of integrated capacitive elements. Goals include demonstration of widely tunable terahertz laser sources in various configurations, including tunable distributed feedback lasers, tunable master-oscillator power-amplifiers, and beam-steerable phased-array THz laser emitters. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is the integration of tunable metamaterial concepts with laser waveguides, in which propagation is sensitively dependent on values of embedded circuit elements. This approach can achieve a much wider range of tunability than can be achieved using temperature or other electrical techniques, with a high degree of monolithic integration. The demonstration of amplifier and distributed feedback configurations will allow the output power to be scaled to several milliwatts or greater with a directive beam pattern. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts lie in the development of a new approach for achieving tunable semiconductor lasers. Additionally, terahertz technology requires improved sources and detectors for sensing, imaging, and spectroscopy. The core of the educational plan is to enhance undergraduate research within the Electrical Engineering department through the development of a coordinated publicity, outreach, and training program, as well as directly employing undergraduates in this research. Multiple campus resources will be leveraged to attract and fund underrepresented minority students to this research and engineering in general.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1150071</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin S Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bswilliams@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3107940102</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513615</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097E</Code>
<Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~4800</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this project was to develop a new type of laser that operates in the terahertz range of the electromagnetic spectrum, whose output wavelength can be &ldquo;tuned&rdquo; via electrical control. Terahertz radiation describes electromagnetic waves with wavelengths between 30 &mu;m and 1 mm; this range resides between the microwave and infrared range, and represents one of the last frontiers of the electromagnetic spectrum. Sources of terahertz radiation are desired for a wide variety of applications, including security screening, nondestructive evaluation, spectroscopy, chemical and gas sensing, astrophysical measurements of the interstellar medium and star formation, high speed secure communications, and biomedical imaging of various types. In particular, many applications require THz sources that are tunable, i.e. that can easily change the wavelength that they emit at. This is particularly important for spectroscopy applications, where one usually tries to tune the wavelength over relevant spectral &ldquo;fingerprint&rdquo; features of some substance, to see how it absorbs/transmits light as a function of wavelength. Terahertz quantum-cascade lasers are an emerging THz source, but it has been difficult to obtain a laser which has a widely tunable wavelength, as well as having a good beam pattern with reasonable output power. The crux of the problem lies in the type of waveguide used to guide the THz radiation; the waveguide has dimensions smaller than the wavelength, which makes it difficult to couple the light out of the cavity, and difficult to prevent reflections from the front facet of the laser.</p> <p>The major outcome from this project was the development of a new scheme for the tuning of terahertz quantum-cascade lasers based upon a so-called metasurface external cavity laser. The novelty lies in the so-called metasurface that is in fact an array of quantum-cascade laser waveguides refashioned to operate as antennas. These antennas can couple the THz radiation so that it can interact with the laser gain material, which is then reradiated. This metasurface acts as a mirror, which not only reflects the THz light, but amplifies it as well via stimulated emission. It can easily be made part of a laser cavity, in which the THz light is trapped between two mirrors, and amplified with each pass. When one of the mirrors is made movable, the wavelength is tuned. Since there is no longer a facet, facet reflections are no longer a problem. We have demonstrated preliminary results of tuning of the wavelength of 10% of its center value, all while maintaining a good power level and good beam quality. What is more, we believe that this performance is the tip of the iceberg, and much larger tuning is feasible in the future. Along the way, our work contributed to many side results, such as demonstration of new types of THz antennas waveguides, development of new theoretical and simulation tools for modeling quantum-cascade lasers, and techniques for microfabrication of the lasers. Several graduate students and undergraduate students were funded for research under this effort, all of which took place within a larger program to promote undergraduate research in engineering at UCLA.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2017<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;S&nbsp;Williams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project was to develop a new type of laser that operates in the terahertz range of the electromagnetic spectrum, whose output wavelength can be "tuned" via electrical control. Terahertz radiation describes electromagnetic waves with wavelengths between 30 &mu;m and 1 mm; this range resides between the microwave and infrared range, and represents one of the last frontiers of the electromagnetic spectrum. Sources of terahertz radiation are desired for a wide variety of applications, including security screening, nondestructive evaluation, spectroscopy, chemical and gas sensing, astrophysical measurements of the interstellar medium and star formation, high speed secure communications, and biomedical imaging of various types. In particular, many applications require THz sources that are tunable, i.e. that can easily change the wavelength that they emit at. This is particularly important for spectroscopy applications, where one usually tries to tune the wavelength over relevant spectral "fingerprint" features of some substance, to see how it absorbs/transmits light as a function of wavelength. Terahertz quantum-cascade lasers are an emerging THz source, but it has been difficult to obtain a laser which has a widely tunable wavelength, as well as having a good beam pattern with reasonable output power. The crux of the problem lies in the type of waveguide used to guide the THz radiation; the waveguide has dimensions smaller than the wavelength, which makes it difficult to couple the light out of the cavity, and difficult to prevent reflections from the front facet of the laser.  The major outcome from this project was the development of a new scheme for the tuning of terahertz quantum-cascade lasers based upon a so-called metasurface external cavity laser. The novelty lies in the so-called metasurface that is in fact an array of quantum-cascade laser waveguides refashioned to operate as antennas. These antennas can couple the THz radiation so that it can interact with the laser gain material, which is then reradiated. This metasurface acts as a mirror, which not only reflects the THz light, but amplifies it as well via stimulated emission. It can easily be made part of a laser cavity, in which the THz light is trapped between two mirrors, and amplified with each pass. When one of the mirrors is made movable, the wavelength is tuned. Since there is no longer a facet, facet reflections are no longer a problem. We have demonstrated preliminary results of tuning of the wavelength of 10% of its center value, all while maintaining a good power level and good beam quality. What is more, we believe that this performance is the tip of the iceberg, and much larger tuning is feasible in the future. Along the way, our work contributed to many side results, such as demonstration of new types of THz antennas waveguides, development of new theoretical and simulation tools for modeling quantum-cascade lasers, and techniques for microfabrication of the lasers. Several graduate students and undergraduate students were funded for research under this effort, all of which took place within a larger program to promote undergraduate research in engineering at UCLA.             Last Modified: 04/20/2017       Submitted by: Benjamin S Williams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
