<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Social Multimedia as Volunteered Geographic Information: Crowdsourcing What-Is-Where on the Surface of the Earth Through Proximate Sensing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>497208.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>527028</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project investigates social multimedia for geographic discovery. Specifically, community-contributed ground-level images and videos are used to map what-is-where on the surface of the Earth in much the same way that overhead images taken from air- or space-borne platforms have been used for decades in the traditional field of remote sensing. The overarching premise is that georeferenced social multimedia data can be considered a form of volunteered geographic information. Further, it can enable geographic discovery not possible through traditional means. The framework, termed proximate sensing, is applied to two challenging geographic discovery problems: 1) land-use classification, and 2) mapping public sentiment such as how scenic a particular geographic location is. Land-use classification is an important problem but is often not possible using overhead images since remote sensing does not record activities. This project instead applies and extends state-of-the-art techniques in image understanding to ground-level images and videos to map land-use. The motivation is similar for mapping public sentiment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts include developing K-12 spatial literacy curricula through an Engineering Projects in Community Service team whose client is the Merced County Office of Education. University of California-Merced was recently classified as an Hispanic Serving Institution, making it one of only a handful of research universities with this designation nationwide. Undergraduate students from underrepresented groups will be involved in developing a GeographUSA project whereby volunteers can upload geographically representative photos of the United States. Results, datasets, and other project artifacts will be made available through the project website (http://vision.ucmerced.edu/projects/socialmultimedia/).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1150115</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Newsam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn Newsam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>snewsam@ucmerced.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2092284167</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000458548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California - Merced</Name>
<CityName>Merced</CityName>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2092012039</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5200 North Lake Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>113645084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, MERCED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California - Merced]]></Name>
<CityName>Merced</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5200 N. Lake Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~100223</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~113156</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~102934</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~106847</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~103868</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit: This project performed a comprehensive investigation into exploiting georeferenced social multimedia for geographic discovery.&nbsp; Specifically, community-contributed ground-level images and videos were used to map what-is-where on the surface of the Earth in much the same way that overhead images taken from air- or space-borne platforms have been used for decades in the traditional field of remote sensing.</p> <p>We were able to show that ground-level images and videos could be used to map a range of phenomenon that are not easy to map using overhead imagery.&nbsp; This includes mapping land use (what a location is used for), mapping activity (where people are performing certain activities), and mapping public sentiment (how people feel about a place).&nbsp; The key technical challenge was how to automatically extract this information from large collections of ground-level images and videos.&nbsp; In this context, we made a number of novel algorithmic contributions to several fields such as computer vision and spatial data analysis.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: The project contributed significantly to the training of a number of students in STEM fields including five undergraduate students in Computer Science and Engineering, two master's students in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, and three PhD students also in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.&nbsp; Two of these PhD students have graduated and found gainful employment, one as a researcher in industry and another as a university lecturer.</p> <p>The principle investigator performed outreach to K-12 students underrepresented in STEM fields by presenting the research to students participating in the summer Science and Technology Enrichment Program (STEP) of the NSF Center for Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) at UC Merced.</p> <p>While the algorithmic contributions were mostly in computer science, the project was interdisciplinary and thus of interest to researchers in geography.&nbsp; The principal investigator gave numerous presentations about the research at venues attended by geography researchers.&nbsp; This stimulated discussions which have resulted in interdisciplinary collaborations.</p> <p>The methods and results of the work have been published in a number of conference and journal manuscripts.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Shawn&nbsp;Newsam</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: This project performed a comprehensive investigation into exploiting georeferenced social multimedia for geographic discovery.  Specifically, community-contributed ground-level images and videos were used to map what-is-where on the surface of the Earth in much the same way that overhead images taken from air- or space-borne platforms have been used for decades in the traditional field of remote sensing.  We were able to show that ground-level images and videos could be used to map a range of phenomenon that are not easy to map using overhead imagery.  This includes mapping land use (what a location is used for), mapping activity (where people are performing certain activities), and mapping public sentiment (how people feel about a place).  The key technical challenge was how to automatically extract this information from large collections of ground-level images and videos.  In this context, we made a number of novel algorithmic contributions to several fields such as computer vision and spatial data analysis.  Broader Impacts: The project contributed significantly to the training of a number of students in STEM fields including five undergraduate students in Computer Science and Engineering, two master's students in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, and three PhD students also in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.  Two of these PhD students have graduated and found gainful employment, one as a researcher in industry and another as a university lecturer.  The principle investigator performed outreach to K-12 students underrepresented in STEM fields by presenting the research to students participating in the summer Science and Technology Enrichment Program (STEP) of the NSF Center for Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) at UC Merced.  While the algorithmic contributions were mostly in computer science, the project was interdisciplinary and thus of interest to researchers in geography.  The principal investigator gave numerous presentations about the research at venues attended by geography researchers.  This stimulated discussions which have resulted in interdisciplinary collaborations.  The methods and results of the work have been published in a number of conference and journal manuscripts.       Last Modified: 08/23/2019       Submitted by: Shawn Newsam]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
