<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Functional Metal-Ligand Assemblies: Self-Sorting, Supramolecular Catalysis and Molecular Dynamics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stamchan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928684</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division supports the research group of Dr. Richard Hooley of the University of California-Riverside to create new water-soluble functional synthetic receptors via metal-ligand based self-assembly and investigate their application towards molecular recognition and supramolecular catalysis.  This research aims to address one of the main deficiencies faced by current synthetic receptors when compared to enzymes; the inability to present a functional group towards a guest bound on the interior of the cavity.  The synthetic route to the metal-ligand clusters is modular and easily tunable, allowing access to a wide scope of introverted groups.  By orienting functional groups towards the bound guest, selective substrate recognition and supramolecular catalysis will be enhanced. The presence of chiral species, hydrogen bond donors or nucleophiles on the interior of the clusters allows a number of novel receptor properties to be studied.  In addition, by positioning catalytically active groups in close proximity with bound substrates, biomimetic reactions and catalysis are possible.  NMR spectroscopy will be used to investigate guest binding, ligand exchange and reaction kinetics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will extend the capabilities of synthetic host molecules in a number of fields including molecular recognition and catalysis and will introduce new avenues of research in biomimetic organic chemistry.  This interdisciplinary project will offer a stimulating research environment for the education and training of students, including members of underrepresented groups. In addition, this research is integrated with an educational component that aims at increasing retention of undergraduate students (and especially underrepresented minorities) in STEM fields by engaging students through the use of collaborative problem-based case studies in the lower division organic chemistry course sequence.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1151773</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hooley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard J Hooley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.hooley@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518274924</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000531463</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 University Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The human body uses large, complex molecules such as proteins to control many cellular processes. Chemists strive to mimic the complexity of these biological structures with artificial analogs, but these mimics cannot approach the complexity of natural enzymes. Self-assembly is a powerful approach to create large, complex molecules without the challenge of complex step-by-step synthesis. This process is similar to molecular-level Lego, whereby individual pieces can be simply put together to make a larger, more complex structure.</p> <p>In this research project, we developed self-assembly approaches to creating new chemical structures that act in a manner similar to proteins. Overall, 30 publications resulted from this grant. We have synthesized a wide variety of cage complexes of different sizes and shapes with different metal-ligand coordinators, and have studied the control of their structural properties, post-assembly reactivity, luminescent properties, and self-sorting between different ligand types. The combination of H-bonding and metal-ligand assembly allows unusual complexes to be accessed, as well as allowing exquisite control over their structure, mirroring the folding behavior of proteins. We have also have studied the synthesis and properties of host molecules that self-fold using metal coordination, and the creation of more active hydrocarbon oxidation catalysts. Finally, we have studied their use for binding biomolecules at membranes, peptide sensing and guest binding in cellular environments.</p> <p>As well as coordinating research endeavors, the CAREER award has been used to enhance educational infrastructure. PI Richard Hooley was involved in implementing real-world active learning case studies and active learning flipped labs in the undergraduate chemistry curriculum designed to increase minority participation in STEM fields. 11 undergraduate students were co-authors on papers published during this grant.<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hooley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The human body uses large, complex molecules such as proteins to control many cellular processes. Chemists strive to mimic the complexity of these biological structures with artificial analogs, but these mimics cannot approach the complexity of natural enzymes. Self-assembly is a powerful approach to create large, complex molecules without the challenge of complex step-by-step synthesis. This process is similar to molecular-level Lego, whereby individual pieces can be simply put together to make a larger, more complex structure.  In this research project, we developed self-assembly approaches to creating new chemical structures that act in a manner similar to proteins. Overall, 30 publications resulted from this grant. We have synthesized a wide variety of cage complexes of different sizes and shapes with different metal-ligand coordinators, and have studied the control of their structural properties, post-assembly reactivity, luminescent properties, and self-sorting between different ligand types. The combination of H-bonding and metal-ligand assembly allows unusual complexes to be accessed, as well as allowing exquisite control over their structure, mirroring the folding behavior of proteins. We have also have studied the synthesis and properties of host molecules that self-fold using metal coordination, and the creation of more active hydrocarbon oxidation catalysts. Finally, we have studied their use for binding biomolecules at membranes, peptide sensing and guest binding in cellular environments.  As well as coordinating research endeavors, the CAREER award has been used to enhance educational infrastructure. PI Richard Hooley was involved in implementing real-world active learning case studies and active learning flipped labs in the undergraduate chemistry curriculum designed to increase minority participation in STEM fields. 11 undergraduate students were co-authors on papers published during this grant.           Last Modified: 04/09/2018       Submitted by: Richard J Hooley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
