<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: MPS-BIO: Mathematical Modeling and Experiments of Neuromechanical Pumping</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>504236.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>504236</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broad goal of this proposal is to create mathematical models of the electrophysiology and neuromechanics of an organ and organism whose dynamics rely on environmental cues and electrical activation through the action of pacemaker cells. Recent advancements in computational fluid dynamics have enabled researchers to efficiently explore problems that involve moving elastic boundaries immersed in fluids for problems such as cardiac fluid dynamics, fish swimming, and the movement of bacteria. These advances have also made modeling the interaction between a fluid and a neuromechanical model of an elastic organ or organism feasible. This project will focus on the development and implementation of such models for two problems: 1) fluid transport through the pumping of tubular hearts, and 2) feeding currents generated by the pulsation of jellyfish bells. This proposal leverages existing computational algorithms for fluid-structure interactions, whereas the mathematical novelty lies in coupling this technology to living boundaries. The models will integrate feedback between the conduction of action potentials, the contraction of muscles, the movement of tissues, and fluid motion. For example, mathematical models will be developed that couple action potentials triggered by noisy pacemaker cells to the generation of tension through appropriate muscle and Ca2+ models. The non-Hookean material properties and geometry of highly deformable heart tubes and jellyfish bells will also be quantified and accurately modeled using discrete differential geometry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will combine computational, mathematical, and experimental tools to ultimately answer some of questions posed in one of the five grand challenges in organismal biology: Integrating living and physical systems. Integrative mathematical models of the neurobiology, muscular mechanics, elasticity, and fluid dynamics of pumping tubular hearts and jellyfish bells will be developed. While great strides have been made in the modeling and simulation of each of these components separately, coupling these fields remains elusive. The working proposition that motivates this research is that modeling the complete neuromechanical system is more tractable for the two selected problems than almost any other given their relative simplicity. The results of this research may also provide a framework for the development of integrative models of other fundamental biological problems such as the movement and regulation of waste through the intestines, air through the lungs, and lymph through the lymphatic system. The educational focus of this proposal is to implement a unified training program for mathematicians and biologists centered on mathematical modeling in biology. The proposed educational activities will include a first year seminar in epidemiology, a course and associated text on mathematical modeling in comparative biomechanics for biologists and mathematicians, and a summer program for mathematical biologists at the UNC Galapagos Center. This educational program is motivated by the fact that it will be critical to train mathematics and biology students at this interface in order to rise to the scientific challenges that will be posed during the 21st century.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1151478</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura A Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lauram9@math.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199432434</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000276453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel HIll</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275993255</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Chapman Hall Room 412]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059E</Code>
<Text>Complex fluids</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~444417</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~59819</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-9e985682-7fff-031e-bff7-1b7844632ece"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This award supported the creation of neuromechanical models of an organ or organism whose dynamics rely on environmental cues and neural activation through the action of pacemakers. This work combined computational, mathematical, and experimental tools to ultimately answer some of questions posed in one of the five grand challenges in organismal biology: Integrating living and physical systems. We have shown that mathematical models that couple the electrophysiology of embryonic and invertebrate heart tubes with the activation of muscular force and the subsequent movement of the elastic heart tube within a fluid better describe tubular heart pumping than models that do not incorporate electromechanics. Similarly, we have shown how desynchronization of the pacemakers in jellyfish result in asymmetric contractions of the bell in order to perform a turn. At least 20 peer-reviewed published or submitted journal publications have directly resulted from this award to date.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The methods and tools that were developed for this project, all of which are freely available online, should find immediate use in a variety of biofluids applications and educational activities. In particular, we have developed 2D MATLAB and Python codes for use in undergraduate research, courses, and for smaller scale research projects (ib2d). This year, we developed a software package that auto detects edges in images and discretizes those boundaries for use in 2D immersed boundary simulations.&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-a84b7ffb-7fff-b39d-4048-32e88af274c3"><span>It is expected that the tools and mathematical frameworks developed in this project will drive innovations in medicine and bioengineering. Given the versatility of immersed boundary methods, the potential impact of this work is quite broad. These methods have already been applied in the group's work to inform studies which aim to address scientific questions such as the fluid-structure interactions which drive the formation of the developing heart to studies that consider the function of the lymphatic system.</span></span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>A unified training program for mathematicians and biologists centered on mathematical modeling in biology was implemented as a result of this project. PI Miller developed an introductory course for quantitative biology with modeling labs and graduate courses on the numerical modeling of biological fluid dynamic problems. Over the past five years, 21 undergraduate students have worked with Miller, and 14 have gone to graduate school in disciplines ranging from mathematics to mechanical engineering to the life sciences. Miller has graduated six doctoral students who have gone on to tenure track faculty positions at Bucknell, U. Akron, and the College of New Jersey. Miller has also mentored 2 postdoctoral fellows who are now faculty at New Mexico Tech and the University of Tennessee Knoxville.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/02/2019<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;A&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128019329_6-moon--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128019329_6-moon--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Jellyfish Vortex Wake"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128019329_6-moon--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Jellyfish Vortex Wake"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fluorescein dye injected to highlight the separated starting vortex of a moon jellyfish.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laura Miller</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;A&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Jellyfish Vortex Wake</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128487260_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128487260_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Vortex wake of a numerical jellyfish"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128487260_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Vortex wake of a numerical jellyfish"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vorticity contours of the wake generated by a numerical model of a swimming jellyfish. A hybrid finite difference finite element version of the immersed boundary method was used to simulate this problem.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Hoover and Laura Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;A&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Vortex wake of a numerical jellyfish</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128552039_Turn_Vectors_med0030--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128552039_Turn_Vectors_med0030--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Turning of a numerical jellyfish"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128552039_Turn_Vectors_med0030--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Turning of a numerical jellyfish"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Velocity vectors showing the flows generated by a numerical model of a jellyfish performing a turn. A hybrid finite difference finite element version of the immersed boundary method was used to simulate this problem.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Hoover and Laura Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;A&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Turning of a numerical jellyfish</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128701166_DSC_0339--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128701166_DSC_0339--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Upside down jellyfish"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1151478/1151478_10207729_1549128701166_DSC_0339--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Upside down jellyfish"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Zoomed in view of the oral arms of an upside down jellyfish.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Grace McLaughlin and Laura Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;A&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Upside down jellyfish</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This award supported the creation of neuromechanical models of an organ or organism whose dynamics rely on environmental cues and neural activation through the action of pacemakers. This work combined computational, mathematical, and experimental tools to ultimately answer some of questions posed in one of the five grand challenges in organismal biology: Integrating living and physical systems. We have shown that mathematical models that couple the electrophysiology of embryonic and invertebrate heart tubes with the activation of muscular force and the subsequent movement of the elastic heart tube within a fluid better describe tubular heart pumping than models that do not incorporate electromechanics. Similarly, we have shown how desynchronization of the pacemakers in jellyfish result in asymmetric contractions of the bell in order to perform a turn. At least 20 peer-reviewed published or submitted journal publications have directly resulted from this award to date.    The methods and tools that were developed for this project, all of which are freely available online, should find immediate use in a variety of biofluids applications and educational activities. In particular, we have developed 2D MATLAB and Python codes for use in undergraduate research, courses, and for smaller scale research projects (ib2d). This year, we developed a software package that auto detects edges in images and discretizes those boundaries for use in 2D immersed boundary simulations. It is expected that the tools and mathematical frameworks developed in this project will drive innovations in medicine and bioengineering. Given the versatility of immersed boundary methods, the potential impact of this work is quite broad. These methods have already been applied in the group's work to inform studies which aim to address scientific questions such as the fluid-structure interactions which drive the formation of the developing heart to studies that consider the function of the lymphatic system.    A unified training program for mathematicians and biologists centered on mathematical modeling in biology was implemented as a result of this project. PI Miller developed an introductory course for quantitative biology with modeling labs and graduate courses on the numerical modeling of biological fluid dynamic problems. Over the past five years, 21 undergraduate students have worked with Miller, and 14 have gone to graduate school in disciplines ranging from mathematics to mechanical engineering to the life sciences. Miller has graduated six doctoral students who have gone on to tenure track faculty positions at Bucknell, U. Akron, and the College of New Jersey. Miller has also mentored 2 postdoctoral fellows who are now faculty at New Mexico Tech and the University of Tennessee Knoxville.             Last Modified: 02/02/2019       Submitted by: Laura A Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
