<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Search for New Physics Beyond the Standard Model at the LHC</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>561853.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>561853</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Randy Ruchti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports a CAREER program at the University of Illinois at Chicago (UIC) to search for signatures of dark matter produced by possible new fundamental interactions at the CERN Large Hadron Collider (LHC) using the Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) Experiment.   A key signature of a massive dark matter particle is that it escapes the detector without a trace, causing an apparent large transverse momentum imbalance. The unique contribution of this project is a generic, inclusive search for highly boosted hadronically decaying particles in events with large missing transverse momentum, giving rise to "funny-looking" jets, be they heavy boosted particles (top's, W's, Z's) or light color-singlet boosted particles (axion-like particles), emitted in the cascade decay chains of possible new heavy, pair-produced colored particles. This plan has the potential to shed light on the origin of dark matter and could break new ground in the search for new phenomena at the LHC.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are directed toward high schools in Chicago area, which use an active discovery format of teaching developed at the University of Arizona, known as "Modeling Physics", as well as inner city Chicago schools not using the "Modeling Physics" method. Together with the UIC College of Education's certification program in secondary science education, lesson plans will be developed within the "Modeling Physics" methodology that enable high school teachers to incorporate some of the latest and most exciting scientific developments of particle physics coming from the LHC into their classrooms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1151640</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Cavanaugh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Cavanaugh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cavana@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129969406</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S. Marshfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MB 502, M/C 551]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098987217</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~101851</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~115001</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~345001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There are two high impact scientific questions which this project investigated: (1) how can the Higgs Boson&rsquo;s mass be so light when gravity is so profoundly weak compared with all other known fundamental forces, and (2) what is the quantum nature of the mysterious astronomical substance known as &ldquo;dark matter&rdquo;, first inferred in 1933 by Fritz Zwicky from his observations of galactic structures and shown more recently by space-based experiments to actually dominate the large-scale structure of our universe. Those two questions might be connected through the fact that we have experimentally confirmed all of the possible symmetries of space and time, save one. &nbsp;A so-called supersymmetry between fundamental particles so far remains undiscovered. It could provide a &ldquo;natural&rdquo; solution, which keeps the Higgs Boson light despite the huge hierarchy in the fundamental interactions of nature, and it can predict a new fundamental particle that might be responsible for dark matter. Hence, the supersymmetry hypothesis provides an exciting and tantalizing possibility of connecting natural phenomena that are observed at the smallest quantum scales with phenomena observed at the largest cosmological scales, offering a profound insight into the very structure of space and time. If supersymmetry provides a natural solution to the Higgs mass problem, then hypothetical supersymmetric partners to the well known top quark (known as top squarks) should exist and have a mass scale which is not too much heavier than the standard model top quark.</p> <p>One of the primary objectives of this project was to analyse the data collected by the Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) Experiment at the CERN Large Hadron Collider (LHC) to search for new, undiscovered phenomena involving heavy, fast-moving particles produced in the presence of large missing momentum. In particular, this project studied high-energy proton-proton collisions for evidence of top quarks produced in association with large missing momentum, a signature which is consistent with the direct production of supersymmetric top squarks together with an unseen dark matter particle. &nbsp;Upon analysing the full Run 1 dataset and much of the Run 2 dataset provided by the LHC, no evidence for either top squarks or dark matter particles have been found in the LHC data. This project was able to infer that the mass of any hypothetical stop-quark must be more than six times heavier than the mass of the top quark, if the mass of the dark matter particle is very light; alternatively, if the mass of the dark matter particle is quite heavy (say five to six times the mass of a W or Z Boson), then the mass of the top squark could still be as light as about three times the mass of the top quark. The impact of the findings from this project is significant as it limits the possibilities that a minimal supersymmetric extension to the standard model of particle physics can provide a both "natural" explanation for the light mass of the Higgs Boson and an explanation for the existence of dark matter -- two of the most profound conundrums in science.</p> <p>Another primary objective of this project was to contribute to the Improved (Phase-1) and High Luminosity (Phase-2) upgrades of the CMS high-speed electronics for on-line data filtering, known as a "Level-1 Trigger" and which makes extensive use of Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) technology. This project played a key role in implementing firmware and in commissioning the Phase-1 upgrade to the CMS Level-1 Trigger. &nbsp;The project also led the preliminary design of a future Level-1 Trigger for the Phase-2 upgrade. &nbsp;As part of our research and development, this project explored the use of machine learning in low-latency, low-power FPGA hardware. We, together with collaborators, contributed to a package based on High-Level Synthesis (HLS) called "hls4ml" to synthesize machine learning architectures onto FPGAs. The use of HLS increases the accessibility of deep learning applications across a broad user community and allows for a dramatic decrease in firmware development time.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, this project partnered with the Student Inquiry and Research Program at the Illinois Math and Science Academy, a local area high-school in the Chicago suburbs. &nbsp;The high-school students worked to analyse CMS datasets in the search for supersymmetry, and presented their results at a special Colloquium event for high-school student research at Illinois Math and Science Academy. &nbsp;During the lifetime of the project, high school students learned the basics of computer programming, statistical inference, and experimental methods. &nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, this project significantly contributed to our understanding of how the Higgs Boson can be so light and what is the particle nature of dark matter. &nbsp;In support of that, novel methods to program high speed electronics were developed and used to record high-energy proton-proton collisions at the Large Hadron Collider. &nbsp;And, this project worked with local area high schools to bring the excitement of discovery science into the classroom.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2018<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Cavanaugh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There are two high impact scientific questions which this project investigated: (1) how can the Higgs Boson?s mass be so light when gravity is so profoundly weak compared with all other known fundamental forces, and (2) what is the quantum nature of the mysterious astronomical substance known as "dark matter", first inferred in 1933 by Fritz Zwicky from his observations of galactic structures and shown more recently by space-based experiments to actually dominate the large-scale structure of our universe. Those two questions might be connected through the fact that we have experimentally confirmed all of the possible symmetries of space and time, save one.  A so-called supersymmetry between fundamental particles so far remains undiscovered. It could provide a "natural" solution, which keeps the Higgs Boson light despite the huge hierarchy in the fundamental interactions of nature, and it can predict a new fundamental particle that might be responsible for dark matter. Hence, the supersymmetry hypothesis provides an exciting and tantalizing possibility of connecting natural phenomena that are observed at the smallest quantum scales with phenomena observed at the largest cosmological scales, offering a profound insight into the very structure of space and time. If supersymmetry provides a natural solution to the Higgs mass problem, then hypothetical supersymmetric partners to the well known top quark (known as top squarks) should exist and have a mass scale which is not too much heavier than the standard model top quark.  One of the primary objectives of this project was to analyse the data collected by the Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) Experiment at the CERN Large Hadron Collider (LHC) to search for new, undiscovered phenomena involving heavy, fast-moving particles produced in the presence of large missing momentum. In particular, this project studied high-energy proton-proton collisions for evidence of top quarks produced in association with large missing momentum, a signature which is consistent with the direct production of supersymmetric top squarks together with an unseen dark matter particle.  Upon analysing the full Run 1 dataset and much of the Run 2 dataset provided by the LHC, no evidence for either top squarks or dark matter particles have been found in the LHC data. This project was able to infer that the mass of any hypothetical stop-quark must be more than six times heavier than the mass of the top quark, if the mass of the dark matter particle is very light; alternatively, if the mass of the dark matter particle is quite heavy (say five to six times the mass of a W or Z Boson), then the mass of the top squark could still be as light as about three times the mass of the top quark. The impact of the findings from this project is significant as it limits the possibilities that a minimal supersymmetric extension to the standard model of particle physics can provide a both "natural" explanation for the light mass of the Higgs Boson and an explanation for the existence of dark matter -- two of the most profound conundrums in science.  Another primary objective of this project was to contribute to the Improved (Phase-1) and High Luminosity (Phase-2) upgrades of the CMS high-speed electronics for on-line data filtering, known as a "Level-1 Trigger" and which makes extensive use of Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) technology. This project played a key role in implementing firmware and in commissioning the Phase-1 upgrade to the CMS Level-1 Trigger.  The project also led the preliminary design of a future Level-1 Trigger for the Phase-2 upgrade.  As part of our research and development, this project explored the use of machine learning in low-latency, low-power FPGA hardware. We, together with collaborators, contributed to a package based on High-Level Synthesis (HLS) called "hls4ml" to synthesize machine learning architectures onto FPGAs. The use of HLS increases the accessibility of deep learning applications across a broad user community and allows for a dramatic decrease in firmware development time.   Finally, this project partnered with the Student Inquiry and Research Program at the Illinois Math and Science Academy, a local area high-school in the Chicago suburbs.  The high-school students worked to analyse CMS datasets in the search for supersymmetry, and presented their results at a special Colloquium event for high-school student research at Illinois Math and Science Academy.  During the lifetime of the project, high school students learned the basics of computer programming, statistical inference, and experimental methods.    In summary, this project significantly contributed to our understanding of how the Higgs Boson can be so light and what is the particle nature of dark matter.  In support of that, novel methods to program high speed electronics were developed and used to record high-energy proton-proton collisions at the Large Hadron Collider.  And, this project worked with local area high schools to bring the excitement of discovery science into the classroom.       Last Modified: 08/28/2018       Submitted by: Richard Cavanaugh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
