<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Geometry of measures in high dimensions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400047.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400047</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI's long term research goal is to investigate the properties of high dimensional probability measures and understand the geometry that lies underneath. In pursuit of this goal the PI plans to quantify the concentration phenomena that appears, by further investigating the structure and geometry of the family of centroid bodies that is generated by the measure. This leads to several research directions that explore the connections of the theory of high-dimensional measures with Convex geometry (and local theory of Banach spaces), classical Analysis (PDE's and isoperimetric inequalities) and Probability theory (including generic chaining).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The general principle in high dimensional systems is that they have the tendency to congregate around typical forms. For general measures this is a relatively new discovery. The proposal is dedicated to the investigation of these phenomena. This theory has already found significant applications in probability, combinatorics, mathematical physics and informatics, with the recurrent theme being that of extending known results to a much broader setting without any assumptions on "randomness". Any progress in the direction of this proposal will be of great importance to every field interested in high dimensional phenomena.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1151711</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grigoris</FirstName>
<LastName>Paouris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Grigoris Paouris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grigoris@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798451474</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433368</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3368 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~26818</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~107595</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~108672</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~109782</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~47180</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>One of the great challenges in many disciplines in our time is that researchers have to handle, understand, or work with systems of enormous complexity to deal with very large data. However, it has recently been understood that high dimensional systems have the tendency to congregate around typical forms and therefore they contain a large part that is typical or simple. The main objective of this project was to bring techniques from different fields of mathematics to investigate and better quantify this phenomenon and in particular to understand the behavior of high-dimensional probability measures.&nbsp;</span><br /><br /><span>A major achievement of the project was that geometric ideas (such as isoperimetry) can be used to establish uniform behavior of high-dimensional measures. A second achievement was that modern notions from probability (such as super-concentration) can be applied to find structure in high dimensions. Also classical ideas in analysis (such as the heat equation) can be applied to further quantify these phenomena. These ideas have been developed by the PI and his coauthors and led to several fascinating applications. Results have been obtained in stochastic geometry, in high dimensional convexity, in computational algebraic geometry, in non-asymptotic random matrix theory and also in functional analysis and probability. Moreover, the PI had the opportunity to train and support&nbsp; several young researchers (at the Graduate, Ph.D, and&nbsp; Postdoctoral levels) at Texas A&amp;M.&nbsp;Results were communicated via publications in leading journals and presented at many national and international conferences.</span></p> <div class="adL">&nbsp;</div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Grigoris&nbsp;Paouris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the great challenges in many disciplines in our time is that researchers have to handle, understand, or work with systems of enormous complexity to deal with very large data. However, it has recently been understood that high dimensional systems have the tendency to congregate around typical forms and therefore they contain a large part that is typical or simple. The main objective of this project was to bring techniques from different fields of mathematics to investigate and better quantify this phenomenon and in particular to understand the behavior of high-dimensional probability measures.   A major achievement of the project was that geometric ideas (such as isoperimetry) can be used to establish uniform behavior of high-dimensional measures. A second achievement was that modern notions from probability (such as super-concentration) can be applied to find structure in high dimensions. Also classical ideas in analysis (such as the heat equation) can be applied to further quantify these phenomena. These ideas have been developed by the PI and his coauthors and led to several fascinating applications. Results have been obtained in stochastic geometry, in high dimensional convexity, in computational algebraic geometry, in non-asymptotic random matrix theory and also in functional analysis and probability. Moreover, the PI had the opportunity to train and support  several young researchers (at the Graduate, Ph.D, and  Postdoctoral levels) at Texas A&amp;M. Results were communicated via publications in leading journals and presented at many national and international conferences.            Last Modified: 03/01/2018       Submitted by: Grigoris Paouris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
