<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  New Technology for Coupling Sound to the Ear in Communications Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>613965</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project focuses on coupling sound to the human ear for communications devices (MP3, Bluetooth, hearing aids, headsets, earbuds) with unprecedented comfort, safety and audio quality. A chip-like device, the diaphonic valve, for harvesting energy from audio communications for the purpose of inflating a coupling device (balloon) in the user's ear has been demonstrated. This inflatable ear coupling mitigates excessive sound pressure levels that often occur within-ear listening devices, such as ear-buds and hearing aids, and which are a cause of audio fatigue and potential hearing damage. Diaphonic valve design has been dramatically improved making it smaller and more effective at pumping air. In this project, production of the critical diaphonic valve-chip component will be increased to a small scale manufacturing level. Additionally, the pressure and power utilization management hardware and algorithms to integrate the diaphonic valve and inflatable ear coupling (bubble) into commercial headsets, and hearing aids will be developed. Finally, work will be done on a non-inflatable ear couple technology, discovered during Phase I of this project, which also improves audio quality and hearing safety.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project centers on revolutionary new person-to-audio couplings, based on an inflatable ear-piece, with applications in consumer audio, Bluetooth headsets, hearing aids, ear-buds, and headsets for professional communications (pilots, law enforcement, military, etc.). This technology has the potential to improve peoples lives by reducing listener fatigue and hearing damage in the population using in-ear devices, as well as making hearing aids more comfortable and better sounding for people who already have hearing loss. Published results from Phase I have shown how existing ear coupling approaches can produce dangerous sound pressures in the ear canal and how the technologies of this project allow ear couplings that alleviate this problem. The first embodiment of this new technology to the market will be a basic version applied to consumer headsets (ear-buds). From there, more complex applications, such as hearing aids, will be addressed. The success of this project will create engineering and business sector jobs as well as manufacturing jobs. The project also includes funding for a high school student or college undergraduate to participate in the research and development activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1152467</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Ambrose</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen D Ambrose</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Stephen.Ambrose@AsiusTechnologies.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037484621</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000566804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Asius Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Longmont</CityName>
<ZipCode>805042668</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7202042676</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1257 Whitehall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>962443748</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASIUS TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Asius Technologies, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Longmont</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805042668</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1257 Whitehall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>166E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IICC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~524000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~49965</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p>Asius Technologies has demonstrated the feasibility of a chiplike&nbsp;device, the diaphonic valve, for harvesting energy from audio communications for the&nbsp;purpose of inflating a coupling device (an airbag-like balloon) in the listener&rsquo;s ear.&nbsp; Commercialization in the form of component sales is underway. Asius has shown that this&nbsp;inflatable ear coupling mitigates excessive sound pressure levels that often occur with in-ear&nbsp;listening devices (earbuds), which are a cause of audio fatigue and potential hearing damage.&nbsp;Asius has also greatly improved diaphonic valve design making it smaller and more effective&nbsp;at pumping air. With its manufacturing partners Asius will be able to scale up production of the&nbsp;critical diaphonic valve-chip component to a large scale manufacturing level and apply the&nbsp;pressure and power utilization management hardware and algorithms so that the diaphonic valve and inflatable ear coupling (bubble) can be combined and added to commercial headsets, and hearing&nbsp;aids.&nbsp; The pump and bubble were combined to create a hybrid hearing aid and In-Ear Monitor which was d&eacute;buted at the Consumer Electronics Show.&nbsp; A non-inflatable ear couple technology, discovered during&nbsp;Phase I, was developed and sold successfully on Kickstarter and is now available for additional licensing beyond the two current licenses.&nbsp; This device also improves audio quality and hearing safety.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong></p> <p>A 2014 study by the UK Commission on Hearing Loss (www.ilcuk.org.uk) found that those with hearing loss are significantly less likely to be in employment and more likely to be underemployed than the general population resulting in a cost to the UK economy of almost &pound;25bn per annum in terms of lost output and 1.6% decrease in GDP.&nbsp; In a survey of more than 40,000 households utilizing the U.S. National Family Opinion panel, hearing loss was shown to negatively impact household income on average up to $12,000 per year depending on the degree of hearing loss. Even though use of hearing aids was shown to mitigate the effects of hearing loss by 50% there are 24 million hearing-impaired Americans who do not use hearing instruments, the impact of untreated hearing loss is quantified to be in excess of $100 billion annually.&nbsp; At a 15% tax bracket, the cost to society could be well in excess of $18 billion due to unrealized taxes.&nbsp; Our product will be more comfortable, functional and compatible with smartphone, making it much more likely to be fully adopted by the millions of hearing impaired globally.</p> <p>Asius&rsquo; inflatable in-ear communications technology is the basis&nbsp;for revolutionary new person-to-audio couplings in consumer audio, Bluetooth headsets,&nbsp;hearing aids, earbuds, and headsets for professional communications (pilots, law&nbsp;enforcement, military, etc.). This technology improves quality of life by&nbsp;reducing listener fatigue and hearing damage in the population using in-ear devices, as well&nbsp;as making hearing aids more comfortable for people who already have hearing loss. Asius&rsquo;&nbsp;published research has shown how existing ear coupling approaches can produce&nbsp;dangerous sound pressures in the ear canal and how Asius&rsquo; ear couplings alleviate this&nbsp;problem. Asius entered the market first with a version of its technology that is applied to&nbsp;existing consumer headsets (earbuds), and professional in-ear monitors followed by hearing aids and hearing protection. Asius markets its&nbsp;own branded products, but is also open to licensing its technology to audio and hearing aid&nbsp;companies. The bubble has been found to offer non-invasive and effective way to restore hearing to anyone with one-sided deafness and even lacking an auditory nerve.&nbsp; The succe...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit  Asius Technologies has demonstrated the feasibility of a chiplike device, the diaphonic valve, for harvesting energy from audio communications for the purpose of inflating a coupling device (an airbag-like balloon) in the listenerÆs ear.  Commercialization in the form of component sales is underway. Asius has shown that this inflatable ear coupling mitigates excessive sound pressure levels that often occur with in-ear listening devices (earbuds), which are a cause of audio fatigue and potential hearing damage. Asius has also greatly improved diaphonic valve design making it smaller and more effective at pumping air. With its manufacturing partners Asius will be able to scale up production of the critical diaphonic valve-chip component to a large scale manufacturing level and apply the pressure and power utilization management hardware and algorithms so that the diaphonic valve and inflatable ear coupling (bubble) can be combined and added to commercial headsets, and hearing aids.  The pump and bubble were combined to create a hybrid hearing aid and In-Ear Monitor which was d&eacute;buted at the Consumer Electronics Show.  A non-inflatable ear couple technology, discovered during Phase I, was developed and sold successfully on Kickstarter and is now available for additional licensing beyond the two current licenses.  This device also improves audio quality and hearing safety.   Broader impacts  A 2014 study by the UK Commission on Hearing Loss (www.ilcuk.org.uk) found that those with hearing loss are significantly less likely to be in employment and more likely to be underemployed than the general population resulting in a cost to the UK economy of almost &pound;25bn per annum in terms of lost output and 1.6% decrease in GDP.  In a survey of more than 40,000 households utilizing the U.S. National Family Opinion panel, hearing loss was shown to negatively impact household income on average up to $12,000 per year depending on the degree of hearing loss. Even though use of hearing aids was shown to mitigate the effects of hearing loss by 50% there are 24 million hearing-impaired Americans who do not use hearing instruments, the impact of untreated hearing loss is quantified to be in excess of $100 billion annually.  At a 15% tax bracket, the cost to society could be well in excess of $18 billion due to unrealized taxes.  Our product will be more comfortable, functional and compatible with smartphone, making it much more likely to be fully adopted by the millions of hearing impaired globally.  AsiusÆ inflatable in-ear communications technology is the basis for revolutionary new person-to-audio couplings in consumer audio, Bluetooth headsets, hearing aids, earbuds, and headsets for professional communications (pilots, law enforcement, military, etc.). This technology improves quality of life by reducing listener fatigue and hearing damage in the population using in-ear devices, as well as making hearing aids more comfortable for people who already have hearing loss. AsiusÆ published research has shown how existing ear coupling approaches can produce dangerous sound pressures in the ear canal and how AsiusÆ ear couplings alleviate this problem. Asius entered the market first with a version of its technology that is applied to existing consumer headsets (earbuds), and professional in-ear monitors followed by hearing aids and hearing protection. Asius markets its own branded products, but is also open to licensing its technology to audio and hearing aid companies. The bubble has been found to offer non-invasive and effective way to restore hearing to anyone with one-sided deafness and even lacking an auditory nerve.  The success of Asius has created engineering and business sector jobs as well as manufacturing and assembly positions. During the period of performance community college students were provided extensive exposure to research and commercialization.  University students were also introduced to Asius via o...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
