<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Hyperconjugative assistance in alkyne cyclizations and cycloadditions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>382970</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project supported by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program of the Division of Chemistry, Professor Igor Alabugin and his research group will extend studies of alkyne reactivity into three new directions. It will use computations to discover stereoelectronic effects capable of controlling anionic cyclizations of alkynes and non-catalyzed alkyne cycloadditions and utilize this knowledge to develop efficient chemical processes. In the first part of this project, the research team will search for the two virtually unexplored alkyne cyclization patterns: 3-exo-dig and 4-exo-dig closures. Proposed experiments will test computational predictions regarding the relative efficiency of different cyclization patterns and utilize cooperative hyperconjugative interactions for the control of reactivity. In the second part, the researchers will use negative hyperconjugation to enable selective endo closures in the delicately poised pairs of competing endo and exo cyclizations. The final part of the project will test hyperconjugative assistance as the new transition state stabilization approach in non-catalyzed alkyne-azide cycloadditions. The intellectual merit of this research is in unraveling the contribution of electronic and structural factors controlling efficiency and selectivity of alkyne cyclizations and cycloaddtions through a combination of experimental and theoretical studies. The underlying focus on orbital interactions will increase the general importance of these findings, broaden our understanding of these fundamental factors and lead to the development of new paradigms of radical and anionic reactivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact will be the laying of mechanistic, structural, and kinetic foundations for successful applications of reactions of alkynes in synthesis and materials science. The proposed research will enhance our understanding of the reactivity of the alkyne moiety as well as radical species. The combination of computations with kinetic studies will be used to validate computational approaches for studies of organic reactions. The theoretical and experimental components of this work will allow training of specialists in each area and will provide researchers at the undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral levels with an opportunity to integrate learning and discovery. The results will be disseminated in publications and through outreach activities, including participation in symposia and lecturing at undergraduate and graduate institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1152491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Igor</FirstName>
<LastName>Alabugin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Igor Alabugin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alabugin@chem.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506445795</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000338413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064390</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[102 Varsity Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~7970</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>More than 90% of individual chemical entities found in Nature contains either a carbo- or a heterocycle. Consequently, the ability to transform acyclic precursors into cyclic structures with precise regiochemical and stereochemical control is a very important requirement for the continuous development of organic chemistry and for the applications of organic compounds as new molecular tools in biology and materials science. Our research refined and redefined the general rules for anionic and radical cyclizations of alkynes and expanded them to the cationic, electrophile-assisted and metal-catalyzed reactions.</p> <p>The two key discoveries made in the project: development of traceless directing groups in radical cascades and design of reactions where alkenes serve as synthetic equivalents of alkynes has the potential to open conceptually new avenues in organic synthesis of cyclic molecules.</p> <p>One of the main tools in our approaches to control of cyclization reactions is hyperconjugative assistance. The importance of hyperconjugative assistance is that every molecule has single bonds and, thus, delocalizing interactions involving such bonds (hyperconjugation) correspond to the most ubiquitous electronic effect in chemistry. Such, often unnoticed and underappreciated, interactions permeate the fabric of chemistry and, once identified and understood, can be used to control a broad variety of chemical processes. The present grant focused on using such interactions in cyclizations and cycloadditions but potential utility of our findings can be expanded to many other classes of organic transformations.</p> <p>Furthermore, the fundamental understanding of electronic factors controlling organic transformations leads to more efficient organic reactions for chemical biology and materials science. For example, the new routes to polyaromatics will facilitate design of conjugated organic molecules and materials for a variety applications ranging from photovotaics, electrochromic compounds, sensors etc.&nbsp; In parallel, design of fast yet robust reagents for azide/alkyne &ldquo;click&rdquo; cycloadditions will increase the utility of these processes in bioorthogonal chemistry, the rapidly developing area of chemical biology</p> <p>The participating students and postdocs received training in organic synthesis, reaction design, computational analysis of mechanisms, spectroscopic and electochemical analysis&nbsp; of new compounds, and application of conjugated materials in materials science.&nbsp; Overall, mechanistic research in organic chemistry lays a solid foundation for the future careers in academia as well as chemical and pharmaceutical industry. It also opens opportunities to pursue research in a variety of molecular sciences ranging from organic process development to chemical biology and materials science.</p> <p>This project provides students with valuable training received in critical thinking, analysis of complex scientific problems, design and execution of synthetic and kinetic experiments, use of spectroscopy for analysis of molecular structure and supramolecular interactions, presenting their findings as oral presentations and peer-reviewed research papers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2016<br>      Modified by: Igor&nbsp;Alabugin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ More than 90% of individual chemical entities found in Nature contains either a carbo- or a heterocycle. Consequently, the ability to transform acyclic precursors into cyclic structures with precise regiochemical and stereochemical control is a very important requirement for the continuous development of organic chemistry and for the applications of organic compounds as new molecular tools in biology and materials science. Our research refined and redefined the general rules for anionic and radical cyclizations of alkynes and expanded them to the cationic, electrophile-assisted and metal-catalyzed reactions.  The two key discoveries made in the project: development of traceless directing groups in radical cascades and design of reactions where alkenes serve as synthetic equivalents of alkynes has the potential to open conceptually new avenues in organic synthesis of cyclic molecules.  One of the main tools in our approaches to control of cyclization reactions is hyperconjugative assistance. The importance of hyperconjugative assistance is that every molecule has single bonds and, thus, delocalizing interactions involving such bonds (hyperconjugation) correspond to the most ubiquitous electronic effect in chemistry. Such, often unnoticed and underappreciated, interactions permeate the fabric of chemistry and, once identified and understood, can be used to control a broad variety of chemical processes. The present grant focused on using such interactions in cyclizations and cycloadditions but potential utility of our findings can be expanded to many other classes of organic transformations.  Furthermore, the fundamental understanding of electronic factors controlling organic transformations leads to more efficient organic reactions for chemical biology and materials science. For example, the new routes to polyaromatics will facilitate design of conjugated organic molecules and materials for a variety applications ranging from photovotaics, electrochromic compounds, sensors etc.  In parallel, design of fast yet robust reagents for azide/alkyne "click" cycloadditions will increase the utility of these processes in bioorthogonal chemistry, the rapidly developing area of chemical biology  The participating students and postdocs received training in organic synthesis, reaction design, computational analysis of mechanisms, spectroscopic and electochemical analysis  of new compounds, and application of conjugated materials in materials science.  Overall, mechanistic research in organic chemistry lays a solid foundation for the future careers in academia as well as chemical and pharmaceutical industry. It also opens opportunities to pursue research in a variety of molecular sciences ranging from organic process development to chemical biology and materials science.  This project provides students with valuable training received in critical thinking, analysis of complex scientific problems, design and execution of synthetic and kinetic experiments, use of spectroscopy for analysis of molecular structure and supramolecular interactions, presenting their findings as oral presentations and peer-reviewed research papers.       Last Modified: 08/25/2016       Submitted by: Igor Alabugin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
