<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Computational Low-cost Arrayed Infrared (CLAIR) Cameras</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>611000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will develop a revolutionary approach to the lens and opto-mechanical design and fabrication process for long wave infrared (LWIR) imagers with the goal of reducing cost, size, and weight.  To date, the high cost of sensors has made LWIR imagers accessible only in markets where performance -not cost - is the driving factor, allowing expensive and bulky optics to reign.  New process improvements are significantly reducing the size and cost of LWIR microbolometer sensors, making optics the limiting factor for weight, size, and cost reduction.  The research objectives are to extend the technology developed in Phase I and validate the final manufacturing and testing process for the optics and camera assembly to show that the final architecture can meet the market requirements for module volume, weight and price when scaled to high volume production.  The development will scale the process to larger arrays and will take the necessary steps to evaluate the solutions mechanical reliability.  The solution will be implemented and tested through arrangements with industry partners.   The anticipated result is a demonstration of an LWIR camera that meets the needs of the infrared (IR) vision enhancement and thermography markets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to extend the sale of IR imagers into cost-sensitive commercial applications.  Currently IR imagers are targeted for expensive military applications, but there is a large need for reduced cost systems in safety, security, and industrial markets where thermal imaging offers enhanced viewing over the visible spectrum.  Thermal imagers provide visibility in complete darkness, which enables imaging in adverse conditions needed by automotive collision detection, search and rescue and security applications that require identification of humans in conditions of no light.  In industrial use, LWIR thermography can improve energy efficiency by identifying thermal leaks and can predict imminent process faults.  The impact to society is as ubiquitous as the commercial opportunities and constitutes an increase in emergency search effectiveness, city street safety, and energy conservation.  The scientific and technological understanding cannot be understated: technological innovation occurs most rapidly near manufacturing capability.  Already, labor costs are driving current labor-intensive IR lens fabrication overseas.  The proposed innovations remove the labor-intensive component, bolstering the US as the dominant manufacturer in this emerging market while enhancing science in parallel process development, material property innovation, and IR sensor performance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1152720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenny</FirstName>
<LastName>Kubala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenny Kubala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kenny.Kubala@fivefocal.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3039002317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000550710</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FiveFocal LLC</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012723</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3039002317</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Range Street Suite 202</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>831559716</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FIVEFOCAL LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FiveFocal LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012723</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 Range street Suite 202]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~11000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Under NSF Phase II Grant IIP-1152720, FiveFocal developed lens and lens fabrication technology for low cost infrared cameras used in industrial thermography, infrastructure and equipment inspection, automotive safety, security, consumer, and other applications.&nbsp; Thermal cameras create an image from the heat radiated from an object &ndash; warm objects appear bright, and cool objects appear dark.&nbsp; Historically the primary market for thermal imagers was military and high-end security imagers.&nbsp; The high expense of thermal imagers precluded their use in other applications.&nbsp; Advances in MEMs and semiconductor manufacturing technology, and the increase in unit volume of thermal imagers have steadily decreased the cost of infrared sensors.&nbsp; As the cost and size of these sensors decrease, the lenses have become the limiting factor in size and cost. Example applications of low cost infrared cameras include supporting predictive maintenance of buildings and machinery, enhancing nighttime security, and improving the safety of vehicles and ships operating at night and in adverse conditions.</p> <p>The overall objective of the Phase II effort was to develop low cost fabrication methods for lenses used with thermal infrared, or long wave infrared (LWIR), imaging applications.&nbsp; The specific objectives and a summary of results undertaken in this Phase II fall into the following categories:</p> <p>Development of LWIR lens designs amenable to the low-cost manufacturing methods under development</p> <ul> <li>In response to market demand, a simple single element lens was designed for VGA (640x480 pixel) thermal sensors.&nbsp; The design was made to be less sensitive to manufacturing errors.</li> <li>The designs were shown to be robust and excellent candidates for molded fabrication processes.</li> </ul> <p>A lens molding process was developed and entailed the design of lens molds, lens preforms, molding equipment, and implemented the molding process.</p> <ul> <li>Using the lens designs, molds were designed and fabricated.&nbsp; A molding station was designed and constructed in house, undergoing several revisions of mold pins, alignment sleeves, and temperature controlled heaters.&nbsp; Single element lenses were successfully molded.</li> <li>Lower cost molding techniques were explored and demonstrated</li> </ul> <p>The fabricated lenses were tested, and a prediction of the cost of the molding process was developed</p> <ul> <li>The fabricated lenses were tested using a LWIR sensor both by acquiring indoor scene imagery and using standard image quality test.&nbsp; The measurements were compared against the expected performance from the optical design and verified correct lens shape.</li> </ul> <p>Methods of computational imaging with thermal imagery were developed with a LWIR camera model to understand the impact of lens design and sensor selection on imaging performance.</p> <ul> <li>Using various LWIR lens designs, a model was developed to show the impact of lens configuration, pixel size, and sensor sensitivity on imaging performance, i.e. CTF (Contrast Transfer Function) and MTF.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2014<br>      Modified by: Kenny&nbsp;Kubala</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1152720/1152720_10159753_1417497298922_lensandmoldwithquarter--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/PO...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Under NSF Phase II Grant IIP-1152720, FiveFocal developed lens and lens fabrication technology for low cost infrared cameras used in industrial thermography, infrastructure and equipment inspection, automotive safety, security, consumer, and other applications.  Thermal cameras create an image from the heat radiated from an object &ndash; warm objects appear bright, and cool objects appear dark.  Historically the primary market for thermal imagers was military and high-end security imagers.  The high expense of thermal imagers precluded their use in other applications.  Advances in MEMs and semiconductor manufacturing technology, and the increase in unit volume of thermal imagers have steadily decreased the cost of infrared sensors.  As the cost and size of these sensors decrease, the lenses have become the limiting factor in size and cost. Example applications of low cost infrared cameras include supporting predictive maintenance of buildings and machinery, enhancing nighttime security, and improving the safety of vehicles and ships operating at night and in adverse conditions.  The overall objective of the Phase II effort was to develop low cost fabrication methods for lenses used with thermal infrared, or long wave infrared (LWIR), imaging applications.  The specific objectives and a summary of results undertaken in this Phase II fall into the following categories:  Development of LWIR lens designs amenable to the low-cost manufacturing methods under development  In response to market demand, a simple single element lens was designed for VGA (640x480 pixel) thermal sensors.  The design was made to be less sensitive to manufacturing errors. The designs were shown to be robust and excellent candidates for molded fabrication processes.   A lens molding process was developed and entailed the design of lens molds, lens preforms, molding equipment, and implemented the molding process.  Using the lens designs, molds were designed and fabricated.  A molding station was designed and constructed in house, undergoing several revisions of mold pins, alignment sleeves, and temperature controlled heaters.  Single element lenses were successfully molded. Lower cost molding techniques were explored and demonstrated   The fabricated lenses were tested, and a prediction of the cost of the molding process was developed  The fabricated lenses were tested using a LWIR sensor both by acquiring indoor scene imagery and using standard image quality test.  The measurements were compared against the expected performance from the optical design and verified correct lens shape.   Methods of computational imaging with thermal imagery were developed with a LWIR camera model to understand the impact of lens design and sensor selection on imaging performance.  Using various LWIR lens designs, a model was developed to show the impact of lens configuration, pixel size, and sensor sensitivity on imaging performance, i.e. CTF (Contrast Transfer Function) and MTF.              Last Modified: 12/02/2014       Submitted by: Kenny Kubala]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
