<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarships for Transfer Students in Science, Engineering, and Mathematics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>528994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>528994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project provides scholarships for academically talented students with financial need who transfer to Hope College from a community college to major in biology, chemistry, computer science, engineering, geological and environmental sciences, mathematics, or physics. Scholarships of up to $10,000 per year are offered to up to seven transferring students each year over four years. The scholarships are renewable for a second year if the student meets eligibility requirements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this project are to (1) improve the collaboration between local community colleges and Hope College STEM programs; (2) recruit to Hope College STEM students at community colleges who would not ordinarily consider attending the college; (3) increase the number of community college students who transfer into STEM programs at Hope College; and (4) increase the retention of community college transfers in STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each year this project will identify and recruit students on seven community college campuses in Hope's geographic region. Scholarship recipients will be selected after personal interviews and review of their college admissions packets. Selection is based on promise for academic success and potential for the scholarship to affect career choice. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All students supported by these scholarships are given the opportunity to participate in a summer research project at Hope College in the summer before they begin studies at Hope. They are also supported in their study by intensive faculty advising, timely and appropriate academic assistance, and education, internship and research opportunities. In addition, S-STEM Transfer Scholars participate in the Fostering a Community of Excellence in Science (FACES) program, which was launched for a cohort of incoming freshmen in the Fall of 2010. This program provides peer mentoring, career counseling and community building activities for STEM majors to help them make the transition to the college and prepare for careers in STEM fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project builds upon the nationally recognized Hope STEM programs, the current Hope CSEMS and S-STEM projects, the FACES mentoring program, and the college's extensive infrastructure for student support to enable students to transfer and pursue degrees in one of the STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project especially targets community college students who usually do not consider attending a private liberal arts college like Hope, thus increasing economic and racial diversity in STEM fields at Hope. A significant number of Hope STEM alumni pursue post-graduate studies in science and engineering fields. Thus graduates with strong STEM educations from Hope will not only enter the workforce, but many of them are likely to pursue post-graduate degrees in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1153600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Herbert</FirstName>
<LastName>Dershem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Herbert L Dershem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dershem@hope.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163957508</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Mader</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine M Mader</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mader@hope.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163957114</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Bonnema</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Bonnema</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bonnema@hope.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163957312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574726</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hope College</Name>
<CityName>Holland</CityName>
<ZipCode>494229000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6163957316</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>141 E. 12th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 9000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050947084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HOPE COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050947084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hope College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>494229000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~528994</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-4265fce3-7fff-e9b2-ed0f-19a0db1e42ac" dir="ltr"><span>The Scholarships to support the Hope STEM Scholars Program participants program provided scholarship support to 27 students 15 of whom transferred to Hope from two-year colleges and 12 of whom were Hope students who had significant financial need and were working significant numbers of hours on campus during the academic year. &nbsp;Students were provided financial support in the form of scholarships.  Students transferring from two-year colleges were provided summer research support the summer before enrolling at Hope, though a few did not take advantage of the opportunity.  Most students participated in summer and academic year research opportunities at Hope College. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Of the 16 transfer students, 1 did not complete their degree at Hope, 13 have graduated from Hope College, all with degrees in Science, Engineering or Mathematics, the remaining two students are on track to graduate in 2019 or 2020. Of the 13 that graduated from Hope College with degrees in STEM fields, three are pursuing graduate degrees in STEM fields, three are pursuing careers health professions, three are employed in STEM professions and the four are still seeking permanent employment in STEM fields. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Many of the program participants are first generation college students. Most found the support of their research mentor and peers were invaluable.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mader</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The Scholarships to support the Hope STEM Scholars Program participants program provided scholarship support to 27 students 15 of whom transferred to Hope from two-year colleges and 12 of whom were Hope students who had significant financial need and were working significant numbers of hours on campus during the academic year.  Students were provided financial support in the form of scholarships.  Students transferring from two-year colleges were provided summer research support the summer before enrolling at Hope, though a few did not take advantage of the opportunity.  Most students participated in summer and academic year research opportunities at Hope College.     Of the 16 transfer students, 1 did not complete their degree at Hope, 13 have graduated from Hope College, all with degrees in Science, Engineering or Mathematics, the remaining two students are on track to graduate in 2019 or 2020. Of the 13 that graduated from Hope College with degrees in STEM fields, three are pursuing graduate degrees in STEM fields, three are pursuing careers health professions, three are employed in STEM professions and the four are still seeking permanent employment in STEM fields.     Many of the program participants are first generation college students. Most found the support of their research mentor and peers were invaluable.          Last Modified: 03/03/2019       Submitted by: Catherine M Mader]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
