<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STS Postdoctoral Fellowship: The impact of mathematics on inferring classifications and phylogenies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Introduction&lt;br/&gt;This proposal will examine the biological basis of mathematical modeling in computational biology. Systematic biologists make classifications and phylogenies of organisms. Doing so depends on the idea that adding more data will cause their results to converge statistically. However, the biological basis for this convergence varies considerably and is heavily contested across inference methods and organisms. This project will approach the problem of justifying statistical convergence in systematic biology by adopting a hybrid approach that integrates philosophical analysis with a historical study of the reception of statistical methods in systematics over the past sixty years, including numerical taxonomy, cladistics, and maximum likelihood methods. The study will emphasize how the use and value of statistical methods varied across areas of systematics, such as microbiology, zoology, and paleontology. The researchers will develop computational methods for tracing reception in published journal articles in order to achieve a comprehensive, comparative analysis. The project will use the path-breaking OCHRE database system, which provides an innovative data structure in the digital humanities that can support changing analytic categories over time (a semi-structured instead of relational database). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;This project is an interdisciplinary collaboration integrating biology, philosophy of science, and history of science to study the strengths and limitations of statistical methods in systematics. The Field Museum is an ideal location for this collaboration because of the excellence and diversity of its research in systematics, including cutting-edge projects on integrating data for biodiversity studies, on molecular techniques for the Tree of Life project, and on the history and philosophy of systematics. The study, with its focus on statistics as a constraint on research in systematics, will open a new epistemological perspective on individuality as a complementary problem, especially with regards to individuating structural elements in classifications or phylogenies and with regards to individuating characters in organisms. Examining how different areas of systematics received and appropriated statistical methods will greatly expand current historical knowledge of theoretical advances in microbiology and botany over the past sixty years. In addition, the project will develop research tools for investigating the mathematization of biology and other sciences, an increasingly important problem in the history and philosophy of science. For example, one result of the proposed research will be computational methods for analyzing the transformative effect mathematization had on the structural relations among research problems in systematics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;Using an integrated interdisciplinary approach to address a key practical problem in biology today, the results of this research will cross boundaries to impact science policy in biology and other fields in the digital humanities. The project will produce a targeted evaluation of the basis of statistical convergence that is relevant to current debates among policy makers and biologists about the value of mathematics and high-throughput data gathering techniques. Results will be disseminated in interdisciplinary journals and conferences that regularly include biologists in their audience. New computational methods developed in the project will be incorporated as Java modules in the OCHRE system, which is made available for use in academic research and has a web-based graphical user interface. The new computational methods and associated results will also be presented at workshops on digital humanities and digital history and philosophy of science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1153114</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Lidgard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott H Lidgard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slidgard@fieldmuseum.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3126657625</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468978</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beckett</FirstName>
<LastName>Sterner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beckett Sterner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bsterner@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3126228569</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000595007</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Field Museum of Natural History</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606052827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3126657240</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 S LAKE SHORE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042072157</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FIELD MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Field Museum of Natural History]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606052827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1353</Code>
<Text>Hist &amp; Philosophy of SET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since the 1950&rsquo;s, statistical methods have supported major advances in medicine and agriculture by improving our ability to classify bacteria and understand the co&shy;evolution of pathogens with their hosts. More generally, taxonomy and phylogenetic systematics have come to depend on statistical consistency: the idea that adding more data will cause their main result, a hierarchical tree that describes the relationships among a set of species or higher taxa, to converge to the true answer. However, the biological basis for this convergence is contested. The problem of justifying mathematical convergence in systematics is two&shy;fold: 1) figuring out the nature of the elements in the hierarchical trees that would support statistical consistency and 2) answering when and why this convergence to the truth should occur.</p> <p>Our project has investigated the historical origins of this dependence on mathematics starting in the late 1950&rsquo;s. We have also analyzed the impact of mathematics on how biologists conceptualize biological individuality, including the nature of species. Our research has led to the publication of five papers, with three more currently in preparation. In one paper, we showed how making mathematics indispensable for classification transformed how scientists conceptualized the linear workflow of classification and regulated each other&rsquo;s best practices. In a paper now in preparation, we use this result to develop a new historiographical frame for the history of systematics. We show how the traditional view, based on the Systematics Wars between two leading schools of classification in the 1970&rsquo;s and 1980&rsquo;s, distorts the growth of methodology from 1900 to the present. In several other papers, we also developed a new account of biological individuality based on the control of life cycles and are currently working on applying that account to give a new definition of biological lineages.</p> <p>In addition, one of the goals of the project has been to develop new computational methods for analyzing scientific change across whole fields or bodies of literature. As a baseline for testing possible computational techniques, we have built a structured collection of about 600 scientific papers published in systematics on the methodology of classification and phylogenetics. Using qualitative methods, we categorized each paper by scoring on multiple, fine-grained criteria related to stages of the classificatory workflow and the corresponding methodological problems it addresses. This structured data set then provides a gold standard for testing the performance of computational methods aimed at classifying scientific papers by research problems. As our next step, we will test our key hypothesis that the frequencies of words and phrases in each paper in the corpus is significantly influenced by its location and neighboring problems in the workflow. In other words, the standardized process of calculation underlying the introduction of mathematics into systematic biology will produce reliable correlations in how often certain terms are used by papers within and across problem categories. If these correlations exist, then it should be possible to design a computational algorithm to detect the existence of the problem categories as clusters within the data set. If correct, our hypothesis would provide a principled theoretical link between the organization of scientific practices (the stages of the workflow) and scientists' published discourse (the frequencies of words in research articles).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Beckett&nbsp;Sterner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since the 1950Æs, statistical methods have supported major advances in medicine and agriculture by improving our ability to classify bacteria and understand the co&shy;evolution of pathogens with their hosts. More generally, taxonomy and phylogenetic systematics have come to depend on statistical consistency: the idea that adding more data will cause their main result, a hierarchical tree that describes the relationships among a set of species or higher taxa, to converge to the true answer. However, the biological basis for this convergence is contested. The problem of justifying mathematical convergence in systematics is two&shy;fold: 1) figuring out the nature of the elements in the hierarchical trees that would support statistical consistency and 2) answering when and why this convergence to the truth should occur.  Our project has investigated the historical origins of this dependence on mathematics starting in the late 1950Æs. We have also analyzed the impact of mathematics on how biologists conceptualize biological individuality, including the nature of species. Our research has led to the publication of five papers, with three more currently in preparation. In one paper, we showed how making mathematics indispensable for classification transformed how scientists conceptualized the linear workflow of classification and regulated each otherÆs best practices. In a paper now in preparation, we use this result to develop a new historiographical frame for the history of systematics. We show how the traditional view, based on the Systematics Wars between two leading schools of classification in the 1970Æs and 1980Æs, distorts the growth of methodology from 1900 to the present. In several other papers, we also developed a new account of biological individuality based on the control of life cycles and are currently working on applying that account to give a new definition of biological lineages.  In addition, one of the goals of the project has been to develop new computational methods for analyzing scientific change across whole fields or bodies of literature. As a baseline for testing possible computational techniques, we have built a structured collection of about 600 scientific papers published in systematics on the methodology of classification and phylogenetics. Using qualitative methods, we categorized each paper by scoring on multiple, fine-grained criteria related to stages of the classificatory workflow and the corresponding methodological problems it addresses. This structured data set then provides a gold standard for testing the performance of computational methods aimed at classifying scientific papers by research problems. As our next step, we will test our key hypothesis that the frequencies of words and phrases in each paper in the corpus is significantly influenced by its location and neighboring problems in the workflow. In other words, the standardized process of calculation underlying the introduction of mathematics into systematic biology will produce reliable correlations in how often certain terms are used by papers within and across problem categories. If these correlations exist, then it should be possible to design a computational algorithm to detect the existence of the problem categories as clusters within the data set. If correct, our hypothesis would provide a principled theoretical link between the organization of scientific practices (the stages of the workflow) and scientists' published discourse (the frequencies of words in research articles).       Last Modified: 10/29/2015       Submitted by: Beckett Sterner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
