<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantification of the Biotransport Phenomena in Low-Cryoprotectant (CPA) Vitrification of Living Cells</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>273945.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1033426&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Contemporary methods for cell cryopreservation often produce a low yield of viable cells due to the harmful effects of ice formation or use of a high concentration of cryoprotectant (CPA). This research seeks to achieve ice-free cryopreservation (vitrification) of cells using a low, nontoxic concentration of CPA (low-CPA). A quantitative understanding of the thermally driven, non-equilibrium phase transition of water in living cells into either a crystalline or a glassy solid, and its correlation with cell survival during low-CPA vitrification has not been achieved to date. Therefore, the objective of this project is to quantify the relevant fundamental phenomena by model development coupled with experimental verification.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: A coupled thermal and phase transition model will be developed which will facilitate quantitative understanding of the pertinent biotransport processes during low-CPA vitrification. Optimal low-CPA vitrification protocols for cryopreserving various living cells will be determined. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The proposed research will assist the advancement of emerging cell-based medicine of which the eventual success relies upon the capability to preserve living cells for distribution to end users. Moreover, the proposed research will be integrated into education through (a) curriculum development, (b) training of graduate, undergraduate, and high school students, and (c) dissemination of the research findings including by a specialized web page.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/05/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1154965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoming</FirstName>
<LastName>He</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoming He</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shawnhe@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014057946</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000386728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/05/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1080 Carmack Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>060E</Code>
<Text>BIO-TRANSPORT &amp; FLUID MECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~273945</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~2000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Contemporary methods for cell cryopreservation often produce a low yield of viable cells due to the harmful effects of ice formation or use of a high concentration of cryoprotectant (CPA). This research seeks to achieve ice-free cryopreservation (vitrification) of cells using a low, nontoxic concentration of CPA (low-CPA). Conventionally, low-CPA vitrification is achieved by creating an ultrafast cooling rate with the use of s small sample volume (up to a few microliters), which is impractical for cryopreserving living cells present in a large quantity (millions to billions) and large volume (in milliliters). We have conducted both computational and experimental studies to achieve a quantitative understanding of the thermally driven, non-equilibrium phase transition of water in living cells into either a crystalline or a glassy solid, and its correlation with cell survival after low-CPA vitrification. Our studies reveal that alginate hydrogel microencapsulation is exceptional in facilitating vitrification during cooling and suppressing devitrification during warming of the vitrification procedure. These findings enable the development of a novel large-volume low-CPA vitrification technology, which makes it practical to cryopreserve living cells in large quantities using low CPA with minimized harmful effects of ice formation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: The models developed and experimental data obtained on ice formation in cells during cryopreservation and cell microencapsulation from this project are published in fourteen high impact journal papers, one edited book, three book chapters, and two patent applications. The models and data should greatly facilitate the quantitative understanding of the biotransport processes associated with microencapsulation of living cells for cryopreservation by low-CPA vitrification, which is important to the development of optimized protocol for cryopreservation of living cells.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: The novel large-volume low-CPA vitrification technology is valuable for assisting the advancement of the burgeoning cell-based medicine, for which the eventual success relies upon the capability to preserve living cells for distribution to end users. Moreover, the proposed research was integrated into education through (a) incorporating the research findings into the biomaterials classes taught by the PI for both graduate and undergraduate students, (b) training a total of six graduate, six undergraduate, and five high school students, and (c) disseminating the research findings via journal and book publications, seminar and conference presentations, and the PI&rsquo;s laboratory website.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/25/2015<br>      Modified by: Xiaoming&nbsp;He</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1154965/1154965_10019255_1445724080648_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1154965/1154965_10019255_1445724080648_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1154965/1154965_10019255_1445724080648_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alginate hydrogel is exceptional in suppressing devitrification during warming of vitrified (cooled in liquid nitrogen, LN2, without visible ice formation) samples, which enables vitrification of living cells in large volume with low and nontoxic conce...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Contemporary methods for cell cryopreservation often produce a low yield of viable cells due to the harmful effects of ice formation or use of a high concentration of cryoprotectant (CPA). This research seeks to achieve ice-free cryopreservation (vitrification) of cells using a low, nontoxic concentration of CPA (low-CPA). Conventionally, low-CPA vitrification is achieved by creating an ultrafast cooling rate with the use of s small sample volume (up to a few microliters), which is impractical for cryopreserving living cells present in a large quantity (millions to billions) and large volume (in milliliters). We have conducted both computational and experimental studies to achieve a quantitative understanding of the thermally driven, non-equilibrium phase transition of water in living cells into either a crystalline or a glassy solid, and its correlation with cell survival after low-CPA vitrification. Our studies reveal that alginate hydrogel microencapsulation is exceptional in facilitating vitrification during cooling and suppressing devitrification during warming of the vitrification procedure. These findings enable the development of a novel large-volume low-CPA vitrification technology, which makes it practical to cryopreserve living cells in large quantities using low CPA with minimized harmful effects of ice formation.   Intellectual Merit: The models developed and experimental data obtained on ice formation in cells during cryopreservation and cell microencapsulation from this project are published in fourteen high impact journal papers, one edited book, three book chapters, and two patent applications. The models and data should greatly facilitate the quantitative understanding of the biotransport processes associated with microencapsulation of living cells for cryopreservation by low-CPA vitrification, which is important to the development of optimized protocol for cryopreservation of living cells.  Broader Impacts: The novel large-volume low-CPA vitrification technology is valuable for assisting the advancement of the burgeoning cell-based medicine, for which the eventual success relies upon the capability to preserve living cells for distribution to end users. Moreover, the proposed research was integrated into education through (a) incorporating the research findings into the biomaterials classes taught by the PI for both graduate and undergraduate students, (b) training a total of six graduate, six undergraduate, and five high school students, and (c) disseminating the research findings via journal and book publications, seminar and conference presentations, and the PIÆs laboratory website.       Last Modified: 10/25/2015       Submitted by: Xiaoming He]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
