<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Montana Minds - Scholarships for Science, Engineering, and Mathematics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>597181.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>597181</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amedinab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Montana Minds, a scholarship program of Montana Tech, is awarding renewable scholarships to 20 academically prepared but financially challenged students so that they will obtain degrees in the STEM degree disciplines of biology, chemistry, mathematics, computer science, or software engineering.  Montana Tech, working with TRiO and GEAR UP staff, will target recruiting at 24 of Montana's impoverished high schools, including all 13 tribal high schools, and 7 tribal colleges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Strategies being used to support scholarship recipients include: &lt;br/&gt;     -  enrolling Montana Minds' scholars in Learning Communities that will ensure that students take several classes together and interact academically and socially to develop as a cohesive self-sustaining group;&lt;br/&gt;     -  enrolling Montana Minds' scholars, during their first years on campus, in a College Success course designed to instill and sharpen the skills needed to succeed in college;&lt;br/&gt;     -  advising within a discipline by a single STEM faculty member who will mentor each student's progress and catalyze relationships with other STEM faculty;&lt;br/&gt;     -  assigning carefully selected upper division undergraduate mentor/tutors to assist the Montana Minds' scholars with their studies and help build community among these scholars;&lt;br/&gt;     -  assisting Montana Minds' scholars in pursuing faculty mentored undergraduate research.&lt;br/&gt;     -  visiting, during the Montana Minds' scholars freshman and sophomore years, national science and engineering laboratories to witness science and engineering done on a grand scale;&lt;br/&gt;     -  providing the financial support for each of the scholars to attend a national meeting during their junior year to broaden their acquaintance with the scope of their discipline; and &lt;br/&gt;     -  encouraging the Montana Minds' scholars to become involved with student clubs in their discipline.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Beyond these special features that enable the scholars' success, Montana Minds includes outreach activities to ensure broad impacts on a statewide level in both the secondary and post secondary educational systems.  Ultimately, this program aims to improve opportunities for students, increase graduation rates, create a more student-focused culture at Montana Tech, and educate faculty on the challenges facing financially disadvantaged students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1154068</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Cameron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Cameron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dcameron@mtech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4064964274</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000412144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuenzi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy J Kuenzi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akuenzi@mtech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4064964793</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336154</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Coe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas A Coe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dcoe@mtech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4064964207</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000411198</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Rossi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Rossi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rrossi@mtech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4064964102</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000598443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Dyne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michele Van Dyne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mvandyne@mtech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4064964102</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000598448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name> Montana Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Butte</CityName>
<ZipCode>597018932</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4064964102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1300 W. Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071408496</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONTANA TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079602596</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Montana Tech of the University of Montana]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597018997</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~145829</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~451352</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h1>Montana Minds, Scholarships for Science, Engineering, and Mathematics</h1> <h1>NSF Award 1154068</h1> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Montana Minds, Scholarships for Science, Engineering, and Mathematics</em> was a National Science Foundation sponsored program designed to increase the absolute number of students successfully pursuing careers in the Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines and in particular to increase the number of students doing so from underrepresented groups.&nbsp; At Montana Tech this $597,181 grant distributed over five years attracted and nurtured the success of 36 financially challenged students of academic promise in the specific majors of biology, chemistry, computer science, engineering, mathematics, software engineering, and statistics.</p> <h2>Goals and accomplishments of this grant included:&nbsp;</h2> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Recruiting high school students to major in STEM fields at Montana Tech with a particular focus on recruiting underrepresented groups</strong>.&nbsp; The initial Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars&rsquo; cohort consisted of 21 high school students of whom four or 19% were Native American.&nbsp; For comparison in 2016 Native Americans or Alaskan Natives made up 6.6% of Montana&rsquo;s population.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Providing scholarship support to financially challenged students with academic potential who are pursuing majors and careers in STEM fields</strong>.&nbsp; Ultimately the grant supported 36 Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars with up to $3,250 of scholarship support per semester, depending on need.&nbsp; Ninety-four of the scholarships we awarded were for the full amount, indicating that 94% of the students had a financial need that exceeded $3,250 per semester.&nbsp; Clearly students with need were supported.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Establishing mentoring and support structures that would allow these Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars to persevere and succeed</strong>.&nbsp; In their first semester Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars were enrolled in Montana Minds 101, a one credit course, where the students were introduced to; Student Success Services (SSS), a history of the National Science Foundation and why it funded their Montana Minds&rsquo; STEM scholarships, Meyer&rsquo;s Brigg&rsquo;s testing of their learning styles, the ins and outs of financial aid, personal histories and science trajectories of the STEM faculty Co-PIs on this grant; and Brain Based Learning.&nbsp; A very proactive and intrusive approach to advising was adopted.&nbsp; This approach involved monitoring the Montana Minds&rsquo; scholar&rsquo;s grades, meeting with students struggling academically to develop plans for improvement, and encouraging students to use the Montana Tech Academic Support Center and the grant supported tutors located in the TRIO Student Support Services tutoring Center.&nbsp; These efforts let the students know that we were monitoring their progress, that we cared how they were doing, and that we were available to help them succeed.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Building community and a culture of service among the Montana Minds&rsquo; Scholars.</strong>&nbsp; Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars volunteered at the 1<sup>st</sup> Tech Challenge Robotics Competition held on the Montana Tech campus and assisting Montana Tech in hosting <em>F1 in Schools</em>, a national activity to promote STEM through a competition in which high school students design, build, test, and race balsa wood models of formula 1 racing cars.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Supporting students of ability, who would succeed academically</strong>.&nbsp; The median cumulative GPA for Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars was 3.14 in all courses.&nbsp; The successful academic performance of the Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars is encouraging in that our students are drawn from a population whose families are financially challenged and who, it might be argued, had less access to appropriate academic preparation than the general student population.&nbsp; </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Exposing students to the breadth, depth, and opportunities available in the STEM fields they were pursuing</strong>.&nbsp; Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars were encouraged to pursue undergraduate research and in some cases co-authored or presented this research with their faculty mentors.&nbsp; In the spring semester of their first year the Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars, traveled to Hamilton, Montana to visit the Rocky Mountain Laboratory, home to several of the divisions of the National Institute of Health, including several in National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.&nbsp; In the fall semester of their second year Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars, traveled to Idaho National Laboratory headquartered in Idaho Falls, where among many other things they witnessed the reprocessing of spent nuclear fuel. &nbsp;In the scholars junior or senior years Montana Minds provided up to $2,000 to assist each scholar to attend a national meeting of their choice.&nbsp; These meetings or conferences included, among others, the American Chemical Society National Meeting, the National Bio-Geographers National Meeting, the Joint American Mathematical Association / Mathematical Association of America National Meeting, the American Computing Machinery visits to Google and Microsoft, and the American Geophysical Union National Meeting.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At the end of four years of grant funding, ten Montana Mind&rsquo;s Scholars have graduated.&nbsp; All ten graduated in STEM fields and are either employed or seeking employment in STEM fields or are pursuing graduate education in a STEM field. Most of the remaining Montana Minds&rsquo; scholars who received maximum grant funding, are nearing graduation in their current majors.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;A&nbsp;Coe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Montana Minds, Scholarships for Science, Engineering, and Mathematics NSF Award 1154068     Montana Minds, Scholarships for Science, Engineering, and Mathematics was a National Science Foundation sponsored program designed to increase the absolute number of students successfully pursuing careers in the Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines and in particular to increase the number of students doing so from underrepresented groups.  At Montana Tech this $597,181 grant distributed over five years attracted and nurtured the success of 36 financially challenged students of academic promise in the specific majors of biology, chemistry, computer science, engineering, mathematics, software engineering, and statistics. Goals and accomplishments of this grant included:      Recruiting high school students to major in STEM fields at Montana Tech with a particular focus on recruiting underrepresented groups.  The initial Montana Minds? scholars? cohort consisted of 21 high school students of whom four or 19% were Native American.  For comparison in 2016 Native Americans or Alaskan Natives made up 6.6% of Montana?s population.      Providing scholarship support to financially challenged students with academic potential who are pursuing majors and careers in STEM fields.  Ultimately the grant supported 36 Montana Minds? scholars with up to $3,250 of scholarship support per semester, depending on need.  Ninety-four of the scholarships we awarded were for the full amount, indicating that 94% of the students had a financial need that exceeded $3,250 per semester.  Clearly students with need were supported.      Establishing mentoring and support structures that would allow these Montana Minds? scholars to persevere and succeed.  In their first semester Montana Minds? scholars were enrolled in Montana Minds 101, a one credit course, where the students were introduced to; Student Success Services (SSS), a history of the National Science Foundation and why it funded their Montana Minds? STEM scholarships, Meyer?s Brigg?s testing of their learning styles, the ins and outs of financial aid, personal histories and science trajectories of the STEM faculty Co-PIs on this grant; and Brain Based Learning.  A very proactive and intrusive approach to advising was adopted.  This approach involved monitoring the Montana Minds? scholar?s grades, meeting with students struggling academically to develop plans for improvement, and encouraging students to use the Montana Tech Academic Support Center and the grant supported tutors located in the TRIO Student Support Services tutoring Center.  These efforts let the students know that we were monitoring their progress, that we cared how they were doing, and that we were available to help them succeed.      Building community and a culture of service among the Montana Minds? Scholars.  Montana Minds? scholars volunteered at the 1st Tech Challenge Robotics Competition held on the Montana Tech campus and assisting Montana Tech in hosting F1 in Schools, a national activity to promote STEM through a competition in which high school students design, build, test, and race balsa wood models of formula 1 racing cars.      Supporting students of ability, who would succeed academically.  The median cumulative GPA for Montana Minds? scholars was 3.14 in all courses.  The successful academic performance of the Montana Minds? scholars is encouraging in that our students are drawn from a population whose families are financially challenged and who, it might be argued, had less access to appropriate academic preparation than the general student population.        Exposing students to the breadth, depth, and opportunities available in the STEM fields they were pursuing.  Montana Minds? scholars were encouraged to pursue undergraduate research and in some cases co-authored or presented this research with their faculty mentors.  In the spring semester of their first year the Montana Minds? scholars, traveled to Hamilton, Montana to visit the Rocky Mountain Laboratory, home to several of the divisions of the National Institute of Health, including several in National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.  In the fall semester of their second year Montana Minds? scholars, traveled to Idaho National Laboratory headquartered in Idaho Falls, where among many other things they witnessed the reprocessing of spent nuclear fuel.  In the scholars junior or senior years Montana Minds provided up to $2,000 to assist each scholar to attend a national meeting of their choice.  These meetings or conferences included, among others, the American Chemical Society National Meeting, the National Bio-Geographers National Meeting, the Joint American Mathematical Association / Mathematical Association of America National Meeting, the American Computing Machinery visits to Google and Microsoft, and the American Geophysical Union National Meeting.      At the end of four years of grant funding, ten Montana Mind?s Scholars have graduated.  All ten graduated in STEM fields and are either employed or seeking employment in STEM fields or are pursuing graduate education in a STEM field. Most of the remaining Montana Minds? scholars who received maximum grant funding, are nearing graduation in their current majors.        Last Modified: 09/15/2017       Submitted by: Douglas A Coe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
