<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarships for Academically Talented but Economically Disadvantaged Students</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Lee</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF-S-STEM-Scholars@StCloud program at St. Cloud State University (SCSU) offers 30 two-year scholarships of up to $9,100 per year to academically talented and financially needy students who are interested in STEM careers in Information Systems, Computer Science and Computer Engineering. This program enhances the ability of these students to complete a high-quality degree program, thus strengthening the STEM workforce and its leadership. The NSF-S-STEM-Scholars@StCloud participants are recruited at the junior level, including transfer students. Full-time faculty mentors provide academic advising and each scholar has a faculty mentor, a graduate assistant or a senior student peer.  Many of SCSU's first-generation students come from low income families. Exceptionally talented students who chose low-cost two-year community, tribal and technical colleges transfer to SCSU to continue their studies. The project is developing liaisons with STEM departments in nearby colleges. SCSU is well-positioned to broaden the participation of economically disadvantaged and talented female and minority students to increase enrollment, recruit, retain and graduate them in STEM disciplines.  NSF-S-STEM-Scholars@StCloud students are graduating with the strong foundation necessary for them to be successful in their chosen careers in industry or in graduate school.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1154398</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayantha</FirstName>
<LastName>Herath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jayantha Herath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jherath@stcloudstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3203082142</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242763</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>Guster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis C Guster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>guster@mcs.stcloudstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3202554961</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000389246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susantha</FirstName>
<LastName>Herath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susantha Herath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sherath@stcloudstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3203082189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>St. Cloud State University</Name>
<CityName>St. Cloud</CityName>
<ZipCode>563014498</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3203084932</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>720 Fourth Avenue South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>027613855</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ST. CLOUD STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064754757</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[St. Cloud State University]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Cloud</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>563014498</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[720 Fourth Avenue South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The St. Cloud State University (SCSU) received an S-STEM grant in 2011 to provide scholarships for academically talented but economically disadvantaged students in Information Systems (IS), Computer Science (CS), and computer engineering (CE). We awarded 36 Scholarships of up to $18,200 and maintained 92% retention rate. Twenty-six scholars completed internships.&nbsp; This project helped to increase enrollment, improve retention and graduation, expand active participation in conferences, workshops and summer internships by scholars, build new structures and strengthen relationships with other 2-year colleges. Specific outcomes are:</p> <p>&nbsp;See Attachment Table 1</p> <p>&nbsp;See Attachment Table 2</p> <p>&nbsp;See Attachment Table 3</p> <ol> <li>Our marketing materials emphasized the promise of computing in the real world, high job growth expected for next ten years and a comparison of lifetime earnings of workers with STEM and other majors. Our key to success in a very short period is cross-advertising along the boundaries of different colleges, schools, and programs. </li> <li><strong>Research, seminars, conferences, workshops and teamwork: </strong>Each<strong> </strong>scholar engaged in a research project with practical applications, presented a paper in local or regional conferences. Scholars were encouraged to continue their research in areas with challenging problems and inspired them to become future professionals. Several excellent researchers from industry, government, and academia were invited to share their experience with scholars. This project brought together a group of faculty from diverse disciplines to initiate the development of a multidisciplinary learning and research community and develop new faculty-student collaborative research projects.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Mentoring</strong> of scholars by experienced faculty, the use of graduate assistants and peers in tutoring, research, seminars and design projects enhanced the scholar&rsquo;s educational experiences. The faculty team was available throughout the academic year for consultation. </li> <li><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>New connections with industry and national labs</strong>: Each year scholars visited at least one industry or a research facility. With the help of the Industrial Advisory Council, a high-tech business outreach effort was made for the benefit of the scholars. This initiative contributed to enhancing our laboratories. These new connections will help to excite and attract more high school or college students to select a career path in STEM. </li> <li><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>Summer Internships: </strong>Industry and government labs helped our scholars to complete internships. Scholars got practical experiences enhancing their academic learning that leads employment after graduation. &nbsp;90% of scholars from cohort 1, 100% from cohorts 2 and 3 completed a summer internship. </li> <li><strong>Leadership:</strong> Each scholar is given a leadership role in a year-long team project while helping them to be an active team member in another project. They were also encouraged to complete a MOOCS leadership course. Several scholars received SCSU leadership awards.</li> <li><strong></strong><strong>Connections with 2-year colleges:</strong>&nbsp; PIs held discussions with STEM program coordinators in community colleges to provide smooth transitioning from 2-year to 4-year college degree programs. The PIs established close relationships with thirteen 2-year colleges. Also, PIs participated in providing summer experiences for high school students from underrepresented groups in residential STEM program.</li> <li><strong></strong><strong>Connections with high schools: </strong>The Annual SCSU Pipeline Summer Camps were held for more than 100 underrepresented high school students. &nbsp;The Annual STEM Summits took place in 2013, 2014 and 2015 for students in grade 7-12. Our scholars shared their experiences and information related to high demanding STEM careers. Also, around 4,000 students in grades 7-12 from forty-six schools participated in Math-Contests. </li> <li><strong></strong><strong>New structures to strengthen STEM workforce:&nbsp; </strong>We have implemented a new 4+1 graduate program in Information Assurance, and Software Engineering (SE) major and 15-credit SE concentration.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </li> </ol> <p class="default">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Susantha&nbsp;Herath</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473772634202_Table1andthegraphillustratethenumberofmajorsforeachprogramforsixyears--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473772634202_Table1andthegraphillustratethenumberofmajorsforeachprogramforsixyears--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473772634202_Table1andthegraphillustratethenumberofmajorsforeachprogramforsixyears--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Table 1 and the graph illustrate the number of majors for each program for six years.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Susantha Herath</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susantha&nbsp;Herath</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473773242500_Table2depictsthenumberofdisadvantagedgroupmembersineachareafor2011--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473773242500_Table2depictsthenumberofdisadvantagedgroupmembersineachareafor2011--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473773242500_Table2depictsthenumberofdisadvantagedgroupmembersineachareafor2011--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Table 2 depicts the number of disadvantaged group members in each area in 2011</div> <div class="imageCredit">Susantha Herath</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susantha&nbsp;Herath</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473773329640_Table3illustratesthedistributionofscholarshipsamongdisadvantagedgroups--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473773329640_Table3illustratesthedistributionofscholarshipsamongdisadvantagedgroups--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1154398/1154398_10163730_1473773329640_Table3illustratesthedistributionofscholarshipsamongdisadvantagedgroups--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Table 3 illustrates the distribution of scholarships among disadvantaged groups</div> <div class="imageCredit">Susantha Herath</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susantha&nbsp;Herath</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The St. Cloud State University (SCSU) received an S-STEM grant in 2011 to provide scholarships for academically talented but economically disadvantaged students in Information Systems (IS), Computer Science (CS), and computer engineering (CE). We awarded 36 Scholarships of up to $18,200 and maintained 92% retention rate. Twenty-six scholars completed internships.  This project helped to increase enrollment, improve retention and graduation, expand active participation in conferences, workshops and summer internships by scholars, build new structures and strengthen relationships with other 2-year colleges. Specific outcomes are:   See Attachment Table 1   See Attachment Table 2   See Attachment Table 3  Our marketing materials emphasized the promise of computing in the real world, high job growth expected for next ten years and a comparison of lifetime earnings of workers with STEM and other majors. Our key to success in a very short period is cross-advertising along the boundaries of different colleges, schools, and programs.  Research, seminars, conferences, workshops and teamwork: Each scholar engaged in a research project with practical applications, presented a paper in local or regional conferences. Scholars were encouraged to continue their research in areas with challenging problems and inspired them to become future professionals. Several excellent researchers from industry, government, and academia were invited to share their experience with scholars. This project brought together a group of faculty from diverse disciplines to initiate the development of a multidisciplinary learning and research community and develop new faculty-student collaborative research projects.   Mentoring of scholars by experienced faculty, the use of graduate assistants and peers in tutoring, research, seminars and design projects enhanced the scholar?s educational experiences. The faculty team was available throughout the academic year for consultation.   New connections with industry and national labs: Each year scholars visited at least one industry or a research facility. With the help of the Industrial Advisory Council, a high-tech business outreach effort was made for the benefit of the scholars. This initiative contributed to enhancing our laboratories. These new connections will help to excite and attract more high school or college students to select a career path in STEM.   Summer Internships: Industry and government labs helped our scholars to complete internships. Scholars got practical experiences enhancing their academic learning that leads employment after graduation.  90% of scholars from cohort 1, 100% from cohorts 2 and 3 completed a summer internship.  Leadership: Each scholar is given a leadership role in a year-long team project while helping them to be an active team member in another project. They were also encouraged to complete a MOOCS leadership course. Several scholars received SCSU leadership awards. Connections with 2-year colleges:  PIs held discussions with STEM program coordinators in community colleges to provide smooth transitioning from 2-year to 4-year college degree programs. The PIs established close relationships with thirteen 2-year colleges. Also, PIs participated in providing summer experiences for high school students from underrepresented groups in residential STEM program. Connections with high schools: The Annual SCSU Pipeline Summer Camps were held for more than 100 underrepresented high school students.  The Annual STEM Summits took place in 2013, 2014 and 2015 for students in grade 7-12. Our scholars shared their experiences and information related to high demanding STEM careers. Also, around 4,000 students in grades 7-12 from forty-six schools participated in Math-Contests.  New structures to strengthen STEM workforce:  We have implemented a new 4+1 graduate program in Information Assurance, and Software Engineering (SE) major and 15-credit SE concentration.                Last Modified: 09/13/2016       Submitted by: Susantha Herath]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
