<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Increasing Student Enrollment and Achievement in Engineering and Engineering Technology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>575000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>575000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is to increase the number of talented, recent high school graduates successfully completing the mechatronics engineering, mechanical engineering technology and electronic engineering technology baccalaureate degree programs at Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology.  The objectives are: 1) to provide 25 four-year scholarships to talented, economically disadvantaged students enrolled in Vaughn's programs; 2) to improve student support services by providing scholarship recipients with a centralized hub of academic support services including: highly qualified tutors, mentors, supplemental instructors and academic advisors - all located in Vaughn's Teaching and Learning Center; 3) to increase the number of students who complete undergraduate research projects under the mentorship of Vaughn faculty; 4). to increase the number of engineering and engineering technologies scholarship recipients securing internships with local companies.  The project includes a number of interventions to achieving its objectives, including tutoring, mentoring, industry internships, and a Technology Day Conference. The project will have a positive impact on the participation of underrepresented minorities in STEM fields, particularly Hispanic Americans. The partnerships with industry and other organizations that include United Technologies Corporation, Delta Airlines, and the Federal Aviation Administration will help to broaden the impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1154000</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>LaVergne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul LaVergne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paul.lavergne@vaughn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7184296600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000161376</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hossein</FirstName>
<LastName>Rahemi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hossein Rahemi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hossein.rahemi@vaughn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7184296600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000158258</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Flushing</CityName>
<ZipCode>113698475</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7184296600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>86-01 23 Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>90</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY90</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066968454</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VAUGHN COLLEGE OF AERONAUTICS AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066968454</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Flushing</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>113691000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[86-01 23rd Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~575000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary objective of this project is to increase the number of students completing a BS degree in STEM field, in our case in engineering or engineering technology programs. This objective has been achieved by providing students with continuous academic support, research opportunities, necessary financial support and implementing faculty mentorship program. The STEM scholarship program was able to provide students with the necessary academic resources and guidance they needed to achieve successful degree completion and prepare a cadre of well-qualified and trained engineering graduates. As of fall 2017, 89% of those who graduated have obtained a full-time job in STEM field, and others received their job offers to join upon graduation.</p> <p>The program is designed to serve two cohorts from freshman year to senior year studying an Engineering or Engineering Technology undergraduate degree program. The first cohort started in fall 2012 with ten students, while the second cohort started in fall 2013 with fifteen students.</p> <p>Both cohorts followed a four-year plan. Freshman year was particularly important to shape students&rsquo; understanding of engineering education and improve their chances to complete their degree. This was achieved by reinforcing the skills related to engineering. Well-rounded learning communities were developed to specifically focus on some of the tools that help students improve their performance in engineering courses. This followed by getting students in the program to utilize the college academic services; and enriching their campus life experience as they were encouraged to be active in students&rsquo; clubs such as robotics and UAV club. In the third and fourth year, the project included activities on research and professional exposure through conference participation and professional presentations.&nbsp;The topics were selected by students with the help of faculty advisors. All participants were required to present their projects in the annual technology day conference of the Engineering and Technology Department which is held at the college in April of each year. Many of these projects were accepted in regional and national conferences such as IEEE and ASEE.</p> <p>&nbsp;The focus in measuring the effectiveness of the program was on the achievement of program objectives. The chart (included) shows the average GPA of students in the program compared with the GPA of all students in degree program at Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology. Although it&rsquo;s recognized that the project is inherently selective in terms of the students&rsquo; academic performance; however, it was important to track this integral measure in order to evaluate the overall effectiveness of the program on students&rsquo; academic performance.</p> <p>The program is initially designed to serve 25 students; however, the services of the program has been benefiting many other students in engineering programs at Vaughn College. During the life of the project, there was a large increase of students&rsquo; club activities, that prompted the creation of 3D prototyping innovation center. The center now encompasses modern technologies such as varieties of 3D printing machines, 3D scanner and industrial CAD and CAM software. Currently, the center is open free of charge to all students at Vaughn College to use and get the adequate training. This active communities of students have been seen in the significant increase of student participation in professional activities and professional conferences. Students from this program led their VEX Robotics U team to win the world championship in 2016 and advanced Vaughn's UAV team to win the second place in 2017 and the first place in 2018 at the annual American Helicopter Society, Micro-UAV competition and many other awards in professional arenas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Hossein&nbsp;Rahemi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534197821458_VEXU2016--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534197821458_VEXU2016--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VEX U 2016"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534197821458_VEXU2016--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VEX U 2016"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Robotics club winning 2016 VEX U World Championship</div> <div class="imageCredit">Vaughn College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hossein&nbsp;Rahemi</div> <div class="imageTitle">VEX U 2016</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534197657488_chart--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534197657488_chart--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chart"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534197657488_chart--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chart"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Average GPA of students in the program compared with overall GPA of students in Vaughn College</div> <div class="imageCredit">Vaughn College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hossein&nbsp;Rahemi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chart</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534198102500_UAV2018--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534198102500_UAV2018--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Vaughn's UAV"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1154000/1154000_10163736_1534198102500_UAV2018--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Vaughn's UAV"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">VAUGHN?S UAV TEAM TAKE FIRST PLACE IN THE SIXTH ANNUAL MICRO AIR VEHICLE COMPETITION</div> <div class="imageCredit">Vaughn College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hossein&nbsp;Rahemi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Vaughn's UAV</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary objective of this project is to increase the number of students completing a BS degree in STEM field, in our case in engineering or engineering technology programs. This objective has been achieved by providing students with continuous academic support, research opportunities, necessary financial support and implementing faculty mentorship program. The STEM scholarship program was able to provide students with the necessary academic resources and guidance they needed to achieve successful degree completion and prepare a cadre of well-qualified and trained engineering graduates. As of fall 2017, 89% of those who graduated have obtained a full-time job in STEM field, and others received their job offers to join upon graduation.  The program is designed to serve two cohorts from freshman year to senior year studying an Engineering or Engineering Technology undergraduate degree program. The first cohort started in fall 2012 with ten students, while the second cohort started in fall 2013 with fifteen students.  Both cohorts followed a four-year plan. Freshman year was particularly important to shape students? understanding of engineering education and improve their chances to complete their degree. This was achieved by reinforcing the skills related to engineering. Well-rounded learning communities were developed to specifically focus on some of the tools that help students improve their performance in engineering courses. This followed by getting students in the program to utilize the college academic services; and enriching their campus life experience as they were encouraged to be active in students? clubs such as robotics and UAV club. In the third and fourth year, the project included activities on research and professional exposure through conference participation and professional presentations. The topics were selected by students with the help of faculty advisors. All participants were required to present their projects in the annual technology day conference of the Engineering and Technology Department which is held at the college in April of each year. Many of these projects were accepted in regional and national conferences such as IEEE and ASEE.   The focus in measuring the effectiveness of the program was on the achievement of program objectives. The chart (included) shows the average GPA of students in the program compared with the GPA of all students in degree program at Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology. Although it?s recognized that the project is inherently selective in terms of the students? academic performance; however, it was important to track this integral measure in order to evaluate the overall effectiveness of the program on students? academic performance.  The program is initially designed to serve 25 students; however, the services of the program has been benefiting many other students in engineering programs at Vaughn College. During the life of the project, there was a large increase of students? club activities, that prompted the creation of 3D prototyping innovation center. The center now encompasses modern technologies such as varieties of 3D printing machines, 3D scanner and industrial CAD and CAM software. Currently, the center is open free of charge to all students at Vaughn College to use and get the adequate training. This active communities of students have been seen in the significant increase of student participation in professional activities and professional conferences. Students from this program led their VEX Robotics U team to win the world championship in 2016 and advanced Vaughn's UAV team to win the second place in 2017 and the first place in 2018 at the annual American Helicopter Society, Micro-UAV competition and many other awards in professional arenas.             Last Modified: 08/13/2018       Submitted by: Hossein Rahemi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
