<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Reciprocity, Generosity, Trust, and Group Solidarity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175499.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210243</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>SES-1155289&lt;br/&gt;Jeffrey Lucas&lt;br/&gt;Carmi Schooler&lt;br/&gt;University of Maryland, College Park&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reciprocity, Generosity, Trust, and Group Solidarity&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research has shown that individuals raised in Western cultures (e.g., U.S. and Canada) and those raised in Eastern cultures (e.g., China and Japan) differ in their views of themselves and their relationships and obligations toward the groups of which they are part. This experimental project has two goals. The first goal is to investigate whether these documented cross-cultural differences can be produced by changes in the social structure. To that end, the experimental conditions in this study vary the types of networks of social exchange in which participants interact. The second goal is to study how variations in structures of exchange contribute to the development of trust and commitment in networks of exchange. The investigators predict that generalized exchange, in which actors give benefits to different actors than those from whom they receive benefits (as opposed, for example, to networks in which actors compete with each other for resources), will produce more interdependent and holistic orientations, as well as higher levels of trust and commitment, than other types of exchange. Ultimately, the research seeks to contribute to our understanding of how changes in social structure can affect profound cultural differences between Eastern and Western societies, a well as differences in trust and group solidarity across cultures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts &lt;br/&gt;Understanding how social conditions, including network structures, shape group solidarity has important implications, both for everyday interactions and in critical situations created e.g., by rapid social change or unexpected events.  If successful, results might suggest interventions to promote cooperative behavior in groups, increase trust and solidarity, and improve performance on various types of tasks. The research also has a significant education component, leading to the training of a number of graduate and undergraduate students in research. Finally, the research will involve modifications to a widely used software program for behavioral experiments, modifications that will be made freely available to interested researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1155289</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Lucas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey W Lucas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlucas2@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056435</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carmi</FirstName>
<LastName>Schooler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carmi Schooler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cschooler@socy.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000538330</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~187499</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~22744</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research in cultural psychology has identified important dimensions on which cultures vary&mdash;collectivist versus individualist, tight versus loose, independent versus interdependent. This work has been noteworthy in part by demonstrating that cultural differences exist beyond simply variations in preferences, beliefs, and customs. For example, individuals in collectivist cultures tend to view threats to their in-groups as powerful threats to themselves, whereas persons in individualistic societies tend to view in-group relationships, even family relationships, as non-binding. More recent research has found that cultural variations extend even to ways that people observe and process stimuli in their environments. In particular, persons in interdependent societies tend to adopt more context-dependent, holistic orientations than persons in independent cultures, who tend to adopt more context-interdependent, analytic orientations.</p> <p>The most dominant explanation for cultural differences in cognitive and perceptional orientation is the rice theory, which proposes that the modes of food production that dominated when societies developed gave rise to differences in how individuals viewed the world. In particular, the theory proposes that the high levels of coordination and cooperation required by rice farming set in motion social processes that ultimately led to relatively holistic cognitive orientations. There are various other explanations, but the one feature they share in common is implicating differences in social structure in giving rise to differences in cognitive orientation. Colleagues and I set out with NSF funding to determine whether by varying social structure in the laboratory we can produce differences in cognitive orientation that mirror those that are thought to reflect profound cultural differences.</p> <p>We focused on social networks and identified two ways that network structures might give rise to differences in cognitive orientation. First, if network structures encourage people to be aware of what is going on in distant parts of the network (such as might be reflected in the coordination required by rice farming for example), it might lead to relatively more holistic orientations. We call this our more structure-based argument. Second, if network structures encourage stronger social bonds (such as might result from the cooperation required by rice farming), it might lead to more holistic orientations.</p> <p>We carried out three experiments aimed at assessing these relationships. In a first study, we had participants interact in network structures that we thought would give rise to different levels of concern about distal relations and different levels of commitment to the networks. After participants interacted in the networks over a number of rounds, we measured cognitive orientation. In general, results supported the more structure-based argument but not the more affect-based argument. In a second experiment, we attempted to directly manipulate concern about the broader structure by varying rules constraining exchange activities and affective attachment by having partners give gifts to participants or not. The second experiment supported the affect-based argument but not the structure-based argument. However, manipulation checks showed that the variation in exchange rules did not manipulate concern about the broader network in ways that we anticipated. A third experiment replicated the second experiment at a university in China. In this experiment, the structure manipulation worked, but the affect manipulation did not&mdash;curiously, participants felt less commitment to partners and networks when they received gifts than when they did not. Interpreting results on cognitive orientation from the third study (and from the second) has proven difficult. Analyses are ongoing.</p> <p>Our studies additionally tested how features of networks gi...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research in cultural psychology has identified important dimensions on which cultures vary&mdash;collectivist versus individualist, tight versus loose, independent versus interdependent. This work has been noteworthy in part by demonstrating that cultural differences exist beyond simply variations in preferences, beliefs, and customs. For example, individuals in collectivist cultures tend to view threats to their in-groups as powerful threats to themselves, whereas persons in individualistic societies tend to view in-group relationships, even family relationships, as non-binding. More recent research has found that cultural variations extend even to ways that people observe and process stimuli in their environments. In particular, persons in interdependent societies tend to adopt more context-dependent, holistic orientations than persons in independent cultures, who tend to adopt more context-interdependent, analytic orientations.  The most dominant explanation for cultural differences in cognitive and perceptional orientation is the rice theory, which proposes that the modes of food production that dominated when societies developed gave rise to differences in how individuals viewed the world. In particular, the theory proposes that the high levels of coordination and cooperation required by rice farming set in motion social processes that ultimately led to relatively holistic cognitive orientations. There are various other explanations, but the one feature they share in common is implicating differences in social structure in giving rise to differences in cognitive orientation. Colleagues and I set out with NSF funding to determine whether by varying social structure in the laboratory we can produce differences in cognitive orientation that mirror those that are thought to reflect profound cultural differences.  We focused on social networks and identified two ways that network structures might give rise to differences in cognitive orientation. First, if network structures encourage people to be aware of what is going on in distant parts of the network (such as might be reflected in the coordination required by rice farming for example), it might lead to relatively more holistic orientations. We call this our more structure-based argument. Second, if network structures encourage stronger social bonds (such as might result from the cooperation required by rice farming), it might lead to more holistic orientations.  We carried out three experiments aimed at assessing these relationships. In a first study, we had participants interact in network structures that we thought would give rise to different levels of concern about distal relations and different levels of commitment to the networks. After participants interacted in the networks over a number of rounds, we measured cognitive orientation. In general, results supported the more structure-based argument but not the more affect-based argument. In a second experiment, we attempted to directly manipulate concern about the broader structure by varying rules constraining exchange activities and affective attachment by having partners give gifts to participants or not. The second experiment supported the affect-based argument but not the structure-based argument. However, manipulation checks showed that the variation in exchange rules did not manipulate concern about the broader network in ways that we anticipated. A third experiment replicated the second experiment at a university in China. In this experiment, the structure manipulation worked, but the affect manipulation did not&mdash;curiously, participants felt less commitment to partners and networks when they received gifts than when they did not. Interpreting results on cognitive orientation from the third study (and from the second) has proven difficult. Analyses are ongoing.  Our studies additionally tested how features of networks give rise to differences in trust and commitment. Results on those items were more strai...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
