<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Researching and Improving Geography Teacher Preparation Through Transatlantic Collaborations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99294.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99294</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative transatlantic research with United States, the United Kingdom, and Finland partners will determine how geography contributes to the overall capabilities of K-12 students. There are two major components to this project that address capabilities, or the principles of understanding topics like autonomy, human rights, citizenship, sustainable development, economy and culture. The first is an international comparative analysis of national geography standards, teacher preparation curricula and practices within the U.S., U.K., and Finland to determine how standards address the capabilities of students. The resulting synthesis report will illustrate for other nations how capability concepts can bridge divergent conceptions and practices in geography education and set the stage for international collaborations in teacher preparation. The second project component will design and implement a workshop convening geography professors and recent graduates from pre-service teacher education programs in the U.S. and EU. Informed by the outcomes of content analysis research performed in the first year, participants will identify and ultimately bridge differing national conceptions of geography as an academic discipline, what it means to "think geographically," and the role of post-secondary teacher preparation in enhancing geographic education. Following the workshop, the participants will develop online educational resources that will connect pre-service geography teachers for international collaborative projects using the Center for Global Geography Education (CGGE) at the Association of American Geographers. These educational resources draw on an approach to curriculum development known as the "capability approach" to unify various national conceptions of geography in a way that enables aspiring geography teachers to engage the perspectives of their peers internationally as they develop expertise in the subject. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Geography plays an important role in everyday decision-making. Thinking geographically underpins the practice of asking questions that identify changing relationships between places, and communicate patterns observed at various scales. These questions become more complex when viewed from an international lens. This project, founded on international partnership, will enhance geographic education through teacher preparation workshops and freely accessible professional development resources. The new CGGE case studies and collaborative projects will connect pre-service teachers online to study and discuss important geographic questions in their respective nations and provide them with important opportunities for cross-cultural understanding and geographic learning in relation to capability principles.  Eventually, the students of project participants will experience similar opportunities to attain international perspectives on geographic content emphasized in national standards.  Together, these cross-cultural research and educational activities will facilitate the development of internationally connected teacher preparation programs rooted in sophisticated international geography perspectives.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1155255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Solem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael N Solem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>msolem@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122454770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201820</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gallagher Heffron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Gallagher Heffron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sgallagher@aag.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022341450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000403832</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Association of American Geographers</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200093104</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2022341450</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1710 16th St. NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074848482</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATION OF AMERICAN GEOGRAPHERS, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Association of American Geographers]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200093104</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1710 16th St NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~99294</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project, GeoCapabilities, produced a theoretical framework for developing teachers as curriculum leaders. The framework is the major achievement of international collaborative research by geographers specializing in teacher education.&nbsp;</p> <p>The motivation of the project was to establish a means for international dialogue and collaboration in geography education. Although there are considerable differences in national standards and curriculum requirements for geography in schools, it is also true that underlying those differences are shared goals and principles:</p> <p>1) Geographical thinking is a human capability that is essential for life, work and citizenship in the modern complex world.</p> <p>2) Schools are sites where students have opportunities to access the geographical knowledge that enables geographical thinking.</p> <p>3) Teachers who understand the nature and characteristics of geographical knowledge are needed to enact the goals of a geography curriculum. &nbsp;</p> <p>The GeoCapabilities framework provides researchers, teachers and teacher trainers with an intellectual apparatus for expressing the goals and purposes of geography education, both internationally and within the context of any given country.&nbsp;</p> <p>The teaching profession carries the pivotal social responsibility of educating children and young people. With each passing year, the classroom beckons new cohorts of teachers hoping to make a difference and a chance to inspire young minds.</p> <p>Although many teachers enjoy a long and satisfying career, at times even the most gifted and committed teachers find it hard to stay motivated and idealistic about their profession. It is difficult work, often for modest pay and sometimes unrecognized by society at large. In an era when high-stakes testing and accountability pressures show little sign of abating, all too often teachers are asked only to concern themselves with technical matters - of how to improve their &lsquo;effectiveness&rsquo; (measured by their students &lsquo;performance&rsquo;).</p> <p>The technical issues of <em>what</em> and <em>how </em>to teach a particular topic or theme are of course crucial. However, even though the importance of the &ldquo;what&rdquo;<em> </em>and the &ldquo;how&rdquo; of geography teaching cannot be disputed, there is an even more pressing matter. The GeoCapabilities approach to teacher education places<strong>&nbsp;</strong>emphasis firmly on the <em>why</em>.</p> <p>As the project shows, children and young people are the ultimate beneficiaries of having teachers know <em>why</em> they are teaching a particular topic or theme. These teachers have a viewpoint about the significance of geography. They have an understanding of what children need to know, understand and be able to do in this day and age in which:</p> <ul> <li>technology is pervasive and highly personal; </li> <li>hundreds of thousands of people migrate daily in search of a better life, with profound implications both for the places they enter and the places left behind; </li> <li>the trade of goods and services in the world economy continues to intensify and deepen connections between people all over, from the smallest villages to the largest cities; </li> <li>global climate change leaves no corner of Earth&rsquo;s environment untouched.</li> </ul> <p>This list could go on an on, but the point is clear: children live in a highly interdependent and globalized world. They need to be educated in a manner that prepares them for this world. The GeoCapabilities&nbsp;approach&nbsp;to teacher training asks teachers to reflect on how geography can enhance students&rsquo; thinking, enabling them to make better, informed choices about how to live.</p> <p><span>Teachers show leadership by taking responsibility for (and being able to justify) content selections. They are crucial in bringing to fruition the goals of a geography curric...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project, GeoCapabilities, produced a theoretical framework for developing teachers as curriculum leaders. The framework is the major achievement of international collaborative research by geographers specializing in teacher education.   The motivation of the project was to establish a means for international dialogue and collaboration in geography education. Although there are considerable differences in national standards and curriculum requirements for geography in schools, it is also true that underlying those differences are shared goals and principles:  1) Geographical thinking is a human capability that is essential for life, work and citizenship in the modern complex world.  2) Schools are sites where students have opportunities to access the geographical knowledge that enables geographical thinking.  3) Teachers who understand the nature and characteristics of geographical knowledge are needed to enact the goals of a geography curriculum.    The GeoCapabilities framework provides researchers, teachers and teacher trainers with an intellectual apparatus for expressing the goals and purposes of geography education, both internationally and within the context of any given country.   The teaching profession carries the pivotal social responsibility of educating children and young people. With each passing year, the classroom beckons new cohorts of teachers hoping to make a difference and a chance to inspire young minds.  Although many teachers enjoy a long and satisfying career, at times even the most gifted and committed teachers find it hard to stay motivated and idealistic about their profession. It is difficult work, often for modest pay and sometimes unrecognized by society at large. In an era when high-stakes testing and accountability pressures show little sign of abating, all too often teachers are asked only to concern themselves with technical matters - of how to improve their æeffectivenessÆ (measured by their students æperformanceÆ).  The technical issues of what and how to teach a particular topic or theme are of course crucial. However, even though the importance of the "what" and the "how" of geography teaching cannot be disputed, there is an even more pressing matter. The GeoCapabilities approach to teacher education places emphasis firmly on the why.  As the project shows, children and young people are the ultimate beneficiaries of having teachers know why they are teaching a particular topic or theme. These teachers have a viewpoint about the significance of geography. They have an understanding of what children need to know, understand and be able to do in this day and age in which:  technology is pervasive and highly personal;  hundreds of thousands of people migrate daily in search of a better life, with profound implications both for the places they enter and the places left behind;  the trade of goods and services in the world economy continues to intensify and deepen connections between people all over, from the smallest villages to the largest cities;  global climate change leaves no corner of EarthÆs environment untouched.   This list could go on an on, but the point is clear: children live in a highly interdependent and globalized world. They need to be educated in a manner that prepares them for this world. The GeoCapabilities approach to teacher training asks teachers to reflect on how geography can enhance studentsÆ thinking, enabling them to make better, informed choices about how to live.  Teachers show leadership by taking responsibility for (and being able to justify) content selections. They are crucial in bringing to fruition the goals of a geography curriculum. By contemplating the why of geography education in the context of this day and age, teachers will be better prepared to engage the goals of a progressive knowledge-led curriculum: they will be better able to make reasoned, purposeful decisions about what to teach and how to teach it.  The ideas developed in this project wil...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
