<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Perception, Planning, Mobility, and Interaction for Next Generation Robotics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>340000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>340000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harriet Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This funding establishes a new Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at the University of Pennsylvania (Penn) focused on next generation robotics. The site is hosted by the General Robotics, Automation, Sensing, and Perception (GRASP) Laboratory inside Penn's School of Engineering and Applied Sciences.  Each summer a cohort of undergraduate students will work with GRASP faculty on cutting-edge research aligned with core projects ongoing in the lab.  The students will participate in professional development activities that make them more aware of graduate school and professional aspects of a computing career. The primary purpose of the site is to extend the GRASP research experience to more students who come from groups traditionally under-represented in science, technology, engineering and mathematics.  These students will have access to the outstanding faculty and facilities available at the university to conduct challenging research using technologies that underpin next generation robotics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies with the strong research team and the focus on next generation robotics technologies. The students will be exposed to the fundamentals of robotics science, spanning a wide spectrum from perception and control theory to planning algorithms and mechanical design, but unified by experiments on concretely defined real-world challenges.  The research has the potential to contribute to the research core of the computing disciplines.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the project include providing a quality research experience to undergraduate students, particularly students from underrepresented groups and from institutions with limited research environments. Thus this project has the potential to produce new computer science graduate students and faculty members and to advance discovery and understanding while promoting learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1156366</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Max</FirstName>
<LastName>Mintz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Max Mintz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mintz@cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158987909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000186353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuchenbecker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine J Kuchenbecker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kuchenbe@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2155732786</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000465871</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~340000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span><strong>Overview:</strong> The "Perception, Planning, Mobility, and Interaction for Next Generation Robotics" REU Site was an integral part of the General Robotics, Automation, Sensing, and Perception (GRASP) Laboratory, a vibrant interdisciplinary laboratory inside the School of Engineering and Applied Science at the University of Pennsylvania. Previously, the vast majority of the undergraduates doing research in the GRASP Lab have been Penn students, with a few individuals from other research universities each year. </span></p> <p><span>The <strong>primary purpose</strong> of this REU Site was to extend the GRASP research experience to more undergraduate students who come from groups traditionally underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), particularly students&nbsp;</span>from low-income backgrounds, ethnic and racial minorities, first-generation college students, and women. The REU Site aimed to accomplish this goal by recruiting eight to twelve qualified external students from these groups each summer, particularly from small four-year colleges where research opportunities in robotics either do not exist or are far less abundant. The program thus enabled significant broader impacts by helping energize and train the students who participated in the program. Specifically, REU students (i) experienced the excitement of doing independent research; (ii) strengthened their thought processes for solving complex problems; (iii) learned how to cope with temporary setbacks and uncertainty; (iv) obtained a preview of graduate study and research as a career; and (v) felt connected to Penn&rsquo;s cross-disciplinary and multi-generational community of robotics scholars.</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <div class="page" title="Page 2"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The <strong>secondary purpose</strong> of this REU Site was to advance the state of the art in robotics research. Participants in the program were exposed to the fundamentals of robotics science, spanning a wide intellectual spectrum from perception and control theory to planning algorithms and mechanical design, but unified by experiments on concretely defined real-world challenges. Each student was matched with an individual project under the mentorship of a GRASP faculty member and a doctoral student or postdoc. The projects actively built on research that was already taking place and were tailored to the background and interests of the recruited student. The projects encompassed kinematics and dynamics, continuous and discrete mathematics, statistical models, machine learning, the analysis and synthesis of algorithms, data structures, programming in high-level languages, hardware-software integration, data analysis, and mechatronics.&nbsp;</span></p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <div class="page" title="Page 4"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><strong>Primary Objectives: </strong><span>As listed above, our primary goal was to extend the GRASP research experience to more undergraduate students who come from groups traditionally underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), particularly students from low-income backgrounds, ethnic and racial minorities, first- generation college students, and women. Further, we sought to recruit students from institutions that were not large research universities. </span></p> <p><strong>Our Evaluation (for years 2012-14): </strong><span>We were successful in accomplishing our primary goal in that none of the twenty-eight participants in the REU Site in years 2012-14 would probably have done research in the GRASP Lab, if not for this program. Four of the twenty-eight participants self-identified as African American and two ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     Overview: The "Perception, Planning, Mobility, and Interaction for Next Generation Robotics" REU Site was an integral part of the General Robotics, Automation, Sensing, and Perception (GRASP) Laboratory, a vibrant interdisciplinary laboratory inside the School of Engineering and Applied Science at the University of Pennsylvania. Previously, the vast majority of the undergraduates doing research in the GRASP Lab have been Penn students, with a few individuals from other research universities each year.   The primary purpose of this REU Site was to extend the GRASP research experience to more undergraduate students who come from groups traditionally underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), particularly students from low-income backgrounds, ethnic and racial minorities, first-generation college students, and women. The REU Site aimed to accomplish this goal by recruiting eight to twelve qualified external students from these groups each summer, particularly from small four-year colleges where research opportunities in robotics either do not exist or are far less abundant. The program thus enabled significant broader impacts by helping energize and train the students who participated in the program. Specifically, REU students (i) experienced the excitement of doing independent research; (ii) strengthened their thought processes for solving complex problems; (iii) learned how to cope with temporary setbacks and uncertainty; (iv) obtained a preview of graduate study and research as a career; and (v) felt connected to PennÆs cross-disciplinary and multi-generational community of robotics scholars.          The secondary purpose of this REU Site was to advance the state of the art in robotics research. Participants in the program were exposed to the fundamentals of robotics science, spanning a wide intellectual spectrum from perception and control theory to planning algorithms and mechanical design, but unified by experiments on concretely defined real-world challenges. Each student was matched with an individual project under the mentorship of a GRASP faculty member and a doctoral student or postdoc. The projects actively built on research that was already taking place and were tailored to the background and interests of the recruited student. The projects encompassed kinematics and dynamics, continuous and discrete mathematics, statistical models, machine learning, the analysis and synthesis of algorithms, data structures, programming in high-level languages, hardware-software integration, data analysis, and mechatronics.           Primary Objectives: As listed above, our primary goal was to extend the GRASP research experience to more undergraduate students who come from groups traditionally underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), particularly students from low-income backgrounds, ethnic and racial minorities, first- generation college students, and women. Further, we sought to recruit students from institutions that were not large research universities.   Our Evaluation (for years 2012-14): We were successful in accomplishing our primary goal in that none of the twenty-eight participants in the REU Site in years 2012-14 would probably have done research in the GRASP Lab, if not for this program. Four of the twenty-eight participants self-identified as African American and two as Hispanic, groups that are drastically under-represented in STEM fields. Nine of the twenty-eight participants self-identified as being the first members of their family to attend college.   Similarly, twelve of the twenty-eight participants were women, another strongly under-represented group in STEM. Two of the twenty-eight participants self-identified as being gay. Unfortunately, we did not ask the students to self-identify on the issue of income level, so we are not able to establish the degree to which we met this objective. None of the students came from the University of ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
