<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Stopping Rule Selection Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>111743.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>123743</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project the Principal Investigator will develop a new theoretical framework for understanding stopping rules in decision making. The  stopping rule is thought to be a crucial component of successful decision making. Over the years, several unconnected explanations have been proposed to account for some observed violations of optimal stopping rules. The current research proposes a unifying explanation for these violations based on a new stopping rule selection (SRS) theory. This theory is innovative in that it proceeds from the assumption that for any given decision problem, a decision maker draws from a large set of different kinds of decision strategies and stopping rules. The SRS theory hypothesizes that there is a storage area for stopping rules -- the so-called decision operative space (DOS) -- and a retrieval mechanism that is used to select stopping rules from the DOS. The SRS theory has shown good fit to some challenging data previously published in the relevant literature. The fits were achieved using pattern analysis, which is a novel approach based on fitting the relative frequency of observed data patterns to the predicted response patterns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of broader impacts, the knowledge gained in the study should be useful to those who seek to develop or improve prescriptive decision aids. Decision aids are commonly employed to improve human performance in complex endeavors, including medicine, aviation, defense and business.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1156681</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mario</FirstName>
<LastName>Fific</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mario Fific</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fificm@gvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163316826</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597879</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Grand Valley State University</Name>
<CityName>Allendale</CityName>
<ZipCode>494019401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6163316840</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 Campus Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059692996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GRAND VALLEY STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059692996</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Grand Valley State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>494019401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~111743</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>One of the most important steps of decision making is determining when to stop collecting evidence and proceed with the final decision. This process is defined as the stopping rule, and it is thought to be an irreplaceable component of everyday decision making. For example, when purchasing merchandise on Amazon, one can decide to read recommendations before buying the product. The question is how many recommendation should be read before making a decision regarding a purchase? Most models of decision making assume that people use only one way to stop collecting evidence and then make a decision. However, individuals report using a variety of stopping rules in reality. For example, some use three recommendations, and the most frequent recommendation determines the decision. Some seek for a difference value (say two) of a sum of recommendations. Some make a decision only if they observe a streak of (say three) recommendations, in a sequence. These stopping rules, when appropriately used can lead to good decision making.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>However, not all stopping rules are equal in different real life situations. Take, for example, a patient who is facing a risky medical treatment. The treatment can have a good outcome&mdash;that is, the patient will benefit from it&mdash;or it can have a bad outcome&mdash;that is, the patient will suffer serious side effects. To the patient&rsquo;s surprise, doctors don&rsquo;t have a unanimous opinion on whether the treatment is beneficial or harmful. Thus, the patient decides to ask for several doctors&rsquo; opinions. But how many doctors&rsquo; opinions is enough? A typical strategy used in this case is to sample a fixed number of opinions, for example using the famous &lsquo;second doctor opinion&rsquo; stopping rule, which involves &nbsp;&nbsp;consulting two doctors only. Using two doctors&rsquo; opinions seems more financially appropriate then using the difference stopping rule of say two doctors&rsquo; opinions, as with the latter the patient may be visiting too many doctors to achieve the difference of two opinions.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>How does a person know which decision making strategy to use and in which situation? This is one of the most important questions of decision-making in modern cognitive science. For if an inappropriate stopping rule is used, this can result in disastrous outcome. Take for example the hypothetical Buridan&rsquo;s donkey case - where an optimally rational donkey is situated midway between two equally attractive piles of hay. Unable to choose between them, it starved to death. The donkey could not collect the critical amount of evidence needed to decide which haystack it should eat. One could say that the Buridan&rsquo;s donkey paradox arises because the donkey was unable to use an effective stopping rule for the given situation. What makes this story almost comical is the recognition that such a disastrous scenario could never happen to a human decision-maker. It seems that all human decision-makers are somehow protected from such paradox. The donkey would surely survive if it used the fixed small number of opinions about the haystacks. For example, prior the decision making, the donkey could add the simple fixed sample stopping rule to his optimal decision making system: &ldquo;I will collect not more than seven opinions about the haystacks -if I can&rsquo;t make the decision up to that number, I should stop and go with the left haystack.&rdquo; Human beings on the other hand are equipped to use stopping rules in a variety of different contexts.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>To explain these phenomena in human decision-making, a stopping rule selection (SRS) theory was proposed. The current research project provides support for the idea that human decision makers can use several stopping rules concurrently, while making a single decision. The SRS theory gives rise to a computational model, which shows how multiple stopping rules are selected and used in decision making. According to this idea, a human estimates how much mental effort is needed to make a decision and how long it takes to collect evidence. Based on this estimates, the automatic process selects a set of useful stopping rules from the proposed storage place and provides them for immediate use. By assuming that a decision maker can simultaneously select from several stopping rules, the SRS theory explains how people react adaptively to challenges in different situations, select effective stopping rules strategies, and eventually avoid the dreadful Buridan&rsquo;s donkey paradox.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The supported project in exploring stopping rules represents an advanced and integrative approach to learning about the human decision-making process and how decision making makes use of a simple adaptive mechanism. The study&rsquo;s findings could have wide-ranging implications in decision analysis in everyday situations as well as in decision making in social environments (e.g., health care, management, marketing, shopping,) in which it is not possible to use optimal approaches. The project outcomes could be used to make a positive contribution to improving the quality of decision making in society. <strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Mario&nbsp;Fific</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  One of the most important steps of decision making is determining when to stop collecting evidence and proceed with the final decision. This process is defined as the stopping rule, and it is thought to be an irreplaceable component of everyday decision making. For example, when purchasing merchandise on Amazon, one can decide to read recommendations before buying the product. The question is how many recommendation should be read before making a decision regarding a purchase? Most models of decision making assume that people use only one way to stop collecting evidence and then make a decision. However, individuals report using a variety of stopping rules in reality. For example, some use three recommendations, and the most frequent recommendation determines the decision. Some seek for a difference value (say two) of a sum of recommendations. Some make a decision only if they observe a streak of (say three) recommendations, in a sequence. These stopping rules, when appropriately used can lead to good decision making.   However, not all stopping rules are equal in different real life situations. Take, for example, a patient who is facing a risky medical treatment. The treatment can have a good outcome&mdash;that is, the patient will benefit from it&mdash;or it can have a bad outcome&mdash;that is, the patient will suffer serious side effects. To the patient?s surprise, doctors don?t have a unanimous opinion on whether the treatment is beneficial or harmful. Thus, the patient decides to ask for several doctors? opinions. But how many doctors? opinions is enough? A typical strategy used in this case is to sample a fixed number of opinions, for example using the famous ?second doctor opinion? stopping rule, which involves   consulting two doctors only. Using two doctors? opinions seems more financially appropriate then using the difference stopping rule of say two doctors? opinions, as with the latter the patient may be visiting too many doctors to achieve the difference of two opinions.   How does a person know which decision making strategy to use and in which situation? This is one of the most important questions of decision-making in modern cognitive science. For if an inappropriate stopping rule is used, this can result in disastrous outcome. Take for example the hypothetical Buridan?s donkey case - where an optimally rational donkey is situated midway between two equally attractive piles of hay. Unable to choose between them, it starved to death. The donkey could not collect the critical amount of evidence needed to decide which haystack it should eat. One could say that the Buridan?s donkey paradox arises because the donkey was unable to use an effective stopping rule for the given situation. What makes this story almost comical is the recognition that such a disastrous scenario could never happen to a human decision-maker. It seems that all human decision-makers are somehow protected from such paradox. The donkey would surely survive if it used the fixed small number of opinions about the haystacks. For example, prior the decision making, the donkey could add the simple fixed sample stopping rule to his optimal decision making system: "I will collect not more than seven opinions about the haystacks -if I can?t make the decision up to that number, I should stop and go with the left haystack." Human beings on the other hand are equipped to use stopping rules in a variety of different contexts.   To explain these phenomena in human decision-making, a stopping rule selection (SRS) theory was proposed. The current research project provides support for the idea that human decision makers can use several stopping rules concurrently, while making a single decision. The SRS theory gives rise to a computational model, which shows how multiple stopping rules are selected and used in decision making. According to this idea, a human estimates how much mental effort is needed to make a decision and how long it takes to collect evidence. Based on this estimates, the automatic process selects a set of useful stopping rules from the proposed storage place and provides them for immediate use. By assuming that a decision maker can simultaneously select from several stopping rules, the SRS theory explains how people react adaptively to challenges in different situations, select effective stopping rules strategies, and eventually avoid the dreadful Buridan?s donkey paradox.              The supported project in exploring stopping rules represents an advanced and integrative approach to learning about the human decision-making process and how decision making makes use of a simple adaptive mechanism. The study?s findings could have wide-ranging implications in decision analysis in everyday situations as well as in decision making in social environments (e.g., health care, management, marketing, shopping,) in which it is not possible to use optimal approaches. The project outcomes could be used to make a positive contribution to improving the quality of decision making in society.                                 Last Modified: 07/29/2016       Submitted by: Mario Fific]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
