<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Socio-political Complexity, Interaction, and Community Ritual at Formative Etlatongo, Oaxaca, Mexico</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>267605.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>267605</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The origin of complex societies--the change from egalitarian to early ranked (or chiefdom level) societies-- is a fundamental transformation explored by social scientists. Due to its diachronic nature, archaeology is particularly well suited to explore the dramatic changes in power and status relationships attendant with complex societies. In ancient Mexico, socio-politically complex societies first appear between 1500 and 850 BC. Substantial debate has centered on the role of political integration, differences in domestic economies and access to exotic materials, interregional interaction, and public ceremony in this major social transition. In order to contribute to this debate, Dr. Blomster will conduct archaeological research at the Nochixtlán Valley site of Etlatongo, in the Mixteca Alta of Oaxaca, Mexico. His research will explore the emergence and dynamics of early ranked society through variation in archaeological correlates including: household assemblages, architecture, craft production, community ritual, access to exotic goods, and interregional interaction. The Mixteca has been characterized as exhibiting less precocious developments in socio-political complexity and interregional interaction than their contemporaries in the nearby Valley of Oaxaca, which provides substantial comparative data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through three years of excavation and laboratory analyses at Etlatongo, the researcher will generate multiple lines of data to explore the emergence and dynamics of early ranked society in the Nochixtlán Valley. The researcher's hypothesis is that Etlatongo developed rapidly into a large center circa 1150 BC due to the confluence of the development of public ritual and greater access to exotic symbols and materials through interregional interaction. He will explore this central hypothesis through two main anthropological questions. The first question is: did Etlatongo, circa 1150 BC, become a ranked society, comparable to the similarly-sized contemporaneous chiefly center of San José Mogote in the Valley of Oaxaca? This issue will be assessed by exploring comparative differences in household architecture, crafting activities, material culture, and participation in feasting. The second question is: if present, what were the key factors in the emergence of socio-political complexity at Etlatongo? This issue will be examined through analysis of public space, ritual, and interregional interaction (including with the Olmec of Mexico's Gulf Coast), to determine if they are associated with nascent leaders both spatially and through their restricted access to ritual paraphernalia and/or exotic materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By documenting Etlatongo's early political history, this research will have a broader impact by increasing awareness of Mixtecs' unique contributions to local and national cultural heritage. Based on the interests of local stakeholders, Dr. Blomster will collaborate in development projects, including a proposed community museum at Etlatongo. Research results will be disseminated to the public through a bilingual English/Spanish project website. The project will also train students from both Mexico and the United States, promoting international collaboration, and will generate dissertation and thesis projects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1156373</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Blomster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Blomster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>blomster@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029944880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000583922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~267605</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through the support of the NSF, the Formative Etlatongo Project (FEP) successfully completed three seasons of excavations at the site of Etlatongo, in the Mixteca Alta of Oaxaca, Mexico. While much of the artifact analysis is still in progress, the excavations and preliminary observations on the materials excavated do allow for assessment of the major questions that guided the research, which focus on socio-political complexity and interregional interaction.</p> <p>The origin of complex societies--the change from egalitarian to early ranked (or chiefdom level) societies&mdash;is a fundamental transformation explored by social scientists. Due to its diachronic nature, archaeology is particularly well suited to explore the dramatic changes in power and status relationships attendant with complex societies. In ancient Mexico, socio-politically complex societies first appear in between 1500 and 850 BC. Substantial debate has centered on the role of political integration, differences in domestic economies and access to exotic materials, interregional interaction, and public ceremony in this major social transition. In order to contribute to this debate, the FEP conducted archaeological research at the Nochixtl&aacute;n Valley site of Etlatongo. This research explored the emergence and dynamics of early ranked society through variation in archaeological correlates including: household assemblages, architecture, craft production, community ritual, access to exotic goods, and interregional interaction. The Mixteca has been characterized as exhibiting less precocious developments in socio-political complexity and interregional interaction than their contemporaries in the nearby Valley of Oaxaca, which provides substantial comparative data.</p> <p>Through three years of excavation and laboratory analyses at Etlatongo, the FEP has generated multiple lines of data to explore the emergence and dynamics of early ranked society in the Nochixtl&aacute;n Valley. The major hypothesis explored by the FEP is that Etlatongo developed rapidly into a large center during the Cruz B phase (circa 1150-850 BC) due to the confluence of the development of public ritual and greater access to exotic symbols and materials through interregional interaction. This central hypothesis was addressed through two main anthropological questions. The first question is: did Etlatongo, circa 1150 BC, become a ranked society, comparable to the similarly-sized contemporaneous chiefly center of San Jos&eacute; Mogote in the Valley of Oaxaca? This issue was assessed by exploring comparative differences in household architecture, crafting activities, and material culture. The FEP exposed portions of houses and domestic space in the northern and eastern portions of the site which did reveal differences in construction techniques, although the artifact analysis, still in progress, will allow for a better determination of comparative socio-economic status and the presence of crafting behavior. It is probable the Cruz B phase houses documented by the FEP are primarily higher status structures although potentially with much variability between them as expressed by objects and raw materials. In terms of the timing of Etlatongo&rsquo;s occupation, the FEP&rsquo;s results also support previous research at the site which has not documented any primary occupations prior to the Cruz B phase, suggesting a very limited occupation prior to the establishment of a large, 26 ha site at Etlatongo.</p> <p>The second question is: if present, what were the key factors in the emergence of socio-political complexity at Etlatongo? This issue was examined through analysis of public space, ritual, and interregional interaction to determine if they are associated with nascent leaders both spatially and through their restricted access to ritual paraphernalia and/or exotic materials. While much of the chemical analysis on materials excavated is still being conducted at laboratories, the FEP focused much of its excavations on a mound in the southern portion of the site, which previous research had identified as a locus of probable Cruz B public space. The FEP did expose a substantial portion of Cruz B public architecture on this mound. The FEP exposed two versions of a probable ballcourt, made by a combination of earthen and stone architecture. Numerous figurine fragments were deposited atop this public space. No evidence of a Cruz B domestic space associated with this public architecture was found by the FEP.</p> <p>The FEP also had a broader impact by increasing awareness of Mixtecs&rsquo; unique contributions to local and national cultural heritage. The FEP conducted numerous tours of the site for local stakeholders and school groups from across the region, and presented posters about the research to the modern town of San Mateo Etlatongo. All project results will be disseminated to the public through a bilingual English/Spanish project website, currently under construction. The FEP also trained students from both Mexico and the United States, promoting international collaboration. The data obtained by the FEP will serve as the basis for several dissertation and thesis projects, with some results already presented at the 2017 SAAs. The FEP will organize a session at the 2018 SAAs that will present data from all periods encountered during the three years of NSF-supported excavations at Etlatongo.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Blomster</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through the support of the NSF, the Formative Etlatongo Project (FEP) successfully completed three seasons of excavations at the site of Etlatongo, in the Mixteca Alta of Oaxaca, Mexico. While much of the artifact analysis is still in progress, the excavations and preliminary observations on the materials excavated do allow for assessment of the major questions that guided the research, which focus on socio-political complexity and interregional interaction.  The origin of complex societies--the change from egalitarian to early ranked (or chiefdom level) societies&mdash;is a fundamental transformation explored by social scientists. Due to its diachronic nature, archaeology is particularly well suited to explore the dramatic changes in power and status relationships attendant with complex societies. In ancient Mexico, socio-politically complex societies first appear in between 1500 and 850 BC. Substantial debate has centered on the role of political integration, differences in domestic economies and access to exotic materials, interregional interaction, and public ceremony in this major social transition. In order to contribute to this debate, the FEP conducted archaeological research at the Nochixtl&aacute;n Valley site of Etlatongo. This research explored the emergence and dynamics of early ranked society through variation in archaeological correlates including: household assemblages, architecture, craft production, community ritual, access to exotic goods, and interregional interaction. The Mixteca has been characterized as exhibiting less precocious developments in socio-political complexity and interregional interaction than their contemporaries in the nearby Valley of Oaxaca, which provides substantial comparative data.  Through three years of excavation and laboratory analyses at Etlatongo, the FEP has generated multiple lines of data to explore the emergence and dynamics of early ranked society in the Nochixtl&aacute;n Valley. The major hypothesis explored by the FEP is that Etlatongo developed rapidly into a large center during the Cruz B phase (circa 1150-850 BC) due to the confluence of the development of public ritual and greater access to exotic symbols and materials through interregional interaction. This central hypothesis was addressed through two main anthropological questions. The first question is: did Etlatongo, circa 1150 BC, become a ranked society, comparable to the similarly-sized contemporaneous chiefly center of San Jos&eacute; Mogote in the Valley of Oaxaca? This issue was assessed by exploring comparative differences in household architecture, crafting activities, and material culture. The FEP exposed portions of houses and domestic space in the northern and eastern portions of the site which did reveal differences in construction techniques, although the artifact analysis, still in progress, will allow for a better determination of comparative socio-economic status and the presence of crafting behavior. It is probable the Cruz B phase houses documented by the FEP are primarily higher status structures although potentially with much variability between them as expressed by objects and raw materials. In terms of the timing of Etlatongo?s occupation, the FEP?s results also support previous research at the site which has not documented any primary occupations prior to the Cruz B phase, suggesting a very limited occupation prior to the establishment of a large, 26 ha site at Etlatongo.  The second question is: if present, what were the key factors in the emergence of socio-political complexity at Etlatongo? This issue was examined through analysis of public space, ritual, and interregional interaction to determine if they are associated with nascent leaders both spatially and through their restricted access to ritual paraphernalia and/or exotic materials. While much of the chemical analysis on materials excavated is still being conducted at laboratories, the FEP focused much of its excavations on a mound in the southern portion of the site, which previous research had identified as a locus of probable Cruz B public space. The FEP did expose a substantial portion of Cruz B public architecture on this mound. The FEP exposed two versions of a probable ballcourt, made by a combination of earthen and stone architecture. Numerous figurine fragments were deposited atop this public space. No evidence of a Cruz B domestic space associated with this public architecture was found by the FEP.  The FEP also had a broader impact by increasing awareness of Mixtecs? unique contributions to local and national cultural heritage. The FEP conducted numerous tours of the site for local stakeholders and school groups from across the region, and presented posters about the research to the modern town of San Mateo Etlatongo. All project results will be disseminated to the public through a bilingual English/Spanish project website, currently under construction. The FEP also trained students from both Mexico and the United States, promoting international collaboration. The data obtained by the FEP will serve as the basis for several dissertation and thesis projects, with some results already presented at the 2017 SAAs. The FEP will organize a session at the 2018 SAAs that will present data from all periods encountered during the three years of NSF-supported excavations at Etlatongo.             Last Modified: 12/14/2017       Submitted by: Jeffrey Blomster]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
