<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Mathematics in Indiana University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>265659.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>265659</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Pearl</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Continuing a forty-six year old tradition, the Department of Mathematics at Indiana University will offer summer intensive research experiences for talented undergraduates. Working one-on-one or in small groups with faculty, eight students will spend eight weeks on our campus working on research problems selected by faculty members.  Typically, these problems are open, accessible, and mathematically significant.  Topics in pure mathematics include the dynamics of billiards, logic, complex dynamics, combinatorial topology, and tilings of surfaces.  Topics in applied mathematics emphasize the growing relationship between mathematics and biology and include population genetics and molecular evolution, polymer organization and cell function, evolution of phenotypes, genome evolution, and phylogenetics.  Housed together in a dormitory and sharing common office space, students benefit from being immersed in mathematics.  Frequent presentations by local faculty give the cohort a broader and deeper understanding of mathematics. Students disseminate their findings by giving brief presentations at a statewide undergraduate mathematics research conference, giving an hour-long formal lecture to peers, faculty, and graduate students, and writing a formal self-contained research report detailing their findings. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The fast pace of technological innovation is creating not only new types of jobs, but also new types of problems.  Many of these problems require quantitative analysis.  In biology, imaging, telecommunications, medicine, finance, and dozens of other fields, our ability to collect large amounts of data is leading to enormous new analytical challenges.  How does one train an individual to work on these large, unsolved, complex problems? By exposing them, early in their career, to the thrill and challenge of mathematical research.  Our summer research experience will give a small group of talented students the opportunity to develop abstract problem-solving skills, intellectual stamina, creativity, perseverance, communication skills, and work ethic.  Our students emerge better prepared to meet the future challenges they will face and to maintain the important intellectual infrastructure of our nation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1156515</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Moss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence S Moss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lmoss@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128558281</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000459308</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Pilgrim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin M Pilgrim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pilgrim@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128553477</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/11/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Connell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher G Connell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>connell@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128551883</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000266785</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474021847</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O Box 1847]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~265659</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF Mathematics REU at Indiana University Bloomington is an integrated 8-week summer research program focused on multiple projects in both theoretical and applied mathematics. The summer 2014 group consisted of 10 students coming from various undergraduate programs: Brigham Young U.,&nbsp;East Tennessee State U., Indiana U. North,&nbsp;Purdue U.,&nbsp;U. Glasgow,&nbsp;Rutgers U.,&nbsp;U. Texas,&nbsp;Harvey Mudd,&nbsp;&nbsp;and U.&nbsp;Rochester. In line with demographic goals of the program, one half of these students were women, twenty percent were under-represented minorities and forty percent were first generation college students.</p> <p>Students worked one-on-one or in pairs with faculty mentors on a wide range of pure math projects including reducing noise in chaotic signals, configurationspaces of linkages, ideal boundaries for dynamical systems, ends of negatively curved surfaces, conformal transformations of generalized Minkowski space. Other students worked on projects with a more applied flavor including homotopy type theory, modeling of face perception in psychology, and the calculus of generalized quantum states. Some of these projects have the potential to positively impact public welfare in the short term through improvements in technology, especially electrical design and algorithms.</p> <p>In addition to conducting research, students participated in a highly structured professional development program where they learned how to write mathematics, explored the software tools needed for their projects, attended presentations from professional mathematicians on current research in various fields, and gave presentations on their own work. In addition, all participants presented their work in a formal talk at the annual statewide undergraduate mathematics research conference. &nbsp;</p> <p>The formal results of every student project are published in a compiled volume that can be found online at the IU Bloomington REU homepage. Moreover, so far one peer-reviewed journal article from the 2014 projects has already been published, and at least one more is in process. Other evidence of the positive impact of these experiences on the future of these students has been profound, as at least four have been admitted to top tier Ph.D. programs in mathematics (Michigan, Indiana, Utah and Cornell) and another has embarked on a career in data analysis. (Most of the others are still completing their undergraduate programs.)</p> <p>Post-program assessment data also indicates a very positive student experience stemming primarily from the rare opportunity and access afforded by the projects to work effectively on cutting edge research problems. However, students are also appreciative of the organized social events which help release pressure from the overall intensity of the work.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;G&nbsp;Connell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF Mathematics REU at Indiana University Bloomington is an integrated 8-week summer research program focused on multiple projects in both theoretical and applied mathematics. The summer 2014 group consisted of 10 students coming from various undergraduate programs: Brigham Young U., East Tennessee State U., Indiana U. North, Purdue U., U. Glasgow, Rutgers U., U. Texas, Harvey Mudd,  and U. Rochester. In line with demographic goals of the program, one half of these students were women, twenty percent were under-represented minorities and forty percent were first generation college students.  Students worked one-on-one or in pairs with faculty mentors on a wide range of pure math projects including reducing noise in chaotic signals, configurationspaces of linkages, ideal boundaries for dynamical systems, ends of negatively curved surfaces, conformal transformations of generalized Minkowski space. Other students worked on projects with a more applied flavor including homotopy type theory, modeling of face perception in psychology, and the calculus of generalized quantum states. Some of these projects have the potential to positively impact public welfare in the short term through improvements in technology, especially electrical design and algorithms.  In addition to conducting research, students participated in a highly structured professional development program where they learned how to write mathematics, explored the software tools needed for their projects, attended presentations from professional mathematicians on current research in various fields, and gave presentations on their own work. In addition, all participants presented their work in a formal talk at the annual statewide undergraduate mathematics research conference.    The formal results of every student project are published in a compiled volume that can be found online at the IU Bloomington REU homepage. Moreover, so far one peer-reviewed journal article from the 2014 projects has already been published, and at least one more is in process. Other evidence of the positive impact of these experiences on the future of these students has been profound, as at least four have been admitted to top tier Ph.D. programs in mathematics (Michigan, Indiana, Utah and Cornell) and another has embarked on a career in data analysis. (Most of the others are still completing their undergraduate programs.)  Post-program assessment data also indicates a very positive student experience stemming primarily from the rare opportunity and access afforded by the projects to work effectively on cutting edge research problems. However, students are also appreciative of the organized social events which help release pressure from the overall intensity of the work.       Last Modified: 10/29/2015       Submitted by: Christopher G Connell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
