<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site:  3D Invertebrate Herbivory and Biodiversity in Deciduous North American Forest Canopies: Inspiring Students with Physical Disabilities to Pursue Field Biology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175942.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>189251</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site award has been made to Baker University in collaboration with the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences to provide research training for 8 students, for 10 weeks during the summers of 2013 &amp; 2014. The research focus is on the three dimensional spatial and temporal variability of plant-invertebrate interactions in a temperate deciduous forest canopy. The PI team will train and supervise the students' accent into the canopy and their collection of tardigrades and leaves which will be measured, tested, and analyzed in the new Baker Ecology Laboratory. Students are trained in field ecology from the experimental design stage to a publishable manuscript.  Students will participate in classes, seminars, and workshops on subjects such as responsible conduct in research, scanning electron microscopy, geographical information systems, professional communication skills, single rope technique climbing, exposure to career opportunities in academia, museums, and industry, and the graduate school application process. Students will also be exposed to local industries, governmental agencies, and the Konza Long-Term Ecological Research site. REU students will learn to use remote access tools to monitor the environment, communicate with experts, and develop scholarly publications. The program's recruitment effort includes traditional "hard copy" formats, e-mail and Facebook digital advertising, and direct contact with organizations for students and veterans with disabilities.  The program is designed to accommodate students with ambulatory disabilities, expected to comprise about 50% of the cohort. Students will be selected based on academic record, desire to learn field biology, and potential for outstanding research in field or ecological biology. Students will be tracked to determine activity in their academic field of study, their career paths, and the lasting influences of the research experience. The program will be assessed by the REU Common Assessment Tool in addition to other tools. More information is available by visiting http://canopy.naturalsciences.org , or by contacting PI (Dr. William Miller at William.Miller@BakerU.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Meg Lowman or Dr. Elzie McCord at canopymeg@gmail.com).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1156550</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William R Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>William.Miller@BakerU.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7855948379</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000293421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Baker University</Name>
<CityName>Baldwin City</CityName>
<ZipCode>660060000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7855948398</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8th and Grove</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>048259584</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE BAKER UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048259584</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Baker University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>660060065</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9232</Code>
<Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~175942</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~6630</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6679</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In 2012, the National Science Foundation awarded a Research Experience for Undergraduates grant (DEB: REU#1156550) to PI William R. Miller at Baker University and Co-PI Margret D. Lowman of the California Academy of Sciences. The project was conducted in the canopy of Kansas and ended with presentations in California.</p> <p>The core objective of the project was to give undergraduates a real research experiences that would help them&nbsp;to understand the challenges and rewards of graduate school using the little known tardigrade or water bear and the equally understudied canopy of North America. The basic research question was "how do tardigrades use the canopy?" Students were challenged to develop and answer hypothesis about the density, distribution and diversity of tardigrades within the canopy. They were professionally trained to climb trees safely and instructed as how to collect, process and extract tardigrades, make microscope slides and identify their specimens. Students used phase contrast (PC), differential interference contrast (DIC) and scanning electron microscopes (SEM) to understand the morphology of the animals.</p> <p>Ten different locations were visited; 225 trees (substrates) of 24 different species were climbed and 1,023 samples of tardigrade habitat (moss and lichen) for four different levels were collected. 12,266 tardigrades of 17 different species were extracted. Six species that were new to Kansas, four of which are new to science were discovered. From this common data set each student extracted a subset, learned the value of accurate data and the headaches of decimal point, spelling, and transposition errors. Students learned to interpret significant differences with statistical analysis for differences between observed and expected data.</p> <p>From the beginning students were told to think about how to write a professional paper. They found, read and established an introduction based on the primary literature and wrote methods about their field and lab work. They selected appropriate data from&nbsp;the common set and summarized it into results with tables and figures. A discussion was developed to explain the results. Finally, a poster, a PowerPoint presentation and a manuscript were created.</p> <p>Seven peer reviewed articles have been published and five additional articles have been submitted for review. The papers include the&nbsp;description of three of the new species, two species previously known from other continents and the demonstration of stratification, i.e. greater tardigrade diversity and density higher in the canopy. Substrate (tree species) has been demonstrated has a significant influence on tardigrade density and habitat suitability.&nbsp;Because the process of publication often takes years, our students remain in contact with us.</p> <p>Individual students have represented the team with 21 poster and oral/PowerPoint presentations at recent Kansas, Missouri and Oregon Academy of Science meetings. Additionally, selected students have presented at the Council for Undergraduate Research in Washington DC, the Sigma Xi national Research Society International meetings in North Carolina and Arizona, the Bay Area REU Symposium and the 13th International Tardigrade Symposium in Modena, Italy.</p> <p>Our students conducted public outreach by running "Water Bear Weekends" at the Overland Park Arboretum, the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences and the California Academy of Sciences at which students have shown tardigrades and our project to more than 3,000 members of the public. In addition, we assisted professional tree climbing trainers in getting more than 300 members of the public into the canopy.</p> <p>Science ethics was taught by lecture, readings, discussion and examples. Program evaluation was by REU standard survey and discussion with each student. Our team has included three students with disabilities, two navy ve...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In 2012, the National Science Foundation awarded a Research Experience for Undergraduates grant (DEB: REU#1156550) to PI William R. Miller at Baker University and Co-PI Margret D. Lowman of the California Academy of Sciences. The project was conducted in the canopy of Kansas and ended with presentations in California.  The core objective of the project was to give undergraduates a real research experiences that would help them to understand the challenges and rewards of graduate school using the little known tardigrade or water bear and the equally understudied canopy of North America. The basic research question was "how do tardigrades use the canopy?" Students were challenged to develop and answer hypothesis about the density, distribution and diversity of tardigrades within the canopy. They were professionally trained to climb trees safely and instructed as how to collect, process and extract tardigrades, make microscope slides and identify their specimens. Students used phase contrast (PC), differential interference contrast (DIC) and scanning electron microscopes (SEM) to understand the morphology of the animals.  Ten different locations were visited; 225 trees (substrates) of 24 different species were climbed and 1,023 samples of tardigrade habitat (moss and lichen) for four different levels were collected. 12,266 tardigrades of 17 different species were extracted. Six species that were new to Kansas, four of which are new to science were discovered. From this common data set each student extracted a subset, learned the value of accurate data and the headaches of decimal point, spelling, and transposition errors. Students learned to interpret significant differences with statistical analysis for differences between observed and expected data.  From the beginning students were told to think about how to write a professional paper. They found, read and established an introduction based on the primary literature and wrote methods about their field and lab work. They selected appropriate data from the common set and summarized it into results with tables and figures. A discussion was developed to explain the results. Finally, a poster, a PowerPoint presentation and a manuscript were created.  Seven peer reviewed articles have been published and five additional articles have been submitted for review. The papers include the description of three of the new species, two species previously known from other continents and the demonstration of stratification, i.e. greater tardigrade diversity and density higher in the canopy. Substrate (tree species) has been demonstrated has a significant influence on tardigrade density and habitat suitability. Because the process of publication often takes years, our students remain in contact with us.  Individual students have represented the team with 21 poster and oral/PowerPoint presentations at recent Kansas, Missouri and Oregon Academy of Science meetings. Additionally, selected students have presented at the Council for Undergraduate Research in Washington DC, the Sigma Xi national Research Society International meetings in North Carolina and Arizona, the Bay Area REU Symposium and the 13th International Tardigrade Symposium in Modena, Italy.  Our students conducted public outreach by running "Water Bear Weekends" at the Overland Park Arboretum, the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences and the California Academy of Sciences at which students have shown tardigrades and our project to more than 3,000 members of the public. In addition, we assisted professional tree climbing trainers in getting more than 300 members of the public into the canopy.  Science ethics was taught by lecture, readings, discussion and examples. Program evaluation was by REU standard survey and discussion with each student. Our team has included three students with disabilities, two navy veterans, two minorities and 10 women. We did not design the program for the disabled, but our personal experience suggested t...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
