<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integrated opto-nanofluidic biosensors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>365400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: Optical label-free biosensors measure analytes in their natural form without fluorescence labeling. Unfortunately, nearly all of them suffer from the detection limit bottleneck of approximately 1 pg/mm2. In contrast to detecting analytes attached to a single solid-liquid interface, the nanoporous based biosensor enables 3-dimensional detection, as multiple solid-liquid interfaces are present in the detection region. As a result, 0.01 pg/mm2 or better detection limit can potentially be achieved. However, one major issue with the nanoporous sensor is the sample delivery. It takes extremely long time for molecules to diffuse into (and out of) the porous detection region. The problem exacerbates when one deals with complex media, as it is very difficult to remove the unwanted interfering molecules from inside the pores, which causes large non-specific binding and severely deteriorates sensing performance.&lt;br/&gt;The proposed opto-nanofluidic sensor overcomes the aforementioned problems while maintaining high sensitivity even in the presence of complex media. It employs a nanostructured capillary placed in a Fabry-Pérot microcavity, which serves simultaneously as a flow-through nanofluidic channel, sample concentrator, and optical label-free sensor. It has a number of distinctive advantages. (1) It retains high sensitivity similar to that in nanoporous biosensors while having much larger Q-factors, which leads to an unprecedented detection limit on the order of fg/mm2; (2) It retains the high analyte capture efficiency due to the large surface-to-volume ratio and meanwhile its built-in flow-through nanofluidic channels enable quick and controlled sample delivery; (3) Detection of analytes from complex media becomes much easier. The interfering molecules can thoroughly be rinsed off, thus minimizing the non-specific binding and enhancing the sensing performance; (4) It is mechanically robust and can be mass-produced at a very low cost with the fiber drawing method; (5) The hole size is highly uniform and can be adjusted to accommodate different sizes of analytes and flow rates; (6) Due to its small size and simplicity, it can be scaled up to an array format for multiplexed detection on the nL scale; and (7) It can easily be connected to upstream sample processing components and downstream sample analyzers for further analysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This project includes prominent education components for graduate, undergraduate, and high school students. The students involved in the proposed project will acquire interdisciplinary knowledge and skills in photonics, nano/microfabrication, chemistry, material sciences, and biotechnology. Furthermore, the results and expertise developed through this project will be directly incorporated into the PI?s teaching at both undergraduate and graduate levels. Additionally, the PI will work closely with local non-Ph.D. granting institutes to develop a summer program for their students to conduct research in the PI?s lab. Finally, the collaboration with industrial companies will be instrumental in opto-nanofluidic sensor design, fabrication, integration, and applications, as well as in student training.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1158638</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xudong</FirstName>
<LastName>Fan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xudong Fan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xsfan@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347631273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000434677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1101 Beal Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>142E</Code>
<Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project is to develop a label-free optical biosensors that have two important features. (1) The sensors have thousands of nanostructures such as nanopillars and nanoholes so that the surface of the sensor can be tremendously increased for improved sensing sensitivity. (2) The sensors have so called "flow through" structure so that samples in liquid can be flowed into and out of those nanostructures easily. We have implemented this nove biosensor concept in two major platforms (1) multi-hole polymer/glass capillaries, which can be fabricated using a&nbsp;fiber drawing method. (2) nanopillar structures fabricated on silicon wafer using the nanoimprinting technology.</p> <p>In our project, we first carried out theoretical calculataion to estimate how much the sensing signal is for a layer of biomolecules deposited onto the surface of the nanostructures and contrast this signal to the signal generated by a conventional biosensor that has only flat surface. 10-100 fold increase in the sensivitiy can&nbsp; be obtained. Then we fabricated both capillary and nanopillar based biosensors. After this we integrated the sensors with home-made microfluidics for sample and reagent delivery. Finally, we tested those sensors using actual biomolecules.</p> <p>We have published a few papers based on the outcomes from the project. Two patents were also filed. In addition, we went through the NSF i-Corps program in order to commercialize this technology. Later a start-up company was formed.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Xudong&nbsp;Fan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1158638/1158638_10184158_1477964156958_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1158638/1158638_10184158_1477964156958_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanopillar based biosensors"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1158638/1158638_10184158_1477964156958_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanopillar based biosensors"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nanopillars can be fabricated using the nanoimprinting technology</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xudong Fan and Zhizheng Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xudong&nbsp;Fan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanopillar based biosensors</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1158638/1158638_10184158_1477964072108_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1158638/1158638_10184158_1477964072108_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Multi-hole capillary based biosensors"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1158638/1158638_10184158_1477964072108_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Multi-hole capillary based biosensors"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Multi-hole capillaries can be fabricated using a fiber drawing method</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xudong Fan and Maung Kyaw Khaing Oo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xudong&nbsp;Fan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Multi-hole capillary based biosensors</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project is to develop a label-free optical biosensors that have two important features. (1) The sensors have thousands of nanostructures such as nanopillars and nanoholes so that the surface of the sensor can be tremendously increased for improved sensing sensitivity. (2) The sensors have so called "flow through" structure so that samples in liquid can be flowed into and out of those nanostructures easily. We have implemented this nove biosensor concept in two major platforms (1) multi-hole polymer/glass capillaries, which can be fabricated using a fiber drawing method. (2) nanopillar structures fabricated on silicon wafer using the nanoimprinting technology.  In our project, we first carried out theoretical calculataion to estimate how much the sensing signal is for a layer of biomolecules deposited onto the surface of the nanostructures and contrast this signal to the signal generated by a conventional biosensor that has only flat surface. 10-100 fold increase in the sensivitiy can  be obtained. Then we fabricated both capillary and nanopillar based biosensors. After this we integrated the sensors with home-made microfluidics for sample and reagent delivery. Finally, we tested those sensors using actual biomolecules.  We have published a few papers based on the outcomes from the project. Two patents were also filed. In addition, we went through the NSF i-Corps program in order to commercialize this technology. Later a start-up company was formed.       Last Modified: 10/31/2016       Submitted by: Xudong Fan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
