<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Hidden Light of Antarctica</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter West</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Hidden Light of Antarctica is a photographic project that will explore the visual effects of ultraviolet and infrared light waves on the landscape of Antarctica. Since ultraviolet and infrared light waves are outside the visible spectrum, these photographs will reveal ?hidden? light. The artist will collaborate with an atmospheric chemist who is developing a long-term record of boundary-layer ozone flux through the investigation of bromine compounds in the Ross Island region. She will compare her photographs taken daily with the data results collected by the scientist and her team to determine if the daily ozone fluctuation can be perceived visually. Combined, these diverse approaches to the exploration of ozone depletion, global warming, and climate change will bring fresh perspectives and expanded insights to these subjects. The resulting images will have their own aesthetic qualities with a direct connection to science that will make them unique. This project will result in a series of photographs, a monograph, and an installation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1158620</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Tuft</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane H Tuft</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>9176261190</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tuft                    Diane          H</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100117055</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tuft                    Diane          H]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100117055</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5294</Code>
<Text>Antarctic Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em><strong>The Hidden Light of Antarctica</strong></p> <p>In 2012 I was awarded a National Science Foundation Artists and Writers grant to photograph the visual effects of light beyond our visible spectrum (infrared and ultraviolet) on the landscape of Antarctica. During my six weeks of living at McMurdo Station, I was able to travel throughout the Ross Dependency and to the South Pole to capture this light in various locations and in different climate conditions. I was also able to talk with several science teams about their research and incorporate some of these research projects into my final anaylsis of Antarctica's landscape.</p> <p>The results of my work have been exhibited at Marlborough Gallery in New York City, Bloomberg Philanthropies, and now are at The Bruce Museum in Greenwich, Connecticut. I hope to continue exhibiting my work in various venues throughout the country in order to reach a broader audience.</p> <p>I have also published a book in conjunction with this work, <em>Gondwana; Images of an Ancient Land,</em> which not only highlights these images but also incorporates four essays, Air, Light, Water and Earth.</p> <p>The essays describe how these elements have shaped Antarctica's landscape of the past and how these elements continue to affect its landscape.</p> <p>While in Antarctica, I created a day to day journal that would record my travels during my six weeks. The journal is now a blog which can be viewed at: gondwanabook.com</p> <p>The photographs attached illustrate some of the elements that have affected Antarctica's landscape.&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Cosmic Surge</em> and <em>Ultraviolet Reflections</em> are great examples of the visual effect of infrared and ultraviolet light waves on Antarctica's landcape.</p> <p><em>Tyndall Figures</em>, captures the gasses that have been trapped in the meromicitc lakes of the dry valleys of Antarcica.</p> <p><em>Snow Grains, South Pole</em> illustrates the lack of reflectivity in the dry cold snow of the south pole.</p> <p>The harsh katabotic and circumpolar winds of Antarctica shape its landscape.&nbsp; <em>Wind Formation, Lower Victoria Glacier </em>and <em>Diamond Dust and Sea Ice</em> are examples of this effect on Antarctica's landscape.</p> <p>Antarctica is a continent that has been frozen in time. Millions of years of past atmospheres have been trapped in its landscape. By sudying these past atmospheres scientists can hope to predict how future atmospheres will affect life on earth.</p> <p>I hope to continue my photographic exploration of the effects of the enviorment the earth's landscape.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/05/2014<br>      Modified by: Diane&nbsp;H&nbsp;Tuft</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1158620/1158620_10201851_1415205898594_CosmicSurge,LakeVanda_2282-17--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1158620/1158620_10201851_1415205898594_CosmicSurge,LakeVanda_2282-17--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cosmic Surge, Lake Vanda"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1158620/1158620_10201851_1415205898594_CosmicSurge,LakeVanda_2282-17--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cosmic Surge, Lake Vanda"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[                                 The Hidden Light of Antarctica  In 2012 I was awarded a National Science Foundation Artists and Writers grant to photograph the visual effects of light beyond our visible spectrum (infrared and ultraviolet) on the landscape of Antarctica. During my six weeks of living at McMurdo Station, I was able to travel throughout the Ross Dependency and to the South Pole to capture this light in various locations and in different climate conditions. I was also able to talk with several science teams about their research and incorporate some of these research projects into my final anaylsis of Antarctica's landscape.  The results of my work have been exhibited at Marlborough Gallery in New York City, Bloomberg Philanthropies, and now are at The Bruce Museum in Greenwich, Connecticut. I hope to continue exhibiting my work in various venues throughout the country in order to reach a broader audience.  I have also published a book in conjunction with this work, Gondwana; Images of an Ancient Land, which not only highlights these images but also incorporates four essays, Air, Light, Water and Earth.  The essays describe how these elements have shaped Antarctica's landscape of the past and how these elements continue to affect its landscape.  While in Antarctica, I created a day to day journal that would record my travels during my six weeks. The journal is now a blog which can be viewed at: gondwanabook.com  The photographs attached illustrate some of the elements that have affected Antarctica's landscape.   Cosmic Surge and Ultraviolet Reflections are great examples of the visual effect of infrared and ultraviolet light waves on Antarctica's landcape.  Tyndall Figures, captures the gasses that have been trapped in the meromicitc lakes of the dry valleys of Antarcica.  Snow Grains, South Pole illustrates the lack of reflectivity in the dry cold snow of the south pole.  The harsh katabotic and circumpolar winds of Antarctica shape its landscape.  Wind Formation, Lower Victoria Glacier and Diamond Dust and Sea Ice are examples of this effect on Antarctica's landscape.  Antarctica is a continent that has been frozen in time. Millions of years of past atmospheres have been trapped in its landscape. By sudying these past atmospheres scientists can hope to predict how future atmospheres will affect life on earth.  I hope to continue my photographic exploration of the effects of the enviorment the earth's landscape.             Last Modified: 11/05/2014       Submitted by: Diane H Tuft]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
