<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cell-type Specific Strategies for Genome Maintenance</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>708841.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>708841</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Cone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kccone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924967</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Broken chromosomes are exceptionally dangerous to the cell, as a single break can result in the simultaneous loss of hundreds of genes. For this reason, all organisms can detect even a single double-strand break (DSB), initiating a response that includes the induction of repair, the arrest of cell division, changes in developmental fate, and in some cases programmed cell death (PCD).  These responses vary from organism to organism, and with cell type.  The cell-type specificity of damage response has not been well characterized in any system, in spite of its importance. Recent advances make it feasible to simultaneously measure changes in the transcription levels of every gene.  Plants exhibit a robust transcriptional response to DSBs, involving the induction or suppression of thousands of genes.  New technologies also allow purification of nuclei from specific cell types.  Combining "transcriptomic" and phenotypic analysis will increase understanding of the role of transcriptional regulation in the repair and tolerance of DSBs.  The transcriptional response in a small and specialized population of cells within the plant which undergo PCD in response to breaks will be compared to that of surrounding cells that do not die in spite of experiencing the same DNA-damaging treatment.  This approach will allow identification of genes required for break-induced programmed cell death, providing insights into the mechanism of the process and markers for early and late steps in the induction of PCD in plants.  Several transcription factors are also induced by chromosomal breaks. Using mutants defective in these regulatory genes, the subroutines within the response and their biological significance will be investigated.&lt;br/&gt;Finally, the natural source of chromosomal breaks that makes this response selectively advantageous in plants is unknown.  Recent work indicates that both the desiccation experienced during seed storage and damage induced by growth in acidic, metal-rich soils provoke the transcriptional response described above, and this hypothesis will be investigated further.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:  This project will contribute to the understanding of cell cycle regulation and the mechanisms of programmed cell death in plants.  Novel assays for genomic stability in plants and exploration of potential natural sources of DSBs in plants should result in findings of relevance to agriculture.  Undergraduates, a graduate student, and a postdoctoral scholar will be employed and trained through this grant, and will be recruited from a very diverse population.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1158443</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Britt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne B Britt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abbritt@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307520699</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000120662</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Plant Biology]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~708841</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Animals are known to invoke a programmed cell death (PCD) response to DNA damage. &nbsp;DNA double strand breaks (DSBs) are perceived by all cells and, in animals, the persistence of DSBs is essentially employed as a "proxy" for the induction of cancer-promoting mutations (as mutations <em>per se</em> cannot be detected). &nbsp;Thus, in animals, cells carrying a certain threshold level of DSBs are destroyed, via a programmed response that clearly contributes to tumor suppression. &nbsp;</p> <p>Plants are inherently less susceptible than animals to the lethal effects of cancer. &nbsp;Deregulated plant cells cannot metastasize, as all plant cells are enclosed by a rigid cell wall. Plant development is also more plastic than that of animals (for example, entire organs are easily regenerated in response to herbivory) and tumors are easily tolerated. &nbsp;This innate resistance to the potentially lethal effects of cancer may explain the lack of DSB-induced PCD in most plant cell types; such a pathway may have no advantageous effect vs. the alternative of allowing a (potentially) mutant cell to continue to contribute to the organism as a whole.</p> <p>DSB-induced PCD has been observed, however, in specific cell types in plants: the stem cell niche of the apical meristems.&nbsp; These are cells that divide to produce the tissues of the root and shoot, and also signal their presence to the rest of the root tip, maintaining the differentiated state of the meristem.&nbsp; The biological significance of this cell-type specific death has remained an open question.&nbsp; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Our work suggests that this response reflects a developmental, rather than anti-carcinogenic, response to DNA damage.</span>&nbsp; We show, at high doses of damage, that the lack of DDR response results in a permanent arrest of root growth. In contrast, in damage response-proficient plants, we observe a rapid (within hours of irradiation) developmental response that includes the loss of cell-type specific markers (dedifferentiation), the induction of death specifically in cells that normally organize the root tip meristem, and the induction of a transcription factor that drives cell division in the surviving neighboring cells.&nbsp; The net result is the programmed excision of the stem cell niche and the subsequent induction of regeneration of the root apical meristem- similar to the response inducted when the root tip is excised. We suggest that this response arose with the evolution of land plants, many of which (including all seed plants) experience a desiccated phase of the life cycle. Cycles of desiccation and rehydration induce DSBs in DNA, and damage response is routinely observed in germinating seeds. The developmental response described here would enable a highly damaged embryo to regenerate the root tip meristem from via transdifferentiation from neighboring mitotically competent cells.&nbsp; Thus DSB response, in plants, triggers a program of organ regeneration.</p> <p>This work also has practical applications.</p> <p>Other labs have recently demonstrated that the presence of DNA double stand breaks triggers inhibition of germination through the damage response pathway under investigation here. &nbsp;Rapid seed germination (termed seed vigor) is a desirable trait in crop plants that rely on simultaneous growth of all plants to facilitate simultaneous, single-pass harvest. Thus inhibition of part or all of this response (for example, through the use of response-inhibiting chemicals) might promote uniformity of germination.</p> <p>Two postdoctoral scholars, a PhD student, a Masters degree student, and 10 Undergraduates were trained during this project. The more senior students are continuing to work in their chosen fields, at Universities or in Industry.&nbsp; Many of the undergraduates have gone on to graduate school or professional school.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;B&nbsp;Britt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Animals are known to invoke a programmed cell death (PCD) response to DNA damage.  DNA double strand breaks (DSBs) are perceived by all cells and, in animals, the persistence of DSBs is essentially employed as a "proxy" for the induction of cancer-promoting mutations (as mutations per se cannot be detected).  Thus, in animals, cells carrying a certain threshold level of DSBs are destroyed, via a programmed response that clearly contributes to tumor suppression.    Plants are inherently less susceptible than animals to the lethal effects of cancer.  Deregulated plant cells cannot metastasize, as all plant cells are enclosed by a rigid cell wall. Plant development is also more plastic than that of animals (for example, entire organs are easily regenerated in response to herbivory) and tumors are easily tolerated.  This innate resistance to the potentially lethal effects of cancer may explain the lack of DSB-induced PCD in most plant cell types; such a pathway may have no advantageous effect vs. the alternative of allowing a (potentially) mutant cell to continue to contribute to the organism as a whole.  DSB-induced PCD has been observed, however, in specific cell types in plants: the stem cell niche of the apical meristems.  These are cells that divide to produce the tissues of the root and shoot, and also signal their presence to the rest of the root tip, maintaining the differentiated state of the meristem.  The biological significance of this cell-type specific death has remained an open question.  Our work suggests that this response reflects a developmental, rather than anti-carcinogenic, response to DNA damage.  We show, at high doses of damage, that the lack of DDR response results in a permanent arrest of root growth. In contrast, in damage response-proficient plants, we observe a rapid (within hours of irradiation) developmental response that includes the loss of cell-type specific markers (dedifferentiation), the induction of death specifically in cells that normally organize the root tip meristem, and the induction of a transcription factor that drives cell division in the surviving neighboring cells.  The net result is the programmed excision of the stem cell niche and the subsequent induction of regeneration of the root apical meristem- similar to the response inducted when the root tip is excised. We suggest that this response arose with the evolution of land plants, many of which (including all seed plants) experience a desiccated phase of the life cycle. Cycles of desiccation and rehydration induce DSBs in DNA, and damage response is routinely observed in germinating seeds. The developmental response described here would enable a highly damaged embryo to regenerate the root tip meristem from via transdifferentiation from neighboring mitotically competent cells.  Thus DSB response, in plants, triggers a program of organ regeneration.  This work also has practical applications.  Other labs have recently demonstrated that the presence of DNA double stand breaks triggers inhibition of germination through the damage response pathway under investigation here.  Rapid seed germination (termed seed vigor) is a desirable trait in crop plants that rely on simultaneous growth of all plants to facilitate simultaneous, single-pass harvest. Thus inhibition of part or all of this response (for example, through the use of response-inhibiting chemicals) might promote uniformity of germination.  Two postdoctoral scholars, a PhD student, a Masters degree student, and 10 Undergraduates were trained during this project. The more senior students are continuing to work in their chosen fields, at Universities or in Industry.  Many of the undergraduates have gone on to graduate school or professional school.                Last Modified: 08/28/2016       Submitted by: Anne B Britt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
