<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Atomic-scale alloys as energy- and cost-efficient catalysts for fuels and chemicals production</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>349999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>349999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Triantafillos Mountziaris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding the molecular-scale adsorption and dissociation behavior of a number of small molecules on catalytically relevant surfaces is crucial for the design of better working catalysts. More efficient, low-cost processes for the production of fuels and chemicals may be developed as a result. Professors Maria Flytzani-Stephanopoulos, Georgios Kyriakou and Charles Sykes form a team at Tufts University, Medford, MA which is receiving an award to utilize their expertise in heterogeneous catalysis and surface science to identify the factors that lead to enhanced catalytic activity and high selectivity of single-atom alloys, particularly aimed at small molecule activations. Their aim is to develop materials and methodologies that will enable wide ranging academic, technical and industrial applications of these catalysts for heterogeneous hydrogenations. The approach is to use a minority metal component such as Pd present as isolated atoms in another metal like Cu, such that the former induces different catalytic properties on the latter. In this example, the Pd atoms can serve to dissociate H2 molecules, and spill over atomic hydrogen to the host metal. Hence the Pd atoms serve as conduits of H atoms to the Cu surface which can now facilitate hydrogenation reactions with gaseous H2, reactions which have been impossible in the previous literature. This novel catalyst system not only reduces the higher temperatures typically required to activate H2 on Cu catalysts and hence reduces waste heat in products but also allows for more selective hydrogenations to proceed at lower temperatures without decomposition observed on the pure metals. In addition to these benefits, alloy particles in which the expensive, active element is atomically dispersed should dramatically reduce the cost of the catalyst materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interdisciplinary nature of the project will clearly impact the education of graduate students and postgraduate fellows at Tufts. Extensive training of young researchers at Brookhaven National Laboratory is planned in the project. A significant number of women students comprise the PI and co-PIs groups, and they will participate in some aspects of the project, while the Tufts summer scholars program for undergraduates will be used to recruit other under- represented groups. To increase dissemination, existing websites of the Nano Catalysis and Energy lab and the Surface Science Sykes lab will add video clips and relevant information material on this project to promote this work both as an educational resource and a recruiting tool.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1159882</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Flytzani-Stephanopoulos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria Flytzani-Stephanopoulos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mflytzan@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273048</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000263768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>E. Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Sykes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>E. Charles H Sykes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Charles.Sykes@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273773</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000216480</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georgios</FirstName>
<LastName>Kyriakou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georgios Kyriakou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Georgios.kyriakou@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273417</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000586220</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021555811</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Colby Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>044E</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~349999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this project was&nbsp; to identify the factors that lead to enhanced catalytic activity and high selectivity of single-atom alloys (SAAs) prepared by imbedding precious metal (Pd, Pt) atoms in the surface of Cu or Au metals. We have found that SAAs behave as bifunctional catalysts with facile dissociation of hydrogen on the precious metal atoms and hydrogen spillover to the majority metal surface on which weak binding of reaction intermediates makes for an efficient and selective catalyst. A new generation of catalysts with one Pt or Pd atom for approximately every 100 Cu atoms can be developed for application to fuel cells, catalytic converters and the production of industrial chemicals.</p> <p>The project used the complementary expertise of two groups at Tufts University headed by the PI (Flytzani-Stephanopoulos) and the co-PI (Sykes) in the areas of heterogeneous catalysis and surface science, respectively. The similarity of findings from the surface science work conducted in UHV over model catalyst surfaces, e.g. PtCu(111), and from the catalysis work in flow reactors operated at ambient pressures over supported SAA nanoparticle catalysts, e.g. Pt<sub>1</sub>Cu, is a major outcome of this investigation. This was true for selective hydrogenation reactions, namely, butadiene to butene and phenylacetylene to styrene, as well as for the selective dehydrogenation of methanol to formaldehyde and hydrogen. We reported the first catalytic results and the first images of Pt<sub>1</sub>Cu nanoparticles prepared as analogs to PtCu(111) SAAs with facile, solution chemistry methods. Advanced characterization techniques like EXAFS, atomic resolution microscopy, STM/STS, and TPD were used to shed light on the mechanistic aspects of the reaction and to guide catalyst design.&nbsp; At the end of the interdisciplinary effort, we have answered key questions regarding the activity and selectivity of a variety of single atom alloys, which can pave the way for a new generation of bifunctional catalysts that operate in a different way to most currently available formulations.</p> <p>There are several other tangible benefits for each of the disciplines involved in the project: new methods for catalyst synthesis, new materials properties specific to the nanoscale of importance to sensors and fuel cell components, and new catalyst designs for low-cost fuels and chemicals production. An overall benefit is a template for rational design of catalysts derived from the interdisciplinary activities of the project.</p> <p>The interdisciplinary nature of the project has clearly impacted the education of graduate students and postgraduate fellows in chemistry and chemical engineering. &nbsp;An equal number of women and men from the PI and co-PI&rsquo;s research groups have participated in various aspects of the project; and in joint bi-weekly group meetings. Extensive training of young researchers at the Argonne, Oak Ridge, and Brookhaven National Laboratories has also taken place. The dissemination of the work has followed the normal channels of publications and presentations at national and international forums. The Sykes lab has also added video clips and relevant information material on this project on the web to promote the work both as an educational resource and a recruiting tool.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;Flytzani-Stephanopoulos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/115988...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project was  to identify the factors that lead to enhanced catalytic activity and high selectivity of single-atom alloys (SAAs) prepared by imbedding precious metal (Pd, Pt) atoms in the surface of Cu or Au metals. We have found that SAAs behave as bifunctional catalysts with facile dissociation of hydrogen on the precious metal atoms and hydrogen spillover to the majority metal surface on which weak binding of reaction intermediates makes for an efficient and selective catalyst. A new generation of catalysts with one Pt or Pd atom for approximately every 100 Cu atoms can be developed for application to fuel cells, catalytic converters and the production of industrial chemicals.  The project used the complementary expertise of two groups at Tufts University headed by the PI (Flytzani-Stephanopoulos) and the co-PI (Sykes) in the areas of heterogeneous catalysis and surface science, respectively. The similarity of findings from the surface science work conducted in UHV over model catalyst surfaces, e.g. PtCu(111), and from the catalysis work in flow reactors operated at ambient pressures over supported SAA nanoparticle catalysts, e.g. Pt1Cu, is a major outcome of this investigation. This was true for selective hydrogenation reactions, namely, butadiene to butene and phenylacetylene to styrene, as well as for the selective dehydrogenation of methanol to formaldehyde and hydrogen. We reported the first catalytic results and the first images of Pt1Cu nanoparticles prepared as analogs to PtCu(111) SAAs with facile, solution chemistry methods. Advanced characterization techniques like EXAFS, atomic resolution microscopy, STM/STS, and TPD were used to shed light on the mechanistic aspects of the reaction and to guide catalyst design.  At the end of the interdisciplinary effort, we have answered key questions regarding the activity and selectivity of a variety of single atom alloys, which can pave the way for a new generation of bifunctional catalysts that operate in a different way to most currently available formulations.  There are several other tangible benefits for each of the disciplines involved in the project: new methods for catalyst synthesis, new materials properties specific to the nanoscale of importance to sensors and fuel cell components, and new catalyst designs for low-cost fuels and chemicals production. An overall benefit is a template for rational design of catalysts derived from the interdisciplinary activities of the project.  The interdisciplinary nature of the project has clearly impacted the education of graduate students and postgraduate fellows in chemistry and chemical engineering.  An equal number of women and men from the PI and co-PIÆs research groups have participated in various aspects of the project; and in joint bi-weekly group meetings. Extensive training of young researchers at the Argonne, Oak Ridge, and Brookhaven National Laboratories has also taken place. The dissemination of the work has followed the normal channels of publications and presentations at national and international forums. The Sykes lab has also added video clips and relevant information material on this project on the web to promote the work both as an educational resource and a recruiting tool.       Last Modified: 05/29/2016       Submitted by: Maria Flytzani-Stephanopoulos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
