<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRFP: Determination of Solvent Effects and Interactions of Silica-Polypeptide Colloidal Particles by Small-Angle Neutron Scattering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>168200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>168200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdudka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The International Research Fellowship Program enables U.S. scientists and engineers to conduct nine to twenty-four months of research abroad. The program's awards provide opportunities for joint research, and the use of unique or complementary facilities, expertise and experimental conditions abroad. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will support a twenty-four-month research fellowship by Dr. Javoris V. Hollingsworth to work with Prof. Charles Han at the Institute of Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Science in Beijing, China. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this research project is to investigate the solvent effects, structural variations and the resulting shell interpenetration of silica-polypeptide colloidal particles. These particles are composed of a silica core, which may or may not possess a superparamagnetic inclusion (Co or Fe3O4). The shell consists of polypeptides covalently bonded to the core. Depending on the properties of the attached polymers, the particles can exhibit solubility in water or organic solvents. Also, the polypeptide coil-helix transition is a useful feature for modifying the surface configuration and particle interactions. These particles are candidates for several potential applications such as responsive materials, chiral separations, catalysis, colloidal crystallization, biomimetic membrane supports and drug delivery systems. A number of features about the particles have been described-for example, they can form colloidal crystals'but very little is known about the dynamic response of the particles under applied fields. An overall goal is to understand these properties and concurrently the findings will have a positive impact on the approach used to design novel responsive materials and devices.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Small angle neutron scattering (SANS) studies are performed at the Neutron Scattering Laboratory, China Institute of Atomic Energy. This SANS device is one of the most recently built neutron systems in the world. After gaining experience with similar particles of interest developed by the host group, the general objective is to investigate shell structural properties as the particles are brought together under applied magnetic fields using SANS, coupled with dynamic light scattering (DLS). The combination of SANS and DLS is ideal for this study because both techniques permit real-time monitoring of structure variations. Particle interactions are detectable by SANS using deuterated and hydrogenous polypeptides covalently attached to silica cores. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the usual development of international partnerships, publications and presentations, the PI will adapt his acquired skills to U.S. neutron sources. This continued research endeavor will contribute to the advancement of materials science by providing insight on microstructural and responsive properties of versatile core-shell colloidal systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1159189</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Javoris</FirstName>
<LastName>Hollingsworth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Javoris V Hollingsworth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7139425045</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597518</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hollingsworth           Javoris        V</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708208310</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hollingsworth           Javoris        V]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708208310</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5956</Code>
<Text>IRFP-Inter Res Fellowship Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5956</Code>
<Text>IRFP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~168200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI has completed his NSF postdoctoral research project titled, "Determination of Solvent Effects and Interactions of Silica-Polypeptide Colloidal Particles by Small-Angle Neutron Scattering". His objective was to understand the fundamental properties of hybrid particles under various experimental conditions. This work was primarily performed at the Institute of Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Sciences (ICCAS) in Beijing, P.R. China in the research laboratory of Charles C. Han.</p> <p>During this experience, the PI gained vast knowledge about scattering techniques and polymer physics by working with research scientists at ICCAS and the China Spallation Neutron Source (CNCS). For instance, to characterize the size, size distrubtion, and dynamic properties of the colloidal particles, static/dynamic light scattering was used. &nbsp;In addition, the PI also received training on using transmission electron microscopy (TEM) to observe the prepared hybrid particles. Before the conclusion of the research period, the PI became an efficient and independent instrument user. Such skills will be transferred to his future academic research endeavors in the U.S.</p> <p>While performing small-angle neutron scattering (SANS) at CNCS, the PI learned about the principles and best practices for the technique. This particular training opportunity was provided under the supervision of expert, Dr. Cheng He. Occassionally, technical issues were encountered at CNCS, which presented many chances to learn more about the innerworks of the equipment while troubleshooting. The PI also traveled to observe other systems and acquire additional neutron scattering data. For instance, he also performed SANS combined with rheology to better understand the dynamics of complex fluid systems.</p> <p>The gathered results and findings were disseminated in peer-reviewed journals and at scientific meetings. Certainly, this unique opportunity allowed the PI to network with researchers from all around the world. As a result, he has established key partnerships and networks abroad, which will contribute to the advancement of science . &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Javoris&nbsp;V&nbsp;Hollingsworth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1159189/1159189_10196974_1465928513458_2014-06-0922.04.49--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1159189/1159189_10196974_1465928513458_2014-06-0922.04.49--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photo with researchers at conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1159189/1159189_10196974_1465928513458_2014-06-0922.04.49--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photo with researchers at conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is a photo of the PI and two graduate research students at the International Symposium on Polymer Physics in Nanjing, China.</div> <div class="imageCredit">NA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Javoris&nbsp;V&nbsp;Hollingsworth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photo with researchers at conference</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1159189/1159189_10196974_1465927025656_2013-12-2014.15.26--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1159189/1159189_10196974_1465927025656_2013-12-2014.15.26--rgov-800width.jpg" title="TEM Training"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1159189/...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI has completed his NSF postdoctoral research project titled, "Determination of Solvent Effects and Interactions of Silica-Polypeptide Colloidal Particles by Small-Angle Neutron Scattering". His objective was to understand the fundamental properties of hybrid particles under various experimental conditions. This work was primarily performed at the Institute of Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Sciences (ICCAS) in Beijing, P.R. China in the research laboratory of Charles C. Han.  During this experience, the PI gained vast knowledge about scattering techniques and polymer physics by working with research scientists at ICCAS and the China Spallation Neutron Source (CNCS). For instance, to characterize the size, size distrubtion, and dynamic properties of the colloidal particles, static/dynamic light scattering was used.  In addition, the PI also received training on using transmission electron microscopy (TEM) to observe the prepared hybrid particles. Before the conclusion of the research period, the PI became an efficient and independent instrument user. Such skills will be transferred to his future academic research endeavors in the U.S.  While performing small-angle neutron scattering (SANS) at CNCS, the PI learned about the principles and best practices for the technique. This particular training opportunity was provided under the supervision of expert, Dr. Cheng He. Occassionally, technical issues were encountered at CNCS, which presented many chances to learn more about the innerworks of the equipment while troubleshooting. The PI also traveled to observe other systems and acquire additional neutron scattering data. For instance, he also performed SANS combined with rheology to better understand the dynamics of complex fluid systems.  The gathered results and findings were disseminated in peer-reviewed journals and at scientific meetings. Certainly, this unique opportunity allowed the PI to network with researchers from all around the world. As a result, he has established key partnerships and networks abroad, which will contribute to the advancement of science .            Last Modified: 06/14/2016       Submitted by: Javoris V Hollingsworth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
