<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: In and Around Theory X</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>466862.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>466862</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the last generation the four-dimensional classical self-dual Yang-Mills equations and their dimensional reductions have had profound consequences for algebraic geometry, differential geometry, low-dimensional topology, integrable systems, and nonlinear PDE.  Now a family of six-dimensional quantum field theories is emerging as an object of acute mathematical interest.  This Focused Research Group brings together researchers working in diverse parts of mathematics and physics to study these theories.  They originally arose as limits of string theories and are usually called 'superconformal (2,0)-theories' to call attention to their symmetries.  The simpler appellation 'Theory X' emphasizes how little is known.  The projects undertaken here have two overall goals.  First, we will make inroads on the structure of Theory X by applying the detailed and profound mathematical understanding of topological and conformal quantum field theories obtained over the past 25 years.  Second, we will use expected properties of Theory X and its compactifications to lower dimensions to deduce new conjectures and new organizing principles in geometric representation theory.  The rapidly developing web of interactions between the six-dimensional quantum Theory X and a host of central topics in twenty-first century geometry, topology, and geometric representation theory indicates that we are seeing the beginnings of a new revolution, one in which Theory X plays the dominant physical role. Progress towards unraveling its structure and its consequences will have broad ramifications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Physics has long fueled developments in mathematics, and the past 30 years have been a particularly fruitful period.  The depth of mathematics which enters fundamental physical theories has steadily intensified, and at the same time the structure and predictions of these theories have had increasingly profound impacts on mathematics.  This project is one of many efforts to mine this intellectually fertile mix of ideas.  Our pursuit of Theory X will inevitably illuminate a much broader circle of ideas and contribute to the mathematical understanding of contemporary physics.  The work of past generations at the mathematics-physics interface fuels the modern world: our computers, GPS systems, transportation, sophisticated medical tools, and much more owe their existence to basic research in this area which stretches back well over a century.  While we cannot predict how current basic research will impact the future, we can say with certainty that the effect will be far-reaching.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1160461</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Freed</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel S Freed</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dafr@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124717136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000309204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ben-Zvi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David D Ben-Zvi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>benzvi@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124718151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000183201</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Neitzke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Neitzke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrew.neitzke@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172307378</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000543038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787137726</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 7726]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~466862</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Theory X is a mysterious object in theoretical physics which, in addition to its own intrinsic interest, spawns many other theories with profound consequences for both mathematics and physics. &nbsp;This particular project had two aspects. &nbsp;The first is an investigation into the internal structure of Theory X using sophisticated tools from geometry. &nbsp;The second focuses on ramifications of Theory X for geometric representation theory, a cutting edge mathematical study of symmetry. &nbsp;The UT Austin group undertook this effort in conjunction with mathematicians and physicists from several other universities. &nbsp;We made progress on several fronts. &nbsp;On the formal side we applied ideas in several areas of mathematics to develop structures which apply far beyond Theory X, in both quantum field theories and condensed matter systems. &nbsp;In the other direction we extracted several new mathematical ideas from Theory X and its cousins. &nbsp;These include advances in geometry as well as in geometric representation theory, the latter more algebraic in nature. &nbsp;<br />This interplay between mathematics and physics is a small part of a large vigorous enterprise whose current period of activity has been thriving for several decades now. &nbsp;The sustained deep interaction has already left its mark on both fields, and promises to do much more in the future. Applications of such basic research beyond the theoretical are impossible to predict and lie well in the future; the confidence that they will materialize and be important is based on the long history of mathematics and its role in society.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;S&nbsp;Freed</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Theory X is a mysterious object in theoretical physics which, in addition to its own intrinsic interest, spawns many other theories with profound consequences for both mathematics and physics.  This particular project had two aspects.  The first is an investigation into the internal structure of Theory X using sophisticated tools from geometry.  The second focuses on ramifications of Theory X for geometric representation theory, a cutting edge mathematical study of symmetry.  The UT Austin group undertook this effort in conjunction with mathematicians and physicists from several other universities.  We made progress on several fronts.  On the formal side we applied ideas in several areas of mathematics to develop structures which apply far beyond Theory X, in both quantum field theories and condensed matter systems.  In the other direction we extracted several new mathematical ideas from Theory X and its cousins.  These include advances in geometry as well as in geometric representation theory, the latter more algebraic in nature.   This interplay between mathematics and physics is a small part of a large vigorous enterprise whose current period of activity has been thriving for several decades now.  The sustained deep interaction has already left its mark on both fields, and promises to do much more in the future. Applications of such basic research beyond the theoretical are impossible to predict and lie well in the future; the confidence that they will materialize and be important is based on the long history of mathematics and its role in society.        Last Modified: 12/27/2017       Submitted by: Daniel S Freed]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
