<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Fundamental Study of Flow Processes in High-Pressure Torsion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gary Shiflet</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The processing of metals through the application of severe plastic deformation provides an opportunity for achieving exceptional grain refinement.  In high-pressure torsion (HPT), where a disk is subjected to a pressure and concurrent torsional straining, it is often feasible to reduce the grain size of a metallic alloy to the nanometer range (&lt;100 nm).  These ultrafine-grained materials exhibit very high strength and a potential for use in superplastic forming processes.  Experiments will be conducted to address four major issues in HPT processing.  First, experimental parameters that are needed to achieve a fully homogeneous microstructure using HPT will be evaluated.  Second, both experimental and theoretical factors that determine the equilibrium grain sizes achieved in HPT will be investigated.  Third, the origin of unusual flow patterns, including the presence of swirls and vortices, that have been reported in materials processed by HPT will be investigated.  Fourth, HPT will be combined with a surface mechanical attrition treatment (SMAT) to evaluate the opportunity for producing hardened disks that will have considerable use in industrial applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grain size of a polycrystalline metal is a critical parameter because it determines fundamental properties such as strength and flow characteristics.  The processing of metals by high-pressure torsion (HPT) is a relatively new procedure that provides an opportunity for producing bulk metals with extremely small grain sizes.  These metals have a very high strength and also exhibit other attractive properties such as excellent formability and good wear resistance.  The proposed research is designed to investigate some of the fundamental properties of the HPT processing technique with the objective of optimizing the technique so that it can be used to produce materials of interest for industrial applications.  The research group will contain one post-doctoral fellow and at least one student, and they will have an opportunity to participate in a major and important research activity.  We will also collaborate with several international groups in Japan, Brazil and Europe, and this will provide the students with an international experience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1160966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terence</FirstName>
<LastName>Langdon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terence G Langdon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>langdon@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137400491</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463668</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890143</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[837 W. Downey Way STO 315]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The fundamental microstructural parameter of all crystalline materials, both metallic and ceramic, is the grain size.&nbsp; It is now very well established that a small grain size increases the strength of a material and at the same time, if these small grains are reasonably stable when heated to elevated temperatures, there is a potential for using these materials for the procesing of complex shapes using superplastic forming operations.&nbsp; Generally, superplastic flow requires a grain size smaller than about 10 micrometers and the superplastic forming industry usually processes metals having grain sizes of about 5 micrometers.&nbsp; There is at present no simple method for reducing the grain size below about 1 micrometer through conventional thermo-mechanical processing whereby the metallic billet is subjected to combinations of heating and straining.</p> <p>It was shown about 30 years ago that it is feasible to introduce submicrometer or even nanometer grains into bulk metallic solids by applying severe plastic deformation (SPD).&nbsp; This SPD processing entails the severe deformation of the metal using processes in which there are no significant changes in the overall dimensions of the starting material but at the same time there is the imposition of a very high strain.&nbsp; This means that line defects, in the form of dislocations, are introduced into the material and these dislocations can re-arrange and align to form grain boundaries so that the average grain size is reduced.&nbsp; There are several ways to do this but the optimum procedure appears to be high-pressure torsion (HPT) where the sample, in the form of a metallic disk, is subjected simultaneously to a high pressure and torsional straining.</p> <p>Processing by HPT has attracted much interest over the last ten years both within the scientific community and also in industry where it provides an opportunity for producing high-strength products such as the stents and fasteners used in biomedical applications.&nbsp; Nevertheless, there has been an important question concerning the flow processes occurring in HPT during the processing operation.&nbsp; Specifically, there is some evidence that the final grain size may be dictated exclusively by the material and therefore it is impossible to produce even smaller grain sizes, and thus even higher strengths, by manipulating the experimental parameters.</p> <p>We addressed this problem in the present NSF grant by conducting HPT processing under selected conditions on a number of simple pure metals and alloys.&nbsp; We showed in our research that there is no minimum grain size representing a lower limit to the processing operation and instead it is possible to achieve even greater grain refinement by appropriate changes in the processing conditions.&nbsp; These results are important both for contributing to a scientific understanding of the HPT process but also by demonstrating to industry the potential for attaining remarkable strength and superplastic forming capabilities even in relatively simple materials.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Terence&nbsp;G&nbsp;Langdon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The fundamental microstructural parameter of all crystalline materials, both metallic and ceramic, is the grain size.  It is now very well established that a small grain size increases the strength of a material and at the same time, if these small grains are reasonably stable when heated to elevated temperatures, there is a potential for using these materials for the procesing of complex shapes using superplastic forming operations.  Generally, superplastic flow requires a grain size smaller than about 10 micrometers and the superplastic forming industry usually processes metals having grain sizes of about 5 micrometers.  There is at present no simple method for reducing the grain size below about 1 micrometer through conventional thermo-mechanical processing whereby the metallic billet is subjected to combinations of heating and straining.  It was shown about 30 years ago that it is feasible to introduce submicrometer or even nanometer grains into bulk metallic solids by applying severe plastic deformation (SPD).  This SPD processing entails the severe deformation of the metal using processes in which there are no significant changes in the overall dimensions of the starting material but at the same time there is the imposition of a very high strain.  This means that line defects, in the form of dislocations, are introduced into the material and these dislocations can re-arrange and align to form grain boundaries so that the average grain size is reduced.  There are several ways to do this but the optimum procedure appears to be high-pressure torsion (HPT) where the sample, in the form of a metallic disk, is subjected simultaneously to a high pressure and torsional straining.  Processing by HPT has attracted much interest over the last ten years both within the scientific community and also in industry where it provides an opportunity for producing high-strength products such as the stents and fasteners used in biomedical applications.  Nevertheless, there has been an important question concerning the flow processes occurring in HPT during the processing operation.  Specifically, there is some evidence that the final grain size may be dictated exclusively by the material and therefore it is impossible to produce even smaller grain sizes, and thus even higher strengths, by manipulating the experimental parameters.  We addressed this problem in the present NSF grant by conducting HPT processing under selected conditions on a number of simple pure metals and alloys.  We showed in our research that there is no minimum grain size representing a lower limit to the processing operation and instead it is possible to achieve even greater grain refinement by appropriate changes in the processing conditions.  These results are important both for contributing to a scientific understanding of the HPT process but also by demonstrating to industry the potential for attaining remarkable strength and superplastic forming capabilities even in relatively simple materials.          Last Modified: 10/31/2017       Submitted by: Terence G Langdon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
