<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHF: Medium: Collaborative Research: Regression Testing Techniques for Real-world Software Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>324883.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>332333</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sol Greenspan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgreensp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927841</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Reports estimate that regression testing, which is the activity of retesting a software system after it has been modified, can consume up to 50% of the cost of software development and maintenance. Although there are many techniques that can reduce the cost of regression testing, most of them do not account for important characteristics of modern systems, such as product lines, web applications, service-oriented architectures, and cloud-based applications.  These systems are increasingly heterogeneous: they may come from different sources, may be written in different languages, and may be accessible in different formats (e.g., source code, binary code, or through remote interfaces). Moreover, modern software is often environment dependent: its behavior can be affected not only by changes in the code, but also by changes in its complex environment (e.g., databases, configuration files, and network layouts).  Because most existing regression-testing techniques do not account for these characteristics, the application of these techniques can result in inadequately tested software, problems during maintenance, and ultimately poor software quality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this research is to go beyond the state of the art in regression testing by defining novel approaches that can be applied to modern, real-world software and account for its characteristics and complexity. To achieve this goal, the research will first extend analysis techniques on which regression-testing approaches rely, such as system modeling, version differencing, coverage analysis, and impact analysis. The research will then leverage these fundamental techniques to develop, evaluate with industrial partners, and make available a family of regression testing techniques and tools that can (1) build comprehensive models of heterogeneous, environment-dependent software systems, (2) evolve these models throughout the systems' lifetimes, and (3) analyze the changes across models to understand their effects on the systems' behavior and retest them effectively and efficiently. The impact of the research will be manyfold. First, the rigorous, transformative, and highly automated techniques developed will help improve the quality of today's large, complex software systems, thus benefitting all segments of society that depend on software. Second, the release of the produced tools and infrastructure will let other researchers and practitioners build on our results, advancing knowledge and understanding. Finally, the research findings will be integrated in curriculum materials that will be made available to the broader scientific community, which will help prepare a globally competitive workforce and further benefit society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1161767</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Myra</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Myra B Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcohen@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152948305</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000124813</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685880115</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~81231</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~243652</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~7450</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research is to go beyond the state of the art in regression testing by defining novel approaches that can be applied to modern, real-world software and account for its characteristics and complexity. To achieve this goal, the research extends analysis techniques on which regression-testing approaches rely, such as system modeling, version differencing, coverage analysis, and impact analysis. The research leverages these fundamental techniques to develop, evaluate with industrial partners, and make available a family of regression testing techniques and tools that can (1) build comprehensive models of heterogeneous, environment-dependent software systems, (2) evolve these models throughout the systems' lifetimes, and (3) analyze the changes across models to understand their effects on the systems' behavior and retest them effectively and efficiently.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp; Throughout the course of this grant we have developed several novel regression testing techniques.&nbsp; We have created search algorithms for test generation in several different domains including the desktop, GUI and embedded systems. We have built genetic algorithms for reverse engineering feature models and have created novel failure avoidance techniques, which are informed by configuration failure history across a distributed set of deployments over time. We have evaluated the impact of configurations on repeatability for testing, and have shown that this requires strict control of the software environment. We have also examined several practical aspects of real-world regression testing such as the structure and life cycle of the configuration space of both open source and industrial software and have discovered inconsistencies between the configuration models and code. Finally, we have extended our work to the emerging domains of synthetic and systems biology, applying regression testing beyond its normal reach.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: During the course of this grant we have involved (and published papers with) both graduate and undergraduate students on this research, some of whom are from underrepresented groups.&nbsp; The research has led to multiple MS/PHD theses and several of these students have continued their graduate education or become faculty members. Students working on this project have also had the opportunity to attend conferences and present their research to the broader community.&nbsp;&nbsp; We have had industrial partners on some of this work and the PI has given several invited talks. Some of the techniques developed in this proposal have been applied to systems biology and published on websites used by computational biologists. Furthermore some undergraduates working on this grant have participated in the International Genetic Engineered Machine Competition (iGEM).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Myra&nbsp;B&nbsp;Cohen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research is to go beyond the state of the art in regression testing by defining novel approaches that can be applied to modern, real-world software and account for its characteristics and complexity. To achieve this goal, the research extends analysis techniques on which regression-testing approaches rely, such as system modeling, version differencing, coverage analysis, and impact analysis. The research leverages these fundamental techniques to develop, evaluate with industrial partners, and make available a family of regression testing techniques and tools that can (1) build comprehensive models of heterogeneous, environment-dependent software systems, (2) evolve these models throughout the systems' lifetimes, and (3) analyze the changes across models to understand their effects on the systems' behavior and retest them effectively and efficiently.  Intellectual Merit:  Throughout the course of this grant we have developed several novel regression testing techniques.  We have created search algorithms for test generation in several different domains including the desktop, GUI and embedded systems. We have built genetic algorithms for reverse engineering feature models and have created novel failure avoidance techniques, which are informed by configuration failure history across a distributed set of deployments over time. We have evaluated the impact of configurations on repeatability for testing, and have shown that this requires strict control of the software environment. We have also examined several practical aspects of real-world regression testing such as the structure and life cycle of the configuration space of both open source and industrial software and have discovered inconsistencies between the configuration models and code. Finally, we have extended our work to the emerging domains of synthetic and systems biology, applying regression testing beyond its normal reach.  Broader Impacts: During the course of this grant we have involved (and published papers with) both graduate and undergraduate students on this research, some of whom are from underrepresented groups.  The research has led to multiple MS/PHD theses and several of these students have continued their graduate education or become faculty members. Students working on this project have also had the opportunity to attend conferences and present their research to the broader community.   We have had industrial partners on some of this work and the PI has given several invited talks. Some of the techniques developed in this proposal have been applied to systems biology and published on websites used by computational biologists. Furthermore some undergraduates working on this grant have participated in the International Genetic Engineered Machine Competition (iGEM).       Last Modified: 10/27/2017       Submitted by: Myra B Cohen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
