<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strongly-Coupled Dusty Plasmas</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>720000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>720000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a fundamental experimental study of waves, transport, nonequilibrium fluctuations, and viscoelastic behavior in strongly coupled dusty plasmas. Strongly coupled plasmas are ionized gases in which the interparticle potential energy is greater than the particle kinetic energy. They behave like a crystal or liquid, unlike the more familiar weakly coupled plasmas, which behave like a gas. A dusty plasma is a four-component mixture of micron-size particles of solid matter, electrons, ions, and neutral gas. The solid particles become charged due to collecting electrons and ions. The electric field in a plasma sheath can levitate these charged particles against gravity, allowing the confinement of 1D, 2D or 3D clouds of particles. A particle's charge is large, typically Q = -10,000 electronic charges, so that pairs of particles have a large interparticle repulsion. The large potential energy of this repulsion, together with a cooling of particles by gas drag, lead to strong coupling among the particles. By tailoring the manipulation and confinement of the particles, experiments are performed to study a variety of physical phenomena in statistical mechanics, transport and nonlinear waves. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project includes: cross-cutting research topics of interest to a wide range of physics disciplines, outreach, training of graduate and undergraduate students, and broad dissemination of results.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1162645</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Goree</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John A Goree</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john-goree@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3193351843</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF IOWA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fundamental physics research was carried out, in a way that contributes to several areas of physics, including plasma physics, statistical physics, nanofluidics, and nonlinear dynamics.</p> <p>Experiments were performed to study strongly coupled plasmas, which are an exotic form of matter that acts like a liquid or solid, but it does not consist of individual molecules the way that most liquids and solids do. In our experiments, we used much larger plastic spheres, which are electrically charged and suspended in an ionized gas. This mixture is called&nbsp; a "dusty plasma", and the microspheres behaved collectively the way that molecules do in a liquid. A dusty plasma has the special advantage, for experimenters, that the spheres are big enough to image with video cameras, so that their motion can be tracked. Such a measurement is not possible with individual molecules, ions, or electrons in a simple liquid.</p> <p>To support these experiments, we also carried out some theory, using computer simulations of the strongly coupled plasma.</p> <p>We discovered new fundamental physics phenomena, which we described in numerous papers that we published in physics journals. Among these new phenomena, one was a threshold for nonlinear synchronization of waves, and another was skewness in distributions of fluctuations in a flow that is sheared.</p> <p>Outreach presentations were done at an elementary school. Graduate and undergraduate students were trained. Graduate students completed PhD theses and took jobs in the U.S. New research methods were transferred from the area of plasma physics to the area of nanofluidics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2016<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goree</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481308609_IMG_3536-contrast-adjusted-cropped--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481308609_IMG_3536-contrast-adjusted-cropped--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Strongly coupled plasma"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481308609_IMG_3536-contrast-adjusted-cropped--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Strongly coupled plasma"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tabletop experiments with strongly coupled plasmas are performed using a "dusty plasma."  Micron size plastic spheres are electrically levitated in a partially ionized gas in a vacuum chamber. The microspheres look yellow because they are illuminated by a yellow laser; the ionized gas is purple.</div> <div class="imageCredit">The University of Iowa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goree</div> <div class="imageTitle">Strongly coupled plasma</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481646724_kudatopfplasmawithdustcloudandwave--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481646724_kudatopfplasmawithdustcloudandwave--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dusty plasma with waves"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481646724_kudatopfplasmawithdustcloudandwave--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dusty plasma with waves"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nonlinear waves in strongly coupled plasmas, experiments are studied with dusty plasmas. A centimeter-size cloud of microspheres is electrically suspended above a metal electrode, in a vacuum chamber. The cloud looks green because of laser illumination. The waves are manipulated by a ring, above.</div> <div class="imageCredit">The University of Iowa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goree</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dusty plasma with waves</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481877221_with-boy-and-balloon--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481877221_with-boy-and-balloon--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outreach at elementary school"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479481877221_with-boy-and-balloon--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outreach at elementary school"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Professor John Goree's effort, as part of this NSF-funded project, included outreach presentations at an elementary school. Here he helps a boy discover how a ballon shrinks when dunked into liquid nitrogen.</div> <div class="imageCredit">The University of Iowa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goree</div> <div class="imageTitle">Outreach at elementary school</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479482019645_CIMG1114--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479482019645_CIMG1114--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outreach at elementary school"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1162645/1162645_10193999_1479482019645_CIMG1114--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outreach at elementary school"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This NSF-funded project included outreach presentations at an elementary school. Here, an undergraduate student supported by the NSF grant shows how a tennis ball, cooled by liquid nitrogen, shatters when it hits the classroom wall.</div> <div class="imageCredit">The University of Iowa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Goree</div> <div class="imageTitle">Outreach at elementary school</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fundamental physics research was carried out, in a way that contributes to several areas of physics, including plasma physics, statistical physics, nanofluidics, and nonlinear dynamics.  Experiments were performed to study strongly coupled plasmas, which are an exotic form of matter that acts like a liquid or solid, but it does not consist of individual molecules the way that most liquids and solids do. In our experiments, we used much larger plastic spheres, which are electrically charged and suspended in an ionized gas. This mixture is called  a "dusty plasma", and the microspheres behaved collectively the way that molecules do in a liquid. A dusty plasma has the special advantage, for experimenters, that the spheres are big enough to image with video cameras, so that their motion can be tracked. Such a measurement is not possible with individual molecules, ions, or electrons in a simple liquid.  To support these experiments, we also carried out some theory, using computer simulations of the strongly coupled plasma.  We discovered new fundamental physics phenomena, which we described in numerous papers that we published in physics journals. Among these new phenomena, one was a threshold for nonlinear synchronization of waves, and another was skewness in distributions of fluctuations in a flow that is sheared.  Outreach presentations were done at an elementary school. Graduate and undergraduate students were trained. Graduate students completed PhD theses and took jobs in the U.S. New research methods were transferred from the area of plasma physics to the area of nanofluidics.       Last Modified: 11/18/2016       Submitted by: John A Goree]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
