<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tensor categories, quantum groups, and Hecke algebras</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>484685.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>536698</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project proposes research on tensor categories; quantum groups; representation theory in complex rank; Hecke algebras, Cherednik algebras, symplectic reflection algebras; noncommutative algebra; Poisson homology. The PI's work plan is as follows. 1) Continue developing the general theory of finite tensor categories, in particular, of fusion categories.  2) Prove a discrete analog of the monodromy theorem of Toledano Laredo for the Casimir connection, using dynamical Weyl groups, prove the Felder-Varchenko conjectures on trace functions, and study the trigonometric, the discrete, and the discrete trigonometric analogs of the quantum shift-of-the-argument algebra. 3) Study finite dimensional representations of rational Cherednik algebras and symplectic reflection algebras, representations of continuous Hecke algebras, unitary representations of Cherednik algebras. Study various constructions which link representation theory of these algebras with Lie theory and the representation theory of quantum groups. 4) Develop the ideas of P. Deligne, and extend representation theories of various classical structures (containing the symmetric group or classical Lie groups) to complex values of the rank parameter n (these structures include degenerate affine Hecke algebras, rational and trigonometric Cherednik algebras, symplectic reflection algebras, real reductive Lie groups, Lie superalgebras, affine Lie algebras, parabolic category O for reductive Lie algebras, Yangians, and other structures). 5) Work on quantizations of multiplicative quiver varieties, and on the structure of the lower central series of associative algebras. 6) Continue to study the structure of the zeroth Poisson homology of Poisson varieties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Representation theory is a study of symmetry in a vector space. In this theory, symmetries are represented by linear transformations of this space (by matrices). Thus, a representation of a given symmetry structure is basically a collection of matrices which satisfy a certain natural system of nonlinear relations. The relations are determined by the exact type of structure to be represented such as a group, a Lie algebra, or an associative algebra.  A higher-level structure is called the category of representations. For some type of structures (e.g. for groups, Lie algebras, quantum groups), representations can be multiplied to form tensor categories.  The present project proposes to study many ordinary and tensor categories, some of which arise as representation categories and some of which don't, and to study connections between them. The PI proposes to study complex rank generalizations of representation categories proposed by Deligne. Roughly speaking, this is a generalization in which the number of rows of a matrix is allowed to be non-integer. This seemingly nonsensical setting becomes meaningful and useful in a situation when the interesting invariants are polynomials of the number of rows.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1000113</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pavel</FirstName>
<LastName>Etingof</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pavel I Etingof</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>etingof@math.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172533669</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000118846</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~97142</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~150200</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~94271</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~95398</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~99687</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Representation theory is a branch of mathematics which studies symmetry in space (of any number of dimensions). Such spaces arise in quantum physics as spaces of states of quantum systems, which is why representation theory is relevant to quantum physics. In fact, the structure of the periodic table (i.e. periodic patterns with periods 2,8,18,etc.), as well as so called quantum numbers (determining chemical properties of substances) can be explained by representation theory. <br /><br />Representation theory was created at the very end of 19th century, and developed rapidly throughout the later part of the 20th century. By now, it is one of the most advanced and sophisticated areas of mathematical research. A new trend in this subject emerged in 1970's and 1980's when ideas from geometry and topology (study of geometric shapes, such as donuts or pretzels, and their algebraic invariants) were used to solve very difficult representation-theoretic problems. Reciprocally, representation theory turned out to have spectacular applications to geometry. This gave rise to a new vibrant subject, called geometric representation theory. <br /><br />The goal of this project was to solve a number of problems in representation theory (including its geometric aspects) and in neighboring areas, such as the theory of tensor categories and quantum groups. <br /><br />The most important results of the project is a conjecture on the relation between representation theories of symplectic reflection algebras and affine Lie algebras (most of which has been proved by Bezrukavnikov and Losev), the work with T. Schedler on coinvariants of Lie algebras of vector fields and D-modules, the work on representation theory in complex rank, the work with Gorsky and Losev on Cherednik algebras and torus knots and its application to Cohen-Macaulayness results for quasiinvariants, and the development with C. Walton and J. Cuadra of a theory of actions of finite dimensional Hopf algebras on division algebras. Also, the PI has published two books - a textbook on representation theory and a textbook on <br />tensor categories. <br /><br />These and other results and new methods developed by the PI in the framework of the project constitute its intellectual merit.<br /><br />Many graduate students and postdocs were involved in closely related work, thus the project contributed to preparation of the next generation of experts. The PI and his postdocs have reported their accomplishments in several international and domestic conferences.<br /><br />The project motivated collaboration and exchange of ideas with colleagues in the U.K., Canada, France, Italy, Switzerland, Israel, Chile, and Russia, thereby promoting international cooperation. Also a number of female mathematicians and one African American mathematician were involved in the project. Also, the project gave rise to many graduate student papers and several Ph.D. theses. Finally, the project gave rise to many subprojects for high school and undergraduate research in MIT high school/undergraduate research programs PRIMES, RSI, SPUR and UROP, which won many prizes in national science competitions (such as the Siemens competition, Intel STS, and the Davidson fellows competition) and to many research papers by high school students and undergraduates. This constitutes the broader impacts of the project.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2015<br>      Modified by: Pavel&nbsp;I&nbsp;Etingof</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Representation theory is a branch of mathematics which studies symmetry in space (of any number of dimensions). Such spaces arise in quantum physics as spaces of states of quantum systems, which is why representation theory is relevant to quantum physics. In fact, the structure of the periodic table (i.e. periodic patterns with periods 2,8,18,etc.), as well as so called quantum numbers (determining chemical properties of substances) can be explained by representation theory.   Representation theory was created at the very end of 19th century, and developed rapidly throughout the later part of the 20th century. By now, it is one of the most advanced and sophisticated areas of mathematical research. A new trend in this subject emerged in 1970's and 1980's when ideas from geometry and topology (study of geometric shapes, such as donuts or pretzels, and their algebraic invariants) were used to solve very difficult representation-theoretic problems. Reciprocally, representation theory turned out to have spectacular applications to geometry. This gave rise to a new vibrant subject, called geometric representation theory.   The goal of this project was to solve a number of problems in representation theory (including its geometric aspects) and in neighboring areas, such as the theory of tensor categories and quantum groups.   The most important results of the project is a conjecture on the relation between representation theories of symplectic reflection algebras and affine Lie algebras (most of which has been proved by Bezrukavnikov and Losev), the work with T. Schedler on coinvariants of Lie algebras of vector fields and D-modules, the work on representation theory in complex rank, the work with Gorsky and Losev on Cherednik algebras and torus knots and its application to Cohen-Macaulayness results for quasiinvariants, and the development with C. Walton and J. Cuadra of a theory of actions of finite dimensional Hopf algebras on division algebras. Also, the PI has published two books - a textbook on representation theory and a textbook on  tensor categories.   These and other results and new methods developed by the PI in the framework of the project constitute its intellectual merit.  Many graduate students and postdocs were involved in closely related work, thus the project contributed to preparation of the next generation of experts. The PI and his postdocs have reported their accomplishments in several international and domestic conferences.  The project motivated collaboration and exchange of ideas with colleagues in the U.K., Canada, France, Italy, Switzerland, Israel, Chile, and Russia, thereby promoting international cooperation. Also a number of female mathematicians and one African American mathematician were involved in the project. Also, the project gave rise to many graduate student papers and several Ph.D. theses. Finally, the project gave rise to many subprojects for high school and undergraduate research in MIT high school/undergraduate research programs PRIMES, RSI, SPUR and UROP, which won many prizes in national science competitions (such as the Siemens competition, Intel STS, and the Davidson fellows competition) and to many research papers by high school students and undergraduates. This constitutes the broader impacts of the project.       Last Modified: 09/03/2015       Submitted by: Pavel I Etingof]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
