<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Derived Equivalences and Mixed Categories in Representation Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>129000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tluo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928448</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A series of major advances in geometric representation theory in the past fifteen years have taken the form of "coherent-constructible equivalences": these theorems assert that the category of coherent sheaves on some variety associated to a reductive group is equivalent (or derived-equivalent) to the category of constructible (or perverse) sheaves on a different variety, associated to the Langlands dual group.  Perhaps the best-known such result is the "geometric Satake equivalence," due to Lusztig, Ginzburg, and Mirkovic-Vilonen.  It relates representations of a group G (equivalently: coherent sheaves on a point) to spherical perverse sheaves on the affine Grassmannian for the dual group.  Another major result is the Arkhipov-Bezrukavnikov-Ginzburg (ABG) equivalence, which states that there is a derived equivalence between perverse sheaves on the affine Grassmannian and coherent sheaves on the cotangent bundle of the flag variety of G.  Both these results may be regarded as part of the geometric Langlands program.  The P.I. hopes to contribute to this picture with the following two projects: (I) In collaboration with S. Riche, the P.I. hopes to prove parabolic versions of several known coherent-constructible equivalences; these results would encompass the ABG and geometric Satake equivalences as special cases. (II) The P.I. hopes to develop a new axiomatic framework which is expected to lead to theorems on derived equivalences and higher Ext-vanishing in a very general setting, with a view to applications to coherent sheaves on the nilpotent cone and on the cotangent bundle of the flag variety.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A "matrix group" is a set of invertible square matrices that contains all products and inverses of its members.  A typical example is SU(2), the group of 2x2 unitary complex matrices.  A "representation" of such a group is a rule that assigns to each member of the group a linear transformation of some vector space, in such a way that it transforms matrix multiplication into composition of linear transformations.  SU(2) has a natural 2-dimensional representation--the rule assigning to each element of SU(2) itself--but there are many others as well: for instance, SU(2) has a representation on the space of polynomials in two variables, given by linear substitutions in the variables.  SU(2) is also a topological space: in fact, it is topologically equivalent to a 3-sphere.  A number of modern results in representation theory involve the geometry of matrix groups and related spaces.  Two celebrated results are the geometric Satake equivalence and the Arkhipov-Bezrukavnikov-Ginzburg (ABG) equivalence, both of which relate representations of a matrix group to "D-modules" (a sophisticated way of working with spaces of local solutions of differential equations) on a certain infinite-dimensional space called the "affine Grassmannian."  The proposed research includes two projects: (I) the P.I., in collaboration with S. Riche, hopes to prove a general "parabolic-parahoric equivalence theorem" that would include the geometric Satake and ABG equivalences as special cases; and (II) the P.I. hopes to study in an axiomatic way certain "positivity phenomena" that occur in the known equivalence theorems, with a view to generalizing those theorems to other settings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1001594</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pramod</FirstName>
<LastName>Achar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pramod N Achar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pramod@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255787990</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000207284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Himes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~129000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Geometric representation theory</em>&nbsp;is subject built around bridges between algebra and topology. Its main theme is that a number of algebraic questions about groups have their answers encoded in the topology or geometry of various spaces related to the group. An important early example was the proof (around 1981) of the Kazhdan-Lusztig conjecture, which gives character formulas for certain Lie algebra representations in terms of the topology of flag manifolds. The research funded under this grant has contributed to advancing the understanding of various specific topics with geometric representation theory, including the geometric Satake equivalence, Koszul duality, and Springer theory.</p> <p>The <em>geometric Satake equivalence</em>, due to Lusztig, Ginzburg, and Mirkovic-Vilonen, essentially asserts that the entire representation theory of an algebraic group is encoded in the topology of a certain infinite-dimensional space called the <em>affine Grassmannian</em>. In the course of this project, the P.I. and S. Riche studied how to translate certain algebraic operations with representations into topological terms. Separately, the P.I. and L. Rider proved the <em>Mirkovic-Vilonen conjecture</em>, which deals with the topological counterpart to an important class of representations called Weyl modules. Finally, the P.I., A. Henderson, and S. Riche discovered a previously unknown connection between the geometric Satake equivalence and the Springer correspondence (see below).</p> <p><em>Koszul duality</em>&nbsp;is a subtle algebraic phenomenon from ring theory. Since a seminal 1996 paper of Beilinson-Ginzburg-Soergel, it has been recognized as playing a central role in the interplay between algebra and topology in geometric representation theory. The P.I. has studied how the Koszul phenomenon arises from topology in the setting of &eacute;tale cohomology (with S. Riche) and in Hodge theory (with S. Kitchen). Subsequently, the P.I. and S. Riche developed a new framework for studying and exploiting Koszul-like phenomena in positive characteristic.</p> <p><em>Springer theory</em>&nbsp;originated with Springer's remarkable 1976 discovery that representations of certain finite groups (Weyl groups) can be constructed in terms of the topology of nilpotent matrices. In 1984, Lusztig extended Springer's work to construct what has come to be known as the "generalized Springer correspondence." Separately, in 2007, D. Juteau initiated the study of Springer theory with coefficients in a field of positive characteristic. In an ongoing joint project, the P.I., A. Henderson, D. Juteau, and S. Riche are developing a theory that unifies Lusztig's work with Juteau's earlier work.</p> <p>During the funding period, the P.I. contributed to human resource development in several ways. Together with his colleague D. Sage, he has been leading a vertically-integrated seminar on topics in geometric representation theory. Participants include undergraduates, graduate students, postdocs, and faculty members. The P.I. has also supervised five Ph.D. students during the funding period.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2014<br>      Modified by: Pramod&nbsp;N&nbsp;Achar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Geometric representation theory is subject built around bridges between algebra and topology. Its main theme is that a number of algebraic questions about groups have their answers encoded in the topology or geometry of various spaces related to the group. An important early example was the proof (around 1981) of the Kazhdan-Lusztig conjecture, which gives character formulas for certain Lie algebra representations in terms of the topology of flag manifolds. The research funded under this grant has contributed to advancing the understanding of various specific topics with geometric representation theory, including the geometric Satake equivalence, Koszul duality, and Springer theory.  The geometric Satake equivalence, due to Lusztig, Ginzburg, and Mirkovic-Vilonen, essentially asserts that the entire representation theory of an algebraic group is encoded in the topology of a certain infinite-dimensional space called the affine Grassmannian. In the course of this project, the P.I. and S. Riche studied how to translate certain algebraic operations with representations into topological terms. Separately, the P.I. and L. Rider proved the Mirkovic-Vilonen conjecture, which deals with the topological counterpart to an important class of representations called Weyl modules. Finally, the P.I., A. Henderson, and S. Riche discovered a previously unknown connection between the geometric Satake equivalence and the Springer correspondence (see below).  Koszul duality is a subtle algebraic phenomenon from ring theory. Since a seminal 1996 paper of Beilinson-Ginzburg-Soergel, it has been recognized as playing a central role in the interplay between algebra and topology in geometric representation theory. The P.I. has studied how the Koszul phenomenon arises from topology in the setting of &eacute;tale cohomology (with S. Riche) and in Hodge theory (with S. Kitchen). Subsequently, the P.I. and S. Riche developed a new framework for studying and exploiting Koszul-like phenomena in positive characteristic.  Springer theory originated with Springer's remarkable 1976 discovery that representations of certain finite groups (Weyl groups) can be constructed in terms of the topology of nilpotent matrices. In 1984, Lusztig extended Springer's work to construct what has come to be known as the "generalized Springer correspondence." Separately, in 2007, D. Juteau initiated the study of Springer theory with coefficients in a field of positive characteristic. In an ongoing joint project, the P.I., A. Henderson, D. Juteau, and S. Riche are developing a theory that unifies Lusztig's work with Juteau's earlier work.  During the funding period, the P.I. contributed to human resource development in several ways. Together with his colleague D. Sage, he has been leading a vertically-integrated seminar on topics in geometric representation theory. Participants include undergraduates, graduate students, postdocs, and faculty members. The P.I. has also supervised five Ph.D. students during the funding period.       Last Modified: 07/18/2014       Submitted by: Pramod N Achar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
