<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>288000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>346477</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project identifies for intensive study several classes of interesting problems concerning the properties of solutions of certain nonlinear partial differential  equations (PDE). The specific topics are analyzing solutions of nonconvex Hamilton-Jacobi equations, improving PDE methods for weak KAM theory, studying regularity of solutions of the  infinity Laplacian equation, developing PDE techniques for "inconsistent" stochastic optimal control problems, formulating variational principles for optimal symplectic maps,  and studying certain strongly nonlinear parabolic systems. The various topics cited above have widely differing structures but are unified by reason of being accessible to either variational, maximum principle and/or energy methods, although usually in certain singular limits. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Vast research experience has shown that simple-looking nonlinear partial differential equations, with mathematically natural structures, appear and reappear in the  pure and applied sciences. In particular, most of the fundamental equations of the physical and engineering sciences are partial differential equations, of which the most difficult, and arguably most important, are nonlinear. So-called perturbation techniques can handle various "close-to-linear" equations, but there remains the real necessity of discovering general principles and methods for various important nonlinear equations in the large. Understanding the existence, uniqueness, and regularity of solutions, and ascertaining as well their behavior, are fundamental mathematical tasks that should have  practical implications in view of the various interpretations of these equations. The particular equations singled out for study in the project are all natural in their structures, and consequently can be expected to arise in various applications. For instance, the nonconvex Hamilton--Jacobi equation is the basic equation for two-person, zero-sum differential games, so understanding the singular structure of its solutions helps directly in the design of optimal strategies.  The proposed extension of partial differential equations methods to the nonstandard stochastic optimal control problems should likewise be fundamental in framing optimality conditions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1001724</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence C Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>evans@math.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106437417</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261846</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~96929</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~94896</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~154652</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes for General Public NSF Grant &nbsp;DMS-1001724 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Lawrence C. Evans&nbsp;</p> <p><br />This grant supported me and several of my PhD students &nbsp;a wide ranging research program on properties of solutions of various nonlinear partial differential equations(PDEs).<br /><br />&nbsp;RESEARCH.<br />A. Envelopes and nonconvex &nbsp; Hamilton-Jacobi PDE. &nbsp;I &nbsp;discovered a &nbsp;new general &nbsp;``envelope'' representation formula for &nbsp;solutions of the Hamilton-Jacobi PDEwith nonconvex Hamiltonians H.My new formula &nbsp;generalizes both the Hopf-Lax representation (for convex H) and Hopf's formula (for convex initial data).&nbsp;<br /><br />&nbsp; B. Sup-norm variational problems. My then student Charlie Smart and I &nbsp; &nbsp;applied a nonlinear adjoint method to the so-called ``infinity Laplacian'' equation, a highly degenerate PDE that arises in variational problemsin the supremum-norm. We resolved a long standing problem by showing that appropriately rescaled blow-up limits are unique and thus solutions are everywhere differentiable.&nbsp;<br /><br />&nbsp; C. Differential games. &nbsp;Optimal strategies for two--person, zero--sum differential games can be computed in principle by solving certain highly nonlinear PDE, but there are many technical problems. In a recent paper I extended &nbsp;a famous condition of R Isaacs for the solution alonga surface of discontinuity and discovered that certain ``entropy type'' inequalities must hold has well. These should make it easier to construct explicit solutions.<br /><br />f D. &nbsp;Liquid crystal models. Some recently proposed models for liquid crystals give &nbsp;highly singular variational problems that do not fall within standard theory. My former student &nbsp;H Tran, my former postdoc&nbsp;O. Kneuss &nbsp;and I have shown partial regularity for minimizers for several of these physically realistic models.<br /><br /><br />EDUCATION: &nbsp; I have recently revised some online notes into the book ``An Introduction to Stochastic DifferentialEquations'', &nbsp;published by the American Math Society in 2014. I have also &nbsp;written a fairly long article &nbsp;on ``Partial differential equations" for the forthcoming &nbsp;``The Princeton Companion to Applied Mathematics''. (I earlier wrote the entry&nbsp;&nbsp;on ``Variational methods'' for &nbsp;``The Princeton Companion to &nbsp;Mathematics''.)<br /><br />&nbsp;Recent PhD students:&nbsp;<br />A. Chen (University of &nbsp;California, Berkeley, 2012, coadvisor: &nbsp;X. Guo ),&nbsp;``Impulse Control and Optimal Stopping''.<br /><br />&nbsp;H. Tran (University of &nbsp;California, Berkeley, 2012),&nbsp;``Some New Methods for Hamilton--Jacobi Type Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations''.<br /><br />J. DeIonno (University of &nbsp;California, Berkeley, 2013),&nbsp;``Quasi-Variational Inequalities for Source-Expanding Hele-Shaw Problems''</p> <p><br />Current PhD students:&nbsp;&nbsp;Khalilah Beal,&nbsp; &nbsp;Woo-Hyun Cook,&nbsp; Te Zhang,&nbsp; Peyam Tabrizian,&nbsp; Peter Vinella,&nbsp;Christoph Kroener&nbsp;<br /><br />&nbsp;Recent postdocs:&nbsp;&nbsp;Hiroyoshi &nbsp;Mitake (Hiroshima University, 2010-2011)<br />Olivier &nbsp;Kneuss (Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne, 2012--2013)<br /><br /><br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/24/2014<br>      Modified by: Lawrence&nbsp;C&nbsp;Evans</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes for General Public NSF Grant  DMS-1001724         Lawrence C. Evans    This grant supported me and several of my PhD students  a wide ranging research program on properties of solutions of various nonlinear partial differential equations(PDEs).   RESEARCH. A. Envelopes and nonconvex   Hamilton-Jacobi PDE.  I  discovered a  new general  ``envelope'' representation formula for  solutions of the Hamilton-Jacobi PDEwith nonconvex Hamiltonians H.My new formula  generalizes both the Hopf-Lax representation (for convex H) and Hopf's formula (for convex initial data).     B. Sup-norm variational problems. My then student Charlie Smart and I    applied a nonlinear adjoint method to the so-called ``infinity Laplacian'' equation, a highly degenerate PDE that arises in variational problemsin the supremum-norm. We resolved a long standing problem by showing that appropriately rescaled blow-up limits are unique and thus solutions are everywhere differentiable.     C. Differential games.  Optimal strategies for two--person, zero--sum differential games can be computed in principle by solving certain highly nonlinear PDE, but there are many technical problems. In a recent paper I extended  a famous condition of R Isaacs for the solution alonga surface of discontinuity and discovered that certain ``entropy type'' inequalities must hold has well. These should make it easier to construct explicit solutions.  f D.  Liquid crystal models. Some recently proposed models for liquid crystals give  highly singular variational problems that do not fall within standard theory. My former student  H Tran, my former postdoc O. Kneuss  and I have shown partial regularity for minimizers for several of these physically realistic models.   EDUCATION:   I have recently revised some online notes into the book ``An Introduction to Stochastic DifferentialEquations'',  published by the American Math Society in 2014. I have also  written a fairly long article  on ``Partial differential equations" for the forthcoming  ``The Princeton Companion to Applied Mathematics''. (I earlier wrote the entry  on ``Variational methods'' for  ``The Princeton Companion to  Mathematics''.)   Recent PhD students:  A. Chen (University of  California, Berkeley, 2012, coadvisor:  X. Guo ), ``Impulse Control and Optimal Stopping''.   H. Tran (University of  California, Berkeley, 2012), ``Some New Methods for Hamilton--Jacobi Type Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations''.  J. DeIonno (University of  California, Berkeley, 2013), ``Quasi-Variational Inequalities for Source-Expanding Hele-Shaw Problems''   Current PhD students:  Khalilah Beal,   Woo-Hyun Cook,  Te Zhang,  Peyam Tabrizian,  Peter Vinella, Christoph Kroener    Recent postdocs:  Hiroyoshi  Mitake (Hiroshima University, 2010-2011) Olivier  Kneuss (Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne, 2012--2013)            Last Modified: 07/24/2014       Submitted by: Lawrence C Evans]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
