<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>218294.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>218294</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jane Prey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is continuing a successful IT apprenticeship program that provides students the opportunity to receive industry-based technical experiences while earning an associate's degree. This activity helps meet the urgent need of local employers for the emerging digital economy.  The program includes an online course for employment readiness, communication skills and job search skills.  A key component of the program is a full-time apprenticeship coach whose responsibility is to prepare students for work, monitor student progress and to encourage local employers to hire displaced workers.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Goals of the project include partnering with local industry to increase the number of available positions and to place an increasing number of students with a particular emphasis on women, minorities and displaced workers.  Mentoring and marketing strategies are being assessed and results will be disseminated to allow other organizations to implement a similar program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1002968</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Berry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith Berry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>berryj4@lcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174831322</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000319367</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/15/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Berghorn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George H Berghorn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>berghorg@lcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5172675901</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scott10@lcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174831031</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Suniga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eduardo Suniga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sunigae@lcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174831187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000591667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lansing Community College</Name>
<CityName>Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>489330000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5174831765</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 N Washington Sq</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 203]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076336882</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LANSING COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076336882</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lansing Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>489330000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 N Washington Sq]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~218294</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship project has significantly serviced the Lansing, Michigan community and has been a valuable resource for Lansing Community College.&nbsp; This grant has provided IT students with job opportunities by creating a structured education and training apprenticeship track where none existed prior. This grant came at a time when the auto industry was down in Michigan and created opportunities for those new to IT to achieve a richer long-term IT education experience while also creating stronger job placement opportunities after graduation. This project addressed issues effectively to create a stronger, self-sustaining apprenticeship model while raising the education level in the region to better satisfy the Capital Region Area achieving a highly skilled workforce for the information and digital economy. The Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship project provided IT students with a Department of Labor registered apprenticeship opportunity that gave them practical experience which better prepared them for transitioning from school to work.&nbsp;</p> <p>The program placed 152 students in apprenticeship positions. Of the 152, 69 have completed their apprenticeships and received a Department of Labor certificate, while the remaining 83 continue to be enrolled in the program. The program developed strong relationships with external programs that focused on minority recruitment and retention in STEM areas. These partnerships contributed to a 26% female and a 24% minority participation rate further impacting the regions presence of women and minorities in IT. There were 80 companies involved in the project providing the apprenticeship activities. This increased the number of workplace openings for students by 30% each semester over 4 years. Surveys attained indicate a 98% employer satisfaction rating of the program, while student participants satisfaction was at 97%. The program was fully funded by the end of the grant period. Information about The Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship project can be found at <a href="http://www.lcc.edu/cit/itapprenticeship">www.lcc.edu/cit/itapprenticeship</a>.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2013<br>      Modified by: Eduardo&nbsp;Suniga</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship project has significantly serviced the Lansing, Michigan community and has been a valuable resource for Lansing Community College.  This grant has provided IT students with job opportunities by creating a structured education and training apprenticeship track where none existed prior. This grant came at a time when the auto industry was down in Michigan and created opportunities for those new to IT to achieve a richer long-term IT education experience while also creating stronger job placement opportunities after graduation. This project addressed issues effectively to create a stronger, self-sustaining apprenticeship model while raising the education level in the region to better satisfy the Capital Region Area achieving a highly skilled workforce for the information and digital economy. The Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship project provided IT students with a Department of Labor registered apprenticeship opportunity that gave them practical experience which better prepared them for transitioning from school to work.   The program placed 152 students in apprenticeship positions. Of the 152, 69 have completed their apprenticeships and received a Department of Labor certificate, while the remaining 83 continue to be enrolled in the program. The program developed strong relationships with external programs that focused on minority recruitment and retention in STEM areas. These partnerships contributed to a 26% female and a 24% minority participation rate further impacting the regions presence of women and minorities in IT. There were 80 companies involved in the project providing the apprenticeship activities. This increased the number of workplace openings for students by 30% each semester over 4 years. Surveys attained indicate a 98% employer satisfaction rating of the program, while student participants satisfaction was at 97%. The program was fully funded by the end of the grant period. Information about The Capital Region Area Information Technology Apprenticeship project can be found at www.lcc.edu/cit/itapprenticeship.       Last Modified: 10/28/2013       Submitted by: Eduardo Suniga]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
