<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Lepton Collider R&amp;D</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15009973.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12818325</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Shank</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshank@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Electrons, positrons and muons are, based on solid experimental evidence, fundamental, elementary particles with no components. This is unlike the (much heavier) proton, for example, which is composed of quarks and gluons.  Thus using these fundamental particles in collisions with those of equal and opposite momenta in the laboratory provides the full center of mass energy for creation of new forms of matter with well defined energy and kinematics. For this reason studies by particle physicists have called for significant investment in the enabling accelerator science and technologies that might lead to lepton colliders with TeV (Tera [10 to the power 12 ] ) electron votes) scale center of mass energies, in addition to existing proton colliders such as the Large Hadron Collider (LHC).  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project covers R&amp;D in several of the key accelerator science and technology components of such a lepton collider; however, the results will be applicable to many existing and future accelerators of all kinds around the world. The research areas that will be pursued directly support these national priorities. Major laboratories around the world are presently conducting accelerator research and development that will lead to detailed designs of a linear electron-positron collider capable of reaching this energy range. The technology being developed for this purpose will also have applications to other areas of science and technology through new generations of intense light sources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Note that there are two basic shapes of accelerators. Linear accelerators ("linacs") accelerate elementary particles along a straight path. Circular accelerators, such as the Tevatron and the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), use circular paths. Circular geometry has significant advantages at energies up to and including tens of GeV (10 to the power 9 electron volts) : With a circular design, particles can be effectively accelerated over longer distances. Also, only a fraction of the particles brought onto a collision course actually collide. In a linear accelerator, the remaining particles are lost; in a ring accelerator, they keep circulating and are available for future collisions. The disadvantage of circular accelerators is that particles moving along bent paths will necessarily emit electromagnetic radiation known as synchrotron radiation. Energy loss through synchrotron radiation is inversely proportional to the fourth power of the mass of the particles in question. Leptons, being light, lose a large amount of energy in this way. That is why it makes sense to build circular accelerators for heavy particles - hadron colliders such as the LHC for protons. An electron-positron collider of the same size would never be able to achieve the same collision energies. In fact, energies at the LEP lepton collider, which used to occupy the tunnel now given over to the LHC, were limited to 209 GeV by energy loss via synchrotron radiation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a result of previous funding the Cornell accelerator is now a flexible, unique-in-the-world test accelerator laboratory, allowing a group of scientists and engineers (with worldwide partnerships)  to test and solve some of the most challenging problems faced by state-of-the-art accelerators today. These worldwide collaborations and joint efforts between labs such as those between Cornell and its extended group of colleagues and partners, and Cornell's outreach to the community, are viewed as exemplary by the community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1002467</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maury</FirstName>
<LastName>Tigner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maury Tigner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mt52@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072554951</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000131845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/04/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Hartill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald L Hartill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlh13@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558787</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000432322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Rubin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Rubin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlr10@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000202762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Rubin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Rubin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlr10@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000202762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/04/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georg</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffstaetter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georg H Hoffstaetter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gh77@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555197</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000322135</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Palmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark A Palmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>map36@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000321279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/14/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~4604785</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~4380000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~3833540</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Lepton colliders are essential tools for the study of the elementary particles that are the fundamental constituents of matter in the universe. Colliders enable the investigation of the most intriguing questions about the structure, evolution and eventual fate of the universe.&nbsp; Why is the universe predominantly matter, rather then antimatter. What is the nature of the dark matter that fills the cosmos? Why are there 3 flavors of leptons and quarks and what is the source of the mass hierarchy? Are there extra dimensions beyond the four of space and time?</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The effectiveness of a collider as a tool for research is determined by the rate at which compact bunches of particles and antiparticles can be accelerated to high energy and brought into collision. The goals of the project were to better understand the phenomena that limit intensity of particle beams in storage rings, to develop specialized beam instrumentation for that study, and to extend the capability of superconducting accelerating structures.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Electrons and positrons are accelerated in bunches. A typical bunch consists of a ribbonlike packet of some 10 billion particles. The packet has length of 10mm and width of about 0.1mm. The height of the packet (some 10 microns) is less than the diameter of a human hair. The electron and positron bunches are prepared in damping rings. The intensity of electron/positron beams (a beam is a train of closely spaced bunches) in damping rings is limited by a variety of phenomena, including electron cloud and ion effects, wakefields and intra-beam scattering. We explored all of the above with the Cornell Electron/positron Storage Ring (CESR) and learned to mitigate the limiting effects by a combination of vacuum chamber surface treatments and optimization of beam parameters, like energy, bunch charge, bunch spacing, etc. &nbsp;The study was enabled by new instrumentation, such as a high speed Xray camera capable of measuring the size of each positron bunch in a train of 30 or more bunches, electron detectors to measure the density of the electron cloud, detectors to precisely measure the position of each passing bunch of particles, and a digital tune tracker. The tune tracker is used to manipulate the beam in order to identify errors in the accelerator guide field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The elementary particles for these experiments, electrons, positrons, and some day perhaps muons, are accelerated with the advanced technology of superconducting accelerating structures. This technology was pioneered at Cornell University, and this grant has allowed us to extend the capability of the technology. The emphasis of this research effort was to improve the efficiency of the structures, so that more of the input power is converted to beam energy and less is dissipated in the structure itself. As superconducting cavities operate in liquid helium, within a few degrees of absolute zero, the size of the refrigeration plant scales with the amount of power lost through dissipation.</p> <p>The benefit of reduced dissipation is a very significant reduction in the size of the refrigeration plant, and in the electrical power required to operate the plant and to accelerate beams of particles and antiparticles to high energy. A Horizontal Test Cryostat (HTC) was designed to enable realistic performance tests of superconducting cavities. It was observed that heat cycles increased the cavity Q. (Higher Q corresponds to reduced dissipation). To understand what produced high-Q during warm-up cycles, we investigated Q for different cool-down speed, for different thermal currents, and for different external magnetic fields. The very high Q achieved in these tests set a new standard of performance for the next generation of superconducting accelerators.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2015<br>      Modified by: David&nb...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Lepton colliders are essential tools for the study of the elementary particles that are the fundamental constituents of matter in the universe. Colliders enable the investigation of the most intriguing questions about the structure, evolution and eventual fate of the universe.  Why is the universe predominantly matter, rather then antimatter. What is the nature of the dark matter that fills the cosmos? Why are there 3 flavors of leptons and quarks and what is the source of the mass hierarchy? Are there extra dimensions beyond the four of space and time?     The effectiveness of a collider as a tool for research is determined by the rate at which compact bunches of particles and antiparticles can be accelerated to high energy and brought into collision. The goals of the project were to better understand the phenomena that limit intensity of particle beams in storage rings, to develop specialized beam instrumentation for that study, and to extend the capability of superconducting accelerating structures.     Electrons and positrons are accelerated in bunches. A typical bunch consists of a ribbonlike packet of some 10 billion particles. The packet has length of 10mm and width of about 0.1mm. The height of the packet (some 10 microns) is less than the diameter of a human hair. The electron and positron bunches are prepared in damping rings. The intensity of electron/positron beams (a beam is a train of closely spaced bunches) in damping rings is limited by a variety of phenomena, including electron cloud and ion effects, wakefields and intra-beam scattering. We explored all of the above with the Cornell Electron/positron Storage Ring (CESR) and learned to mitigate the limiting effects by a combination of vacuum chamber surface treatments and optimization of beam parameters, like energy, bunch charge, bunch spacing, etc.  The study was enabled by new instrumentation, such as a high speed Xray camera capable of measuring the size of each positron bunch in a train of 30 or more bunches, electron detectors to measure the density of the electron cloud, detectors to precisely measure the position of each passing bunch of particles, and a digital tune tracker. The tune tracker is used to manipulate the beam in order to identify errors in the accelerator guide field.     The elementary particles for these experiments, electrons, positrons, and some day perhaps muons, are accelerated with the advanced technology of superconducting accelerating structures. This technology was pioneered at Cornell University, and this grant has allowed us to extend the capability of the technology. The emphasis of this research effort was to improve the efficiency of the structures, so that more of the input power is converted to beam energy and less is dissipated in the structure itself. As superconducting cavities operate in liquid helium, within a few degrees of absolute zero, the size of the refrigeration plant scales with the amount of power lost through dissipation.  The benefit of reduced dissipation is a very significant reduction in the size of the refrigeration plant, and in the electrical power required to operate the plant and to accelerate beams of particles and antiparticles to high energy. A Horizontal Test Cryostat (HTC) was designed to enable realistic performance tests of superconducting cavities. It was observed that heat cycles increased the cavity Q. (Higher Q corresponds to reduced dissipation). To understand what produced high-Q during warm-up cycles, we investigated Q for different cool-down speed, for different thermal currents, and for different external magnetic fields. The very high Q achieved in these tests set a new standard of performance for the next generation of superconducting accelerators.             Last Modified: 07/31/2015       Submitted by: David Rubin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
