<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Conference on Advances in Partial Differential Equations and their Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wang&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1002618&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advances in the theory of partial differential equations have had profound implications and applications in mathematics, science, engineering and industry.  The interplay between partial differential equations and applications has been particularly interesting in geophysical fluid dynamics and climate dynamics.  The investigator and his colleagues hold an International conference on Advances in Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations and their Applications to Geophysical Fluid Dynamics during May 31 - June 4, 2010 in Fudan University, Shanghai, China.  Funding supports US researchers, in particular, junior, women, and under-represented researchers, to attend the conference.  The conference contributes in promoting, enhancing, and stimulating international research interactions and collaborations in the mathematical sciences, more specifically, in applied and computational mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this international conference is to bring together experts who work on diverse frontiers of nonlinear PDEs and their applications to geophysical fluid dynamics to survey recent progress and current challenges, to discuss how new ideas and methods could advance the field in coming years.  The conference involves a large number of researchers from the United States, China, and other countries, and contributes significantly to the development of the international applied and computational mathematics community.  A special forward-looking session is arranged for panel discussions, focusing on the challenges and opportunities facing the fields of nonlinear partial differential equations and geophysical fluid dynamics.  Findings from this special session, together with other papers by the speakers and the participants, are published in the Chinese Annuals of Mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1002618</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Shen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Shen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shen@math.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941923</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000289537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shouhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shouhong Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>showang@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128558350</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000290820</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoming</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoming Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wxm@math.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506442202</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[509 E 3RD ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~27000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><pre><pre>This grant was funded for supporting US participants to the International</pre> <pre>Conference on Advances in Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations and&nbsp;</pre> <pre>their Applications which was  held in Fudan University, Shanghai, China,&nbsp;</pre> <pre>during May 31 -  June 4, 2010. The aim of this international  conference&nbsp;</pre> <pre>was to bring together experts who work on diverse frontiers of </pre> <pre>nonlinear PDEs  and their applications to geophysical fluid dynamics to survey recent progress and current  challenges, and to discuss how new&nbsp;</pre> <pre>ideas and methods could advance the field in coming years.&nbsp;</pre> <pre><span><br /></span></pre> <pre><span>Participants and invited speakers include both leading experts and young</span></pre> <pre>researchers in the  related fields. The NSF grant supported participants&nbsp;</pre> <pre>include 5 women mathematicians and  2  African-American mathematicians,&nbsp;</pre> <pre>and a larger portion of the fund was used to support junior  researchers.</pre> <pre><br /></pre> <pre>Two special issues of Chinese Annuals of Mathematics (Volume 31, Number</pre> <pre>5 &amp; 6, 2010) are published based on talks given in this conference.&nbsp;</pre> <pre>These two issues contain 21 articles. <br /></pre> <pre>During the conference, we also organized a two-hour  forward-looking panel &nbsp;</pre> <pre>discussion. Various open  and challenging problems as well</pre> <pre>as emerging and future  directions were discussed. In particular,&nbsp;</pre> <pre>a number of importan scientific problems in the modeling, analysis&nbsp;</pre> <pre>and computation for climate dynamics<span style="font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;">&nbsp;</span>and multi-scale physics&nbsp;</pre> <pre>in material science were identified and suggested to young participants.</pre> </pre><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2011<br>      Modified by: Shouhong&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This grant was funded for supporting US participants to the International Conference on Advances in Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations and  their Applications which was  held in Fudan University, Shanghai, China,  during May 31 -  June 4, 2010. The aim of this international  conference  was to bring together experts who work on diverse frontiers of  nonlinear PDEs  and their applications to geophysical fluid dynamics to survey recent progress and current  challenges, and to discuss how new  ideas and methods could advance the field in coming years.    Participants and invited speakers include both leading experts and young researchers in the  related fields. The NSF grant supported participants  include 5 women mathematicians and  2  African-American mathematicians,  and a larger portion of the fund was used to support junior  researchers.   Two special issues of Chinese Annuals of Mathematics (Volume 31, Number 5 &amp; 6, 2010) are published based on talks given in this conference.  These two issues contain 21 articles.   During the conference, we also organized a two-hour  forward-looking panel   discussion. Various open  and challenging problems as well as emerging and future  directions were discussed. In particular,  a number of importan scientific problems in the modeling, analysis  and computation for climate dynamics and multi-scale physics  in material science were identified and suggested to young participants.        Last Modified: 07/31/2011       Submitted by: Shouhong Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
