<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Homological Techniques in Commutative Algebra</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>125044.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>125044</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Commutative algebra is crucial in developing the foundations of algebraic geometry. Two central topics of research in these fields are multiplicities and the homological behavior of modules. This proposal concerns questions related to these topics and especially their interplay. The first project involves studying whether Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity, an intriguing and not well-understood measure of the complexity of a singularity in positive characteristic, has an interpretation in characteristic zero where it could be simpler or clearer to interpret geometrically (some known examples show that a limit as the characteristic goes to infinity might exist and seems to be a simpler number). The second concerns the homology of Koszul complexes, and although in this case the approaches are not exclusively from the realm of complete intersection rings, many of the same ideas arise since the Koszul complex is the first step in constructing a Tate resolution. Many directions are being examined, with several new approaches to old problems studied by Huneke, Simis, Vasconcelos and many others. The third concerns an older conjecture in rational homotopy theory, a field with which the ideas from resolutions of complete intersections and from differential graded resolutions have a long history of interaction, but have not yet been used for this particular problem; preliminary results of this approach look encouraging. The fourth concerns Serre's intersection multiplicity over non-regular rings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These projects are at the center of some of the main directions in commutative algebra, but with a view towards neighboring fields of mathematics or subfields of algebra. For example, the first and main project concerns multiplicities, which are numerical measures of the complexity of a non-smooth (that is, sharp) point on a curve, surface, or higher dimensional object. The investigator is especially interested in these in an algebraic or number theoretic setting that is not directly related to the physical geometry of an object. Known results show quite mysterious behavior of these numbers and the investigator hopes to shed some light on the situation by relating the setting to a more geometric one where classical geometric techniques might be applied. This is a delicate procedure and work in progress. Likewise, the third project involves a problem that would apply ideas from her abstract field of algebra to a part of topology, a field which deals with physical spaces. In summary, although the subjects of the projects are quite varied, they hold a common theme that may not be immediately evident: Namely, the investigator proposes to apply her experience in her own area to various problems further removed from this area and not traditionally studied in this way.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1003384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudia M Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>clamille@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154431493</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000258026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~125044</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>These projects lie in commutative algebra, the crucial foundation of algebraic geometry, one of the most important areas of pure mathematics, entailing the study of curves, surfaces, and higher dimensional geometric objects described by polynomial equations. This field is more than a century old and yet thriving, developing in highly technical ways on its own, but always ending up having the most astounding applications all over, to coding theory, to communications, to mirror symmetry, and to many other such seemingly remote fields of science and engineering.&nbsp;</p> <p>Two central topics of research in these fields are multiplicities of singularities and the homological behavior of modules and these projects concern questions related to these topics and especially their interplay.&nbsp;</p> <p>The first and main project concerns multiplicities, which are numerical measures of the complexity of a nonsmooth (that is, sharp) point on a curve, surface, or higher dimensional object. One numerical measure of the severity such a singularity is its classical multiplicity. This is well understood and almost a century old. A newer and more subtle measure is its&nbsp;Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity, but this remains almost impossible to understand. The investigator's long-term goal is to shed some light on the situation by relating the setting to a more geometric one where classical geometric techniques might be applied.</p> <p>To this end, one of the major accomplishments of this project was the development of a certain kind of very powerful operations, called Adams operations, in the modern context of matrix factorizations (central in string theory) for which the classic tool of Dold-Kan correspondence is not available. These operations are classic in other settings and have an important history in solving some of the biggest questions in mathematics, such as Serre's Vanishing Conjecture and the beahavior of the Hopf Invariant. In this new setting they once again serve as a strong tool: Indeed the investigator and coauthors have used them to solve an open conjecture on the vanishing of Hochster's theta invariant in the remaining most difficult case of mixed characteristic. The PI hopes that in the future this tool will help to unravel the geometric meaning in the Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity of a singularity.</p> <p>The second project concerns Koszul homology of ideals,&nbsp;a widely studied invariant of the singularity of the curve, surface, or higher dimensional object given by the ideals. The main accomplishment of this project is the extension of a classic duality theorem for&nbsp;certain very special ideals to a&nbsp;duality&nbsp;theorem that holds for all&nbsp;singularities! In addition, the machinery involved in establishing this duality was also investigated intensely to obtain more subtle results under certain conditions, extending those known by other techniques. This project is leading the investigator and coauthors to more difficult questions, with partial results, towards understanding these fundamental invariants better.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the third project, the outcome generalizes results on the torsion and cotorsion of the module of p-differentials, an important invariant of local hypersurface singularities, to the case of a local complete intersection singularities. This extends long-known results to cases where the singularities are not necessarily isolated point, but can lie along ridges, or other higher dimensional subvarieties.</p> <p>This grant has also enabled the PI to be heavily involved in mentoring and in contributing to communication:</p> <p>1) Co-organizer for Route 81 Conference in Commutative Algebra and Algebraic Geometry, Syracuse.</p> <p>2) Co-organizer for the NSF-funded conference "Interactions between Commutative Algebra and Representation Theory", Syracuse.</p> <p>3) Co-organizer&nbsp;of 3 Special Sessions, at AWM meeting and AMS meetings, one d...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ These projects lie in commutative algebra, the crucial foundation of algebraic geometry, one of the most important areas of pure mathematics, entailing the study of curves, surfaces, and higher dimensional geometric objects described by polynomial equations. This field is more than a century old and yet thriving, developing in highly technical ways on its own, but always ending up having the most astounding applications all over, to coding theory, to communications, to mirror symmetry, and to many other such seemingly remote fields of science and engineering.   Two central topics of research in these fields are multiplicities of singularities and the homological behavior of modules and these projects concern questions related to these topics and especially their interplay.   The first and main project concerns multiplicities, which are numerical measures of the complexity of a nonsmooth (that is, sharp) point on a curve, surface, or higher dimensional object. One numerical measure of the severity such a singularity is its classical multiplicity. This is well understood and almost a century old. A newer and more subtle measure is its Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity, but this remains almost impossible to understand. The investigator's long-term goal is to shed some light on the situation by relating the setting to a more geometric one where classical geometric techniques might be applied.  To this end, one of the major accomplishments of this project was the development of a certain kind of very powerful operations, called Adams operations, in the modern context of matrix factorizations (central in string theory) for which the classic tool of Dold-Kan correspondence is not available. These operations are classic in other settings and have an important history in solving some of the biggest questions in mathematics, such as Serre's Vanishing Conjecture and the beahavior of the Hopf Invariant. In this new setting they once again serve as a strong tool: Indeed the investigator and coauthors have used them to solve an open conjecture on the vanishing of Hochster's theta invariant in the remaining most difficult case of mixed characteristic. The PI hopes that in the future this tool will help to unravel the geometric meaning in the Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity of a singularity.  The second project concerns Koszul homology of ideals, a widely studied invariant of the singularity of the curve, surface, or higher dimensional object given by the ideals. The main accomplishment of this project is the extension of a classic duality theorem for certain very special ideals to a duality theorem that holds for all singularities! In addition, the machinery involved in establishing this duality was also investigated intensely to obtain more subtle results under certain conditions, extending those known by other techniques. This project is leading the investigator and coauthors to more difficult questions, with partial results, towards understanding these fundamental invariants better.   In the third project, the outcome generalizes results on the torsion and cotorsion of the module of p-differentials, an important invariant of local hypersurface singularities, to the case of a local complete intersection singularities. This extends long-known results to cases where the singularities are not necessarily isolated point, but can lie along ridges, or other higher dimensional subvarieties.  This grant has also enabled the PI to be heavily involved in mentoring and in contributing to communication:  1) Co-organizer for Route 81 Conference in Commutative Algebra and Algebraic Geometry, Syracuse.  2) Co-organizer for the NSF-funded conference "Interactions between Commutative Algebra and Representation Theory", Syracuse.  3) Co-organizer of 3 Special Sessions, at AWM meeting and AMS meetings, one designed to build a bridge between areas.  4) PhD advisor to 3 graduate students, and possible 2 more soon.  6) Faculty co-advisor for the Syracuse University Math Clu...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
