<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Secure Logistics Curriculum Enhancement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>344055.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>344055</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Valerie Barr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ongoing work with industry and educational representatives has voiced a strong need for more specific training on logistics security at all levels in the logistics workforce, as well as relevant, practical materials based on best practices and industry experiences. This project expands existing curricula to include more advanced topics and continuing education in direct response to industry demand and furthers collaborative efforts with other institutions. Working extensively with industry partners, this project is developing targeted learning materials that focus on the various strategies and best practices used to safely and securely transfer goods from the manufacturer to the consumer.   Planned learning materials include curriculum modules, case studies and classroom exercises that focus on applied logistics and logistics security. Faculty from two other colleges are involved to identify and document relevant, comprehensive case and classroom exercise scenarios that enhance the learning experience by providing real-world, level-of-experience appropriate examples for students. These learning materials are being integrated into an existing logistics degree and certificate program. The dissemination of the developed materials, to other adopters who desire to use them in similar programs, is web-based.  Curriculum modules focused on industry best practices in secure logistics is based on discussions with local and statewide transportation authorities, and in addition to being added to the existing program curricula and web-based resources, it is made available to local and statewide industry members for educating management as well as workers at all levels of the organization.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1003507</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erika</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowles</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erika A Bowles</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebowles@tacomacc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2535665253</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000064547</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tacoma Community College</Name>
<CityName>Tacoma</CityName>
<ZipCode>984666100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2535665022</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6501 South 19th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041826798</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TACOMA COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041826798</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tacoma Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Tacoma</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>984666100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6501 South 19th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~344055</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="tinyMCEContent">Under this grant funding, a series of seventeen applied case studies were developed for use by instructors and students in 2-4 year college programs in logistics and supply chain management.&nbsp; The case study titles are as follows:<br /> <table border="1"> <tbody> <tr> <td> <p>Safeway - "Trash to Cash"</p> <p>OfficeMax DC Consolidation</p> <p>Carolina Sporting Goods</p> <p>Port of Nhava Sheva</p> <p>Port of Tacoma "Boom or Bust"</p> <p>Darigold Reengineering</p> <p>Northern Triangle Recreation</p> <p>Detention Limited</p> <p>Warehouse Performance</p> </td> <td> <p>Port of Tacoma Trucking Congestion</p> <p>Elgiganten Electronics</p> <p>Managing the 'Cool Chain'</p> <p>Monitoring the "Cool Chain"</p> <p>Aerotropolis</p> <p>Short-haul Truckers - Orphans of the Logistics Industry</p> <p>MicroTablets</p> <p>Lenovo</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to tne case studies, a report "An Enquiry into Experiences, Funding, and Best Practices in Port Security in Washington and Oregon' was developed.</p> <p>A course "Logistics Security" was also developed and added to the Logistics curriculum previously developed under an earlier related grant.</p> <p>All seventeen case studies, the report on Port Security, as well as all of the coursework completed by this and the previous related grant were catalogued at NSF ATE Central making them available to users of this online library.&nbsp; In the first year of the availability of the case studies, report, and curriculum through ATE Central, 65 downloads were reported.</p> <p>The most popular downloads were:</p> <p>LOG 104: Applied Warehouse and Inventory Management&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: The Aerotropolis&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: Port of Tacoma Trucking Congestion&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: Port of Nhava Sheva Congestion&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: Darigold Reengineering - "The Perfect Order Project"&nbsp;</p> <p>LOG 110: International Trade&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: Lenovo&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: Office Max Customer Fulfillment Center (CFC) Consolidation&nbsp;</p> <p>Case Study: Managing the "Cool Chain"&nbsp;</p> <p>LOG 115: Logistics Security and Risk Management <strong><br /> </strong></p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2014<br>      Modified by: Erika&nbsp;A&nbsp;Bowles</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Under this grant funding, a series of seventeen applied case studies were developed for use by instructors and students in 2-4 year college programs in logistics and supply chain management.  The case study titles are as follows:       Safeway - "Trash to Cash"  OfficeMax DC Consolidation  Carolina Sporting Goods  Port of Nhava Sheva  Port of Tacoma "Boom or Bust"  Darigold Reengineering  Northern Triangle Recreation  Detention Limited  Warehouse Performance    Port of Tacoma Trucking Congestion  Elgiganten Electronics  Managing the 'Cool Chain'  Monitoring the "Cool Chain"  Aerotropolis  Short-haul Truckers - Orphans of the Logistics Industry  MicroTablets  Lenovo         In addition to tne case studies, a report "An Enquiry into Experiences, Funding, and Best Practices in Port Security in Washington and Oregon' was developed.  A course "Logistics Security" was also developed and added to the Logistics curriculum previously developed under an earlier related grant.  All seventeen case studies, the report on Port Security, as well as all of the coursework completed by this and the previous related grant were catalogued at NSF ATE Central making them available to users of this online library.  In the first year of the availability of the case studies, report, and curriculum through ATE Central, 65 downloads were reported.  The most popular downloads were:  LOG 104: Applied Warehouse and Inventory Management   Case Study: The Aerotropolis   Case Study: Port of Tacoma Trucking Congestion   Case Study: Port of Nhava Sheva Congestion   Case Study: Darigold Reengineering - "The Perfect Order Project"   LOG 110: International Trade   Case Study: Lenovo   Case Study: Office Max Customer Fulfillment Center (CFC) Consolidation   Case Study: Managing the "Cool Chain"   LOG 115: Logistics Security and Risk Management           Last Modified: 08/18/2014       Submitted by: Erika A Bowles]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
