<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1004610</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Koytcheff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin M Koytcheff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2022883678</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Koytcheff               Robin          M</Name>
<CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>940253203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Koytcheff               Robin          M]]></Name>
<CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940253203</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~135000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Introduction</strong></p> <p>This project concerned the area of topology, particularly the study of embedding spaces, such as spaces of knots and links.&nbsp; Topology is the study of &ldquo;flexible properties&rdquo; of spaces, and embedding spaces are very large spaces. The results of this project established/verified two important principles:</p> <p>(1) &nbsp;One can understand embedding spaces (and perhaps other large spaces) via certain geometric and algebraic methods. &nbsp;The methods used in this project can be summarized as (a) utilizing <em>configuration spaces</em> and (b) studying <em>operations</em> on spaces, analogous to multiplication.</p> <p>(2) &nbsp;Studying the <em>space of all objects</em> (e.g., the space of all knots) reveals information about those objects (knots) themselves. &nbsp;</p> <p>Understanding large spaces in general is especially interesting in view of the large data sets that technology now provides us. &nbsp;Recently, algebraic topology has revealed patterns that were unseen by previous methods (e.g., in genetic data related to cancer incidences). &nbsp;This recent work on large data also provides a way of describing principle (2) above in more concrete terms: one can, for example, better understand an individual's genetic traits by looking the genetic traits of the whole population. &nbsp;The development of methods in studying embedding spaces may provide insight into other large spaces too.</p> <p>Furthermore, embedding spaces themselves arise in applications.&nbsp; In fact, the simplest embedding space is a configuration space, which consists of points that cannot collide.&nbsp; These arise in robotics (as spaces of robots avoiding collisions), as well as fluid dynamics and quantum physics. &nbsp;Beyond showing their importance in&nbsp;studying the larger embedding spaces of knots and links, this project helped gain some insight into configuration spaces themselves.</p> <p><strong>Knots, links, and spaces of knots/links</strong></p> <p>The study of spaces of knots and links is a generalization of classical knot theory. The original problem of knot theory is to tell whether a string can be untangled.&nbsp; For example, can one untangle the string shown in Figure 1 without moving the endpoints of the string?&nbsp; If not, can one prove that it is impossible to do so?&nbsp; More generally, given two knots (such as Figures 1 and 2), one wants to know if they are the same knot type, that is, if the first one can be untangled to look like the second one.&nbsp; A <em>knot invariant</em> is a formula that produces a number for any knot, such that the number depends only on the knot type.&nbsp; One can ask analogous questions for links, which are like knots but with multiple tangled strings (Figures 3 and 4). &nbsp;Studying the <em>space</em> of knots means understanding not just knot types, but <em>families</em> of knots. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Configuration spaces and knots/links</strong></p> <p>Much of the work in this project generalized the linking number of Gauss.&nbsp; Gauss integrated over configuration spaces to measure the linking of two closed curves.&nbsp; One can also obtain this linking number by counting crossings (Figure 5). &nbsp;In the 1990&rsquo;s, Bott and Taubes constructed <em>knot</em> invariants from configuration spaces, using the perspective of the space of knots.&nbsp; Their methods later produced&nbsp;<em>cohomology classes</em> in spaces of knots, which are numbers associated to families of knots.&nbsp; In my PhD thesis, I constructed classes which are integers rather than arbitrary real numbers.&nbsp; In this project, I made progress towards recovering the invariants of previous authors; completing this goal would show that these numbers count something, like Gauss&rsquo; linking integral counts crossings in a link diagram.&nbsp;</p> <p>This progress built on joint work with Munson and Volic undert...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Introduction  This project concerned the area of topology, particularly the study of embedding spaces, such as spaces of knots and links.  Topology is the study of "flexible properties" of spaces, and embedding spaces are very large spaces. The results of this project established/verified two important principles:  (1)  One can understand embedding spaces (and perhaps other large spaces) via certain geometric and algebraic methods.  The methods used in this project can be summarized as (a) utilizing configuration spaces and (b) studying operations on spaces, analogous to multiplication.  (2)  Studying the space of all objects (e.g., the space of all knots) reveals information about those objects (knots) themselves.    Understanding large spaces in general is especially interesting in view of the large data sets that technology now provides us.  Recently, algebraic topology has revealed patterns that were unseen by previous methods (e.g., in genetic data related to cancer incidences).  This recent work on large data also provides a way of describing principle (2) above in more concrete terms: one can, for example, better understand an individual's genetic traits by looking the genetic traits of the whole population.  The development of methods in studying embedding spaces may provide insight into other large spaces too.  Furthermore, embedding spaces themselves arise in applications.  In fact, the simplest embedding space is a configuration space, which consists of points that cannot collide.  These arise in robotics (as spaces of robots avoiding collisions), as well as fluid dynamics and quantum physics.  Beyond showing their importance in studying the larger embedding spaces of knots and links, this project helped gain some insight into configuration spaces themselves.  Knots, links, and spaces of knots/links  The study of spaces of knots and links is a generalization of classical knot theory. The original problem of knot theory is to tell whether a string can be untangled.  For example, can one untangle the string shown in Figure 1 without moving the endpoints of the string?  If not, can one prove that it is impossible to do so?  More generally, given two knots (such as Figures 1 and 2), one wants to know if they are the same knot type, that is, if the first one can be untangled to look like the second one.  A knot invariant is a formula that produces a number for any knot, such that the number depends only on the knot type.  One can ask analogous questions for links, which are like knots but with multiple tangled strings (Figures 3 and 4).  Studying the space of knots means understanding not just knot types, but families of knots.    Configuration spaces and knots/links  Much of the work in this project generalized the linking number of Gauss.  Gauss integrated over configuration spaces to measure the linking of two closed curves.  One can also obtain this linking number by counting crossings (Figure 5).  In the 1990Æs, Bott and Taubes constructed knot invariants from configuration spaces, using the perspective of the space of knots.  Their methods later produced cohomology classes in spaces of knots, which are numbers associated to families of knots.  In my PhD thesis, I constructed classes which are integers rather than arbitrary real numbers.  In this project, I made progress towards recovering the invariants of previous authors; completing this goal would show that these numbers count something, like GaussÆ linking integral counts crossings in a link diagram.   This progress built on joint work with Munson and Volic undertaken during this project, where we constructed "higher invariants" of links via configuration space integrals.  For an example of such an invariant, consider the Borromean rings (Figure 6).  Each pair of circles is unlinked, but the Milnor triple linking number detects that the three circles cannot be pulled apart.  Our work used the space of links, but the results pertain to links themselves.  This w...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
