<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Egypt Cooperative Research: Health Hazards due to Radiation from Mobile Base Stations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rapid growth of wireless communications and applications has necessitated the construction and ongoing maintenance of a large number of mobile base stations. These stations emit a radiation pattern that varies spatially and can pose a serious health hazard to the human body through radiation absorption. Global standard safety limits, which are determined by specific absorption rates, are set to regulate the interaction of antenna radiation with the human body. RF/microwaves emitted from the base stations are several orders of magnitude greater than handheld devices and pose potential health risks to people who live near these stations and those who install and maintain these stations can potentially be at risk. The main objective of this proposal is to develop a user friendly software simulation environment that will accurately and quickly calculate the health effects of base station radiation. Rather than using human subjects and measuring the radiation directly, the proposed work will employ a simulation package that will quickly and efficiently simulate the radiation field from a mobile base station and use that information to calculate specific absorption rates for a human body. To achieve these goals, the PI will collaborate with Dr. Hala Abdel Monem Elsadek and Dr. Hesham Ezzat Salem Eldeeb from the Electronics Research Institute, Giza, Egypt. Prior collaboration between these researchers yielded a simulation package and a parallel processing scheme that will enable the complex calculations and modeling to simulate the health effects and by hosting this environment of the institute's websites the project will enable other researchers to use and collect simulated radiation effects data. .&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit.  The biological effects of electromagnetic radiations present an important and challenging problem from technical, social, economical and legal points of view. This work employs an innovative approach to use numerical techniques to simulate the radiation field emitted from a base station and to calculate the radiation absorption rates without using human subjects. Coupling a simulation package with parallel processing schemes will allow these calculations to be made accurately and quickly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts.  The proposed work builds on several years of discussions and research between US and Egyptian scientists on the development of numerical modeling techniques and parallel computing schemes. This project will provide the opportunity to further this collaboration and to develop new applications for these techniques and scheme that may be effective in improving safety of mobile base stations and reduce the risk to human health. For US junior scientists and students, this project will provide opportunities for scientific and cultural exchange. Early career Egyptian scientists and students will be trained at the University of California-Irvine with support from the Egyptian side.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is funded under the US-Egypt Joint Fund Program, which provides grants to scientists and engineers in both countries to undertake cooperative research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1004355</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nader</FirstName>
<LastName>Bagherzadeh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nader Bagherzadeh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nader@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498248720</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000367188</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J292</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5944</Code>
<Text>EGYPT (COOP SCIENCE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As the technology for mobile devices such as cell phones improves in terms of providing new services, that helps users address new features, it needs to have more powerful antennas.&nbsp; Mobile devices antennas radiate energy and receive energy as part of their functionality. &nbsp;Having such a concentrated and powerful source of radiation near human body and close to the head of a person is of great concern.&nbsp; There have been many studies for the potential health hazard risks due to increasing use of cellular phones.&nbsp; These studies have not been conclusive and have not been repeated for newer technologies</p> <p>One of the major shortcomings of these studies is lack of accurate modeling of the antenna radiation. Precise software techniques must be developed to evaluate radiation on human skull.&nbsp; Majority of these methods require many hours of calculations on ordinary computers.&nbsp;</p> <p>What we have done for this project is to improve the software and find ways of making the software work on more powerful computers that have many resources working together.&nbsp; The work done for this project greatly impacts the design of the next generation cellular phones, allowing designers to use tools such as ours to accurately analyze their designs and evaluate the potential health hazards due to antenna radiation, and find ways of improving their products.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2013<br>      Modified by: Nader&nbsp;Bagherzadeh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1004355/1004355_10031192_1384343874660_withphone--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1004355/1004355_10031192_1384343874660_withphone--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Effects of radiation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1004355/1004355_10031192_1384343874660_withphone--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Effects of radiation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">It shows how radiation impacts a person's head</div> <div class="imageCredit">Internet</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nader&nbsp;Bagherzadeh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Effects of radiation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1004355/1004355_10031192_1384343951805_image2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1004355/1004355_10031192_1384343951805_image2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cell phone and the tower"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1004355/1004355_10031192_1384343951805_image2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cell phone and the tower"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This one shows how the radiation is spread from the cell tower</div> <div class="imageCredit">Internet</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nader&nbsp;Bagherzadeh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cell phone and the tower</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As the technology for mobile devices such as cell phones improves in terms of providing new services, that helps users address new features, it needs to have more powerful antennas.  Mobile devices antennas radiate energy and receive energy as part of their functionality.  Having such a concentrated and powerful source of radiation near human body and close to the head of a person is of great concern.  There have been many studies for the potential health hazard risks due to increasing use of cellular phones.  These studies have not been conclusive and have not been repeated for newer technologies  One of the major shortcomings of these studies is lack of accurate modeling of the antenna radiation. Precise software techniques must be developed to evaluate radiation on human skull.  Majority of these methods require many hours of calculations on ordinary computers.   What we have done for this project is to improve the software and find ways of making the software work on more powerful computers that have many resources working together.  The work done for this project greatly impacts the design of the next generation cellular phones, allowing designers to use tools such as ours to accurately analyze their designs and evaluate the potential health hazards due to antenna radiation, and find ways of improving their products.        Last Modified: 11/13/2013       Submitted by: Nader Bagherzadeh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
