<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Summer Undergraduate Research Experience in Physics at the University of Michigan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>258400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>258400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the REU site in the Physics Department at the University of Michigan.   The site will support ten students per summer in a variety of physics-related research.   REU students take part in every aspect of the research group's scientific work and social activities, and pursue individual research projects under the supervision of an experienced faculty member. The REU students are fully integrated into the research group and will interact closely with other Michigan undergraduates, graduate students and postdocs as well as their faculty supervisor.   In addition to their own research, the REU students are exposed to a variety of research topics and methodologies through a series of research seminars. To assist in their professional development, students also participate in tutorials on ethics, applying to graduate school and giving scientific presentations.   Towards the end of the summer program, the students present their results to their peers and faculty mentors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1004415</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James T Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jimliu@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347634314</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000298364</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~83600</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~86100</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~88700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The University of Michigan Department of Physics has a long tradition of undergraduate research, and since the early 1990&rsquo;s it has offered an REU program to a diverse set of students from around the country.&nbsp; Over the three-year period of this award, the REU Site brought in a total of 29 students from a variety of institutions, including many from small liberal arts colleges, and provided them with a summer research experience in a major research department.</p> <p>While the main focus of the REU Site is on providing a transformative research experience involving one-on-one interactions with a world-class faculty mentor, the students were also exposed to a variety of professional development and enrichment activities.&nbsp; These included weekly research seminars, discussions on the responsible conduct of research, on scientific writing and presentations, and on the graduate school experience.&nbsp; Professional training also included instruction in laboratory safety and a highly regarded machine shop course.&nbsp; As identified by the students, one of the highlights of the REU experience was a field trip to Fermilab where they were able to interact directly with scientists at a major national research facility.</p> <p>At the end of each summer, the students presented their summer research in a joint REU symposium involving several REU Sites at the University of Michigan.&nbsp; In this way, the students were able to put their projects in perspective in the context of a larger research community.&nbsp; The entire summer program, from research in the laboratory to writing scientific reports and presenting at the symposium, provided a rewarding experience and an introduction to what a scientific career would entail.</p> <p>One of the aims of this REU Site is to provide a meaningful research experience to students with little prior research experience and with limited opportunities to participate in research at their home institutions.&nbsp; This is meant to introduce them to the possibility of having a rewarding career in Physics in particular and the STEM fields in general.&nbsp; Based on student surveys, this program has succeeded in having the students gain confidence in performing research and in their own abilities to function independently in a laboratory setting.&nbsp; Moreover, of the 29 students covered by this award, 24 have indeed gone on to graduate school in the STEM fields.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/08/2014<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;T&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The University of Michigan Department of Physics has a long tradition of undergraduate research, and since the early 1990Æs it has offered an REU program to a diverse set of students from around the country.  Over the three-year period of this award, the REU Site brought in a total of 29 students from a variety of institutions, including many from small liberal arts colleges, and provided them with a summer research experience in a major research department.  While the main focus of the REU Site is on providing a transformative research experience involving one-on-one interactions with a world-class faculty mentor, the students were also exposed to a variety of professional development and enrichment activities.  These included weekly research seminars, discussions on the responsible conduct of research, on scientific writing and presentations, and on the graduate school experience.  Professional training also included instruction in laboratory safety and a highly regarded machine shop course.  As identified by the students, one of the highlights of the REU experience was a field trip to Fermilab where they were able to interact directly with scientists at a major national research facility.  At the end of each summer, the students presented their summer research in a joint REU symposium involving several REU Sites at the University of Michigan.  In this way, the students were able to put their projects in perspective in the context of a larger research community.  The entire summer program, from research in the laboratory to writing scientific reports and presenting at the symposium, provided a rewarding experience and an introduction to what a scientific career would entail.  One of the aims of this REU Site is to provide a meaningful research experience to students with little prior research experience and with limited opportunities to participate in research at their home institutions.  This is meant to introduce them to the possibility of having a rewarding career in Physics in particular and the STEM fields in general.  Based on student surveys, this program has succeeded in having the students gain confidence in performing research and in their own abilities to function independently in a laboratory setting.  Moreover, of the 29 students covered by this award, 24 have indeed gone on to graduate school in the STEM fields.          Last Modified: 03/08/2014       Submitted by: James T Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
