<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Energy Density Plasmas in Ultrafast Micro-Capillary Discharges</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>591000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>591000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Important plasma applications depend on the ability to generate hot and dense plasma columns of high homogeneity. This project studies the efficient generation of extremely hot and dense uniform plasma columns consisting in the rapid excitation of micro-capillary channels with ultrafast (&lt; 3 ns risetime) current pulses with current densities exceeding 0.5 Giga-Amperes cm-2. Model simulations suggest this new concept has the potential to heat dense homogenous  plasma columns to very high electron temperatures (500-1000 eV) using only modest currents. Experiments and simulations will be combined to elucidate the fundamental aspects of the dynamics of these high power density micro-capillary plasmas and optimize their generation for applications. The understanding of the physics of these discharges and their scaling laws can potentially impact the way in which hot dense plasmas are generated for numerous applications. These include the development of compact X-ray lasers, very highly ionized plasma waveguides for high intensity laser-plasma interactions, the generation of high harmonic from ions, and other high density plasma applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research and educational activities are designed to have a broad impact in the training of students and young scientists in different stages of their career, ranging from high school to post-doctoral fellows. Significant efforts will be conducted to attract a diverse group of students into science and engineering by continuing our research collaboration with minority serving Colleges and the Colorado AGEP program. The participating graduate and undergraduate students will be involved in an experimental and theoretical effort that will include aspects of discharge physics, advanced discharge technology, spectroscopy and advanced modeling of plasmas. The broader impact will be enhanced by the participation of high school students, and middle school and high school teachers during the summer.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1004295</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
<LastName>Rocca</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jorge J Rocca</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rocca@engr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704918371</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vyacheslav</FirstName>
<LastName>Shlyaptsev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vyacheslav Shlyaptsev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>snocturne2@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704918371</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516137</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S Howes St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~411000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Creating Plasma Columns with Extreme Ionization by Heating Micro-Capillary Channels with Ultrafast Discharges </strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The efficient generation of hot and highly homogeneous narrow plasma columns is a challenging problem of significant interest for important applications. These include the development of new compact soft x-ray lasers, the generation of<strong> </strong>plasma channels to guide intense laser beams for particle acceleration, and neutron production. &nbsp;Pulsed electrical discharges are the simplest method to create hot, dense plasmas by direct transfer of electromagnetic energy into plasma heating. However, dense, large-scale plasmas with electron temperatures of several million degrees have typically required the use of large pulsed power machines producing mega ampere level currents.&nbsp; Moreover, severe plasma column distortions arising from non-uniform compression of the plasma by the electromagnetic forces and large-scale instabilities have limited their use in applications requiring high plasma uniformity. We have previously shown that discharges generated by injecting moderately fast current pulses in capillary channels a few millimeter diameters can generate hot plasma columns of remarkable uniformity that meet the demanding stability requirements necessary to produce highly coherent soft x-ray laser beams. However, applications such as the development of sub-10 nm wavelength lasers -more than 50 times shorter than the wavelength of visible light- require the efficient generation of axially uniform plasma columns that are significantly hotter and more highly ionized.&nbsp; Such scaling is a major challenge, in particular for plasmas containing highly ionized heavy atoms.&nbsp; These heavy ions emit large amounts of short wavelength incoherent light, which amounts to a large energy loss that cools the plasma.</p> <p>In this NSF project experiments and simulations were conducted to demonstrate the efficient generation of hot plasma columns with an extremely high degree of ionization by rapid resistive heating of gas-filled microcapillary channels of sub-millimeter diameter with ultrafast current pulses of unusually low amplitude. Contrary to the case of discharges in larger diameter channels, in this ultrafast micro-capillary discharge regime the dominant plasma heating source is resistive (ohmic) heating, resembling the electric current heating of the filament of an incandescent light bulb. The&nbsp;kinetic energy of the column still contributes to the heating of the plasma core, but it is not the major heat source in the energy balance. By decreasing the channel diameter we decrease the cross sectional area by two orders of magnitude with respect to conventional capillary discharges. The resulting increase in current density allows us to reach temperatures several times higher than those achieved in conventional capillary discharges excited with similar peak currents. This new approach was successfully used to reduce by nearly an order of magnitude the current necessary to heat dense homogeneous plasma columns</p> <p>Results published in Physical Review Letters [1] show for the first time that high-aspect-ratio capillary plasma columns with extremely high degree of ionization can be generated by a modest current pulse in a compact discharge device. Injection of ultrafast current pulses of relatively modest amplitude and current rises of a few billionths of a second into 0.5 millimeter diameter gas-filled capillary channels generated xenon plasma columns in which the atoms were ionized 28 times. &nbsp;When a small amount of xenon was introduced in hydrogen micro-capillary discharges the xenon atoms were observed to be ionized up to 30 times (Fig.1). &nbsp;Spectra from these plasmas agree with those resulting from simulations that predict on-axis electron temperatures of several million kelvin degrees. Sequences...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Creating Plasma Columns with Extreme Ionization by Heating Micro-Capillary Channels with Ultrafast Discharges      The efficient generation of hot and highly homogeneous narrow plasma columns is a challenging problem of significant interest for important applications. These include the development of new compact soft x-ray lasers, the generation of plasma channels to guide intense laser beams for particle acceleration, and neutron production.  Pulsed electrical discharges are the simplest method to create hot, dense plasmas by direct transfer of electromagnetic energy into plasma heating. However, dense, large-scale plasmas with electron temperatures of several million degrees have typically required the use of large pulsed power machines producing mega ampere level currents.  Moreover, severe plasma column distortions arising from non-uniform compression of the plasma by the electromagnetic forces and large-scale instabilities have limited their use in applications requiring high plasma uniformity. We have previously shown that discharges generated by injecting moderately fast current pulses in capillary channels a few millimeter diameters can generate hot plasma columns of remarkable uniformity that meet the demanding stability requirements necessary to produce highly coherent soft x-ray laser beams. However, applications such as the development of sub-10 nm wavelength lasers -more than 50 times shorter than the wavelength of visible light- require the efficient generation of axially uniform plasma columns that are significantly hotter and more highly ionized.  Such scaling is a major challenge, in particular for plasmas containing highly ionized heavy atoms.  These heavy ions emit large amounts of short wavelength incoherent light, which amounts to a large energy loss that cools the plasma.  In this NSF project experiments and simulations were conducted to demonstrate the efficient generation of hot plasma columns with an extremely high degree of ionization by rapid resistive heating of gas-filled microcapillary channels of sub-millimeter diameter with ultrafast current pulses of unusually low amplitude. Contrary to the case of discharges in larger diameter channels, in this ultrafast micro-capillary discharge regime the dominant plasma heating source is resistive (ohmic) heating, resembling the electric current heating of the filament of an incandescent light bulb. The kinetic energy of the column still contributes to the heating of the plasma core, but it is not the major heat source in the energy balance. By decreasing the channel diameter we decrease the cross sectional area by two orders of magnitude with respect to conventional capillary discharges. The resulting increase in current density allows us to reach temperatures several times higher than those achieved in conventional capillary discharges excited with similar peak currents. This new approach was successfully used to reduce by nearly an order of magnitude the current necessary to heat dense homogeneous plasma columns  Results published in Physical Review Letters [1] show for the first time that high-aspect-ratio capillary plasma columns with extremely high degree of ionization can be generated by a modest current pulse in a compact discharge device. Injection of ultrafast current pulses of relatively modest amplitude and current rises of a few billionths of a second into 0.5 millimeter diameter gas-filled capillary channels generated xenon plasma columns in which the atoms were ionized 28 times.  When a small amount of xenon was introduced in hydrogen micro-capillary discharges the xenon atoms were observed to be ionized up to 30 times (Fig.1).  Spectra from these plasmas agree with those resulting from simulations that predict on-axis electron temperatures of several million kelvin degrees. Sequences of time-resolved soft x-ray images of the plasma column acquired with a pinhole camera show the formation of homogeneous plasma channels with &gt; 300:1 length...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
