<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Ergodic Theory of Decisions Under Partial Information</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>145594.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>145594</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is concerned with sequential decision problems under partial information.  In such problems, decisions must be made sequentially in time. The decision maker has access to an observed component of an ergodic Markov process, but the cost of her decisions is determined also by the unobserved part of the process.  The decision maker aims to minimize the long time average cost by the choice of a strategy that is adapted to the filtration generated by the observations only.  The goal of the project is to characterize the fundamental properties of optimal decisions, such as pathwise optimality and ergodic theorems, and to investigate certain sub-optimal decision algorithms which can be efficiently implemented in practice.  The research will build on and extend recent advances in the ergodic theory of nonlinear filters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partially observed stochastic systems are ubiquitous in a wide range of disciplines including signal processing, communications, navigation and tracking, robotics, data assimilation and forecasting, bioinformatics, physics, economics and finance.  In such problems, one is faced with two major difficulties: uncertainty in the dynamics of the system of interest, and the limited availability of information.  This project aims to understand how one can best make decisions in an uncertain environment when only partial information is available.  The development of a mathematical theory characterizing the properties of optimal decisions can help elucidate the fundamental limitations one faces in making decisions with limited information, as well as lead to practical algorithms for making near-optimal decisions which can be used in applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1005575</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramon</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Handel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramon Van Handel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rvan@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000548947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Adm]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7552</Code>
<Text>COFFES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~145594</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The problem of making decisions is ubiquitous in all areas of human endeavor. &nbsp;Decisions must often be made sequentially in time: in each time period we must choose an action, on the basis of the available information to date, that will affect what happens in the next time period. &nbsp;Our ability to make good decisions is limited by three distinct effects: the unpredictability of the future (randomness); the complexity of the set of possible decisions; and the information available to the decision maker. A core aim of the present research is to develop a general understanding of the interactions between these key effects.</p> <p>While eminently practical of origin, such problems motivate fundamental mathematical questions in the theory of probability. &nbsp;The effect of partial information is far from well understood, and leads to unique paradoxes in the context of decision problems. &nbsp;More generally, the interactions between randomness, complexity, and information lie at the heart of many practical as well as mathematical questions. &nbsp;The results of this research provide a theory that explains when it is possible to choose decision strategies that are optimal in a "typical" time period, and yield practical methods to implement such decisions. &nbsp;On the other hand, the investigation of such problems has led to developments connecting decision problems in novel ways to other areas of mathematics, and to new mathematical tools that can be used to address a broader range of problems in different areas. &nbsp;Of particular importance are new techniques that make it possible to begin to address, both mathematically and practically, increasingly complex problems with partial information that arise in very high-dimensional systems (motivated by applications such as weather forecasting).</p> <p>Beside the scientific component of the research, the present grant has supported the training and development of a much needed STEM workforce, including two new Ph.D.'s and numerous undergraduate students who are now pursuing further studies at the graduate level, as well as the development of freely available educational materials on advanced topics in probability theory.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2013<br>      Modified by: Ramon&nbsp;Van Handel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The problem of making decisions is ubiquitous in all areas of human endeavor.  Decisions must often be made sequentially in time: in each time period we must choose an action, on the basis of the available information to date, that will affect what happens in the next time period.  Our ability to make good decisions is limited by three distinct effects: the unpredictability of the future (randomness); the complexity of the set of possible decisions; and the information available to the decision maker. A core aim of the present research is to develop a general understanding of the interactions between these key effects.  While eminently practical of origin, such problems motivate fundamental mathematical questions in the theory of probability.  The effect of partial information is far from well understood, and leads to unique paradoxes in the context of decision problems.  More generally, the interactions between randomness, complexity, and information lie at the heart of many practical as well as mathematical questions.  The results of this research provide a theory that explains when it is possible to choose decision strategies that are optimal in a "typical" time period, and yield practical methods to implement such decisions.  On the other hand, the investigation of such problems has led to developments connecting decision problems in novel ways to other areas of mathematics, and to new mathematical tools that can be used to address a broader range of problems in different areas.  Of particular importance are new techniques that make it possible to begin to address, both mathematically and practically, increasingly complex problems with partial information that arise in very high-dimensional systems (motivated by applications such as weather forecasting).  Beside the scientific component of the research, the present grant has supported the training and development of a much needed STEM workforce, including two new Ph.D.'s and numerous undergraduate students who are now pursuing further studies at the graduate level, as well as the development of freely available educational materials on advanced topics in probability theory.       Last Modified: 09/04/2013       Submitted by: Ramon Van Handel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
