<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>8th International LISA Symposium 2010; Stanford, CA; June 2010</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Beverly K. Berger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the 8th International LISA Symposium to be held at Stanford University in June 2010. The Symposium focuses on various aspects of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA), the NASA / European Space Agency space-based gravitational wave detection and observation project, expected to complement the NSF-funded ground-based gravitational wave observatory, LIGO, and other ground-based gravitational wave detectors. The Conference will include LISA Technology and Design, Astronomy/Astrophysics with LISA, Cosmology/Fundamental Physics with LISA, Data Analysis and simulations, LISA PathFinder, and ground-based and other space-based detectors. Plenary talks, contributed talks organized in two parallel sessions, and posters will be presented during the Symposium. The presentations will be collected in the Conference Proceedings to be published in a reviewed journal.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1005662</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Byer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert L Byer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>byer@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507230226</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1252</Code>
<Text>LIGO RESEARCH SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>LISA will be the space-based partner of NSF&rsquo;s ground based  gravitational wave observatory which is known as LIGO. &nbsp;Operating in  space, LISA will not be exposed to seismic noise which limits LIGO&rsquo;s  sensitivity at low frequencies, and it will thus open up an important  part of the gravitational wave spectrum that has not yet been  accessible.&nbsp; LISA, still in the planning stage, is being developed by an  international collaboration of partnering institutions which hold  periodic symposia for this purpose.</p> <p>Eighteen different countries were represented at the 8th  International LISA Symposium held at SLAC on the Stanford University  campus in June 2010. &nbsp;Throughout the 6 day symposium there were 376  registered participants, 92 of which were international Ph.D. candidate  students, and 108 local Ph.D. candidate students. Partial support from  NSF was used for 50% of the international students' travel and 50% for  domestic students' travel (including Canada). NSF funds provided meals  and transportation (SLAC is not on the main Stanford Campus) for 30  summer high school students and their 9 teachers who were participating  in the Stanford Office of Science Outreach Office's Summer Science  Program. There were invited guests such as the Director of SLAC, Final  Report: 1005662 Director of Physics, Stanford Dean of Research and Vice  Provost, and many faculty members from Stanford, Berkeley, and Caltech.</p> <p>The symposium provided an avenue for students and invited speakers to  present their up-to-the-minute results on their research for their LISA  projects. All told there was an estimate of 550 participants of the  week long symposium.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/24/2011<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Byer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ LISA will be the space-based partner of NSFÆs ground based  gravitational wave observatory which is known as LIGO.  Operating in  space, LISA will not be exposed to seismic noise which limits LIGOÆs  sensitivity at low frequencies, and it will thus open up an important  part of the gravitational wave spectrum that has not yet been  accessible.  LISA, still in the planning stage, is being developed by an  international collaboration of partnering institutions which hold  periodic symposia for this purpose.  Eighteen different countries were represented at the 8th  International LISA Symposium held at SLAC on the Stanford University  campus in June 2010.  Throughout the 6 day symposium there were 376  registered participants, 92 of which were international Ph.D. candidate  students, and 108 local Ph.D. candidate students. Partial support from  NSF was used for 50% of the international students' travel and 50% for  domestic students' travel (including Canada). NSF funds provided meals  and transportation (SLAC is not on the main Stanford Campus) for 30  summer high school students and their 9 teachers who were participating  in the Stanford Office of Science Outreach Office's Summer Science  Program. There were invited guests such as the Director of SLAC, Final  Report: 1005662 Director of Physics, Stanford Dean of Research and Vice  Provost, and many faculty members from Stanford, Berkeley, and Caltech.  The symposium provided an avenue for students and invited speakers to  present their up-to-the-minute results on their research for their LISA  projects. All told there was an estimate of 550 participants of the  week long symposium.       Last Modified: 06/24/2011       Submitted by: Robert L Byer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
