<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshops in Geometric Topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>67300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>67300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal is for continued NSF support of an established series of summer workshops in Geometric Topology. The proposal is for support of the 27th through 31st Annual Workshops in Geometric Topology to be held in 2010 through 2014. The workshops will be advertised nationally with NSF funding primarily used to support travel of active research mathematicians without current NSF support and graduate students working in geometric topology. The 2010 workshop will be held in Colorado Springs on June 10-12, with Colorado College serving as host; Rob Ghrist has agreed to be the principal speaker. The 2011 workshop will be hosted by Oregon State University and the 2012 workshop by Calvin College (Grand Rapids, Michigan). The hosts of the 2013 and 2014 workshops will be Brigham Young University and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, respectively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; A primary goal of these workshops is to provide mathematicians with active research programs but limited support an opportunity to discuss their work with others in the field. Another important goal is to expand the interests of the participants by having a nationally recognized expert discuss an area that is related to, but outside, the focus of their current work. A third goal is to provide a serious but informal research atmosphere in which graduate students in geometric topology can meet and learn from others in the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1005906</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerard</FirstName>
<LastName>Venema</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerard A Venema</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>venema@calvin.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6165266402</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318709</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>Garity</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis J Garity</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>garity@math.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417375138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000335834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
<LastName>Tinsley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frederick Tinsley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ftinsley@ccnode.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7193896544</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000400167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Guilbault</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig R Guilbault</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>craigg@uwm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142294586</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284576</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Swenson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric L Swenson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eric@math.byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8013787896</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000411425</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee</Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142294853</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O BOX 340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627906399</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O BOX 340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~13460</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~13460</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~13460</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~13460</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~13460</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF Grant DMS-1005906 funded the annual &ldquo;Workshops in Geometric Topology&rdquo; in the years 2010-2014; a no-cost extension allowed some unspent funds to help with the 2015 workshop as well. Nearly all funding was used to cover travel expenses of workshop participants, with most going to participants without other means of support. Graduate students and recent graduates were given special consideration for funding.</p> <p>The Geometric Topology Workshops provide an annual opportunity for active researchers and graduate students to interact in a setting that provides multiple tangible benefits, including: &nbsp;attending the lectures of the principal speaker to receive an in-depth introduction to important current streams of research being performed by nationally recognized experts; learning about a breadth of other research activities by attending shorter talks given by the other workshop participants; the opportunity to share their own work by giving talks in a congenial environment; and important time for informal discussion and interaction among participants and with the principal speaker. To further broaden the impact of the workshops, the talks of the principal speakers were recorded and posted to the internet.</p> <p>Colorado College hosted the 2010 workshop, which was held on their campus in Colorado Springs. Rob Ghrist of the University of Pennsylvania delivered the principal lectures on &ldquo;Topology Applied&rdquo;. Among the thirty-seven mathematicians attending the conference were eleven graduate students and two post-docs. Of these young mathematicians, four gave talks on their work.</p> <p>Brigham Young University hosted the 2011 workshop, which was held in Park City, UT. David Gabai of Princeton University lectured on &ldquo;The Topology of Ending Lamination Spaces&rdquo;. Among the twenty-nine mathematicians attending the conference were eleven graduate students and two post-docs. Three recent PhDs gave talks on their work.</p> <p>Oregon State University hosted the 2012 Workshop, which was held on their campus in Corvallis. Benson Farb of the University of Chicago delivered the principal lectures on several different topics in Geometric Topology and Geometric Group Theory. Among the thirty-three mathematicians attending the conference were thirteen graduate students and two post-docs. In addition to farb&rsquo;s lectures, there were twelve thirty-minute talks contributed by other workshop participants; two of those were by post-docs and one by a graduate student.</p> <p>Calvin College hosted the 2013 Workshop, which was held on their campus in Grand Rapids, Michigan. Pedro Ontaneda of Binghamton University delivered the principal lectures on his significant recent work on &ldquo;Riemannian Hyperbolization&rdquo;. Among the thirty-seven mathematicians attending the conference were seventeen graduate students along with an undergraduate from the host institution. Nine graduate students gave twenty-minute talks on research related to their dissertations.</p> <p>The University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee hosted the 2014 workshop. Kevin Whyte of the University of Illinois, Chicago provided the principal talks on &ldquo;Infinite Groups in Geometric Topology&rdquo;. Forty &nbsp;mathematicians attended, including one postdoc and nineteen graduate students, eight of whom gave talks on their research.</p> <p>The 2015 Workshop was partially funded by Grant DMS-1005906 via a no-cost extension. It was hosted at Texas Christian University in Fort Worth, Texas. The principal lecturer was Wolfgang L&uuml;ck of the University of Bonn and the Hausdorff Research Institute for Mathematics, who gave three lectures titled: &ldquo;Introduction to L2-invariants,&rdquo; &ldquo;Introduction to the Farrell-Jones Conjecture,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Some applications to 3-manifolds.&rdquo; Forty-two mathematicians attended the conference, including 17 graduate students and 5 postdocs. There were 22 contributed twenty-minute talks, of which 13 were given by students and 3 by postdocs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2016<br>      Modified by: Craig&nbsp;R&nbsp;Guilbault</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF Grant DMS-1005906 funded the annual "Workshops in Geometric Topology" in the years 2010-2014; a no-cost extension allowed some unspent funds to help with the 2015 workshop as well. Nearly all funding was used to cover travel expenses of workshop participants, with most going to participants without other means of support. Graduate students and recent graduates were given special consideration for funding.  The Geometric Topology Workshops provide an annual opportunity for active researchers and graduate students to interact in a setting that provides multiple tangible benefits, including:  attending the lectures of the principal speaker to receive an in-depth introduction to important current streams of research being performed by nationally recognized experts; learning about a breadth of other research activities by attending shorter talks given by the other workshop participants; the opportunity to share their own work by giving talks in a congenial environment; and important time for informal discussion and interaction among participants and with the principal speaker. To further broaden the impact of the workshops, the talks of the principal speakers were recorded and posted to the internet.  Colorado College hosted the 2010 workshop, which was held on their campus in Colorado Springs. Rob Ghrist of the University of Pennsylvania delivered the principal lectures on "Topology Applied". Among the thirty-seven mathematicians attending the conference were eleven graduate students and two post-docs. Of these young mathematicians, four gave talks on their work.  Brigham Young University hosted the 2011 workshop, which was held in Park City, UT. David Gabai of Princeton University lectured on "The Topology of Ending Lamination Spaces". Among the twenty-nine mathematicians attending the conference were eleven graduate students and two post-docs. Three recent PhDs gave talks on their work.  Oregon State University hosted the 2012 Workshop, which was held on their campus in Corvallis. Benson Farb of the University of Chicago delivered the principal lectures on several different topics in Geometric Topology and Geometric Group Theory. Among the thirty-three mathematicians attending the conference were thirteen graduate students and two post-docs. In addition to farb?s lectures, there were twelve thirty-minute talks contributed by other workshop participants; two of those were by post-docs and one by a graduate student.  Calvin College hosted the 2013 Workshop, which was held on their campus in Grand Rapids, Michigan. Pedro Ontaneda of Binghamton University delivered the principal lectures on his significant recent work on "Riemannian Hyperbolization". Among the thirty-seven mathematicians attending the conference were seventeen graduate students along with an undergraduate from the host institution. Nine graduate students gave twenty-minute talks on research related to their dissertations.  The University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee hosted the 2014 workshop. Kevin Whyte of the University of Illinois, Chicago provided the principal talks on "Infinite Groups in Geometric Topology". Forty  mathematicians attended, including one postdoc and nineteen graduate students, eight of whom gave talks on their research.  The 2015 Workshop was partially funded by Grant DMS-1005906 via a no-cost extension. It was hosted at Texas Christian University in Fort Worth, Texas. The principal lecturer was Wolfgang L&uuml;ck of the University of Bonn and the Hausdorff Research Institute for Mathematics, who gave three lectures titled: "Introduction to L2-invariants," "Introduction to the Farrell-Jones Conjecture," and "Some applications to 3-manifolds." Forty-two mathematicians attended the conference, including 17 graduate students and 5 postdocs. There were 22 contributed twenty-minute talks, of which 13 were given by students and 3 by postdocs.       Last Modified: 08/11/2016       Submitted by: Craig R Guilbault]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
