<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantitative Aberration-Corrected Observations of Magnetic Domain Walls in Multi-Ferroic Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>438799.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>446799</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:  Aberration-corrected Lorentz Transmission Electron Microscopy (LTEM) will be used to study magnetic domain wall behavior in a number of multi-ferroic materials, i.e. materials that exhibit multiple phase transitions, each giving rise to a fine-scale domain microstructure. The main focus of this research is on the interactions between the domain walls and other boundaries, such as twins and anti-phase boundaries. The alloys of choice are the ferromagnetic shape memory alloys with compositions near Ni2MnGa, and Fe-Pd alloys with around 30 at. % Pd. The research will consist mainly of experimental observations of domain walls under static and dynamic conditions, supported by image simulations based on micro-magnetic models. The research will be carried out on an aberration-corrected Titan 80-300 transmission electron microscope and will include in-situ magnetic fields applied to the samples. A newly developed experimental approach, vector-field electron tomography, will be applied to these materials to generate, for the first time, detailed three-dimensional views of the magnetization configurations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:  This project seeks to apply advanced microscopy methods to the study of magnetic materials, in order to improve the level of understanding of this important class of materials.  Magnets are ubiquitous in today's society, and an improved understanding of their behavior will impact a wide range of engineering applications, including magnetic recording media used in computer hard drives, and microscopic mechanical systems that make use of magnets. The outreach component of this project is called TACTILS (Teaching Advanced Characterization Tools In Local Schools), and will impact middle and high school science education in several schools in the Pittsburgh area by making portable electron microscopes available for use in local schools. Science teachers will have an opportunity to learn about these instruments and subsequently convey this new knowledge to the students in their own classrooms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1005330</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
<LastName>De Graef</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marc J De Graef</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>degraef@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122688527</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~161309</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~160860</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~124630</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project is entitled "Quantitative Aberration-Corrected&nbsp;Observations of Magnetic Domain Walls in&nbsp;Multi-Ferroic Materials". Multi-ferroic materials are materials that can undergo multiple changes as a function of an external stimulus, such as the combination of a magnetic field and an applied stress. In our case, we have studied the Ni<sub>2</sub>MnGa system, which can undergo a transition from non-magnetic to magnetic as well as a change of crystal structure upon cooling (see Figure "Crystal structure models for Ni2MnGa"). &nbsp;Magnetic domain walls are entities inside magnetic materials that separate regions in which the magnetic moments (essentially small bar magnets with a North and South pole) are oriented in different directions. &nbsp;These wall can move when a field is applied, but their movement can be hindered by the presence of other features (defects) in the crystal lattice. &nbsp;We have used transmission electron microscopy to study how these domain walls get around the crystal defects. &nbsp;The words "aberration-corrected" in the title refer to the fact that we have used an electron microscope with a set of extra lenses to correct spherical aberration (similar to the corrective optics that was mounted on the Hubble space telescope after launch, when it was found that the primary mirror was incorrectly ground and displayed spherical aberration). &nbsp;</p> <p>Figure "Example magnetic domain configuration" shows a typical result from our observations. &nbsp;The colored regions correspond to magnetic domains; the colorwheel on the right indicates the direction of the magnetic moment, for instance, in a yellow region the moment points upwards, in a green region it points towards the left. &nbsp;Across the zig-zag feature in the image, the magnetic moment reverses direction, whereas across the nearly vertical lines, the moment direction changes by 90 degrees.</p> <p>As part of the outreach activities in this project, we have made progress in three areas. &nbsp;We have created an educational web site (http://mpg.web.cmu.edu) with illustrations of all possible magnetic point symmetries; using mathematical models, one can show that there are 122 possible cases that are consistent with the symmetries of crystal lattices (the so-called "magnetic point groups"). The site allows the user to understand how these symmetries are put together (see example images in Figure "Magnetic symmetry illustrations"). &nbsp;The International Union for Crystallography has taken the information on this site and turned it into a Teaching Pamphlet (#23,&nbsp;http://www.iucr.org/education/pamphlets/23).</p> <p>A second result from our outreach is the publication of the second edition of an undergraduate text book on the Structure of Materials. &nbsp;Figure "Structure textbooks" shows the cover of this text book and its predecessor, which we have used at CMU at the Sophomore level, and is also widely used for undergraduate teaching of crystallography in the USA and abroad. &nbsp;We have recently completed the solution sets for more than 600 student problems and made them available to educators via the publisher's web site (Cambridge University Press).</p> <p>Finally, we have started a project called TACTILS (Teaching Advanced Characterization Tools In Local Schools), in which we provide training to high school science teachers to incorporate table top scanning electron microscopes in their lesson plans. &nbsp;We have provided two training workshops (Summer 2011 and 2012) for around 25 teachers. &nbsp;Example project images are shown in Figure "Micrometeorites", which displays two scanning electron microscope images of small meteorites which were extracted from the roof gutter of the house of one the teachers. &nbsp;These meteorites fall to the ground continuously, and are a nice example of the use of materials characterization tools at a level that is accessible to hi...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project is entitled "Quantitative Aberration-Corrected Observations of Magnetic Domain Walls in Multi-Ferroic Materials". Multi-ferroic materials are materials that can undergo multiple changes as a function of an external stimulus, such as the combination of a magnetic field and an applied stress. In our case, we have studied the Ni2MnGa system, which can undergo a transition from non-magnetic to magnetic as well as a change of crystal structure upon cooling (see Figure "Crystal structure models for Ni2MnGa").  Magnetic domain walls are entities inside magnetic materials that separate regions in which the magnetic moments (essentially small bar magnets with a North and South pole) are oriented in different directions.  These wall can move when a field is applied, but their movement can be hindered by the presence of other features (defects) in the crystal lattice.  We have used transmission electron microscopy to study how these domain walls get around the crystal defects.  The words "aberration-corrected" in the title refer to the fact that we have used an electron microscope with a set of extra lenses to correct spherical aberration (similar to the corrective optics that was mounted on the Hubble space telescope after launch, when it was found that the primary mirror was incorrectly ground and displayed spherical aberration).    Figure "Example magnetic domain configuration" shows a typical result from our observations.  The colored regions correspond to magnetic domains; the colorwheel on the right indicates the direction of the magnetic moment, for instance, in a yellow region the moment points upwards, in a green region it points towards the left.  Across the zig-zag feature in the image, the magnetic moment reverses direction, whereas across the nearly vertical lines, the moment direction changes by 90 degrees.  As part of the outreach activities in this project, we have made progress in three areas.  We have created an educational web site (http://mpg.web.cmu.edu) with illustrations of all possible magnetic point symmetries; using mathematical models, one can show that there are 122 possible cases that are consistent with the symmetries of crystal lattices (the so-called "magnetic point groups"). The site allows the user to understand how these symmetries are put together (see example images in Figure "Magnetic symmetry illustrations").  The International Union for Crystallography has taken the information on this site and turned it into a Teaching Pamphlet (#23, http://www.iucr.org/education/pamphlets/23).  A second result from our outreach is the publication of the second edition of an undergraduate text book on the Structure of Materials.  Figure "Structure textbooks" shows the cover of this text book and its predecessor, which we have used at CMU at the Sophomore level, and is also widely used for undergraduate teaching of crystallography in the USA and abroad.  We have recently completed the solution sets for more than 600 student problems and made them available to educators via the publisher's web site (Cambridge University Press).  Finally, we have started a project called TACTILS (Teaching Advanced Characterization Tools In Local Schools), in which we provide training to high school science teachers to incorporate table top scanning electron microscopes in their lesson plans.  We have provided two training workshops (Summer 2011 and 2012) for around 25 teachers.  Example project images are shown in Figure "Micrometeorites", which displays two scanning electron microscope images of small meteorites which were extracted from the roof gutter of the house of one the teachers.  These meteorites fall to the ground continuously, and are a nice example of the use of materials characterization tools at a level that is accessible to high school students.  The project web site is located at http://mpg.web.cmu.edu/TACTILS.html.             Last Modified: 09/25/2013       Submitted by: Marc J De Graef]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
