<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Investigation of Superconducting Nanowires and Graphene Junctions Using a Coplanar Fabry-Perot Microwave Resonator as a Qubit Device</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gtessema@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924935</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, it became clear that quantum mechanics, which is traditionally used to describe individual and small groups of elementary particles (e.g., electrons and atoms), can also predict the behavior of the so-called "mesoscopic" objects, i.e. systems containing a large number of atoms like large molecules or nanodevices.  The goal of this project is to investigate how the laws of quantum mechanics apply to nanowires.  These nanowires are metallic cylinders having a diameter of a few billionth of a meter.  The project will explore nanowires made out of superconducting metals.  The scientific question to be addressed is the applicability of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle to the electrical current and electrical charge in nanodevices involving nanowires.  The most advanced nanoscience and nanotechnology will be used to fabricate such wires.  The measurements on nanowires will be done using a novel experimental approach, namely a nanowire will be inserted into a special type of microwave resonator called a microwave superconducting Fabry-Perot resonator.  This project will explore the possibility of using the hybrid nanowire-resonator devices as qubits, the quantum mechanical analog of the classical "bit" that stores information in a computer.  This project will support the education of graduate students in these advanced technologies, which will prepare them for scientific careers in academia and in our most advanced technology industries.  Undergraduate students will also participate in the project, gaining training and hands-on experience in the most advanced scientific research.  The project will also provide training to a postdoc.  This research project receives support from the Division of Materials Research and the Physics Division.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, it became clear that macroscopic degrees of freedom, such as electrical current, can be described by laws of quantum mechanics for so-called mesoscopic systems: for example quantum mechanics is important for describing results of transport measurements in systems involving large molecules, nanoparticles, or superconducting nanodevices.  The goal of this project is to investigate how the laws of macroscopic quantum mechanics apply to superconducting nanowires.  In particular, quantum phase slips will be investigated.  A novel experimental approach will be used, namely the nanowires will be coupled to a superconducting microwave Fabry-Perot resonator.  Such a hybrid device will provide complementary experimental information when compared with traditional dc electrical transport measurements.  The nanowires are expected to act as nonlinear kinetic inductors.  This project will explore the possibility of using the hybrid nanowire-resonator devices as qubits.  Such nanowire-qubits should be free of the decoherence mechanisms affecting Josephson tunnel junction so far employed for superconducting qubits.  The nanowires will be fabricated and imaged by the most advanced nanotechnology.  The measurements will be carried out using ultra-low-temperature refrigerators and ultra-low-noise microwave measurements. This project will support the education of graduate students in these advanced technologies, which will prepare them for scientific careers in academia and in our most advanced technology industries.  Undergraduate students will also participate in the project, gaining training and hands-on experience in the most advanced scientific research.  The project will also provide training to a postdoc.  This research project receives support from the Division of Materials Research and the Physics Division.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1005645</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexey</FirstName>
<LastName>Bezryadin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexey Bezryadin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bezryadi@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173339580</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000104870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7281</Code>
<Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The list of the most significant achievements is as follows: (1) Development of a microwave or radiofrequency experimental setup to measure electrical characteristics of extremely thin wires, only about 20 to 100 atoms across. The setup involves a resonator, somewhat analogous to the Fabry-Perot resonator. Two types of resonator have been tested successfully, namely resonators made of very thin films, deposited on Si substrate and bulk microwave cavities, about one inch in size. (2) A method was developed&nbsp; that allows an independent microwave measurement of the critical temperature of the nanowire. The critical temperature is an important characteristics of the sample. It is the remperature at which the electrical resistance, as defined by Ohm's law, goes to zero. (3) A theoretically predicted formula that predicts how the critical current of a very thin wire changes with temperatures has been confirmed. The critical current is the maximum current up to which the resistance of the wire remains zero.&nbsp; (4) Single phase slips have been detected in superconducting wires for the first time. Their distributions have been studied, and the macroscopic quantum tunneling effect confirmed in homogeneous nanowires. The phase slip is an abrupt jump when the wire resistance becomes rather high for a short period of time so that the electrical current get reduced. The macroscopic quantum tunneling is the effect analogous to the ordinary quantum&nbsp; tunneling effect, but in the case the whole macroscopic electronic device experiences a significant change of its properties, in the cases when classical physics prohibits such changes. (5) A book summarizing the results obtained on superconducting nanowires was published. The reference is &ldquo;A. Bezryadin, "Superconductivity in Nanowires: Fabrication and Quantum Transport" (Wiley-VCH, 2012)&rdquo;. (6) The PI group was able to demonstrate that independently of the nature of the superconducting weak link, higher moments of the distribution of the critical current take universal values. The numerical analysis shows that introduction of extraneous noise into the system leads to significant deviations from the universal values. This finding suggests that it might be possible to use the discovered universality of higher moments as a robust tool for checking against undesirable effects on noise in various types of measurements including experiments with qubits (quantum bits used to build quantum computers). The results have been published in Physical Review Letters (2013).</p> <p>Students and postdoc have been extensively exposed to the diverse phenomenology of modern concepts and approaches in the fields of nanoscience and nanotechnology. They have developed competency in various analytical, computational, computer simulation and experimental research methods. Preparation of papers for publications and seminar presentations based on the research have developed writing skills and the ability to successfully conduct scientific dialogue. The experience and knowledge gained by the students and postdoc will be broadly applicable in both academia and industry. Both students and postdoc have learned how to conduct high-precision and low-noise cryogenic measurements of electronic device. The data analysis was organized by sophisticated software, which was also done by the members of the PI team, including students and postdoc. Their skills of writing research papers and making conferences presentations have been perfected in the course of this project. The students and postdoc have been able to learn in depth the principles of scientific research, development and analysis.</p> <p>The scientific awareness of the general public is very important for the well-being of the society. In this day and age, the informed participation of the citizenry in decisions related to science is crucial for our well-being. One well-known example is the...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The list of the most significant achievements is as follows: (1) Development of a microwave or radiofrequency experimental setup to measure electrical characteristics of extremely thin wires, only about 20 to 100 atoms across. The setup involves a resonator, somewhat analogous to the Fabry-Perot resonator. Two types of resonator have been tested successfully, namely resonators made of very thin films, deposited on Si substrate and bulk microwave cavities, about one inch in size. (2) A method was developed  that allows an independent microwave measurement of the critical temperature of the nanowire. The critical temperature is an important characteristics of the sample. It is the remperature at which the electrical resistance, as defined by Ohm's law, goes to zero. (3) A theoretically predicted formula that predicts how the critical current of a very thin wire changes with temperatures has been confirmed. The critical current is the maximum current up to which the resistance of the wire remains zero.  (4) Single phase slips have been detected in superconducting wires for the first time. Their distributions have been studied, and the macroscopic quantum tunneling effect confirmed in homogeneous nanowires. The phase slip is an abrupt jump when the wire resistance becomes rather high for a short period of time so that the electrical current get reduced. The macroscopic quantum tunneling is the effect analogous to the ordinary quantum  tunneling effect, but in the case the whole macroscopic electronic device experiences a significant change of its properties, in the cases when classical physics prohibits such changes. (5) A book summarizing the results obtained on superconducting nanowires was published. The reference is "A. Bezryadin, "Superconductivity in Nanowires: Fabrication and Quantum Transport" (Wiley-VCH, 2012)". (6) The PI group was able to demonstrate that independently of the nature of the superconducting weak link, higher moments of the distribution of the critical current take universal values. The numerical analysis shows that introduction of extraneous noise into the system leads to significant deviations from the universal values. This finding suggests that it might be possible to use the discovered universality of higher moments as a robust tool for checking against undesirable effects on noise in various types of measurements including experiments with qubits (quantum bits used to build quantum computers). The results have been published in Physical Review Letters (2013).  Students and postdoc have been extensively exposed to the diverse phenomenology of modern concepts and approaches in the fields of nanoscience and nanotechnology. They have developed competency in various analytical, computational, computer simulation and experimental research methods. Preparation of papers for publications and seminar presentations based on the research have developed writing skills and the ability to successfully conduct scientific dialogue. The experience and knowledge gained by the students and postdoc will be broadly applicable in both academia and industry. Both students and postdoc have learned how to conduct high-precision and low-noise cryogenic measurements of electronic device. The data analysis was organized by sophisticated software, which was also done by the members of the PI team, including students and postdoc. Their skills of writing research papers and making conferences presentations have been perfected in the course of this project. The students and postdoc have been able to learn in depth the principles of scientific research, development and analysis.  The scientific awareness of the general public is very important for the well-being of the society. In this day and age, the informed participation of the citizenry in decisions related to science is crucial for our well-being. One well-known example is the global warming question, where it is especially clear that the decisions made by society are of grea...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
