<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Potential Impacts of Aerosol Particles on Severe Storms and Mesoscale Convective Systems (MCSs)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>534625.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>601208</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nanderso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924715</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will involve continued assessment of the potential impacts of aerosol pollution and natural dust sources on severe convective storms and mesoscale convective systems (MCSs).  Prior research by this investigator based upon the Regional Atmospheric Modeling System (RAMS) model has suggested that dust-aerosol influences could significantly influence the evolution of storm outbreaks in the central plains and (ultimately) alter the potential for tornadogenesis within individual convective storms, while other research has pointed to possible aerosol influences on hail formation.  To further pursue these topics the research team will focus three key areas, each contributing to the intellectual merit of this effort:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  * Assessing aerosol/dust influences on tornadogenesis:  Using RAMS version 4.3.0, the researchers will assess the direct radiative effects of dust on the environmental thermodynamic profile with special attention to the "capping inversion," the ability of dust serving as nuclei to alter supercell thunderstorm dynamics, and conduct simulations of actual storm events with attention to assessing impacts of ingested dust.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  * Modeling hail formation using a triple-moment cloud microphysical scheme:  The researchers will further modify a newly developed triple moment scheme, perform additional sensitivity tests, and simulate one or more real-world cases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  * Assessing aerosol influences on MCSs and hailstorms:  The researchers will examine how the variability of cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) concentrations may impact hail formation and size under various environmental conditions, and perform simulations of several observed MCSs that evidently ingested highly polluted air to determine if there are significant feedbacks of ingested CCN on overall storm dynamics and microphysics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this research will include the participation of multiple graduate students in the outlined research activities.  Modeling resources developed under the grant will be made available to the scientific community via their ultimate inclusion in the Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model.  The work ultimately has the potential for societal benefits through improved forecasts of severe convective weather events.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1005041</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Cotton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William R Cotton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cotton@atmos.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704918593</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000121758</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S Howes St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~534625</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~66583</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this grant we investigated the potential impacts of aerosols on severe convective storms and Mesoscale Convective Systems(MCSs) using the Regional Atmospheric Modeling System(RAMS).&nbsp; We focus on aerosols generated by human activities as well as wind-borne dust generated during major storm events in the southwest United States.&nbsp; First we examined the impacts of pollution aerosols on an idealized supercell thunderstorm. It was found that anthropogenic pollution actually increased the likelihood of formation of a tornado. In the second set of idealized simulations, &nbsp;the impacts of varying amounts of aerosol pollution was put in the context of varying amounts of instability in the atmosphere and low-level moisture. The combined influence of low-level moisture and atmospheric instability played a noticeably larger role on tornadogenesis compared to the aerosol influence. &nbsp;However, the aerosol effect was still evident. &nbsp;In both idealized model ensembles, the strongest, longest-lived tornado-like vortices were associated with warmer and weaker cold-pools beneath the supercell storm, greater instability, and less negative buoyancy in the near-vortex environment compared to those storms that produced shorter-lived, weaker vortices. Subsequently,&nbsp; a set of actual cases study &nbsp;simulations of the 15-16 April 2003 tornadic storms outbreak in Texas were performed to examine dust impacts on cloud physics and direct radiative impacts. It was found that dust enhanced the likelihood of formation of more intense supercell storms while simulations without dust generated a more linear line of convection with a single, weak embedded mesocyclone.</p> <p>&nbsp; In another study under support of this grant, the cloud microphysics in the RAMS model was improved to better enable it to represent hail sizes and intensity. This refined model was tested against observations made in an actual case study in which significant amounts of hail were observed. The evaluation of the refined model showed a significant improvement of the simulated storm structure and evolution using the refined cloud microphysics scheme. This new microphysics scheme was then used to examine the role of anthropogenic pollution aerosol on the sizes and amounts of hail. It was found that large amounts of anthropogenic pollution resulted in larger hail sizes and greater amounts of large diameter hail at the surface. Aerosol pollution impacts on hailstorms was also examined in the context of varying cloud base heights or amounts of low-level moisture. It was found that the greatest impacts of aerosol pollution on hailstorms occurred for clouds with high cloud bases, and weaker effects were found for lower cloud base storms.</p> <p>&nbsp; Finally, an actual case study of a meosocale convective system that produced severe straight-line winds(called a derecho) was simulated with RAMS. Simulations were performed with and without sources of anthropogenic aerosol pollution.&nbsp; It was found that aerosol pollution had little impact on total precipitation in the region of the storm. &nbsp;Nonetheless, aerosol pollution enhanced precipitation in the convective region while suppressing precipitation from the stratiform-anvil of the storm. Enhanced aerosols led to invigoration of updrafts within the convective region which enhanced precipitation processes in the convective regions. On the other hand, larger aerosol concentrations in the free troposphere as well as in the boundary layer reduced precipitation forming processes within the stratiform-anvil region. As a consequence, the more polluted simulations produced the least amounts of &nbsp;precipitation from the stratiform-anvil. &nbsp;In terms of the strength of winds produced by the storm, moderate amounts of aerosol concentration reduced the intensity of the severe winds, while greater aerosol concentrations produced similar wind speeds, but ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this grant we investigated the potential impacts of aerosols on severe convective storms and Mesoscale Convective Systems(MCSs) using the Regional Atmospheric Modeling System(RAMS).  We focus on aerosols generated by human activities as well as wind-borne dust generated during major storm events in the southwest United States.  First we examined the impacts of pollution aerosols on an idealized supercell thunderstorm. It was found that anthropogenic pollution actually increased the likelihood of formation of a tornado. In the second set of idealized simulations,  the impacts of varying amounts of aerosol pollution was put in the context of varying amounts of instability in the atmosphere and low-level moisture. The combined influence of low-level moisture and atmospheric instability played a noticeably larger role on tornadogenesis compared to the aerosol influence.  However, the aerosol effect was still evident.  In both idealized model ensembles, the strongest, longest-lived tornado-like vortices were associated with warmer and weaker cold-pools beneath the supercell storm, greater instability, and less negative buoyancy in the near-vortex environment compared to those storms that produced shorter-lived, weaker vortices. Subsequently,  a set of actual cases study  simulations of the 15-16 April 2003 tornadic storms outbreak in Texas were performed to examine dust impacts on cloud physics and direct radiative impacts. It was found that dust enhanced the likelihood of formation of more intense supercell storms while simulations without dust generated a more linear line of convection with a single, weak embedded mesocyclone.    In another study under support of this grant, the cloud microphysics in the RAMS model was improved to better enable it to represent hail sizes and intensity. This refined model was tested against observations made in an actual case study in which significant amounts of hail were observed. The evaluation of the refined model showed a significant improvement of the simulated storm structure and evolution using the refined cloud microphysics scheme. This new microphysics scheme was then used to examine the role of anthropogenic pollution aerosol on the sizes and amounts of hail. It was found that large amounts of anthropogenic pollution resulted in larger hail sizes and greater amounts of large diameter hail at the surface. Aerosol pollution impacts on hailstorms was also examined in the context of varying cloud base heights or amounts of low-level moisture. It was found that the greatest impacts of aerosol pollution on hailstorms occurred for clouds with high cloud bases, and weaker effects were found for lower cloud base storms.    Finally, an actual case study of a meosocale convective system that produced severe straight-line winds(called a derecho) was simulated with RAMS. Simulations were performed with and without sources of anthropogenic aerosol pollution.  It was found that aerosol pollution had little impact on total precipitation in the region of the storm.  Nonetheless, aerosol pollution enhanced precipitation in the convective region while suppressing precipitation from the stratiform-anvil of the storm. Enhanced aerosols led to invigoration of updrafts within the convective region which enhanced precipitation processes in the convective regions. On the other hand, larger aerosol concentrations in the free troposphere as well as in the boundary layer reduced precipitation forming processes within the stratiform-anvil region. As a consequence, the more polluted simulations produced the least amounts of  precipitation from the stratiform-anvil.  In terms of the strength of winds produced by the storm, moderate amounts of aerosol concentration reduced the intensity of the severe winds, while greater aerosol concentrations produced similar wind speeds, but over a larger area.    In summary, this project clearly demonstrates that anthropogenic aerosol pollution can impact the likelihood of torn...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
