<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Impact of Microstructure on Fluoride Substitution in Mineralized Tissues</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>370173.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>370173</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research to Rutgers University is to study the mechanism of fluoride substitution into mineralized tissues and, hence, to determine the optimal levels of exposure to fluoride ions. This research will test the hypothesis that the mechanism of fluoride substitution into mineralized tissues is highly dependent on the microstructure of the mineral/organic matrix. In particular, it is postulated that fluoride can substitute readily into the porous structure of bone and dentin, but it can only entire dental enamel in significant quantities when the enamel's structure has been compromised, for instance during caries formation. Fluoride is known to be beneficial in reducing the incidence of tooth decay, but it can also have detrimental effects with over exposure causing a condition known as fluorosis which can affect both bones and teeth. The results of the research will have significant implications in the areas of oral hygiene, public health and water fluoridation. Through an educational outreach program (Nanotechnology In Classroom Education), school teachers from selected New Jersey schools with significant numbers of minority and disadvantaged students are brought to Rutgers University each summer to develop simple, but exciting, experimental demonstrations and lessons that can be used in K-12 school classrooms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fluoride in drinking water and oral hygiene products can have significant beneficial effects in terms of reducing tooth decay. However, over exposure to fluoride can cause fluorosis which discolors teeth and increases the risk of bone fracture. This research will help identify how the beneficial effects of fluoride treatments can be increased while the detrimental effects are mitigated. The information developed by this project will assist oral hygiene companies in developing better products to prevent tooth decay, and help federal and local government agencies set standards for water fluoridation. Nanotechnology is of growing importance in many industries and a workforce educated in the essentials of this topic has been highlighted as essential to the future of the US economy. An educational program, Nanotechnology In Classroom Education, is being developed in parallel to the research program that will help K-12 school teachers educate their students about the basics of nanotechnology. Each summer the selected teachers will work at Rutgers University on developing simple, but exciting, experimental demonstrations and lessons that can be utilized in a K-12 school environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1006723</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Mann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian B Mann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abmann@rci.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484458421</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230049</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[33 Knightsbridge Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~120760</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~122581</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~126832</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fluoride in toothpaste and oral hygiene products is well known for its ability to mitigate tooth decay, but the role of fluoride in mineralized tissues (teeth and bones) is complex, with a risk of serious medical conditions like fluorosis developing from overexposure. It is also perplexing that for all of fluoride's ability to reduce the frequency of dental cavities it is actually only present, if at all, in very small quantities in healthy teeth. By applying scientific instruments and theoretical models originally developed for metals, semiconductors and ceramics to the study of mineralized tissues a new insight into the role of fluoride has been obtained.</p> <p>Teeth and bones consist of a hard, but brittle ceramic (hydroxyapatite) phase embedded in a softer, but less fracture prone protein matrix. These form a natural nanoscale composite material that is both mechanically strong and of relatively low weight. Acid attacking the hydroxyapatite starts the process of cavity formation. It has generally been assumed that one of the main roles played by fluoride is substituting into the hydroxyapatite phase displacing hydoxyl groups to form fluorapatite or a mixed fluor-hydroxyapatite. In teeth this is chemically and mechanically more resilient than the hydroxyapatite, but in bone the fluoride substitution changes the apatite crystals, which damages the overall balance between the ceramic and protein leading to an increased risk of fracture.</p> <p>Using micro-Raman and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy the chemistry of early dental cavities and their "re-mineralization" using fluoride containing solutions has been examined. This reveals that the acid attack that leads to the formation of cavities only removes a small fraction of the apatite phase. However, finite element simulations and nanoindentation testing of dental enamel has revealed that this is sufficient to cause a major deterioration in the mechanical properties of dental enamel. In essence, the apatite crystals which begin as solid hexagonal rods are hollowed-out to form hexagonal tubes. These are then easily compressed in the direction perpendicular to the tube's length. Fluoride treatments appear to give rise to a fluorapatite phase inside the tubes which restores the mechanical properties of the enamel. Crucially, just a small amount of apatite needs to be replaced and, hence, only a tiny quantity of fluoride is needed. In bones the apatite crystals are not hexagonal rods, but rather flat hexagonal disks. This different geometry gives a much larger surface area which makes substitution of fluoride directly into the apatite crystals feasible.</p> <p>From a societal perspective the study has importance because of the on-going debate about the presence of fluoride in drinking water and oral hygiene products. The results suggest that topical treatments of teeth using toothpastes, oral hygiene products and by dental practitioners&nbsp;should be more effective in adding fluoride to dental enamel than by systemic exposure&nbsp;which might result from&nbsp;water fluoridation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2015<br>      Modified by: Adrian&nbsp;B&nbsp;Mann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fluoride in toothpaste and oral hygiene products is well known for its ability to mitigate tooth decay, but the role of fluoride in mineralized tissues (teeth and bones) is complex, with a risk of serious medical conditions like fluorosis developing from overexposure. It is also perplexing that for all of fluoride's ability to reduce the frequency of dental cavities it is actually only present, if at all, in very small quantities in healthy teeth. By applying scientific instruments and theoretical models originally developed for metals, semiconductors and ceramics to the study of mineralized tissues a new insight into the role of fluoride has been obtained.  Teeth and bones consist of a hard, but brittle ceramic (hydroxyapatite) phase embedded in a softer, but less fracture prone protein matrix. These form a natural nanoscale composite material that is both mechanically strong and of relatively low weight. Acid attacking the hydroxyapatite starts the process of cavity formation. It has generally been assumed that one of the main roles played by fluoride is substituting into the hydroxyapatite phase displacing hydoxyl groups to form fluorapatite or a mixed fluor-hydroxyapatite. In teeth this is chemically and mechanically more resilient than the hydroxyapatite, but in bone the fluoride substitution changes the apatite crystals, which damages the overall balance between the ceramic and protein leading to an increased risk of fracture.  Using micro-Raman and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy the chemistry of early dental cavities and their "re-mineralization" using fluoride containing solutions has been examined. This reveals that the acid attack that leads to the formation of cavities only removes a small fraction of the apatite phase. However, finite element simulations and nanoindentation testing of dental enamel has revealed that this is sufficient to cause a major deterioration in the mechanical properties of dental enamel. In essence, the apatite crystals which begin as solid hexagonal rods are hollowed-out to form hexagonal tubes. These are then easily compressed in the direction perpendicular to the tube's length. Fluoride treatments appear to give rise to a fluorapatite phase inside the tubes which restores the mechanical properties of the enamel. Crucially, just a small amount of apatite needs to be replaced and, hence, only a tiny quantity of fluoride is needed. In bones the apatite crystals are not hexagonal rods, but rather flat hexagonal disks. This different geometry gives a much larger surface area which makes substitution of fluoride directly into the apatite crystals feasible.  From a societal perspective the study has importance because of the on-going debate about the presence of fluoride in drinking water and oral hygiene products. The results suggest that topical treatments of teeth using toothpastes, oral hygiene products and by dental practitioners should be more effective in adding fluoride to dental enamel than by systemic exposure which might result from water fluoridation.       Last Modified: 06/04/2015       Submitted by: Adrian B Mann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
