<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doping Profiles in Semiconductor Nanowires</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical: Semiconductor nanowires are potentially transformative materials for electronics and photonics technologies, and doping and composition modulation are the foundation of semiconductor devices. The objective of this project is to understand and control dopant incorporation rates and junction profiles in silicon and germanium nanowires in order to establish a foundation for nanowire device fabrication. Atom probe tomography is used to map the 3-dimensional distribution of donor and acceptor dopant atoms in vapor-liquid-solid and vapor-solid-solid grown nanowires with single dopant atom sensitivity. Varied catalysts and growth conditions will be employed to understand the thermodynamic and kinetic factors that influence doping rates. Such understanding is expected to establish the ultimate limits of junction abruptness for both radial junctions, as in core-shell structures, and axial junctions. Electrical transport and scanning probe measurements, including scanning Kelvin probe microscopy and scanning photocurrent microscopy, are used to determine the fraction of active dopants and measure the electrical profiles of dopant homojunctions. The integrated activities of synthesis, composition mapping, and electrical characterization permit distinctions between electrical properties that arise from nanoscale dopant distributions and those that arise from modified screening on the nano/meso scale. &lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of materials science with high technological relevance. The activity is expected to advance materials and metrology of critical importance to the semiconductor industry. The project integrates research and education by advancing discovery and understanding through involvement of the PI and his graduate students in a new Student Investigative Research program at a local high school and engaging student groups from a senior level process design course in the discovery and optimization of nanowire processing-structure relationships.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1006069</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lincoln</FirstName>
<LastName>Lauhon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lincoln Lauhon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lauhon@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474912232</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390409</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 N. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>New materials, and conventional materials in new forms, can improve existing technologies and lead to the creation of new technologies. This project developed a fundamental understanding of how the well-known semiconductor materials silicon and germanium behave in different, interesting, and potentially useful ways when they have extremely small nanoscale dimensions. The project focused particularly on a widely employed method to grow nanoscale silicon and germanium wires that are being incorporated in technologies such as chemical sensing, information processing, and solar energy conversion. In most of these applications, the electrical properties of the materials are controlled by tiny quantities of &ldquo;dopant&rdquo; atoms whose distribution is strongly influenced by the growth process. This project resulted in important discoveries of the fundamental growth factors that control the incorporation of dopant atoms. To achieve the project goals, researchers utilized a highly specialized microscopy technique known as an atom probe tomography. The atom probe can look inside the very smallest devices that have ever been made and map out the distribution of all the elements that are present. The atomic scale maps of dopant distributions were correlated with maps of the electrical properties of nanoscale silicon and germanium wires to uncover the influence of the materials growth process on the behavior of the materials in important device applications. There are hundreds of research groups across the world working on nanoscale semiconducting wires, and the findings of this project have great value in guiding researchers and technologists working to overcome the technical challenges of incorporating these nanomaterials into new technologies. Furthermore, the capabilities for analyzing nanoscale materials and devices atom by atom that have been demonstrated by this project are of great interest to industrial researchers who can now also use the atom probe to solve pressing technological problems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2013<br>      Modified by: Lincoln&nbsp;Lauhon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ New materials, and conventional materials in new forms, can improve existing technologies and lead to the creation of new technologies. This project developed a fundamental understanding of how the well-known semiconductor materials silicon and germanium behave in different, interesting, and potentially useful ways when they have extremely small nanoscale dimensions. The project focused particularly on a widely employed method to grow nanoscale silicon and germanium wires that are being incorporated in technologies such as chemical sensing, information processing, and solar energy conversion. In most of these applications, the electrical properties of the materials are controlled by tiny quantities of "dopant" atoms whose distribution is strongly influenced by the growth process. This project resulted in important discoveries of the fundamental growth factors that control the incorporation of dopant atoms. To achieve the project goals, researchers utilized a highly specialized microscopy technique known as an atom probe tomography. The atom probe can look inside the very smallest devices that have ever been made and map out the distribution of all the elements that are present. The atomic scale maps of dopant distributions were correlated with maps of the electrical properties of nanoscale silicon and germanium wires to uncover the influence of the materials growth process on the behavior of the materials in important device applications. There are hundreds of research groups across the world working on nanoscale semiconducting wires, and the findings of this project have great value in guiding researchers and technologists working to overcome the technical challenges of incorporating these nanomaterials into new technologies. Furthermore, the capabilities for analyzing nanoscale materials and devices atom by atom that have been demonstrated by this project are of great interest to industrial researchers who can now also use the atom probe to solve pressing technological problems.                Last Modified: 11/29/2013       Submitted by: Lincoln Lauhon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
