<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometry of the Moduli Spaces of Complex Manifolds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Moduli spaces of Calabi-Yau manifolds, Riemann surfaces and general type manifolds, stable bundles and stable maps have played fundamental roles in many subjects of mathematics from geometry, topology, algebraic geometry, to number theory and are also important in string theory. Mirror symmetry has motivated many deep mathematical results and theories. In this project the PI will study various local and global problems of the geometry of these moduli spaces. These problems include the deformation of canonical metrics such as the Kahler-Einstein metrics and Bergman metrics with respect to various gauges. This study lead to a geometric quantization of the Weil-Petersson type metrics. The PI will also study the global properties of the period map from the Teichmuller and moduli spaces to the classifying spaces of variation of Hodge structures and their quotients. The PI will also investigate the geometric properties on canonical and new Kahler metrics on these moduli spaces as well as the general existence of Kahler-Einstein and Hermitian-Einstein metrics on noncompact manifolds and bundles over them.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Teichmuller and moduli spaces of Kahler-Einstein manifolds are important for both mathematics and theoretical physics. In string theory, many fundamental partition functions can be reduced to geometric or topological invariants of moduli spaces which also motivated many beautiful conjectures. The study of these important conjectures not only enhanced the development of various branches of mathematics but also help in verifying theory in high energy physics. The research of the PI also has potential applications in industry such as medical image processing and 3D cameras. For example, with the explicit construction of the period map the speed of compressing/decompressing pictures can be significantly increased.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1006696</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaofeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaofeng Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xis205@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107583760</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488336</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808264444</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068570936</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Alumni Building 27]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~130500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Kahler-Einstein and Calabi-Yau (CY) manifolds and their moduli spaces are the fundamental objects in string theory which is the most promising theory for the grand unification of all fundamental forces in the nature. String theory is based on the study of sigma models which are maps from Riemann surfaces to Riemannian manifolds. One of the most important cases is when the target manifolds are Kahler-Einstein manifolds especially those with trivial canonical bundle, namely the Calabi-Yau manifolds</p> <p>An important question is to understand the deformation of \ke manifolds, that is the geometry of the moduli spaces. This is particularly important in unravel the mystery of mirror symmetry. A natural generalization of Kahler-Einstein metrics are solitons which are self-similar solutions of geometric flows. The soliton metrics also play an important role in physics.</p> <p>By the support of the NSF grant the PI and his collaborators systemically studied the variation of canonical metrics under the deformation of complex structures. They also established a canonical local expansion of holomorphic sections of vector bundles with respect to the deformation of complex structures. A direct consequence of these works is the quantization of the Weil-Petersson type metrics on the moduli spaces of Kahler-Einstein manifolds. In fact these Weil-Petersson metrics can by approximated by the normalized Ricci curvatures of the natural metrics on certain direct image sheaves. This theory also gives the curvature formulas of these natural metrics on other direct image sheaves of associated bundles and positivity/negativity of these bundles. The PI and his collaborators also studied gradient Yamabe solitons and they classified complete gradient Yamabe solitons.</p> <p>Yamabe solitons are self-similar solutions of the Yamabe flow. By the support from NSF the PI and his collaborators classified gradient Yamabe solitons. Especially they showed that a nontrivial complete gradient Yamabe soliton admits a warped product structure. Among other results they also showed that a locally conformally flat Yamabe soliton is a warped product with a space form if the potential function has no critical point.</p> <p><br />In the study of deformation of Kahler-Einstein metrics, the PI and his collaborators first established the equivalence of the Kuranishi gauge and the divergence gauge. By using this the PI established the expansion of the Kahler &nbsp;forms of Kahler-Einstein metrics with respect to the Kuranishi-divergence &nbsp;gauge. As a corollary they established a canonical way to construct local sections of the direct image sheaves of the relative pluricanonical bundles. Furthermore, the normalized Ricci curvature of the $L^2$ metrics on these direct image sheaves will converge to the WP metric on the moduli space. The PI and his collaborators also studied the structure of the Teichmuller space of Kahler-Einstein manifolds of general type. Among other results they constructed a pluri-subharmonic function on these Teichmuller spaces.</p> <p>The work of the PI under the support of NSF has potential applications in high energy physics as well as image processing.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2013<br>      Modified by: Xiaofeng&nbsp;Sun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Kahler-Einstein and Calabi-Yau (CY) manifolds and their moduli spaces are the fundamental objects in string theory which is the most promising theory for the grand unification of all fundamental forces in the nature. String theory is based on the study of sigma models which are maps from Riemann surfaces to Riemannian manifolds. One of the most important cases is when the target manifolds are Kahler-Einstein manifolds especially those with trivial canonical bundle, namely the Calabi-Yau manifolds  An important question is to understand the deformation of \ke manifolds, that is the geometry of the moduli spaces. This is particularly important in unravel the mystery of mirror symmetry. A natural generalization of Kahler-Einstein metrics are solitons which are self-similar solutions of geometric flows. The soliton metrics also play an important role in physics.  By the support of the NSF grant the PI and his collaborators systemically studied the variation of canonical metrics under the deformation of complex structures. They also established a canonical local expansion of holomorphic sections of vector bundles with respect to the deformation of complex structures. A direct consequence of these works is the quantization of the Weil-Petersson type metrics on the moduli spaces of Kahler-Einstein manifolds. In fact these Weil-Petersson metrics can by approximated by the normalized Ricci curvatures of the natural metrics on certain direct image sheaves. This theory also gives the curvature formulas of these natural metrics on other direct image sheaves of associated bundles and positivity/negativity of these bundles. The PI and his collaborators also studied gradient Yamabe solitons and they classified complete gradient Yamabe solitons.  Yamabe solitons are self-similar solutions of the Yamabe flow. By the support from NSF the PI and his collaborators classified gradient Yamabe solitons. Especially they showed that a nontrivial complete gradient Yamabe soliton admits a warped product structure. Among other results they also showed that a locally conformally flat Yamabe soliton is a warped product with a space form if the potential function has no critical point.   In the study of deformation of Kahler-Einstein metrics, the PI and his collaborators first established the equivalence of the Kuranishi gauge and the divergence gauge. By using this the PI established the expansion of the Kahler  forms of Kahler-Einstein metrics with respect to the Kuranishi-divergence  gauge. As a corollary they established a canonical way to construct local sections of the direct image sheaves of the relative pluricanonical bundles. Furthermore, the normalized Ricci curvature of the $L^2$ metrics on these direct image sheaves will converge to the WP metric on the moduli space. The PI and his collaborators also studied the structure of the Teichmuller space of Kahler-Einstein manifolds of general type. Among other results they constructed a pluri-subharmonic function on these Teichmuller spaces.  The work of the PI under the support of NSF has potential applications in high energy physics as well as image processing.        Last Modified: 09/30/2013       Submitted by: Xiaofeng Sun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
