<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Quantum Criticality in Rare-Earth and Actinide-Based Intermetallics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Classical phase transitions, such as the freezing or boiling of water, involve heat energy.  This individual investigator award will support a study of quantum phase transitions which occur at absolute zero where there is no heat.  Zero-point energy, associated with the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle, plays the role of heat in these transitions.  Quantum phase transitions can dramatically affect the behavior of matter at surprisingly high temperatures and lead to characteristic changes in volume as the temperature or a magnetic field changes.  A high-precision technique, developed with NSF support, will be used to search for these characteristic changes in volume in order to identify and characterize the underlying quantum phase transition.  Novel states of matter that may occur near quantum phase transitions will be sought out and studied.  Undergraduate students will participate in all aspects of this work, both on-campus and during trips to national laboratories and other collaborating institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This individual investigator award will support a study of quantum criticality in several rare-earth and actinide-based intermetallic compounds.  The thermal expansion and magnetostriction of these materials will be measured using a capacitive dilatometer developed with NSF support.  Phase diagrams will be mapped out and phase transitions between the low temperature states of these materials will be thermodynamically characterized.  These dilation measurements will be combined with existing specific heat measurements in a Gruneisen analysis to determine the volume dependence of the characteristic energies of these fascinating materials.  Specific signatures of quantum criticality will be sought, such as a sign change of the thermal expansion and divergence of the Gruneisen parameter as the temperature approaches absolute zero.  Novel states of matter that may occur near quantum phase transitions will be sought out and studied.  Undergraduate students will participate in all aspects of this work, both on-campus and during trips to national laboratories and other collaborating institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1006118</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmiedeshoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George M Schmiedeshoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gms@oxy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3232592800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Occidental College</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900413314</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3232591414</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Campus Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046436051</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OCCIDENTAL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046436051</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Occidental College]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900413314</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 Campus Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~270000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project is to better understand the nature of matter near quantum phase transitions, phase transitions at absolute zero that can influence the behavior of matter at higher, accessible temperatures, sometimes at much higher temperatures.&nbsp; Unusual states of matter (novel superconductivity, for example) can form near quantum phase transitions, and we wish to better understand these states and their nature too.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our principle experimental tool is a capacitive dilatometer, a device that can measure the very small length changes that can occur when a material changes temperature.&nbsp; If we load a dime into the dilatometer, for example, we can measure changes in its thickness that are smaller than the diameter of a hydrogen atom!&nbsp; This dilatometer was developed with NSF support.</p> <p>Our most recent work focused on two materials that are thought to contain quantum phase transitions: YbAgGe and YbBiPt.&nbsp; For both materials we made extensive measurements of the thermal expansion (length changes due to temperature changes) and magnetostriciton (length changes due to a change in the magnetic field applied to the material).&nbsp; We mapped out phase diagrams of both materials and searched for the finite temperature "fingerprints" of quantum phase transitions.&nbsp;</p> <p>We found evidence for two kinds of quantum phase transitions in YbAgGe a quantum critical point, and a more exotic quantum bi-critical point.&nbsp; Our measurements on YbBiPt revealed that the thermal expansion has a very unusual time-dependent component the origin of which is still under investigation, but we have never seen a phenomenon like this before and are still trying to confirm its existence with related measurements.</p> <p>To extend these measurements to lower temperatures we started to develop specialized dilatometers.&nbsp; During the period of support, the Principle Investigator also consulted with Quantum Design to help them develop a new commercial dilatometer for operation at low temperatures and in high magnetic fields.</p> <p>Nine undergraduate students participated in this work.&nbsp; They loaded samples in the dilatometer, helped cool the sytem down, took data using a computer based data acquisition system, and analyzed the data using commercial analysis software.&nbsp; Most of these students have moved on to advanced training in engineering or physics, some have entered the work-force, and one has not graduated yet.&nbsp; Several participated in the construction of dilatometers, one has participated in the design of new dilatometers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/06/2015<br>      Modified by: George&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schmiedeshoff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project is to better understand the nature of matter near quantum phase transitions, phase transitions at absolute zero that can influence the behavior of matter at higher, accessible temperatures, sometimes at much higher temperatures.  Unusual states of matter (novel superconductivity, for example) can form near quantum phase transitions, and we wish to better understand these states and their nature too.   Our principle experimental tool is a capacitive dilatometer, a device that can measure the very small length changes that can occur when a material changes temperature.  If we load a dime into the dilatometer, for example, we can measure changes in its thickness that are smaller than the diameter of a hydrogen atom!  This dilatometer was developed with NSF support.  Our most recent work focused on two materials that are thought to contain quantum phase transitions: YbAgGe and YbBiPt.  For both materials we made extensive measurements of the thermal expansion (length changes due to temperature changes) and magnetostriciton (length changes due to a change in the magnetic field applied to the material).  We mapped out phase diagrams of both materials and searched for the finite temperature "fingerprints" of quantum phase transitions.   We found evidence for two kinds of quantum phase transitions in YbAgGe a quantum critical point, and a more exotic quantum bi-critical point.  Our measurements on YbBiPt revealed that the thermal expansion has a very unusual time-dependent component the origin of which is still under investigation, but we have never seen a phenomenon like this before and are still trying to confirm its existence with related measurements.  To extend these measurements to lower temperatures we started to develop specialized dilatometers.  During the period of support, the Principle Investigator also consulted with Quantum Design to help them develop a new commercial dilatometer for operation at low temperatures and in high magnetic fields.  Nine undergraduate students participated in this work.  They loaded samples in the dilatometer, helped cool the sytem down, took data using a computer based data acquisition system, and analyzed the data using commercial analysis software.  Most of these students have moved on to advanced training in engineering or physics, some have entered the work-force, and one has not graduated yet.  Several participated in the construction of dilatometers, one has participated in the design of new dilatometers.       Last Modified: 10/06/2015       Submitted by: George M Schmiedeshoff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
