<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Broadening Workstation Connectivity to Enhance Research Productivity and Student Preparation in Computational Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1176470.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1176470</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01120000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Audrey Levine</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number:  EPS-1006983&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: Broadening Workstation Connectivity to Enhance Research Productivity and Student Preparation in Computational Sciences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution:  Mississippi State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This EPSCoR Research Infrastructure Improvement Inter-Campus and Intra-Campus Cyber Connectivity project includes upgrades at four Mississippi research institutions: Jackson State University, Mississippi State University, the University of Mississippi, and the University of Southern Mississippi. The institutions will significantly expand the number of workstations connected via gigabit per second links and establish an e-meeting facility in order to bolster collaborative research and STEM-related education offerings in the state. The resulting state-wide cyberinfrastructure will enable researchers to connect from their desktops to resources throughout the state and beyond. The investment in e-meeting infrastructure will serve to integrate research and education and support increased inter-institutional research and education activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;Enhancing the connectivity and integration of research in modeling and simulation of complex systems will enable research contributions in the areas of multi-scale biological simulation, computational biology and chemistry, and support research efforts crosscutting a number of diverse disciplines, including chemistry, biochemistry, biology, physiology, ecoinformatics, genomics and numerous computer science sub-disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The activities of this project are designed to directly support improvements to the infrastructure, research and development capacity, and high-technology commercialization opportunities in Mississippi. In addition to bolstering research output by linking researchers, the cyberinfrastructure enhancements will help link computational science researchers with industry partners in order to establish collaboration between universities and private employers, to strengthen economic competitiveness, and to create high technology jobs for graduating students. Professional development for secondary teachers and community college faculty and curriculum enrichment and development are expected to increase exposure and interest in STEM-related disciplines among high school and community college students in Mississippi. The institutions will deliver workshops to geographically dispersed students and teachers via enhanced e-meeting facilities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount>1176470</ARRAAmount>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1006983</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bridges</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Bridges</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bridges@cse.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623257505</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000356442</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Tschumper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory S Tschumper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tschumpr@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6629157301</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382484</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yoginder</FirstName>
<LastName>Dandass</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yoginder S Dandass</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yogi@cse.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623252131</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463940</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chaoyang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chaoyang Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chaoyang.zhang@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6012664119</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000359204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glake</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Glake Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>glakeh@icnanotox.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6019791699</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482050</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MISSISSIPPI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mississippi State University]]></Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 6156]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7217</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Research Infrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6890</Code>
<Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>01R9</Code>
<Name>RRA RECOVERY ACT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040101</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1176470</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Mississippi research institutions of higher learning (MRIHLs) consisting of Jackson State University (JSU) &ndash; the state&rsquo;s largest HBCU, Mississippi State University (MSU), University of Mississippi (UM), and University of Southern Mississippi (USM) have competitive research laboratory and teaching facilities.&nbsp; However, inadequate connectivity between the researchers and educators at these institutions has been a barrier to accelerated growth</p> <p>The funding provided by RII-C2 project had the following three major objectives: a) to bring 1Gbps connectivity to workstations and desktops; b) to provide an e-meeting facility; and c) to enhance the availability of cluster computing resources to researchers, educators, and students in Mississippi.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the first year of the project, the four MRIHLs drew up plans for acquiring the equipment and services outlined in the proposal and began the equipment acquisition process.&nbsp; In the second year, the RII-C2 team focused on completing the acquisition and installation of equipment and services to implement the infrastructure upgrade plans.&nbsp; Towards the end of the second year, the RII-C2 team sought and received a one year extension in order to complete the acquisition of e-meeting infrastructure.&nbsp; This infrastructure was placed into service at the beginning of the third year.</p> <p>At MSU, 10Gb line cards were installed at various buildings housing the following departments: Computer Science and Engineering, Computer and Electrical Engineering, Chemical Engineering, Entomology, Mechanical Engineering, and the College of Veterinary Medicine, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Plant and Soil Sciences, Geosciences, Physics and Astronomy, Agriculture and Biological&nbsp; Engineering, Business and Accountancy, Architecture, Psychology, Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology, African American Studies, and Industrial Education.&nbsp; Many of these departments are non-EPSCOR affiliated.&nbsp; In addition, 18 technology classrooms and the following facilities are also impacted: Pace (now part of the Institute for Genomics, Biocomputing, and Biotechnology &ndash; IGBB), and the Mitchell Memorial Library.</p> <p>At JSU, a Cisco 6509 10-Gig router and an ASA 5585 10-Gig firewall were installed impacting the E. E. Just Science Hall.&nbsp; Departments within this building include Chemistry and Biochemistry, Biological Sciences, Mathematics, and Physics.&nbsp; In addition, JSU installed Life Size Video Conference equipment that is used by EPSCoR researchers in Computational Biology and Computational Chemistry.&nbsp; The equipment will also be used for instruction and to conduct remotely delivered workshops.</p> <p>At USM, equipment to combine two small compute clusters into a larger grid has been acquired and installed.&nbsp; The research cluster directly impacts EPSCoR researchers in Computational Biology and Computational Chemistry.&nbsp; Furthermore, upgrades to network infrastructure directly impacts the following: Department of Biological Sciences, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Department of Mathematics, and The School of Computing.</p> <p>University of Mississippi (UM) has installed upgraded gigabit Ethernet capability in buildings housing the following: Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, and Computer Science. In addition, UM has acquired a license for WebEx, a web-based teleconferencing service.&nbsp; Although the license is managed at UM, any EPSCoR-affiliated researcher in the state can request access to this service.</p> <p>The infrastructure improvements provided by this EPSCoR RII-C2 grant are primarily focused on supporting the activities of the RII researchers in the following broad areas: Biological Simulation (BioSim),&nbsp; Computational Biology (CompBio), and Computational Chemistry (CompChem).</p> <p>The Bio...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Mississippi research institutions of higher learning (MRIHLs) consisting of Jackson State University (JSU) &ndash; the stateÆs largest HBCU, Mississippi State University (MSU), University of Mississippi (UM), and University of Southern Mississippi (USM) have competitive research laboratory and teaching facilities.  However, inadequate connectivity between the researchers and educators at these institutions has been a barrier to accelerated growth  The funding provided by RII-C2 project had the following three major objectives: a) to bring 1Gbps connectivity to workstations and desktops; b) to provide an e-meeting facility; and c) to enhance the availability of cluster computing resources to researchers, educators, and students in Mississippi.   During the first year of the project, the four MRIHLs drew up plans for acquiring the equipment and services outlined in the proposal and began the equipment acquisition process.  In the second year, the RII-C2 team focused on completing the acquisition and installation of equipment and services to implement the infrastructure upgrade plans.  Towards the end of the second year, the RII-C2 team sought and received a one year extension in order to complete the acquisition of e-meeting infrastructure.  This infrastructure was placed into service at the beginning of the third year.  At MSU, 10Gb line cards were installed at various buildings housing the following departments: Computer Science and Engineering, Computer and Electrical Engineering, Chemical Engineering, Entomology, Mechanical Engineering, and the College of Veterinary Medicine, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Plant and Soil Sciences, Geosciences, Physics and Astronomy, Agriculture and Biological  Engineering, Business and Accountancy, Architecture, Psychology, Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology, African American Studies, and Industrial Education.  Many of these departments are non-EPSCOR affiliated.  In addition, 18 technology classrooms and the following facilities are also impacted: Pace (now part of the Institute for Genomics, Biocomputing, and Biotechnology &ndash; IGBB), and the Mitchell Memorial Library.  At JSU, a Cisco 6509 10-Gig router and an ASA 5585 10-Gig firewall were installed impacting the E. E. Just Science Hall.  Departments within this building include Chemistry and Biochemistry, Biological Sciences, Mathematics, and Physics.  In addition, JSU installed Life Size Video Conference equipment that is used by EPSCoR researchers in Computational Biology and Computational Chemistry.  The equipment will also be used for instruction and to conduct remotely delivered workshops.  At USM, equipment to combine two small compute clusters into a larger grid has been acquired and installed.  The research cluster directly impacts EPSCoR researchers in Computational Biology and Computational Chemistry.  Furthermore, upgrades to network infrastructure directly impacts the following: Department of Biological Sciences, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Department of Mathematics, and The School of Computing.  University of Mississippi (UM) has installed upgraded gigabit Ethernet capability in buildings housing the following: Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, and Computer Science. In addition, UM has acquired a license for WebEx, a web-based teleconferencing service.  Although the license is managed at UM, any EPSCoR-affiliated researcher in the state can request access to this service.  The infrastructure improvements provided by this EPSCoR RII-C2 grant are primarily focused on supporting the activities of the RII researchers in the following broad areas: Biological Simulation (BioSim),  Computational Biology (CompBio), and Computational Chemistry (CompChem).  The BioSim researchers are developing a multi-scale simulation framework for investigation of human biological processes and make this framework freely available via cyber-infrastructure for researc...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
