<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Crystal Growth and Neutron Scattering Studies of Complex Oxides</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>410000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;Complex oxide materials offer myriad opportunities to discover and learn about novel fundamental magnetic and electronic phenomena and phases relevant to both fundamental science and technology.  This award supports a project that will address some of the most timely and intellectually challenging scientific issues in this field by pursuing advanced crystal growth and neutron scattering studies of a number materials that are likely to hold the key to resolving such timely questions as: the role of disorder in model quantum magnets; why the temperature where a material becomes a superconductor is very high in some materials, but not in others; the roles of coexisting and competing phases and of magnetic excitations.  A comprehensive approach will be pursued through collaborations with experts using complementary experimental tools.  This effort covers the full range from crystal growth, to materials characterization, to neutron scattering, to extensive collaborations.  Consequently, this materials-based research program will provide rich educational opportunities in materials physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;This individual investigator award supports a project that will investigate some of the most timely topics in the field of correlated-electron materials by pursuing crystal growth and neutron scattering studies of a number of complex oxides that are likely to hold the key to resolving such timely questions as: the role of disorder in model quantum magnets; the fundamental differences between electron and hole doping of the high transition-temperature (Tc) cuprate superconductors; why Tc is very high in some cuprates, but not in others; the roles of coexisting and competing phases and of magnetic excitations.  A comprehensive approach will be pursued through collaborations with experts using complementary experimental tools.  This effort covers the full range from crystal growth, to materials characterization, to neutron scattering, to extensive collaborations.  Consequently, this materials-based research program will provide rich educational opportunities in materials physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1006617</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Greven</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin Greven</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>greven@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126247542</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~35000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI and his students have addressed some of the timeliest and most challenging issues in the field of correlated-electron materials via crystal growth, torque magnetometry, neutron and X-ray scattering, as well as extensive collaborations with scientists who pursue complementary experimental techniques. In particular, the goal has been to better understand the differences between electron-doped cuprate superconductors, especially (Nd,Ce)2CuO4 (NCCO), and the hole-doped cuprate superconductors.</p> <p>Antiferromagnetic (AF) correlations have been argued to be responsible for the unconventional superconductivity in the cuprates. Motivated by prior NSF-sponsored neutron scattering measurements of AF correlations in NCCO [Motoyama et al., Nature 445, 186 (2007)], the PI and his group have carried out further neutron scattering and new collaborative muon spin rotation measurements [results to be published] to arrive at a more detailed picture of the doping and temperature evolution of AF correlations. Complementary inelastic X-ray scattering measurements have led to new insights into the doping dependence of the strength of AF excitations and revealed a new type of charge excitation in superconducting crystals [Lee et al., to appear in Nature Physics]. Additional charge transport measurements in high magnetic fields (conducted at the National High Magnetic Field Laboratory) yielded complementary information regarding the evolution with doping and temperature of the charge degrees of freedom [to be published].</p> <p>Collaborative photomemission experiments on NCCO led to a deeper understanding of so-called matrix-element effects [Rienks et al., to appear in Phys. Rev. Lett.], while non-equilibrium optical measurements on NCCO show indirect evidence for order in competition with the superconductivity [Hinton et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. (2013)].</p> <p>The award has enabled the training and mentoring of a large number of students: one graduate student and four undergraduate students. It has furthermore provided partial support for one postdoctoral researcher. Last, but not least, it has enabled the participation of a high scool student.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2014<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;Greven</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI and his students have addressed some of the timeliest and most challenging issues in the field of correlated-electron materials via crystal growth, torque magnetometry, neutron and X-ray scattering, as well as extensive collaborations with scientists who pursue complementary experimental techniques. In particular, the goal has been to better understand the differences between electron-doped cuprate superconductors, especially (Nd,Ce)2CuO4 (NCCO), and the hole-doped cuprate superconductors.  Antiferromagnetic (AF) correlations have been argued to be responsible for the unconventional superconductivity in the cuprates. Motivated by prior NSF-sponsored neutron scattering measurements of AF correlations in NCCO [Motoyama et al., Nature 445, 186 (2007)], the PI and his group have carried out further neutron scattering and new collaborative muon spin rotation measurements [results to be published] to arrive at a more detailed picture of the doping and temperature evolution of AF correlations. Complementary inelastic X-ray scattering measurements have led to new insights into the doping dependence of the strength of AF excitations and revealed a new type of charge excitation in superconducting crystals [Lee et al., to appear in Nature Physics]. Additional charge transport measurements in high magnetic fields (conducted at the National High Magnetic Field Laboratory) yielded complementary information regarding the evolution with doping and temperature of the charge degrees of freedom [to be published].  Collaborative photomemission experiments on NCCO led to a deeper understanding of so-called matrix-element effects [Rienks et al., to appear in Phys. Rev. Lett.], while non-equilibrium optical measurements on NCCO show indirect evidence for order in competition with the superconductivity [Hinton et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. (2013)].  The award has enabled the training and mentoring of a large number of students: one graduate student and four undergraduate students. It has furthermore provided partial support for one postdoctoral researcher. Last, but not least, it has enabled the participation of a high scool student.       Last Modified: 08/29/2014       Submitted by: Martin Greven]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
