<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A probabilistic approach to the Navier-Stokes equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>165124.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>165124</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project is devoted to a study of the Navier-Stokes equations using probabilistic techniques. Using stochastic Lagrangian techniques we will study the inviscid limit of the Navier Stokes equations in bounded domains. The probabilistic approach will allow us to address new questions (e.g. the asymptotic limit of the probability that a particle starting close to the boundary arrives in the interior of the domain). The project will also study probabilistic global existence theorems in the following sense: find a process whose expectation is a strong solution to the (deterministic) Navier-Stokes equations, and prove that for arbitrary initial data, the blow up time of the process is infinity with non-zero probability. A secondary aim of this research is to study the nonlocal, nonlinear PDEs associated with incompressible flows that promote the creation of hot spots.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will study mathematical aspects of fluid dynamics using probabilistic techniques. One fundamental, unresolved question addressed will be the separation of the boundary layer and the zero viscosity limit. This is of great practical interest in studying problems such as the determination of air flow about an airplane wing. Other problems studied are probabilistic global existence questions. While the question of existence for all time of solutions of the equations governing the evolution of incompressible fluids is unresolved, this project will address a probabilistic analogue of this question. Namely, can one find a criterion that allows one to decide that certain realizations of the flow are turbulent and stop them, and show that the remainder "live forever" with nonzero probability? A secondary aim of this project is to study certain peculiar stirring methods that keep the fluid hot (i.e. what is the best way to stir your coffee so that it is hot for as long as possible); this has applications to combustion processes, and chemical reactions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1007914</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gautam</FirstName>
<LastName>Iyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gautam Iyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gautam@math.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122688419</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304397</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7552</Code>
<Text>COFFES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~165124</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Mathematically, the motion of incompressible fluids is described by Navier-Stokes equations. These equations are non-local and nonlinear making their analytical (and numerical) study extremely hard. However, applications of fluid dynamics are ubiquitous in real life and range from meteorology and turbulence to ink jet printing. This makes the study of the Navier-Stokes equations and related models a problem of fundamental importance. The main content of this research was to use new probabilistic methods to study these equations.</p> <p>This report provides brief (simplified) descriptions of some of the findings of this project.</p> <ol> <li> <p>One of the early results obtained through this research was an exact probabilistic description of viscous fluids in domains with boundary by adding noise to the inviscid dynamics and averaging. Previously, this was only understood in domains without boundary. Boundaries added a major complication. Numerical evidence and physical intuition suggest that the fluid is perfectly still at rigid boundaries. Conventional wisdom suggests that this produces vorticity at the boundary, and this is propagated to the fluid interior by a non-linear and nonlocal mechanism. Our eventual aim is to use apply our results to the study of boundary layer dynamics and see if one can understand a probabilistic notion of detachment of the boundary layer. We hope this will eventually help in the study of practical problems such as air-flow around an airplane wing where detachment of the boundary layer plays a crucial role in the dynamics.</p> </li> <li> <p>It is easy to see that the temperature distribution starting from a point source of heat is "self-similar". That is, as time evolves a temperature profile maintains the same shape after a natural rescaling. Such self-similar evolutionary profiles are present in many naturally occurring situations, and one result of the funded research was to study these self-similar evolutionary profiles context of coagulation. Explicitly we study general coalescent processes  where more than two clusters may coalesces at any time, and obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of a self similar size distribution. We further characterize all such (non-degenerate) size distributions, develop a direct, simpler, approach to understanding this coagulation model through a rescaled limit of discrete branching processes. The analysis and study of this model has many applications ranging from voter demographics to gel formation.</p> </li> <li> <p>Liquid crystals are a multi-billion dollar industry having numerous applications, and are commonplace in every day life. The funded research studies a model for liquid crystals arising from the Landau de Gennes "Q-Tensor". The simplest possible scenario that is invariant with respect to the natural symmetries and captures the essential physical features has a rather peculiar feature: an cubic nonlinearity in the energy. We study the mathematical well-posedness of this model, and explore the meaning of physicality. A better understanding of these mathematical models will eventually translate to better LCD technology.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Other problems that were studied in this funded research were equations arising from numerical schemes for incompressible fluids that are BOTH accurate and efficient, and questions about optimal mixing rates.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2014<br>      Modified by: Gautam&nbsp;Iyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Mathematically, the motion of incompressible fluids is described by Navier-Stokes equations. These equations are non-local and nonlinear making their analytical (and numerical) study extremely hard. However, applications of fluid dynamics are ubiquitous in real life and range from meteorology and turbulence to ink jet printing. This makes the study of the Navier-Stokes equations and related models a problem of fundamental importance. The main content of this research was to use new probabilistic methods to study these equations.  This report provides brief (simplified) descriptions of some of the findings of this project.    One of the early results obtained through this research was an exact probabilistic description of viscous fluids in domains with boundary by adding noise to the inviscid dynamics and averaging. Previously, this was only understood in domains without boundary. Boundaries added a major complication. Numerical evidence and physical intuition suggest that the fluid is perfectly still at rigid boundaries. Conventional wisdom suggests that this produces vorticity at the boundary, and this is propagated to the fluid interior by a non-linear and nonlocal mechanism. Our eventual aim is to use apply our results to the study of boundary layer dynamics and see if one can understand a probabilistic notion of detachment of the boundary layer. We hope this will eventually help in the study of practical problems such as air-flow around an airplane wing where detachment of the boundary layer plays a crucial role in the dynamics.    It is easy to see that the temperature distribution starting from a point source of heat is "self-similar". That is, as time evolves a temperature profile maintains the same shape after a natural rescaling. Such self-similar evolutionary profiles are present in many naturally occurring situations, and one result of the funded research was to study these self-similar evolutionary profiles context of coagulation. Explicitly we study general coalescent processes  where more than two clusters may coalesces at any time, and obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of a self similar size distribution. We further characterize all such (non-degenerate) size distributions, develop a direct, simpler, approach to understanding this coagulation model through a rescaled limit of discrete branching processes. The analysis and study of this model has many applications ranging from voter demographics to gel formation.    Liquid crystals are a multi-billion dollar industry having numerous applications, and are commonplace in every day life. The funded research studies a model for liquid crystals arising from the Landau de Gennes "Q-Tensor". The simplest possible scenario that is invariant with respect to the natural symmetries and captures the essential physical features has a rather peculiar feature: an cubic nonlinearity in the energy. We study the mathematical well-posedness of this model, and explore the meaning of physicality. A better understanding of these mathematical models will eventually translate to better LCD technology.    Other problems that were studied in this funded research were equations arising from numerical schemes for incompressible fluids that are BOTH accurate and efficient, and questions about optimal mixing rates.       Last Modified: 08/21/2014       Submitted by: Gautam Iyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
