<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Atomic Modeling and Controlled Formation of III-V Nanopillars by Catalyst-Free Growth Mode</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical: This project seeks fundamental understanding of surface kinetics and crystal formation with respect to patterned nanopillar MOCVD epitaxy. Specific goals are to establish a physical model to predict preferential adatom incorporation on III-V semiconductor nanopillars, and to experimentally verify and optimize the formation and characteristics of the nanopillar structures. The project has three primary components: 1) experiment verifiable predictive physical modeling of 3D surface dynamics, 2) correlated nanopillar characterizations and analytical simulations, and 3) controlled preferential nanopillar epitaxy on predetermined sites. Unlike semiconductor nanowires grown using catalytic metal nanoparticles (e.g., Au), these nanopillars are grown without catalysts on masked substrates with lithographically defined nanopatterns. This approach obviates metallic contamination and provides  nanopillar placement, along with subsequent device mask registration. Simulation of atomic surface dynamics, based on ab-initio density functional theory, Wulff's theory and integrated with elastic strain and thermal kinetics components, will be conducted to relate preferential adatom incorporation to nanopillar faceting, surface energy, and growth parameters. Correlated measurements of structural, compositional, electrical, and optical properties will be performed, and combined with mathematical simulation for extraction of nanopillar properties including surface state density, carrier dynamics, and quantum effects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of materials science with technological relevance in electronics and photonics. The materials and nanostructures being studied can potentially serve as basic building blocks for advanced optoelectronic devices. The project emphasizes integrated education and research in training of pre-college, undergraduate, and graduate students through laboratory participation, complementary coursework development, and scientifically focused community K-12 involvement. Both PIs are strongly committed to inclusion and broadening participation of under-represented minority groups in undergraduate and graduate research. Support for undergraduate laboratory employment is budgeted and a plan is in place for focused recruiting through student URM (underrepresented minorities) societies and historically URM colleges, as well through the UCLA Center for Engineering Excellence and Diversity (CEED). Technology transfer is included through collaboration with several companies and national laboratories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1007051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Huffaker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diana Huffaker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dianah@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3103027841</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000422393</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ratsch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christian Ratsch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cratsch@math.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2138254321</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000258178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 Wilshire Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <strong>intellectual merit </strong>of this project is addressed by the scientific discoveries that correlate 3D nanopillar (NP) formation to the predictive physical modeling of surface kinetics, which have ultimately led to a complete understanding of controlling the 3D growth dynamics in several III-V semiconductor materials systems. As a result of such understanding, we have been able to address several shortcomings associated with NP technology that have previously hindered further advancement in this field, such as a poor surface passivation scheme and a lack of control of heterostructure qualities in the NPs. Surface passivation has been accomplished via the development of an in-situ technique, which has significantly improved the optical and electrical properties. Control of different types of heterostructures is realized by successfully predicting the ideal growth environment for adatom diffusion up the sidewalls with theoretical calculations. Several heterostructures, that are unachievable in conventional planar growth techniques due to the lattice mismatch, have been realized.</p> <p>The <strong>broader impacts</strong> have been addressed through the outcomes of this award by integrating education and research in training of pre-college, undergraduate, and graduate students with laboratory participation, complementary coursework development, and scientifically focused K-12 involvement. The graduate students funded by this project are involved in high school outreach programs, organized by California Nano-Systems Institute, that bring high school teachers and students to UCLA to learn nano-science by participating in hands-on experiments, such as self-assembly, dye-sensitized solar cells, and water filtration using nanoparticles (see Fig. 1). Furthermore, both PIs are both committed to the inclusion and broadening participation of under-represented minority (URM) groups in research as there are several URM undergraduate and graduate students who are partially involved in this project. Finally, the outcomes of this project have led to an advanced understanding of 3D nanostructure synthesis. These resulting materials have been realized into interesting and unique nano-devices that can potentially serve as building blocks for future optoelectronics and electronics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/10/2013<br>      Modified by: Diana&nbsp;Huffaker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1007051/1007051_10017328_1378841420281_cleanenergyday34--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1007051/1007051_10017328_1378841420281_cleanenergyday34--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1007051/1007051_10017328_1378841420281_cleanenergyday34--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Clean Energy Day with Garfield High School (LAUSD)</div> <div class="imageCredit">California NanoSystems Institute, UCLA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Diana&nbsp;Huffaker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit of this project is addressed by the scientific discoveries that correlate 3D nanopillar (NP) formation to the predictive physical modeling of surface kinetics, which have ultimately led to a complete understanding of controlling the 3D growth dynamics in several III-V semiconductor materials systems. As a result of such understanding, we have been able to address several shortcomings associated with NP technology that have previously hindered further advancement in this field, such as a poor surface passivation scheme and a lack of control of heterostructure qualities in the NPs. Surface passivation has been accomplished via the development of an in-situ technique, which has significantly improved the optical and electrical properties. Control of different types of heterostructures is realized by successfully predicting the ideal growth environment for adatom diffusion up the sidewalls with theoretical calculations. Several heterostructures, that are unachievable in conventional planar growth techniques due to the lattice mismatch, have been realized.  The broader impacts have been addressed through the outcomes of this award by integrating education and research in training of pre-college, undergraduate, and graduate students with laboratory participation, complementary coursework development, and scientifically focused K-12 involvement. The graduate students funded by this project are involved in high school outreach programs, organized by California Nano-Systems Institute, that bring high school teachers and students to UCLA to learn nano-science by participating in hands-on experiments, such as self-assembly, dye-sensitized solar cells, and water filtration using nanoparticles (see Fig. 1). Furthermore, both PIs are both committed to the inclusion and broadening participation of under-represented minority (URM) groups in research as there are several URM undergraduate and graduate students who are partially involved in this project. Finally, the outcomes of this project have led to an advanced understanding of 3D nanostructure synthesis. These resulting materials have been realized into interesting and unique nano-devices that can potentially serve as building blocks for future optoelectronics and electronics.       Last Modified: 09/10/2013       Submitted by: Diana Huffaker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
