<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Vanishing Quantum Dimensions in Low-dimensional Topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135510.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135510</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The first main theme of the proposed research is quantum 6j-symbols and 3-manifold invariants.  The Principal Investigator, Patureau-Mirand and Turaev have shown that categories with vanishing quantum dimensions naturally give rise to modified 6j-symbols and re-normalized link and 3-manifold invariants.  The project continues this work with a goal of further understanding these objects by deriving explicit formulas for these modified 6j-symbols and constructing Topological Quantum Field Theories (TQFTs) from the re-normalized 3-manifold invariants.  This work is related to the Volume Conjecture.  The proposed research will also focus on constructing generalized Kashaev-type quantum hyperbolic invariants of 3-manifolds with an aim of defining Chern-Simons-type invariants for non-compact groups.   A final theme of the proposed research is the construction of new state-sum invariants of shadows.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the influx of quantum field theory into low-dimensional topology, the past two decades have seen the emergence of a revolutionary point of view in the theory of link and 3-manifold invariants.   The discovery of the V. Jones polynomial by Jones in 1984 and its 3-dimensional quantum field theory interpretation by E. Witten in 1989 have opened the door for the use of new algebraic techniques to study topology.  These developments led to a new branch of mathematic known as "quantum topology."  Many useful and interesting topics of quantum topology are enriched by vanishing quantum dimensions; for example the construction of quantum 3-manifold invariants and the Volume Conjecture both depend on the subtleties of such vanishing.  This project has three components, all concerning the vanishing of quantum dimensions in low-dimensional topology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1007197</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Geer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan C Geer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nathan.geer@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9702164386</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417729</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1415 Old Main Hill ~ Room 64]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~135510</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As a pure mathematician, I am often asked the following questions about my work:</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">I thought all mathematics was understood, what kind of research is there to do in mathematics?</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">Are your research papers just really big equations?</p> <p>The answers to these questions are surprising to most people. &nbsp;First, there is a hugh beautiful world of unknown mathematics waiting to be discovered or created. &nbsp;Second, the world of pure mathematics is rooted in words and ideas rather than numbers and algebraic equations. &nbsp;At first glance these words and ideas seem foreign and unrelated to the natural world. &nbsp;However, pure mathematics is the language of modern physics. &nbsp;This relationship is a miracle that is not well understood, but is productively used. &nbsp;My research is centered in this context. &nbsp;In particular, I am creating new mathematicswith the aim of understanding physical phenomena.</p> <p><br />One of the fundamental ways mathematics arises in nature is through geometry and more generally topology. &nbsp;In particular, geometric objects called manifolds are used to model space and time in general relativity. &nbsp;Surprisingly, manifolds can be studied by knots and more generally links.</p> <p>Knots appear in many places ranging from everyday items such as tied shoe laces to string theory and protein folding. &nbsp;In mathematics, knots and &nbsp;links are fundamental basic objects in topology. &nbsp;Knots as mathematical objects have been studied since the 19th century. &nbsp;More recently, with the influx of quantum field theory into topology, the past two decades have seen the emergence of a revolutionary point of view in the theory of links and 3-manifold invariants. &nbsp;The discovery of the Jones polynomial by V. Jones&nbsp;in 1984 and its 3-dimensional quantum field theory interpretation by E. Witten&nbsp;&nbsp;in 1989 have opened the door for the use of new algebraic techniques to study topology.&nbsp;&nbsp; These developments led to a new branch of mathematics known as "quantum topology." &nbsp;This area has connections to theoretical physics, including quantum gravity, topological quantum field theory and quantum computing. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />A principal feature of quantum topology is its interplay between topology and representation theory (or more generally algebra). &nbsp;The work of NSF grant DMS-1007197 is centered around this interplay. &nbsp;The productive interplay between quantum topology and quantum algebra &nbsp;has been used extensively. &nbsp;The work of this grant focused on extending this interplay to settings where something called quantum dimensions vanish. &nbsp;This work is non-trivial because such vanishings make many established techniques in quantum topology trivial. &nbsp;The results of this grant lead to new invariants in quantum topology whose physical meaning is now being considered. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2013<br>      Modified by: Nathan&nbsp;C&nbsp;Geer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As a pure mathematician, I am often asked the following questions about my work: I thought all mathematics was understood, what kind of research is there to do in mathematics? Are your research papers just really big equations?  The answers to these questions are surprising to most people.  First, there is a hugh beautiful world of unknown mathematics waiting to be discovered or created.  Second, the world of pure mathematics is rooted in words and ideas rather than numbers and algebraic equations.  At first glance these words and ideas seem foreign and unrelated to the natural world.  However, pure mathematics is the language of modern physics.  This relationship is a miracle that is not well understood, but is productively used.  My research is centered in this context.  In particular, I am creating new mathematicswith the aim of understanding physical phenomena.   One of the fundamental ways mathematics arises in nature is through geometry and more generally topology.  In particular, geometric objects called manifolds are used to model space and time in general relativity.  Surprisingly, manifolds can be studied by knots and more generally links.  Knots appear in many places ranging from everyday items such as tied shoe laces to string theory and protein folding.  In mathematics, knots and  links are fundamental basic objects in topology.  Knots as mathematical objects have been studied since the 19th century.  More recently, with the influx of quantum field theory into topology, the past two decades have seen the emergence of a revolutionary point of view in the theory of links and 3-manifold invariants.  The discovery of the Jones polynomial by V. Jones in 1984 and its 3-dimensional quantum field theory interpretation by E. Witten  in 1989 have opened the door for the use of new algebraic techniques to study topology.   These developments led to a new branch of mathematics known as "quantum topology."  This area has connections to theoretical physics, including quantum gravity, topological quantum field theory and quantum computing.     A principal feature of quantum topology is its interplay between topology and representation theory (or more generally algebra).  The work of NSF grant DMS-1007197 is centered around this interplay.  The productive interplay between quantum topology and quantum algebra  has been used extensively.  The work of this grant focused on extending this interplay to settings where something called quantum dimensions vanish.  This work is non-trivial because such vanishings make many established techniques in quantum topology trivial.  The results of this grant lead to new invariants in quantum topology whose physical meaning is now being considered.                    Last Modified: 09/07/2013       Submitted by: Nathan C Geer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
