<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AMC-SS: Analysis of Fluctuations for PDEs with Random Coefficients</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>206923.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>206923</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many physical systems described by partial differential equations (PDEs) are influenced by microscopic variations that may be characterized as random.  A fundamental scientific and mathematical problem is to understand how these random variations influence the system at a macroscopic level. The investigator will study partial differential equations with random coefficients. In some regimes, the macroscopic system is well-approximated by the solution to a simpler "effective equation." In other regimes, however, the macroscopic effective equation is insufficient to characterize the system's behavior because random microscopic variations produce residual fluctuations in the macroscopic system.  In this case, it is important to understand the deviations from the mean behavior. The first part of the project is to characterize the random fluctuations of the wave-like and pulse-like solutions to reaction-diffusion equations and some related equations. Because of the random fluctuation in the coefficients, the solution is random, and it is important to understand how the statistical character of the solution depends on statistical properties of the medium. The second goal is to study random fluctuations of solutions to higher-dimensional models for interface motion. The third goal of the project is to study fluctuations of solutions to elliptic equations with random coefficients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the effect of random microstructure on a macroscopic mathematical model is an important problem in many scientific and engineering applications. How can one quantify uncertainty in predictions of a model when only some statistical properties of the model parameters are known? The analytical techniques developed through this project will have an impact in the area of uncertainty quantification for PDE-based mathematical models.  The specific equations to be studied include reaction-diffusion equations which arise in models of phenomena in turbulent combustion, population ecology, and neuroscience, for example.  The project also will consider elliptic equations which arise in applications such as hydrology and materials science. In these applications, material properties like permeability or electrical conductivity vary randomly and only some statistical properties of these parameters are known.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1007572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Nolen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James H Nolen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nolen@math.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196602862</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000373224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St, Suite 710]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~206923</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br />Many physical systems are influenced by microscopic disorder that may be characterized as random. Therefore, a fundamental scientific and mathematical problem is to characterize and quantify the effect of microscopic uncertainty on the macroscopic behavior of a physical system.&nbsp; Many such systems are modeled mathematically by partial differential equations (PDEs); incorporating microscopic uncertainty or randomness in these models means that the parameters or coefficients in the governing equation should be treated as random. <br /><br />This project focussed on analyzing partial differential equations PDEs with random parameters or coefficients.&nbsp; Previous work in this research area had developed methods for understanding the "average" or "homogenized" behavior of solutions to these equations.&nbsp; The overall goal of this project was to go beyond an understanding of this "average" behavior and to understand how the random solutions fluctuate around the average behavior, in the way that the Central Limit Theorem of probability refines the Law of Large Numbers.&nbsp; This involved developing some mathematical techniques which combine ideas from the areas of probability and of partial differential equations.&nbsp; <br /><br />Much of the work focussed on elliptic equations which are important to applications such as hydrology or materials science. In that setting, one wants to understand how bulk physical properties of the system (such as electrical or thermal conductivity) fluctuate if there is random variation at the microscopic scale.&nbsp; The project also involved reaction-diffusion PDEs which model the motion of fronts and interfaces in a variable environment.&nbsp; Such equations are used to describe biological populations dispersing in a heterogeneous environment, for example.&nbsp; Regarding elliptic PDEs, a major outcome of the project was the development of a central limit theorm for certain statistics of solutions to the PDE.&nbsp; This relied on a novel application of a mathematical technique in probability known as Stein's method.&nbsp; This collection of results gives a rigorous mathematical motivation for modeling certain effective properties of a random material as Gaussian random variables.&nbsp; Regarding reaction diffusion equations, the PI developed mathematical tools for studying reaction-diffusion fronts in random media. In particular, the PI and collaborators developed a stability theory for certain reaction diffusion equations (KPP-type) with periodic coefficients; when extended further, this stability theory will play an important role in understanding the behavior of solutions when the parameters are random.&nbsp; The PI also derived an estimate on the variance of solutions to a Hamilton-Jacobi equation with random coefficients, showing that the solutions exhibit non-classical scaling of fluctuations.&nbsp; <br /><br />The PI's work on PDEs with random coefficients also stimulated the development of some novel results in related areas. First, the PI and collaborators began developing an asymptotic theory for random sampling of data in non-Euclidean geometric spaces. One motivation for this comes from the study of phylogenetic trees, where the trees are biological data sets that may be regarded as points in a certain geometric space.&nbsp; The PI's work in this direction was to develop a central limit theorem for this geometric setting.&nbsp; The PI and a collaborator also developed mathematical theory for understanding rare events in certain stochastic systems, including random graphs and systems modeled by stochastic differential equations.<br /><br />From an educational point of view, the project involved training of multiple students, both graduate and undergraduate. The PI was co-organizer of a research workshop on random media, co-organizer of a workshop on the simulation of rare events, and co-organizer of a graduate ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Many physical systems are influenced by microscopic disorder that may be characterized as random. Therefore, a fundamental scientific and mathematical problem is to characterize and quantify the effect of microscopic uncertainty on the macroscopic behavior of a physical system.  Many such systems are modeled mathematically by partial differential equations (PDEs); incorporating microscopic uncertainty or randomness in these models means that the parameters or coefficients in the governing equation should be treated as random.   This project focussed on analyzing partial differential equations PDEs with random parameters or coefficients.  Previous work in this research area had developed methods for understanding the "average" or "homogenized" behavior of solutions to these equations.  The overall goal of this project was to go beyond an understanding of this "average" behavior and to understand how the random solutions fluctuate around the average behavior, in the way that the Central Limit Theorem of probability refines the Law of Large Numbers.  This involved developing some mathematical techniques which combine ideas from the areas of probability and of partial differential equations.    Much of the work focussed on elliptic equations which are important to applications such as hydrology or materials science. In that setting, one wants to understand how bulk physical properties of the system (such as electrical or thermal conductivity) fluctuate if there is random variation at the microscopic scale.  The project also involved reaction-diffusion PDEs which model the motion of fronts and interfaces in a variable environment.  Such equations are used to describe biological populations dispersing in a heterogeneous environment, for example.  Regarding elliptic PDEs, a major outcome of the project was the development of a central limit theorm for certain statistics of solutions to the PDE.  This relied on a novel application of a mathematical technique in probability known as Stein's method.  This collection of results gives a rigorous mathematical motivation for modeling certain effective properties of a random material as Gaussian random variables.  Regarding reaction diffusion equations, the PI developed mathematical tools for studying reaction-diffusion fronts in random media. In particular, the PI and collaborators developed a stability theory for certain reaction diffusion equations (KPP-type) with periodic coefficients; when extended further, this stability theory will play an important role in understanding the behavior of solutions when the parameters are random.  The PI also derived an estimate on the variance of solutions to a Hamilton-Jacobi equation with random coefficients, showing that the solutions exhibit non-classical scaling of fluctuations.    The PI's work on PDEs with random coefficients also stimulated the development of some novel results in related areas. First, the PI and collaborators began developing an asymptotic theory for random sampling of data in non-Euclidean geometric spaces. One motivation for this comes from the study of phylogenetic trees, where the trees are biological data sets that may be regarded as points in a certain geometric space.  The PI's work in this direction was to develop a central limit theorem for this geometric setting.  The PI and a collaborator also developed mathematical theory for understanding rare events in certain stochastic systems, including random graphs and systems modeled by stochastic differential equations.  From an educational point of view, the project involved training of multiple students, both graduate and undergraduate. The PI was co-organizer of a research workshop on random media, co-organizer of a workshop on the simulation of rare events, and co-organizer of a graduate summer school for training students in mathematical techniques related to PDEs with random parameters.  In additional to journal publications, the results of this research have been ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
