<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Numerical Inversion of the Laplace Transform and its Applications to Evolution Equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100068.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100068</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Jara&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1008101&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     The investigator studies the theory and applications of the&lt;br/&gt;numerical inversion of the vector-valued Laplace transform.  The&lt;br/&gt;objectives are (i) to extend the investigator's results for the&lt;br/&gt;numerical inversion of the Laplace transform beyond the&lt;br/&gt;noise-free case, (ii) to develop new approximation methods for&lt;br/&gt;the numerical inversion of the vector-valued Laplace transform,&lt;br/&gt;(iii) to show that the inversion of the Laplace transform&lt;br/&gt;together with the theory of finite elements provide a solid&lt;br/&gt;foundation for the numerical approximation of solutions of&lt;br/&gt;evolution equations of convolution type, (iv) to apply the&lt;br/&gt;approximation methods to problems arising from transport in&lt;br/&gt;multiscale porous materials, and (v) to provide research&lt;br/&gt;experience for undergraduate students.  The main idea is that&lt;br/&gt;approximation methods for the shift operator semigroup on the&lt;br/&gt;space of continuous and exponentially bounded functions with&lt;br/&gt;values in a general Banach space translates into approximation&lt;br/&gt;methods for the inversion of the Laplace transform of these&lt;br/&gt;functions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     Evolution processes arise in many scientific problems, such&lt;br/&gt;as fluid flows, image processing, mechanical systems, relativity,&lt;br/&gt;mathematical finance, and mathematical biology.  These processes&lt;br/&gt;are described by the solutions of certain integro-partial&lt;br/&gt;differential equations.  However, in most of these cases, the&lt;br/&gt;solutions cannot be calculated explicitly because either they&lt;br/&gt;cannot be found or they are not obtained in a plain algebraic&lt;br/&gt;form.  Thus, in order to obtain an accurate description of the&lt;br/&gt;evolution process, one needs to develop accurate approximations&lt;br/&gt;to the solutions of these equations.  The scalable methods&lt;br/&gt;recently developed by the investigator and his collaborators&lt;br/&gt;concerning the Laplace transform provide accurate approximations&lt;br/&gt;to solutions of integro-partial differential equations of&lt;br/&gt;convolution type.  The principal investigator further develops&lt;br/&gt;and implements new approximation methods, and uses these methods&lt;br/&gt;for the accurate description of different evolution processes. &lt;br/&gt;Undergraduate research experience is provided to students by&lt;br/&gt;using the different methods to approximate the solutions of&lt;br/&gt;problems related to transport in multiscale porous materials,&lt;br/&gt;like oil and gas exploration, or controlling underground sources&lt;br/&gt;of pollution such as high-level radioactive waste and&lt;br/&gt;geologically stored carbon dioxide.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1008101</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patricio</FirstName>
<LastName>Jara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patricio Jara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pjara@tnstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6159635000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000543413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tennessee State University</Name>
<CityName>nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372091561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6159637631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3500 John A. Merritt Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>108814179</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TENNESSEE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>878135631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tennessee State University]]></Name>
<CityName>nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372091561</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3500 John A. Merritt Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~100068</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project studied the theory and applications of the numerical inversion of the vector-valued Laplace transform. The objectives were (i) to extend the investigator's results for the numerical inversion of the Laplace transform, (ii) to develop new approximation methods for the numerical inversion of the vector-valued Laplace transform, (iii) to show that the inversion of the Laplace transform together with the theory of finite elements provide a solid foundation for the numerical approximation of solutions of evolution equations of convolution type,&nbsp; and (iv) to provide research experience for undergraduate students.&nbsp; Evolution processes arise in many scientific problems, such as fluid flows, image processing, mechanical systems, relativity, mathematical finance, and mathematical biology. These processes are described by the solutions of certain integro-partial differential equations. However, in most of these cases, the solutions cannot be calculated explicitly because either they cannot be found or they are not obtained in a plain algebraic form. Thus, in order to obtain an accurate description of the evolution process, one needs to develop accurate approximations to the solutions of these equations. The scalable methods recently developed by the investigator and his collaborators concerning the Laplace transform provide accurate approximations to solutions of integro-partial differential equations of convolution type. The research experience for students included students developing Bachelor degree&nbsp; Senior Project, a one month Summer Workshop and two students who obtained their masters degree in Mathematics. Several papers have been submitted for publication.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2015<br>      Modified by: Patricio&nbsp;Jara</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project studied the theory and applications of the numerical inversion of the vector-valued Laplace transform. The objectives were (i) to extend the investigator's results for the numerical inversion of the Laplace transform, (ii) to develop new approximation methods for the numerical inversion of the vector-valued Laplace transform, (iii) to show that the inversion of the Laplace transform together with the theory of finite elements provide a solid foundation for the numerical approximation of solutions of evolution equations of convolution type,  and (iv) to provide research experience for undergraduate students.  Evolution processes arise in many scientific problems, such as fluid flows, image processing, mechanical systems, relativity, mathematical finance, and mathematical biology. These processes are described by the solutions of certain integro-partial differential equations. However, in most of these cases, the solutions cannot be calculated explicitly because either they cannot be found or they are not obtained in a plain algebraic form. Thus, in order to obtain an accurate description of the evolution process, one needs to develop accurate approximations to the solutions of these equations. The scalable methods recently developed by the investigator and his collaborators concerning the Laplace transform provide accurate approximations to solutions of integro-partial differential equations of convolution type. The research experience for students included students developing Bachelor degree  Senior Project, a one month Summer Workshop and two students who obtained their masters degree in Mathematics. Several papers have been submitted for publication.       Last Modified: 07/31/2015       Submitted by: Patricio Jara]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
