<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Education Policy Studies - Empirical Research: Urban High School Opportunity Structures, Figured Worlds of STEM, and Choice of Major and College Destination</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>749756.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>899756</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen King</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This longitudinal, empirical, collaborative research study seeks to identify the influence of expanded "opportunity structures" in high school for preparation in mathematics and science on choice of college destinations by non-privileged high school students and their selection of STEM majors. Students studied in this longitudinal study will initially be sophomores in two geographically different urban settings - Buffalo, NY and Denver, CO.  The students in the sample have math grades that place in them in the top 20% of their class but have limited social, economic, and cultural capital (for example, parents whose education ended with little or no-college attendance). Because prior work has found that matriculation in good colleges and selection of STEM majors has varied widely in comparing students who seem to come from comparable high schools in terms of socioeconomic status, this study will add to our understanding of underlying factors.  Also, the extensive investment across US Public high schools in AP, IB, magnet schools, after-school programs, science competitions, and other enrichment activities indicates that improved understanding of the impact of these investments would be likely to be valuable to many school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Prior research has shown that expanded opportunity structures in science and math facilitate greater college attendance, including at elite colleges.  But there is not sufficient research on which types of students are helped by this and on how such structures influence student choice of academic major.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study builds upon extensive prior research including those that employed anthropological and sociological investigations of indicators that influence personal perceptions and subsequent decisions regarding students' roles in society. This study is grounded by theoretical support from Bourdieu's Theory of Social Practice (1977) and Arum, Gamoran, and Shavit's Theory of Educational Expansion and Differentiation (2007). Answers to the research questions guiding this study are expected to advance understanding of the impact of school structures to expand educational opportunities in science and math to non-socially and non-culturally capitalized students. The PIs hypothesize that when such opportunities for educational expansion are implemented they should contribute to the reduction of inequalities associated with STEM pursuits and outcomes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1008215</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lois</FirstName>
<LastName>Weis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lois Weis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>weis@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7168677661</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000548102</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 Lee Entrance]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REESE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~238804</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~249614</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~261338</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~69999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~80001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goals of this project were to investigate the implications of (1) high school opportunity structures (math/science course availability, content/context, sequences/requirements; teacher experience; guidance/counseling services; technology use; extracurricular offerings; and student experience) and (2) 'figured worlds of STEM' (cultural models of the kinds of people who pursue STEM, and why) for choice of major (STEM vs. non-STEM) and college destination.&nbsp;</p> <p>Longitudinal ethnographic case studies were conducted in 4 urban non-selective high schools in Buffalo, NY, with additional ethnographic observations and ethnographic interviews with approximately 48 focal students (all of whom were high-achieving in math and science after 9<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;grade) at each school and their parents/guardians. Ethnographic research was conducted over three years (2010-2013) as the students moved from being high school sophomores to seniors.</p> <p>This research is in collaboration with a team led by Professor Margaret Eisenhart at the University of Colorado-Boulder; the Colorado team conducted a comparable set of studies in Denver, with specific focus on four high schools that serve similarly capitalized students as those in Buffalo. In addition, the proportion of underrepresented minorities was largely comparable in sample schools in both cities.</p> <p>Results of our research show the following:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;Public non-criterion based high schools with similar student populations (~70-80% free/reduced lunch; ~ 75% minority) differ substantially in how they promote and organize STEM opportunities.&nbsp; Some do so via Honors and AP courses; others do so via 'academies' (course offerings organized by interest area) or 'tracks' (a forensics track); others do so via required coursework for graduation. &nbsp;Within one school, several different arrangements may be available.&nbsp;</p> <p>2) In both cities, the labeling of schools as 'STEM-focused' has proliferated and some public high schools that were not meeting NCLB standards have been converted to STEM schools.&nbsp; The STEM schools in our study are of this type and we find that these schools are awash in the reform agenda.&nbsp;As a rule, these schools receive no or few sustained extra resources specifically for STEM, as compared to traditional high schools. Despite their (STEM-focused) name, these schools turn out to be a far cry from the model STEM schools promoted by policy makers.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>3) Focal students in Buffalo and Denver share similar and familiar 'figured worlds' of schooling and STEM, but they differ substantially in their outlook on and expectations for both lived-out and articulated high school and college-going opportunities. Students in Denver tend to be more positive about schooling and their future prospects than those in Buffalo.&nbsp;</p> <p>4)&nbsp;The schools in both Buffalo and Denver vigorously promote a discourse supporting education in general and the importance of going to a 4-year college in particular.&nbsp; Vocational and technical trajectories are available and of interest to some focal students, but the prevailing discourse accords them very low status.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>5)&nbsp;With the exception of students at one Denver school with a somewhat higher demographic profile, the worlds of college and career aspirations across city are vaguely configured or absent specific content pertaining to college life, college expectations, or the preparatory structures for college admission and career development.</p> <p>6)&nbsp;There is broad-based interest in both STEM careers and education more generally among students and parents across the two cities. Focal students work relatively hard compared to other students in their schools and attain good grades in their courses, including science and math. But these same students exhibit misaligned ambitions. This lack of knowledge, coupled with limited meaningful school counseling and guidance, makes college success problematic and careers in STEM largely out of reach for this population.</p> <p>7)&nbsp;In terms of actual opportunities to learn about college, careers, or STEM, students and parents in both cities exhibit scant knowledge of what is available and how they can access it.</p> <p>8) In contrast to Buffalo, Denver appears to exhibit some sustained expansion in the number of STEM related opportunities (course offerings; proportion of schools devoted to STEM) for low-income underrepresented minorities. However, even in Denver, efforts to expand offerings have not always been realized, and overall student proficiency in math and science remains below average.&nbsp;Our findings&nbsp;suggest ways in which fundamentally good intentions related to expansion of opportunities for the population under consideration can be quickly eroded, as well as key mechanisms and spaces within which such erosion takes place. Such wholesale erosion of intended opportunities leads to marked constriction for STEM in college and careers for low-income URM.</p> <p>9) Qualitative and descriptive statistical analyses completed enable us to begin to see important links between high school opportunity structure, figured worlds of STEM in high school, postsecondary matriculation patterns, and choice of college major. Our approach draws attention to the aspects of opportunity structures that students actually respond to and answer as they orchestrate identities, how and when these identities shift and interconnect, and how they can launch individuals forward into the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Lois&nbsp;Weis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1008215/1008215_10047659_1572659490095_Publications--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1008215/1008215_10047659_1572659490095_Publications--rgov-800width.jpg" title="List of Grant Publications"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1008215/1008215_10047659_1572659490095_Publications--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="List of Grant Publications"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Publications Resulting From NSF Grant #1008215</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lois&nbsp;Weis</div> <div class="imageTitle">List of Grant Publications</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this project were to investigate the implications of (1) high school opportunity structures (math/science course availability, content/context, sequences/requirements; teacher experience; guidance/counseling services; technology use; extracurricular offerings; and student experience) and (2) 'figured worlds of STEM' (cultural models of the kinds of people who pursue STEM, and why) for choice of major (STEM vs. non-STEM) and college destination.   Longitudinal ethnographic case studies were conducted in 4 urban non-selective high schools in Buffalo, NY, with additional ethnographic observations and ethnographic interviews with approximately 48 focal students (all of whom were high-achieving in math and science after 9th grade) at each school and their parents/guardians. Ethnographic research was conducted over three years (2010-2013) as the students moved from being high school sophomores to seniors.  This research is in collaboration with a team led by Professor Margaret Eisenhart at the University of Colorado-Boulder; the Colorado team conducted a comparable set of studies in Denver, with specific focus on four high schools that serve similarly capitalized students as those in Buffalo. In addition, the proportion of underrepresented minorities was largely comparable in sample schools in both cities.  Results of our research show the following:  1) Public non-criterion based high schools with similar student populations (~70-80% free/reduced lunch; ~ 75% minority) differ substantially in how they promote and organize STEM opportunities.  Some do so via Honors and AP courses; others do so via 'academies' (course offerings organized by interest area) or 'tracks' (a forensics track); others do so via required coursework for graduation.  Within one school, several different arrangements may be available.   2) In both cities, the labeling of schools as 'STEM-focused' has proliferated and some public high schools that were not meeting NCLB standards have been converted to STEM schools.  The STEM schools in our study are of this type and we find that these schools are awash in the reform agenda. As a rule, these schools receive no or few sustained extra resources specifically for STEM, as compared to traditional high schools. Despite their (STEM-focused) name, these schools turn out to be a far cry from the model STEM schools promoted by policy makers.    3) Focal students in Buffalo and Denver share similar and familiar 'figured worlds' of schooling and STEM, but they differ substantially in their outlook on and expectations for both lived-out and articulated high school and college-going opportunities. Students in Denver tend to be more positive about schooling and their future prospects than those in Buffalo.   4) The schools in both Buffalo and Denver vigorously promote a discourse supporting education in general and the importance of going to a 4-year college in particular.  Vocational and technical trajectories are available and of interest to some focal students, but the prevailing discourse accords them very low status.    5) With the exception of students at one Denver school with a somewhat higher demographic profile, the worlds of college and career aspirations across city are vaguely configured or absent specific content pertaining to college life, college expectations, or the preparatory structures for college admission and career development.  6) There is broad-based interest in both STEM careers and education more generally among students and parents across the two cities. Focal students work relatively hard compared to other students in their schools and attain good grades in their courses, including science and math. But these same students exhibit misaligned ambitions. This lack of knowledge, coupled with limited meaningful school counseling and guidance, makes college success problematic and careers in STEM largely out of reach for this population.  7) In terms of actual opportunities to learn about college, careers, or STEM, students and parents in both cities exhibit scant knowledge of what is available and how they can access it.  8) In contrast to Buffalo, Denver appears to exhibit some sustained expansion in the number of STEM related opportunities (course offerings; proportion of schools devoted to STEM) for low-income underrepresented minorities. However, even in Denver, efforts to expand offerings have not always been realized, and overall student proficiency in math and science remains below average. Our findings suggest ways in which fundamentally good intentions related to expansion of opportunities for the population under consideration can be quickly eroded, as well as key mechanisms and spaces within which such erosion takes place. Such wholesale erosion of intended opportunities leads to marked constriction for STEM in college and careers for low-income URM.  9) Qualitative and descriptive statistical analyses completed enable us to begin to see important links between high school opportunity structure, figured worlds of STEM in high school, postsecondary matriculation patterns, and choice of college major. Our approach draws attention to the aspects of opportunity structures that students actually respond to and answer as they orchestrate identities, how and when these identities shift and interconnect, and how they can launch individuals forward into the future.          Last Modified: 11/01/2019       Submitted by: Lois Weis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
