<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Collaborative Research: Quantifying the Role of Impurities that Control Stress-Driven Grain Growth in Nanocrystalline Metals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Haiyan Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Materials World Network award supports an international multidisciplinary research team from University of Pennsylvania, Johns Hopkins University, and University of Sydney (Australia) to elucidate the fundamental role of impurities on coupled grain boundary migration as manifest in the observation of stress-assisted room temperature grain growth in nanocrystalline metals.  This study is motivated by recent findings that showed that deformation mechanisms in nanocrystalline metals are not only different to those in microcrystalline metals but are dynamic as well. Local grain boundary pinning by impurities is central to the understanding, and ultimately control, of stress-driven microstructural evolution, but until recently the atomic-level experimental characterization of local dopant concentration and spatial distribution has not been possible.  Our global team will use state-of-the-art 3D atom probe tomography to investigate local structure and impurity segregation in nanocrystalline metal thin films that have been synthesized by reactive sputtering to introduce systematically varied amounts of dopants in the material.  Special emphasis will be placed on characterizing the effect of intrinsic and extrinsic parameters (grain size, impurity content, boundary orientation, etc.) on both grain growth and the attendant, dynamic, mechanical behavior of nanocrystalline films.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Controlling impurity pinning of grain boundaries controlling stress-driven microstructural evolution offers a unique avenue for tailoring the mechanical properties of nanocrystalline materials.  The combination of a microstructure?s ability to augment its deformation mechanisms to accommodate stress via dynamic evolution and control of the threshold stress for grain boundary migration by local spatially controlled doping would facilitate atomic-level engineering and potentially introduce a new class of materials. Novel characterization and in situ testing tools and methods will be developed and utilized, pushing the frontier of experimental nanoscience. The proposed Materials World Network team will design and teach short courses about 3D atom probe tomography and in situ mechanical testing targeted at research and industrial scientists and engineers.  The proposed integration of undergraduate students will engage young scientists and engineers in novel and international research activities, providing experiences and opportunities that will allow students to become better global citizens.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1008222</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Gianola</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel S Gianola</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gianola@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058938143</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539860</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Research Services]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Key outcomes for the Materials World Network project, which catalyzed an international collaborative effort between senior and junior researchers from University of Pennsylvania (USA), Johns Hopkins University (USA), and University of Sydney (Australia), are summarized below. &nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>We provided direct experimental evidence of the segregation of impurity elements to grain boundaries in nominally pure nanocrystalline metals. We found a strong correlation between the strength and ductility of nanocrystalline Al thin films and the amount of O segregation. The increased strength (and reduced ductility) was beyond that which could be expected due to solid solution strengthening and was attributed to a change in the critical stress required for stress-assisted grain boundary migration and associated grain growth.</li> <li>We combined site-specific in situ TEM nanoindentation with 3D atom probe tomography to provide the missing link between grain boundary excess and the critical shear stress for grain boundary migration &ndash; the precursor to stress-assisted grain growth.&nbsp; <strong></strong></li> <li>We showed that a critical grain boundary excess of impurities is required to stabilize nanocrystalline materials against mechanical driving forces, providing a new avenue for controlling deformation mechanisms and tailoring mechanical properties, apart from grain size alone.<strong></strong></li> <li>We demonstrated convincing control of grain boundary chemistry to tailor thermal and mechanical stability &nbsp;&ndash; by differing extents &ndash; of nanocrystalline thin films.<strong></strong></li> <li>We developed novel quantitative in situ mechanical probes and analysis tools including microtensile specimen fabrication, instrumented in situ mechanical testing, automated full-field orientation mapping, and 3D atom probe tomography and analysis.<strong></strong></li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Our project provided key insights to a delineation between mechanically dynamic and static nanocrystalline microstructures, as controlled by the impurity content (and thus grain boundary excess), which has dramatic ramifications for the mechanical response in terms of accommodation of plastic deformation and damage tolerance. The striking implication from our collective and collaborative efforts made possible by this project are two-fold.&nbsp; First, a critical stress exists for the operation of mechanically driven grain boundary motion, the precursor for widespread grain growth, in nanocrystalline metals and alloys.&nbsp; Second, the value of this stress can be tailored by rational synthesis and processing with alloying species that segregate to grain boundaries.&nbsp; Our work sets the stage for systematic comparisons of the degree of alloying required for thermal stability with that of mechanical stability, and for further examining the atomic mechanisms responsible for thermodynamic stability or retarded kinetics.&nbsp; Notably, our results suggest a crossover between dynamic and static deformation mechanisms, and consequently a tunable mechanical stability of nanocrystalline materials, with only a dilute concentration of alloying species.&nbsp; This enables the wide spectrum of materials design with minimal constraints of materials costs and abundance.&nbsp; Most tantalizing, though, is the notion of a new structural materials engineering paradigm that offers high strength coupled with a thermally and mechanically stable nanostructure, juxtaposed with an adaptive deformation mechanism that can respond to locally high stresses in extreme conditions in a self-healing fashion.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/04/2015<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;S&nbsp;Gianola</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</s...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Key outcomes for the Materials World Network project, which catalyzed an international collaborative effort between senior and junior researchers from University of Pennsylvania (USA), Johns Hopkins University (USA), and University of Sydney (Australia), are summarized below.    We provided direct experimental evidence of the segregation of impurity elements to grain boundaries in nominally pure nanocrystalline metals. We found a strong correlation between the strength and ductility of nanocrystalline Al thin films and the amount of O segregation. The increased strength (and reduced ductility) was beyond that which could be expected due to solid solution strengthening and was attributed to a change in the critical stress required for stress-assisted grain boundary migration and associated grain growth. We combined site-specific in situ TEM nanoindentation with 3D atom probe tomography to provide the missing link between grain boundary excess and the critical shear stress for grain boundary migration &ndash; the precursor to stress-assisted grain growth.   We showed that a critical grain boundary excess of impurities is required to stabilize nanocrystalline materials against mechanical driving forces, providing a new avenue for controlling deformation mechanisms and tailoring mechanical properties, apart from grain size alone. We demonstrated convincing control of grain boundary chemistry to tailor thermal and mechanical stability  &ndash; by differing extents &ndash; of nanocrystalline thin films. We developed novel quantitative in situ mechanical probes and analysis tools including microtensile specimen fabrication, instrumented in situ mechanical testing, automated full-field orientation mapping, and 3D atom probe tomography and analysis.    Our project provided key insights to a delineation between mechanically dynamic and static nanocrystalline microstructures, as controlled by the impurity content (and thus grain boundary excess), which has dramatic ramifications for the mechanical response in terms of accommodation of plastic deformation and damage tolerance. The striking implication from our collective and collaborative efforts made possible by this project are two-fold.  First, a critical stress exists for the operation of mechanically driven grain boundary motion, the precursor for widespread grain growth, in nanocrystalline metals and alloys.  Second, the value of this stress can be tailored by rational synthesis and processing with alloying species that segregate to grain boundaries.  Our work sets the stage for systematic comparisons of the degree of alloying required for thermal stability with that of mechanical stability, and for further examining the atomic mechanisms responsible for thermodynamic stability or retarded kinetics.  Notably, our results suggest a crossover between dynamic and static deformation mechanisms, and consequently a tunable mechanical stability of nanocrystalline materials, with only a dilute concentration of alloying species.  This enables the wide spectrum of materials design with minimal constraints of materials costs and abundance.  Most tantalizing, though, is the notion of a new structural materials engineering paradigm that offers high strength coupled with a thermally and mechanically stable nanostructure, juxtaposed with an adaptive deformation mechanism that can respond to locally high stresses in extreme conditions in a self-healing fashion.       Last Modified: 05/04/2015       Submitted by: Daniel S Gianola]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
