<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mathematical Analysis of Interfacial Dynamics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>233460.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>233460</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Chen&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1008905&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     The objective of this project is to provide a systematic&lt;br/&gt;study of multi-phase transitions.  There are macroscopic free&lt;br/&gt;boundary models, which are based on observable quantities and are&lt;br/&gt;needed to deal with singularities due to topological changes of&lt;br/&gt;free boundaries, and microscopic continuum models, derived at the&lt;br/&gt;molecular level and (always) well-posed.  One goal of the project&lt;br/&gt;is to derive critical information from continuum models for free&lt;br/&gt;boundary models when the latter become indeterminate.  Another is&lt;br/&gt;to develop new microscopic continuum models for phase transitions&lt;br/&gt;among phases such as solid/liquid and different grains in a&lt;br/&gt;polycrystalline material.  The main tools used here are theories&lt;br/&gt;of partial differential equations, singular perturbations,&lt;br/&gt;asymptotic expansions, complex analysis, bifurcation, center&lt;br/&gt;manifolds, global analysis, dynamical systems, and geometric&lt;br/&gt;measure.  From time to time, computer assistance is used to first&lt;br/&gt;stimulate, then validate, and further extend theoretical&lt;br/&gt;conclusions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     The investigator studies interfacial phenomena, which are&lt;br/&gt;commonplace in nature and occur whenever there is a continuum&lt;br/&gt;that can exist in at least two different phases and there is some&lt;br/&gt;mechanism that generates a spatial separation of these phases. &lt;br/&gt;The spatial boundaries that separate these phases, referred to as&lt;br/&gt;interfaces or free boundaries, evolve with time due to some&lt;br/&gt;enforcement of transitions of phases from one to another.  A&lt;br/&gt;typical two-phase transition is a solidification process of a&lt;br/&gt;liquid.  A classical multi-phase transition arises from&lt;br/&gt;evolutions of grains in a polycrystal where alignments of atoms&lt;br/&gt;in different grains do not match at grain boundaries.  The growth&lt;br/&gt;of a solid polycrystal from a liquid involves a two-phase&lt;br/&gt;transition between liquid and solid and a multi-phase transition&lt;br/&gt;among grains.  These phenomena motivate new theoretical&lt;br/&gt;development in free boundary problems, systems of parabolic or&lt;br/&gt;elliptic partial or ordinary differential equations, and&lt;br/&gt;dynamical systems.  Insights gained from the project increase&lt;br/&gt;connections between mathematicians and materials scientists.  New&lt;br/&gt;models developed here provide scientists with tools for&lt;br/&gt;understanding and designing new materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1008905</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xinfu</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xinfu Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Xinfu@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248362</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288983</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Murdoch Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~233460</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project carried out research on interfacial dynamics, e.g., the motion of boundary between liquid and solid. Significant results are obtained and are published in 26 papers in high quality journals.</p> <p>Two free boundary models are proposed and mathematically analyzed. One for the motion of boundary between solid and liquid and one for the contact angle at the intersection of&nbsp;vapor, liquid, and solid. For the first model, anisotropy (the mathematical base for the formation of snowflakes instead of ice balls) and long-range molecular interactions are considered. For the second model, the change of contact angles during the movement of liquid along solid surface with microscopic surface structure are considered. To analyze the models, advanced&nbsp;mathematical theories are developed and novel methods are introduced.</p> <p>This project also developed a free boundary model for&nbsp;optimal investment and consumption with transaction cost. The free boundaries&nbsp;here are the price levels and amounts&nbsp;at which financial assets are&nbsp;sold or purchased. Mathematical theories are built for the model. Optimal strategies for the trading are described and analyzed.</p> <p>Several classical free boundary problems proposed in the project&nbsp;are also investigated with significant results produced and published.&nbsp;New insights&nbsp;are obtained through the research.&nbsp;For&nbsp;the advancement of liquid front&nbsp;in a&nbsp;solidification process of undercooled&nbsp;liquid, a new method&nbsp;is introduced to&nbsp;produce a&nbsp;long anticipating result regarding the property of the liquid front. Also probabilistic models are introduced for phase changes,&nbsp;such as liquid&nbsp;and solid phase switch at freezing temperature.</p> <p>The models proposed through the research provided&nbsp;new ingredients in the area of free boundary study. Mathematical theories developed greatly enhanced the power of&nbsp;mathematics. The novel methods introduced will be used for many existing open problems in the area of free boundary research.</p> <p>Insight gained from the project greatly increased the connection between mathematics and its application. The research on investment and consumption provides a&nbsp;practitioner useful tool in evaluating financial situation and making rational decision. The new models developed from the project&nbsp;provide useful&nbsp;theoretical apparatus&nbsp;for scientists not specialized in mathematics to study&nbsp;the underling interfacial phenomena. They can be used to design new materials.</p> <p>This project provided undergraduate and graduate students opportunities in conducting research using mathematical tools. Teaching materials are also developed from the research and are&nbsp;used in teaching undergraduate and graduate courses. These materials enhanced students'&nbsp;interests and their ability to solve real life&nbsp;problems using mathematics.</p> <p>The research results are&nbsp;advocated through many national and international seminars, colloquiums, and conferences.&nbsp;These activities improved general public's appreciation of mathematics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/13/2015<br>      Modified by: Xinfu&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project carried out research on interfacial dynamics, e.g., the motion of boundary between liquid and solid. Significant results are obtained and are published in 26 papers in high quality journals.  Two free boundary models are proposed and mathematically analyzed. One for the motion of boundary between solid and liquid and one for the contact angle at the intersection of vapor, liquid, and solid. For the first model, anisotropy (the mathematical base for the formation of snowflakes instead of ice balls) and long-range molecular interactions are considered. For the second model, the change of contact angles during the movement of liquid along solid surface with microscopic surface structure are considered. To analyze the models, advanced mathematical theories are developed and novel methods are introduced.  This project also developed a free boundary model for optimal investment and consumption with transaction cost. The free boundaries here are the price levels and amounts at which financial assets are sold or purchased. Mathematical theories are built for the model. Optimal strategies for the trading are described and analyzed.  Several classical free boundary problems proposed in the project are also investigated with significant results produced and published. New insights are obtained through the research. For the advancement of liquid front in a solidification process of undercooled liquid, a new method is introduced to produce a long anticipating result regarding the property of the liquid front. Also probabilistic models are introduced for phase changes, such as liquid and solid phase switch at freezing temperature.  The models proposed through the research provided new ingredients in the area of free boundary study. Mathematical theories developed greatly enhanced the power of mathematics. The novel methods introduced will be used for many existing open problems in the area of free boundary research.  Insight gained from the project greatly increased the connection between mathematics and its application. The research on investment and consumption provides a practitioner useful tool in evaluating financial situation and making rational decision. The new models developed from the project provide useful theoretical apparatus for scientists not specialized in mathematics to study the underling interfacial phenomena. They can be used to design new materials.  This project provided undergraduate and graduate students opportunities in conducting research using mathematical tools. Teaching materials are also developed from the research and are used in teaching undergraduate and graduate courses. These materials enhanced students' interests and their ability to solve real life problems using mathematics.  The research results are advocated through many national and international seminars, colloquiums, and conferences. These activities improved general public's appreciation of mathematics.       Last Modified: 05/13/2015       Submitted by: Xinfu Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
