<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Deformation via the Transformation of Hierarchical Microstructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>480000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gary Shiflet</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Materials World Network research project between Prof. Peter Müllner, Prof. William Knowlton, and Res. Assist. Prof. Paul Lindquist at Boise State University (BSU) and Profs. Steffen Brinckmann and Alexander Hartmaier at the Ruhr University Bochum, Germany, focuses on the deformation mechanism of materials with hierarchically twinned microstructures. While such microstructures occur in many functional materials including shape-memory alloys and ferroelastic ceramics, the experimental part of this study concentrates on magnetic shape-memory alloys (MSMAs). The mechanical and magneto-mechanical properties of magnetic shape-memory alloys strongly depend on details of the twin microstructure, which can be varied via appropriate thermo-magneto-mechanical training treatments. For well-trained single crystals with a single operating twinning system, the twinning stress is very low (about 0.1 MPa), the magnetic-field-induced strain is large (6-10 %), and the fatigue life is short (about 10,000 cycles). For un-trained single crystals with self-accommodated, hierarchically twinned martensite, the twinning stress is relatively high (about 2 MPa), the magnetic-field-induced strain is small (about 0.1 %), and the fatigue life is long (exceeding 100 million cycles). The deformation mechanism of hierarchically twinned microstructures will be studied experimentally at Boise State University on all length scales with in-situ deformation experiments while numerical studies will be performed at the Ruhr University Bochum. The experiments include in-situ straining in the transmission electron microscope (microscale), in the scanning probe microscope (mesoscale), and with optical imaging in the tensile test bench (macroscale). The defect content of the twin microstructure will be obtained from the experimental study. Disclination dipoles, i.e. mesoscopic line defects with a shear displacement field, represent the displacement fields of twins on all hierarchical levels. A disclination dynamics code will be developed and applied to a large scale numerical study. By supplying the numerical study with experimental data, and by systematically varying experimental and numerical parameters, a quantitative fundamental understanding of the mechanical (and magneto-mechanical) properties of (magnetic) shape-memory alloys with complex hierarchical twin-microstructures will be generated. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A strong impact on technology is anticipated: The quantitative understanding gained with this study will allow the development of fast and high-rescission MSMA actuators with large stroke and long lifetime for applications including valves for ink-jet printers and micropumps for biomedical systems. This project will produce the computational tools required for leading MSMAs from the research laboratory to industrial technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1008167</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Knowlton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William B Knowlton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bknowlton@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2084265705</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000443481</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Mullner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Mullner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>petermullner@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2084265136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Lindquist</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Lindquist</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paullindquist@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2084265660</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000549271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boise State University</Name>
<CityName>Boise</CityName>
<ZipCode>837250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2084261574</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1910 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072995848</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOISE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072995848</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boise State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boise</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>837250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1910 University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Magnetic shape memory alloys provide new avenues for building machines. Since we are describing a technology you do not see in today&rsquo;s products, it may help to use familiar science fiction to explain what it is and how it works. In the movie <em>Terminator 2</em> (1991), Arnold Schwarzenegger starred as the hero, the T-800 robot sent back from the future to save the world. Although sophisticated by our standards, Schwarzenegger&rsquo;s robot was built out of numerous interlinking electro-mechanical parts. His nemesis, however, was a more advanced T?1000 robot, fabricated from a single material. Its &ldquo;liquid metal&rdquo; structure allowed it to fluidly morph into new shapes, recover, and control the operation: in this innovative engineering paradigm, the material is the machine.</p> <p>Magnetic shape memory alloys (MSMAs) are similar in concept to the &ldquo;liquid metal&rdquo; robot. Although not humanoid, MSMA does shape-shift, here in response to magnetic fields. Apply a magnetic field, and the material changes shape. Remove it, and the new shape remains. Apply a different magnetic field and the material re-forms into a new shape. Do this quickly and with purpose and you have a motor or pump.</p> <p>In this project, we studied the internal mechanisms enabling magnetic-field-induced deformation on length scales from the atom to the sample, i.e. over seven orders of magnitude. We measured the mechanical properties of Ni-Mn-Ga MSMA single crystals. We further employed advanced transmission electron microscopy techniques to analyze the arrangement and dynamic response of crystallographic defects. Using these results, we developed a microstructure model with mesoscopic crystal defects characterizing a hierarchical twin microstructure. Our international project partners at Ruhr University Bochum, Germany, developed a &ldquo;discrete disclination dynamics model&rdquo; based on our microstructure model. Our project partners then studied the effect of stochastic variations in the hierarchical twin microstructure on mechanical properties. Consistent with our experimental findings the model predicted that deviations from a regular to a stochastic twin microstructure harden the material.</p> <p>One of the advantages of MSMA based actuators is the gigantic stroke of 10%. Development of such actuators is hindered due to failure during cyclic actuation. MSMA with densely twinned microstructures achieve a long lifetime, however, with significant reduction of stroke. The quantitative understanding gained with this study will allow developing MSMA actuators with large stroke and long lifetime. This project produced computational tools required for leading MSMA from the research laboratory to industrial technologies. Graduate and undergraduate students were trained in cutting edge characterization methods relevant for the nanotechnology and microelectronic industries. The US student, who performed the experimental studies at Boise State University, visited the international partner at Ruhr University Bochum, Germany three times. This program prepared students to successfully contribute to and compete in the demanding and challenging global technology market. One graduate student is now working as a post-doctoral researcher at a national laboratory.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2014<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Mullner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Magnetic shape memory alloys provide new avenues for building machines. Since we are describing a technology you do not see in todayÆs products, it may help to use familiar science fiction to explain what it is and how it works. In the movie Terminator 2 (1991), Arnold Schwarzenegger starred as the hero, the T-800 robot sent back from the future to save the world. Although sophisticated by our standards, SchwarzeneggerÆs robot was built out of numerous interlinking electro-mechanical parts. His nemesis, however, was a more advanced T?1000 robot, fabricated from a single material. Its "liquid metal" structure allowed it to fluidly morph into new shapes, recover, and control the operation: in this innovative engineering paradigm, the material is the machine.  Magnetic shape memory alloys (MSMAs) are similar in concept to the "liquid metal" robot. Although not humanoid, MSMA does shape-shift, here in response to magnetic fields. Apply a magnetic field, and the material changes shape. Remove it, and the new shape remains. Apply a different magnetic field and the material re-forms into a new shape. Do this quickly and with purpose and you have a motor or pump.  In this project, we studied the internal mechanisms enabling magnetic-field-induced deformation on length scales from the atom to the sample, i.e. over seven orders of magnitude. We measured the mechanical properties of Ni-Mn-Ga MSMA single crystals. We further employed advanced transmission electron microscopy techniques to analyze the arrangement and dynamic response of crystallographic defects. Using these results, we developed a microstructure model with mesoscopic crystal defects characterizing a hierarchical twin microstructure. Our international project partners at Ruhr University Bochum, Germany, developed a "discrete disclination dynamics model" based on our microstructure model. Our project partners then studied the effect of stochastic variations in the hierarchical twin microstructure on mechanical properties. Consistent with our experimental findings the model predicted that deviations from a regular to a stochastic twin microstructure harden the material.  One of the advantages of MSMA based actuators is the gigantic stroke of 10%. Development of such actuators is hindered due to failure during cyclic actuation. MSMA with densely twinned microstructures achieve a long lifetime, however, with significant reduction of stroke. The quantitative understanding gained with this study will allow developing MSMA actuators with large stroke and long lifetime. This project produced computational tools required for leading MSMA from the research laboratory to industrial technologies. Graduate and undergraduate students were trained in cutting edge characterization methods relevant for the nanotechnology and microelectronic industries. The US student, who performed the experimental studies at Boise State University, visited the international partner at Ruhr University Bochum, Germany three times. This program prepared students to successfully contribute to and compete in the demanding and challenging global technology market. One graduate student is now working as a post-doctoral researcher at a national laboratory.          Last Modified: 10/28/2014       Submitted by: Peter Mullner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
