<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cosmic rays in the galactic environment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>394692.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>394692</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a theoretical and computational effort to understand quantitatively the effects of cosmic rays on the interstellar gas in galaxies. The Principal Investigator and a postdoctoral researcher supported and mentored under this award, along with collaborators, will develop and implement a cosmic-ray physics module for the widely used magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) code FLASH. This module will permit the simulation of anisotropic thermal conduction and viscosity, and a broad array of cosmic ray energy loss, acceleration, and transfer processes; the new module will be tested against the predictions of linear theory. The team will then use the enhanced FLASH code to (1) simulate the formation of, and internal physical conditions in, molecular clouds, using a two-fluid approximation; (2) simulate the effects of cosmic rays on important MHD instabilities known or suspected to be important in galactic disks; (3) model the correlation between radio and far-infrared emission observed in starburst galaxies; (4) model the radio synchrotron emission from galaxy halos; (5) model the diffuse gamma-ray emission from galactic winds; and (6) model the stripping of galactic gas through interactions with the surrounding intergalactic medium. The Principal Investigator will also participate in an extensive list of outreach activities, including creation of a museum exhibit, public lectures, design of planetarium shows, telescope tours, popular writings, and coordination between his academic department and schools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1008454</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mateusz</FirstName>
<LastName>Ruszkowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mateusz Ruszkowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mateuszr@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7342554249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000493631</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~128011</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~131540</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~135141</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">We studied the interactions between galaxies and their surroundings across a range of cosmic scales &mdash; from the scales of individual galaxies to those of galaxy clusters. As part of this project, we investigated the impact of star formation and cosmic rays injected by supernovae on launching galaxy-scale winds and the impact of supermassive black hole jet outflows both in the context of our Galaxy and brightest cluster galaxies. Some of the most important results of these investigations include predictions and theoretical interpretations of the famous Fermi bubbles observed in our Galaxy, elucidating the role of cosmic rays and their interactions with galactic magnetic fields in launching galactic winds, and unraveling the role of precipitation of cold gas in extended atmospheres of galaxies in feeding of and feedback from black holes. A significant portion of the project utilized a cosmic ray physics modules that our team developed as part of an adaptive mesh refinement magnetohydrodynamical code.</span></p> <p class="p2"><span class="s1">&nbsp;</span>This project enabled training of three postdoctoral researchers, three graduate students, and four undergraduate students. Project outcomes were disseminated via peer-reviewed publications and talks. The PI initiated a theory and computation workshop series. These workshops serve as a venue for fostering collaborations among participants who share closely related interests: magnetic fields, physics of the interstellar/intracluster medium, and the interaction of galaxies with their environments.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2015<br>      Modified by: Mateusz&nbsp;Ruszkowski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[We studied the interactions between galaxies and their surroundings across a range of cosmic scales &mdash; from the scales of individual galaxies to those of galaxy clusters. As part of this project, we investigated the impact of star formation and cosmic rays injected by supernovae on launching galaxy-scale winds and the impact of supermassive black hole jet outflows both in the context of our Galaxy and brightest cluster galaxies. Some of the most important results of these investigations include predictions and theoretical interpretations of the famous Fermi bubbles observed in our Galaxy, elucidating the role of cosmic rays and their interactions with galactic magnetic fields in launching galactic winds, and unraveling the role of precipitation of cold gas in extended atmospheres of galaxies in feeding of and feedback from black holes. A significant portion of the project utilized a cosmic ray physics modules that our team developed as part of an adaptive mesh refinement magnetohydrodynamical code.  This project enabled training of three postdoctoral researchers, three graduate students, and four undergraduate students. Project outcomes were disseminated via peer-reviewed publications and talks. The PI initiated a theory and computation workshop series. These workshops serve as a venue for fostering collaborations among participants who share closely related interests: magnetic fields, physics of the interstellar/intracluster medium, and the interaction of galaxies with their environments.          Last Modified: 12/04/2015       Submitted by: Mateusz Ruszkowski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
