<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Palomar Transient Factory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1044634.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1044634</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nigel Sharp</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nsharp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Transient and explosive phenomena in the heavens have been a cause of astonishment and a source of enlightenment, from Cepheid variables and pulsars to supernovae, explosive X-ray sources and gamma-ray bursts.  Thus, Cepheid variables showed that the Universe was much larger than had been imagined, supernovae revealed the buildup of elements in the Universe, pulsars touch on the physics of strong gravity and the densest matter, and gamma-ray bursts serve as beacons to the young Universe.  Technological innovations now make it practical and timely to search the optical heavens for transients, and this project, the Palomar Transient Factory (PTF), is optimized for a systematic and very high throughput survey for transients and variables to the 21st magnitude level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PTF program will yield guaranteed science in certain known areas, such as ultra-high energy cosmic rays, energetic neutrinos, tera-electron-volt photons, and gravitational wave sources.  The localization of these sources is currently very poor, but PTF will be able to respond because of its large field of view, as well as measuring the rates of background and foreground events.  PTF will also explore the unexpected or ill-defined transient sky, including hypothesized objects brighter than novae but fainter than supernovae.  Such systematic charting of the sky every few days will reveal around seven hundred thermonuclear supernovae and several hundred core-collapse supernovae, whose follow-on will require more than just this project's resources, considerable as they are.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The impact of cosmic transient objects is indicated by the excitement caused by reports of items like the farthest gamma-ray burst, the most brilliant supernova, and the fastest pulsar.  This project will continue to offer early career (student and postdoctoral) researchers hands-on experience with cutting edge research.  The planned public archive with built-in easy access will not only benefit the scientific community but also expose the public to science in action, and contribute to the education of college and talented high school students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1009987</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shrinivas</FirstName>
<LastName>Kulkarni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shrinivas R Kulkarni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>srk@astro.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263954010</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~306892</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~364799</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~372943</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The night sky is by and large very peaceful and placid. However, were it not for dramatic events, namely cosmic explosions, our Universe would have been quite boring. There would be no elements beyond that left behind by the aftermath of the Big Bang: Hydrogen and Helium. It is through explosive stellar deaths ("supernovae") that the periodic table is slowly filled up.&nbsp; As Car Sagan noted "The nitrogen in our DNA, the calcium in our teeth, the iron in our blood, the carbon in our apple pies were made in the interiors of collapsing stars.&nbsp; We are made of starstuff." <br /><br />The NSF grant 1009987 entitled "The Palomar Transient Factory" was a project to undertake a systematic exploration of the night sky at optical or visible wavelength. At the Palomar Observatory, borrowing ideas from manufacturing industires, we designed and implemented a highly automated supernova search program. In the process, students and postdoctoral fellows built up experience with automation, used ideas from computer science (particularly Machine Learning) to transfer tedious activities, normally undertaken by humans, to computers.&nbsp; <br /><br />We discovered and classified over a thousand supernovae. In the process we expanded the repertoire (classes, subclasses) of supernovae.&nbsp; Some supernovae, surprsingly, are specializes -- they primarily make Calcium!&nbsp; Supernovae of type Ia are partiucularly important for all of us (they make the iron in your car) and for astronomersa (they are used to determine the geometry of the Universe). Yet their origin remained unkown and even controversial. During the course of our project we were able to show that Nature makes these supernovae in multiple ways. Other highlights include potentially finding a new class of cosmological explosions (so called "dirty fireballs") and unexplained transients in nuclear giant black holes.<br /><br />While astronomical research is a primary goal of the project no less is the training of young people. Some of them, upon graduation, takinga advantage of their technical training, have gone into high tech industries while others have continue in academia, making steady progress to faculty or research jobs.</p> <p>An NPR interview nicely summarizes the spirit of this project: http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2014/12/04/367874189/to-search-for-a-new-supernova-build-a-new-camera (or search for "NPR Kulkarni")</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Shrinivas&nbsp;R&nbsp;Kulkarni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The night sky is by and large very peaceful and placid. However, were it not for dramatic events, namely cosmic explosions, our Universe would have been quite boring. There would be no elements beyond that left behind by the aftermath of the Big Bang: Hydrogen and Helium. It is through explosive stellar deaths ("supernovae") that the periodic table is slowly filled up.  As Car Sagan noted "The nitrogen in our DNA, the calcium in our teeth, the iron in our blood, the carbon in our apple pies were made in the interiors of collapsing stars.  We are made of starstuff."   The NSF grant 1009987 entitled "The Palomar Transient Factory" was a project to undertake a systematic exploration of the night sky at optical or visible wavelength. At the Palomar Observatory, borrowing ideas from manufacturing industires, we designed and implemented a highly automated supernova search program. In the process, students and postdoctoral fellows built up experience with automation, used ideas from computer science (particularly Machine Learning) to transfer tedious activities, normally undertaken by humans, to computers.    We discovered and classified over a thousand supernovae. In the process we expanded the repertoire (classes, subclasses) of supernovae.  Some supernovae, surprsingly, are specializes -- they primarily make Calcium!  Supernovae of type Ia are partiucularly important for all of us (they make the iron in your car) and for astronomersa (they are used to determine the geometry of the Universe). Yet their origin remained unkown and even controversial. During the course of our project we were able to show that Nature makes these supernovae in multiple ways. Other highlights include potentially finding a new class of cosmological explosions (so called "dirty fireballs") and unexplained transients in nuclear giant black holes.  While astronomical research is a primary goal of the project no less is the training of young people. Some of them, upon graduation, takinga advantage of their technical training, have gone into high tech industries while others have continue in academia, making steady progress to faculty or research jobs.  An NPR interview nicely summarizes the spirit of this project: http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2014/12/04/367874189/to-search-for-a-new-supernova-build-a-new-camera (or search for "NPR Kulkarni")       Last Modified: 12/30/2015       Submitted by: Shrinivas R Kulkarni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
