<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>From Clusters to Voids: Gas and Galaxy Evolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>418947.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>418947</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia Knezek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project consists of three complementary observational efforts, intended to test the conceptual picture that galaxies may gain mass from their surroundings not by accretion of hot plasma that cools as it settles into the galaxy, but rather by accretion of gas that has already cooled in the intergalactic environment and remains cold as it flows into the galaxy, possibly on orderly streams with preferred directions. This idea has gained theoretical support in recent years through hydrodynamical simulations of galaxy formation; observational tests to be performed by the PI consist of radio observations, primarily in the 21 cm neutral hydrogen line, of (1) the outer parts of the nearby Virgo cluster of galaxies, (2) large volumes surrounding  two distinctly different clusters at redshift z=0.2, and (3) galaxies located in extremely under-dense void regions. This work will exploit the newly enhanced capabilities of the Westerbork Synthesis Radio Telescope (WSRT) in the Netherlands and the Expanded Very Large Array (EVLA) in the US. The new data will be combined with archived data to compare the morphologies, star forming properties, environments, and (where appropriate) locations within the clusters of galaxies with, and without, spatially extended cold gas. The observations will be compared against predictions made by high-resolution hydrodynamical simulations performed by a collaborator on the project; and the Virgo observations, in particular, will be made available to the research community through a website. The work will involve the participation of undergraduate and graduate students from under-represented groups, and will be highlighted in public presentations in schools and other venues.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1009476</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
<LastName>van Gorkom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacqueline H van Gorkom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jvangork@astro.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546850</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2960 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7480</Code>
<Text>ARCHIVAL DATA ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~158596</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~260351</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>From Clusters to Voids: Gas and Galaxy Evolution</strong><br /><br />One of the main questions in galaxy evolution today is: how<br />do galaxies get and lose their gas. In the last decade a renaissance has taken place in numerical simulations with a much more sophisticated approach to the physics of the gas than was previously possible. The prediction of the simulations is that the dominant growth mode of galaxies is through accretion&nbsp; of gas.&nbsp; The accretion rate depends on redshift, it is much more important at early times in the universe, on galaxy mass and on environment.&nbsp; In the local universe this process is predicted to still take place in the lowest density environments and in the smallest galaxies. Observations indicate that the star formation rate has declined dramatically since z=1 and a major question is why.<br />In this project we addressed these issues by imaging the gas in<br />galaxies in a wide range of environments and comparing the results to<br />high quality hydrodynamical simulations.<br /><br /><strong>The Void Galaxy Survey. </strong>Voids represents a unique environment for the study of galaxy evolution. The lower density should result in slower evolution of&nbsp; galaxies. As accretion of cold gas is thought to still occur in the present in the smallest galaxies and lowest densities, voids may be the ideal place<br />to look for this. We did an imaging survey in neutral hydrogen of the deepest <br />underdensities of 60 voids selected from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey. <br />Interestingly there are indeed no massive galaxies in the void. Most are <br />are small, star forming disk galaxies. The most interesting result is that <br />the neutral gas is generally very extended and many galaxies show signs that the gas has been disturbed recently, which could be evidence for infall.<br />We published two papers on the optical and gaseous properties of the<br />void galaxies in addition to several papers on detailed studies of selected <br />systems. A comparison with a high resolution hydrodynamic simulation of<br />the evolution of a void shows in general good agreement, except that the <br />simulations overpredict the amount of gas present. <br /><br /><strong>Clusters of Galaxies</strong>. At the other extreme we studied the evolution of<br />galaxies in the highest density environments, the centers of<br />clusters. As follow up of our neutral hydrogen imaging survey of<br />galaxies in the Virgo cluster, we carried out detailed multiwavelength<br />studies of individual systems and combined these with modelling to<br />constrain the orbital histories of the galaxies.&nbsp; Galaxies begin to<br />lose their gas in the outskirts of clusters and they get almost<br />completely stripped by ram pressure stripping by the hot gas as they<br />traverse the cluster.&nbsp; They are likely to evolve into non star forming<br />S0 galaxies. In a study of two clusters at a redshift of z=0.2 we obtained spectra on thousands of galaxies and used those to define<br />the substructure of the clusters.&nbsp; We then related neutral hydrogen<br />content and star formation activity to local galaxy density. We find<br />that galaxies are beginning to lose their gas in groups before they<br />fall into the clusters.</p> <p><br /><strong>A pilot for an HI deep field</strong></p> <p>Lastly we performed a pilot for a neutral hydrogen deep field with the<br />upgraded Very Large Array (VLA). Soon it will be possible to observe in one<br />setting all the hydrogen out to a redshift of z=0.5. We pioneered such an<br />observation while the VLA was being commissioned, observing all the<br />hydrogen out to z=0.2. This pilot was extremely successful, we<br />detected neutral hydrogen over the entire redshift range and found<br />different morphologies in different environments. We also learned how<br ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[         From Clusters to Voids: Gas and Galaxy Evolution  One of the main questions in galaxy evolution today is: how do galaxies get and lose their gas. In the last decade a renaissance has taken place in numerical simulations with a much more sophisticated approach to the physics of the gas than was previously possible. The prediction of the simulations is that the dominant growth mode of galaxies is through accretion  of gas.  The accretion rate depends on redshift, it is much more important at early times in the universe, on galaxy mass and on environment.  In the local universe this process is predicted to still take place in the lowest density environments and in the smallest galaxies. Observations indicate that the star formation rate has declined dramatically since z=1 and a major question is why. In this project we addressed these issues by imaging the gas in galaxies in a wide range of environments and comparing the results to high quality hydrodynamical simulations.  The Void Galaxy Survey. Voids represents a unique environment for the study of galaxy evolution. The lower density should result in slower evolution of  galaxies. As accretion of cold gas is thought to still occur in the present in the smallest galaxies and lowest densities, voids may be the ideal place to look for this. We did an imaging survey in neutral hydrogen of the deepest  underdensities of 60 voids selected from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey.  Interestingly there are indeed no massive galaxies in the void. Most are  are small, star forming disk galaxies. The most interesting result is that  the neutral gas is generally very extended and many galaxies show signs that the gas has been disturbed recently, which could be evidence for infall. We published two papers on the optical and gaseous properties of the void galaxies in addition to several papers on detailed studies of selected  systems. A comparison with a high resolution hydrodynamic simulation of the evolution of a void shows in general good agreement, except that the  simulations overpredict the amount of gas present.   Clusters of Galaxies. At the other extreme we studied the evolution of galaxies in the highest density environments, the centers of clusters. As follow up of our neutral hydrogen imaging survey of galaxies in the Virgo cluster, we carried out detailed multiwavelength studies of individual systems and combined these with modelling to constrain the orbital histories of the galaxies.  Galaxies begin to lose their gas in the outskirts of clusters and they get almost completely stripped by ram pressure stripping by the hot gas as they traverse the cluster.  They are likely to evolve into non star forming S0 galaxies. In a study of two clusters at a redshift of z=0.2 we obtained spectra on thousands of galaxies and used those to define the substructure of the clusters.  We then related neutral hydrogen content and star formation activity to local galaxy density. We find that galaxies are beginning to lose their gas in groups before they fall into the clusters.   A pilot for an HI deep field  Lastly we performed a pilot for a neutral hydrogen deep field with the upgraded Very Large Array (VLA). Soon it will be possible to observe in one setting all the hydrogen out to a redshift of z=0.5. We pioneered such an observation while the VLA was being commissioned, observing all the hydrogen out to z=0.2. This pilot was extremely successful, we detected neutral hydrogen over the entire redshift range and found different morphologies in different environments. We also learned how to deal with man made radio frequency interference caused by satellites, which will be a major issue for future surveys.  The void galaxy survey formed the bulk of the thesis of one graduate student. The pilot survey is part of the thesis of another graduate student. Two students from the Bridge to the PhD program at Columbia, which is meant to prepare minority students for graduate school in the sciences, did t...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
