<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Computational Geometric Mechanics: Foundations, Computation, and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/29/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425099.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>425099</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Date:  November 21, 2007&lt;br/&gt;Proposal:  DMS- 0747659&lt;br/&gt;PI:  Leok, Melvin &lt;br/&gt;Institution: Purdue University&lt;br/&gt;Title: CAREER: Computational Geometric Mechanics: Foundations, Computation, and Applications&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Symmetry, and the study of invariant and equivariant objects, is a deep and unifying principle underlying a variety of mathematical fields. In particular, geometric mechanics is characterized by the application of symmetry and differential geometric techniques to Lagrangian and Hamiltonian mechanics, and geometric integration is concerned with the construction of numerical methods with geometric invariant and equivariant properties. Computational geometric mechanics blends these fields, and uses a self-consistent discretization of geometry and mechanics to systematically construct geometric structure-preserving numerical schemes. The proposed research will combine theoretical and computational tools arising from Dirac mechanics and geometry, noncommutative harmonic analysis, and uncertainty quantification to dramatically extend the applicability of computational geometric mechanics and geometric control to engineering problems that evolve intrinsically on nonlinear spaces, such as Lie groups and homogeneous spaces. This will provide insights into the canonical discretization of Dirac constraints, nonholonomic constraints, and interconnected systems. In addition, the study of uncertainty in the context of geometric control will improve the robustness and reliability of the resulting numerical and computational tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will improve our ability to control interconnected systems of autonomous vehicles in a robust and efficient fashion, by explicitly taking into account the uncertainty inherent in our knowledge of the surrounding environment. Our results will be applicable to the control of distributed sensor networks, consisting of an interconnected set of satellites, unmanned aerial vehicles and underwater vehicles. Such sensor networks are an exciting new development in the field of remote sensing that has the potential to dramatically increase the efficiency, coverage, and reliability of the information we obtain about our oceans, environment, and climate.  &lt;br/&gt;More broadly, most complex engineering systems can be expressed as an interconnected system of more elementary components, and our mathematical framework will allow us to more readily understand complex systems in terms of the behavior of its component parts and the manner in which they are interconnected.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1010687</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melvin</FirstName>
<LastName>Leok</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melvin Leok</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mleok@math.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585342126</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488328</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930112</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~127738</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~44599</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~74693</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~87294</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~90775</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported the development of innovative and novel numerical methods for modeling a broad range of mechanical systems arising in contemporary engineering applications, including robots, underwater vehicles, and spacecraft. In particular, we have developed systematic methods for constructing structure-preserving numerical methods that can be used to model complex systems comprising of hierarchical multiphysics models that involve the interconnection of simpler subsystems.</p> <p>These methods provide a rigorous mathematical foundation for developing efficient control strategies for such mechanical systems, and they are particularly effective for problems where the controls are applied over a very long time horizon, which pose a particular challenge when approached using more conventional techniques. Additionally, the methods developed for the control of interconnected systems can be applied to the distributed control of collections of autonomous vehicles, which is of particular relevance to the efficient control and deployment of distributed sensor networks.</p> <p>During the course of this project, the PI mentored four postdoctoral scholars, who are now employed in industry and academia. Additionally, two graduate students successfully defended their Ph.D.s, who are now employed in industry. Of the six junior researchers involved in this project, three of them are female. The first volume of a two volume research monograph, aimed at broadly disseminating the results of the research project to a broad audience of scientists and engineers has been completed, and is currently undergoing review.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Melvin&nbsp;Leok</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported the development of innovative and novel numerical methods for modeling a broad range of mechanical systems arising in contemporary engineering applications, including robots, underwater vehicles, and spacecraft. In particular, we have developed systematic methods for constructing structure-preserving numerical methods that can be used to model complex systems comprising of hierarchical multiphysics models that involve the interconnection of simpler subsystems.  These methods provide a rigorous mathematical foundation for developing efficient control strategies for such mechanical systems, and they are particularly effective for problems where the controls are applied over a very long time horizon, which pose a particular challenge when approached using more conventional techniques. Additionally, the methods developed for the control of interconnected systems can be applied to the distributed control of collections of autonomous vehicles, which is of particular relevance to the efficient control and deployment of distributed sensor networks.  During the course of this project, the PI mentored four postdoctoral scholars, who are now employed in industry and academia. Additionally, two graduate students successfully defended their Ph.D.s, who are now employed in industry. Of the six junior researchers involved in this project, three of them are female. The first volume of a two volume research monograph, aimed at broadly disseminating the results of the research project to a broad audience of scientists and engineers has been completed, and is currently undergoing review.       Last Modified: 09/28/2015       Submitted by: Melvin Leok]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
