<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CNH: Collaborative Research: Explaining Socioecological Resilience Following Collapse: Forest Recovery in Appalachian Ohio</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1246612.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1246612</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Much is known about the processes leading to forest loss, that understanding must be complemented with new knowledge regarding the socioecological factors that influence forest recovery and sustainability.  This knowledge is critical for predicting where and when second- and third-generation forests might emerge and for understanding the conditions necessary to maintain them.  Furthermore, such knowledge is urgently required to inform global climate models, climate change mitigation scenarios, and a suite of other environmental issues.  This interdisciplinary research project will focus on the human and ecological linkages that give rise to specific forest forms (including forest extent, species composition, and land-cover patterns) and functions (including benefits of the forest like timber, recreation, privacy, and wildlife habitat).  The investigators will examine the extent to which those linkages and the forests emergent from them lead to irreversible changes in socioecological systems.  They will focus their attention on Appalachian Ohio, an area whose which forests have returned and where there is sufficient time depth to examine the underlying socioecological processes that give rise to them.  A former extractive periphery devastated in the 19th and early 20th centuries, its extensive forests have emerged in surprising ways over the last century.  Project goals are (1) to compare forest composition between pre-settlement forests and contemporary forests; (2) to describe the social and ecological form and function of recovered forests; (3) to explain the emergence of the forest over time; and (4) to predict how these socioecological systems will function in the future.  The methods to be used include an agent-based model representing land-use decision-making and implementation coupled with the landscape disturbance and succession model, which simulates forest succession and regrowth.  To inform the models with empirical data, the researchers will collect field data on forest structure and composition, generate time-series classifications of remotely sensed images, and investigate political, economic, infrastructural, and cultural dynamics using archival and field-derived data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will make important contributions to theory and methods for understanding dynamically coupled socioecological systems.  The project will advance basic understanding of forest transitions by focusing on forest resilience, thus treating forest recovery as an emergent property of complex socioecological systems.  The project will focus attention on differences in ecosystem attributes before and long after massive disturbance, showing that humans and ecosystems have together created unexpected ecologies.  The project will demonstrate specific ways that forest form and function respond to local forces and distant shocks that are both social and ecological.  Methodologically, the project will advance agent-based modeling science by using innovative metrics to incorporate social inequality and power dynamics and by coupling social simulation with landscape-level forest growth models.  As a collaborative project between two Ohio-based universities and the U.S. Forest Service, the project will provide practical information regarding pressing social and environmental issues in Appalachian Ohio, including rural poverty, ecological change, and management of public and private forests.  Global applications of this portable framework include enhancing the ways that scholars and policy makers understand, plan for, and help to foster ecological recovery, in particular by drawing attention to the role of social inequalities in shaping socioecological resilience.  The findings of this research can also inform climate modeling and mitigation.  This project is supported by the NSF Dynamics of Coupled Natural and Human Systems (CNH) Program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1010314</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darla</FirstName>
<LastName>Munroe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darla K Munroe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>munroe.9@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142478382</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000415088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kendra</FirstName>
<LastName>McSweeney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kendra McSweeney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcsweeney.14@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142476400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000171013</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Becky</FirstName>
<LastName>Mansfield</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Becky K Mansfield</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mansfield.32@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142477264</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000217222</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Desheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Desheng Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>liu.738@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142472775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000500302</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>BE: DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9186</Code>
<Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9278</Code>
<Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1246612</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual merit</span>. Much research exists that focuses on the causes and effects of deforestation.&nbsp; We focused instead on a region that for the past 100 years has experienced widespread forest recovery, and therefore raises different questions about how and why forests change. What is required to maintain and enhance recovered forests and the resources they provide? Our study site is southeastern Ohio, in the Appalachian foothills, where despite high poverty and ongoing resource exploitation (for oil, gas, coal, and timber), a long period of forest recovery has been followed by several decades of stable (but not increasing) forest cover.</p> <p>Our research demonstrated the many ways in which the forest depends upon society, and society depends upon the forest. Forest resources are used for timber; as a place to grow products like ginseng; for recreation and privacy; as a scenic view that adds to housing value; and a place for regional tourists and residents to hike, hunt, or enjoy wildlife. We found that while local people do not identify themselves as &ldquo;environmentalists&rdquo; they have nevertheless been good for sustaining forests&mdash;especially landowners who own relatively small areas of forest. These people manage forests in multiple ways by actively planting trees, removing invasive species or removing land from agricultural production. This forest management may or may not happen &lsquo;formally&rsquo;&mdash;i.e., scripted by a forest management plan overseen by the County Auditor or a service forester working for the Department of Natural Resources.</p> <p>We found that seemingly incompatible land uses were not always so incompatible. Tourism, second-home development, mine reclamation and low-income housing were often found in close proximity. Therefore, long-term management of places like Appalachian Ohio requires careful attention to the many ways communities and forests support each other&rsquo;s function, and that would-be managers are open to the surprising synergies among forests and residents.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also developed new methods for analyzing these systems, including geospatial and statistical techniques for analyzing a long time-series of satellite data, which account for environmental history. For example, agricultural fields can become forests over 30 years, but open pit mines cannot. We combined different sources of information about forests (including original surveys conducted 200 years ago, historical topographical maps, aerial photographs from the 1940s, and satellite-derived forest species maps) in statistical models to better understand forest changes over time. We also generated new spatially explicit datasets of forest tourism (e.g., mapping hot-tub cabin locations) and of landownership over four decades. The landowner dataset tracks parcel subdivisions and transfer of ownership among private residences, industry, government and utilities (mining, natural gas, etc.). Combined, these new methods and datasets help better understand how dynamic this region is.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader impacts.</span> The project&rsquo;s broader impacts are numerous. We initiated a working relationship between Ohio State, Ohio University and US Forest Service researchers, which resulted in ongoing collaboration around how Ohio&rsquo;s forests have changed since European settlement, and the insights from this collaboration have been shared in a variety of venues with very different audiences. In addition to scientific publications and presentations, senior Personnel and graduate students have given ~25 public presentations about the research in Ohio and in national and international settings. At OSU, Dr. Munroe conducted a campus-wide training workshop (attended by 20 researchers) to share her intellectual and technical knowledge in developing an &lsquo;agent-b...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit. Much research exists that focuses on the causes and effects of deforestation.  We focused instead on a region that for the past 100 years has experienced widespread forest recovery, and therefore raises different questions about how and why forests change. What is required to maintain and enhance recovered forests and the resources they provide? Our study site is southeastern Ohio, in the Appalachian foothills, where despite high poverty and ongoing resource exploitation (for oil, gas, coal, and timber), a long period of forest recovery has been followed by several decades of stable (but not increasing) forest cover.  Our research demonstrated the many ways in which the forest depends upon society, and society depends upon the forest. Forest resources are used for timber; as a place to grow products like ginseng; for recreation and privacy; as a scenic view that adds to housing value; and a place for regional tourists and residents to hike, hunt, or enjoy wildlife. We found that while local people do not identify themselves as "environmentalists" they have nevertheless been good for sustaining forests&mdash;especially landowners who own relatively small areas of forest. These people manage forests in multiple ways by actively planting trees, removing invasive species or removing land from agricultural production. This forest management may or may not happen æformallyÆ&mdash;i.e., scripted by a forest management plan overseen by the County Auditor or a service forester working for the Department of Natural Resources.  We found that seemingly incompatible land uses were not always so incompatible. Tourism, second-home development, mine reclamation and low-income housing were often found in close proximity. Therefore, long-term management of places like Appalachian Ohio requires careful attention to the many ways communities and forests support each otherÆs function, and that would-be managers are open to the surprising synergies among forests and residents.   We also developed new methods for analyzing these systems, including geospatial and statistical techniques for analyzing a long time-series of satellite data, which account for environmental history. For example, agricultural fields can become forests over 30 years, but open pit mines cannot. We combined different sources of information about forests (including original surveys conducted 200 years ago, historical topographical maps, aerial photographs from the 1940s, and satellite-derived forest species maps) in statistical models to better understand forest changes over time. We also generated new spatially explicit datasets of forest tourism (e.g., mapping hot-tub cabin locations) and of landownership over four decades. The landowner dataset tracks parcel subdivisions and transfer of ownership among private residences, industry, government and utilities (mining, natural gas, etc.). Combined, these new methods and datasets help better understand how dynamic this region is.  Broader impacts. The projectÆs broader impacts are numerous. We initiated a working relationship between Ohio State, Ohio University and US Forest Service researchers, which resulted in ongoing collaboration around how OhioÆs forests have changed since European settlement, and the insights from this collaboration have been shared in a variety of venues with very different audiences. In addition to scientific publications and presentations, senior Personnel and graduate students have given ~25 public presentations about the research in Ohio and in national and international settings. At OSU, Dr. Munroe conducted a campus-wide training workshop (attended by 20 researchers) to share her intellectual and technical knowledge in developing an æagent-based model.Æ We talked with community foresters to better understand their practices and to share our perspectives on forest management. The post-doctoral researcher and research associate attended several forest management workshops for land...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
