<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>National Geographic FieldScope</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2705836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2705836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Neufeld</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will expand the functions and applications of  FieldScope, a web-based science information portal currently supported by the National Geographic Society (NGS).  The goal is to create a single, powerful infrastructure for Public Participation in Science Research (PPSR) projects that any organization can use to create their own  project and support their own community of participants. FieldScope currently provides various tools and applications for use by its existing user base that includes the GLOBE project and the Chesapeake Bay monitoring system. The application enables users to contribute volunteered geographic data collection efforts and sharing information among both professional and amateur users. The project would develop and test an enhanced version of the existing FieldScope application.  The project supports major programming development for a fully-functional web-based application that would significantly enhance the usability of the current application.  Along with programming new features and capabilities, the project involves extensive evaluation of the new capabilities and involves three citizen-based organizations as testbeds.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will increase the capability of the existing system to handle large numbers of users and user groups and also increase the number and variety of tools available to any user; provide customization through the adaption of common APIs; and provide for expansion of computer space through use of virtual servers in a cloud computing environment thereby limiting the need  for installed hardware.  This approach would maximize storage and computing power by being able to call on resources when necessary and scaling back when demand decreases.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The platform would include advanced visualization capabilities as part of a suite of analytic tools available to the user.  Social networking applications would also be incorporated as a way of enabling communication among users of a particular site. The operation of the portal would be supported by the NGS and made available free of charge to any group of users applying for space. Nominal fees will be applied to large organizations requiring large computing space or additional features.  User groups can request NGS supply custom features for the cost of development and deployment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The evaluation of this project is extensive and focused on formative evaluation as a means to identify user preferences, from look and feel of the site to types of tools desired and types of uses expected. The formative evaluation would be conducted ahead of any commitment to programming and formatting of the features of the site. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project responds to a need expressed throughout the citizen science community for web-based applications that enable individuals to engage in a topic of interest, interact in various ways on such a site including the submission of data and information, analyze the information in concert with others and with working scientists in the field, and utilize state-of-the-art tools such as visualization as a way of making sense of the data being collected.  There have been numerous proposals to create similar types of sites from various groups, each based on its own perceived needs and grounded in its own particular discipline or topic.  This activity could serve this community more broadly and save similar groups the trouble and expense of creating sites from scratch.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1010749</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Edelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel C Edelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dedelson@ngs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028286680</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/30/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwille</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathleen Schwille</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kschwill@ngs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028625249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200364701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028073186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1145 17TH ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003247756</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003247756</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200364701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1145 17TH ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1578169</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~616049</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~375078</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~136540</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Normal1" style="text-align: center;"><strong>National Geographic FieldScope</strong></p> <p class="Normal1" style="text-align: center;"><strong>Project Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p class="Normal1" style="text-align: center;"><strong>May 2016</strong></p> <p class="Normal1">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Normal1">Over the last several years, the National Geographic Society (NGS) has been developing and supporting FieldScope, a web-based citizen science portal. Through FieldScope&rsquo;s interactive mapping platform, citizen scientists have access to tools that enable them to document and understand the world around them. In 2010, NGS received an award from the National Science Foundation (NSF) to expand the functions and applications of FieldScope. The goal was to create a powerful infrastructure for citizen science research projects that any organization could use to create a project and support a community of participants. Along with programming new features and capabilities, the award also involved evaluation of the impact on three organizations that joined as testbed partners.</p> <p class="Normal1">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Normal1">FieldScope is implemented in a citizen science project through the creation of a custom map that includes the project&rsquo;s required data fields and relevant map layers. The FieldScope development conducted under this award was done in conjunction with the testbed partners to support the needs of these organizations and their participants. Staff at each of the testbed sites worked regularly with NGS staff to ensure that the FieldScope project websites fulfilled their needs. The three testbed partners that participated in the project were:</p> <p class="Normal1">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>FrogWatch USA</strong> (<a href="https://www.aza.org/frogwatch/">https://www.aza.org/frogwatch/</a>) is a citizen science program at the Association of Zoos and Aquariums (AZA), that, according to its website, &ldquo;provides individuals, groups, and families with an opportunity to learn about wetlands in their communities and report data on the calls of local frogs and toads.&rdquo; FrogWatch USA uses a model where volunteers are organized into chapters, most of which are run by a local AZA member organization. Chapter coordinators provide training on frog monitoring and use of FieldScope. Since the FrogWatch USA program moved to AZA approximately ten years ago, volunteers had recorded their data on paper forms. FieldScope has provided FrogWatch USA with more timely data, greater quality control, and a platform for accessing and analyzing 18 years worth of data. The FrogWatch FieldScope project can be found at <a href="http://frogwatch.fieldscope.org/">http://frogwatch.fieldscope.org/</a></li> </ul> <p class="Normal1">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Project BudBurst</strong> (<a href="http://budburst.org/">http://budburst.org/</a>), which is now housed at the National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON), was established in 2007 with the goal to &ldquo;get you outside taking a moment to observe how plants in your community change with the seasons.&rdquo; Their mission statement captures outcomes of their citizen science program: &ldquo;When you share your observations with us, they become part of an ecological record.&rdquo; Project BudBurst participants enter their data on the Project BudBurst site, and these data are then shared with FieldScope. Although some data visualizations are available on the Project BudBurst website, the organization wanted a robust mapping tool where data could be accessed and analyzed. The Project BudBurst FieldScope project can be found at <a href="http://budburst.fieldscope.org/">http://budburst.fieldscope.org/</a></li> </ul> <p class="Normal1">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Trash Free Potomac</strong> (<a href="http://fergusonfoundation.org/trash-free-potomac-watershed-initiative/">http://fergusonfoundation.org/trash-free-po...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[National Geographic FieldScope Project Outcomes Report May 2016   Over the last several years, the National Geographic Society (NGS) has been developing and supporting FieldScope, a web-based citizen science portal. Through FieldScopeÆs interactive mapping platform, citizen scientists have access to tools that enable them to document and understand the world around them. In 2010, NGS received an award from the National Science Foundation (NSF) to expand the functions and applications of FieldScope. The goal was to create a powerful infrastructure for citizen science research projects that any organization could use to create a project and support a community of participants. Along with programming new features and capabilities, the award also involved evaluation of the impact on three organizations that joined as testbed partners.   FieldScope is implemented in a citizen science project through the creation of a custom map that includes the projectÆs required data fields and relevant map layers. The FieldScope development conducted under this award was done in conjunction with the testbed partners to support the needs of these organizations and their participants. Staff at each of the testbed sites worked regularly with NGS staff to ensure that the FieldScope project websites fulfilled their needs. The three testbed partners that participated in the project were:    FrogWatch USA (https://www.aza.org/frogwatch/) is a citizen science program at the Association of Zoos and Aquariums (AZA), that, according to its website, "provides individuals, groups, and families with an opportunity to learn about wetlands in their communities and report data on the calls of local frogs and toads." FrogWatch USA uses a model where volunteers are organized into chapters, most of which are run by a local AZA member organization. Chapter coordinators provide training on frog monitoring and use of FieldScope. Since the FrogWatch USA program moved to AZA approximately ten years ago, volunteers had recorded their data on paper forms. FieldScope has provided FrogWatch USA with more timely data, greater quality control, and a platform for accessing and analyzing 18 years worth of data. The FrogWatch FieldScope project can be found at http://frogwatch.fieldscope.org/     Project BudBurst (http://budburst.org/), which is now housed at the National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON), was established in 2007 with the goal to "get you outside taking a moment to observe how plants in your community change with the seasons." Their mission statement captures outcomes of their citizen science program: "When you share your observations with us, they become part of an ecological record." Project BudBurst participants enter their data on the Project BudBurst site, and these data are then shared with FieldScope. Although some data visualizations are available on the Project BudBurst website, the organization wanted a robust mapping tool where data could be accessed and analyzed. The Project BudBurst FieldScope project can be found at http://budburst.fieldscope.org/     Trash Free Potomac (http://fergusonfoundation.org/trash-free-potomac-watershed-initiative/). In 2005, the Alice Ferguson Foundation (AFF) started the Trash Free Potomac (TFP) Watershed Initiative as a solution to the problem of trash in the Potomac watershed. The initiative was designed to provide a forum where leaders, businesses, organization, and citizens would come together to solve this problem. Per their website, the Initiative "includes annual Potomac River Watershed Cleanup and Potomac Watershed Trash Summit, as well as a strategic framework with five core components including public education, policy, regulation, enforcement, and market-based approaches." The individuals who lead cleanup events upload their data to an AFF website, and these data are then shared with FieldScope, where they are available to other users and the public. AFF adopted FieldScope because it allowed for easy data ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
