<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CNH: Acequia Water Systems Linking Culture and Nature: Integrated Analysis of Community Resilience to Climate and Land-Use Changes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1400892.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1400892</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In arable valleys of water-limited regions worldwide, community water management systems have evolved to sustain communities in the face of unreliable precipitation.  The acequias of the southwestern United States are community irrigation systems that are based largely on ancient technology introduced to the region by 16th-century settlers.  Acequias consist of gravity-fed earthen canals that divert stream flow for distribution to fields.  They lie at the center of a set of complex self-maintaining interactions between culture and nature that appear to enable drought survival and maintain other sociocultural and ecosystem benefits.  Local water management groups inherent in acequias ensure equitable distribution of water to each community, allocating less water for all users in dry years and more in wet years.  Acequias help maintain community identity and cohesion, economic sustainability, enhanced floodplain hydrologic function, and wildlife habitat.  Contemporary acequia-based communities face new socioeconomic and natural resource pressures that threaten their existence, however.  Population growth is accelerating the change from agricultural to residential land and water uses, while climate change threatens to bring warmer winters with less precipitation and earlier spring snowmelt.  Traditional acequias create and sustain intrinsic linkages between human and natural systems that increase community and ecosystem resilience to climatic and socioeconomic stresses.  Greater knowledge about these interconnections and what can cause them to change or fail will be essential to determine how the communities relying on acequias can adapt to changing conditions.  This interdisciplinary research project will explore socioeconomic and cultural linkages within and between acequia communities and associated landscapes; hydrologic linkages between surface water and groundwater in irrigated river valleys and contributing watersheds; and wildlife habitat and grazing distribution connections between valley riparian areas and upland forests and grasslands.  The investigators will quantify the role of acequias in hydrologic function, community resilience, and ecosystem health, and they will identify potential tipping points for acequia community survival.  Integrative tools informed by examinations of socioeconomic, cultural, and ecohydrological factors will indicate the resilience level of acequia-centered systems.  A system dynamics model will simulate effects of climate and land-use stressors on relationships between economic, social, cultural, climatic, hydrologic, vegetation, and wildlife components.  The model will quantify the magnitude of stressors needed to undermine community and ecosystem resilience.  Mapping will capture spatial linkages and help communicate the findings to a larger audience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide new insights into the relationships between traditional water management systems, communities, and landscapes.  It will broaden participation of minorities by conducting research in rural Hispanic communities.  Community members will be active participants in the project and help determine keys to their own community survival.  Project results will be made available to researchers, policy makers, local stakeholders, and the general public through scientific publications, presentations, extension documents, and workshops.  Teachers from the region will be involved in participatory training in order to reach K-12 students.  Undergraduate students will be directly involved in the research, as will graduate students who will be trained as future scientists and community leaders.  A major museum exhibit will integrate spirituality and sense of place into presentation of community resource governance.  Cross-pollination of ideas with international experts will take place through a global comparative workshop and a comparative study in Chile.  Policy guidance resulting from this study should help maintain acequia communities and similar common-pool resource systems worldwide.  This project is supported by the NSF Dynamics of Coupled Natural and Human Systems (CNH) Program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1010516</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John L Wilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.wilson@nmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5058355634</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000264178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Rivera</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose A Rivera</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrivera@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052773488</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480015</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Fernald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander G Fernald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fernald@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5756464337</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416276</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
<LastName>Tidwell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vincent Tidwell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vctidwe@sandia.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000552462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MSC OGC, Box 30002]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>173851965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW MEXICO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>861367373</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Mexico State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewa]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1325</Code>
<Text>WATER &amp; ENERGY: ATMO, VEG, EARTH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>BE: DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7979</Code>
<Text>CRI Unpooled</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9186</Code>
<Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9278</Code>
<Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1400892</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A dynamic group of project investigators, undergraduates, and graduate students conducted cutting edge science working closely with rural Hispanic community members in northern New Mexico to help maintain traditional irrigation acequia communities and assess their climate change vulnerabilities and adaptation opportunities. The project provided: policy guidance; new insights into the relationships between traditional water management systems, communities, and landscapes; improved understanding of hydrologic linkages between surface water and groundwater in irrigated river valleys and contributing watersheds as well as socioeconomic and cultural linkages within and between acequia communities; assessments of perceived climate and water-related risks; opportunities to build adaptive capacity; and new awareness of wildlife habitat and grazing distribution connections between valley riparian areas and upland forests and grasslands.</p> <p>Multidisciplinary research conclusions include: 1) traditional knowledge of local ecology and customary practices in Spanish and English are vital components of social capital for transmission to the next generation that is essential to continuity of acequia agriculture and culture; 2) acequia culture is based on reciprocal relationships between irrigation and community that create sense of place, attachment to land, and shared cultural identity based on membership in community groups; 3) mutual networks and social density result in water sharing cooperation when acequias are confronted with drought or other extra-community stressors; 4) customary practices combine hydrologic and sociocultural strategies to respond collectively to spring snow-melt and summer variable precipitation; and 5) autonomous decision making structures in acequia governance permit rapid adjustments in operational rules and practices of each acequia when warranted by changing wet or dry season environmental conditions.</p> <p>In one study of river water diverted into an earthen irrigation canal system, some was consumed by crop evapotranspiration (7.4%) while the rest returned to the river as surface return flow (59.3%) and shallow groundwater return flow that originated as seepage from canals (12.1%), and fields (21.2%). In another study, the recharge from irrigated agriculture using these traditional systems yielded up to 1350 mm/yr to the shallow local aquifer. Also, acequia flow was significantly correlated with river flow, showing that shortage and abundance are shared equally and that acequia flow is vulnerable to reduced river flow from climate change. The data show the benefits of acequias for hydrologic connectivity.</p> <p>Aside from being able to survive political-administrative changes, acequias aid in the health of aquifers, benefit livestock by providing water, and are key sources of community drinking water. Acequia hydrology plays an important role in contributing to an ecologically healthy, agriculturally productive, and community-sustaining floodplain agroecosystem.</p> <p>Integration of valley farming and rangeland grazing is critical to the resilience of north-central New Mexico acequia communities. New knowledge was gained regarding the nature of valley-upland linkages and their role in supporting contemporary acequia farming systems. The valley-upland linkage provides habitat for many wildlife species that use both upland mountain forests and valley riparian habitats. Livestock raising continues to be critical to the acequia agropastoral economy and the ability to grow hay during the winter largely regulates demand for summer grazing on public forested rangelands.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project succeeded in the development of a multidisciplinary model of acequia community function. This groundbreaking effort integrated social, economic, hydrologic and ecologic dynamics to study acequia system natural and social stressors. System Dynamics (SD) was adopted for the modeling platform as it is particularly designed for multidisciplinary systems that express organized complexity and evolve over time. Model development relied heavily on stakeholder input and interactions with multiple discipline subject matter experts. One challenge overcome was quantifying key social dynamics; sensitivity analyses were conducted to quantify their role in overall system behavior and to quantify related uncertainties. Moral economy, mutualism and sense of place were key social components of community resilience. Preliminary results indicate a strong hydrologic connectivity between snow-melt driven runoff in the headwaters and the recharge of the shallow aquifer in the valley, mainly driven by the use of traditionally irrigated agriculture systems. Ultimately the SD model provides a platform to engage stakeholders to explore alternative adaptive measures for acequia communities.</p> <p>A major museum exhibit attended by approximately 25,000 people, <em>El Agua es Vida: Acequias in New Mexico</em>, at the Maxwell Museum of Anthropology in Albuquerque, integrated spirituality and sense of place into presentation of community resource governance; connected art with research; conveyed the interconnected features of upstream and downstream rural and urban populations linked by acequias; combined modern and archival photographs, artwork, traditional and modern objects and artifacts, texts, and audiovisual materials to tell the story of acequias.</p> <p>&ldquo;Acequias and the Future of Resilience in Global Perspective&rdquo; was a free public international symposium held in Las Cruces, NM, that included the project team with invited scholars of autonomous irrigation systems in Spain, U.S.A., Chile, Bali, Peru, Mexico, Morocco, and the Mediterranean. A combined workshop included acequia researchers, activists and community members.</p> <p>Project outcomes can be found at <a href="http://wcrg.nmsu.edu/">http://wcrg.nmsu.edu/</a>.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/20/2016<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482267737799_Acequiaconnectionsbetweenhydrologyandcommunityillustrations_BS--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482267737799_Acequiaconnectionsbetweenhydrologyandcommunityillustrations_BS--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Acequia connections between hydrology and community"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482267737799_Acequiaconnectionsbetweenhydrologyandcommunityillustrations_BS--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Acequia connections between hydrology and community"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The graphic illustrates project elements to include: climatic data, acequia flows, manual flow measurements, soil moisture data, community interaction, field irrigation amounts, ET information, groundwater level monitoring, data collection, remote sensing, students, and river inflows and outflows.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alexander Fernald</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</div> <div class="imageTitle">Acequia connections between hydrology and community</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482257518413_NMSUgraduateresearchpresentation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482257518413_NMSUgraduateresearchpresentation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="A presentation on graduate student research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482257518413_NMSUgraduateresearchpresentation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="A presentation on graduate student research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Jose Juan Cruz, an NMSU PhD student, and Alejandro Lopez Moreno, a former NMSU masters student, presented their research on flow measurement instrumentation, water flow, and soil moisture flow monitoring on acequia lands to faculty, community members, and other researchers in northern New Mexico.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Peggy Risner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</div> <div class="imageTitle">A presentation on graduate student research</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482260353476_Chilevisit--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482260353476_Chilevisit--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project collaborators meet in Chile, South America"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482260353476_Chilevisit--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project collaborators meet in Chile, South America"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Per the "CNH" project collaboration with a Chilean sister research site, CNH project participants listen to representatives of the canal association while visiting the Dam of the Bocatoma Asociacion de Canalistas del Laja.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jesslyn Ratliff</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project collaborators meet in Chile, South America</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482255595929_Gutierrez-Juradoresearch--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482255595929_Gutierrez-Juradoresearch--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Acequia research in northern New Mexico conducted by a former NMSU graduate student"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482255595929_Gutierrez-Juradoresearch--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Acequia research in northern New Mexico conducted by a former NMSU graduate student"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Karina Gutierrez-Jurado, a former graduate student from NMSU, performed research at three different sites in northern New Mexico. The research suggested that acequia irrigated valleys could function as temporary hydraulic reservoirs in northern New Mexico.</div> <div class="imageCredit">D. Esquibel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</div> <div class="imageTitle">Acequia research in northern New Mexico conducted by a former NMSU graduate student</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482269810674_SDmodelbuildingblocks--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482269810674_SDmodelbuildingblocks--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Building blocks of the projects System Dynamics (SD) model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482269810674_SDmodelbuildingblocks--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Building blocks of the projects System Dynamics (SD) model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conceptual diagram that shows the linkages between system building blocks of the multidisciplinary acequia model</div> <div class="imageCredit">"Sustainability" (open access journal from MDPI)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</div> <div class="imageTitle">Building blocks of the projects System Dynamics (SD) model</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482271162947_ElAguaesVidaAcequiasinNewMexicosavethedate--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482271162947_ElAguaesVidaAcequiasinNewMexicosavethedate--rgov-800width.jpg" title="El Agua Es Vida: Acequias in New Mexico"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1010516/1010516_10035871_1482271162947_ElAguaesVidaAcequiasinNewMexicosavethedate--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="El Agua Es Vida: Acequias in New Mexico"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The exhibition opening of El Agua Es Vida: Acequias in New Mexico integrated research, food, music, tradition, and poetry.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maxwell Museum of Anthropology at University of New Mexico</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;G&nbsp;Fernald</div> <div class="imageTitle">El Agua Es Vida: Acequias in New Mexico</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A dynamic group of project investigators, undergraduates, and graduate students conducted cutting edge science working closely with rural Hispanic community members in northern New Mexico to help maintain traditional irrigation acequia communities and assess their climate change vulnerabilities and adaptation opportunities. The project provided: policy guidance; new insights into the relationships between traditional water management systems, communities, and landscapes; improved understanding of hydrologic linkages between surface water and groundwater in irrigated river valleys and contributing watersheds as well as socioeconomic and cultural linkages within and between acequia communities; assessments of perceived climate and water-related risks; opportunities to build adaptive capacity; and new awareness of wildlife habitat and grazing distribution connections between valley riparian areas and upland forests and grasslands.  Multidisciplinary research conclusions include: 1) traditional knowledge of local ecology and customary practices in Spanish and English are vital components of social capital for transmission to the next generation that is essential to continuity of acequia agriculture and culture; 2) acequia culture is based on reciprocal relationships between irrigation and community that create sense of place, attachment to land, and shared cultural identity based on membership in community groups; 3) mutual networks and social density result in water sharing cooperation when acequias are confronted with drought or other extra-community stressors; 4) customary practices combine hydrologic and sociocultural strategies to respond collectively to spring snow-melt and summer variable precipitation; and 5) autonomous decision making structures in acequia governance permit rapid adjustments in operational rules and practices of each acequia when warranted by changing wet or dry season environmental conditions.  In one study of river water diverted into an earthen irrigation canal system, some was consumed by crop evapotranspiration (7.4%) while the rest returned to the river as surface return flow (59.3%) and shallow groundwater return flow that originated as seepage from canals (12.1%), and fields (21.2%). In another study, the recharge from irrigated agriculture using these traditional systems yielded up to 1350 mm/yr to the shallow local aquifer. Also, acequia flow was significantly correlated with river flow, showing that shortage and abundance are shared equally and that acequia flow is vulnerable to reduced river flow from climate change. The data show the benefits of acequias for hydrologic connectivity.  Aside from being able to survive political-administrative changes, acequias aid in the health of aquifers, benefit livestock by providing water, and are key sources of community drinking water. Acequia hydrology plays an important role in contributing to an ecologically healthy, agriculturally productive, and community-sustaining floodplain agroecosystem.  Integration of valley farming and rangeland grazing is critical to the resilience of north-central New Mexico acequia communities. New knowledge was gained regarding the nature of valley-upland linkages and their role in supporting contemporary acequia farming systems. The valley-upland linkage provides habitat for many wildlife species that use both upland mountain forests and valley riparian habitats. Livestock raising continues to be critical to the acequia agropastoral economy and the ability to grow hay during the winter largely regulates demand for summer grazing on public forested rangelands.   The project succeeded in the development of a multidisciplinary model of acequia community function. This groundbreaking effort integrated social, economic, hydrologic and ecologic dynamics to study acequia system natural and social stressors. System Dynamics (SD) was adopted for the modeling platform as it is particularly designed for multidisciplinary systems that express organized complexity and evolve over time. Model development relied heavily on stakeholder input and interactions with multiple discipline subject matter experts. One challenge overcome was quantifying key social dynamics; sensitivity analyses were conducted to quantify their role in overall system behavior and to quantify related uncertainties. Moral economy, mutualism and sense of place were key social components of community resilience. Preliminary results indicate a strong hydrologic connectivity between snow-melt driven runoff in the headwaters and the recharge of the shallow aquifer in the valley, mainly driven by the use of traditionally irrigated agriculture systems. Ultimately the SD model provides a platform to engage stakeholders to explore alternative adaptive measures for acequia communities.  A major museum exhibit attended by approximately 25,000 people, El Agua es Vida: Acequias in New Mexico, at the Maxwell Museum of Anthropology in Albuquerque, integrated spirituality and sense of place into presentation of community resource governance; connected art with research; conveyed the interconnected features of upstream and downstream rural and urban populations linked by acequias; combined modern and archival photographs, artwork, traditional and modern objects and artifacts, texts, and audiovisual materials to tell the story of acequias.  "Acequias and the Future of Resilience in Global Perspective" was a free public international symposium held in Las Cruces, NM, that included the project team with invited scholars of autonomous irrigation systems in Spain, U.S.A., Chile, Bali, Peru, Mexico, Morocco, and the Mediterranean. A combined workshop included acequia researchers, activists and community members.  Project outcomes can be found at http://wcrg.nmsu.edu/.       Last Modified: 12/20/2016       Submitted by: Alexander G Fernald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
