<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Development of Nonorthogonal Fusion Frames and Reflective Sensing with Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>158507.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>158507</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Li&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1010058&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     The investigator develops a new (non-orthogonal) fusion&lt;br/&gt;frame, a notion of reflective sensing, and their applications. &lt;br/&gt;They are derived from the need for sparse fusion frame operators&lt;br/&gt;for efficient data fusion applications in general distributed&lt;br/&gt;systems.  Theme 1 of the project defines a new non-orthogonal&lt;br/&gt;fusion frame.  Preliminary studies show that the matrix&lt;br/&gt;representation of the new fusion frame operator can be diagonal&lt;br/&gt;over the same example where the existing fusion frame operator is&lt;br/&gt;completely sparse-less.  Because the fusion operation ultimately&lt;br/&gt;involves the inverse of the fusion frame operator, and because&lt;br/&gt;subspace transformations are generally unavailable in practical&lt;br/&gt;data fusion applications, such a new fusion frame with sparse or&lt;br/&gt;diagonal fusion operator becomes crucial.  Theme 2 studies a&lt;br/&gt;notion of multi-fusion frames based on multiple non-orthogonal&lt;br/&gt;projections onto one subspace.  Nearly surprisingly, the new&lt;br/&gt;multi-fusion frame operator defined on one proper subspace can be&lt;br/&gt;easily positive and invertible.  A number of theoretical issues&lt;br/&gt;are to be understood.  Rooted in studies of themes 1 and 2, theme&lt;br/&gt;3 outlines a notion of reflective sensing and multiple reflective&lt;br/&gt;sensing.  Their theory and applications in side-measured&lt;br/&gt;tomography and multi-path wireless signal receiving are examined. &lt;br/&gt;It is relevant to point out that the implementation of&lt;br/&gt;non-orthogonal projection operators is naturally achievable,&lt;br/&gt;based on earlier work by the investigator on pseudoframes for&lt;br/&gt;subspaces. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     The project relates to signal processing applications. &lt;br/&gt;Signal processing generally refers to making the signal easy to&lt;br/&gt;handle or of better quality.  It is everywhere seen in our modern&lt;br/&gt;society.  In this project, the principal novelties introduced to&lt;br/&gt;signal processing are the new notion of non-orthogonal fusion&lt;br/&gt;frames and ideas of performing data fusion from, e.g., wireless&lt;br/&gt;signals received from multiple paths.  Fusion frame is a notion&lt;br/&gt;developed specifically for various data fusion applications. &lt;br/&gt;Data fusion means combining data measured by different devices or&lt;br/&gt;by different means in order to obtain refined data.  The&lt;br/&gt;advantage of non-orthogonal fusion frames lies in the fact that&lt;br/&gt;they greatly improve efficiency of the data fusion procedure in&lt;br/&gt;practical sensor networks, particularly when the amount of data&lt;br/&gt;is large.  The project aims to develop effective methods of&lt;br/&gt;combining data detected in an array of sensors where information&lt;br/&gt;overlay (among sensors) is abundant and unpredictable.  With&lt;br/&gt;extremely complicated information overlaps, exact and efficient&lt;br/&gt;data combination is made possible by non-orthogonal fusion&lt;br/&gt;frames.  In particular, the project explores image fusion to&lt;br/&gt;provide a combined image of much greater precision or resolution&lt;br/&gt;without ad-hoc procedures present in conventional techniques. &lt;br/&gt;Data fusion problems arise in many applications, ranging from&lt;br/&gt;commercial imaging to geographic survey, mapping, wireless&lt;br/&gt;communication, multi-sensor/camera surveillance systems, and a&lt;br/&gt;great number of sensor network applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1010058</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shidong</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shidong Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shidong@sfsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4153381481</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Francisco State University</Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<ZipCode>941321722</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4153387090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Holloway Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ADM 471]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>942514985</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Francisco State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941321722</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 Holloway Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~158507</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Development about the new notion of <em>non-orthogonal fusion frames</em> (NogFF) is carried out.&nbsp; Extended construction studies of NogFF are provided.&nbsp; We show that employing non-orthogonal projections can always make the new fusion frame operator sparse.&nbsp; We also show that multiple non-orthogonal projections can always enable the new fusion frame operator to become diagonal. Specific constructions are given.&nbsp; The notion of <em>reflective sensing</em> is also positively confirmed.&nbsp; Conditions and construction means are provided. Reflective sensing states that if a signal is projected onto a subspace by a number of non-orthogonal projections, there can be no loss of information even if the subspace is strictly proper (a strictly &ldquo;smaller&rdquo; subspace). This conclusion is against the conventional wisdom about orthogonal projections, where loss of information is inevitable if a subspace is proper.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Theoretical merit includes the advances of the more general theory of fusion frames. We show, for instance, that the subject of study in fusion frames should have been the projection operators in general (other than subspaces). We also demonstrate that subspace rotations and transformations are generally unavailable in sensor network data fusion applications.&nbsp; However, non-orthogonal data collection by the means of <em>pseudoframe for subspaces</em> (an earlier NSF sponsored research outcome by the PI) is implementable. As a result, making the (new) fusion frame operator sparse and diagonal through non-orthogonal projections is a valid and effective new approach. Practical merit includes the understanding how the fusion process in data fusion applications by the principle of NogFF can be simplified.&nbsp; The principle of reflective sensing may also find practical applications in data collections where sampling devices always possess merely proper observation subspaces. &nbsp;</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The sponsored work relates to signal processing applications. Signal processing generally refers to making the signal easy to handle and/or of better quality.&nbsp; It is everywhere seen in our modern society.&nbsp; One impact that this project has is to further advance the technology of image fusion, for instance, to combine images taken from multiple medias/cameras into a refined one (say, of higher resolution).&nbsp; Another impact could be the advances of data collection and reconstruction technologies by the principle of reflective sensing. Since any practical sensing/sampling device possesses merely a proper observation subspace, multiple non-orthogonal data collections, by the means of non-orthogonal projections, would enrich the signal fidelity. Taking mobile communication, for example, each mobile phone device has limited fidelity capacity (since the signal receiving subspace is limited). A mobile device made by the principle of reflective sensing can have improved signal quality.&nbsp; In general, the results of this project have impacts in the information industry ranging from commercial imaging to geographic survey, mapping, wireless communication, multi-sensor/camera surveillance systems and generally sensor network data applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2014<br>      Modified by: Shidong&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Development about the new notion of non-orthogonal fusion frames (NogFF) is carried out.  Extended construction studies of NogFF are provided.  We show that employing non-orthogonal projections can always make the new fusion frame operator sparse.  We also show that multiple non-orthogonal projections can always enable the new fusion frame operator to become diagonal. Specific constructions are given.  The notion of reflective sensing is also positively confirmed.  Conditions and construction means are provided. Reflective sensing states that if a signal is projected onto a subspace by a number of non-orthogonal projections, there can be no loss of information even if the subspace is strictly proper (a strictly "smaller" subspace). This conclusion is against the conventional wisdom about orthogonal projections, where loss of information is inevitable if a subspace is proper.   Theoretical merit includes the advances of the more general theory of fusion frames. We show, for instance, that the subject of study in fusion frames should have been the projection operators in general (other than subspaces). We also demonstrate that subspace rotations and transformations are generally unavailable in sensor network data fusion applications.  However, non-orthogonal data collection by the means of pseudoframe for subspaces (an earlier NSF sponsored research outcome by the PI) is implementable. As a result, making the (new) fusion frame operator sparse and diagonal through non-orthogonal projections is a valid and effective new approach. Practical merit includes the understanding how the fusion process in data fusion applications by the principle of NogFF can be simplified.  The principle of reflective sensing may also find practical applications in data collections where sampling devices always possess merely proper observation subspaces.     The sponsored work relates to signal processing applications. Signal processing generally refers to making the signal easy to handle and/or of better quality.  It is everywhere seen in our modern society.  One impact that this project has is to further advance the technology of image fusion, for instance, to combine images taken from multiple medias/cameras into a refined one (say, of higher resolution).  Another impact could be the advances of data collection and reconstruction technologies by the principle of reflective sensing. Since any practical sensing/sampling device possesses merely a proper observation subspace, multiple non-orthogonal data collections, by the means of non-orthogonal projections, would enrich the signal fidelity. Taking mobile communication, for example, each mobile phone device has limited fidelity capacity (since the signal receiving subspace is limited). A mobile device made by the principle of reflective sensing can have improved signal quality.  In general, the results of this project have impacts in the information industry ranging from commercial imaging to geographic survey, mapping, wireless communication, multi-sensor/camera surveillance systems and generally sensor network data applications.          Last Modified: 09/19/2014       Submitted by: Shidong Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
