<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Summer Symposium in Real Analysis 34</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15770.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15770</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Clancey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support to defray expenses of participants in a week-long summer symposium on recent advances in real analysis at The College of Wooster in Wooster, Ohio from  July 13 -17, 2010.  This is the 34th Summer Symposium in Real Analysis. Much of the funding will be directed to the goal of disseminating knowledge to and inclusion of underrepresented minorities and women mathematicians. In addition to this clear goal of dissemination of knowledge, this conference has the broader goal to provide a nurturing environment for young researchers and to be an exemplar of an exciting research community to the students of The College of Wooster.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the past dozen years there has been a resurgence of vibrant research in the area of real analysis, coupled with greater international correspondence. The Summer Symposium, which throughout its existence attracted a large international audience, will play a central role in future developments. The Symposium will offer researchers the opportunity to hear and share the newest findings in the field of real analysis.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1011888</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Humke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Humke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>humke@stolaf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5073018475</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000340718</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pamela</FirstName>
<LastName>Pierce</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pamela Pierce</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ppierce@wooster.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3302632389</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of Wooster</Name>
<CityName>Wooster</CityName>
<ZipCode>446912363</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3302632293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1189 Beall Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076744085</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE COLLEGE OF WOOSTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076744085</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of Wooster]]></Name>
<CityName>Wooster</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>446912363</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1189 Beall Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~15770</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Summer Symposium XXXIV</p> <p>Held at the College of Wooster, Wooster, OH</p> <p>July 13-17, 2010</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Thirty-Fourth Summer Symposium in Real Analysis (The Buckeye Symposium) was hosted by The College of Wooster July 13-17, 2010.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The local conference host was Pamela Pierce, Professor of Mathematics at the College of Wooster, while Paul Humke of St. Olaf College and Washington and Lee University served as co-director of the Symposium.&nbsp; We wish to thank The National Science Foundation which generously provided grant support to help fund this conference and make it possible for a diverse group of participants to attend the Symposium.&nbsp;&nbsp; Grant DMS-1011888 from the National Science Foundation provided partial funding, and The College of Wooster provided financial and administrative support to help make this conference possible.&nbsp; NSF grant money specifically allowed us to award small grants to participants with diverse backgrounds who otherwise would not have been able to attend.&nbsp; These grants covered the registration and housing fees for the participants.&nbsp; The conference was attended by 42 participants from 10 different countries. This represents one of the highest attendance numbers for the Summer Symposium in recent years, and we were extremely pleased with the diverse backgrounds and mathematical interests that were represented at the conference. Several graduate students attended, as well as two undergraduates, and this opportunity to network with researchers in real analysis was extremely valuable to them.<br /><br />Thirty-two talks were presented by the participants, including two invited hour-long talks by Stephen Krantz and Marianna Csornyei.&nbsp; All of the talks were well-received and followed by lively discussion.&nbsp; The atmosphere was one of collegial support and encouragement for the ongoing research being done in real analysis.&nbsp; In addition to the formal mathematical program, time was set aside for research collaboration and a problem session.&nbsp; Wednesday evening found many of the participants enjoying the Ohio Light Opera's production of John Philip Sousa's&nbsp; "El Capitain".&nbsp; On Thursday afternoon, the symposium participants were treated to a delightfully informative tour of the Amish region near Wooster.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; At the traditional Friday evening banquet, Conference Director Pierce awarded the ``Andrew Bruckner Award''&nbsp; to&nbsp; invited speaker Marianna Csornyei.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/19/2011<br>      Modified by: Pamela&nbsp;Pierce</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summer Symposium XXXIV  Held at the College of Wooster, Wooster, OH  July 13-17, 2010     The Thirty-Fourth Summer Symposium in Real Analysis (The Buckeye Symposium) was hosted by The College of Wooster July 13-17, 2010.    The local conference host was Pamela Pierce, Professor of Mathematics at the College of Wooster, while Paul Humke of St. Olaf College and Washington and Lee University served as co-director of the Symposium.  We wish to thank The National Science Foundation which generously provided grant support to help fund this conference and make it possible for a diverse group of participants to attend the Symposium.   Grant DMS-1011888 from the National Science Foundation provided partial funding, and The College of Wooster provided financial and administrative support to help make this conference possible.  NSF grant money specifically allowed us to award small grants to participants with diverse backgrounds who otherwise would not have been able to attend.  These grants covered the registration and housing fees for the participants.  The conference was attended by 42 participants from 10 different countries. This represents one of the highest attendance numbers for the Summer Symposium in recent years, and we were extremely pleased with the diverse backgrounds and mathematical interests that were represented at the conference. Several graduate students attended, as well as two undergraduates, and this opportunity to network with researchers in real analysis was extremely valuable to them.  Thirty-two talks were presented by the participants, including two invited hour-long talks by Stephen Krantz and Marianna Csornyei.  All of the talks were well-received and followed by lively discussion.  The atmosphere was one of collegial support and encouragement for the ongoing research being done in real analysis.  In addition to the formal mathematical program, time was set aside for research collaboration and a problem session.  Wednesday evening found many of the participants enjoying the Ohio Light Opera's production of John Philip Sousa's  "El Capitain".  On Thursday afternoon, the symposium participants were treated to a delightfully informative tour of the Amish region near Wooster.     At the traditional Friday evening banquet, Conference Director Pierce awarded the ``Andrew Bruckner Award''  to  invited speaker Marianna Csornyei.        Last Modified: 02/19/2011       Submitted by: Pamela Pierce]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
