<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Shipboard Scientific Support Equipment for the R/V Savannah</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>35103.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>35103</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Hawkins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mjhawkin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927407</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;25 July 2010&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number:  1012818&lt;br/&gt;Institution:  Skidaway Institute of Oceanography&lt;br/&gt;PI:   J. Sanders&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal requests several Shipboard Scientific Support Equipment (SSSE) items for the R/V SAVANNAH operated by Skidaway Institute of Oceanography; namely portable deck capstans, navigational echo sounders and trawl blocks.  These items will improve safety, bring the vessel into compliance with latest UNOLS standards, and enhance science support capabilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:   The R/V SAVANNAH supports federally funded scientific research in the southeast Atlantic in order to expand human knowledge of the ocean environment.  During operations, the vessel routinely exposes graduate and undergraduate students to seagoing oceanography.  Pubic outreach is also achieved through open house events and educational cruises funded by both NSF and the State of Georgia.  The SAVANNAH is scheduled to complete approximately 60 NSF sponsored days in 2010.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1012818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Sanders</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James G Sanders</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sandersj@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9125983340</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Skidaway Institute of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>Savannah</CityName>
<ZipCode>314111011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9125982400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 Ocean Science Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>W6DP PEO IEW&amp;S ALEXANDRIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Skidaway Institute of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName>Savannah</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>314111011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10 Ocean Science Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5416</Code>
<Text>SHIPBOARD SCIENTIFIC SUPP EQUI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~35103</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The award funded several items of shipboard scientific support equipment for the Research Vessel, <em>Savannah</em>, which is operated by the Skidaway Institute of Oceanography.&nbsp; This<em>&nbsp;</em>92-foot vessel supports a range of research and education projects, primarily in the estuarine, coastal and shelf waters off the Southeast U.S.&nbsp; The <em>R/V Savannah</em> is part of the NSF University National Oceanographic Laboratories (UNOLS) research fleet.&nbsp; In 2010-2012, many separate projects (most funded by NSF programs) utilized the vessel for a range of 140-160 days in the field per year.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The funded equipment consisted of:&nbsp; 1) Rolls-Royce ODIM Brooke Ocean 19' metered sheave; 2) upgrades and improvements to a companion sheave; 3) a Furuno FCV-1150 echo sounder that was installed in the ship&rsquo;s wheelhouse; and 4) a Furuno FCV-585 echo sounder that was installed in the ship&rsquo;s science dry lab.&nbsp; Following delivery, the systems were configured and tested by the ship&rsquo;s Marine Technician, and became integral components in the <em>R/V Savannah&rsquo;s</em> data and sample collection systems.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These upgrades have been employed on all cruises since installation.&nbsp; The vessel&rsquo;s data system acquires and displays data collected from the ship&rsquo;s echo sounders, as well as from its navigational system, meteorological sensors, acoustic Doppler current profiler, and an underway flow-through system (measuring surface water properties).&nbsp; &nbsp;Real-time displays are available in the ship&rsquo;s dry and wet labs and on the bridge.&nbsp; In addition to enhanced bottom habitat and bathymetric feature discrimination the new units provide a significant increase in depth range.&nbsp; The new and upgraded sheaves are components of the sheave monitoring system which provides wire payout and tension information in real-time to the operator of the ship&rsquo;s CTD winch that is used for profiling and water sampling operations.&nbsp;All of these components improve the utilization of the <em>R/V Savannah</em> for a range of research and education applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/18/2012<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;G&nbsp;Sanders</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The award funded several items of shipboard scientific support equipment for the Research Vessel, Savannah, which is operated by the Skidaway Institute of Oceanography.  This 92-foot vessel supports a range of research and education projects, primarily in the estuarine, coastal and shelf waters off the Southeast U.S.  The R/V Savannah is part of the NSF University National Oceanographic Laboratories (UNOLS) research fleet.  In 2010-2012, many separate projects (most funded by NSF programs) utilized the vessel for a range of 140-160 days in the field per year.     The funded equipment consisted of:  1) Rolls-Royce ODIM Brooke Ocean 19' metered sheave; 2) upgrades and improvements to a companion sheave; 3) a Furuno FCV-1150 echo sounder that was installed in the shipÆs wheelhouse; and 4) a Furuno FCV-585 echo sounder that was installed in the shipÆs science dry lab.  Following delivery, the systems were configured and tested by the shipÆs Marine Technician, and became integral components in the R/V SavannahÆs data and sample collection systems.      These upgrades have been employed on all cruises since installation.  The vesselÆs data system acquires and displays data collected from the shipÆs echo sounders, as well as from its navigational system, meteorological sensors, acoustic Doppler current profiler, and an underway flow-through system (measuring surface water properties).   Real-time displays are available in the shipÆs dry and wet labs and on the bridge.  In addition to enhanced bottom habitat and bathymetric feature discrimination the new units provide a significant increase in depth range.  The new and upgraded sheaves are components of the sheave monitoring system which provides wire payout and tension information in real-time to the operator of the shipÆs CTD winch that is used for profiling and water sampling operations. All of these components improve the utilization of the R/V Savannah for a range of research and education applications.          Last Modified: 10/18/2012       Submitted by: James G Sanders]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
