<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Symposium in Geometry and Topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>36300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>36300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This international symposium will bring together leading mathematicians to discuss the latest work and developments in geometry, topology and related &amp;#64257;elds. The distinguished invited speakers at this conference will speak about the current edge of our knowledge and highlight the areas that are likely to lead to future progress. The conference makes it possible for the community of geometers and topologists from the region and around the country to learn the most recent developments, to meet with each other and to share mathematics. Since the topics cover a wide range from geometry, topology, algebra, and mathematical physics, we expect a great deal of interchange of ideas during the symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium will provide a rich environment in which US graduate students and recent Ph.D.?s can learn about new and important developments in geometry and topology. Participation by women and minorities will be actively sought and encouraged. An important component of the conference is to attract and help graduate students, recent Ph.Ds, and members of underrepresented groups to come from all over the country and other parts of the world to learn and interact with the leaders of the &amp;#64257;elds featured during this conference.&lt;br/&gt;A special poster session will be held to allow participants, especially young mathematicians, to present their work and to interact with senior researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1012225</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David L Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.johnson@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107583759</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000465240</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huai-Dong</FirstName>
<LastName>Cao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huai-Dong Cao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huc2@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6107583726</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808264444</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068570936</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Alumni Building 27]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~36300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Under the support of the NSF grant, an International Symposium in Geometry and Topology was held at Lehigh University, May 28-31, 2010. In addition, the NSF grant also supported the 2012 Lehigh University Geometry and Topology Conference, held May 25-27, 2012. The Symposium and the Geometry-Topology Conference made it possible for the community of geometers and topologists from the region and around the country to learn the most recent developments, to meet and share mathematics, and to exchange ideas. There were ample opportunities for graduate students, junior investigators, women mathematicians and mathematicians from underrepresented groups to present their work at the conference and to interact with the speakers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>I. 2010 Lehigh University International Symposium on Geometry</strong></p> <p>The 2010 symposium brought a number of leading researchers of national and international stature in geometry and topology to discuss the forefront of these fields, including the recent achievements and future directions of geometry and topology, and related fields. The symposium was dedicated to late Professor C.C. Hsiung, the founder of the JDG, who passed away in May 2009.</p> <p>There were about 100 participants attending the Symposium, among them 5 undergraduate students, 30 graduate students, 26 post-docs, 17 women mathematicians and 3 mathematicians from other underrepresented groups. The speakers presented their new findings in geometry and analysis and interacted with conference participants.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>II. 2012 Lehigh University Geometry and Topology Conference</strong></p> <p>The 2012 Lehigh University Geometry and Topology Conference took place May 25-27, 2012. The conference featured 7 principal speakers who presented their recent findings in geometry and topology. In addition, there were 28 contributed talks by participants.</p> <p>There were 72 registered participants in the conference, including 27 graduate students, 15 recent Ph.Ds, and 16 women mathematicians and other members of underrepresented groups.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2013<br>      Modified by: Huai-Dong&nbsp;Cao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Under the support of the NSF grant, an International Symposium in Geometry and Topology was held at Lehigh University, May 28-31, 2010. In addition, the NSF grant also supported the 2012 Lehigh University Geometry and Topology Conference, held May 25-27, 2012. The Symposium and the Geometry-Topology Conference made it possible for the community of geometers and topologists from the region and around the country to learn the most recent developments, to meet and share mathematics, and to exchange ideas. There were ample opportunities for graduate students, junior investigators, women mathematicians and mathematicians from underrepresented groups to present their work at the conference and to interact with the speakers.     I. 2010 Lehigh University International Symposium on Geometry  The 2010 symposium brought a number of leading researchers of national and international stature in geometry and topology to discuss the forefront of these fields, including the recent achievements and future directions of geometry and topology, and related fields. The symposium was dedicated to late Professor C.C. Hsiung, the founder of the JDG, who passed away in May 2009.  There were about 100 participants attending the Symposium, among them 5 undergraduate students, 30 graduate students, 26 post-docs, 17 women mathematicians and 3 mathematicians from other underrepresented groups. The speakers presented their new findings in geometry and analysis and interacted with conference participants.     II. 2012 Lehigh University Geometry and Topology Conference  The 2012 Lehigh University Geometry and Topology Conference took place May 25-27, 2012. The conference featured 7 principal speakers who presented their recent findings in geometry and topology. In addition, there were 28 contributed talks by participants.  There were 72 registered participants in the conference, including 27 graduate students, 15 recent Ph.Ds, and 16 women mathematicians and other members of underrepresented groups.       Last Modified: 06/29/2013       Submitted by: Huai-Dong Cao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
