<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Toward Homogeneous Carbon Media for Separation Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kelsey Cook</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kcook@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927490</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Prof. Susan Olesik and her group at Ohio State University are supported by the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program to study a newly discovered means of producing carbon media that can increase by at least two orders of magnitude the number of components separated per unit distance in a separation device.  Their approach includes development of molecularly-imprinted carbon and entails thorough study of how and why these media have such high performance characteristics, with an aim of providing even greater improvements in compound separations.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Highly selective adsorptive carbon surfaces should have broad-reaching applications, such as pollution remediation and disease detection.   The carbon adsorbents under study also have potential relevance in addressing many of the world's most challenging problems - for example, large-scale selective adsorption of CO2 from the atmosphere and highly selective separations of DNA fragments for disease detection and drug development.  Undergraduate students in instrumental analysis will be involved in aspects of these studies through an extension of the REEL program (Research Experience to Enhance Education).  Through discussions about the properties of the unique carbon materials, students will make decisions about how this new technology can be used in their class projects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1012279</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Olesik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan V Olesik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>olesik.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142920733</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000293597</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~280000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>.&nbsp; Analytical chemistry provides quantitative and qualitative information on the components of complex mixtures.&nbsp; These mixtures may range from trace analysis of environmental samples to forensic analyses to clinical test methods. State-of-the-art analytical chemistry attempts to make these analyses either faster or more effective or more informative. <br /><br />Innovative separation devices based on nanofibers that have two of their dimensions in the 100 - 400 nm size range were developed in this work. <br />Today polar pharmaceutical compounds are found more and more in municipaldrinking water.&nbsp; Improvements as high as 32 times greater in the amount extracted were noted for rates of removal of polarpharmaceutical compound in water compared to the best commercial methods.<br /><br />New methods of detecting organic and biopolymers by mass spectrometry, an<br />analytical technique that can measure mass to very low levels, were developed based on the nanofibers as the supports for laser desorption ionization. Improved detection limits for proteins and organic polymers, such as polyethylene glycol, were noted.&nbsp; Polyethylene glycol is used in a large range of biomedical applications. One such application is drug delivery. Also, the ability to measure proteins at a lower concentration level will help in studies to detect diseases earlier.<br /><br />Broader Impacts: An experiment was developed using a nanofiber based separation device for undergraduate teaching laboratory. This experiment allows to the students to determine the amount of aspartame in diet sodas. <br /><br />The PI has a long standing science outreach effort (Wonders of Our World) that works with the elementary school students in inner-city Columbus schools approximately once a month. This program continues to show success in enhancing the students&rsquo; interest in science and improving the teacher&rsquo;s interest in science.&nbsp; This program impacts hundreds of elementary<br />school students every year.&nbsp;&nbsp; Experiments on nanoscience are also taken to Washington State Community College (Appalachian area of Ohio) once a year to participate in YES Days (Young Engineers and Scientists).&nbsp;&nbsp; Hundreds of middle school students do hands-on experiments in this project every year.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2015<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;V&nbsp;Olesik</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1012279/1012279_10021075_1447122083667_nanofiberspng--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1012279/1012279_10021075_1447122083667_nanofiberspng--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanofiber"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1012279/1012279_10021075_1447122083667_nanofiberspng--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanofiber"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mat of polymer nanofiber</div> <div class="imageCredit">Image taken by Martin Beres</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;V&nbsp;Olesik</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanofiber</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1012279/1012279_10021075_1447122745157_PEG--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1012279/1012279_10021075_1447122745157_PEG--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mass spectrum of PEG"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1012279/1012279_10021075_1447122745157_PEG--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mass spectrum of PEG"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Laser Desorption Mass Spectrum of Polyethylene glycol</div> <div class="imageCredit">Martin Beres</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;V&nbsp;Olesik</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mass spectrum of PEG</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit.  Analytical chemistry provides quantitative and qualitative information on the components of complex mixtures.  These mixtures may range from trace analysis of environmental samples to forensic analyses to clinical test methods. State-of-the-art analytical chemistry attempts to make these analyses either faster or more effective or more informative.   Innovative separation devices based on nanofibers that have two of their dimensions in the 100 - 400 nm size range were developed in this work.  Today polar pharmaceutical compounds are found more and more in municipaldrinking water.  Improvements as high as 32 times greater in the amount extracted were noted for rates of removal of polarpharmaceutical compound in water compared to the best commercial methods.  New methods of detecting organic and biopolymers by mass spectrometry, an analytical technique that can measure mass to very low levels, were developed based on the nanofibers as the supports for laser desorption ionization. Improved detection limits for proteins and organic polymers, such as polyethylene glycol, were noted.  Polyethylene glycol is used in a large range of biomedical applications. One such application is drug delivery. Also, the ability to measure proteins at a lower concentration level will help in studies to detect diseases earlier.  Broader Impacts: An experiment was developed using a nanofiber based separation device for undergraduate teaching laboratory. This experiment allows to the students to determine the amount of aspartame in diet sodas.   The PI has a long standing science outreach effort (Wonders of Our World) that works with the elementary school students in inner-city Columbus schools approximately once a month. This program continues to show success in enhancing the students? interest in science and improving the teacher?s interest in science.  This program impacts hundreds of elementary school students every year.   Experiments on nanoscience are also taken to Washington State Community College (Appalachian area of Ohio) once a year to participate in YES Days (Young Engineers and Scientists).   Hundreds of middle school students do hands-on experiments in this project every year.       Last Modified: 11/09/2015       Submitted by: Susan V Olesik]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
