<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Stabilized Bioanode Enzymes for Micro Power Biofuel Cells</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>146837.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>146837</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anthony Walters</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project will develop an enzymatic bio-fuel cell using a unique enzyme stabilization technology.  The technology overcomes the stability and lifetime issues faced by conventional bio-fuel cells where rare metals serve as the catalyst.  Development of the bioanode for the fuel cell power supply is based on Akermin?s proprietary enzyme stabilization technology. Such a fuel cell can be used for many lower power devices, including microelectrical mechanical devices, unattended ground sensors, and small mobile power devices. This technology has advantages over similar competing technologies (i.e., batteries and conventional fuel cells) when addressing the needs of small remote sensors and electronics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impacts of the proposed project will be: 1. that it will be environment friendly because a successful enzyme-based fuel cell holds the promise of replacing batteries currently used in many applications including remote sensing and human implants; 2. it will provide improved power supplies for both remote sensors and drug delivery devices that would be a significant benefit to society; and 3. the proposed product has reasonable commercial potential and potential customers have been identified.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1013873</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wayne</FirstName>
<LastName>Gellett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wayne Gellett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gellettw@akermin.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3148241970</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Akermin, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631343115</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3148241970</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4633 World Parkway Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>145926239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AKERMIN, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Akermin, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631343115</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4633 World Parkway Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9197</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL TECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~146837</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This SBIR Phase I project, &ldquo;Stabilized Bioanode Enzymes for Micro Power Biofuel Cells&rdquo;, focused on the feasibility determination and development of a bioanode for a coin cell sized fuel cell power supply based on Akermin&rsquo;s patented enzyme stabilization technology.&nbsp; Such a fuel cell can be used for many lower power commercial applications, including microelectrical mechanical devices, unattended ground sensors, and small mobile power devices.&nbsp; This technology has advantages over similar competing technologies (i.e., batteries and conventional fuel cells) when addressing the needs of small remote sensors and electronics.&nbsp; Akermin&rsquo;s unique enzyme immobilization and stabilization technology for biofuel cell technology has overcome the limitations traditionally associated with enzymatic biofuel cells such as instability at extreme pH&rsquo;s, short operational and shelf lifetimes, and poor stability relative to temperature changes.&nbsp; The primary benefit for consumer applications will be the displacement of existing batteries that contain toxic materials with an environmentally benign biofuel cell alternative.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the course of this Phase I project, Akermin demonstrated the technical feasibility of a bioanode for an integrated power supply based on biofuel cell technology. The program R&amp;D plan focused on stabilization of anode enzymatic catalysts for oxidation of fuel, evaluation of bio-based fuels (glycerol, ethanol, methanol, or glucose), and initial anode electrode support designs that maximized enzymatic activity. &nbsp;Finally, Akermin developed the initial design and engineering requirements for the purpose of determining technical feasibility of a coin cell sized biofuel cell system based on the results of this program.&nbsp; The key results of this program include the identification of enzyme/fuel combinations for a bioanode application and the experimental evaluation of electron transfer pathways for the enzymes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2011<br>      Modified by: Wayne&nbsp;Gellett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This SBIR Phase I project, "Stabilized Bioanode Enzymes for Micro Power Biofuel Cells", focused on the feasibility determination and development of a bioanode for a coin cell sized fuel cell power supply based on AkerminÆs patented enzyme stabilization technology.  Such a fuel cell can be used for many lower power commercial applications, including microelectrical mechanical devices, unattended ground sensors, and small mobile power devices.  This technology has advantages over similar competing technologies (i.e., batteries and conventional fuel cells) when addressing the needs of small remote sensors and electronics.  AkerminÆs unique enzyme immobilization and stabilization technology for biofuel cell technology has overcome the limitations traditionally associated with enzymatic biofuel cells such as instability at extreme pHÆs, short operational and shelf lifetimes, and poor stability relative to temperature changes.  The primary benefit for consumer applications will be the displacement of existing batteries that contain toxic materials with an environmentally benign biofuel cell alternative.      During the course of this Phase I project, Akermin demonstrated the technical feasibility of a bioanode for an integrated power supply based on biofuel cell technology. The program R&amp;D plan focused on stabilization of anode enzymatic catalysts for oxidation of fuel, evaluation of bio-based fuels (glycerol, ethanol, methanol, or glucose), and initial anode electrode support designs that maximized enzymatic activity.  Finally, Akermin developed the initial design and engineering requirements for the purpose of determining technical feasibility of a coin cell sized biofuel cell system based on the results of this program.  The key results of this program include the identification of enzyme/fuel combinations for a bioanode application and the experimental evaluation of electron transfer pathways for the enzymes.           Last Modified: 03/31/2011       Submitted by: Wayne Gellett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
