<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Rydberg Fingerprint Spectroscopy for Sensitive Identification of Isomerically-Dependent Environmental Pollutants. Test Case: Dioxins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149798.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149798</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anthony Walters</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project will develop a spectroscopic device for detecting and discriminating congeners of isomeric compounds based on their Rydberg spectroscopic "fingerprints."  It enables the development of a new&lt;br/&gt;analytical tool for the detection of dioxins which are environmental contaminants that arise from combustion of organic materials in the presence of chlorine. Dioxins build up in human tissues, causing long-term health problems including cancer, diabetes, endometriosis and others. The toxicity of many isomers is unknown, as it is difficult to selectively identify many isomeric forms of dioxins. Current analytical methods involve mass spectrometry (MS), or tandem-MS techniques. However, the former cannot identify individual isomers, while the latter lacks sufficient sensitivity to reach low detection limits. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impact of the project will be to potentially impact the $6 billion worldwide market for mass spectrometers, of which the investigators expect to capture 1 percent, or $60 million.  In addition, differentiation of isomeric forms with high sensitivity in a compact form-factor would be a new and welcome capability in multiple scientific fields, including air pollution monitoring, toxicology, and exposure assessment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1013149</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Geiser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph D Geiser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joseph.geiser@ryontech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4015235277</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000552859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ryon Technologies Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029034762</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4015235277</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 Davol Square</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 301]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>801937298</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RYON TECHNOLOGIES, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ryon Technologies Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029034762</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3 Davol Square]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1584</Code>
<Text>ENVIRO GEOCHEM AND BIOGEOCHEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9181</Code>
<Text>BIOPROCESSING/BIOMOLECULAR MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~149798</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 7.9px Arial} p.p2 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 9.8px Arial} span.s1 {font: 9.8px Arial} span.Apple-tab-span {white-space:pre} --> <p class="p1"><strong><em>For Public Release</em></strong></p> <p class="p2">The identification of trace amounts of pollutants in environmental samples remains a challenging analytical problem. A particularly important issue of great practical relevance is the identification of dioxins, a class of toxic molecules that can exist in many isomeric forms. Dioxins are formed as a by-product in many industrial and waste incineration processes. Isomers are compounds with the same molecular formula but with a different structural formula. Consequently, they have different physical and chemical properties including toxicity levels. Using traditional methods, many of the dioxin isomers are not readily distinguishable with sufficient sensitivity. However, by measuring their Rydberg energies, i.e. the energy difference between an infinitely far removed electron and an electron very loosely attached to a positive molecular ion core, the molecular shape or fingerprint can be distinguished. This is primarily due to the fact that the Rydberg energy of a molecule has been identified as a molecular property that is highly sensitive toward the molecular structure.</p> <p class="p2">With the aid of an NSF SBIR Phase I award, Ryon Technologies Inc. has designed and developed a new analytical tool called Rydberg Fingerprint Spectroscopy (RFS). RFS measures the binding energy of Rydberg electrons in coincidence with the mass of the corresponding ion, which allows us to rapidly and unambiguously identify the 75 dioxins isomers. Towards this end, designs were modeled using the Simion ion optics simulation software, CAD drawings were completed, the component pieces were machined and the first RFS instrument prototype was assembled. All vacuum components, sample lines, timing electronics and data acquisition for the new spectrometer were successfully assembled and tested.</p> <p class="p2">In Phase II of this project, the prototype will be optimized to include design changes from lessons-learned in Phase I. The sensitivity, resolution, and detection limit of the instrument will be explored. Additionally, a library of dioxin RFS spectra will be generated, allowing the instrument to be used as an analytical tool for dioxin identification. We will test the instrument&rsquo;s ability to identify dioxins in simulated and in real samples. Finally, it will be packaged as a commercial instrument with an appropriate user interface.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/16/2011<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;D&nbsp;Geiser</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For Public Release The identification of trace amounts of pollutants in environmental samples remains a challenging analytical problem. A particularly important issue of great practical relevance is the identification of dioxins, a class of toxic molecules that can exist in many isomeric forms. Dioxins are formed as a by-product in many industrial and waste incineration processes. Isomers are compounds with the same molecular formula but with a different structural formula. Consequently, they have different physical and chemical properties including toxicity levels. Using traditional methods, many of the dioxin isomers are not readily distinguishable with sufficient sensitivity. However, by measuring their Rydberg energies, i.e. the energy difference between an infinitely far removed electron and an electron very loosely attached to a positive molecular ion core, the molecular shape or fingerprint can be distinguished. This is primarily due to the fact that the Rydberg energy of a molecule has been identified as a molecular property that is highly sensitive toward the molecular structure. With the aid of an NSF SBIR Phase I award, Ryon Technologies Inc. has designed and developed a new analytical tool called Rydberg Fingerprint Spectroscopy (RFS). RFS measures the binding energy of Rydberg electrons in coincidence with the mass of the corresponding ion, which allows us to rapidly and unambiguously identify the 75 dioxins isomers. Towards this end, designs were modeled using the Simion ion optics simulation software, CAD drawings were completed, the component pieces were machined and the first RFS instrument prototype was assembled. All vacuum components, sample lines, timing electronics and data acquisition for the new spectrometer were successfully assembled and tested. In Phase II of this project, the prototype will be optimized to include design changes from lessons-learned in Phase I. The sensitivity, resolution, and detection limit of the instrument will be explored. Additionally, a library of dioxin RFS spectra will be generated, allowing the instrument to be used as an analytical tool for dioxin identification. We will test the instrumentÆs ability to identify dioxins in simulated and in real samples. Finally, it will be packaged as a commercial instrument with an appropriate user interface.          Last Modified: 01/16/2011       Submitted by: Joseph D Geiser]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
