<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Rare-Earth-Doped Wavelength Conversion Material and Optical Element</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>164867</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Grace Jinliu Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to integrate up and down conversion materials into a single photonic device to solve the problem of mismatch between the solar spectrum and solar cells formed from single absorbers such as silicon.  Cooperative nonradiative energy transfer between rare-earth dopants will be employed as the physical mechanism to support wavelength conversion.  By integrating up and down converting materials, this approach will not only enhance quantum efficiency above and below the absorber band gap, but also recover losses associated with down conversion in the up converter.  In this project, fluorine-based materials developed for solid state lasers will be doped specifically for solar applications, and will be tested to determine the feasibility of efficient synergistic up and down conversion between 1 and 1000 suns. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impact of this project will be the potential to significantly improve energy conversion efficiency of solar cells.  The spectrum mismatch addressed in this work is responsible for the loss of 50% of the energy reaching solar cells.  In addition, this technology does not require changes to the solar cells or electrical connections.  Therefore, the integration of this optical product into solar energy systems is straightforward.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1013378</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Spitzer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark B Spitzer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbspitzer@photonicglass.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7814929200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518091</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Photonic Glass Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Norwood</CityName>
<ZipCode>020624603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7814929200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>661 Pleasant Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>826239506</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PHOTONIC GLASS CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Photonic Glass Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Norwood</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>020624603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[661 Pleasant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1984</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS SYNTHESIS &amp; PROCESSN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9163</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~149867</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This report is the final outcome of a Phase I SBIR project to investigate the feasibility of increasing the energy conversion efficiency of low cost silicon concentrator solar cells.&nbsp; The improvement of solar cell efficiency is broadly important to the Nation&rsquo;s increasing need for renewable energy, and to the development of new solar cell designs and manufacturing processes.</p> <p>The energy conversion efficiency improvement method investigated here is based on employing rare earth elements such as erbium to actively modify the solar spectrum.&nbsp; The modification occurs by optical absorption and re-emission processes that redistribute the energy from the solar spectrum into a more narrow spectrum.&nbsp; In this way, solar energy might be more efficiently absorbed by silicon solar cells.</p> <p>Crystals of sodium yttrium fluoride, barium yttrium fluoride, and potassium yttrium fluoride were grown for this investigation.&nbsp; Although such crystals are known to exhibit optical effects when doped with erbium and other rare earth elements, they have been primarily studied for use in lasers.&nbsp; In this work, we specifically evaluated the materials as energy converters. &nbsp; During growth, all crystals were doped with erbium at three doping levels. Three materials were studied because the erbium optical transition rates are known to be related to the electric fields present in the crystal; thus the use of three crystalline materials allowed comparison of three different environments.&nbsp; &nbsp; Three doping concentration were studied because the optical transitions also depend on erbium spacing within the crystal.</p> <p>We found that in barium yttrium fluoride and potassium yttrium fluroide crystals, high energy photons are downconverted by erbium to energies that are more efficiently absorbed by silicon.&nbsp; We also found in all three materials that photons that are too low in energy to be absorbed by silicon can be upconverted to energies that can be absorbed by silicon.&nbsp; Parasitic absorption processes were also evaluated.&nbsp; Improvement in the solar cell response to high energy photons was observed.&nbsp;&nbsp; The magnitude of the downconversion response in the ultraviolet depended on erbium concentration, indicating that the erbium dopant was indeed improving the response.&nbsp; The overall finding of this work is that the use of optical processes based on rare earth elements is a feasible route to solar cell efficiency improvement.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2011<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;B&nbsp;Spitzer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This report is the final outcome of a Phase I SBIR project to investigate the feasibility of increasing the energy conversion efficiency of low cost silicon concentrator solar cells.  The improvement of solar cell efficiency is broadly important to the NationÆs increasing need for renewable energy, and to the development of new solar cell designs and manufacturing processes.  The energy conversion efficiency improvement method investigated here is based on employing rare earth elements such as erbium to actively modify the solar spectrum.  The modification occurs by optical absorption and re-emission processes that redistribute the energy from the solar spectrum into a more narrow spectrum.  In this way, solar energy might be more efficiently absorbed by silicon solar cells.  Crystals of sodium yttrium fluoride, barium yttrium fluoride, and potassium yttrium fluoride were grown for this investigation.  Although such crystals are known to exhibit optical effects when doped with erbium and other rare earth elements, they have been primarily studied for use in lasers.  In this work, we specifically evaluated the materials as energy converters.   During growth, all crystals were doped with erbium at three doping levels. Three materials were studied because the erbium optical transition rates are known to be related to the electric fields present in the crystal; thus the use of three crystalline materials allowed comparison of three different environments.    Three doping concentration were studied because the optical transitions also depend on erbium spacing within the crystal.  We found that in barium yttrium fluoride and potassium yttrium fluroide crystals, high energy photons are downconverted by erbium to energies that are more efficiently absorbed by silicon.  We also found in all three materials that photons that are too low in energy to be absorbed by silicon can be upconverted to energies that can be absorbed by silicon.  Parasitic absorption processes were also evaluated.  Improvement in the solar cell response to high energy photons was observed.   The magnitude of the downconversion response in the ultraviolet depended on erbium concentration, indicating that the erbium dopant was indeed improving the response.  The overall finding of this work is that the use of optical processes based on rare earth elements is a feasible route to solar cell efficiency improvement.        Last Modified: 06/30/2011       Submitted by: Mark B Spitzer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
