<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Using Non-linear Dynamics to Improve Compositional Contrast in Atomic Force Microscopy in Liquids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1014660</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiracofe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel R Kiracofe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6145790506</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553132</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kiracofe                Daniel         R</Name>
<CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479042558</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kiracofe                Daniel         R]]></Name>
<CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479042558</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of my research is on Atomic Force Microscopes (AFM).  Compared to its cousin the light microscope (which was invented in the 1600s), the Atomic Force Microscope is a relatively new invention, having been invented in the 1980s.  Like all microscopes, AFM allows scientists to see small objects.  However, the AFM can see objects that are much much smaller than a traditional light microscope.  Light microscopes can see objects as small as 100 &ndash; 200 nm (e.g. most bacteria can be seen under a light microscope, but viruses are usually too small to be seen with a light microscope) however, AFM can see objects as small as individual atoms!<br /><br /> The AFM works by tapping on objects with a small probe.  The best analogy is a blind person who taps a cane around in order to discern his/her surroundings.  In the same way, the AFM can tap on small objects such as viruses and literally feel them.  AFM can tell a scientist not only what something looks like, but also if it is hard or soft, or sticky or squishy.  <br /><br /> To give just one example of the usefulness of this device: it has recently been discovered using AFM that some cancer cells are significantly softer than normal cells, even though they look similar to  normal cells.  The ability to distinguish between normal and cancerous cells will be very helpful to scientists who are trying to understand (and eventually cure) cancer.<br /><br /> The research that I am conducting is primarily focused around building a better microscope.  I want to help build the enabling technology that allows others to more easily use and understand the AFM.  To this end, I used money from this NSF grant to spend a summer conducting research with Professors Hirofumi Yamada and Kei Kobayashi at Kyoto University in Japan.  The researchers at this lab are well known for their research in AFM.<br /><br /> In particular, I worked on an AFM method called photothermal excitation.  The mechanical probe used in AFM must be vibrated up and down so that it can tap on the sample object.  Photothermal excitation is one method for doing this, which involves heating the probe up with a laser until it bends.  Because the probe is very small, it heats up quickly, so by turning the laser on and off repeatedly, the probe can be made to vibrate.  This is a simple method with many desirable qualities, but unfortunately the efficiency is low.  This means that a relatively high powered laser must be used.  Sometimes excess laser light can spill over the edge of the probe and damage sensitive samples.  During my stay in Kyoto, the researchers there and I were able to refine a method to increase the efficiency of photothermal excitation.  This allows the use of the photothermal method with a significantly lower powered laser, opening this method up for use with sensitive samples.<br /><br /> During the course of my stay in Japan, I have also built connections and relationship with other researchers.  This has led to two other international collaborations on different projects.<br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/23/2011<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;R&nbsp;Kiracofe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of my research is on Atomic Force Microscopes (AFM).  Compared to its cousin the light microscope (which was invented in the 1600s), the Atomic Force Microscope is a relatively new invention, having been invented in the 1980s.  Like all microscopes, AFM allows scientists to see small objects.  However, the AFM can see objects that are much much smaller than a traditional light microscope.  Light microscopes can see objects as small as 100 &ndash; 200 nm (e.g. most bacteria can be seen under a light microscope, but viruses are usually too small to be seen with a light microscope) however, AFM can see objects as small as individual atoms!   The AFM works by tapping on objects with a small probe.  The best analogy is a blind person who taps a cane around in order to discern his/her surroundings.  In the same way, the AFM can tap on small objects such as viruses and literally feel them.  AFM can tell a scientist not only what something looks like, but also if it is hard or soft, or sticky or squishy.     To give just one example of the usefulness of this device: it has recently been discovered using AFM that some cancer cells are significantly softer than normal cells, even though they look similar to  normal cells.  The ability to distinguish between normal and cancerous cells will be very helpful to scientists who are trying to understand (and eventually cure) cancer.   The research that I am conducting is primarily focused around building a better microscope.  I want to help build the enabling technology that allows others to more easily use and understand the AFM.  To this end, I used money from this NSF grant to spend a summer conducting research with Professors Hirofumi Yamada and Kei Kobayashi at Kyoto University in Japan.  The researchers at this lab are well known for their research in AFM.   In particular, I worked on an AFM method called photothermal excitation.  The mechanical probe used in AFM must be vibrated up and down so that it can tap on the sample object.  Photothermal excitation is one method for doing this, which involves heating the probe up with a laser until it bends.  Because the probe is very small, it heats up quickly, so by turning the laser on and off repeatedly, the probe can be made to vibrate.  This is a simple method with many desirable qualities, but unfortunately the efficiency is low.  This means that a relatively high powered laser must be used.  Sometimes excess laser light can spill over the edge of the probe and damage sensitive samples.  During my stay in Kyoto, the researchers there and I were able to refine a method to increase the efficiency of photothermal excitation.  This allows the use of the photothermal method with a significantly lower powered laser, opening this method up for use with sensitive samples.   During the course of my stay in Japan, I have also built connections and relationship with other researchers.  This has led to two other international collaborations on different projects.          Last Modified: 06/23/2011       Submitted by: Daniel R Kiracofe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
