<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Novel attractants for the Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will provide better attractants for the Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri. D. citri vectors citrus greening disease and is thus the most serious pest faced by the US citrus industry. The pest already has severely affected Florida citrus production, has entered Texas, and is spreading into California, yet no accurate means of assessing population densities or range exist due to a lack of effective attractants for use in bait stations and traps. The approach described uses rational design to isolate compounds that bind to critical psyllid chemosensory proteins, and then identifies those compounds capable of attracting psyllids. This project incorporates several novel platform technologies comprising a high-throughput assay system for rapidly identifying molecules that interact with insect chemosensory proteins.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project are platform technologies applicable to the development of control products for insect pest species of economic, agricultural, or medicinal significance. No psyllid attractant currently exists; traps used for psyllids rely solely on color and are ineffective in gathering reliable population density or range data. A trap utilizing an effective attractant would benefit the citrus industry since it would yield data useful in monitoring the psyllid and in generating control strategies. Key market players include the current manufacturers of colored sticky traps; however, the attractant proposed could be incorporated into these traps, creating a highly effective end product with a very high market demand. Citrus growers have already expressed their keen interest in purchasing such a product.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1014283</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Woods</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel F Woods</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dan@inscent.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9499553129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000152621</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Inscent, Inc</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926146387</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9499553129</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>17905 Sky Park Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE P]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020040486</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INSCENT INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Inscent, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926146387</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17905 Sky Park Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1167</Code>
<Text>MULTIDISCIPLINARY BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Asian citrus psyllid (ACP), Diaphorina citri, is an invading pest species that has reached the United States from countries in Asia, the Indian Ocean and the Persian Gulf. D. citri vectors Huanglongbing (HLB), or citrus greening disease, and has caused severe damage to citrus crops in affected areas. HLB causes chlorosis with yellow shoots, sparse foliage, leaf mottling, stunted tree growth, foliage loss and fruit loss. Infected trees produce smaller, abnormally shaped and colored, harder, and bitter fruit. Nearly all citrus species and hybrids are susceptible to HLB and the disease devastates affected groves. HLB can kill young trees within two years, and infected trees soon become non-productive and ultimately require replacement. <br /><br />The psyllid is now in California according to USDA and CDFA data, and has been found on trees in Southern California as well as in floral shipments from Mexico and curry leaf shipments from Hawaii. One key limitation in controlling HLB is the lack of effective traps to monitor psyllid populations, as demonstrated by the recent discovery of psyllids in Los Angeles that are thought to have been present for several years; in fact, existing monitoring programs rely heavily on yellow card traps that lack chemosensory means to attract psyllids.<br /><br />The current state of the art in HLB control is difficult to implement, comprising the replacement of infected cultures with clean stock, the thorough elimination of any sources of inoculum, fastidious control of psyllid populations on non-crop species in order to avoid disease vector reservoirs, and judicious use of pesticides to control psyllid populations on crop cultures. However, it should be noted that despite all these efforts, to our knowledge no reports exist of a location where HLB has been successfully managed, much less eradicated. HLB is thus a very serious disease that can truly limit citrus production. <br /><br />This project has focused on the development of novel psyllid attractants intended to facilitate better trapping methods for both monitoring programs and future bait-and-kill stations in order to gain a better understanding of the extent of psyllid infestation while facilitating an effective population control strategy. The strategy employed highlights a series of transformative platform technologies that target specific components of the insect chemosensory system for control product development and then use rational design to rapidly isolate novel control compounds. <br /><br />The insect chemosensory system is responsible for allowing the insect to detect crucial scents and odors from the environment, and thus controls important aspects of insect behavior including feeding, mating, etc. We and other laboratories have established that interfering with the insect chemosensory system by using compounds that bind to the proteins making up the system can alter insect behavior, resulting in attraction, repulsion, or other effects. We have therefore isolated protein components of the psyllid chemosensory system in the laboratory and screened combinatorial chemical libraries for compounds capable of binding to these chemosensory proteins; the compounds that do bind the proteins are then screened for behavioral effects on living psyllids. During the course of this project we isolated hundreds of compounds, used computer modeling and structural analyses to group them into families based on their composition, and eliminated those compounds predicted to pose health threats. <br /><br />Compounds selected in this manner are now being evaluated for attractant effects on living psyllids under controlled conditions. This project has therefore resulted in development work focusing on novel control products for a very dangerous invading pest species. Moreover, this project highlights the platform technologies and methodologies necessary to quickly develop control prod...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Asian citrus psyllid (ACP), Diaphorina citri, is an invading pest species that has reached the United States from countries in Asia, the Indian Ocean and the Persian Gulf. D. citri vectors Huanglongbing (HLB), or citrus greening disease, and has caused severe damage to citrus crops in affected areas. HLB causes chlorosis with yellow shoots, sparse foliage, leaf mottling, stunted tree growth, foliage loss and fruit loss. Infected trees produce smaller, abnormally shaped and colored, harder, and bitter fruit. Nearly all citrus species and hybrids are susceptible to HLB and the disease devastates affected groves. HLB can kill young trees within two years, and infected trees soon become non-productive and ultimately require replacement.   The psyllid is now in California according to USDA and CDFA data, and has been found on trees in Southern California as well as in floral shipments from Mexico and curry leaf shipments from Hawaii. One key limitation in controlling HLB is the lack of effective traps to monitor psyllid populations, as demonstrated by the recent discovery of psyllids in Los Angeles that are thought to have been present for several years; in fact, existing monitoring programs rely heavily on yellow card traps that lack chemosensory means to attract psyllids.  The current state of the art in HLB control is difficult to implement, comprising the replacement of infected cultures with clean stock, the thorough elimination of any sources of inoculum, fastidious control of psyllid populations on non-crop species in order to avoid disease vector reservoirs, and judicious use of pesticides to control psyllid populations on crop cultures. However, it should be noted that despite all these efforts, to our knowledge no reports exist of a location where HLB has been successfully managed, much less eradicated. HLB is thus a very serious disease that can truly limit citrus production.   This project has focused on the development of novel psyllid attractants intended to facilitate better trapping methods for both monitoring programs and future bait-and-kill stations in order to gain a better understanding of the extent of psyllid infestation while facilitating an effective population control strategy. The strategy employed highlights a series of transformative platform technologies that target specific components of the insect chemosensory system for control product development and then use rational design to rapidly isolate novel control compounds.   The insect chemosensory system is responsible for allowing the insect to detect crucial scents and odors from the environment, and thus controls important aspects of insect behavior including feeding, mating, etc. We and other laboratories have established that interfering with the insect chemosensory system by using compounds that bind to the proteins making up the system can alter insect behavior, resulting in attraction, repulsion, or other effects. We have therefore isolated protein components of the psyllid chemosensory system in the laboratory and screened combinatorial chemical libraries for compounds capable of binding to these chemosensory proteins; the compounds that do bind the proteins are then screened for behavioral effects on living psyllids. During the course of this project we isolated hundreds of compounds, used computer modeling and structural analyses to group them into families based on their composition, and eliminated those compounds predicted to pose health threats.   Compounds selected in this manner are now being evaluated for attractant effects on living psyllids under controlled conditions. This project has therefore resulted in development work focusing on novel control products for a very dangerous invading pest species. Moreover, this project highlights the platform technologies and methodologies necessary to quickly develop control products for other pest species, be they pre-existing or newly-introduced insects. Thus, the work described here is ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
