<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Biodiversity and Evolution of Entomopathogenic Fungi in China</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015717</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Quandt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A Quandt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5417375284</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553137</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Owensby                 Catherine      A</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973306007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Owensby                 Catherine      A]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973306007</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As climate change continues to greatly impact our planet and the populations of organisms inhabiting it, there has never been a more important time to document biodiversity.&nbsp; Through my research, I am trying to add to our understanding and documentation of fungal biodiversity, and build upon the recent efforts to elucidate their evolutionary relationships.&nbsp; Fungi play key roles in all ecologies (e.g. ectomycorrhizae in forests, molds in decomposition), human society (e.g. yeasts in food and alcohol production), and also in their production of secondary metabolites that humans have used as antibiotics, anticoagulants, and recreational drugs among other things.&nbsp; Without knowing the diversity of organisms that exist, how they are related to one another, and what genes they have, it will be impossible to find novel substances that could improve human life.&nbsp; To address this need and through the funding of this EAPSI fellowship, I collected <em>Cordyceps</em>-like fungi in 4 provinces of China.&nbsp; There are over 500 species of <em>Cordyceps</em>-like organsims, many of which are insect pathogens.&nbsp; Through my work, I have collected genetic data for many of these species (which were previously unsampled), and used this data to create evolutionary trees in order to understand the relationships between these species.&nbsp; These analyses will enable the recognition of characters useful for further ecological and evolutionary investigation.&nbsp; Personally, I collected more than 60 specimens while in China, representing more than 30 different <em>Cordyceps</em>-like species, extracted DNA from all these, took over 1000 images (including macroscopic photos in the field and microscopic images in the laboratory), and recorded important collection information such as locality, host, and ecological niche, and added this to our growing database of information about these fungi.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; There have been many broader impacts through my work.&nbsp; Since returning from China, I have helped train a visiting graduate student from Colombia in the techniques I employ both in the lab doing genetic analyses and computationally in creating phylogenetic trees.&nbsp; &nbsp;Also, through a Saturday program called &ldquo;Winter Wonderings&rdquo; in Corvallis, OR, I taught elementary school children about fungi and their importance in our world.&nbsp; In this program, I showed students photos of the <em>Cordyceps</em> I collected in China, brought in preserved specimens, and created stations to expose students to fungal diversity, lichen symbioses, and the role of fungi in our forests.&nbsp; Many of these students were fascinated not just by the fungi, but also the prospect that a career in science could include doing research in another part of the world.&nbsp; I was also invited to give a presentation to the North American Truffling Society, based in Corvallis, about my field work collecting <em>Cordyceps</em> in China.&nbsp; This was a particularly valuable experience, in which I could share not just the diversity of organisms I encountered in a relatively short period of time, but also meet community members with whom I&rsquo;ve set up potential collaborations for collecting certain <em>Cordyceps</em>-like fungi which are very rare here in Oregon.&nbsp; In addition to these, with much of the data and images I collected in China, I have spent a considerable amount of time further developing the electronic monograph of <em>Cordyceps</em>-like organisms, <a href="http://cordyceps.us/">http://cordyceps.us</a>. This website was created by the Spatafora lab at Oregon State University, and it is an important means of disseminating current and accurate information and images of these fascinating fungi to a wide audience.&nbsp; As our society relies more and more upon web-based r...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As climate change continues to greatly impact our planet and the populations of organisms inhabiting it, there has never been a more important time to document biodiversity.  Through my research, I am trying to add to our understanding and documentation of fungal biodiversity, and build upon the recent efforts to elucidate their evolutionary relationships.  Fungi play key roles in all ecologies (e.g. ectomycorrhizae in forests, molds in decomposition), human society (e.g. yeasts in food and alcohol production), and also in their production of secondary metabolites that humans have used as antibiotics, anticoagulants, and recreational drugs among other things.  Without knowing the diversity of organisms that exist, how they are related to one another, and what genes they have, it will be impossible to find novel substances that could improve human life.  To address this need and through the funding of this EAPSI fellowship, I collected Cordyceps-like fungi in 4 provinces of China.  There are over 500 species of Cordyceps-like organsims, many of which are insect pathogens.  Through my work, I have collected genetic data for many of these species (which were previously unsampled), and used this data to create evolutionary trees in order to understand the relationships between these species.  These analyses will enable the recognition of characters useful for further ecological and evolutionary investigation.  Personally, I collected more than 60 specimens while in China, representing more than 30 different Cordyceps-like species, extracted DNA from all these, took over 1000 images (including macroscopic photos in the field and microscopic images in the laboratory), and recorded important collection information such as locality, host, and ecological niche, and added this to our growing database of information about these fungi.                   There have been many broader impacts through my work.  Since returning from China, I have helped train a visiting graduate student from Colombia in the techniques I employ both in the lab doing genetic analyses and computationally in creating phylogenetic trees.   Also, through a Saturday program called "Winter Wonderings" in Corvallis, OR, I taught elementary school children about fungi and their importance in our world.  In this program, I showed students photos of the Cordyceps I collected in China, brought in preserved specimens, and created stations to expose students to fungal diversity, lichen symbioses, and the role of fungi in our forests.  Many of these students were fascinated not just by the fungi, but also the prospect that a career in science could include doing research in another part of the world.  I was also invited to give a presentation to the North American Truffling Society, based in Corvallis, about my field work collecting Cordyceps in China.  This was a particularly valuable experience, in which I could share not just the diversity of organisms I encountered in a relatively short period of time, but also meet community members with whom IÆve set up potential collaborations for collecting certain Cordyceps-like fungi which are very rare here in Oregon.  In addition to these, with much of the data and images I collected in China, I have spent a considerable amount of time further developing the electronic monograph of Cordyceps-like organisms, http://cordyceps.us. This website was created by the Spatafora lab at Oregon State University, and it is an important means of disseminating current and accurate information and images of these fascinating fungi to a wide audience.  As our society relies more and more upon web-based resources, it is imperative to make scientific findings available electronically, and this website succeeds in doing just that.       Last Modified: 06/30/2011       Submitted by: Catherine A Owensby]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
