<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  China Looking Ahead: Projecting the Ecological Effects of a Growing Transportation Infrastructure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015241</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>dorsey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>p</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>benjamin p dorsey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>4066001230</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>dorsey                  benjamin       p</Name>
<CityName>bozeman</CityName>
<ZipCode>597710000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[dorsey                  benjamin       p]]></Name>
<CityName>bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597710000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>I reviewed the published impacts of surface transportation infrastructure on wildlife and compared that to the 10 year national road development plan in China. From that review, I created a poster presentation shown at the ICOET 2011 conference in Seattle, WA. It focused on China&rsquo;s wild primates, many of which have disappeared or are decreasing rapidly. The remaining populations are found in lesser developed regions with low road density and low per-capita vehicle ownership. Many of these areas are building infrastructure to foster economic development and alleviate poverty.</p> <p>In China and other countries such as Brazil, and India with high primate endemism; enormous economic and societal shifts are occurring. These three countries hold over a fourth of the world&rsquo;s primate species, 76 of which are listed as Threatened by the IUCN and 11 as Critically Endangered. Here unprecedented increases in infrastructure development and vehicle ownership are occurring which will likely further threaten non-human primates and counteract efforts to curtail poaching and deforestation. Similarly, Klaus Toepfer, executive director of the United Nations Environment Program said in 2002: "Roads are being built in the few remaining pristine forests of Africa and South East Asia to extract timber, minerals and oil. Uncontrolled road construction in these areas is fragmenting and destroying the great apes' last homes and making it easier for poachers to slaughter them for meat and their young more vulnerable to capture for the illegal pet trade".</p> <p>China provides a relevant example, with the highest growth rate of vehicle ownership (10.6% annually) followed by India (7%) and Indonesia (6.5%). By 2030, China will have 269 vehicles per 1000 people resulting in 390 million vehicles on the road. China has the most impervious road surface (87,182 square kilometers) with Brazil and India second only to the United States. The Chinese Ministry of Transport plans to complete a 85,000 kilometer expressway network and a national railway network of over120,000 km in the next twenty years.</p> <p>For the poster, I evaluated national trends in transportation, social behavior, and economic growth for China, Brazil, and India to project and rank pressures in the coming decades on non-human primate species. Pressures were identified from a literature review of the impacts of transportation on primates, including roads and railways then grouped into four categories. I highlighted regions within each country and species likely affected so that location specific approaches can be investigated to balance human and non-human needs. Lastly, I described in more detail projected transportation pressures on China&rsquo;s primate species in the south-western provinces.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/18/2012<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;P&nbsp;Dorsey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ I reviewed the published impacts of surface transportation infrastructure on wildlife and compared that to the 10 year national road development plan in China. From that review, I created a poster presentation shown at the ICOET 2011 conference in Seattle, WA. It focused on ChinaÆs wild primates, many of which have disappeared or are decreasing rapidly. The remaining populations are found in lesser developed regions with low road density and low per-capita vehicle ownership. Many of these areas are building infrastructure to foster economic development and alleviate poverty.  In China and other countries such as Brazil, and India with high primate endemism; enormous economic and societal shifts are occurring. These three countries hold over a fourth of the worldÆs primate species, 76 of which are listed as Threatened by the IUCN and 11 as Critically Endangered. Here unprecedented increases in infrastructure development and vehicle ownership are occurring which will likely further threaten non-human primates and counteract efforts to curtail poaching and deforestation. Similarly, Klaus Toepfer, executive director of the United Nations Environment Program said in 2002: "Roads are being built in the few remaining pristine forests of Africa and South East Asia to extract timber, minerals and oil. Uncontrolled road construction in these areas is fragmenting and destroying the great apes' last homes and making it easier for poachers to slaughter them for meat and their young more vulnerable to capture for the illegal pet trade".  China provides a relevant example, with the highest growth rate of vehicle ownership (10.6% annually) followed by India (7%) and Indonesia (6.5%). By 2030, China will have 269 vehicles per 1000 people resulting in 390 million vehicles on the road. China has the most impervious road surface (87,182 square kilometers) with Brazil and India second only to the United States. The Chinese Ministry of Transport plans to complete a 85,000 kilometer expressway network and a national railway network of over120,000 km in the next twenty years.  For the poster, I evaluated national trends in transportation, social behavior, and economic growth for China, Brazil, and India to project and rank pressures in the coming decades on non-human primate species. Pressures were identified from a literature review of the impacts of transportation on primates, including roads and railways then grouped into four categories. I highlighted regions within each country and species likely affected so that location specific approaches can be investigated to balance human and non-human needs. Lastly, I described in more detail projected transportation pressures on ChinaÆs primate species in the south-western provinces.          Last Modified: 09/18/2012       Submitted by: Benjamin P Dorsey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
