<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Impacts of global change on the magnitude of variation of annual phenological events for P. yedoensis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015324</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rose</FirstName>
<LastName>Abramoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rose Z Abramoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8585310176</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000551298</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Abramoff                Rose           Z</Name>
<CityName>Allston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021342631</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Abramoff                Rose           Z]]></Name>
<CityName>Allston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021342631</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The EAPSI program funded me to work with Hiromi Kobori in her lab at Tokyo City University during the summer of 2010. In the Primack lab at Boston University, I study the seasonal timing of plants and their response to urbanization. For this project I wanted to look at the affect of warmer temperatures and urbanization on cherry trees in Japan using a large data set of first flowering dates. First I attempted to define an appropriate urban impact area. We established three different rural-to-urban gradients on three different latitude lines, including the following cities: 1) Matsumoto, Maebashi, Kumagaya, Utsunomiya, Mito; 2) Iida, Kofu, Choshi, Yokohama, Tokyo; 3) Hamamatsu, Shizuoka, Tateyama, Oshima. However, after creating plots of the variation of flowering for cherry trees in these cities, I found the variation to be too small to make statistically significant comparisons with weather data.</p> <p>I then changed my project to look at another organism that is very sensitive to changes in temperature and urbanization and is also important to Japanese culture &ndash; the dragonfly. The dragonfly has always been an important symbol in Japanese culture. Like butterflies and fireflies, the dragonfly and damselfly are popular charismatic species. Dragonflies are also valued for their links to the satoyama, a traditional Japanese agricultural landscape composed of many different semi-natural habitats, which include ponds and other small waterways, secondary forests and grasslands as well as rice paddy fields. Satoyama are rich in biodiversity as a result of the mosaic structure of the landscape and intermediate ecological disturbance caused by humans during the process of rice farming and are an ideal habitat for many dragonfly species.</p> <p>While several studies have focused on the habitat preferences of the dragonflies I studied, few have looked at their habitat preferences in a highly urbanized setting like Yokohama Bay. In 2003 the Yokohama city government established a conservation project to create approximately 160 urban habitats for dragonflies, involving many local industries in the creation and management of dragonfly habitats in urban Yokohama. During my summer in Japan, I participated in a large community event in which scientists and community volunteers monitored dragonflies at 10 of these restored habitats, within a 3.3 km x 5.2 km area of urban coastal zone surrounding Yokohama Bay. The size of these ponds ranged from 20 to 235 m<sup>2</sup> with an average water surface area of 96 m<sup>2</sup>. Participants caught a total of 619 dragonflies representing 10 species. The most common species were <em>Orthetrum triangulare melania, Orthetrum albistylum speciosum, </em>and<em> Crocothemis servilia,</em> respectively known as the Greater Blue Skimmer, the Common Skimmer, and the Scarlet Skimmer. Only one dragonfly, the Scarlet Skimmer<em>,</em> migrated from one pond to another with the distance of 1.3 km.</p> <p>We noted relevant habitat characteristics at these ponds in order to determine the habitat preferences of urban dragonflies. We looked at water surface area, distance to other habitats and reserves, water depth, concentration of nutrients, exposure to sunlight, and vegetation cover and type. The habitat characteristics that created the most successful habitats with a high abundance and diversity of dragonflies were distance to large natural reserves, distance to nearby ponds, large water surface area, high nutrient concentrations, and large surrounding grasslands. Many dragonflies are heavily dependent on green areas, especially grasslands and rice paddies.</p> <p>There are some obstacles specific to this program that apply to conservation programs generally, such as motivation of the private sector and community participation. There is no ordinance that defines necessary upkeep, so maintenance of habitats depends on a consistent stream of int...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The EAPSI program funded me to work with Hiromi Kobori in her lab at Tokyo City University during the summer of 2010. In the Primack lab at Boston University, I study the seasonal timing of plants and their response to urbanization. For this project I wanted to look at the affect of warmer temperatures and urbanization on cherry trees in Japan using a large data set of first flowering dates. First I attempted to define an appropriate urban impact area. We established three different rural-to-urban gradients on three different latitude lines, including the following cities: 1) Matsumoto, Maebashi, Kumagaya, Utsunomiya, Mito; 2) Iida, Kofu, Choshi, Yokohama, Tokyo; 3) Hamamatsu, Shizuoka, Tateyama, Oshima. However, after creating plots of the variation of flowering for cherry trees in these cities, I found the variation to be too small to make statistically significant comparisons with weather data.  I then changed my project to look at another organism that is very sensitive to changes in temperature and urbanization and is also important to Japanese culture &ndash; the dragonfly. The dragonfly has always been an important symbol in Japanese culture. Like butterflies and fireflies, the dragonfly and damselfly are popular charismatic species. Dragonflies are also valued for their links to the satoyama, a traditional Japanese agricultural landscape composed of many different semi-natural habitats, which include ponds and other small waterways, secondary forests and grasslands as well as rice paddy fields. Satoyama are rich in biodiversity as a result of the mosaic structure of the landscape and intermediate ecological disturbance caused by humans during the process of rice farming and are an ideal habitat for many dragonfly species.  While several studies have focused on the habitat preferences of the dragonflies I studied, few have looked at their habitat preferences in a highly urbanized setting like Yokohama Bay. In 2003 the Yokohama city government established a conservation project to create approximately 160 urban habitats for dragonflies, involving many local industries in the creation and management of dragonfly habitats in urban Yokohama. During my summer in Japan, I participated in a large community event in which scientists and community volunteers monitored dragonflies at 10 of these restored habitats, within a 3.3 km x 5.2 km area of urban coastal zone surrounding Yokohama Bay. The size of these ponds ranged from 20 to 235 m2 with an average water surface area of 96 m2. Participants caught a total of 619 dragonflies representing 10 species. The most common species were Orthetrum triangulare melania, Orthetrum albistylum speciosum, and Crocothemis servilia, respectively known as the Greater Blue Skimmer, the Common Skimmer, and the Scarlet Skimmer. Only one dragonfly, the Scarlet Skimmer, migrated from one pond to another with the distance of 1.3 km.  We noted relevant habitat characteristics at these ponds in order to determine the habitat preferences of urban dragonflies. We looked at water surface area, distance to other habitats and reserves, water depth, concentration of nutrients, exposure to sunlight, and vegetation cover and type. The habitat characteristics that created the most successful habitats with a high abundance and diversity of dragonflies were distance to large natural reserves, distance to nearby ponds, large water surface area, high nutrient concentrations, and large surrounding grasslands. Many dragonflies are heavily dependent on green areas, especially grasslands and rice paddies.  There are some obstacles specific to this program that apply to conservation programs generally, such as motivation of the private sector and community participation. There is no ordinance that defines necessary upkeep, so maintenance of habitats depends on a consistent stream of interested community members or volunteers from the parent company or school in which the pond was built. Because of community neglect, so...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
