<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Single-Molecule Conductance Measurements of Silanes for the Design of More Efficient Solar Energy and Fuel Cell Technologies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015722</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Wood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marissa Wood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8018307906</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000554112</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wood                    Marissa</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981194903</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wood                    Marissa]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981194903</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Building electronic circuits out of individual molecules has attracted much attention in recent years. As the demand for smaller electronic components continues to rise, molecular building blocks represent the ultimate miniaturization limit.&nbsp; Utilizing molecules allows for precise control over component properties, but choosing the right ones is critical to effective performance.&nbsp; Knowing the conductance through different molecules is thus extremely important to making selections that will optimize the system and enable maximum control over electronic circuits.&nbsp; However, due to the small size and spatial confinement of a single molecule attached to two electrodes, measuring its electronic conductance is quite challenging.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; National Taiwan University in Taipei, Taiwan is a premier institution for cutting-edge scientific research.&nbsp; Dr. Chun-hsien Chen, a professor in the Chemistry Department, has had considerable experience measuring the single-molecule conductance of various organic molecules to determine how different molecular properties affect electron transfer.&nbsp; Dr. Chen&rsquo;s research group is at the forefront of this field, allowing me to learn from many distinguished graduate student and post-doctoral researchers who contributed individual expertise and knowledge.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; One of the key factors influencing conductance is the molecule-electrode interface, which is greatly affected by the identities of both the molecule and electrodes.&nbsp; While many different molecules have been investigated, the most commonly studied system has been saturated carbon chains with various terminal groups between two gold electrodes.&nbsp; Using silver electrodes instead should have a significant effect on the conductance, since silver has different electrical properties than gold. We focused on dicarboxylic acid-terminated alkanes, which have been studied previously on gold substrates.&nbsp; We used atomic force microscopy (AFM) to measure the single-molecule conductance of dicarboxylic acid-terminated alkanes of three different lengths on a silver substrate to gain a better understanding of how molecule-electrode interfaces and chain length affect conductance. The conductive silver AFM tip was used to grab one end of a molecule and pull it into a vertical configuration while the other end remained attached to the silver surface on which it was originally placed.&nbsp; The molecule was thus anchored between two electrodes, enabling conductance measurements across the molecule.&nbsp; The fundamental conductance for each molecule length was determined from multiple trials, and it was found that the silver surface greatly enhances the conductance through the molecule when compared to results for the same molecule on a gold surface.&nbsp; When compared to results obtained using alkanes with dithiol rather than carboxylic acid headgroups, it was found that headgroup identity does make an important difference, with the dicarboxylic acid/silver interface producing a higher conductance than the dithiol/gold interface.&nbsp; The cause of this increased conductance has yet to be determined, but it could be due to the lower work function of silver and specific binding properties at the headgroup-electrode interface.&nbsp; In addition, shorter carbon chains were found to increase the conductance, which was consistent with past experiments.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Future work will focus on determining how the conformation of the molecule changes over time.&nbsp; These changes can influence how the molecule binds to the surface and may have a significant effect on conductance.&nbsp; Other conductive surfaces such as copper will also be investigated to better understand the nature of the electrode-molecule interface.&nb...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[        Building electronic circuits out of individual molecules has attracted much attention in recent years. As the demand for smaller electronic components continues to rise, molecular building blocks represent the ultimate miniaturization limit.  Utilizing molecules allows for precise control over component properties, but choosing the right ones is critical to effective performance.  Knowing the conductance through different molecules is thus extremely important to making selections that will optimize the system and enable maximum control over electronic circuits.  However, due to the small size and spatial confinement of a single molecule attached to two electrodes, measuring its electronic conductance is quite challenging.         National Taiwan University in Taipei, Taiwan is a premier institution for cutting-edge scientific research.  Dr. Chun-hsien Chen, a professor in the Chemistry Department, has had considerable experience measuring the single-molecule conductance of various organic molecules to determine how different molecular properties affect electron transfer.  Dr. ChenÆs research group is at the forefront of this field, allowing me to learn from many distinguished graduate student and post-doctoral researchers who contributed individual expertise and knowledge.          One of the key factors influencing conductance is the molecule-electrode interface, which is greatly affected by the identities of both the molecule and electrodes.  While many different molecules have been investigated, the most commonly studied system has been saturated carbon chains with various terminal groups between two gold electrodes.  Using silver electrodes instead should have a significant effect on the conductance, since silver has different electrical properties than gold. We focused on dicarboxylic acid-terminated alkanes, which have been studied previously on gold substrates.  We used atomic force microscopy (AFM) to measure the single-molecule conductance of dicarboxylic acid-terminated alkanes of three different lengths on a silver substrate to gain a better understanding of how molecule-electrode interfaces and chain length affect conductance. The conductive silver AFM tip was used to grab one end of a molecule and pull it into a vertical configuration while the other end remained attached to the silver surface on which it was originally placed.  The molecule was thus anchored between two electrodes, enabling conductance measurements across the molecule.  The fundamental conductance for each molecule length was determined from multiple trials, and it was found that the silver surface greatly enhances the conductance through the molecule when compared to results for the same molecule on a gold surface.  When compared to results obtained using alkanes with dithiol rather than carboxylic acid headgroups, it was found that headgroup identity does make an important difference, with the dicarboxylic acid/silver interface producing a higher conductance than the dithiol/gold interface.  The cause of this increased conductance has yet to be determined, but it could be due to the lower work function of silver and specific binding properties at the headgroup-electrode interface.  In addition, shorter carbon chains were found to increase the conductance, which was consistent with past experiments.          Future work will focus on determining how the conformation of the molecule changes over time.  These changes can influence how the molecule binds to the surface and may have a significant effect on conductance.  Other conductive surfaces such as copper will also be investigated to better understand the nature of the electrode-molecule interface.  This research has further illuminated the importance of electrode and headgroup identity on molecular conductance and represents one of many critical steps toward better understanding and correlating these factors with observed effects.  This knowledge is crucial to the realization of molecu...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
