<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Wrapping Targets with a Casting Manipulator</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5877.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5877</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015195</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ross</FirstName>
<LastName>Hatton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ross L Hatton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5477371129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000549789</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hatton                  Ross           L</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hatton                  Ross           L]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5877</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The EAPSI program is designed to combine good technical research with networking and cultural experiences that train researchers to operate in international environments.</p> <p>The technical side of my work on this program had the goal of getting robots to perform the "Indiana Jones" trick of wrapping a whip around a target object. Such capability will allow robots to navigate through challenging environments, and also serves as a good outreach platform for exciting students about engineering research. During the program, I analyzed the physics of the whip wrapping around a target and established performance characteristics like the minimum speed the whip must move with to successfully wrap the target. The physics model I developed visually agrees with experiments we carried out with a robotic arm, and the host laboratory in Japan is currently developing more detailed experiments to further validate the model.</p> <p>Participating in the EAPSI program has greatly expanded my network of professional contacts. I spent most of the summer at one of the main Japanese national laboratories, and worked closely with several top robotics researchers there. I also had the opportunity to give talks at many universities and research labs, which both introduced me to other researchers and broadened my awareness of the state of the art in Japanese robotics.</p> <p>Culturally, the program gave me the opportunity to live in Japan for an extended period of time and become attuned to the local customs. As Japan is a major player in robotics and I intend to continue work in this field, I will be able to draw on these cultural experiences in future research collaborations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2010<br>      Modified by: Ross&nbsp;L&nbsp;Hatton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The EAPSI program is designed to combine good technical research with networking and cultural experiences that train researchers to operate in international environments.  The technical side of my work on this program had the goal of getting robots to perform the "Indiana Jones" trick of wrapping a whip around a target object. Such capability will allow robots to navigate through challenging environments, and also serves as a good outreach platform for exciting students about engineering research. During the program, I analyzed the physics of the whip wrapping around a target and established performance characteristics like the minimum speed the whip must move with to successfully wrap the target. The physics model I developed visually agrees with experiments we carried out with a robotic arm, and the host laboratory in Japan is currently developing more detailed experiments to further validate the model.  Participating in the EAPSI program has greatly expanded my network of professional contacts. I spent most of the summer at one of the main Japanese national laboratories, and worked closely with several top robotics researchers there. I also had the opportunity to give talks at many universities and research labs, which both introduced me to other researchers and broadened my awareness of the state of the art in Japanese robotics.  Culturally, the program gave me the opportunity to live in Japan for an extended period of time and become attuned to the local customs. As Japan is a major player in robotics and I intend to continue work in this field, I will be able to draw on these cultural experiences in future research collaborations.       Last Modified: 11/15/2010       Submitted by: Ross L Hatton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
