<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Modeling and Simulation of Vehicle Vibration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015593</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenjun</FirstName>
<LastName>Gu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenjun Gu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2023196671</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000551441</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gu                      Wenjun</Name>
<CityName>potomac</CityName>
<ZipCode>208544078</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gu                      Wenjun]]></Name>
<CityName>potomac</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>208544078</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>1</strong><strong>?INTRODUCTION</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The research in pavement design and infrastructure management has been growing rapidly in recent years. The nation&rsquo;s investment in transportation infrastructure (highways, bridges, railways, airports) amounts to over $7 trillion by 2009. From a pavement design point of view, pavement response, damage and performance are essentially the result of long-term vehicle-pavement interaction (VPI). Also?VPI has a profound impact on infrastructure management, vehicle suspension design and transportation economy. There is no question that there is a great and urgent need for fundamental research on VPI due to rapid deterioration of huge highway infrastructure nationwide, tight maintenance budget and the key role played by VPI.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Currently National Science Foundation is sponsoring a CAREER project (CMMI-0644552, from 2007.1-2011.12) entitled &ldquo;Stochastic and Dynamic Interaction of Vehicle-Pavement Systems and Its Applications to Transportation Infrastructure&rdquo;. As a member of the research team working on this CAREER project, I am responsible for conducting the modeling of vehicle suspension systems and simulation of vehicle vibration. Therefore, in this EAPSI project, I, as a principal investigator, conducted the related research activities during this summer in China to bring additional benefit to the existing CAREER project.<strong></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>2. RESEARCH METHODOLOGIES</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Two approaches are commonly used for the study of vehicle vibration: experimental measurements and computer simulation. Experimental measurements offer real and valuable results, but they are very costly and limited by safety requirements. Moreover, results obtained from measurements are testing condition dependent.</p> <p class="Preformatted">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Computer simulation is a more popular and viable approach and has been successfully used in railway, automobile and air transportation industries for years.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This EAPSI project took advantages of both approaches for studying vehicle random vibration using computer simulation (primary method) and field experiments (secondary method) to verify and validate simulation results. This combination provides a cost-effective means. <strong></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>3. PROJECT OUTCOMES, INTELLECTUAL MERIT AND BROADER IMPACT</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This eight-week project was organized in three tasks:</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp; Modeling and simulation of steady state and transient vehicle vibration</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp; Survey vehicle suspension systems and configurations</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;&nbsp; Developing a software toolkit for automated modeling and simulation of vehicle vibration</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The first two tasks have been completed and the third one is software development which is in the process of testing and validation.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The EAPSI project is an integrated and interdisciplinary research effort including methodological, analytical, numerical and experimental work across the spectrum of vehicle vibration and computer simulation. It adds new scientific knowledge to the subject by providing better understanding of VPI, and a foundation for developing a far-sighted research program with long reach. Particularly, the main outcome is the development of a software toolkit to automate modeling and simulation of vehicle vibration and to analyze dynamic pavement response under various dynamic loads with real data of vehicle suspension systems and configuration from automobile industry. The engineeri...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 1?INTRODUCTION           The research in pavement design and infrastructure management has been growing rapidly in recent years. The nationÆs investment in transportation infrastructure (highways, bridges, railways, airports) amounts to over $7 trillion by 2009. From a pavement design point of view, pavement response, damage and performance are essentially the result of long-term vehicle-pavement interaction (VPI). Also?VPI has a profound impact on infrastructure management, vehicle suspension design and transportation economy. There is no question that there is a great and urgent need for fundamental research on VPI due to rapid deterioration of huge highway infrastructure nationwide, tight maintenance budget and the key role played by VPI.          Currently National Science Foundation is sponsoring a CAREER project (CMMI-0644552, from 2007.1-2011.12) entitled "Stochastic and Dynamic Interaction of Vehicle-Pavement Systems and Its Applications to Transportation Infrastructure". As a member of the research team working on this CAREER project, I am responsible for conducting the modeling of vehicle suspension systems and simulation of vehicle vibration. Therefore, in this EAPSI project, I, as a principal investigator, conducted the related research activities during this summer in China to bring additional benefit to the existing CAREER project.     2. RESEARCH METHODOLOGIES           Two approaches are commonly used for the study of vehicle vibration: experimental measurements and computer simulation. Experimental measurements offer real and valuable results, but they are very costly and limited by safety requirements. Moreover, results obtained from measurements are testing condition dependent.         Computer simulation is a more popular and viable approach and has been successfully used in railway, automobile and air transportation industries for years.          This EAPSI project took advantages of both approaches for studying vehicle random vibration using computer simulation (primary method) and field experiments (secondary method) to verify and validate simulation results. This combination provides a cost-effective means.      3. PROJECT OUTCOMES, INTELLECTUAL MERIT AND BROADER IMPACT            This eight-week project was organized in three tasks:  (1)   Modeling and simulation of steady state and transient vehicle vibration  (2)   Survey vehicle suspension systems and configurations  (3)   Developing a software toolkit for automated modeling and simulation of vehicle vibration          The first two tasks have been completed and the third one is software development which is in the process of testing and validation.           The EAPSI project is an integrated and interdisciplinary research effort including methodological, analytical, numerical and experimental work across the spectrum of vehicle vibration and computer simulation. It adds new scientific knowledge to the subject by providing better understanding of VPI, and a foundation for developing a far-sighted research program with long reach. Particularly, the main outcome is the development of a software toolkit to automate modeling and simulation of vehicle vibration and to analyze dynamic pavement response under various dynamic loads with real data of vehicle suspension systems and configuration from automobile industry. The engineering science field would be advanced as a result of this work due to having better models to predict dynamic vehicle response. Moreover, the research will also benefit the nationÆs transportation economy by mitigating vehicle vibration, and therefore the operation and maintenance costs of vehicles and roadways. The methodologies and results of this research can also be borrowed and used for the study of train-railway and aircraft-airfield interactions.             From this project, two journal publications have been made, in which one is scheduled for publication, the other is submitted for re-review.     4. CONCLUSION          ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
