<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:  Microbial Enhancement of Coalbed Methane</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jong-on Hahm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration/>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1015339</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Papendick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel L Papendick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>9702159859</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000548350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Papendick               Samuel         L</Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<ZipCode>577034130</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Papendick               Samuel         L]]></Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>577034130</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5912</Code>
<Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Waking Up the Bugs In Coal</p> <p>Sam Papendick</p> <p><em>South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Because of the environmental challenges associated with coal generated power, "clean" coal technologies are in demand and developing worldwide. Coal is a heterogeneous substance and varies with depositional environment, like every swamp and forest we see today. With such diversity, multiple clean technologies are needed, each tuned to their specific coal source. Microbial Enhanced Coalbed Methane (MECoM) emerged in the mid 90's and uses microorganisms to convert coal to methane by stimulating naturally occurring or freshly introduced "bugs" in the coal, which may have the combined effect of increasing gas reserves and improving production rates.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Methane, the main component of natural gas, is easily transported by pipeline and burns with a fraction the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions of coal. Natural gas can be associated with petroleum or stand alone in sources such as shale or coal. While conventional natural gas can require treatment for hydrogen sulfide or other contaminants, coalbed methane (CBM) is often greater than 90% methane with few impurities. Heat driven gas generation in different reservoirs can produce gas of various composition, but a biological generation of gas often results in high purity. This is the same biological process we are attempting to jump-start.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In 2009, the DOE reported that around 7.5% of US natural gas production was from CBM, and the US led the world in CBM production.&nbsp; However, Australian natural gas production is almost 9% CBM and growing fast, with plans to develop the world&rsquo;s first CBM fed liquefied natural gas (LNG) plant. My advisor at the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, Dr. Patrick Gilcrease, has been collaborating with Dr. Sue Golding, Dr. Victor Rudolph, and Dr. Paul Massarotto at the University of Queensland for about 2 years and brought me on board for a PhD. &nbsp;After receiving a B.S. in Chemical and Biological Engineering from Colorado State University, dubbed The Green University, <em>biofuels</em> was the buzz word with algae or corn-to-ethanol becoming common and saturated terms. When I returned home to South Dakota and organized a chance meeting with Dr. Gilcrease, I was drawn in by the concept of MECoM and the potential to collaborate internationally.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Six months after I started work at SDSM&amp;T, a joint fellowship called the East Asia and Pacific Student Institute (EAPSI) between the Australian Academy of Science (AAS) and the NSF provided an opportunity to travel to Australia for research. &nbsp;Of the two hundred plus US science and math graduate students sent to the East Asia and Pacific countries (China, Japan, Korea, Taiwan, Singapore, Australia, and New Zealand), three were chosen from the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology Department of Chemical and Biological Engineering.&nbsp;Amanda Grill and Tim Shenk were the other two PhD students accepted from SDSM&amp;T; they traveled to Australia and Singapore for their research, respectively.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>EAPSI lasted seven weeks, during&nbsp; which time I designed, built, and troubleshooted a lab capable of culturing the bugs found in coal seams. These bugs, actually a consortium of bacteria and archaeabacteria, are not your typical microorganisms. They only survive as a community by passing molecules between each member and belong to a unique category called strict anaerobes &ndash; meaning they have no tolerance for oxygen. The same microorganisms are responsible for methane produced in cattle rumen or termite guts and are important for processing wastewater treatment facilities. Anaerobic culturing techniques developed for these known systems were applied to our coal system and require three main pieces of equipment; an ana...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Waking Up the Bugs In Coal  Sam Papendick  South Dakota School of Mines and Technology     Because of the environmental challenges associated with coal generated power, "clean" coal technologies are in demand and developing worldwide. Coal is a heterogeneous substance and varies with depositional environment, like every swamp and forest we see today. With such diversity, multiple clean technologies are needed, each tuned to their specific coal source. Microbial Enhanced Coalbed Methane (MECoM) emerged in the mid 90's and uses microorganisms to convert coal to methane by stimulating naturally occurring or freshly introduced "bugs" in the coal, which may have the combined effect of increasing gas reserves and improving production rates.      Methane, the main component of natural gas, is easily transported by pipeline and burns with a fraction the CO2 emissions of coal. Natural gas can be associated with petroleum or stand alone in sources such as shale or coal. While conventional natural gas can require treatment for hydrogen sulfide or other contaminants, coalbed methane (CBM) is often greater than 90% methane with few impurities. Heat driven gas generation in different reservoirs can produce gas of various composition, but a biological generation of gas often results in high purity. This is the same biological process we are attempting to jump-start.      In 2009, the DOE reported that around 7.5% of US natural gas production was from CBM, and the US led the world in CBM production.  However, Australian natural gas production is almost 9% CBM and growing fast, with plans to develop the worldÆs first CBM fed liquefied natural gas (LNG) plant. My advisor at the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, Dr. Patrick Gilcrease, has been collaborating with Dr. Sue Golding, Dr. Victor Rudolph, and Dr. Paul Massarotto at the University of Queensland for about 2 years and brought me on board for a PhD.  After receiving a B.S. in Chemical and Biological Engineering from Colorado State University, dubbed The Green University, biofuels was the buzz word with algae or corn-to-ethanol becoming common and saturated terms. When I returned home to South Dakota and organized a chance meeting with Dr. Gilcrease, I was drawn in by the concept of MECoM and the potential to collaborate internationally.     Six months after I started work at SDSM&amp;T, a joint fellowship called the East Asia and Pacific Student Institute (EAPSI) between the Australian Academy of Science (AAS) and the NSF provided an opportunity to travel to Australia for research.  Of the two hundred plus US science and math graduate students sent to the East Asia and Pacific countries (China, Japan, Korea, Taiwan, Singapore, Australia, and New Zealand), three were chosen from the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology Department of Chemical and Biological Engineering. Amanda Grill and Tim Shenk were the other two PhD students accepted from SDSM&amp;T; they traveled to Australia and Singapore for their research, respectively.     EAPSI lasted seven weeks, during  which time I designed, built, and troubleshooted a lab capable of culturing the bugs found in coal seams. These bugs, actually a consortium of bacteria and archaeabacteria, are not your typical microorganisms. They only survive as a community by passing molecules between each member and belong to a unique category called strict anaerobes &ndash; meaning they have no tolerance for oxygen. The same microorganisms are responsible for methane produced in cattle rumen or termite guts and are important for processing wastewater treatment facilities. Anaerobic culturing techniques developed for these known systems were applied to our coal system and require three main pieces of equipment; an anaerobic chamber to provide an oxygen free environment during media preparation and inoculation, a gassing manifold for the manipulation and use of oxygen free gas, and a gas chromatograph (GC) for detecting and quantifying methane...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
