<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:Transfected cell microarray technology based on microfluidic electroporation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>290403.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>374394</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Friedrich Srienc</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0747105&lt;br/&gt;Lu&lt;br/&gt;The broad and long-term goal of this project is to develop microfluidics-based transfected cell arrays using electroporation as the transfection method for large-scale gene screening based on both cell lines and primary cells. Electroporation occurs when a critical electrical field strength has been achieved and the cell membrane becomes effectively permeable to large biomolecules. As a physical method, electroporation does not have strong cell type dependency and has been shown effective in transfecting primary cells. In this project, the Principal Investigator (PI) will systematically study the transfection of cell lines and primary cells based on a novel microfluidic electroporation technique developed in the PI's laboratory and also demonstrate proof-of-concept transfected cell arrays for gene screening. In the educational plan, the PI will develop "electronic field trips" for middle/high school students to disseminate the knowledge about biological engineering and establish cyberinfrastructure for K-12 outreach. The PI will also develop a new course on emerging technologies in biological engineering and train undergraduate and graduate students in this highly interdisciplinary project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1016547</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chang</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chang Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>changlu@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402318681</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs 0170]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>006E</Code>
<Text>BIOPROCESS ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>009E</Code>
<Text>Metabolic engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>017E</Code>
<Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7974</Code>
<Text>GRAD RESEARCH SUPPLEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9181</Code>
<Text>BIOPROCESSING/BIOMOLECULAR MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~48236</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~119720</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~161709</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~44729</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our main goal for the project is to develop microfluidics-based transfected cell arrays using electroporation as the transfection method for large-scale gene screening. In this project, we developed transfected cell microarrays for gene screening based on a novel microfluidic flow-through electroporation technique developed in our lab. In this study, we established general guidelines for efficient delivery of plasmid DNA into cell lines and primary cells using microfluidic electroporation.</p> <p>Several specific research and education achievements from the project:</p> <ol> <li>We systematically optimized the flow-through electroporation device for high-efficiency gene delivery. The electric parameters of the electroporation have been varied by changing the geometry of the electroporation device. We have improved the transfection efficiency by pEGFP-C1 to 75% or better. In addition, the cell sample throughput handled was increased up to 20 ml/min. </li> <li>We harnessed inertial Dean flow effects that arise in curved microchannels to expose the cells to a combination of transverse migration and rotation during flow-through electroporation. The resulting complex motion overcomes the major drawback of static electroporation methods by enabling the entire cell surface to be permeabilized and accessed by exogenous DNA. We showed substantial increase in transfection efficiency due to this newly discovered mechanism. This work was highlighted by Nature.</li> <li>We summarized flow-through electroporation for transfection application in a Nature Protocols paper. We presented a protocol for DNA delivery via flow-through electroporation by constant voltage. In our protocol, instead of using a pulse generator, we use a common power supply that applies a constant voltage across a fluidic channel. Cell suspension mixed with DNA molecules flows through the channel which has multiple sections of designed cross-sectional areas.</li> <li>We developed flow-through electroporation based on alternating current (ac) field for high-efficiency gene delivery at the microscale. We generated electropermeabilization and DNA delivery using low-frequency sine-wave or square-wave ac field of 10-10k Hz by modulating a constant ac field across a microfluidic channel with alternating wide and narrow sections.</li> <li>We developed individually addressable microfluidic cell arrays for transfection and gene screening.</li> <li>We have held successful sessions on microfluidic biotechnology in the annual C-Tech2 - Computers and Technology at Virginia Tech summer camp for high school girls. C-Tech2 promotes interests of women in engineering and sciences. Our sessions were attended by 40 high-school girls from all over Virginia (two sessions with 20 girls in each). They included a number of minority students.</li> </ol><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2014<br>      Modified by: Chang&nbsp;Lu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our main goal for the project is to develop microfluidics-based transfected cell arrays using electroporation as the transfection method for large-scale gene screening. In this project, we developed transfected cell microarrays for gene screening based on a novel microfluidic flow-through electroporation technique developed in our lab. In this study, we established general guidelines for efficient delivery of plasmid DNA into cell lines and primary cells using microfluidic electroporation.  Several specific research and education achievements from the project:  We systematically optimized the flow-through electroporation device for high-efficiency gene delivery. The electric parameters of the electroporation have been varied by changing the geometry of the electroporation device. We have improved the transfection efficiency by pEGFP-C1 to 75% or better. In addition, the cell sample throughput handled was increased up to 20 ml/min.  We harnessed inertial Dean flow effects that arise in curved microchannels to expose the cells to a combination of transverse migration and rotation during flow-through electroporation. The resulting complex motion overcomes the major drawback of static electroporation methods by enabling the entire cell surface to be permeabilized and accessed by exogenous DNA. We showed substantial increase in transfection efficiency due to this newly discovered mechanism. This work was highlighted by Nature. We summarized flow-through electroporation for transfection application in a Nature Protocols paper. We presented a protocol for DNA delivery via flow-through electroporation by constant voltage. In our protocol, instead of using a pulse generator, we use a common power supply that applies a constant voltage across a fluidic channel. Cell suspension mixed with DNA molecules flows through the channel which has multiple sections of designed cross-sectional areas. We developed flow-through electroporation based on alternating current (ac) field for high-efficiency gene delivery at the microscale. We generated electropermeabilization and DNA delivery using low-frequency sine-wave or square-wave ac field of 10-10k Hz by modulating a constant ac field across a microfluidic channel with alternating wide and narrow sections. We developed individually addressable microfluidic cell arrays for transfection and gene screening. We have held successful sessions on microfluidic biotechnology in the annual C-Tech2 - Computers and Technology at Virginia Tech summer camp for high school girls. C-Tech2 promotes interests of women in engineering and sciences. Our sessions were attended by 40 high-school girls from all over Virginia (two sessions with 20 girls in each). They included a number of minority students.        Last Modified: 07/18/2014       Submitted by: Chang Lu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
