<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NetSE:Small: Long-Lasting Wireless Sensor Networks for Event Detection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>447654.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>447654</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Phillip Regalia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pregalia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922981</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Event detection is a function common to many wireless sensor network (WSN) applications, e.g. intruder detection in surveillance networks, presence of people detection in building energy management applications, and crack detection in strain sensor networks. Cost of deployment and maintenance is considered by many to be the reason why WSN technology is not more widespread.  While hierarchical or single-hop network architectures are attractive from a communication performance point of view, their required highly functional and long-transmission-range nodes are prohibitively expensive in large-area applications. This leaves multi-hop WSNs as the only possibility for large-area, cost-constrained WSN applications.  However, multi-hop WSNs are still limited in terms of battery life.  While ambient energy harvesting and rechargeable storage elements extend WSN lifetime, these technologies add to the cost of the network.  Therefore, the demand still exists for extremely low-cost sensors that can run on low-cost non-rechargeable batteries.&lt;br/&gt;     In this project, we investigate new routing and medium access control (MAC) protocols to optimize the lifetime of a WSN that does event detection, while taking advantage of a new cooperative transmission (CT) range-extension forwarding strategy.  CT is a technique wherein one or more radios assist another radio, in the physical (PHY) layer (i.e. the radios form a ?virtual transmit array?), to transmit a single message. In the context of multi-hop WSNs, CT range extension becomes a very promising energy balancing mechanism.  This project defines realistic energy consumption models and optimizes MAC and routing metrics that are specifically tied to event detection quality and WSN lifetime, assuming CT range extension is available, along with other life-extension strategies, such as such as in-network filtering, sleep scheduling, energy-aware routing, and non-uniform node deployment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1017984</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>Weitnauer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary Ann Weitnauer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maryann.ingram@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048949482</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000265624</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raghupathy</FirstName>
<LastName>Sivakumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raghupathy Sivakumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>siva@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043852257</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000310027</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7794</Code>
<Text>NETWORK SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~447654</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> &nbsp;Wireless sensor networks, a key component in the Internet of Things, measure and convey to the cloud myriad types of information, such as, pollutant levels, health of civil structures (e.g., bridges), traffic congestion, wildlife activity, energy usage, crop needs, product tracking, natural disaster early warning, etc. Multi-hop wireless sensor networks (MHWSNs) save money, compared to single-hop networks, by allowing a small number of gateways, which are high-functioning radio platforms requiring connection to the internet, to collect data from a large number of inexpensive, low-functioning sensors over a large area. &nbsp;Because sensor radios are battery powered or harvest their energy from their environment, they have short radio range. Therefore &ldquo;close-in&rdquo; sensors near the gateways in conventional networks must relay messages received from more distant sensors. Because of their disproportionate relay burden, the close-in sensors drain their batteries sooner, creating the so-called &ldquo;energy hole,&rdquo; which cuts off the rest of the sensors from the gateways, rendering the network dead. &nbsp;Close in energy harvesting (EH) sensors are offline more to replace spent energy, reducing throughput to the gateway. The project showed how cooperative transmission range extension (CTREX) solves the energy hole problem in MHWSNs, and integrates it with very popular duty cycling, which allows sensors to turn off their radios most of the time. &nbsp;In CTREX, several sensor radios extend radio range by pooling their transmit energy and avoiding radio fades through spatial diversity. &nbsp;CTREX enables distant sensors to reach gateways directly, sparing the close-in sensors, thereby preventing the energy hole and extending the lifetime of the network. One concern about CTREX is its higher level of network overhead, e.g., control packets to select and schedule the multiple sensor radios involved in a single CTREX transmission; more packets mean more energy consumed, so major goals of the project were to design practical protocols that minimize overhead energy and to compare their performance to the optimal performance.</p> <p>Wireless networks have several layers, including network, medium access control (MAC), and physical layers. This project has produced many peer reviewed papers and has had measurable impact at all three layers.&nbsp; At the network layer, optimal lifetime and routing behavior was derived theoretically and near-optimal practical routing metrics were created; the main journal article reporting these results has been cited in 11 papers by other authors. &nbsp;At the MAC layer, arranging CTREX with duty cycling is challenging because several radios must be on at the same time to communicate. Using a Markov Decision Process (MDP) approach, the optimal (i.e., longest possible) lifetime of battery-driven MHWSNs and the optimal (i.e., highest possible) throughput of EH MHWSNs were derived, taking into account the MAC layer overhead. Lifetimes of optimal CTREX MHWSNs were almost double those of optimal non-CTREX MHWSNs. The paper reporting the MDP results has been cited in a recent survey of MDP methods in WSNs.&nbsp;&nbsp; A practical MAC protocol that seamlessly integrates CTREX and duty cycling was designed and analyzed; these results were reported in a conference paper and an extended journal version is currently under review. A journal paper reviewing CTREX methods in multi-hop networks, which highlights the results of this project, was recently published and has already been cited in a paper about milestones and open research challenges.&nbsp;&nbsp; At the physical layer, the project resulted in the key novel technique of cooperative synchronization (CS). All receivers must synchronize prior to decoding a packet. CS extends the range at which synchronization can be done, and is therefore a neces...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  Wireless sensor networks, a key component in the Internet of Things, measure and convey to the cloud myriad types of information, such as, pollutant levels, health of civil structures (e.g., bridges), traffic congestion, wildlife activity, energy usage, crop needs, product tracking, natural disaster early warning, etc. Multi-hop wireless sensor networks (MHWSNs) save money, compared to single-hop networks, by allowing a small number of gateways, which are high-functioning radio platforms requiring connection to the internet, to collect data from a large number of inexpensive, low-functioning sensors over a large area.  Because sensor radios are battery powered or harvest their energy from their environment, they have short radio range. Therefore "close-in" sensors near the gateways in conventional networks must relay messages received from more distant sensors. Because of their disproportionate relay burden, the close-in sensors drain their batteries sooner, creating the so-called "energy hole," which cuts off the rest of the sensors from the gateways, rendering the network dead.  Close in energy harvesting (EH) sensors are offline more to replace spent energy, reducing throughput to the gateway. The project showed how cooperative transmission range extension (CTREX) solves the energy hole problem in MHWSNs, and integrates it with very popular duty cycling, which allows sensors to turn off their radios most of the time.  In CTREX, several sensor radios extend radio range by pooling their transmit energy and avoiding radio fades through spatial diversity.  CTREX enables distant sensors to reach gateways directly, sparing the close-in sensors, thereby preventing the energy hole and extending the lifetime of the network. One concern about CTREX is its higher level of network overhead, e.g., control packets to select and schedule the multiple sensor radios involved in a single CTREX transmission; more packets mean more energy consumed, so major goals of the project were to design practical protocols that minimize overhead energy and to compare their performance to the optimal performance.  Wireless networks have several layers, including network, medium access control (MAC), and physical layers. This project has produced many peer reviewed papers and has had measurable impact at all three layers.  At the network layer, optimal lifetime and routing behavior was derived theoretically and near-optimal practical routing metrics were created; the main journal article reporting these results has been cited in 11 papers by other authors.  At the MAC layer, arranging CTREX with duty cycling is challenging because several radios must be on at the same time to communicate. Using a Markov Decision Process (MDP) approach, the optimal (i.e., longest possible) lifetime of battery-driven MHWSNs and the optimal (i.e., highest possible) throughput of EH MHWSNs were derived, taking into account the MAC layer overhead. Lifetimes of optimal CTREX MHWSNs were almost double those of optimal non-CTREX MHWSNs. The paper reporting the MDP results has been cited in a recent survey of MDP methods in WSNs.   A practical MAC protocol that seamlessly integrates CTREX and duty cycling was designed and analyzed; these results were reported in a conference paper and an extended journal version is currently under review. A journal paper reviewing CTREX methods in multi-hop networks, which highlights the results of this project, was recently published and has already been cited in a paper about milestones and open research challenges.   At the physical layer, the project resulted in the key novel technique of cooperative synchronization (CS). All receivers must synchronize prior to decoding a packet. CS extends the range at which synchronization can be done, and is therefore a necessary part of CTREX.  CS was reported in two conference papers and was implemented in software defined radio (SDR).  Furthermore, CS was recently adapted to cooperat...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
