<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TC: Small: An Algorithmic Framework for Distributed Network Security Policies Management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>485000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>493000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Networks are created to provide reachability; yet, network reachability is not well understood due to the many sophisticated network security policies configured on network devices to limit reachability for security and privacy purposes and the various factors such as routing that may affect reachability in unexpected ways. Due to the lack of distributed network security policy management tools, network operators have been using primitive tools to manage the increasingly complex reachability issues following a ``trial and error'' approach, which leads to many policy and reachability errors. While providing more reachability than necessary opens doors to unwanted traffic, providing less reachability than necessary may disrupt normal business operations. This project employs proactive approaches to reachability management and helps operators to design, verify, analyze, troubleshoot, and optimize distributed network security policies. The new concepts, models, theorems, and algorithms developed in this project advance our knowledge and understanding of network reachability, and the comprehensive network reachability toolkits developed in this project significantly improve network security and reliability. The rigorous models and mathematical formulations of network reachability serves as the theoretical foundation of future work on this fundamental network security issue. The comprehensive toolkit for network reachability quantification, verification, query, monitoring, analysis, and optimization can be used by network operators to troubleshoot and debug reachability problems. This technology enables the seamless collaboration of distributed network security policies and ensure the right amount of reachability is enforced. To promote learning, this effort actively involves high school, undergraduate, graduate students, especially students from under-represented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1017598</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>X</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex X Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alexliu@cse.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5178020805</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482202</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7795</Code>
<Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~485000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Networks are created to provide reachability; yet, network reachability is not well understood due to the many sophisticated network security policies configured on network devices to limit reachability for security and privacy purposes and the various factors such as routing that may affect reachability in unexpected ways. Due to the lack of distributed network security policy management tools, network operators have been using primitive tools to manage the increasingly complex reachability issues following a "trial and error" approach, which leads to many policy and reachability errors. While providing more reachability than necessary opens doors to unwanted traffic, providing less reachability than necessary may disrupt normal business operations. This project employed proactive approaches to reachability management and helps operators to design, verify, analyze, troubleshoot, and optimize distributed network security policies. The new concepts, models, theorems, and algorithms developed in this project advanced our knowledge and understanding of network reachability, and the comprehensive network reachability toolkits developed in this project significantly can improve network security and reliability. The rigorous models and mathematical formulations of network reachability serves as the theoretical foundation of future work on this fundamental network security issue. The comprehensive toolkit for network reachability quantification, verification, query, monitoring, analysis, and optimization can be used by network operators to troubleshoot and debug reachability problems. This technology enables the seamless collaboration of distributed network security policies and ensure the right amount of reachability is enforced.<br /><br />In this project, we have successfully achieved the three main objectives of this project for developing proactive approaches to distributed network security policy management from three integral aspects of reachability: quantification, verification, and optimization, considering the complex interaction between security policies and networking mechanisms. The high level objective of this project is to develop theories, algorithms, and tools for managing the security policies of large interconnect networks. To this end, first, we have developed rigorous models and mathematical formulations for network reachability, which will serve as the theoretical foundation of this fundamental networking issue. Second, we have designed efficient algorithms for quantifying, querying, verifying, monitoring, and optimizing network reachability. Third, we have implemented and integrated our algorithms in a user-friendly and easy-to-deploy tool for network reachability management.<br /><br />The fundamental concepts developed in this project have led to a much deeper understanding of network reachability quantification, verification, and optimization. The key concepts, methods, and algorithms developed in this project are useful beyond this project. For example, our privacy-preserving range query schemes are useful for the cloud computing paradigm. As another example, our TCAM-based network reachability optimization schemes are useful on the design of firewalls, routers, and intrusion detection/prevention systems. Our work helps to bridge several different communities including networking, security, theory, architecture, programming languages, and foster interaction and communication among them.<br /><br />Our research results have been successfully published in top tier computer science conferences (such as INFOCOM, ICNP, and ICDCS), and computer science journals (such as IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications, IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics &amp; Security). This project has supported a number of Ph.D. students, some of them have successfully graduated with Ph.D. degrees.<br /><br />The results that we developed in this project has been incorporated into the graduate courses CSE 825 "Computer and Network Security" at Michigan State University that the PI has been teaching. The PI has designed course projects based on this project for students to work on. The course materials help to educate the next generation of computer engineers for the nation. In addition, our project has provided new opportunities for Ph.D. students to develop their research skills as they pursue their doctoral degrees and eventual careers in academia and/or industry.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Alex&nbsp;X&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Networks are created to provide reachability; yet, network reachability is not well understood due to the many sophisticated network security policies configured on network devices to limit reachability for security and privacy purposes and the various factors such as routing that may affect reachability in unexpected ways. Due to the lack of distributed network security policy management tools, network operators have been using primitive tools to manage the increasingly complex reachability issues following a "trial and error" approach, which leads to many policy and reachability errors. While providing more reachability than necessary opens doors to unwanted traffic, providing less reachability than necessary may disrupt normal business operations. This project employed proactive approaches to reachability management and helps operators to design, verify, analyze, troubleshoot, and optimize distributed network security policies. The new concepts, models, theorems, and algorithms developed in this project advanced our knowledge and understanding of network reachability, and the comprehensive network reachability toolkits developed in this project significantly can improve network security and reliability. The rigorous models and mathematical formulations of network reachability serves as the theoretical foundation of future work on this fundamental network security issue. The comprehensive toolkit for network reachability quantification, verification, query, monitoring, analysis, and optimization can be used by network operators to troubleshoot and debug reachability problems. This technology enables the seamless collaboration of distributed network security policies and ensure the right amount of reachability is enforced.  In this project, we have successfully achieved the three main objectives of this project for developing proactive approaches to distributed network security policy management from three integral aspects of reachability: quantification, verification, and optimization, considering the complex interaction between security policies and networking mechanisms. The high level objective of this project is to develop theories, algorithms, and tools for managing the security policies of large interconnect networks. To this end, first, we have developed rigorous models and mathematical formulations for network reachability, which will serve as the theoretical foundation of this fundamental networking issue. Second, we have designed efficient algorithms for quantifying, querying, verifying, monitoring, and optimizing network reachability. Third, we have implemented and integrated our algorithms in a user-friendly and easy-to-deploy tool for network reachability management.  The fundamental concepts developed in this project have led to a much deeper understanding of network reachability quantification, verification, and optimization. The key concepts, methods, and algorithms developed in this project are useful beyond this project. For example, our privacy-preserving range query schemes are useful for the cloud computing paradigm. As another example, our TCAM-based network reachability optimization schemes are useful on the design of firewalls, routers, and intrusion detection/prevention systems. Our work helps to bridge several different communities including networking, security, theory, architecture, programming languages, and foster interaction and communication among them.  Our research results have been successfully published in top tier computer science conferences (such as INFOCOM, ICNP, and ICDCS), and computer science journals (such as IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications, IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics &amp; Security). This project has supported a number of Ph.D. students, some of them have successfully graduated with Ph.D. degrees.  The results that we developed in this project has been incorporated into the graduate courses CSE 825 "Computer and Network Security" at Michigan State University that the PI has been teaching. The PI has designed course projects based on this project for students to work on. The course materials help to educate the next generation of computer engineers for the nation. In addition, our project has provided new opportunities for Ph.D. students to develop their research skills as they pursue their doctoral degrees and eventual careers in academia and/or industry.       Last Modified: 03/06/2017       Submitted by: Alex X Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
