<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>National Optical Astronomy Observatory Science Research Support</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>72253.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184028</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vernon Pankonin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Optical Astronomy Observatory (NOAO) is the US center for peer reviewed community access to ground based optical-infrared astronomical observing facilities.  A primary goal for NOAO is to maintain a suite of world leading capabilities that allow the community to do research at the highest level.  A key aspect to fulfilling this goal is fostering collaborations and research across all of modern astronomy facilities including space based and radio observatories. Modern astronomy has evolved to a panchromatic endeavor that utilizes data obtained from gamma rays to radio waves.  NOAO astronomers involved in research collaborations that take advantage of space telescopes (e.g. Hubble, Chandra, and Spitzer) and radio/sub-millimeter telescopes (e.g., VLA and ALMA) enhance the development of NOAO's ground based facilities through complementary observations across the electromagnetic spectrum.  Research collaborations with these other facilities ensure NOAO astronomers are engaged in the most relevant areas of study in modern astronomy, and so they maximize the contribution from NOAO's own ground based telescopes to this effort through significant ground based observing programs, technology development, and the training of the next generation of scientists and engineers.  This support via interagency transfers from other governmental agencies will provide research support to NOAO scientists.  This support will help NOAO carry out its core mission of developing the best ground based facilities for the entire US community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1019067</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William S Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wsmith@aura-astronomy.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2024832101</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000366920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/15/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David R.</FirstName>
<LastName>Silva</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David R. Silva</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dsilva@noao.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2024832101</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000517239</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles Mattias</FirstName>
<LastName>Mountain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Mattias Mountain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Matt.Mountain.NSF@aura-astronomy.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2024832101</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000693831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200040000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024832101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 Pennsylvania Ave. NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Ste 1475]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057905887</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATION OF UNIVERSITIES FOR RESEARCH IN ASTRONOMY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057905887</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200040000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1331 Pennsylvania Ave. NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J200</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J288</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>K538</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~142590</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~69889</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>All of the research supported by this grant either developed or used the techniques of multi-telescope optical interferometry.&nbsp; This is a method where several telescopes operate in synchronism, achieving the resolving power of a much-larger telescope.&nbsp; Most of the work was carried out at the CHARA telescope array on Mt. Wilson, north of Los Angeles.&nbsp; CHARA is a project of Georgia State University's Center for High Angular Resolution Astronomy and is an optical/interferometric array of six telescopes. There, the telescope spacing of 300 meters achieves resolution approximately 100 times better than the <em>Hubble Space Telescope</em>.&nbsp; The method currently works only for bright stars, and so the applications are for the study of stellar physics as revealed in some of the most familiar targets, such as the stars Betelgeuse and Aldebaran.&nbsp; As in most of astronomy, multiple techniques are needed for in-depth study, and the programs undertaken in this research also employed the large 10-meter telescope at the Keck Observatory; adaptive optics imaging at the large European telescope, the Very Large Telescope (VLT); optical imaging from the <em>Hubble</em>; and microwave imaging from IRAM, a radio telescope observatory in France.&nbsp; These programs were directed toward the study of stars in the late stages of evolution, at a time when enormous expansion of the atmosphere and increasingly violent convection and pulsation lead to the ejection of clouds of gas and dust, and the formation of shells and spectacular nebulae.</p> <p>Some of the grant resources were used to support advances in instrumentation related to high-resolution imaging.&nbsp; The prototype Fibered Imager for Single Telescope (FIRST) was built in the laboratory and first operated successfully at Lick Observatory. An experimental method for obtaining simultaneous very high spectral resolution and very high spatial resolution was implemented at the CHARA Array and operated over a period of two years, proving the technique but establishing that systematic use will require more sensitive detectors, which are now under development. They are expected to be available in approximately two years.</p> <p>The method of adaptive optics, allowing a telescope to remove the disturbing optical effects of the atmosphere, is increasingly used on the world's most powerful telescopes. Optical interferometery can benefit from adaptive optics even more effectively than most other instruments. Providing adaptive optics for the CHARA Array will be a major upgrade in capability and sensitivity.&nbsp; Following several years of planning and prototyping, partially supported by this grant, the CHARA Array adaptive optics program is underway.&nbsp; Phase I, implementation of infrastructure changes and faint star trackers, is nearing completion.&nbsp; Phase II, the acquisition of special flexible mirrors for control of the telescope image, is beginning now and is expected to be completed in two years.</p> <p>This grant was the principal investigator&rsquo;s primary source of research support for five years and was partial support for three students to participate in the research. These students were able to obtain experience at observatories and gather research materials and results used in their theses. The grant supported scientist and student travel, hardware purchases, and publication costs. Nineteen publications in scientific journals were enabled in whole or in part by this support.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2015<br>      Modified by: David R.&nbsp;Silva</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ All of the research supported by this grant either developed or used the techniques of multi-telescope optical interferometry.  This is a method where several telescopes operate in synchronism, achieving the resolving power of a much-larger telescope.  Most of the work was carried out at the CHARA telescope array on Mt. Wilson, north of Los Angeles.  CHARA is a project of Georgia State University's Center for High Angular Resolution Astronomy and is an optical/interferometric array of six telescopes. There, the telescope spacing of 300 meters achieves resolution approximately 100 times better than the Hubble Space Telescope.  The method currently works only for bright stars, and so the applications are for the study of stellar physics as revealed in some of the most familiar targets, such as the stars Betelgeuse and Aldebaran.  As in most of astronomy, multiple techniques are needed for in-depth study, and the programs undertaken in this research also employed the large 10-meter telescope at the Keck Observatory; adaptive optics imaging at the large European telescope, the Very Large Telescope (VLT); optical imaging from the Hubble; and microwave imaging from IRAM, a radio telescope observatory in France.  These programs were directed toward the study of stars in the late stages of evolution, at a time when enormous expansion of the atmosphere and increasingly violent convection and pulsation lead to the ejection of clouds of gas and dust, and the formation of shells and spectacular nebulae.  Some of the grant resources were used to support advances in instrumentation related to high-resolution imaging.  The prototype Fibered Imager for Single Telescope (FIRST) was built in the laboratory and first operated successfully at Lick Observatory. An experimental method for obtaining simultaneous very high spectral resolution and very high spatial resolution was implemented at the CHARA Array and operated over a period of two years, proving the technique but establishing that systematic use will require more sensitive detectors, which are now under development. They are expected to be available in approximately two years.  The method of adaptive optics, allowing a telescope to remove the disturbing optical effects of the atmosphere, is increasingly used on the world's most powerful telescopes. Optical interferometery can benefit from adaptive optics even more effectively than most other instruments. Providing adaptive optics for the CHARA Array will be a major upgrade in capability and sensitivity.  Following several years of planning and prototyping, partially supported by this grant, the CHARA Array adaptive optics program is underway.  Phase I, implementation of infrastructure changes and faint star trackers, is nearing completion.  Phase II, the acquisition of special flexible mirrors for control of the telescope image, is beginning now and is expected to be completed in two years.  This grant was the principal investigatorÆs primary source of research support for five years and was partial support for three students to participate in the research. These students were able to obtain experience at observatories and gather research materials and results used in their theses. The grant supported scientist and student travel, hardware purchases, and publication costs. Nineteen publications in scientific journals were enabled in whole or in part by this support.             Last Modified: 10/28/2015       Submitted by: David R. Silva]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
