<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Oceanographic Instrumentation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jholik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927711</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A request is made to fund additional and back-up instrumentation on the R/V Point Sur, a 135? general purpose Regional research vessel. The vessel is operated by Moss Landing Marine Labs as part of the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System research fleet. The request includes two items listed by priority:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; 1) Network Upgrade&lt;br/&gt; 2) Precision Spectral Pyranometer&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1019040</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Coale</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth H Coale</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>coale@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8317714406</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000465203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/20/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Harvey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James T Harvey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>harvey@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8317714434</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stewart</FirstName>
<LastName>Lamerdin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stewart K Lamerdin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slamerdin@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8317714134</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000456473</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/29/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Jokinen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin M Jokinen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bjokinen@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4089241400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/20/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Murray</FirstName>
<LastName>Stein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Murray Stein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mstein@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4089241400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000646659</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Jose</CityName>
<ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>056820715</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>056820715</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Jose State University]]></Name>
<CityName>san jose</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>951920139</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Washington Square]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5413</Code>
<Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~47400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The R/V Point Sur is a 135 foot research vessel based in Monterey Bay, California.&nbsp; The Point Sur is capable of taking a science party of up to twelve out on expeditions lasting several weeks or more.&nbsp; She also sails day trips in Monterey Bay, supporting up to thirty scientists or students at a time.</p> <p>As research increases it's reliance on digital data collection and collaboration between sea-going scientists and their shore-side colleagues, the outdated computers and rudimentary computer network on the R/V Point Sur were no longer able to adequately meet scientists' needs.</p> <p>This Oceanographic Instrumentation grant allowed for the upgrade of the R/V Point Sur's data collection computers as well as to install a robust computer network within the ship.&nbsp; Important extras such as shared network storage, a data backup system and monitors to allow for real-time viewing of collected data were also installed.</p> <p>Older desktop computers were replaced with modern rack-mounted machines, allowing for improved computing power, a reduced physical footprint and increased resistance to damage and vibration.&nbsp; These last two features are particularly welcome on a small and mobile platform such as a research vessel.</p> <p>Wired and wireless networks were added and extended to all major areas of the ship, allowing scientists to access stored data, email, collaborate on and off the ship, access the internet and print.&nbsp; Crew are also able to access these resources, improving their ability to operate and manage the vessel and plan for scientific expeditions.</p> <p>Networking additions during this upgrade, include hardware that allows for file sharing, data and file backup, security protection against viruses and video monitors in the laboratory that allow the science party to view data as it's collected.</p> <p>The overall goal of this upgrade was to create a computing and networked environment equivalent to what is found in a modest, modern shore-side research facility.&nbsp; Thanks to this grant, we were able to achieve our goal and have created a digital platform that is able to support science with improved data collection, display, backups and collaboration with in the ship as well as between ship and shore.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2014<br>      Modified by: Murray&nbsp;Stein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The R/V Point Sur is a 135 foot research vessel based in Monterey Bay, California.  The Point Sur is capable of taking a science party of up to twelve out on expeditions lasting several weeks or more.  She also sails day trips in Monterey Bay, supporting up to thirty scientists or students at a time.  As research increases it's reliance on digital data collection and collaboration between sea-going scientists and their shore-side colleagues, the outdated computers and rudimentary computer network on the R/V Point Sur were no longer able to adequately meet scientists' needs.  This Oceanographic Instrumentation grant allowed for the upgrade of the R/V Point Sur's data collection computers as well as to install a robust computer network within the ship.  Important extras such as shared network storage, a data backup system and monitors to allow for real-time viewing of collected data were also installed.  Older desktop computers were replaced with modern rack-mounted machines, allowing for improved computing power, a reduced physical footprint and increased resistance to damage and vibration.  These last two features are particularly welcome on a small and mobile platform such as a research vessel.  Wired and wireless networks were added and extended to all major areas of the ship, allowing scientists to access stored data, email, collaborate on and off the ship, access the internet and print.  Crew are also able to access these resources, improving their ability to operate and manage the vessel and plan for scientific expeditions.  Networking additions during this upgrade, include hardware that allows for file sharing, data and file backup, security protection against viruses and video monitors in the laboratory that allow the science party to view data as it's collected.  The overall goal of this upgrade was to create a computing and networked environment equivalent to what is found in a modest, modern shore-side research facility.  Thanks to this grant, we were able to achieve our goal and have created a digital platform that is able to support science with improved data collection, display, backups and collaboration with in the ship as well as between ship and shore.          Last Modified: 08/06/2014       Submitted by: Murray Stein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
