<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>LTREB:  Experimental tests of alternative states on rocky intertidal shores</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425136.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>425136</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betsy Von Holle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mvonholl@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924974</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research investigates the ecological factors that drive the patchwork pattern of algal stands and mussel beds common in the rocky intertidal zone along ocean coasts. In the Gulf of Maine, winter ice scour often removes mussels and macroalgae, which are known as rockweeds, but it is not known if the species re-establishment is accidental (that is, ice scour can switch a rockweed stand into a mussel bed and vice versa) or deterministic (mussel beds always return to mussel beds).  In ecology, the idea that disturbances such as fires, hurricanes, and even oil spills can abruptly switch one community type into another is known as theory of alternative stable states.  Petraitis and Dudgeon are testing this theory using large experimental clearings they created in 1996-1997 and followed through 2008.  In 2010, half of the experimental plots will be re-cleared, re-set to initial conditions, and followed for at least five more years.  Plots that are not re-cleared serve as controls.  If rockweed stands and mussel beds are truly alternative states, then re-setting experimental plots to initial conditions should produce different outcomes than previously observed.  If succession is deterministic, then the past should predict the future. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This approach has never been used to test for alternative states under natural conditions and the research has broad implications for studies of alternative states in other ecological communities. The project includes plans for online management and dissemination of data, involvement of K-12 students and teachers, and outreach efforts to the local community in Maine where the research is being done. High school students and teachers are involved in data collection. Datasets from this study represent one of the most comprehensive collections of data on intertidal systems world-wide and are invaluable for establishing long-term baselines, data mining and retrospective analyses unrelated to this specific project.  Data files and results will be made accessible to high school students and K-12 teachers through the development of a separate web page.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1020480</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Petraitis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter S Petraitis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ppetrait@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158984207</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000439817</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Dudgeon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven R Dudgeon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steve.dudgeon@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186777322</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000465695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Research Services]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1196</Code>
<Text>LONG-TERM RSCH IN ENVIR BIO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~425136</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research investigated the role of chance events in the establishment and the development of seaweed stands and mussel beds as two alternative communities on rocky intertidal shores in the Gulf of Maine.&nbsp; The project used a set of 60 experimental clearings in seaweed stands that were created in 1996-97 to mimic the effects of ice scour.&nbsp; Between 1997 and 2010, thirty-seven percent of large clearings became mussel beds and the rest returned to seaweed stands.&nbsp; The pattern of recovery supported the idea that seaweed stands and mussel beds represented alternative community states. &nbsp;The attached image shows the chance replacement of mussels by seaweeds under natural conditions.&nbsp;</p> <p>There were two unresolved issues from this earlier study.&nbsp; First, it is possible that development of mussels in some places and seaweeds in others could have been due to undetected environmental conditions. &nbsp;Second, while some experimental clearings became mussel beds and others became seaweed states, it is not certain that these two states would be persistent and resilient.&nbsp; In order to explore these possibilities, half of the original experimental clearings were re-scraped in 2010 and have been monitored continuously since then.&nbsp; New experiments were also undertaken.&nbsp; Much of the monitoring was done with help from K-12 teachers and students.</p> <p>If unknown environmental conditions drove the patterns of succession and change seen from 1997 to 2010, then these past patterns should predict the patterns seen from 2010 to 2015 in the re-scraped areas.&nbsp; If chance events were important, then past patterns should be a poor predictor of future changes.</p> <p>Resilience and persistence were examined in the clearings left intact.&nbsp; If seaweeds stands and mussels beds were persistent, then there should be little or no change from 2010 to 2015.&nbsp; Resilience was tested by creating small clearings in the areas with established seaweed stands and observing if these small clearings bounced back to seaweed stands.</p> <p>From the data collected between 2010 and 2015, it is clear that seaweed stands, but not mussel beds, are both persistent and resilient.&nbsp; Seaweeds, but not mussels colonized areas that were re-scraped.&nbsp; Areas left intact tended to develop into seaweed stands, even those that had been mussel beds.&nbsp; The pattern of recovery, however, could not be predicted with any accuracy by the 1997-2010 results, suggesting succession was driven by chance events in each experimental clearing and not by undetected environmental differences among clearings.&nbsp;</p> <p>The unpredictable arrival of juvenile mussels and seaweed zygotes from the surround ocean waters onto the shore appeared to be the critical driver of haphazard pattern of succession.&nbsp; Between 30% and 40% of the variation in mussel and seaweed recruitment could not be explained by the size of clearing, location, yearly effects or past events.&nbsp; Mortality of mussels and changes in other invertebrate species were equally variable.&nbsp;</p> <p>The most surprising finding was a long-term decline in mussel recruitment and other mollusk species.&nbsp; The arrival of juvenile mussels to the shore has declined by 15% per year from 1997 to 2015.&nbsp; This represents a 200-fold change in about 20 years.&nbsp; Other snails and limpets have also declined but not by as much.&nbsp; The cause of the declines is unknown but it may be due to ocean acidification, which can interfere with shell formation of juvenile snails and limpets while they are developing in offshore waters.</p> <p>&nbsp;Two conclusions can be drawn from this research.&nbsp; First, the enormous variation in seaweed and mussel recruitment can drive chance events and lead to the development of either mussel beds or seaweed stands.&nbsp; Thus the mosaic like pattern of mussels and seaweeds on the shore cannot be easily predicted by knowing the local conditions.&nbsp; Second, the long-term decline in mussel recruitment is the likely cause of the recent disappearance of mussels from the Gulf of Maine.&nbsp; The patterns on the shores in Maine appear to be shifting from patchwork of mussels and seaweeds to a monoculture of seaweeds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petraitis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1020480/1020480_10018990_1475678658674_millpondpointakastorepoint--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1020480/1020480_10018990_1475678658674_millpondpointakastorepoint--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Switch from mussels to seaweeds"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1020480/1020480_10018990_1475678658674_millpondpointakastorepoint--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Switch from mussels to seaweeds"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photographs show the change from mussels in the mid 1980s to seaweeds by 2015 under natural conditions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Photographs taken by Peter Petraitis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;S&nbsp;Petraitis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Switch from mussels to seaweeds</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research investigated the role of chance events in the establishment and the development of seaweed stands and mussel beds as two alternative communities on rocky intertidal shores in the Gulf of Maine.  The project used a set of 60 experimental clearings in seaweed stands that were created in 1996-97 to mimic the effects of ice scour.  Between 1997 and 2010, thirty-seven percent of large clearings became mussel beds and the rest returned to seaweed stands.  The pattern of recovery supported the idea that seaweed stands and mussel beds represented alternative community states.  The attached image shows the chance replacement of mussels by seaweeds under natural conditions.   There were two unresolved issues from this earlier study.  First, it is possible that development of mussels in some places and seaweeds in others could have been due to undetected environmental conditions.  Second, while some experimental clearings became mussel beds and others became seaweed states, it is not certain that these two states would be persistent and resilient.  In order to explore these possibilities, half of the original experimental clearings were re-scraped in 2010 and have been monitored continuously since then.  New experiments were also undertaken.  Much of the monitoring was done with help from K-12 teachers and students.  If unknown environmental conditions drove the patterns of succession and change seen from 1997 to 2010, then these past patterns should predict the patterns seen from 2010 to 2015 in the re-scraped areas.  If chance events were important, then past patterns should be a poor predictor of future changes.  Resilience and persistence were examined in the clearings left intact.  If seaweeds stands and mussels beds were persistent, then there should be little or no change from 2010 to 2015.  Resilience was tested by creating small clearings in the areas with established seaweed stands and observing if these small clearings bounced back to seaweed stands.  From the data collected between 2010 and 2015, it is clear that seaweed stands, but not mussel beds, are both persistent and resilient.  Seaweeds, but not mussels colonized areas that were re-scraped.  Areas left intact tended to develop into seaweed stands, even those that had been mussel beds.  The pattern of recovery, however, could not be predicted with any accuracy by the 1997-2010 results, suggesting succession was driven by chance events in each experimental clearing and not by undetected environmental differences among clearings.   The unpredictable arrival of juvenile mussels and seaweed zygotes from the surround ocean waters onto the shore appeared to be the critical driver of haphazard pattern of succession.  Between 30% and 40% of the variation in mussel and seaweed recruitment could not be explained by the size of clearing, location, yearly effects or past events.  Mortality of mussels and changes in other invertebrate species were equally variable.   The most surprising finding was a long-term decline in mussel recruitment and other mollusk species.  The arrival of juvenile mussels to the shore has declined by 15% per year from 1997 to 2015.  This represents a 200-fold change in about 20 years.  Other snails and limpets have also declined but not by as much.  The cause of the declines is unknown but it may be due to ocean acidification, which can interfere with shell formation of juvenile snails and limpets while they are developing in offshore waters.   Two conclusions can be drawn from this research.  First, the enormous variation in seaweed and mussel recruitment can drive chance events and lead to the development of either mussel beds or seaweed stands.  Thus the mosaic like pattern of mussels and seaweeds on the shore cannot be easily predicted by knowing the local conditions.  Second, the long-term decline in mussel recruitment is the likely cause of the recent disappearance of mussels from the Gulf of Maine.  The patterns on the shores in Maine appear to be shifting from patchwork of mussels and seaweeds to a monoculture of seaweeds.             Last Modified: 10/29/2016       Submitted by: Peter S Petraitis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
