<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RIG: Cryptic Speciation in Jumping Spiders: Multimodal Courtship Divergence in Jumping Spiders of the Sonoran Desert 'Sky Islands'</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>180000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Elekonich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>melekoni@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927202</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cataloging the diversity of life and the processes that drive and maintain this diversity is one of the most important goals facing scientists today. One important hotspot of diversity is the "sky-islands" of southeastern Arizona and northern Mexico.  The so-called sky islands are named for their resemblance to islands as woodlands at the tops of mountain ranges are separated by desert "oceans".  On different sky-islands, groups of animals have diversified into a variety of forms and this has served as a &lt;br/&gt;"natural experiment" to investigate species formation.  The research proposal uses an innovative blend of techniques from behavioral and engineering sciences to look at the processes which lead to species diversification on the sky-islands, specifically in two groups of jumping spiders.  Jumping spiders are one of the most diverse animal groups and their behavior has received attention as males use courtship "song and dances" to attract mates.  The research proposal will look at courtship behavior and in particular (1) how behavior has diverged on the different sky-islands, (2) how females make decisions based on male behavior on the different sky-islands, and (3) how the environment influences the development of male and female mating behavior.  Because differences in courtship behavior often define species, the proposal will be important to cataloging unknown diversity ("cryptic speciation") in one of the most important American habitats.  In addition, by investigating a system where the process of species diversification is currently ongoing, the proposal will allow the researchers to test hypotheses on what drives the maintenance of species and how variation in the environment leads to the diversity of forms found in nature.  Results from the proposal will be used to generate online educational materials which will freely available and used as a resource for educators interested in learning about behavior, ecology, animal senses, and conservation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1021385</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Damian</FirstName>
<LastName>Elias</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Damian O Elias</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>doelias@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106426396</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000530340</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7487</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7692</Code>
<Text>RIG/CAA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The increased loss of natural habitats is leading to the wide spread decimation of worldwide biodiversity. Unfortunately, much biodiversity that is disappearing is still is unknown, therefore, cataloging biodiversity and the mechanisms that drive and maintain biodiversity is one of the most important goals facing scientists today. In keeping with these objectives, the major goals of proposal 1021385 were to (1) examine biodiversity in jumping spiders, (2) test hypotheses about the ecological forces driving biodiversity, and (3) examine some potential mechanisms maintaining biodiversity. Significant progress was made into meeting these goals.&nbsp; First, we described the mating displays of several spider species in two peer reviewed publications (Elias et al. 2012; Girard et al. 2011). Besides being the first to record, observe, and catalogue this diversity of display behavior, we also developed techniques to describe and quantify complex, multisensory mating displays (Elias et al. 2012).&nbsp; These techniques will enable future biodiversity work across many taxa.&nbsp; Additionally this proposal was instrumental in developing a framework for understanding how animals deal with rapidly fluctuating environments and how understanding adaptations to &ldquo;change&rdquo; may be critical to understanding the evolution of animal groups (Elias et al. 2011).&nbsp; From this, several additional studies are underway to look at particular environmental variables and their effect on mating behavior and biodiversity.&nbsp; In particular these studies have investigated the role of elevation, habitat composition, temperature, and signaling environments on the diversity of spider communities in the American Southwest. Future peer reviewed publications are expected. Besides the ecological mechanisms driving biodiversity, this proposal helped fund research that unlocked a previously unknown mechanism of signaling, aeroelastic flutter.&nbsp; Aeroelastic flutter is a property inherent in bird and insect wings and some groups of hummingbirds have evolved a variety of morphologies to use aeroelastic flutter in mating displays (Clark et al. 2011, Clark et al. 2013a, Clark et al. 2013b).&nbsp; Finally, this proposal supported the writing of two book reviews on the diversity of vibratory displays (Elias and Mason, in press) and the diversity of spider communication behavior (Uhl and Elias 2011).</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In addition to the research and intellectual goals of this proposal, this proposal also sought to (1) increase visibility and scientific literacy of basic behavioral and biodiversity research, (2) provide access of educational materials to community college, university and GK-12 instructors, (3) train undergraduates and post-graduate students in experimental techniques, and (4) recruit under-represented groups into biological research.&nbsp; We made significant progress in meeting those aims. The proposal helped to fund the design and implementation of a lab research website and YouTube channel with freely accessible links to multimedia material, primary scientific research, and accessible information targeted to the lay public (podcasts, news articles, blog posts, video presentations etc). The website and YouTube channel have been and continue to be successful, with the YouTube channel receiving over 50,000 views in 2013. Videos from the YouTube channel were featured on several prominent websites (Krulich Wonders, Buzzfeed, The Daily What), social networking platforms (Twitter, Facebook), and national television shows (The Tonight Show with Jay Leno). Work directly funded from this proposal was also featured in several scientific television programs (BBC, Discovery Channel, Discovery Channel Canada). Public presentations of data gathered in the proposal was presented to to high school students (Marin High Schoo...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The increased loss of natural habitats is leading to the wide spread decimation of worldwide biodiversity. Unfortunately, much biodiversity that is disappearing is still is unknown, therefore, cataloging biodiversity and the mechanisms that drive and maintain biodiversity is one of the most important goals facing scientists today. In keeping with these objectives, the major goals of proposal 1021385 were to (1) examine biodiversity in jumping spiders, (2) test hypotheses about the ecological forces driving biodiversity, and (3) examine some potential mechanisms maintaining biodiversity. Significant progress was made into meeting these goals.  First, we described the mating displays of several spider species in two peer reviewed publications (Elias et al. 2012; Girard et al. 2011). Besides being the first to record, observe, and catalogue this diversity of display behavior, we also developed techniques to describe and quantify complex, multisensory mating displays (Elias et al. 2012).  These techniques will enable future biodiversity work across many taxa.  Additionally this proposal was instrumental in developing a framework for understanding how animals deal with rapidly fluctuating environments and how understanding adaptations to "change" may be critical to understanding the evolution of animal groups (Elias et al. 2011).  From this, several additional studies are underway to look at particular environmental variables and their effect on mating behavior and biodiversity.  In particular these studies have investigated the role of elevation, habitat composition, temperature, and signaling environments on the diversity of spider communities in the American Southwest. Future peer reviewed publications are expected. Besides the ecological mechanisms driving biodiversity, this proposal helped fund research that unlocked a previously unknown mechanism of signaling, aeroelastic flutter.  Aeroelastic flutter is a property inherent in bird and insect wings and some groups of hummingbirds have evolved a variety of morphologies to use aeroelastic flutter in mating displays (Clark et al. 2011, Clark et al. 2013a, Clark et al. 2013b).  Finally, this proposal supported the writing of two book reviews on the diversity of vibratory displays (Elias and Mason, in press) and the diversity of spider communication behavior (Uhl and Elias 2011).   In addition to the research and intellectual goals of this proposal, this proposal also sought to (1) increase visibility and scientific literacy of basic behavioral and biodiversity research, (2) provide access of educational materials to community college, university and GK-12 instructors, (3) train undergraduates and post-graduate students in experimental techniques, and (4) recruit under-represented groups into biological research.  We made significant progress in meeting those aims. The proposal helped to fund the design and implementation of a lab research website and YouTube channel with freely accessible links to multimedia material, primary scientific research, and accessible information targeted to the lay public (podcasts, news articles, blog posts, video presentations etc). The website and YouTube channel have been and continue to be successful, with the YouTube channel receiving over 50,000 views in 2013. Videos from the YouTube channel were featured on several prominent websites (Krulich Wonders, Buzzfeed, The Daily What), social networking platforms (Twitter, Facebook), and national television shows (The Tonight Show with Jay Leno). Work directly funded from this proposal was also featured in several scientific television programs (BBC, Discovery Channel, Discovery Channel Canada). Public presentations of data gathered in the proposal was presented to to high school students (Marin High School, Dublin High School), to high school and community college educators (Think Evolution workshops), and at the Expanding Your Horizons conference, a program to encourage young urban middle school gi...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
