<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Identifying new regulators of sex-specific neurogenesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>517912.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>517912</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Ann Asson-Batres</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sexually dimorphic neurons, which are distinct in males and females, control unique behaviors and are essential to reproductive success in most animals, including humans.  Learning how sex-determining genes work with regulators of cell identity, division, and patterning to generate unique neurons in each sex is critical for understanding normal development, and may also provide clues about developmental disorders with higher incidence in one sex, such as autism.  As a result, the relatively simple neuronal development of the nematode C. elegans has become an essential model for understanding sex-specific neuron specialization.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using C. elegans as a tool for gene discovery, the goal of the proposed work is to investigate how sexually dimorphic neurons that control mating arise during embryonic development.  A pilot genetic screen for msd (male-specific division defective) mutants, which fail to generate male-specific motor neurons, identified two mutations, ccc1 and ccc3.  Additional msd mutations will be sought in a continued genetic screen.  The genes affected by these msd mutations will be identified and their role in promoting sex-specific neuronal division will be explored using molecular genetic techniques and fluorescent markers of neuronal fate.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide Carleton College undergraduates and high school students participating in Carleton's Summer Science Institute hands-on experience with lab techniques and data presentation that will help them to succeed in their classes and empower them to seek out further engagement with scientific research.  Students involved in the project will make significant, original research contributions to the field of neurobiology by discovering and studying new genes that mediate the development of neurons that regulate reproduction.  As genes that control fundamental processes are often similar among diverse organisms, these studies may provide a basis for future investigations that shed light on human reproduction and on nervous system diseases that exhibit higher incidence in one sex.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1021705</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Wolff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer R Wolff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwolff@carleton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5072224324</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carleton College</Name>
<CityName>Northfield</CityName>
<ZipCode>550574001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5072224303</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One North College Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068184449</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARLETON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068184449</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carleton College]]></Name>
<CityName>Northfield</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>550574001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One North College Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7712</Code>
<Text>Organization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1096</Code>
<Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~206245</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~154246</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~157421</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Sexually dimorphic neurons, which are distinct in males and females, control unique behaviors and are essential to reproductive success in most animals, including humans. Learning how sex-determining genes work with regulators of cell identity, division, and patterning to generate unique neurons in each sex is critical for understanding normal development, and may also provide clues about developmental disorders with higher incidence in one sex. As a result, the relatively simple neuronal development of the nematode <em>C. elegans</em>&nbsp;has become an essential model for understanding sex-specific neuron specialization.</p> <p>The goal of this work was investigate how sexually dimorphic neurons that control mating arise during embryonic development, using <em>C. elegans</em> as a tool for gene discovery. We performed genetic screens to identify <em>msd</em> (<span style="text-decoration: underline;">m</span>ale-<span style="text-decoration: underline;">s</span>pecific <span style="text-decoration: underline;">d</span>ivision defective)<em> </em>mutants, which fail to generate the normal complement of sex-specific neurons in the male ventral nerve cord. Using whole genome sequencing technology, we identified the genes affected by these <em>msd</em> mutations and explored their function using molecular genetic techniques. In order to effectively complete these studies, we developed a toolkit of fluorescent protein-based markers that fluorescently label different classes of sex-specific neurons in living worms. This toolkit not only provided a valuable resource for our own studies, but is freely available to the <em>C. elegans</em> neuroscience community and can be used by others interested in understanding how different types of neurons arise during development.</p> <p>Our work identified several genes that are necessary for normal sex-specific neuronal development. The identification of a group of patterning genes in our screens led us to focus on how neurons become patterned along the anterior-posterior (head-to-tail) axis. Neurons arising at different locations in the <em>C. elegans</em> ventral nerve cord have different functions depending on their anterior-posterior location. A similar situation exists in the vertebrate spinal cord, where spinal motor neurons differ along the head-to-tail axis such that distinct neurons innervate the arms, trunk, and legs, for example. In both <em>C. elegans</em> and vertebrates, positional fates are controlled by a group of transcription factors called <em>Hox</em> proteins, which essentially provide a cell its anterior-posterior &ldquo;address&rdquo; during development. Our studies of mutations in the <em>Hox </em>genes <em>lin-39 </em>and <em>mab-5, </em>using the marker toolkit,<em> </em>revealed that these overlapping <em>Hox</em> genes collaborate to create three zones of neuronal identity in the ventral nerve cord in males. Further studies of how these <em>Hox</em> genes interact will contribute to our understanding of <em>C. elegans</em> neurogenesis and may shed light on the mechanisms of similar interactions in the spinal cord of vertebrate animals. In addition to our studies of the <em>Hox</em> genes, our screens revealed a new role for the transcription factor UNC-4 in preventing inappropriate development of male-specific neurons in hermaphrodites (the worms&rsquo; second sex, a self-fertile female).</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>A major goal of this work, which took place at Carleton College, a primarily undergraduate institution, was to give undergraduates and high school students participating in Carleton&rsquo;s Summer Science Institute hands-on experience with lab techniques and data presentation to help them to succeed in their classes and empower them to seek out further engagement with scientific research. During the grant period, fourteen undergr...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  Sexually dimorphic neurons, which are distinct in males and females, control unique behaviors and are essential to reproductive success in most animals, including humans. Learning how sex-determining genes work with regulators of cell identity, division, and patterning to generate unique neurons in each sex is critical for understanding normal development, and may also provide clues about developmental disorders with higher incidence in one sex. As a result, the relatively simple neuronal development of the nematode C. elegans has become an essential model for understanding sex-specific neuron specialization.  The goal of this work was investigate how sexually dimorphic neurons that control mating arise during embryonic development, using C. elegans as a tool for gene discovery. We performed genetic screens to identify msd (male-specific division defective) mutants, which fail to generate the normal complement of sex-specific neurons in the male ventral nerve cord. Using whole genome sequencing technology, we identified the genes affected by these msd mutations and explored their function using molecular genetic techniques. In order to effectively complete these studies, we developed a toolkit of fluorescent protein-based markers that fluorescently label different classes of sex-specific neurons in living worms. This toolkit not only provided a valuable resource for our own studies, but is freely available to the C. elegans neuroscience community and can be used by others interested in understanding how different types of neurons arise during development.  Our work identified several genes that are necessary for normal sex-specific neuronal development. The identification of a group of patterning genes in our screens led us to focus on how neurons become patterned along the anterior-posterior (head-to-tail) axis. Neurons arising at different locations in the C. elegans ventral nerve cord have different functions depending on their anterior-posterior location. A similar situation exists in the vertebrate spinal cord, where spinal motor neurons differ along the head-to-tail axis such that distinct neurons innervate the arms, trunk, and legs, for example. In both C. elegans and vertebrates, positional fates are controlled by a group of transcription factors called Hox proteins, which essentially provide a cell its anterior-posterior "address" during development. Our studies of mutations in the Hox genes lin-39 and mab-5, using the marker toolkit, revealed that these overlapping Hox genes collaborate to create three zones of neuronal identity in the ventral nerve cord in males. Further studies of how these Hox genes interact will contribute to our understanding of C. elegans neurogenesis and may shed light on the mechanisms of similar interactions in the spinal cord of vertebrate animals. In addition to our studies of the Hox genes, our screens revealed a new role for the transcription factor UNC-4 in preventing inappropriate development of male-specific neurons in hermaphrodites (the wormsÆ second sex, a self-fertile female).  Broader Impacts  A major goal of this work, which took place at Carleton College, a primarily undergraduate institution, was to give undergraduates and high school students participating in CarletonÆs Summer Science Institute hands-on experience with lab techniques and data presentation to help them to succeed in their classes and empower them to seek out further engagement with scientific research. During the grant period, fourteen undergraduates worked on the project in the PIÆs laboratory, with nearly all of them presenting their work at regional or local scientific meetings. Four students were authors on a publication in the journal Developmental Cell, and six presented their work at the International C. elegans meeting, a professional research conference. The grant also provided funding to train a postdoctoral fellow, who gained teaching experience and training in the classroom and...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
