<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Response of Arctic Clouds to Changes in Sea Ice during Autumn</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>551250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>551250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Neil R. Swanberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Clouds play a major role in the arctic surface energy balance controlling the growth and melt of sea ice.  At the same time the processes involved in the formation, maintenance and dissipation of cloud cover over the Arctic Ocean are thought to be strongly influenced by the sea ice itself.  The proposed project will advance the understanding of this interaction and feedback by asking:  What is the response of Arctic clouds to diminishing sea ice? In answering this question, the PI's will consider (i) the physical processes that cause and modulate this response, (ii) the role of large-scale atmospheric dynamics, (iii) the potential effects on the heat and energy balance and in climate feedbacks, and (iv) the limitations of observing from space the response of clouds to changes in sea ice.  The approach will be to conduct a series of experiments with different configurations of a regional atmospheric model, the Weather Research and Forecast (WRF) model.  Focusing on the autumn season, sea ice and sea surface temperature will be altered and changes in cloud cover associated with sea ice will be examined in the context of large scale dynamics.  Model experiments designed to better understand the physical processes involved in the response of clouds to diminishing sea ice will be performed. The impact on the surface and the top of the atmosphere energy balance of sea-ice driven changes on cloud cover and the atmospheric temperature and humidity will be examined.  Differences in sea ice-cloud interactions between the WRF model and a typical global climate model (e.g. CAM) will be assessed. Finally, satellite cloud detection criteria used in typical visible and infrared-based algorithms will be evaluated for their ability to properly detect cloud changes in the context of significant changes in surface properties by performing radiative transfer calculations to simulate the spectral signal at the satellite from modeled atmospheric and cloud responses for different surface conditions. This research will address significant questions of the ?Understanding Change? aspect of the Study of Arctic Environmental Change (SEARCH).  In particular the questions/activities "What are the critical interactions among ocean, ice, land, and atmosphere as they relate to Arctic Change?", "What is the direction and relative importance of feedbacks?" will benefit from this analysis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1021274</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Lindsay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ronald W Lindsay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lindsay@apl.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065435409</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Axel</FirstName>
<LastName>Schweiger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Axel Schweiger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>axel@apl.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065431312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419326</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCSS-Arctic System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~551250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Activities:</strong></p> <ul> <li>We developed a regional model for Beaufort and Chukchi Seas and validated the model using measurements of atmospheric properties derived from Aircraft, ship-board, and satellite remote sensing data. Data collected during Coast Guard ADA flights during 2013 with 2015 were compared with our regional model as well as global forecast models and reanalyses. </li> <li>We examined the role of alternating lateral and surface boundary conditions on model results.&nbsp; Integrations with GSF and ECMWF Interim data were conducted and compared to observations. The relative improvement of nested regional models over global forecast and reanalysis models with respect to atmospheric properties was examined. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>We contributed an inter-comparison and validation of 7 reanalysis data sets in the Arctic. </li> </ul> <ul> <li> We conducted an analysis short term sea ice drift forecasts using a couple ice ocean model</li> </ul> <ul> <li>We constructed a 2d model cloud resolving model that provides a section across the ice-edge. We examined the response of boundary layer depth and boundary layer clouds to varying initial conditions and model parameters. This model is designed to provide a clearer understanding of the impact of the ice edge on atmospheric properties we analyzed from observations and reanalysis data. </li> <li>We examined ice thickness observations from observations and models to use as boundary conditions for regional model simulations.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Results:</strong></p> <p>The projects contributed to 7 peer reviewed papers and numerous conference presentations. It helped communicate high latitude research to the public. Forecasts fo sea ice variability and drift will be directly affected by this research. Specific results are:</p> <ul> <li>Regional model simulations using WRF demonstrates superior performance with respect to the representation of the vertical wind profile over GFS and ERA-Interim boundary forcing data. In particular a near surface low level jet is better characterized in regional model simulations. </li> <li>Both GFS and ERA-interim models capture the general structure of temperature, humidity and wind profiles. Both models show considerable differences to observations in relative humidity with a significant moist bias that likely impacts cloud formation.</li> <li>Oure regional model simulations can better represent low level inversions than GFS and ERA-interim models</li> <li>Improved parameterizations rather than higher resolution appear to be responsible for the improved performance of regional models vs. global analysis and reanalysis systems.</li> <li>Differences in sea surface temperatures are responsible for differences in near surface atmospheric properties.</li> <li>We identified a problem in the ECMWF processing of SST and ice concentration. If satellite derived sea surface temperatures exceed a specific threshold, corresponding ice concentrations are set to 0. Errors in SST retrievals can lead to substantial changes in ECMWF model boundary conditions. </li> <li>2-d cloud resolving model experiments CRM are capable of producing a cloud top boundary layer with increasing thickness with distance from the ice edge </li> <li>The inter-comparison of 7 reanalysis data sets in the Arctic identified shortcomings in all data sets. </li> <li>Comparison of sea ice observations and sea ice reanalysis information from PIOMAS with global climate simulations from the CMIP-5 archive demonstrate that the ensemble mean of CMIP-5 simulations underestimate observed and reanalyzed sea ice volume loss. However individual ensemble members are well within the uncertainties of PIOMAS trends.</li> <li>Arctic sea ice thickness reconstructed from remote sensing and in situ data shows a reduction basin wide reduction in sea ice thickness.&nbsp; We find that the annual meanice thickness has decreased from ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Activities:  We developed a regional model for Beaufort and Chukchi Seas and validated the model using measurements of atmospheric properties derived from Aircraft, ship-board, and satellite remote sensing data. Data collected during Coast Guard ADA flights during 2013 with 2015 were compared with our regional model as well as global forecast models and reanalyses.  We examined the role of alternating lateral and surface boundary conditions on model results.  Integrations with GSF and ECMWF Interim data were conducted and compared to observations. The relative improvement of nested regional models over global forecast and reanalysis models with respect to atmospheric properties was examined.    We contributed an inter-comparison and validation of 7 reanalysis data sets in the Arctic.     We conducted an analysis short term sea ice drift forecasts using a couple ice ocean model   We constructed a 2d model cloud resolving model that provides a section across the ice-edge. We examined the response of boundary layer depth and boundary layer clouds to varying initial conditions and model parameters. This model is designed to provide a clearer understanding of the impact of the ice edge on atmospheric properties we analyzed from observations and reanalysis data.  We examined ice thickness observations from observations and models to use as boundary conditions for regional model simulations.   Results:  The projects contributed to 7 peer reviewed papers and numerous conference presentations. It helped communicate high latitude research to the public. Forecasts fo sea ice variability and drift will be directly affected by this research. Specific results are:  Regional model simulations using WRF demonstrates superior performance with respect to the representation of the vertical wind profile over GFS and ERA-Interim boundary forcing data. In particular a near surface low level jet is better characterized in regional model simulations.  Both GFS and ERA-interim models capture the general structure of temperature, humidity and wind profiles. Both models show considerable differences to observations in relative humidity with a significant moist bias that likely impacts cloud formation. Oure regional model simulations can better represent low level inversions than GFS and ERA-interim models Improved parameterizations rather than higher resolution appear to be responsible for the improved performance of regional models vs. global analysis and reanalysis systems. Differences in sea surface temperatures are responsible for differences in near surface atmospheric properties. We identified a problem in the ECMWF processing of SST and ice concentration. If satellite derived sea surface temperatures exceed a specific threshold, corresponding ice concentrations are set to 0. Errors in SST retrievals can lead to substantial changes in ECMWF model boundary conditions.  2-d cloud resolving model experiments CRM are capable of producing a cloud top boundary layer with increasing thickness with distance from the ice edge  The inter-comparison of 7 reanalysis data sets in the Arctic identified shortcomings in all data sets.  Comparison of sea ice observations and sea ice reanalysis information from PIOMAS with global climate simulations from the CMIP-5 archive demonstrate that the ensemble mean of CMIP-5 simulations underestimate observed and reanalyzed sea ice volume loss. However individual ensemble members are well within the uncertainties of PIOMAS trends. Arctic sea ice thickness reconstructed from remote sensing and in situ data shows a reduction basin wide reduction in sea ice thickness.  We find that the annual meanice thickness has decreased from 3.59m in 1975 to 1.25m in 2012, a 65% reduction. A coupled ice ocean model driven with forecast atmospheric conditions provides substantially improved sea ice drift forecasts up to 72h from forecast time. Drift speed errors are in the order of 4.5 km/day and position errors are 6 km after 24 hours. T...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
