<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Regulation of Receptor Kinase Signaling by Tyrosine Phosphorylation and Calmodulin Binding</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499166.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499166</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>elsbeth walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Hormonal signals in plants regulate critical processes as diverse as growth and reproduction to adaptation to environmental stresses.  Collectively, these processes dictate agricultural productivity and plant adaptation to environmental change.  The project takes a combined biochemical and molecular approach to understand how the mechanisms of action of a steroid hormone, brassinolide (BR), are regulated.  This hormone has profound effects on plant growth and development.  The PI and co-PI will exploit the unexpected and newly described interactions between the BR receptor, BRI1, and the regulatory protein calmodulin to elucidate a broader network of responses required for optimum plant growth and reproductive success that were previously unrecognized.  Their experimental approach will involve defining changes to BRI1 that disrupt its interaction with calmodulin by mutating the BRI1 protein.  Altered forms of BRI identified in these experiments will then be introduced into a dwarf mutant lacking BRI1 activity.  The effects of this transformation on gene expression patterns, plant growth and reproduction will be quantified to provide new insights into the molecular bases for regulating plant growth.  In addition to the new scientific information generated, the project will provide hands-on research opportunities for students from groups under-represented in science by specifically recruiting them for summer internships on the project.  As part of a program to enhance both the scientific and mentorship skills of a next-generation research scientist, a postdoctoral researcher will participate in the project together with the PI and co-PI.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1022177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
<LastName>Zielinski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raymond E Zielinski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zielinsk@life.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173336785</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000220808</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Huber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Huber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steven.huber@ars.usda.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172650909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526697</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~151200</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~230163</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~117803</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Plants have a large family of receptor-like kinases that control a number of important processes ranging from growth and development to responses to the environment and pathogens. The receptor kinases are proteins embedded in the cell outer (plasma) membrane and transmit signals from the outside of the cell to the interior, without the signal itself entering the cell.&nbsp; The signals are often molecules (ligands) that bind to the extracellular portion of the receptor kinase.&nbsp; In plants, this binding induces the receptor kinase to interact with a specific co-receptor kinase, which then results in their mutual activation by a process involving protein phosphorylation but many details of that process are not clear.&nbsp; Our studies focused on the brassinosteroid hormone receptor kinase, known as BRI1, and its co-receptor kinase, known as BAK1.&nbsp; All members of the plant receptor kinase family are classified as serine-threonine kinases but BRI1 was known to be a dual-specificity kinase, capable of autophosphorylation on serine, threonine and tyrosine residues.&nbsp; Protein phosphorylation is a powerful regulatory mechanism in higher organisms, and our results highlight the profound importance seemingly small changes in protein phosphorylation can have on the function of a whole organism.&nbsp; Our studies established the mechanism of autophosphorylation of BRI1 on tyrosine residues and revealed that phosphorylation of a specific tyrosine residue (Tyr-831) functioned to attenuate receptor kinase signaling in vivo.&nbsp; Preventing phosphorylation at the tyrosine-831, by substituting a phenylalanine that cannot be phosphorylated, resulted in enhanced signaling through the brassinosteroid pathway and increased plant growth rate. We also identified serine-891, located in the ATP-binding domain, as another site that when phosphorylated results in inhibition of kinase activity.&nbsp; Both phosphosites are new targets for manipulation to potentially enhance activity of the growth-promoting pathway in crop plants.</p> <p>Studies with BAK1 established it as a dual-specificity kinase and identified a specific tyrosine residue (Tyr-610) located near the carboxy-terminus of the protein, as a major site of phosphorylation.&nbsp; The carboxy-terminal polypeptide of BAK1 may be playing a particularly important role.&nbsp; Our working model is that the carboxy-terminal polypeptide of BAK1 inhibits its protein kinase activity, and that inhibition is relieved when the carboxy-terminal polypeptide binds to BRI1. As a result, the two proteins are properly positioned so that BAK1 can phosphorylate and activate BRI1. Binding to BRI1 appears to be enhanced by phosphorylation of BAK1 at the tyrosine-610 site, but interestingly, prevention of tyrosine-610 phosphorylation does not interfere with brassinosteroid signaling in vivo as might be expected.&nbsp; &nbsp;These results increase our understanding of how plant receptor kinases function, and may provide a general model for receptor:co-receptor interactions.&nbsp; Understanding these molecular interactions may also provide novel approaches to engineer signaling pathways in plants.</p> <p>Finally, our studies identified a potentially new mechanism for cross talk between calcium signaling and receptor kinase signaling. The new mechanism involves binding of calmodulin, which is a highly conserved protein in eukaryotes that functions as a calcium sensor.&nbsp; When the concentration of free calcium in the cell is elevated (as occurs in response to stress), calmodulin becomes activated and binds to a variety of cellular target proteins.&nbsp; We found that the BRI1 receptor kinase is one of those targets, and identified a possible functional consequence as calmodulin binding inhibits the activation of BRI1 by autophosphorylation. This mechanism may function to down regulate BRI1 and the growth-promoting brassinosteroid signaling path...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Plants have a large family of receptor-like kinases that control a number of important processes ranging from growth and development to responses to the environment and pathogens. The receptor kinases are proteins embedded in the cell outer (plasma) membrane and transmit signals from the outside of the cell to the interior, without the signal itself entering the cell.  The signals are often molecules (ligands) that bind to the extracellular portion of the receptor kinase.  In plants, this binding induces the receptor kinase to interact with a specific co-receptor kinase, which then results in their mutual activation by a process involving protein phosphorylation but many details of that process are not clear.  Our studies focused on the brassinosteroid hormone receptor kinase, known as BRI1, and its co-receptor kinase, known as BAK1.  All members of the plant receptor kinase family are classified as serine-threonine kinases but BRI1 was known to be a dual-specificity kinase, capable of autophosphorylation on serine, threonine and tyrosine residues.  Protein phosphorylation is a powerful regulatory mechanism in higher organisms, and our results highlight the profound importance seemingly small changes in protein phosphorylation can have on the function of a whole organism.  Our studies established the mechanism of autophosphorylation of BRI1 on tyrosine residues and revealed that phosphorylation of a specific tyrosine residue (Tyr-831) functioned to attenuate receptor kinase signaling in vivo.  Preventing phosphorylation at the tyrosine-831, by substituting a phenylalanine that cannot be phosphorylated, resulted in enhanced signaling through the brassinosteroid pathway and increased plant growth rate. We also identified serine-891, located in the ATP-binding domain, as another site that when phosphorylated results in inhibition of kinase activity.  Both phosphosites are new targets for manipulation to potentially enhance activity of the growth-promoting pathway in crop plants.  Studies with BAK1 established it as a dual-specificity kinase and identified a specific tyrosine residue (Tyr-610) located near the carboxy-terminus of the protein, as a major site of phosphorylation.  The carboxy-terminal polypeptide of BAK1 may be playing a particularly important role.  Our working model is that the carboxy-terminal polypeptide of BAK1 inhibits its protein kinase activity, and that inhibition is relieved when the carboxy-terminal polypeptide binds to BRI1. As a result, the two proteins are properly positioned so that BAK1 can phosphorylate and activate BRI1. Binding to BRI1 appears to be enhanced by phosphorylation of BAK1 at the tyrosine-610 site, but interestingly, prevention of tyrosine-610 phosphorylation does not interfere with brassinosteroid signaling in vivo as might be expected.   These results increase our understanding of how plant receptor kinases function, and may provide a general model for receptor:co-receptor interactions.  Understanding these molecular interactions may also provide novel approaches to engineer signaling pathways in plants.  Finally, our studies identified a potentially new mechanism for cross talk between calcium signaling and receptor kinase signaling. The new mechanism involves binding of calmodulin, which is a highly conserved protein in eukaryotes that functions as a calcium sensor.  When the concentration of free calcium in the cell is elevated (as occurs in response to stress), calmodulin becomes activated and binds to a variety of cellular target proteins.  We found that the BRI1 receptor kinase is one of those targets, and identified a possible functional consequence as calmodulin binding inhibits the activation of BRI1 by autophosphorylation. This mechanism may function to down regulate BRI1 and the growth-promoting brassinosteroid signaling pathway in response to stress, which elevates cytoplasmic calcium, thereby allowing for diversion of cellular energy and resources into stress-mediating ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
