<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TCUP Ecological Ahupuaa Monitoring in Urban Polynesia (TEAM-UP)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2199890.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2499869</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lura Chase</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lchase@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Kapiolani Community College (KCC) is the second largest of 10 public universities and colleges in the University of Hawaii (UH) System. A two-year urban institution, we provide high quality liberal arts and 21st century career programs to a diverse population of Native Hawaiian (NH) and multi-ethnic students and communities. KCC bears the name of Queen Julia Kapiolani, whose motto was "Kulia i ka nuu,"? "To Reach for the Highest." This motto sets the standard for the College?s vision and mission as a learning-centered institution. Likewise, it inspires the proposed TEAM-UP project as we move students progressively to more challenging science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) levels. This new TEAM-UP proposal focuses on Life Sciences that are grounded in the NH ahupuaa (ah-who-poo-ah-ah) at its center. An ahupuaa is a traditional division of land running along the banks of a stream and extending from the mountains to the sea that has been a part of the Hawaiian culture for hundreds of years. It provides an intellectual framework that serves as an excellent touch stone for NH students. This proposal also uses key ?building blocks? of NH knowledge, to contextualize the science of Hawaii?s mountain to sea ecosystems. KCC has benefited from previous NSF grants to build a strong STEM infrastructure that integrates the comprehensive, research-based, STEM Student Support and Success System proposed in this TEAM-UP project.&lt;br/&gt;Goals: The project has two goals: Goal 1) To implement a new STEM Learning Continuum that progressively advances NH students, including those with disabilities, in biology, ecology, biotechnology, eco-engineering, and technology; Goal 2) To implement a NH Community of Practice that connects NH students, mentors, and undergraduate researchers with faculty, researchers, and community partners. The project has ten objectives to achieve these goals, detailed in the proposal, and four major outcomes: 1) creation of a comprehensive and sustainable participant support system for 175 NH students; 2) completion of the ASNS degree in Life Sciences and/or transfer to biological science fields at UH Manoa or UH Hilo by 140 NH students; 3) completion of a STEM baccalaureate degree at UHM or UHH by 100 NH students; and 4) new partnerships with the NH community, the private sector and state government, and opportunities for competitive research in the life sciences will provide a strong foundation for future sustainability and growth of the KCC Life and Physical Sciences program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1023665</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leon</FirstName>
<LastName>Richards</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leon Richards</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lr24@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089567800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000352760</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/28/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/26/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Rand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John D Rand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrand@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8087349776</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000088019</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/28/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/07/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Bautista</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria Bautista</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mariab@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8087349356</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000555875</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Bautista</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria Bautista</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mariab@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8087349356</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000555875</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/28/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/26/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2440 Campus Road, Box 368]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>Tribal College &amp; Univers Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~399922</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~449992</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1349976</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~299979</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The &ldquo;TCUP Ecological Ahupua&rsquo;a Monitoring in Urban Polynesia&rdquo; (TEAM-UP) goals were (1) to implement a new STEM Learning Continuum that advances Native Hawaiian (NH) students in the Life Science fields from a routine methodological expertise to a hypothesis-driven expertise, (2) to implement a NH Community of practice that connects NH students, mentors and undergraduate researches with faculty, researchers, and community partners, and (3) to implement a Math Immersion Model (MIM) providing students with the opportunity to reach calculus level in one semester. The primary objective was to increase enrollment of NHs and other underrepresented minorities in the Associate in Science in Natural Science (ASNS) with concentration in Biological Sciences by using key &ldquo;building blocks&rdquo; of NH knowledge to contextualize the science of Hawaii&rsquo;s mountain to sea ecosystem.</p> <p>For each year of the grant, two Summer Bridge Programs were conducted simultaneously. Summer Ecological Experience at Kapi&rsquo;olani (SEEK), for recent high school graduates, introduced the students to a college level science courses via classroom and fieldwork. In the second bridge, Summer Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE), for students who had completed their first year at KapCC, students experienced conducting hypothesis-driven Undergraduate Research Experience (URE) within the context of traditional Hawaiian land divisions (&ldquo;ahupua&rsquo;a&rdquo; mountain-to-the-reef/sea ecosystems). In both summer bridges, a &ldquo;Mathematics Emporium&rdquo; consisting of a mathematics review and instruction was conducted in the morning, and cultural enrichment was provided by field trips to sites unique to Hawaiian culture and through interactions with NH experts from the community. During the academic year, SEEK students participated in introductory-level undergraduate research projects while qualified SURE students registered in the STEM Research Courses (SCI 295). &nbsp;In addition, they had the opportunity to participate in the MIM program, which combined the content of three semesters of Mathematics courses into one in addition to a research component. The TEAM-UP efforts supported 228 Native Hawaiian and Underrepresented Minority students in Summer Bridge programs, 39 students participated in Summer Internships and 31 presented their research projects in local and national conferences. Thirty-nine students participated in the MIM program with the success rate of 44% in one semester, being twice as high compared to traditional courses compounded success rates at Kapi&rsquo;olani. Seventy students transferred to the four-year University or graduated with the ASNS degree in Biological Sciences and 89 students graduated with a baccalaureate degree.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;Bautista</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The "TCUP Ecological Ahupua?a Monitoring in Urban Polynesia" (TEAM-UP) goals were (1) to implement a new STEM Learning Continuum that advances Native Hawaiian (NH) students in the Life Science fields from a routine methodological expertise to a hypothesis-driven expertise, (2) to implement a NH Community of practice that connects NH students, mentors and undergraduate researches with faculty, researchers, and community partners, and (3) to implement a Math Immersion Model (MIM) providing students with the opportunity to reach calculus level in one semester. The primary objective was to increase enrollment of NHs and other underrepresented minorities in the Associate in Science in Natural Science (ASNS) with concentration in Biological Sciences by using key "building blocks" of NH knowledge to contextualize the science of Hawaii?s mountain to sea ecosystem.  For each year of the grant, two Summer Bridge Programs were conducted simultaneously. Summer Ecological Experience at Kapi?olani (SEEK), for recent high school graduates, introduced the students to a college level science courses via classroom and fieldwork. In the second bridge, Summer Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE), for students who had completed their first year at KapCC, students experienced conducting hypothesis-driven Undergraduate Research Experience (URE) within the context of traditional Hawaiian land divisions ("ahupua?a" mountain-to-the-reef/sea ecosystems). In both summer bridges, a "Mathematics Emporium" consisting of a mathematics review and instruction was conducted in the morning, and cultural enrichment was provided by field trips to sites unique to Hawaiian culture and through interactions with NH experts from the community. During the academic year, SEEK students participated in introductory-level undergraduate research projects while qualified SURE students registered in the STEM Research Courses (SCI 295).  In addition, they had the opportunity to participate in the MIM program, which combined the content of three semesters of Mathematics courses into one in addition to a research component. The TEAM-UP efforts supported 228 Native Hawaiian and Underrepresented Minority students in Summer Bridge programs, 39 students participated in Summer Internships and 31 presented their research projects in local and national conferences. Thirty-nine students participated in the MIM program with the success rate of 44% in one semester, being twice as high compared to traditional courses compounded success rates at Kapi?olani. Seventy students transferred to the four-year University or graduated with the ASNS degree in Biological Sciences and 89 students graduated with a baccalaureate degree.       Last Modified: 12/06/2017       Submitted by: Maria Bautista]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
