<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Theory of Complex Transportation Network Design</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>310000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>310000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eduardo Misawa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emisawa@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925353</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>What is the best design for a transportation network? This question is especially important today because of the pervasive nature of transportation congestion. However, the design of efficient transportation networks is very challenging because of their extraordinary complex nature. That complexity arises from both the immense size of many transportation networks and their intrinsic coupling to social and economic networks that influence transportation patterns. This project will employ a type of mathematical model known as a leader-foll0wer dynamic game to mimic the experience of a metropolitan planning organization (MPO) charged with deciding how to expand and operate a complex urban road network, wherein individual drivers compete for available network capacity and retain considerable autonomy in destination, start time, and route choice for the trips they undertake. The proposed MPO-driver game will be the first mathematical model to explicitly consider the coupled nature of dynamic social, economic, and transportation networks. Through both numerical simulations and mathematical analyses of the dynamic MPO-driver game, it will determine which network architectures and operating rules make a traffic network resilient to incidents such as accidents, signal failures, and inclement weather. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will also explore the role of social networking and ubiquitous personal computing in achieving and maintaining efficient traffic flows. Likewise, it will investigate the role of taxes, tolls, and maintenance in the financial sustainability of road infrastructure. Finally, it will explore what contributions network design can make to the important issue of environmental sustainability. Results of such individual explorations will be combined to create general principles for designing complex road networks. Additionally, via a project website, this project will make available the methodology, including details of game-theoretic mathematical model and solution software, for complex road network design.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1024707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>Friesz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terry L Friesz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tfriesz@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148632445</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Bressan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto Bressan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bressan@math.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651667</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tao</FirstName>
<LastName>Yao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tao Yao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tyy1@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148658040</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490818</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7478</Code>
<Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7552</Code>
<Text>COFFES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7722</Code>
<Text>COMPLEXITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~310000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project has resulted in a computable theory of transportation network design that may be used by interest groups, metropolitan planning organizations, regional transportation authorities, and Federal over sight agencies to compare and design alternative future transportation networks serving large complex urban centers and their surrounds.</span></p> <p><span>Our computable theory of transportation network design is explicitly dynamic in that it recognizes both the day-to-day and the within-day timescales. The day-to-day timescale is used to model the formation of demand for transportation; decisions corresponding to this timescale are primarily the post-dinner decisions by all drivers whether to commute to work the following morning; each such decision includes the route to be followed and the time of departure. The within-day time scale is that of minute-by-minute or second-by-second decisions that alter departure times, routes, and trip purpose. When the two time scales are integrated we have a dual timescale model. The family of models we have developed include single and dual timescale models.</span></p> <p><span>At the heart of our modeling framework is a continuous-time network loading model; it is based on a hydrodynamic network traffic flow model that includes vehicle spillback. Our network loading model describes traffic dynamics arising from given path departure rates and computes the corresponding route travel times. In mathematical language, our network loading model is a system of differential algebraic equations. Its concise statement and ease of solution owes to our use of the Lax formula to express the Lighthill-Whitham-Richards (LWR) partial differential equation describing traffic flow. </span></p> <p><span>The aforementioned network loading model provides route delays for a dynamic user equilibrium (DUE) model, which is a Nash-like noncooperative game in normal form. The network loading model is embedded within the DUE model; as such the overall modeling framework is &ldquo;simultaneous&rdquo; and not &ldquo;sequential&rdquo; in its calculation of route choice, departure time, and route delay.</span></p> <p><span>The complete DUE model is a within-day model that takes the form of a differential variational inequality in continuous time for which travel demand may be updated on a day-to-day time scale. An alternative for of the complete DUE model treats elastic travel demand and boundedly rational selection of routes by users.</span></p> <p><span>The modeling paradigm described above has been combined with a variety of solution methods and solved in both continuous and discrete time. Among the solution methods studied are fixed point, proximal point and gap function algorithms. These algorithms have been studied from a theoretical (not numerical) perspective as stipulated in the Building Engineered Complex Systems (BECS) call for proposals that resulted in this award.</span></p> <p><span>The DUE theory we have described was created to facilitate the construction of Stackelberg network design games. Among the Stackelberg-type design models studied are the capacity addition problem, the link addition problem, the traffic signal setting problem, the urban supply chain management problem, and the emission control problem. In each case we developed mathematical formulations along with existence results, exposition of promising algorithms, and regularity conditions promoting algorithm convergence. No numerical calculations were undertaken, in keeping with the BECS theory-only stipulation.</span></p> <p><span>The design model thrust of our research is exemplified by our continuum approximation of the traffic signal setting problem. Our approach is novel in that we introduced a linear decision rule (LDR) for real time signal control, along with which we integrated a vehicle emissions model within the network loading model (of the complete DUE ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has resulted in a computable theory of transportation network design that may be used by interest groups, metropolitan planning organizations, regional transportation authorities, and Federal over sight agencies to compare and design alternative future transportation networks serving large complex urban centers and their surrounds.  Our computable theory of transportation network design is explicitly dynamic in that it recognizes both the day-to-day and the within-day timescales. The day-to-day timescale is used to model the formation of demand for transportation; decisions corresponding to this timescale are primarily the post-dinner decisions by all drivers whether to commute to work the following morning; each such decision includes the route to be followed and the time of departure. The within-day time scale is that of minute-by-minute or second-by-second decisions that alter departure times, routes, and trip purpose. When the two time scales are integrated we have a dual timescale model. The family of models we have developed include single and dual timescale models.  At the heart of our modeling framework is a continuous-time network loading model; it is based on a hydrodynamic network traffic flow model that includes vehicle spillback. Our network loading model describes traffic dynamics arising from given path departure rates and computes the corresponding route travel times. In mathematical language, our network loading model is a system of differential algebraic equations. Its concise statement and ease of solution owes to our use of the Lax formula to express the Lighthill-Whitham-Richards (LWR) partial differential equation describing traffic flow.   The aforementioned network loading model provides route delays for a dynamic user equilibrium (DUE) model, which is a Nash-like noncooperative game in normal form. The network loading model is embedded within the DUE model; as such the overall modeling framework is "simultaneous" and not "sequential" in its calculation of route choice, departure time, and route delay.  The complete DUE model is a within-day model that takes the form of a differential variational inequality in continuous time for which travel demand may be updated on a day-to-day time scale. An alternative for of the complete DUE model treats elastic travel demand and boundedly rational selection of routes by users.  The modeling paradigm described above has been combined with a variety of solution methods and solved in both continuous and discrete time. Among the solution methods studied are fixed point, proximal point and gap function algorithms. These algorithms have been studied from a theoretical (not numerical) perspective as stipulated in the Building Engineered Complex Systems (BECS) call for proposals that resulted in this award.  The DUE theory we have described was created to facilitate the construction of Stackelberg network design games. Among the Stackelberg-type design models studied are the capacity addition problem, the link addition problem, the traffic signal setting problem, the urban supply chain management problem, and the emission control problem. In each case we developed mathematical formulations along with existence results, exposition of promising algorithms, and regularity conditions promoting algorithm convergence. No numerical calculations were undertaken, in keeping with the BECS theory-only stipulation.  The design model thrust of our research is exemplified by our continuum approximation of the traffic signal setting problem. Our approach is novel in that we introduced a linear decision rule (LDR) for real time signal control, along with which we integrated a vehicle emissions model within the network loading model (of the complete DUE model). The emissions model was introduced to allow investigations of environmental impacts associated with signal control in the in the interest of sustainability.                  Last Modified: 10/13/2015       Submitted b...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
