<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dakota Defenders Information Assurance Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1304492.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1514913</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpiotrow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dakota State University (DSU) proposes to create the Dakota Defenders Information Assurance Scholarship Program for undergraduate students in the Computer and Network Security (CONS) degree program and to host three cohorts of Scholarship for Service (SFS) students. This project increases national research and development capabilities in Information Assurance (IA) and produces new entrants to the federal government workforce. The CONS program includes extensive hands-on technical exercises in offensive security practices in hardware, operating systems, networks, databases, and software. All Dakota Defenders take part in innovative mechanisms of community building such as the Student Research Initiative (SRI), the Security Group of the ACM Computer Club, InfraGard meetings, and the North Central Region of the Collegiate Cyber Defense Competition. The Dakota Defenders program strives to serve women interested in Information Assurance by recruiting applicants from the University's 35 current members in the Women in Science and Technology group. Program graduates are well-versed in security policy, infrastructure operations, and defensive programming and exhibit strong oral and written communication skills.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1026114</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Streff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin F Streff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kevin.Streff@dsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6052565077</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000402349</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Pauli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua J Pauli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Josh.Pauli@dsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6052565181</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416749</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dakota State University</Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<ZipCode>570421799</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6052565112</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>820 N. Washington Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929923506</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>929538999</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dakota State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>570421799</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[820 N. Washington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1668</Code>
<Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>K627</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7254</Code>
<Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~726499</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~432539</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~337800</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~18075</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The DSU Cyber Corps supported 29 students in the 4 years of this initial award. We successfully placed 100% of our interns and full-time employees as part of the program and have created meaningful partnerships with the National Security Agency (NSA), Johns Hopkins University's Applied Physics Labratory (JHU-APL), US Cyber Command, Navy SPAWAR, and the State of South Dakota.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also recieved supplemental funding during the award lifetime for the GenCyber Summer Camp project to provide summer camps for high school students as supported by NSF and NSA. We are also part of the INSuRE project with Purdue University that provides research projects for DSU graduate students (masters and doctorate) and an agency/lab Technical Director to help guide the research.&nbsp;</p> <p>We received our NSF-SFS CyberCorps renewal in August 2014 for four more years of project funding and look forward to continuing and expanding our role with the program. In February 2015, we started working with St. Cloud State University in St. Cloud, MN as a mentor as they are a new institution to the NSF-SFS Cyber Corps program. We (DSU &amp; SCSU) also plan to work together on a consortium for community colleges as supported by NSF-SFS in the coming year.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pauli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The DSU Cyber Corps supported 29 students in the 4 years of this initial award. We successfully placed 100% of our interns and full-time employees as part of the program and have created meaningful partnerships with the National Security Agency (NSA), Johns Hopkins University's Applied Physics Labratory (JHU-APL), US Cyber Command, Navy SPAWAR, and the State of South Dakota.   We also recieved supplemental funding during the award lifetime for the GenCyber Summer Camp project to provide summer camps for high school students as supported by NSF and NSA. We are also part of the INSuRE project with Purdue University that provides research projects for DSU graduate students (masters and doctorate) and an agency/lab Technical Director to help guide the research.   We received our NSF-SFS CyberCorps renewal in August 2014 for four more years of project funding and look forward to continuing and expanding our role with the program. In February 2015, we started working with St. Cloud State University in St. Cloud, MN as a mentor as they are a new institution to the NSF-SFS Cyber Corps program. We (DSU &amp; SCSU) also plan to work together on a consortium for community colleges as supported by NSF-SFS in the coming year.        Last Modified: 03/01/2015       Submitted by: Joshua J Pauli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
