<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Polar Year Legacy: Workshop to Integrate and Document the Lessons of IPY 2007-2008</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>465000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>465000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Isern</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aisern@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928500</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Academy of Sciences (NAS), with resources, staff support, and oversight provided by the NAS Polar Research Board (PRB) is proposing a synthesis activity for U.S. efforts, accomplishments, and lessons learned during IPY 2007-2008. The workshop will use a theme approach to facilitate integration and illustrate how IPY combined to move forward polar understanding. The workshop will feature invited presentations, discussions, and breakout group synthesis, to explore issues such as the research capacity and data that resulted from IPY, the value added lessons from international partnerships and education efforts, and the scientific discoveries made, especially related to the role of the polar regions in the global earth system. The workshop will be organized by an ad hoc committee of volunteer experts appointed by the NAS, with resources, staff support, and oversight provided by the PRB, the U.S. National Committee to IPY. The appointed committee will reflect a diversity of expertise and experience. The workshop will result in a peer reviewed National Academies report. The intended impact is to leave a record of IPY 2007-2008 for current decision makers, future scholars, and polar enthusiasts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The PRB will appoint a diverse planning committee and involve diverse workshop participants. The workshop will strive to foster partnerships amongst researchers and will bring to the public and policy makers an understanding of what took place, why, and how the IPY foundation might be built upon for future endeavors. The PRB will use the tools of the NAS to ensure broad dissemination of the resulting report and will prepare Reports in Brief for easy distribution (both in the U.S. and to our international partners).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1026273</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Elfring</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chris Elfring</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>celfring@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023343426</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000312462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 FIFTH STREET NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5130</Code>
<Text>ANT Coordination &amp; Information</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5201</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~465000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>International Polar Year 2007-2008 (IPY) was an intense, coordinated field campaign of observations, research, and analysis. With the completion of the main, fieldwork phase of IPY, a National Research Council (NRC) committee was commissioned in 2010 to write a report that highlights the outcomes of the multi-faceted IPY campaign from a U.S. perspective, integrates the lessons from different activities, and records U.S. IPY efforts so they are available to a broad audience.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To gather input from the wider scientific community, the NRC committee organized a special two day workshop in June 2011 that engaged more than 70 people from the polar research community and beyond. The committee&rsquo;s final product was a report entitled &ldquo;Lessons and Legacies of International Polar Year 2007-2008,&rdquo; which is organized around five main themes: the Human Element of IPY, Scientific Advances and Discoveries, Scientific Tools and Infrastructure, Knowledge to Action, and Reflections.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As the report describes, overall, IPY was an outstanding success. IPY engaged the public to communicate the relevance of polar research to the entire planet, strengthened connections with the Indigenous people of the Arctic, and established new observational networks. Activities at both poles led to scientific discoveries that provided a step change in scientific understanding and helped translate scientific knowledge into policy-relevant information&mdash;and at a time when the polar regions are undergoing a transformation from an icy wilderness to a new zone for human affairs, these insights could not be more timely or more relevant. From outreach activities that engaged the general public to projects that brought researchers from multiple disciplines and several nations together, the legacies of IPY extend far beyond the scientific results achieved, and valuable lessons learned from the process will guide future endeavors of similar magnitude.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The report can be found here: <a href="http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Lessons-Legacies-International/13321">http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Lessons-Legacies-International/13321</a>. This website includes a listing of key findings, a report in brief and a recording of webinar given by the committee co-chairs. This website has been redone as part of this study effort and describes multiple activities of the National Academies related to IPY: <a href="http://nas-sites.org/us-ipy/">http://nas-sites.org/us-ipy/</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, the broader impact of the work of the National Research Council is to ensure that the best possible science is available in the public policy arena. Recommendations from NRC reports have helped steer public policy, government programs, and academic institutions. This Committee's report will help inform policy and government programs related to the poles, as well as contribute to the Nation's understanding of the value of polar science and the activities undertaken as part of International Polar Year 2007-2008.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/03/2013<br>      Modified by: Chris&nbsp;Elfring</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ International Polar Year 2007-2008 (IPY) was an intense, coordinated field campaign of observations, research, and analysis. With the completion of the main, fieldwork phase of IPY, a National Research Council (NRC) committee was commissioned in 2010 to write a report that highlights the outcomes of the multi-faceted IPY campaign from a U.S. perspective, integrates the lessons from different activities, and records U.S. IPY efforts so they are available to a broad audience.     To gather input from the wider scientific community, the NRC committee organized a special two day workshop in June 2011 that engaged more than 70 people from the polar research community and beyond. The committeeÆs final product was a report entitled "Lessons and Legacies of International Polar Year 2007-2008," which is organized around five main themes: the Human Element of IPY, Scientific Advances and Discoveries, Scientific Tools and Infrastructure, Knowledge to Action, and Reflections.     As the report describes, overall, IPY was an outstanding success. IPY engaged the public to communicate the relevance of polar research to the entire planet, strengthened connections with the Indigenous people of the Arctic, and established new observational networks. Activities at both poles led to scientific discoveries that provided a step change in scientific understanding and helped translate scientific knowledge into policy-relevant information&mdash;and at a time when the polar regions are undergoing a transformation from an icy wilderness to a new zone for human affairs, these insights could not be more timely or more relevant. From outreach activities that engaged the general public to projects that brought researchers from multiple disciplines and several nations together, the legacies of IPY extend far beyond the scientific results achieved, and valuable lessons learned from the process will guide future endeavors of similar magnitude.     The report can be found here: http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Lessons-Legacies-International/13321. This website includes a listing of key findings, a report in brief and a recording of webinar given by the committee co-chairs. This website has been redone as part of this study effort and describes multiple activities of the National Academies related to IPY: http://nas-sites.org/us-ipy/     Overall, the broader impact of the work of the National Research Council is to ensure that the best possible science is available in the public policy arena. Recommendations from NRC reports have helped steer public policy, government programs, and academic institutions. This Committee's report will help inform policy and government programs related to the poles, as well as contribute to the Nation's understanding of the value of polar science and the activities undertaken as part of International Polar Year 2007-2008.       Last Modified: 04/03/2013       Submitted by: Chris Elfring]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
