<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UBM-Group, RUI: BioMaPS (Biology and Mathematics in Population Studies) II</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Zia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lzia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925140</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project builds on a previous UBM project (0531885) at Murray State University (MSU). To foster the development of professionals who understand the mathematics behind the biology and the biological implications of mathematical models, the Biology and Mathematics in Population Studies program (BioMaPS) II at MSU is providing a collaborative research environment for mathematics and biology undergraduates to investigate patterns in plants and animal populations. Under the mentorship of BioMaPS II faculty, 12 students over a three-year period are being equipped with skills to investigate such patterns and to develop accurate models of biomedical and ecological phenomena by engaging in transformative projects that analyze stability and controllability of population dynamics. Within this intensive year-long research experience, students attend BioMaPS meetings and national workshops with research mentors and nationally recognized experts. Collegiate and high school presentations give the BioMaPS students experience in explaining their research to non-specialists, while professional presentations at regional and national symposia help students formulate and articulate their discoveries to an expert audience.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The BioMaPS II program advances discovery at the intersection of mathematics and biology and promotes the integration of research and teaching by engaging students and faculty as both researchers and teachers. The projects include modeling of ecological and evolutionary processes relating to biophysical traits of invasive plants, genetic diversity, climate change impacts in the tropics, and emerging infectious diseases. All projects focus on mathematical and biological questions that are of current and significant importance to the disciplines studied.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Nine faculty investigators across two disciplines with different but complementary backgrounds collaborate on this project. These collaborators have mentored over 175 undergraduates, who have given over 140 research presentations with results in 40 publications, a record of success upon which the BioMaPS II program continues to build. The program is continuing to strengthen existing partnerships with Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory, Hancock Biological Station, and NIMBioS, as well as to foster the development of new partnerships.  The BioMaPS II program is making an interesting and challenging area of study available to students through curriculum reform - a Mathematical Biology minor is being designed to complement a successful Biomathematics area of concentration that was introduced in 2007. These BioMaPS II directives impact approximately 200 university calculus and biology students each academic year, and more than 100 local high school students and their teachers through outreach endeavors.  The program creates avenues for future collaborative courses across the STEM disciplines at Murray State University, with opportunities to extend the courses to state and national institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1028125</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>Derting</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terry L Derting</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tderting@murraystate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2708096327</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Whiteman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard H Whiteman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hwhiteman@murraystate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2708096753</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000217682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Fister</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine R Fister</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>renee.fister@murraystate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2708092491</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000342705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kate</FirstName>
<LastName>He</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kate He</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kate.he@murraystate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2708093135</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000555451</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Croteau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily K Croteau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ekcroteau@valdosta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2293335773</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000555806</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Murray State University</Name>
<CityName>Murray</CityName>
<ZipCode>420713318</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2708093534</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>328 Wells Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041980632</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MURRAY STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041980632</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Murray State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Murray</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>420713318</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[328 Wells Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7317</Code>
<Text>INTERDISC TRNG IN BIO &amp; MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7904</Code>
<Text>UBM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The BioMaPS (Biology and Mathematics in Population Studies) II program advances discovery at the intersection of mathematics and biology.&nbsp; Students and faculty teams work on interdisciplinary projects that ask innovative questions from biological and mathematical viewpoints.&nbsp; The projects analyze population dynamics relating to biophysical traits in invasive plants, genetic diversity, climate change impacts, delay dynamics in cancer studies, and emerging infection diseases.&nbsp; The teams of two to four students work with at least one mathematics and one biology faculty member on proposal development, the actual research, and the final report.&nbsp; Our student BioMaPS fellows with half male and half female participants have been involved in work associated with 35 publications and have given 15 presentations at local, regional, and national venues over the last three years.&nbsp; The faculty and students have submitted 10 other research grants related to the topics at hand.</p> <p>The monthly BioMaPS seminar has granted 75 faculty and approximately 900 students the opportunity to learn from the students about their research and to hear from other experts from the National Science Foundation, Virginai Commonwealth University, Appalachian State University, NIMBioS, University of Tennessee, Old Dominion University, Marymount University, Mississippi State University, Ohio State University, Dartmouth College, College of Charleston, and University of Alberta.&nbsp; The development of a biomathematics area for students to study and particular courses that enhance mathematical biology principles have involved students in multiple STEM disciplines.&nbsp; The students and faculty have made their research available to the local K-12 school systems through Math and Science clubs and interactive programs to increase the excitement for STEM disciplines.&nbsp; Additionally, the assessment of the program through normalized, national assessments has provided a template for others in our university to follow and has been disseminated through presentations to respected national organziations.&nbsp; The emphasis on student learning through the interaction of biology and mathematical research has created opportunities for change within our programs and with the inclusion of other disciplines. &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2014<br>      Modified by: Katherine&nbsp;R&nbsp;Fister</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1028125/1028125_10019884_1407772740836_BioMaPSgroup2012--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1028125/1028125_10019884_1407772740836_BioMaPSgroup2012--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BioMaPS group"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1028125/1028125_10019884_1407772740836_BioMaPSgroup2012--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BioMaPS group"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is the faculty and student Fellows for the BioMaPS program from 2012.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Murray State University</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katherine&nbsp;R&nbsp;Fister</div> <div class="imageTitle">BioMaPS group</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1028125/1028125_10019884_1407772844119_Glenna--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1028125/1028125_10019884_1407772844119_Glenna--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Math student harvesting salamanders"><img src="/p...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The BioMaPS (Biology and Mathematics in Population Studies) II program advances discovery at the intersection of mathematics and biology.  Students and faculty teams work on interdisciplinary projects that ask innovative questions from biological and mathematical viewpoints.  The projects analyze population dynamics relating to biophysical traits in invasive plants, genetic diversity, climate change impacts, delay dynamics in cancer studies, and emerging infection diseases.  The teams of two to four students work with at least one mathematics and one biology faculty member on proposal development, the actual research, and the final report.  Our student BioMaPS fellows with half male and half female participants have been involved in work associated with 35 publications and have given 15 presentations at local, regional, and national venues over the last three years.  The faculty and students have submitted 10 other research grants related to the topics at hand.  The monthly BioMaPS seminar has granted 75 faculty and approximately 900 students the opportunity to learn from the students about their research and to hear from other experts from the National Science Foundation, Virginai Commonwealth University, Appalachian State University, NIMBioS, University of Tennessee, Old Dominion University, Marymount University, Mississippi State University, Ohio State University, Dartmouth College, College of Charleston, and University of Alberta.  The development of a biomathematics area for students to study and particular courses that enhance mathematical biology principles have involved students in multiple STEM disciplines.  The students and faculty have made their research available to the local K-12 school systems through Math and Science clubs and interactive programs to increase the excitement for STEM disciplines.  Additionally, the assessment of the program through normalized, national assessments has provided a template for others in our university to follow and has been disseminated through presentations to respected national organziations.  The emphasis on student learning through the interaction of biology and mathematical research has created opportunities for change within our programs and with the inclusion of other disciplines.              Last Modified: 12/01/2014       Submitted by: Katherine R Fister]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
