<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Trabecular bone ontogeny and locomotor development in humans and non-human primates</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>184068.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184068</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Analyses of bone structure in living and extinct primates typically assume a direct relationship between bone form and function even though the mechanisms of bone's adaptive response to loads is not fully understood. The primary objective of this project is collecting comparative age-related data on the development of bone from a number of locations in the postcranial skeleton of humans, chimpanzees, and macaques to test an explanatory model for the patterns of change associated with locomotor development in these species.  This project quantifies the changes in trabecular bone microstructure and elastic properties during ontogeny in humans, chimpanzees, and macaques using high-resolution computed tomography (CT) scan data in the postcranial skeleton. The relative contributions of locomotor loading, body mass, sex, and age on the development of trabecular and cortical bone structure are examined, as are kinematic and kinetic analyses of locomotor ontogeny in a sample of juvenile modern humans to relate structural changes to changes in locomotion in humans.  By quantifying the ontogenetic changes in bone structure across three different primates with divergent locomotor behaviors and developmental trajectories, the role of general developmental processes, genetic patterning, and the mechanical loading environment on bone structure are more clearly defined. The simultaneous analysis of locomotor development, bone structural and mechanical adaptations, and within and between species variation is unique and produces a more concrete understanding of bone functional morphology. Ultimately, this study will provide insight into the adaptive response of trabecular bone to mechanical loads and will provide important information regarding the functional utility of trabecular bone structure in the mammalian skeleton. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study contributes to the training of undergraduate and graduate students at three universities, results in the production of a large comparative dataset of high-resolution CT and kinematic data for use by other researchers and for incorporation into the biological anthropology curriculum, has direct relevance for understanding the normal and pathological locomotor system in children and adults and will be of broad interest in orthopedics, internal medicine, bone metabolism, and biomechanics, and, finally, the results of this study will also contribute relevant data to the understanding of the prevalent health conditions of osteoporosis and osteoarthritis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1028793</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Gosman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James H Gosman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gosman.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142923732</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000279278</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~72876</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~111192</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has created a very large imaging-based dataset on human (and non-human primate) skeletal development for a locomotor suite of anatomical elements, including the humerus, vertebra, proximal and distal femur, and proximal and distal tibia. These data include both trabecular and cortical bone. New methods have been developed to analyze and quantify bone developmental morphology, bone accrual and loss, and biomechanical competence. Both the data and methods have direct relevance to research questions of concern to Anthropology, including skeletal biology, bioarchaeology, paleoanthropology, locomotion, and issues of human variation. Data outcomes from this project have resulted in a total of over twenty podium/poster presentations, symposium participations, published peer-reviewed journal articles, and book chapters.</p> <p>A key component of this project lies in developing concepts and skills of bone imaging and quantification involving bone developmental biology for graduate students in the disciplines of anthropology and anatomy. Our research agenda, data, and methods have directly led to newly approved (and ongoing) dissertation research projects for graduate students in anthropology.</p> <p>Our developmental data on bone structural change have a clear translational relevance to medical clinicians interested in early bone gain and later loss, as well as fracture risk and care. In addition these data, demonstrating the age-specificity of biomechanical competence of long bones, may be of interest to the Department of Defense (blast injuries), space exploration/travel, the automotive industry (childhood crash injury prevention), and sports-training experts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/02/2015<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Gosman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has created a very large imaging-based dataset on human (and non-human primate) skeletal development for a locomotor suite of anatomical elements, including the humerus, vertebra, proximal and distal femur, and proximal and distal tibia. These data include both trabecular and cortical bone. New methods have been developed to analyze and quantify bone developmental morphology, bone accrual and loss, and biomechanical competence. Both the data and methods have direct relevance to research questions of concern to Anthropology, including skeletal biology, bioarchaeology, paleoanthropology, locomotion, and issues of human variation. Data outcomes from this project have resulted in a total of over twenty podium/poster presentations, symposium participations, published peer-reviewed journal articles, and book chapters.  A key component of this project lies in developing concepts and skills of bone imaging and quantification involving bone developmental biology for graduate students in the disciplines of anthropology and anatomy. Our research agenda, data, and methods have directly led to newly approved (and ongoing) dissertation research projects for graduate students in anthropology.  Our developmental data on bone structural change have a clear translational relevance to medical clinicians interested in early bone gain and later loss, as well as fracture risk and care. In addition these data, demonstrating the age-specificity of biomechanical competence of long bones, may be of interest to the Department of Defense (blast injuries), space exploration/travel, the automotive industry (childhood crash injury prevention), and sports-training experts.           Last Modified: 11/02/2015       Submitted by: James H Gosman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
