<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:  Exploration of the presence and ecological significance of viral pathogens in the dynamics of Daphnia, a major pelagic grazer</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>107100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alan Tessier</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>atessier@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927198</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Little is known about the identity or ecological significance of viruses in freshwater ecosystems, despite well-known disease effects of viruses on plants and animals in other ecosystems.  This EAGER project makes the prediction that viruses are a widespread and important component of the food web of lakes.  The research will measure the diversity and abundance of viruses that infect the dominant consumers of algal production in lakes, the crustacean zooplankton.  While much is understood about the factors regulating the abundance of zooplankton in lakes, viruses have been almost entirely invisible to the approaches used.  It is only recently that techniques have been developed capable of identifying the DNA sequences of uncultivated viruses, and permitting identification of viruses that infect zooplankton.  Because there are currently no described viruses of freshwater zooplankton, and because of the high cost of obtaining viral DNA sequences, sufficient background data do not exist to justify a wider study of zooplankton viruses.  Thus, this research will break new ground by determining the identity, infection rate, and distribution of viruses infecting Daphnia, a dominant freshwater crustacean in lakes world-wide.  The viral infection rate within host populations will be investigated seasonally in Oneida Lake, New York, where extensive data on Daphnia dynamics already exist.  Data on viruses will be compared with birth and death rates of zooplankton to understand the role of viruses in seasonal changes of zooplankton abundance.  The spatial distribution of viruses in Oneida Lake, and in other nearby lakes will also be examined.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project represents a new, interdisciplinary collaboration between a virologist and an aquatic ecologist.  Newly discovered viral genes will be made freely available to the wider scientific community for comparison to studies conducted elsewhere, which will expand our knowledge of the ecological significance of viral diversity.  This project will also involve several undergraduate students who will receive research training in field ecology and microbiology, including cutting-edge molecular biological techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1028898</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nelson</FirstName>
<LastName>Hairston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nelson G Hairston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ngh1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072544231</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000324784</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>Hewson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ian Hewson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hewson@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072550151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499940</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~7100</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We investigated the presence and ecological significance of viruses in Daphnia, an important pelagic grazer in freshwater ecosystems. We used a metagenomic approach to identify viruses of Daphnia in Oneida and Cayuga Lakes (upstate New York). We identified several highly represented putative eukaryotic circular single-stranded deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) viral genomes. Amongst these, we discovered a genotype similar in both sequence and genomic architecture to a virus previously reported from a hyperthermal lake that shares characteristics of both single-stranded ribonucleic acid (RNA) and single-stranded DNA viruses. We used quantitative polymerase chain reactions to study the prevalence and viral load of both positive-sense and negative-sense strands of the Daphnia mendotae- associated (Cladocera) Hybrid Virus (DMClaHV) over a summer season in Oneida and Cayuga Lakes. DMClaHV had high prevalence within Daphnia populations, where viral load and the proportion of virus-positive individuals were higher preceding host population decline. DMClaHV viral load was different between two species of Daphnia (D. mendotae and D. retrocurva), and the dynamics between viruses and their hosts varied between the two lakes. We detected DMClaHV in eggs (ephippia) retrieved from Oneida Lake sediments with an estimated age of 30 yr. Using transmission electron microscopy, we observed small (20 nm diameter) virus-like particles in an ecologically dominant freshwater consumer, the cladoceran Daphnia, that were well away from gut tissues and not associated with intracellular parasites. Because Daphnia plays a critical role in many lake ecosystems, DMClaHV may have important effects on herbivory and thus carbon flow through the lake ecosystem. This is the first report of viruses in any freshwater zooplankton, and is the first application of a combined viral metagenomics and quantitative ecology approach to understand how uncultivated viruses impact their hosts.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/14/2013<br>      Modified by: Ian&nbsp;Hewson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We investigated the presence and ecological significance of viruses in Daphnia, an important pelagic grazer in freshwater ecosystems. We used a metagenomic approach to identify viruses of Daphnia in Oneida and Cayuga Lakes (upstate New York). We identified several highly represented putative eukaryotic circular single-stranded deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) viral genomes. Amongst these, we discovered a genotype similar in both sequence and genomic architecture to a virus previously reported from a hyperthermal lake that shares characteristics of both single-stranded ribonucleic acid (RNA) and single-stranded DNA viruses. We used quantitative polymerase chain reactions to study the prevalence and viral load of both positive-sense and negative-sense strands of the Daphnia mendotae- associated (Cladocera) Hybrid Virus (DMClaHV) over a summer season in Oneida and Cayuga Lakes. DMClaHV had high prevalence within Daphnia populations, where viral load and the proportion of virus-positive individuals were higher preceding host population decline. DMClaHV viral load was different between two species of Daphnia (D. mendotae and D. retrocurva), and the dynamics between viruses and their hosts varied between the two lakes. We detected DMClaHV in eggs (ephippia) retrieved from Oneida Lake sediments with an estimated age of 30 yr. Using transmission electron microscopy, we observed small (20 nm diameter) virus-like particles in an ecologically dominant freshwater consumer, the cladoceran Daphnia, that were well away from gut tissues and not associated with intracellular parasites. Because Daphnia plays a critical role in many lake ecosystems, DMClaHV may have important effects on herbivory and thus carbon flow through the lake ecosystem. This is the first report of viruses in any freshwater zooplankton, and is the first application of a combined viral metagenomics and quantitative ecology approach to understand how uncultivated viruses impact their hosts.       Last Modified: 08/14/2013       Submitted by: Ian Hewson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
