<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Long term impacts of grass invasions and fire on community change and plant soil feedbacks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>564953.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>587453</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the past twenty years, scientists, land managers and the public have come to recognize the dramatic consequences of species invasions. Despite this recognition, few studies have documented long-term ecosystem consequences of invasions when those invasions go unchecked. The proposed research evaluates long-term impacts of fire-promoting grasses in seasonally dry woodlands in Hawai'i. These grasses, originally introduced as pasture forage, escaped into wildlands where they promote the spread of fire. Native species in these sites are not fire-adapted resulting in a dramatic loss of native species and strongly altered nutrient cycling including losses of nitrogen, a critical resource for plant growth.  The proposed research uses observations and experimentation to evaluate how invader-induced changes in ecosystem nitrogen cycling that were well documented in the 1990s, have changed over time since invasion and what the consequences of current growth conditions are for native species. Experiments will evaluate nitrogen loss rates over time, changes in soil carbon pools and the consequences of these changes for native and non-native species. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fire-promoting non-native grasses are a significant management concern in arid and semi-arid ecosystems. The results of this research will provide greater understanding of the long-term consequences of not managing these invasions both in terms of fuel loads and soil nutrient conditions and in terms of whether native species will eventually recover in burned invaded sites under fire suppression. Lastly, results will provide site specific information regarding which native species and restoration treatments can be used in sites degraded by fire and grass invasion.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1029168</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carla</FirstName>
<LastName>D'Antonio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carla M D'Antonio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dantonio@es.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058932796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000118578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Research]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~214284</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~196607</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~169062</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Invasions by non-native plant species into unmanaged ecosystems can change the functioning of those systems in substantial ways. For example, stands of invasive trees can transpire enormous amounts of water thereby lowering groundwater. Invasive grasses can increase the continuity of flammable material on the landscape thereby increasing fire occurrence, spread rate, and size.&nbsp; It has been suggested that many aggressive invaders create positive feedbacks that contribute to their own success making their management challenging.&nbsp; While invasive plants now dominate many ecosystems, there has been surprisingly little research on whether impacts persist over long time scales (&gt;20 years) without management or whether they decline over time.&nbsp; This is an important missing link in our understanding of invader impacts:&nbsp; if the ecosystem impacts of a non-native species change over the course of invasion, this may lead to misdirected management strategies. This research project took advantage of past research on the impacts of alien grass invasions into Hawaiian dry forests to ask whether initial effects persisted over decadal time scales, and what this might mean for ecosystem management.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Investigators returned to dry forest sites in Hawai'i Volcanoes National Park that were invaded by exotic grasses in the 1960&rsquo;s and then burned in grass-fueled fires in the 1970s and 80s. The ecosystem consequences of invasion and fire were studied intensively in the 1990&rsquo;s by the lead PI and her students, and it was found that fires drive the conversion of native woodlands to African grass-dominated savannas. The African grass that dominates after fire suppresses native woody plant recovery and has high leaf litter turnover resulting in high soil nitrogen availability compared to the unburned forest. The grasses themselves thrive with high available soil nitrogen. Thus the grasses appeared to create a positive feedback to their own growth. Yet, their growth, leaf area, and productivity could not compensate for that lost with the removal of native woody species resulting in overall low ecosystem productivity throughout the 1990s. In the current research, we asked: &nbsp;(1) How has the impact of these invasive grasses on nitrogen cycling and ecosystem productivity changed since the1990s? (2) What plant species may be able to come into this ecosystem and how might those species change the ecosystem? (3) How can management increase the presence of native plant species in the ecosystem?&nbsp; And (4) what are the consequences of restoring different canopy tree species to these sites?&nbsp; We returned to these African-grass dominated sites and compared them to remnant, unburned native dry forest sites and burned areas that had been planted with native canopy trees.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We found that soil nitrogen cycling rates and N availability were no longer different between the African grass savannas and the woodland from which they were derived and that grass cover and biomass had declined compared to the 1990s. Yet experimental field planting of a suite of native and non-native woody plants showed that African grasses were still competitive against native woody plants despite their lower size.&nbsp;&nbsp; Thus the decline in soil N and in grass cover still did not benefit native species. Instead, the species that benefited most from current conditions was an invasive tree <em>Morella faya</em>. This nitrogen-fixing tree has high growth rates, and was best-suited to invade the current low N ecosystem.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We also re-measured ecosystem net primary productivity and standing pools of carbon and...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Invasions by non-native plant species into unmanaged ecosystems can change the functioning of those systems in substantial ways. For example, stands of invasive trees can transpire enormous amounts of water thereby lowering groundwater. Invasive grasses can increase the continuity of flammable material on the landscape thereby increasing fire occurrence, spread rate, and size.  It has been suggested that many aggressive invaders create positive feedbacks that contribute to their own success making their management challenging.  While invasive plants now dominate many ecosystems, there has been surprisingly little research on whether impacts persist over long time scales (&gt;20 years) without management or whether they decline over time.  This is an important missing link in our understanding of invader impacts:  if the ecosystem impacts of a non-native species change over the course of invasion, this may lead to misdirected management strategies. This research project took advantage of past research on the impacts of alien grass invasions into Hawaiian dry forests to ask whether initial effects persisted over decadal time scales, and what this might mean for ecosystem management.                  Investigators returned to dry forest sites in Hawai'i Volcanoes National Park that were invaded by exotic grasses in the 1960Æs and then burned in grass-fueled fires in the 1970s and 80s. The ecosystem consequences of invasion and fire were studied intensively in the 1990Æs by the lead PI and her students, and it was found that fires drive the conversion of native woodlands to African grass-dominated savannas. The African grass that dominates after fire suppresses native woody plant recovery and has high leaf litter turnover resulting in high soil nitrogen availability compared to the unburned forest. The grasses themselves thrive with high available soil nitrogen. Thus the grasses appeared to create a positive feedback to their own growth. Yet, their growth, leaf area, and productivity could not compensate for that lost with the removal of native woody species resulting in overall low ecosystem productivity throughout the 1990s. In the current research, we asked:  (1) How has the impact of these invasive grasses on nitrogen cycling and ecosystem productivity changed since the1990s? (2) What plant species may be able to come into this ecosystem and how might those species change the ecosystem? (3) How can management increase the presence of native plant species in the ecosystem?  And (4) what are the consequences of restoring different canopy tree species to these sites?  We returned to these African-grass dominated sites and compared them to remnant, unburned native dry forest sites and burned areas that had been planted with native canopy trees.                  We found that soil nitrogen cycling rates and N availability were no longer different between the African grass savannas and the woodland from which they were derived and that grass cover and biomass had declined compared to the 1990s. Yet experimental field planting of a suite of native and non-native woody plants showed that African grasses were still competitive against native woody plants despite their lower size.   Thus the decline in soil N and in grass cover still did not benefit native species. Instead, the species that benefited most from current conditions was an invasive tree Morella faya. This nitrogen-fixing tree has high growth rates, and was best-suited to invade the current low N ecosystem.                  We also re-measured ecosystem net primary productivity and standing pools of carbon and nitrogen in the various habitats. We found that native density was still greatly depressed 25 years since the last fire but rates of productivity were returning to pre-grass invasion levels because of the increase in plant biomass with Morella faya invasion.                  We also evaluated the influence of native canopy trees used in restoration of the African-gras...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
