<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Online Optimization for Dynamic Resource Allocation Problems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>295000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald Hearn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this project is for the development of general online optimization methodologies and algorithms for addressing resource allocation problems with the following combined characteristics: (i) dynamic input streams with significant uncertainty about their patterns and (ii) requirements for full or partial online decision making. A corresponding class of canonical problems of increasing complexity will be proposed. The mathematical tools for the analysis of these data-driven optimization problems will expand the competitive analysis proposed for online problems, by incorporating, when appropriate, stochastic information about future data and/or limited learning capabilities from past data. The design of the online algorithms will use greedy techniques as well as general principles from primal-dual concepts. It will incorporate probabilistic information when available. The analysis of the algorithms will be based on theoretical competitive analysis, including asymptotic consideration, and on empirical testing within a controlled numerical simulation framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will help understand how to tackle/solve complex new data-driven problems that have been made possible from continuing developments in telecommunication, computing, and other information technologies. While the basic technologies needed for the development of dynamic online systems are already available, the results of this research would provide algorithms that exploit the dynamic information supplied by these technologies and leverage processes to generate cost effective solutions. In addition we hope that this research will shed lights on the following basic questions: (i) How to quantify the degree of uncertainty in data-driven problems, and its impact on the ability to solve them? (ii) How to quantify the value of additional (deterministic and/or probabilistic) information for solving such problems?</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1029603</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Jaillet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick Jaillet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jaillet@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174523379</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5514</Code>
<Text>OPERATIONS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>073E</Code>
<Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9147</Code>
<Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~295000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project outcomes:</p> <p><br />Intellectual Merit: The last two decades have witnessed a growing scientific interest in processes where data are incomplete and uncertain, and where decisions have to be made under very short time restrictions. This development was helped by crucial problems in computer science, engineering, and economics and has led to the emergence of online and real-time optimization. In addition, with the growing importance of the internet, electronic commerce and the recent promise of ubiquitous information, a third aspect is becoming increasingly important: extremely large data sets.</p> <p><br />This proposal has considered these three phenomena (incomplete and uncertain data, short time restriction for decisions, and extremely large data sets) in an integrated fashion, developed appropriate models for their real-time solutions and analyses, and proposed new algorithmic solutions and paradigms. This proposal also aimed to quantify the value of additional stochastic or deterministic information in large-scale dynamic and stochastic models. The focus has been on problems arising from applications in the general area of matching goods and services to customers, covering important societal problems such as those arising from (i) kidney exchange programs, (ii) other markets in which agents arrive and match over time, such as with online platforms designed for labor markets and for housing markets, and (iii) transportation sharing systems.</p> <p><br />Broader Impact: Continuing developments in telecommunication and information technologies provide unprecedented opportunities for using real-time information to enhance productivity, optimize performance, and improve global competitiveness of many industrial sectors. The outcomes of this project has the potential to provide industry with the tools to exploit efficiently and effectively real-time information supplied by new technologies, and this in turn will have an impact on the economy. The proposal also contributed to the training of graduate and post-doctoral students, important to maintain the competitiveness of our workforce and guarantee the best possible training for the next generation of faculty members teaching on our college campuses. &nbsp;The prospects for commercialization of these technologies are very good, in light of their increased relevance created by the explosive growth of &ldquo;on demand&rdquo; services.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Patrick&nbsp;Jaillet</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project outcomes:   Intellectual Merit: The last two decades have witnessed a growing scientific interest in processes where data are incomplete and uncertain, and where decisions have to be made under very short time restrictions. This development was helped by crucial problems in computer science, engineering, and economics and has led to the emergence of online and real-time optimization. In addition, with the growing importance of the internet, electronic commerce and the recent promise of ubiquitous information, a third aspect is becoming increasingly important: extremely large data sets.   This proposal has considered these three phenomena (incomplete and uncertain data, short time restriction for decisions, and extremely large data sets) in an integrated fashion, developed appropriate models for their real-time solutions and analyses, and proposed new algorithmic solutions and paradigms. This proposal also aimed to quantify the value of additional stochastic or deterministic information in large-scale dynamic and stochastic models. The focus has been on problems arising from applications in the general area of matching goods and services to customers, covering important societal problems such as those arising from (i) kidney exchange programs, (ii) other markets in which agents arrive and match over time, such as with online platforms designed for labor markets and for housing markets, and (iii) transportation sharing systems.   Broader Impact: Continuing developments in telecommunication and information technologies provide unprecedented opportunities for using real-time information to enhance productivity, optimize performance, and improve global competitiveness of many industrial sectors. The outcomes of this project has the potential to provide industry with the tools to exploit efficiently and effectively real-time information supplied by new technologies, and this in turn will have an impact on the economy. The proposal also contributed to the training of graduate and post-doctoral students, important to maintain the competitiveness of our workforce and guarantee the best possible training for the next generation of faculty members teaching on our college campuses.  The prospects for commercialization of these technologies are very good, in light of their increased relevance created by the explosive growth of "on demand" services.        Last Modified: 11/30/2015       Submitted by: Patrick Jaillet]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>