<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NanoExperiences: Pathways to Workforce Success</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>999964.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1029814</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Haury</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NanoExperiences: Pathways to Workforce Success is an out-of-school program that supports high school students in Career and Technical Education to prepare for post secondary education in multiple STEM career pathways related to nanoscale science and technology (NS&amp;T).  The project builds on NS&amp;T instructional materials developed and tested by Mid-Continent Research for Education and Learning (McREL), and others, on professional development being developed by McREL and on recent recommendations for structuring academically-focused out-of-school programs.  The one-year program combines academic learning of background information with additional supports.  In the first spring 20 students and their parents in two schools are introduced to NS&amp;T concepts, tools and instrumentation; NS&amp;T related occupations; and societal implications.  The five three hour sessions include large group meetings, presentations (both real and virtual) by workers in NS&amp;T industries with teamwork projects between sessions.  In the summer, students and their parents plan for and make on-site visits at industries using NS&amp;T and plan for their final projects on an NS&amp;T related career.  In the fall, students plan the presentation on their project to be given in a symposium in November.  The project will evaluate and refine the experiences to modify the program for the second year with 20 students in the same schools and 20 more students in two other schools.  A NanoExperiences Toolkit developed and tested provides guidance for Colorado high schools to replicate the program with state partners including the Colorado Community College System.  The project is designed around common features of Career and Technology Education programs and should be useful across the nation.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The evaluation, done by an external evaluator, measures student participation and the impact on student learning, interest and presentation skills.  The evaluation also investigates the collaborations with businesses, and the evidence for scalability to determine that NanoExperiences can serve as a national model.  Data are collected through teacher, student and collaborator surveys and interviews, student assessments, and observations.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the strategies project is to create a national model for developing an out-of-school time program to increase career and technical education students' interest and ability in STEM intensive careers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1029491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Ristvey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John D Ristvey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jristvey@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034972591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000210127</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Ristvey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John D Ristvey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jristvey@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034972591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000210127</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/23/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danette</FirstName>
<LastName>Parsley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danette Parsley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Danette.Parsley@educationnorthwest.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5032759633</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000406109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danette</FirstName>
<LastName>Parsley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danette Parsley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Danette.Parsley@educationnorthwest.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5032759633</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000406109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/23/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mid-Continent Research for Education and Learning</Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<ZipCode>802372596</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3033370990</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4601 DTC Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076287226</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MCREL INTERNATIONAL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mid-Continent Research for Education and Learning]]></Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>802372596</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4601 DTC Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~333322</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~666642</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~29850</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>NanoExperiences: Pathways to Workforce Success</strong></p> <p><em>NanoExperiences: Pathways to Workforce Success</em> is an <strong><em>ITEST strategies project</em></strong> designed to support <strong><em>high school students</em></strong> in multiple science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) career pathways related to <strong><em>nanoscale science and technology (NS&amp;T).</em></strong> McREL International (McREL) and project partners (Education Northwest and Stanford Nanofabrication Facility with external evaluator, BSCS) developed and evaluated <em>NanoExperiences</em>, an out-of-school-time (OST) program that combines diverse learning experiences that introduce emerging STEM content buttressed with additional supports&mdash;motivating students by establishing high expectations and deepening background knowledge&mdash;to prepare high school Career and Technical Education (CTE) students for postsecondary learning and credentials leading to participation in the STEM workforce. Through the spring (NanoSurvey), summer (Nano@Work), and fall (NanoSymposium), students work <em>locally</em> and<em> remotely</em> with nanotechnology researchers and professionals as they pursue a personal project, conducting investigations and preparing a final presentation. The project goals are to: (1) increase student knowledge of NS&amp;T content, (2) increase student foundational knowledge, skills, and dispositions for academic and career success, (3) increase student interest in and motivation for participating in the STEM workforce, and (4) develop a replicable model for states to develop programs that prepare students for the STEM workforce.</p> <p><strong><em>Intellectual Merit</em></strong>. <em>NanoExperiences </em>advances substantial investments that the National Science Foundation (NSF) has made in NS&amp;T and builds on the existing findings and resources generated from these projects, including <em>NanoLeap</em> and <em>NanoSense</em>. The project also builds upon McREL&rsquo;s long history in STEM education and out-of-school-time programming and two NSF-funded projects: <em>A NanoLeap into New Science</em> (#ESI-0426401) which developed NS&amp;T modules for high school students, and <em>NanoTeach: Professional Development in NanoScale Science,</em> which targets the needs of STEM teachers in emerging sciences (# DRL-0822128). The project addresses several critical needs: reaching students with emerging STEM content <em>before</em> they have chosen career pathways; providing additional supports for students that helps them to pursue postsecondary learning for middle-skills jobs in the STEM workforce; meeting the demand for an educated middle-skills workforce in emerging sciences; and addressing critical reform areas in CTE&mdash;rigor, relevance, and relationships.</p> <p><strong><em>Broader Impacts</em></strong>. The project targets CTE programs, a significant component of the U.S. high school experience, and a growing national industry need for an educated &ldquo;middle-skills&rdquo; workforce in emerging sciences such as NS&amp;T. This strategies project designed a model for immediate replication across Colorado and for eventual scale-up across the nation. The resulting <em>NanoExperiences Toolkit</em> provides ready guidance for Colorado high schools to replicate the program across the state with project advisors, including the Colorado Community College System (a critical link between K-12 CTE programs and postsecondary options), positioned to support these sustainability efforts. Further, the model is designed around the big ideas of NS&amp;T to make the program adaptable to various contexts, including different states and/or STEM content areas. Project advisors who are interested in taking this strategies project to scale across the nation provide guidance to ensure the program is replicable and collaborate on future scale-up efforts.</p> ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NanoExperiences: Pathways to Workforce Success  NanoExperiences: Pathways to Workforce Success is an ITEST strategies project designed to support high school students in multiple science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) career pathways related to nanoscale science and technology (NS&amp;T). McREL International (McREL) and project partners (Education Northwest and Stanford Nanofabrication Facility with external evaluator, BSCS) developed and evaluated NanoExperiences, an out-of-school-time (OST) program that combines diverse learning experiences that introduce emerging STEM content buttressed with additional supports&mdash;motivating students by establishing high expectations and deepening background knowledge&mdash;to prepare high school Career and Technical Education (CTE) students for postsecondary learning and credentials leading to participation in the STEM workforce. Through the spring (NanoSurvey), summer (Nano@Work), and fall (NanoSymposium), students work locally and remotely with nanotechnology researchers and professionals as they pursue a personal project, conducting investigations and preparing a final presentation. The project goals are to: (1) increase student knowledge of NS&amp;T content, (2) increase student foundational knowledge, skills, and dispositions for academic and career success, (3) increase student interest in and motivation for participating in the STEM workforce, and (4) develop a replicable model for states to develop programs that prepare students for the STEM workforce.  Intellectual Merit. NanoExperiences advances substantial investments that the National Science Foundation (NSF) has made in NS&amp;T and builds on the existing findings and resources generated from these projects, including NanoLeap and NanoSense. The project also builds upon McRELÆs long history in STEM education and out-of-school-time programming and two NSF-funded projects: A NanoLeap into New Science (#ESI-0426401) which developed NS&amp;T modules for high school students, and NanoTeach: Professional Development in NanoScale Science, which targets the needs of STEM teachers in emerging sciences (# DRL-0822128). The project addresses several critical needs: reaching students with emerging STEM content before they have chosen career pathways; providing additional supports for students that helps them to pursue postsecondary learning for middle-skills jobs in the STEM workforce; meeting the demand for an educated middle-skills workforce in emerging sciences; and addressing critical reform areas in CTE&mdash;rigor, relevance, and relationships.  Broader Impacts. The project targets CTE programs, a significant component of the U.S. high school experience, and a growing national industry need for an educated "middle-skills" workforce in emerging sciences such as NS&amp;T. This strategies project designed a model for immediate replication across Colorado and for eventual scale-up across the nation. The resulting NanoExperiences Toolkit provides ready guidance for Colorado high schools to replicate the program across the state with project advisors, including the Colorado Community College System (a critical link between K-12 CTE programs and postsecondary options), positioned to support these sustainability efforts. Further, the model is designed around the big ideas of NS&amp;T to make the program adaptable to various contexts, including different states and/or STEM content areas. Project advisors who are interested in taking this strategies project to scale across the nation provide guidance to ensure the program is replicable and collaborate on future scale-up efforts.  Field Test Results. The field test year of the NanoExperiences project included a full test of the program in four participating high schools in the Denver Metro area. While there was significant attrition during the field test year, similar to the pilot year, external evaluators from BSCS were able to collect key data from a group of students a...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
