<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Plate Boundary Evolution and Physics at an Oceanic Transform Fault System - The Blanco Transform OBS Experiment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>622173.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>622173</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most earthquakes occur along the boundaries of rocky ?plates? that make up the Earth?s surface. Most great earthquakes occur where plates converge, as in Indonesia, Japan and Cascadia. Other damaging events are associated with ?transform? faults, where the plates slide past each other, in places such as Turkey and along the San Andreas Fault in California. Oceanic Transform Faults (OTFs) in the seafloor are geologically simpler than those onshore, and thus offer a natural laboratory for studying their seismicity. This study will deploy a dense array of 55 Ocean Bottom Seismographs (OBSs) off the coast of Oregon for one year to study the Blanco Transform fault. This deployment of OBSs will also be an important adjunct to the Cascadia Initiative (CI), an ongoing onshore/offshore seismic and geodetic experiment that includes an array of seismometers on the seafloor to complement an array of stations onshore. A primary aim of the Cascadia Initiative is to gain a better understanding seismicity associated with subduction along the Pacific margin of Washington, Oregon and northern California, where the risk of a ?megathrust? earthquake is high. Among the broader impacts of this project are support for two graduate students and participation by several graduate students. The immediate scientific benefit is better understanding of seismicity and mechanics of Oceanic Transform Faults (OTFs), but the chief broader impact of this project will be its very significant contribution to the broader, Cascadia Initiative.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1031858</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Nabelek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John L Nabelek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nabelek@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417372757</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000398763</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~129089</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~256747</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~236337</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 61"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>Oceanic transform faults, connecting offset mid-ocean spreading&nbsp;<span><span>centres</span></span>, rupture quasi-periodically in earthquakes up to about magnitude&nbsp;M&nbsp;7.0 that are often preceded by&nbsp;<span><span>foreshocks</span></span>. In addition to <span><span>seis</span></span><span><span>mic</span></span>&nbsp;slip, a large portion of slip takes place as&nbsp;<span><span>aseismic</span></span>&nbsp;creep, which likely influences initiation of large earthquakes. Although oceanic transform faults are one of the major types of plate boundaries, the exact mode of slip and interaction between the <span><span>seis</span></span><span><span>mic</span></span>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<span><span>aseismic</span></span>&nbsp;motion remains unclear.</p> <p>We deployed 55 three-component broadband and short-period Ocean Bottom Seismometers (OBS) and Differential Pressure <span><span>Gauges</span></span> (<span><span>DPG</span></span>) along the entire length of the <span><span>Blanco</span></span> Transform Fault (<span><span>BTF</span></span>) and recorded about 30,000 earthquakes over a one-year period.</p> <p><span>Two broad issues are addressed: 1) improve understanding of earthquake rupture physics in&nbsp;</span>relation to material and fault zone properties along transform plate boundaries; 2) understand <span><span>geodynamic</span></span> effects of plate boundary evolution and reorientation on transform fault structure. The aim is to go beyond simple general tectonic characterizations of transform faults to a detailed process-oriented view.</p> <p>Results of our studies contribute to the knowledge of how seismically active faults are loaded during <span><span>interseismic</span></span> period, what is the role of episodic creep, and what generates <span><span>foreshocks</span></span> before larger events. The lessons learned here could be applied to the <span><span>subduction</span></span> zones and continental transform faults.</p> <p>We published three papers in refereed journals covering a) <span><span>teleseismic</span></span> tomography of the fault zone, b) lithospheric S-wave anisotropy, and c) crust-mantle interaction during seismic and <span><span>interseismic</span></span> periods. We continue research on this deep dataset.</p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"></div> </div> <p>The project supported M.S. and Ph.D. graduate student thesis research. Students and volunteers contributed to the deployment and recovery of the OBS.</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/22/2019<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;L&nbsp;Nabelek</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Oceanic transform faults, connecting offset mid-ocean spreading centres, rupture quasi-periodically in earthquakes up to about magnitude M 7.0 that are often preceded by foreshocks. In addition to seismic slip, a large portion of slip takes place as aseismic creep, which likely influences initiation of large earthquakes. Although oceanic transform faults are one of the major types of plate boundaries, the exact mode of slip and interaction between the seismic and aseismic motion remains unclear.  We deployed 55 three-component broadband and short-period Ocean Bottom Seismometers (OBS) and Differential Pressure Gauges (DPG) along the entire length of the Blanco Transform Fault (BTF) and recorded about 30,000 earthquakes over a one-year period.  Two broad issues are addressed: 1) improve understanding of earthquake rupture physics in relation to material and fault zone properties along transform plate boundaries; 2) understand geodynamic effects of plate boundary evolution and reorientation on transform fault structure. The aim is to go beyond simple general tectonic characterizations of transform faults to a detailed process-oriented view.  Results of our studies contribute to the knowledge of how seismically active faults are loaded during interseismic period, what is the role of episodic creep, and what generates foreshocks before larger events. The lessons learned here could be applied to the subduction zones and continental transform faults.  We published three papers in refereed journals covering a) teleseismic tomography of the fault zone, b) lithospheric S-wave anisotropy, and c) crust-mantle interaction during seismic and interseismic periods. We continue research on this deep dataset.     The project supported M.S. and Ph.D. graduate student thesis research. Students and volunteers contributed to the deployment and recovery of the OBS.          Last Modified: 07/22/2019       Submitted by: John L Nabelek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
