<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Magnetic Tunable Nanostructures: Property Characterization and Modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>588394.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>588394</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alewis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to systematically determine the magnetic properties of nanoscaled ferromagnetic materials and to compare them to their coarse-grained counterparts for use as electronically tunable magnetic nanostructures.  The research involves synthesis, processing, and characterization of their magnetic properties as a function of material variables and applied electric field.  These results, complemented by modeling will provide a fundamental understanding of the effects of electric field, chemistry, and microstructure on the properties of magnetic tunable nanostructures.  The synthesis involves an eight source molecular beam epitaxy and an eight-target DC/RF sputtering deposition systems, with in-situ characterization capabilities.  Their magnetic properties (MS, MR, HC, Hb, and TC, First Order Reversal Curves, etc.) will be characterized using SQUID and SQUID VSM magnetometers, Lorentz microscopy, FMR, and Kerr Effect spectroscopy.  The microstructural features will be examined by LEED, TEM, STEM, XRD, Lorentz and Mössbauer spectroscopies.  The results will advance the understanding of these nanostructures and promote their technological applications. This is a German-American collaborative effort, involving the Institute of Nanotechnology, Karlsruhe, Germany with George Washington University, Washington, DC and the National Institute of Standards and Technology, Gaithersburg, MD.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research are expected not only to promote the understanding of tunable nanostructures, but also impact the understanding of the magnetic behavior of the broader class of magnetic nanostructures that include tunnel junctions, quantum dots, and patterned media.  Future efforts are expected to lead to tailoring and optimization of the properties of various magnetic nanostructures for their use in a wide range of technological applications, including magnetic data storage and sensor devices.  Graduate and undergraduate students and post-doctoral fellows will benefit through acquiring comprehension in advanced experimental magnetic measurements and taking opportunities to exchange visits between the U.S. and Germany.  This project is funded jointly by the Division of Civil, Mechanical, and Manufacturing Innovation and the Office of International Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1031619</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Della Torre</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward Della Torre</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>edt@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029940410</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000178695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Bennett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence H Bennett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lbennett@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5715538299</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165234</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1922 F Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1633</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~588394</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The magnetic recording industry is trying to push the areal density (AD) of stored information beyond the superparamagnetic limits of 1Tbits/in<sup>2</sup>. This requires the advancement in the fundamental understanding of the magnetic behavior of recording media at nanometer scales alongwith the improvements in the read and write elements of the transducers. It has been shown for many nanostructures that an applied electrostatic field, or in another words surface charge, can bring about a noticeable magnetoelectric response for various ferro- and ferrimagnetic materials. However, this phenomenon is mostly observed in either semiconductors with free charge carrier concentration (FCCC) of 10-1000 monolayers or in metallic ultrathin films with thickness less than 5nm. We explored the possibility of reversible and dynamic tuning of the magnetic properties of thicker metallic nanostructures. The current magnetic storage devices employ high currents to induce flips on electron spins which lead to limitations in the capacity of data storage. However, field induced magnetic storage devices can push the density of stored information beyond the superparamagnetic limits. This can lead to the manipulation, storage, and transfer of information by means of electron spin at the commercial level.</p> <p>This project was a collaborative effort between the George Washington University (GWU), Washington DC, and the Institute of Technology (INT) at the Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Germany. We designed and built an in-situ experimental system, which consists of a MOKE apparatus, a three-electrode electrochemical cell and a Potentiostat for the measurement of surface charge induced variations in magnetic properties. A suitable ferromagnetic system, CoPt<sub>3</sub> thin films that exhibits perpendicular magnetization, was selected and fabricated. Magnetic properties of the CoPt<sub>3</sub> system were measured and</p> <p>characterized, including longitudinal and polar Kerr effect and magnetization dynamics at room temperature. Electrochemical charging of the working electrode takes place when the electrodes are under potentiostatic control and a non-zero bias potential between the counter electrode and the working electrode is applied. When small negative voltages (-0.8 V ~ -0.3 V) were applied, variations in critical magnetic parameters, i.e. saturation magnetization, coercivity and switching field distribution were observed. The change in coercivity indicated that the magnetization switching process can be modulated electrically. Thus electrostatic fields were applied to an electrolyte/magnetic material interface to achieve dynamic and reversible control of the magnetic properties (tuning). Such reversible control over the magnetic state has been demonstrated in metals, only in ultra-thin films (a few atomic monolayers).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The knowledge and new insight obtained from this project not only promotes the knowledge and understanding of the tunable nanostructure but also positively impact the understanding on the magnetic</p> <p>behavior of the broader class of magnetic nanostructures. The distribution of the various project tasks judiciously exploited the synergism, complementary, and reinforcing expertise and experience in material synthesis, measurement science, and characterization tools available at the participating institutions. We have now demonstrated, using our magneto-optical Kerr effect (MOKE) apparatus, the same tuning in a much thicker metal. Our German partners have called this discovery as &ldquo;<strong>truly remarkable</strong>&rdquo;.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During this project, a team of six graduate students from GWU and one graduate student from INT, Karlsruhe, Germany were involved. Two of the PhD students, Yi Jin and Shuo Gu completed their degrees successfully. The monthly meetings between the institutes were held through video conferencing. A...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The magnetic recording industry is trying to push the areal density (AD) of stored information beyond the superparamagnetic limits of 1Tbits/in2. This requires the advancement in the fundamental understanding of the magnetic behavior of recording media at nanometer scales alongwith the improvements in the read and write elements of the transducers. It has been shown for many nanostructures that an applied electrostatic field, or in another words surface charge, can bring about a noticeable magnetoelectric response for various ferro- and ferrimagnetic materials. However, this phenomenon is mostly observed in either semiconductors with free charge carrier concentration (FCCC) of 10-1000 monolayers or in metallic ultrathin films with thickness less than 5nm. We explored the possibility of reversible and dynamic tuning of the magnetic properties of thicker metallic nanostructures. The current magnetic storage devices employ high currents to induce flips on electron spins which lead to limitations in the capacity of data storage. However, field induced magnetic storage devices can push the density of stored information beyond the superparamagnetic limits. This can lead to the manipulation, storage, and transfer of information by means of electron spin at the commercial level.  This project was a collaborative effort between the George Washington University (GWU), Washington DC, and the Institute of Technology (INT) at the Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Germany. We designed and built an in-situ experimental system, which consists of a MOKE apparatus, a three-electrode electrochemical cell and a Potentiostat for the measurement of surface charge induced variations in magnetic properties. A suitable ferromagnetic system, CoPt3 thin films that exhibits perpendicular magnetization, was selected and fabricated. Magnetic properties of the CoPt3 system were measured and  characterized, including longitudinal and polar Kerr effect and magnetization dynamics at room temperature. Electrochemical charging of the working electrode takes place when the electrodes are under potentiostatic control and a non-zero bias potential between the counter electrode and the working electrode is applied. When small negative voltages (-0.8 V ~ -0.3 V) were applied, variations in critical magnetic parameters, i.e. saturation magnetization, coercivity and switching field distribution were observed. The change in coercivity indicated that the magnetization switching process can be modulated electrically. Thus electrostatic fields were applied to an electrolyte/magnetic material interface to achieve dynamic and reversible control of the magnetic properties (tuning). Such reversible control over the magnetic state has been demonstrated in metals, only in ultra-thin films (a few atomic monolayers).     The knowledge and new insight obtained from this project not only promotes the knowledge and understanding of the tunable nanostructure but also positively impact the understanding on the magnetic  behavior of the broader class of magnetic nanostructures. The distribution of the various project tasks judiciously exploited the synergism, complementary, and reinforcing expertise and experience in material synthesis, measurement science, and characterization tools available at the participating institutions. We have now demonstrated, using our magneto-optical Kerr effect (MOKE) apparatus, the same tuning in a much thicker metal. Our German partners have called this discovery as "truly remarkable".     During this project, a team of six graduate students from GWU and one graduate student from INT, Karlsruhe, Germany were involved. Two of the PhD students, Yi Jin and Shuo Gu completed their degrees successfully. The monthly meetings between the institutes were held through video conferencing. Also, one of the senior researchers, Dr. Virgil Provenzano visited Germany on behalf of US team worked closely with Dr. R. Kruk, a group leader at INT, and Mr. R. Witte, graduat...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
