<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strategies: Bridging Math Literacy and Digital Media Creation: Students as Learners, Teachers, and Leaders of STEM Content</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1097974.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1097974</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth VanderPutten</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>evanderp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925147</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project leaders guided high school students through a mathematics-based, programming experience that prepared the high school students to teach mathematics and programming to middle school students. Using a "drag and drop" programming language, the participants explored mathematical concepts. Products of the project include two modules, the first using video games based on existing mathematics games and the second using simulations to explore social issues. The goals of the project are (1) to develop computational literacy as well as mathematical literacy and (2) encourage students to pursue STEM careers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1031633</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eli</FirstName>
<LastName>Tucker-Raymond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eli Tucker-Raymond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>etuckerr@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3128600564</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maisha</FirstName>
<LastName>Moses</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Mrs</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maisha Moses</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maishamoses@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6014622331</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000535544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
<LastName>Milner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chad Milner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmilner@typp.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173548991</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Young People's Project, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021393428</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6179103643</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>99 Bishop Allen Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>141249909</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YOUNG PEOPLES PROJECT INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Young People's Project, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021393428</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[99 Bishop Allen Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~351446</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~402686</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~343842</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Bridging Math and Digital Media Literacy (BMDML) was a four-year ITEST Strategies project aimed primarily at a) broadening participation in technologically-rich informal mathematics learning environments and b) developing career pathways for young people from underrepresented groups in STEM fields. Particularly, BMDML was developed at The Young People&rsquo;s Project (YPP), a not-for-profit math literacy organization that works with and through young people in cities across the country. At three YPP sites (Urban Northeast, Rural Midwest, and Urban South), college and high school students created a BMDML integrated computational and mathematical thinking plan of study for two YPP games (Flagway and Road Coloring) that were typically played over the course of a semester. In the activities, middle and elementary school students learned a combination of computer programming and computational thinking through the drag and drop software program Scratch, and mathematical thinking in either Flagway or Road Coloring. Young people then created video games in Scratch that addressed either the mathematics or game play of the two YPP games. BMDML served 17 college students as College Math Literacy Workers (CMLW), 77 high school students as High School Math Literacy Workers (MLW), and 163 middle and elementary school students as the outreach population. At two sites, 95% of participants were students from ethnic/racial communities underrepresented in STEM fields. The other site was primarily an economically disadvantaged White community in a rural area. The outreach population was 61% girls.</p> <p>In the Northeast we served a total of 8 CMLW, 34 MLW, 65 elementary and middle school participants. In the Midwest we served a total of 5 CMLW, 29 MLW, 58 elementary and middle school participants, and in the Deep South we served a total of 3 CMLW, 15 MLW, and 40 middle and elementary school participants. In all BMDM provided direct STEM career experience in the form of Mathematics Literacy Work, for 69 college and high school young people from communities underrepresented in STEM fields.</p> <p>Major outcomes from the work include two full curricula created by college and high school math literacy workers. One curricula, developed mostly in the Northeast was devoted to the Flagway game. This curricula was implemented in the Northeast site and the Southern site. One curricula, developed mostly in the Midwest, was devoted to the Road Coloring game and was implemented in the Midwest. Curricula are modular, and can be implemented from half a semester to a year long. They are meant to be adapted and expanded by local sites focusing on computational thinking, mathematics, STEM careers, or their integration at different times and for different purposes. Participants also created video games in Scratch to demonstrate computational concepts and the mathematical games.</p> <p>150 participants were also served at STEAM days which highlighted STEAM career skills such as computational thinking, professional protocols, and collaboration.</p> <p>Youth presented their work outside of the workshops for middle and elementary school students on multiple occasions including family math nights, a youth conference, and recruiting events.</p> <p>All high school students who participated more than one year went on to college. One received a four year scholarship to a technical university. One college participant, who started with no previous programming experience and later became a lead instructor at one of the sites went on to an entry level position at a technology firm and began in-house training to be a programmer.</p> <p>Major research findings showed that high school students scored significantly higher (p=&lt;.05) on post tests of math concepts related to the content than they did on pre tests. Findings also showed statistically significant growth in computational skills by college, high school, and...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Bridging Math and Digital Media Literacy (BMDML) was a four-year ITEST Strategies project aimed primarily at a) broadening participation in technologically-rich informal mathematics learning environments and b) developing career pathways for young people from underrepresented groups in STEM fields. Particularly, BMDML was developed at The Young PeopleÆs Project (YPP), a not-for-profit math literacy organization that works with and through young people in cities across the country. At three YPP sites (Urban Northeast, Rural Midwest, and Urban South), college and high school students created a BMDML integrated computational and mathematical thinking plan of study for two YPP games (Flagway and Road Coloring) that were typically played over the course of a semester. In the activities, middle and elementary school students learned a combination of computer programming and computational thinking through the drag and drop software program Scratch, and mathematical thinking in either Flagway or Road Coloring. Young people then created video games in Scratch that addressed either the mathematics or game play of the two YPP games. BMDML served 17 college students as College Math Literacy Workers (CMLW), 77 high school students as High School Math Literacy Workers (MLW), and 163 middle and elementary school students as the outreach population. At two sites, 95% of participants were students from ethnic/racial communities underrepresented in STEM fields. The other site was primarily an economically disadvantaged White community in a rural area. The outreach population was 61% girls.  In the Northeast we served a total of 8 CMLW, 34 MLW, 65 elementary and middle school participants. In the Midwest we served a total of 5 CMLW, 29 MLW, 58 elementary and middle school participants, and in the Deep South we served a total of 3 CMLW, 15 MLW, and 40 middle and elementary school participants. In all BMDM provided direct STEM career experience in the form of Mathematics Literacy Work, for 69 college and high school young people from communities underrepresented in STEM fields.  Major outcomes from the work include two full curricula created by college and high school math literacy workers. One curricula, developed mostly in the Northeast was devoted to the Flagway game. This curricula was implemented in the Northeast site and the Southern site. One curricula, developed mostly in the Midwest, was devoted to the Road Coloring game and was implemented in the Midwest. Curricula are modular, and can be implemented from half a semester to a year long. They are meant to be adapted and expanded by local sites focusing on computational thinking, mathematics, STEM careers, or their integration at different times and for different purposes. Participants also created video games in Scratch to demonstrate computational concepts and the mathematical games.  150 participants were also served at STEAM days which highlighted STEAM career skills such as computational thinking, professional protocols, and collaboration.  Youth presented their work outside of the workshops for middle and elementary school students on multiple occasions including family math nights, a youth conference, and recruiting events.  All high school students who participated more than one year went on to college. One received a four year scholarship to a technical university. One college participant, who started with no previous programming experience and later became a lead instructor at one of the sites went on to an entry level position at a technology firm and began in-house training to be a programmer.  Major research findings showed that high school students scored significantly higher (p=&lt;.05) on post tests of math concepts related to the content than they did on pre tests. Findings also showed statistically significant growth in computational skills by college, high school, and middle school students as measured by a sampling on pre and post holistic scores on Scratch project ass...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
