<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Tanzania Planning Visit:  Investigating high-latitude climate change recorded in upper Paleozoic non-marine strata of East Africa</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20398.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20398</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports a planning visit for Dr. Michael Soreghan at the University of Oklahoma and two US graduate students to develop new collaborative research projects in the geosciences with Tanzanian colleagues. The US team will meet with Dr. Hudson Nkotagu at the University of Dar es Salaam and the Tanzanian Geological Survey to develop plans for future international collaborative research proposals to NSF. The probable outcomes of the proposed research will be 1) a detailed record of regional climate change for the late Paleozoic; and 2) a sequence stratigraphic model for certain lacustrine rocks in order to predict the distribution of economically viable deposits of coal and uranium within these strata.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. Ultimate results of this research will provide a high-resolution terrestrial record of past climate change for high-latitude Pangaea that can be compared to better studied records from the high-latitude marine realm and the (paleo)tropics across Pangaea. One of the main keys to advancing our understanding of "deep time" (pre-Quaternary) climate is the need for better age constraints, since lack of correlation of key climate records has precluded high-resolution, spatially extensive studies of deep-time climate. Thus an immediate outcome of the proposed planning fieldwork will be improved age constraints for these poorly dated lacustrine strata in collaboration with Dr. M. Schmitz (Boise State University). In addition, a detailed analysis of facies changes and the climatic control on these facies transitions will provide a predictive model for evaluating the distribution of the coal and uranium bearing strata in these basins.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. Results of the proposed research ultimately bears on the question of whether low- and high-latitude climate change is synchronous and/or which responds more sensitively to change, and thus is relevant to both recent and future climate change. Results will also have potential economic value to Tanzania through enhanced depositional models of coal and uranium-bearing strata. In addition to scientific impacts, the proposed field trip will provide a mechanism to enhance geological field skills for African scientists and African and U.S. students. Field experiences and research projects are a critical component of any geologic training, but are very limited in the geological curricula of many African universities. The PI has a long-standing interest in science education and in incorporating active science in the classroom, and the results and experiences from this project will be incorporated in general education, major, and graduate-level courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is being funded by the Office of International Science and Engineering's, Africa, Near East, and South Asia program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1033143</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Soreghan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Soreghan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>msoreg@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4053253393</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455898</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Five Partners Place, Suite 3100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>848348348</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oklahoma Norman Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Stephenson Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7338</Code>
<Text>TANZANIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~20398</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The primary goal of the funded research was to 1) foster collaborative research between U.S. and Tanzanian scientists and students; and 2) increase our ability to interpret climate change during the late Paleozoic (300-250 million years ago) through the analysis of ancient lake beds preserved in southwestern Tanzania.&nbsp; We live in a rare time in Earth history where large ice sheets have formed on continents, although we are in what is termed an interglacial period--and we also appear to be further altering the climate through greenhouse gas emissions.&nbsp; Prior to our present time, the late Paleozoic is the most recent period in geologic history in which large ice sheets have formed on continents. &nbsp; Thus a better understanding of the natural climate variability that existed during this time will provide climate scientists with scenarios to evaluate more recent climate change. The ancient lake beds exposed in southwestern Tanzania potentially contain a detailed record of regional climate change for this time period.&nbsp; Further, plate tectonic processes had shifted this part of Tanzania to within 30&deg; of the south pole.&nbsp; Thus, the record of climate change in these high-latitude, lake deposits can be matched to similar records of climate change already under study by the PI and students from locations near the equator.&nbsp; It is only after we begin to match climate change across large areas of the globe that we can begin to understand the processes that lead to climate change. &nbsp; &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The collaborative stage included meeting with scientists at the University of Dar es Salaam, St. Augustine University and the Tanzanian Ministry of Minerals and Energy.&nbsp; The team involved in field work included the PI, three US students from the University of Oklahoma and two Tanzanians.&nbsp; Field work, located ~30 km northwest of Songea, Tanzania, consisted of measuring and describing the ancient lake beds, mapping the deposits and collecting samples. &nbsp; The detailed descriptions and samples provide data that allow interpretations of changes in the lake level, which can be tied to climate change. Back in the U.S., samples were analyzed geochemically to provide information about the nature of the mountainous regions from which the sediment was eroded.&nbsp; Further, two students travelled to the University of Arizona to analyze samples on their (NSF funded) LA-ICPMS instrument in order to determine the U-Pb ages of individual zircon mineral grains extracted from the lake beds to better document the source of the sediment and to attempt to constrain the age at which the sediments were deposited.&nbsp; These data will be used for one MS thesis for a graduate student at the University of Oklahoma, in a scientific article by the PI and students in preparation, and as pilot data for a follow-up proposal. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Ultimate results of this research will provide a detailed record of past climate change for high-latitude Pangaea that can be compared to other studied records from the high-latitude ocean realm and the (paleo)tropics across the supercontinent known as Pangaea.&nbsp; One of the main keys to advancing our understanding of &ldquo;deep time&rdquo; climate is to develop methods to determine precise ages of these ancient sedimentary layers that lack fossils. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Results of this research also have potential economic value because the rocks under study contain coal, and in similar rocks in neighboring Malawi they contain economic deposits of Uranium.&nbsp; Thus a better understanding of the climate at the time the lakes formed will also add to our understanding of coal and uranium formation.&nbsp; In addition to scientific impacts, the project provided a research experience for three US students in in int...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of the funded research was to 1) foster collaborative research between U.S. and Tanzanian scientists and students; and 2) increase our ability to interpret climate change during the late Paleozoic (300-250 million years ago) through the analysis of ancient lake beds preserved in southwestern Tanzania.  We live in a rare time in Earth history where large ice sheets have formed on continents, although we are in what is termed an interglacial period--and we also appear to be further altering the climate through greenhouse gas emissions.  Prior to our present time, the late Paleozoic is the most recent period in geologic history in which large ice sheets have formed on continents.   Thus a better understanding of the natural climate variability that existed during this time will provide climate scientists with scenarios to evaluate more recent climate change. The ancient lake beds exposed in southwestern Tanzania potentially contain a detailed record of regional climate change for this time period.  Further, plate tectonic processes had shifted this part of Tanzania to within 30&deg; of the south pole.  Thus, the record of climate change in these high-latitude, lake deposits can be matched to similar records of climate change already under study by the PI and students from locations near the equator.  It is only after we begin to match climate change across large areas of the globe that we can begin to understand the processes that lead to climate change.         The collaborative stage included meeting with scientists at the University of Dar es Salaam, St. Augustine University and the Tanzanian Ministry of Minerals and Energy.  The team involved in field work included the PI, three US students from the University of Oklahoma and two Tanzanians.  Field work, located ~30 km northwest of Songea, Tanzania, consisted of measuring and describing the ancient lake beds, mapping the deposits and collecting samples.   The detailed descriptions and samples provide data that allow interpretations of changes in the lake level, which can be tied to climate change. Back in the U.S., samples were analyzed geochemically to provide information about the nature of the mountainous regions from which the sediment was eroded.  Further, two students travelled to the University of Arizona to analyze samples on their (NSF funded) LA-ICPMS instrument in order to determine the U-Pb ages of individual zircon mineral grains extracted from the lake beds to better document the source of the sediment and to attempt to constrain the age at which the sediments were deposited.  These data will be used for one MS thesis for a graduate student at the University of Oklahoma, in a scientific article by the PI and students in preparation, and as pilot data for a follow-up proposal.       Ultimate results of this research will provide a detailed record of past climate change for high-latitude Pangaea that can be compared to other studied records from the high-latitude ocean realm and the (paleo)tropics across the supercontinent known as Pangaea.  One of the main keys to advancing our understanding of "deep time" climate is to develop methods to determine precise ages of these ancient sedimentary layers that lack fossils.       Results of this research also have potential economic value because the rocks under study contain coal, and in similar rocks in neighboring Malawi they contain economic deposits of Uranium.  Thus a better understanding of the climate at the time the lakes formed will also add to our understanding of coal and uranium formation.  In addition to scientific impacts, the project provided a research experience for three US students in in international field work--understanding the logistical and cultural issues of working in a foreign country.  It also paved the way for future collaboration between the University of Oklahoma and two universities in Tanzania.  During the research we collaborated with a professor from the University of ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
