<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Small: Sensor Lattices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>490000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>490000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Using the newly introduced idea of a sensor lattice, this project conducts a systematic study of the ``granularity'' at which the world can be sensed and how that affects the ability to accomplish common tasks with cyberphysical systems (CPSs).  A sensor is viewed as a device that partitions the physical world states into measurement-invariant equivalence classes, and the sensor lattice indicates how all sensors are related.  Several distinctive characteristics of the pursued approach are: 1) Virtual sensor models are developed, which correspond to minimal information requirements of common tasks and are independent of particular physical sensor implementations.  2) Uncertainty is decoupled into disturbances and preimages, the latter of which yields the measurement-invariant equivalence classes and sensor lattice.  3) The development of particular spatial and temporal filters that are based on minimal information requirements of a task. 4) Formally establishing the conditions that enable sensors in a CPS to be interchanged, and then determining the relative complexity tradeoffs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is to understand how mappings from the physical world to sensor outputs affect the solvability and complexity of commonly occurring tasks.  This is a critical step in the development of mathematical and computational CPS foundations.  Broader impact is expected by improving design methodologies for CPS solutions to societal problems such as assisted living, environmental monitoring, and automated agriculture.  The sensor lattice approach is transformative because it represents a new paradigm with which to address basic sensor-based inference issues, which extend well beyond the traditional academic boundaries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1035345</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Lavalle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Lavalle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lavalle@cs.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172656313</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000398881</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~490000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project conducted a systematic study of the &ldquo;granularity&rdquo; at which the world can be sensed and how that affects the ability to accomplish common tasks that involve sensors, actuators, and computers. &nbsp; A sensor is viewed as a device that partitions the physical world states into measurement-invariant equivalence classes, and the sensor lattice indicates how all sensors are related.&nbsp; This enables the pursuit of questions inspired by the classical theory of computation and asks:&nbsp; What does it mean for one sensor to be more powerful than another? If a more powerful sensor is substituted for another, what are the complexity tradeoffs? What problems are provably unsolvable by a particular family of sensors, regardless of what system they appear in?&nbsp; The intellectual merit of this work is that it improved our understanding of the necessary sensing requirements for complex engineering systems and tasks.&nbsp; The broader impact is that it may facilitate the design and analysis of sensing systems across a broad array of disciplines, such as assisted living, environmental<br />monitoring, and automated agriculture.&nbsp; Some of the general principles of this grant were applied by the PI to develop novel head tracking methods, which were used in the Oculus Rift and Samsung Gear VR devices.&nbsp; The filtering methods have been used in millions of units and helped to stimulate a global revolution in virtual and augmented reality.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lavalle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1035345/1035345_10021193_1499176299540_lattice--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1035345/1035345_10021193_1499176299540_lattice--rgov-800width.jpg" title="lattice"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1035345/1035345_10021193_1499176299540_lattice--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="lattice"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example of a hierarchy of sensor types based on refinements of partititions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven M. LaValle</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lavalle</div> <div class="imageTitle">lattice</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project conducted a systematic study of the "granularity" at which the world can be sensed and how that affects the ability to accomplish common tasks that involve sensors, actuators, and computers.   A sensor is viewed as a device that partitions the physical world states into measurement-invariant equivalence classes, and the sensor lattice indicates how all sensors are related.  This enables the pursuit of questions inspired by the classical theory of computation and asks:  What does it mean for one sensor to be more powerful than another? If a more powerful sensor is substituted for another, what are the complexity tradeoffs? What problems are provably unsolvable by a particular family of sensors, regardless of what system they appear in?  The intellectual merit of this work is that it improved our understanding of the necessary sensing requirements for complex engineering systems and tasks.  The broader impact is that it may facilitate the design and analysis of sensing systems across a broad array of disciplines, such as assisted living, environmental monitoring, and automated agriculture.  Some of the general principles of this grant were applied by the PI to develop novel head tracking methods, which were used in the Oculus Rift and Samsung Gear VR devices.  The filtering methods have been used in millions of units and helped to stimulate a global revolution in virtual and augmented reality.       Last Modified: 07/04/2017       Submitted by: Steven M Lavalle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
