<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cloud Condensation Nuclei (CCN) Spectral Measurements in the Tropical Phase of the Ice in Clouds Experiment (ICE-T)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>359610.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405834</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Tropical phase of the Ice in Clouds Experiment (ICE-T) is planned for the summer of 2011 in the Caribbean.  The overarching goal of these aircraft field experiments is to determine whether out-of-cloud aerosol measurements can predict cloud ice in tropical mixed-phase clouds.  Measurements of cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) spectra will be crucial for ICE-T field experiment.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In tropical clouds the production of cloud ice depends more heavily on the liquid/warm phase, which is especially prominent in warm, humid environments where cloud bases are low.  Ice production by direct and secondary processes is hypothesized to depend on droplet and drop size spectra.  More active warm rain processes are thought to enhance ice production; that is large cloud drops tend to promote both warm precipitation and the production of ice.  It is well accepted that liquid cloud microphysics depends on the input aerosol - namely CCN.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merits.  In this study, we will conduct both in-situ sampling and post experiment analysis of data taken with two Desert Research Institute's (DRI, University of Nevada) cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) spectrometers during the upcoming ICE-T field campaign.  The DRI's CCN spectrometers can provide more complete CCN spectra at high temporal and supersaturation resolution than other available CCN probes.  One unique feature of the DRI CCN spectrometers is their wide range of operational supersaturations.  Simultaneous measurements of large and giant nuclei, activated at very low supersaturatons (&lt;0.001%), are of particular importance for the relatively clean tropical ocean environment in which ICE-T will be conducted.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The DRI CCN spectrometers will provide not only detailed, accurate, and complete spectra necessary for such an important endeavor, but they also provide supplementary volatility and CCN size measurements.  These additional efforts afford important clues about CCN compositions and origins, which may also provide understandings on how dust and biomass burning affects the ICE-T clouds.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts.  The measurements of full CCN spectrum are critical for studies on fundamental cloud physics.  The data obtained from ICE-T will be available to the scientific community for further analysis and use, such as in modeling studies.  The measurements of composition and origin of CCN may have broader implication in studying aerosol and cloud interactions and climate research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will support training of a graduate student.  The student will gain valuable learning experience by participating in the field project, as well as involving in subsequent analysis and preparation of scientific manuscripts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1035230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hudson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James G Hudson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hudson@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7756747020</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000327144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nevada System of Higher Education, Desert Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7756737300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2215 Raggio Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>134599174</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Nevada System of Higher Education, Desert Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2215 Raggio Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~142809</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~110300</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~106501</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~46224</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) are the particles that cloud droplets grow upon. &nbsp;Anthropogenic CCN (air pollution) cause the indirect aerosol effect (IAE), which is the largest climate uncertainty. &nbsp;This is because the anthropogenic versus natural CCN ratio is unknown. &nbsp;And the effects of either are unknown becasue it is so difficult to separate their effects on clouds. &nbsp;It is generally thought that IAE is a global cooling effect because it increases cloud droplet concentrations, which causes more reflection of solar radiation, and the higher concentrations inhibit precipitation, which increases cloudines, which thus also increases reflection of solar radiation by clouds. &nbsp;</p> <p>An important factor is the level of cloud supersaturations, S, which vary considerably. &nbsp;Since CCN are characterized according to S they can be matched with cloud droplet concentrations to determine cloud S. &nbsp;The Desert Research Institute CCN spectrometer is the only CCN instrument that can cover the entire CCN spectrum simultaneously. &nbsp;Therefore, it is best suited to determine cloud S. &nbsp;During the course of this grant it was realized that the DRI CCN spectrometer has such good S resolution that it can also detect bimodal CCN spectra. &nbsp;The S value at the minimum concentrations between the modes provides an alternate S estimate. &nbsp;This is because processes within clouds cause the bimodality of CCN spectra. &nbsp;We have confirmed that these are different processes depending on cloud type. &nbsp;In stratus the predominant process is chemical and in cumulus clouds coalescence among dropelets is the predominant mechanism for making bimodal CCN spectra. &nbsp;Chemical processing increases CCN concentrations, which then makes more droplets in the next cloud whereas coalescence reduces droplet and CCN concentrations. &nbsp;The greater number of droplets caused by cloud processing thus increases solar reflection and the consequent reduced droplet sizes inhibit precipitation. &nbsp;Both of these effects increase IAE. &nbsp;Stratus clouds over the ocean predomanate IAE so cloud processing tends to increase IAE. &nbsp;</p> <p>We have observed that clouds associated with CCN spectra that are bimodal have more small droplets that reflect more solar energy and fewer large droplets that can precipitate. &nbsp;Thus cloud processing acts as an addition to IAE that is above and beyond the effect of original IAE. &nbsp;</p> <p>The S that is inferred from the bimodal CCN spectra is lower than that of the more conventional determination of S from CCN spectral comparisons with cloud droplet concentrations. &nbsp;Thus, clous S may have been underestimated. &nbsp;This needs to be corrected so that global models can better quantify IAE.</p> <p>The high-resolution CCN spectra from the DRI instruments can also determine particle hygroscopcity, water solubility, which is an important CCN property, which can help distinguish anthropogenic CCN from natural CCN. &nbsp;The bimodality of the CCN spectra makes this an easier task as the spectra needs to be overlain with particle size spectra in order to determine hygrosopicity. &nbsp;This is a much faster and easier way to determine particle hygroscopicity. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;G&nbsp;Hudson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) are the particles that cloud droplets grow upon.  Anthropogenic CCN (air pollution) cause the indirect aerosol effect (IAE), which is the largest climate uncertainty.  This is because the anthropogenic versus natural CCN ratio is unknown.  And the effects of either are unknown becasue it is so difficult to separate their effects on clouds.  It is generally thought that IAE is a global cooling effect because it increases cloud droplet concentrations, which causes more reflection of solar radiation, and the higher concentrations inhibit precipitation, which increases cloudines, which thus also increases reflection of solar radiation by clouds.    An important factor is the level of cloud supersaturations, S, which vary considerably.  Since CCN are characterized according to S they can be matched with cloud droplet concentrations to determine cloud S.  The Desert Research Institute CCN spectrometer is the only CCN instrument that can cover the entire CCN spectrum simultaneously.  Therefore, it is best suited to determine cloud S.  During the course of this grant it was realized that the DRI CCN spectrometer has such good S resolution that it can also detect bimodal CCN spectra.  The S value at the minimum concentrations between the modes provides an alternate S estimate.  This is because processes within clouds cause the bimodality of CCN spectra.  We have confirmed that these are different processes depending on cloud type.  In stratus the predominant process is chemical and in cumulus clouds coalescence among dropelets is the predominant mechanism for making bimodal CCN spectra.  Chemical processing increases CCN concentrations, which then makes more droplets in the next cloud whereas coalescence reduces droplet and CCN concentrations.  The greater number of droplets caused by cloud processing thus increases solar reflection and the consequent reduced droplet sizes inhibit precipitation.  Both of these effects increase IAE.  Stratus clouds over the ocean predomanate IAE so cloud processing tends to increase IAE.    We have observed that clouds associated with CCN spectra that are bimodal have more small droplets that reflect more solar energy and fewer large droplets that can precipitate.  Thus cloud processing acts as an addition to IAE that is above and beyond the effect of original IAE.    The S that is inferred from the bimodal CCN spectra is lower than that of the more conventional determination of S from CCN spectral comparisons with cloud droplet concentrations.  Thus, clous S may have been underestimated.  This needs to be corrected so that global models can better quantify IAE.  The high-resolution CCN spectra from the DRI instruments can also determine particle hygroscopcity, water solubility, which is an important CCN property, which can help distinguish anthropogenic CCN from natural CCN.  The bimodality of the CCN spectra makes this an easier task as the spectra needs to be overlain with particle size spectra in order to determine hygrosopicity.  This is a much faster and easier way to determine particle hygroscopicity.         Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: James G Hudson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
