<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC CGI :  SenSIP -  A Research Site of the Net-Centric Software and Systems Center</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Sensor Signal and Information Processing (SenSIP) consortium at the Arizona State University (ASU) is planning to join the Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) entitled "Net-Centric Software and Systems" which currently is a multi- university Center comprised of the University of North Texas (lead institution), and the University of Texas at Dallas. The mission of SenSIP at ASU is to develop signal and information processing foundations for next-generation integrated multidisciplinary sensing applications in biomedicine, defense, energy, and other systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ASU requests funding for becoming a third site of the NSF Center for Net-Centric Software and Systems under the leadership of Professor Andreas Spanias. ASU will bring to the existing Center much needed complementary capabilities in the areas of digital signal and image processing, multimedia systems, sensor networks, information theory and wireless communications. The proposed site will enable the creation of new capabilities in sensor signal processing and will bridge the gap between sensor development and large scale sensor deployment; and, is uniquely positioned to promote industry research, education, scholarship that will integrate well with the existing Net-Centric I/UCRC umbrella. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will advance the development of signal processing and communication technologies for sensing systems. The proposed research activities at this site are expected to lead to inexpensive, compact, and reusable sensors for industry applications of relevance to medicine, sustainability, entertainment, and defense. The proposed site has several dissemination programs and established structures for recruiting students from underrepresented groups, involving undergraduate students in research, and mechanisms to create and package online modules with interdisciplinary research and education content.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1035086</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
<LastName>Spanias</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreas S Spanias</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>spanias@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809651837</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000248204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ORSPA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>122E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8046</Code>
<Text>REV Supplements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~118000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~68000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ASU Industry University Collaborative Research Center (I/UCRC) site of the Net Centric Cloud and Computing Systems (NCSS) works closely with industry partners in the areas of signal processing, sensor networks and communications systems.&nbsp; &nbsp; The site is also strongly affiliated with the ASU Sensor Signal and Information Processing (SenSIP) center which is an Arizona State board of regents entity. &nbsp; In Phase 1 of this I/UCRC program, the ASU NCSS site signed I/UCRC membership agreements with more than 10 companies including Freescale (NXP), Intel, LG Electronics, Lockheed Martin, National Instruments, Raytheon, and Sprint.&nbsp; The center also engaged in collaborative research agreements with two SBIR companies. &nbsp;</p> <p>During the Phase 1 period of this I/UCRC, the ASU site trained more than thirty Ph.D. and Masters students several of whom are working for high-tech company members.&nbsp; Three former students of the PI have started their own companies and three others have been hired as tenure-track faculty. The center has also established internships with industry partners and some of the ASU Site students have obtained summer internships in industry labs. &nbsp;In addition, the I/UCRC site has &nbsp;trained undergraduate students through REV and REU supplements. These undergraduate students have worked with our graduate students to co-develop a ranging Android App.&nbsp; A patent pre-disclosure on the research enabling this app is co-authored by one of the REU students.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The I/UCRC award had a leveraging effect across several research fronts.&nbsp; During Phase 1, our I/UCRC program established intellectual property in several related areas involving signal processing.&nbsp; Faculty affiliated with this ASU site, have developed intellectual property in digital signal processing and sensor systems. In all, nine patent pre-disclosures were filed and two US patents were established by the PI and his colleagues. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Center projects have been established in several challenging research areas that involve signal processing and sensor systems.&nbsp; These activities included work in sustainability, health and wellness, and defense and security. &nbsp; Collaborative research in radar resulted in IP, publications and monographs in MIMO radar, exploitation of video, and sparse representations.&nbsp; Work in architectures resulted in design tools for low power implementation of speech and audio processing functions.&nbsp; Studies in embedded systems resulted in design of efficient machine learning algorithms for managing sensor data in Internet of Things (IoT) applications. Experimental investigation on mobile devices resulted in research products in motion and gesture estimation.&nbsp; Research in imaging for flow sensors addressed medical applications including aneurysm&nbsp; prediction.&nbsp; Sustainability endeavors of the center include a project on embedding multiple sensors in solar panels and monitoring utility-scale photovoltaic arrays.</p> <p>The ASU I/UCRC site also established international research partnerships with signed agreements with Imperial College (IC) funded by British Council,&nbsp; University of Cyprus (UCY) funded by the Cyprus Promotion foundation (prime EU), and Tecnol&oacute;gico de Monterrey (ITESM) funded by NSF. Papers were co-authored with IC on sensor array localization, publications were co-authored with UCy on speech detection, and research was initiated with ITESM on communication aspects of sensors.</p> <p>The ASU I/UCRC established several important research facilities including an LTE system installed&nbsp; by Sprint, &nbsp;a dedicated 18kW solar monitoring facility at the ASU research park, and networking sensing and computing facilities in the sensor lab.&nbsp; The center also established award winning signal processing simulation apps that are disseminated freely on iT...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ASU Industry University Collaborative Research Center (I/UCRC) site of the Net Centric Cloud and Computing Systems (NCSS) works closely with industry partners in the areas of signal processing, sensor networks and communications systems.    The site is also strongly affiliated with the ASU Sensor Signal and Information Processing (SenSIP) center which is an Arizona State board of regents entity.   In Phase 1 of this I/UCRC program, the ASU NCSS site signed I/UCRC membership agreements with more than 10 companies including Freescale (NXP), Intel, LG Electronics, Lockheed Martin, National Instruments, Raytheon, and Sprint.  The center also engaged in collaborative research agreements with two SBIR companies.    During the Phase 1 period of this I/UCRC, the ASU site trained more than thirty Ph.D. and Masters students several of whom are working for high-tech company members.  Three former students of the PI have started their own companies and three others have been hired as tenure-track faculty. The center has also established internships with industry partners and some of the ASU Site students have obtained summer internships in industry labs.  In addition, the I/UCRC site has  trained undergraduate students through REV and REU supplements. These undergraduate students have worked with our graduate students to co-develop a ranging Android App.  A patent pre-disclosure on the research enabling this app is co-authored by one of the REU students.    The I/UCRC award had a leveraging effect across several research fronts.  During Phase 1, our I/UCRC program established intellectual property in several related areas involving signal processing.  Faculty affiliated with this ASU site, have developed intellectual property in digital signal processing and sensor systems. In all, nine patent pre-disclosures were filed and two US patents were established by the PI and his colleagues.      Center projects have been established in several challenging research areas that involve signal processing and sensor systems.  These activities included work in sustainability, health and wellness, and defense and security.   Collaborative research in radar resulted in IP, publications and monographs in MIMO radar, exploitation of video, and sparse representations.  Work in architectures resulted in design tools for low power implementation of speech and audio processing functions.  Studies in embedded systems resulted in design of efficient machine learning algorithms for managing sensor data in Internet of Things (IoT) applications. Experimental investigation on mobile devices resulted in research products in motion and gesture estimation.  Research in imaging for flow sensors addressed medical applications including aneurysm  prediction.  Sustainability endeavors of the center include a project on embedding multiple sensors in solar panels and monitoring utility-scale photovoltaic arrays.  The ASU I/UCRC site also established international research partnerships with signed agreements with Imperial College (IC) funded by British Council,  University of Cyprus (UCY) funded by the Cyprus Promotion foundation (prime EU), and Tecnol&oacute;gico de Monterrey (ITESM) funded by NSF. Papers were co-authored with IC on sensor array localization, publications were co-authored with UCy on speech detection, and research was initiated with ITESM on communication aspects of sensors.  The ASU I/UCRC established several important research facilities including an LTE system installed  by Sprint,  a dedicated 18kW solar monitoring facility at the ASU research park, and networking sensing and computing facilities in the sensor lab.  The center also established award winning signal processing simulation apps that are disseminated freely on iTunes and Google Play.   The center engaged in outreach to middle schools, high schools and high-school Hispanic conferences for technology exposition and recruitment to engineering and STEM areas. Outreach included also high sc...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
