<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC CGI:  Center for Energy Harvesting Materials and Systems (CEHMS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>305372</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>I/UCRC for Energy Harvesting Materials and Systems &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1035042 Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Daniel Inman &lt;br/&gt;1035024 University of Texas, Dallas; Bruce Gnade &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center for Energy Harvesting Materials and Systems ((CEHMS) will focus on recovery (harvesting) of unused energy from various sources such as radio and television towers, satellites and various portable electronics. Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VT) and the University of Texas, Dallas (UTD) are collaborating to establish the proposed center, with VT as the lead institution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal seeks a grant for a new multi-university Center for Energy Harvesting Materials and Systems to focus on energy harvesting approaches. The focus of research within this center will be to investigate a wide range of potential energy harvesting opportunities in power systems, human activity, industrial machines, vehicles, vibrating structures and other such sources. While the energy harvested in any one of the opportunities is small, the accumulation effect can be very significant. The proposed researchers have identified some unique and creative opportunities to assess the value and potential for harvesting energy that would otherwise be untapped. The research is important to the US and much of the world in efforts to capture new sources of energy. The reduction in dependence on foreign oil is always of significant value. The PIs have excellent credentials for conducting the research effort, and the involvement of a number of qualified researchers from the two collaborative universities is impressive. The proposal is very well written and the project descriptions are clear and well documented. The research tasks are appropriate and appear to be very well conceived. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center has the potential to improve sustainability and profitability of US manufacturing firms by developing new technologies that will reduce energy consumption and harvest energy that is normally wasted. The proposal uses a diverse group of researchers to develop new technologies that can be used in developing new industries, new jobs, new products and new services in the future. The research team is made up of various ethnic and gender groups that have a variety of educational and professional experiences including minority and disadvantage groups. The technologies that are developed by this proposal have the potential to have a large economical impact by producing jobs in new industries and reducing the need for existing fossil fuels. The plan for involving underrepresented students and faculty in the center is very well presented and appropriate. The research program will enhance the already impressive infrastructure at the two universities. Because of the wide range of topics, the dissemination of the results will be primarily through publications and industry meeting. The students involved with the program will be well prepared to enter the workforce and provide additional technology transfer.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1035024</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Gnade</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce Gnade</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bgnade@mail.smu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2147681717</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000400222</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/04/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis W Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dwsmith@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728832782</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000395544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ray</FirstName>
<LastName>Baughman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ray Baughman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ray.baughman@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836538</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000217408</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/25/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mihaela</FirstName>
<LastName>Stefan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mihaela Stefan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mci071000@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836581</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/08/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lund</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Lund</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>benjamin.lund@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728832313</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653636</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>MANUEL</FirstName>
<LastName>QUEVEDO</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>MANUEL QUEVEDO</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>MANQUELOP@GMAIL.COM</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728835714</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000751859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>122E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>127E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ENERGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~55000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~55000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~195372</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>CEHMS addressed an important problem of our generation facing the sensor networks, wireless communication and microelectronics industries related to energy sources. We investigated electrical energy harvesting from various environmental sources such as light, temperature gradient, wind, and vibrations at nano - macro scale with minimal cost that would dramatically enhance current systems while opening a new set of devices and functionalities such as portability for currently non-portable systems.</p> <p>We believe that electric energy generation from these freely available environmental sources will lead to the development of &ldquo;self-powered&rdquo; systems. This is possible by utilizing unused power in various forms such as industrial machines, human activity, vehicles, vibrating structures and various other environmental sources. During the duration of this program, research in this arena led to the development of a wide variety of prototypes demonstrating feasibility of implementing energy harvesting systems in practical components and devices. Further, prototypes at various scales ranging from nano to macro scale applications were demostrated.</p> <p>CEHMS brought together expertise in energy harvesting areas ranging from materials to system integration to realize &ldquo;self-powered&rdquo; integrated hybrid systems. CEHMS students were exposed to &nbsp;leading edge research for energy harvesting as well as industrial research. CEHMS impacted areas in our society ranging from electronics, sensors, aircraft, medical, wireless communication, storage, textile, and materials.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Manuel&nbsp;Quevedo-Lopez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ CEHMS addressed an important problem of our generation facing the sensor networks, wireless communication and microelectronics industries related to energy sources. We investigated electrical energy harvesting from various environmental sources such as light, temperature gradient, wind, and vibrations at nano - macro scale with minimal cost that would dramatically enhance current systems while opening a new set of devices and functionalities such as portability for currently non-portable systems.  We believe that electric energy generation from these freely available environmental sources will lead to the development of "self-powered" systems. This is possible by utilizing unused power in various forms such as industrial machines, human activity, vehicles, vibrating structures and various other environmental sources. During the duration of this program, research in this arena led to the development of a wide variety of prototypes demonstrating feasibility of implementing energy harvesting systems in practical components and devices. Further, prototypes at various scales ranging from nano to macro scale applications were demostrated.  CEHMS brought together expertise in energy harvesting areas ranging from materials to system integration to realize "self-powered" integrated hybrid systems. CEHMS students were exposed to  leading edge research for energy harvesting as well as industrial research. CEHMS impacted areas in our society ranging from electronics, sensors, aircraft, medical, wireless communication, storage, textile, and materials.                Last Modified: 06/15/2017       Submitted by: Manuel Quevedo-Lopez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
