<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 18th IEEE International Conference on Nework Protocols (ICNP), Kyoto, Japan - October 5-8, 2010</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darleen Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit This travel grant supports approximately fifteen graduate students from United States institutions to attend the premier network protocol conference, the IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP) 2010 which will be held in Kyoto Japan from October 5 through October 8, 2010. The objective of the award is to widen the audience attending ICNP and, as a result, raise the level of interactions among attendees, and increase the potential for new collaboration, new investigations, and higher quality research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. Conference attendance is a crucial part of the life of a researcher. By creating new opportunities for graduate students to attend this high-quality conference, this project will benefit the research community in several ways. The students benefit from the opportunity to meet and interact with many other researchers in a favorable setting, and from seeing research presented that may be related to what they are working on, or may inspire them to try a new direction. The research community benefits from the improvement of the students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives. All attendees benefit from increased diversity of participants attending the conference, through discussions and other interactions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036856</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sonia</FirstName>
<LastName>Fahmy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sonia Fahmy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fahmy@cs.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654946183</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The funding provided by NSF for the ICNP Student Travel Grant Program proved very successful yet again in 2010. Overall, 8 students were provided travel support, including one female student (from University of Massachusetts). Two of the students (from Colorado State University and UCLA) are US citizens.<br /><br />We received 23 applications for the travel grant, though a few of these were missing recommendation letters. The applicant population was diverse, with several relatively new PhD students who had not previously attended a conference. In most cases, it appears the students would not have been able to attend if not for support from NSF, especially that travel costs to Japan from the US are high. Although 8 students were supported by NSF, we were able to obtain additional support from IEEE, enabling us to support an additional 7 students, including 2 additional female students from China. KDDI, AT&amp;T, and several companies from Japan, where the conference was located, provided significant corporate support. The support enabled us to keep registration fees low, provided greater opportunities for the research community to attend, and allowed the NSF travel grant money to support more of the travel cost of each student.</p> <p>The conference was attended by a total of 106 attendees from several countries. Several highly visible academics and industrial researchers attended and spent significant time discussing future opportunities with students.</p> <p>The ability to support a greater attendance at a premier conference<br />contributes to the ability of ICNP to help extend the professional network of the current generation of researchers and to help prepare the next generation of researchers. The continued growth of ICNP and its healthy balance between students, faculty, and industrial researchers creates a nearly ideal forum for education and interaction. Support from NSF is in no small way responsible for the continued health and visibility of the conference.<br /><br />The conference was able to provide outstanding content for the<br />students. ICNP 2010 featured two keynote speeches; 31 technical paper<br />presentations organized into nine sessions; a panel session on 'Security and Privacy in the Cloud'; a student poster session, and a PhD Forum session.<br /><br />Professor P. R. Kumar (University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign,<br />USA) and Dr. Shigeyuki Akiba (President of KDDI Research and Development Inc., Japan) were ICNP keynote speakers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2011<br>      Modified by: Sonia&nbsp;Fahmy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1036856/1036856_10034179_1313018726695_icnp1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1036856/1036856_10034179_1313018726695_icnp1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ICNP 2010"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1036856/1036856_10034179_1313018726695_icnp1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ICNP 2010"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Professor Higashino speaks during the opening session of ICNP 2010 in Kyoto, Japan in October 2010</div> <div class="imageCredit">ICNP 2010 organizing committee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sonia&nbsp;Fahmy</div> <div class="imageTitle">ICNP 2010</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1036856/1036856_10034179_131...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The funding provided by NSF for the ICNP Student Travel Grant Program proved very successful yet again in 2010. Overall, 8 students were provided travel support, including one female student (from University of Massachusetts). Two of the students (from Colorado State University and UCLA) are US citizens.  We received 23 applications for the travel grant, though a few of these were missing recommendation letters. The applicant population was diverse, with several relatively new PhD students who had not previously attended a conference. In most cases, it appears the students would not have been able to attend if not for support from NSF, especially that travel costs to Japan from the US are high. Although 8 students were supported by NSF, we were able to obtain additional support from IEEE, enabling us to support an additional 7 students, including 2 additional female students from China. KDDI, AT&amp;T, and several companies from Japan, where the conference was located, provided significant corporate support. The support enabled us to keep registration fees low, provided greater opportunities for the research community to attend, and allowed the NSF travel grant money to support more of the travel cost of each student.  The conference was attended by a total of 106 attendees from several countries. Several highly visible academics and industrial researchers attended and spent significant time discussing future opportunities with students.  The ability to support a greater attendance at a premier conference contributes to the ability of ICNP to help extend the professional network of the current generation of researchers and to help prepare the next generation of researchers. The continued growth of ICNP and its healthy balance between students, faculty, and industrial researchers creates a nearly ideal forum for education and interaction. Support from NSF is in no small way responsible for the continued health and visibility of the conference.  The conference was able to provide outstanding content for the students. ICNP 2010 featured two keynote speeches; 31 technical paper presentations organized into nine sessions; a panel session on 'Security and Privacy in the Cloud'; a student poster session, and a PhD Forum session.  Professor P. R. Kumar (University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA) and Dr. Shigeyuki Akiba (President of KDDI Research and Development Inc., Japan) were ICNP keynote speakers.          Last Modified: 08/10/2011       Submitted by: Sonia Fahmy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
