<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GSE/RES: Exploring the STEM Gender Gap: Introductory College Mathematics and Statistics Instruction and its Association with Self-Efficacy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>521423.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>528923</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>dana britton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual merit: This project studies in detail the factors through which mathematics and statistics training influences career options and choices in STEM fields, with emphasis on gender differences.  The project includes a detailed analysis of course and instructor related factors that impact women's (and men's) STEM career choices in the theoretical context of social cognitive career theory. These factors include course format, instructor characteristics (gender, minority status, native speaker, research faculty vs. teaching faculty vs. teaching graduate assistants vs. others), and characteristics of the learning environment (instructor availability, test and grading policies and frequencies, homework expectations, assessment types of student progress, instructor and course ratings, support networks including office hours, help rooms, learning communities, and supplemental instruction). Hypotheses regarding gender specific impacts of these factors are tested using two sets of data: The complete mathematical history of students from high school through community college to university major, linked with course and instructor data for all students that have entered Iowa State University since AY 2006, and a survey instrument that measures self-efficacy and mathematical self-confidence before and after basic mathematical and statistical training at Iowa State.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: The project team of educators, mathematicians and statisticians will use the findings of this study to explore instructional changes involving those factors that substantially contribute to career changes away from STEM fields, in particular for female students. Many of the factors under consideration are, at least to some extent, results of the instructional planning of academic departments. Changes in planning practices also provide the foundation for collaboration with high schools and community colleges on gender related transition and career guidance issues that would become particularly pressing if significant differences are found between graduates from different high schools or community colleges. Furthermore, collaboration with other universities will address course and instructor related factors that influence women?s attitudes and achievements in introductory mathematics and statistics courses, together with options of implementing changes aimed at closing the STEM gender gap at these institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is co-funded with the NSF EPSCoR office.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036791</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wolfgang</FirstName>
<LastName>Kliemann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wolfgang H Kliemann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kliemann@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152941752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000389615</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Dougherty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara J Dougherty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bdougher@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089564939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000393625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alicia</FirstName>
<LastName>Carriquiry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alicia L Carriquiry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alicia@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152945242</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000298456</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ulrike</FirstName>
<LastName>Genschel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ulrike Genschel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ulrike@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152947766</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000391968</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elgin</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elgin Johnston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ehjohnst@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152945225</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000531991</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1138 Pearson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1544</Code>
<Text>RES ON GENDER IN SCI &amp; ENGINE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~521423</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Regardless of gender, introductory level mathematics and statistics courses are often considered gatekeepers to bachelor&rsquo;s degree completion in the STEM sciences. In this study we investigated the role such introductory level courses play in the retention of female students in the STEM sciences and explored the association between students&rsquo; mathematical background from high school, gender specific differences in students&rsquo; self-efficacy beliefs as well as course and instructor related factors of introductory level mathematics and statistics courses. &nbsp;We further examined how these factors contribute to the retention of female students in STEM disciplines.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our findings show that female students enrolled in our study are as a group academically less&nbsp;prepared to enter a STEM science major than their male peers. Significantly fewer female students take calculus or other advanced mathematics courses in high school (33% of all female students earned at least one credit of high school calculus compared to 45% of male students. Additionally, the average ACT mathematics score is about 3 points lower for female students. Among students with high school calculus credit about 66% of females chose a STEM degree versus 86% of males. Likewise, among students with no calculus background only 38% of females pursue a STEM major versus 63% of male students.</p> <p>Mathematical self-efficacy beliefs, perceived value of mathematics, outcome expectations and interest for female students are below those of male students while we see the reverse in regards to effort that females expect to expand in order to succeed in introductory level mathematics and statistics course.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These results require, however, the following qualification: Definitions on which sciences are considered STEM differ widely and can vary from more to less inclusive. For the purpose of this study we distinguished between math-intensive and non-math-intensive STEM majors and deemed a major as math-intensive STEM if it required completion of first semester engineering calculus or equivalent. Remaining majors were classified as STEM, Social Science or Humanities. While this definition is project and institution specific it very likely merits application to a much broader group of institutions. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The implementation of this definition greatly affected our earlier findings on gender differences. While gender differences with respect to mathematical background, academic readiness and mathematical self-efficacy believes were pronounced under a more inclusive definition of STEM, these differences decreased or even disappeared for students in math-intensive STEM majors. Female students in these majors are on par with their male peers and often achieve higher grades in the first mathematics/statistics course taken.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The analyses of gender differences in STEM attrition rates suggest that a student&rsquo;s mathematical self-efficacy beliefs, perceived value, outcome expectations and interest play a decisive role and accounting for these factors explains otherwise observed gender differences. However, unlike their male peers female students leave STEM much sooner, typically within the first two semesters while male students are more likely to leave in their second year of college. The study did not find convincing evidence that any of the hypothesized contextual factors such as instructor gender, class size, instructor title and qualifications (graduate student instructor, lecturer, Assistant Professor, Tenured Associate Professor or Full Professor), native English speaker as well as years of teaching experiences of the instructor in introductory level statistics and mathematics courses contribute to a student's decision to leave STEM. This negative finding can perhaps be explained by the strong association bet...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Regardless of gender, introductory level mathematics and statistics courses are often considered gatekeepers to bachelorÆs degree completion in the STEM sciences. In this study we investigated the role such introductory level courses play in the retention of female students in the STEM sciences and explored the association between studentsÆ mathematical background from high school, gender specific differences in studentsÆ self-efficacy beliefs as well as course and instructor related factors of introductory level mathematics and statistics courses.  We further examined how these factors contribute to the retention of female students in STEM disciplines.     Our findings show that female students enrolled in our study are as a group academically less prepared to enter a STEM science major than their male peers. Significantly fewer female students take calculus or other advanced mathematics courses in high school (33% of all female students earned at least one credit of high school calculus compared to 45% of male students. Additionally, the average ACT mathematics score is about 3 points lower for female students. Among students with high school calculus credit about 66% of females chose a STEM degree versus 86% of males. Likewise, among students with no calculus background only 38% of females pursue a STEM major versus 63% of male students.  Mathematical self-efficacy beliefs, perceived value of mathematics, outcome expectations and interest for female students are below those of male students while we see the reverse in regards to effort that females expect to expand in order to succeed in introductory level mathematics and statistics course.     These results require, however, the following qualification: Definitions on which sciences are considered STEM differ widely and can vary from more to less inclusive. For the purpose of this study we distinguished between math-intensive and non-math-intensive STEM majors and deemed a major as math-intensive STEM if it required completion of first semester engineering calculus or equivalent. Remaining majors were classified as STEM, Social Science or Humanities. While this definition is project and institution specific it very likely merits application to a much broader group of institutions.      The implementation of this definition greatly affected our earlier findings on gender differences. While gender differences with respect to mathematical background, academic readiness and mathematical self-efficacy believes were pronounced under a more inclusive definition of STEM, these differences decreased or even disappeared for students in math-intensive STEM majors. Female students in these majors are on par with their male peers and often achieve higher grades in the first mathematics/statistics course taken.        The analyses of gender differences in STEM attrition rates suggest that a studentÆs mathematical self-efficacy beliefs, perceived value, outcome expectations and interest play a decisive role and accounting for these factors explains otherwise observed gender differences. However, unlike their male peers female students leave STEM much sooner, typically within the first two semesters while male students are more likely to leave in their second year of college. The study did not find convincing evidence that any of the hypothesized contextual factors such as instructor gender, class size, instructor title and qualifications (graduate student instructor, lecturer, Assistant Professor, Tenured Associate Professor or Full Professor), native English speaker as well as years of teaching experiences of the instructor in introductory level statistics and mathematics courses contribute to a student's decision to leave STEM. This negative finding can perhaps be explained by the strong association between self-efficacy beliefs and STEM retention suggesting that perhaps most detrimental to the goal of increasing the proportion of females in the STEM sciences is the studyÆs findings o...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
