<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Petascale Computing Capabilities to Address Climate Change Uncertainties</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18963.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18963</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irene Qualters</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award facilitates scientific research using the large, new, computational resource named Blue Waters being developed by IBM and scheduled to be deployed at the University of Illinois. It provides travel funds to support technical coordination between the principal investigators, the Blue Waters project team and the vendor technical team.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project addresses on-going and crucial needs for understanding and reducing uncertainties associated with numerical modeling of climate change through characterizing and accounting for current model limitations in order to reduce uncertainty associated with projected trends in our climate. The simulations and analyses are designed to use the Blue Waters petascale computing resources. The two major objectives of the project will address long recognized issues associated with understanding climate sensitivity and with model resolution. The unique super-ensemble approach used in the climate sensitivity studies and the advanced dynamical model cores used in the high resolution studies both require petascale capabilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will use state-of-the-art computational resources, namely Blue Waters, and cutting-edge modeling software in advancing the study of climate that will contribute to international (and national) assessments of the potential impacts of climate change over this century. The proposed research will be carried out collaboratively by a team of leading climate scientists who will also provide interdisciplinary training to students and postdoctoral fellows through cross-disciplinary fertilization in both thinking and ideas that will be fostered through the close interactions on this project. This will provide them with invaluable insights into both the research and educational processes. The data produced by the simulations  will be made available to the larger community of research scientists.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036146</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Wuebbles</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald J Wuebbles</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wuebbles@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172441568</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000298212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin-Zhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Liang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xin-Zhong Liang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xliang@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000125561</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>PETASCALE - TRACK 1</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~18963</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This collaborative research between the University of Illinois, the National Center for Atmospheric Research, and the University of Maryland is aimed at using the Blue Waters petascale resources to address key uncertainties associated with the numerical modeling of the Earth&rsquo;s climate system and the ability to accurately analyze past and projected future changes in climate. The project brings together a team of atmospheric and computer scientists to address these issues with well-recognized expertise in the study of past and future projections of climate and extensive experience in national and international assessments of climate change. The petascale computing capabilities allow us to pursue analyses of uncertainties in ways that were impossible before. At the same time, the high resolution of our studies allow for new science understanding that is unprecedented. Our studies are based around the latest, most advanced, versions of the Community Earth System Model, CESM, developed by NCAR, the DOE laboratories, and the university community. In addition, we also explore climate sensitivity associated with structure differences in representing physical processes through the use of the recent Cloud-Aerosol-Radiation (CAR) ensemble modeling system as coupled in the regional Climate-Weather Research and Forecasting model (CWRF). We are also using the WRF model for high resolution modeling of the climate for the United States.</p> <p>With the updated high resolution (0.25 degree atmosphere) CESM model, one 40-year present day Atmospheric Model Intercomparison (AMIP) simulation (with ocean boundary forcing taken from observations) and one 30-year future RCP8.5 AMIP simulation (using ocean forcing from an existing 1.0 degree atmosphere/ocean coupled future simulation) were completed which will be used to compare to the coarser resolution integrations.</p> <p>CESM runs of 100+ years for an 1850 control is being completed. Then we will complete the 100 year 1850 control by the end of May timeline. These results will provide the initial conditions for a historical (1850-present) simulation, which in turn facilitates a future RCP8.5 emissions scenario of the future (present-2100). These simulations, as well as additional ensemble members of each, are central to the plans for this summer and the rest of the 2015-2016 allocation, where we will also begin studies for the next major international model intercomparison, CMIP6.</p> <p>Three present day AMIP (1979-2010) experiments were conducted using CAM5 at 0.25<sup>o</sup> resolution. After examining the simulations in detail we believe the modified coupling approach (flux calculations on the higher-resolution atmosphere grid) is correct. We are modifying the existing coupler software.</p> <p>The CAM5 simulations suggest that the global number of tropical storms and hurricanes per year will decrease in a warming climate. However, there are noticeable increases in the intensity of the most intense storms and therefore the frequency of the major hurricanes (category 4 and 5). When focusing on the North Atlantic basin a decrease in the number of tropical cyclones and hurricanes is also seen in the RCP8.5 scenario. The paper by Reed et al. (2015) examines the impact of the choice of CAM5's dynamical core on tropical cyclone frequency, distribution and intensity in a pair of 26-year AMIP simulations. The dynamical core, the central fluid flow component of any general circulation model, is often overlooked in the analysis of a model's ability to simulate tropical cyclones compared to the impact of more commonly documented components (e.g., physical parameterizations). It is shown that the selection of a dynamical core can have a significant impact on tropical cyclone intensity and frequency even in the presence of similar climatology and large-scale environments.</p> <p>The Weather Research &amp; Forecasting&nbsp; (WRF) model is ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This collaborative research between the University of Illinois, the National Center for Atmospheric Research, and the University of Maryland is aimed at using the Blue Waters petascale resources to address key uncertainties associated with the numerical modeling of the EarthÆs climate system and the ability to accurately analyze past and projected future changes in climate. The project brings together a team of atmospheric and computer scientists to address these issues with well-recognized expertise in the study of past and future projections of climate and extensive experience in national and international assessments of climate change. The petascale computing capabilities allow us to pursue analyses of uncertainties in ways that were impossible before. At the same time, the high resolution of our studies allow for new science understanding that is unprecedented. Our studies are based around the latest, most advanced, versions of the Community Earth System Model, CESM, developed by NCAR, the DOE laboratories, and the university community. In addition, we also explore climate sensitivity associated with structure differences in representing physical processes through the use of the recent Cloud-Aerosol-Radiation (CAR) ensemble modeling system as coupled in the regional Climate-Weather Research and Forecasting model (CWRF). We are also using the WRF model for high resolution modeling of the climate for the United States.  With the updated high resolution (0.25 degree atmosphere) CESM model, one 40-year present day Atmospheric Model Intercomparison (AMIP) simulation (with ocean boundary forcing taken from observations) and one 30-year future RCP8.5 AMIP simulation (using ocean forcing from an existing 1.0 degree atmosphere/ocean coupled future simulation) were completed which will be used to compare to the coarser resolution integrations.  CESM runs of 100+ years for an 1850 control is being completed. Then we will complete the 100 year 1850 control by the end of May timeline. These results will provide the initial conditions for a historical (1850-present) simulation, which in turn facilitates a future RCP8.5 emissions scenario of the future (present-2100). These simulations, as well as additional ensemble members of each, are central to the plans for this summer and the rest of the 2015-2016 allocation, where we will also begin studies for the next major international model intercomparison, CMIP6.  Three present day AMIP (1979-2010) experiments were conducted using CAM5 at 0.25o resolution. After examining the simulations in detail we believe the modified coupling approach (flux calculations on the higher-resolution atmosphere grid) is correct. We are modifying the existing coupler software.  The CAM5 simulations suggest that the global number of tropical storms and hurricanes per year will decrease in a warming climate. However, there are noticeable increases in the intensity of the most intense storms and therefore the frequency of the major hurricanes (category 4 and 5). When focusing on the North Atlantic basin a decrease in the number of tropical cyclones and hurricanes is also seen in the RCP8.5 scenario. The paper by Reed et al. (2015) examines the impact of the choice of CAM5's dynamical core on tropical cyclone frequency, distribution and intensity in a pair of 26-year AMIP simulations. The dynamical core, the central fluid flow component of any general circulation model, is often overlooked in the analysis of a model's ability to simulate tropical cyclones compared to the impact of more commonly documented components (e.g., physical parameterizations). It is shown that the selection of a dynamical core can have a significant impact on tropical cyclone intensity and frequency even in the presence of similar climatology and large-scale environments.  The Weather Research &amp; Forecasting  (WRF) model is being used for high resolution regional climate studies over the contiguous U.S. Specifically, we are downscaling ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
