<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ATOL:  Collaborative Research:  Assembling the Green Algal Tree of Life (GRAToL)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>561000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>561000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Green Algae Tree of Life (GRAToL) is a project involving the collaboration of five institutions to understand the evolutionary relationships of all of the major groups of green algae, a diverse group of more than 14,000 photosynthetic species worldwide.  Green algae are abundant and play important roles in a wide variety of terrestrial and aquatic habitats, including deserts, extremely salty ponds, and coral reefs, and several species are symbiotic partners with lichens and animals.  Thus, green algae are important primary producers in most ecosystems.  Green algae are diverse in form - from microscopic single cells to large seaweeds - and function as important primary producers in most ecosystems.  The project will employ DNA sequence data to assemble a tree of life reflecting the evolutionary history of the group.  This tree will be critical for an improved classification of known species of algae as well as species that are yet to be discovered.  The project will facilitate further studies of green algae genomics and evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will train 3-4 postdoctoral researchers, several graduate students, and numerous undergraduate students in basic research on algae and genomics.  New analytical tools will be developed for use by the broader scientific community.  A public exhibit on the GRAToL will be produced, along with a web site containing images and other information on evolution of the group that will be of interest to educators and the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036466</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Karol</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth G Karol</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kkarol@nybg.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7188178719</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508102</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York Botanical Garden</Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<ZipCode>104585126</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7188178840</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2900 Southern Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073250946</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073250946</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York Botanical Garden]]></Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>104585126</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2900 Southern Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7689</Code>
<Text>ASSEMBLING THE TREE OF LIFE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7689</Code>
<Text>Assembling the Tree of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~158000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~403000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Overview of the project on Assembling the Green Algal Tree of Life (GrAToL)</p> <p>Green algae are a diverse assemblage that has an estimated 14,720 described species, of which 90% are primarily freshwater species. This is surely an underestimate of global green algal diversity because many species have only recently been discovered and concepts about what constitutes a species are changing rapidly. Green algae are abundant and play important roles in terrestrial and aquatic habitats, from extremely dry deserts to hypersaline ponds, to coral reefs, and as symbiotic partners with lichens and animals. Consequently, green algae are important primary producers in many ecosystems and their ecological and evolutionary importance can scarcely be overestimated. Although molecular studies have revealed two major groups of green algae, &ldquo;chlorophytes&rdquo; and &ldquo;charophytes&rdquo;, the relationships among major lineages within the green algae are poorly known. The goal of this GrAToL project was to generate a robust family tree for the green algae that can be used to examine important evolutionary questions and formulate a new classification for this diverse and ecologically important group of organisms. The project involved 5 institutions with 6 lead researchers that have broad expertise in algal systematics, phylogenetic analysis, and algal genomics. The team used an approach that is a hybrid of next-generation sequencing methods and PCR-based multi-gene sequencing. Together we resolved large areas of uncertainty in the phylogeny of major groups of green algae, clarified their relationship to land plants, and compiled an extensive genomic dataset that is being used to address questions of gene and genome evolution.</p> <p>Products and Discoveries</p> <p>This GrAToL research has illuminated some of the earliest events in the evolutionary history of green algae including an improved understanding of their chloroplast and mitochondrial genome evolution. We have identified one of the earliest lineages of green algae and from this named a new class, the Palmophyllophyceae. We were part of a larger team that assembled a draft nuclear genome of <em>Chara braunii</em>, a species in the freshwater green algal group called &ldquo;stoneworts,&rdquo; which is closely related to all land plants. Evolutionary novelties were identified in this genome that improve our understanding of how algae evolved into land plants more than 450 million years ago. We also discovered new stonewort species and resolved major questions in the family tree of this group. We discovered species in the USA that were thought to be extinct in the New World since the pre-Cretaceous period. These new discoveries reveal that there are many species of algae yet to be discovered and our knowledge of where different species grow is far from complete. More than 30 papers in peer-reviewed journals and books have been published, and our research has been featured in the Wall Street Journal and on popular science websites including ScienceDaily and IFLScience. Presentations of papers and posters were contributed to two International Phycological Congresses, and national meetings, including the Phycological Society of America and the Botanical Society of America, as well as regional meetings such as the Northeast Algal Symposium.</p> <p>Public Engagement and Broader Impacts</p> <p>The GrAToL project supported four PhD students, two from City University of New York and two from Fordham University. The project also supported numerous undergraduate students, predominately from Sarah Lawrence College. These students gained valuable experience and skills that they used in choosing graduate programs and use in their careers as professionals. Classroom lessons and several independent study courses were developed for undergraduates at Sarah Lawrence College. Annual workshops were given to aquatic resource managers on algal identification and diversity from Minnesota to New England. In addition, a permanent museum display is being installed in the New York Botanical Garden&rsquo;s Britton Rotunda, a public exhibition space that features some of NYBG&rsquo;s research projects. This display incorporates major findings uncovered during the course of this GrAToL project and will reach thousands of NYBG visitors annually.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2018<br>      Modified by: Kenneth&nbsp;G&nbsp;Karol</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview of the project on Assembling the Green Algal Tree of Life (GrAToL)  Green algae are a diverse assemblage that has an estimated 14,720 described species, of which 90% are primarily freshwater species. This is surely an underestimate of global green algal diversity because many species have only recently been discovered and concepts about what constitutes a species are changing rapidly. Green algae are abundant and play important roles in terrestrial and aquatic habitats, from extremely dry deserts to hypersaline ponds, to coral reefs, and as symbiotic partners with lichens and animals. Consequently, green algae are important primary producers in many ecosystems and their ecological and evolutionary importance can scarcely be overestimated. Although molecular studies have revealed two major groups of green algae, "chlorophytes" and "charophytes", the relationships among major lineages within the green algae are poorly known. The goal of this GrAToL project was to generate a robust family tree for the green algae that can be used to examine important evolutionary questions and formulate a new classification for this diverse and ecologically important group of organisms. The project involved 5 institutions with 6 lead researchers that have broad expertise in algal systematics, phylogenetic analysis, and algal genomics. The team used an approach that is a hybrid of next-generation sequencing methods and PCR-based multi-gene sequencing. Together we resolved large areas of uncertainty in the phylogeny of major groups of green algae, clarified their relationship to land plants, and compiled an extensive genomic dataset that is being used to address questions of gene and genome evolution.  Products and Discoveries  This GrAToL research has illuminated some of the earliest events in the evolutionary history of green algae including an improved understanding of their chloroplast and mitochondrial genome evolution. We have identified one of the earliest lineages of green algae and from this named a new class, the Palmophyllophyceae. We were part of a larger team that assembled a draft nuclear genome of Chara braunii, a species in the freshwater green algal group called "stoneworts," which is closely related to all land plants. Evolutionary novelties were identified in this genome that improve our understanding of how algae evolved into land plants more than 450 million years ago. We also discovered new stonewort species and resolved major questions in the family tree of this group. We discovered species in the USA that were thought to be extinct in the New World since the pre-Cretaceous period. These new discoveries reveal that there are many species of algae yet to be discovered and our knowledge of where different species grow is far from complete. More than 30 papers in peer-reviewed journals and books have been published, and our research has been featured in the Wall Street Journal and on popular science websites including ScienceDaily and IFLScience. Presentations of papers and posters were contributed to two International Phycological Congresses, and national meetings, including the Phycological Society of America and the Botanical Society of America, as well as regional meetings such as the Northeast Algal Symposium.  Public Engagement and Broader Impacts  The GrAToL project supported four PhD students, two from City University of New York and two from Fordham University. The project also supported numerous undergraduate students, predominately from Sarah Lawrence College. These students gained valuable experience and skills that they used in choosing graduate programs and use in their careers as professionals. Classroom lessons and several independent study courses were developed for undergraduates at Sarah Lawrence College. Annual workshops were given to aquatic resource managers on algal identification and diversity from Minnesota to New England. In addition, a permanent museum display is being installed in the New York Botanical Garden?s Britton Rotunda, a public exhibition space that features some of NYBG?s research projects. This display incorporates major findings uncovered during the course of this GrAToL project and will reach thousands of NYBG visitors annually.           Last Modified: 02/08/2018       Submitted by: Kenneth G Karol]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
