<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ATIP US-China Workshop on High-Performance Computing (HPC): Specialized Hardware Challenges and Advantages</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99489.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99489</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Almadena Chtchelkanova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>achtchel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927498</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ATIP requests support for a US-China Workshop on High-Performance Computing (HPC) emphasizing specialized hardware. The Workshop will include a significant set of presentations, posters, and panels from a delegation of Chinese academic, research laboratory, and industry experts as well as graduate students. Participants will address topics that include Government support for the research, development, and utilization of special purpose hardware, including GPU and self-developed processors; in addition, applications will also be stressed. Speakers from industry will provide perspectives of the importance of such hardware for real applications.&lt;br/&gt;In addition, a special effort will be made to include HPC R&amp;D developments in Hong Kong. Another important component will be a panel in which panelists and the audience identify topics that are suitable for collaborative (US-China) research and the mechanisms for developing those collaborations. A key aspect of the proposed Workshop will be the unique opportunity for members of the US research community to interact and have direct discussions with top Chinese scientists who will travel to the US to participate. A specific goal of the Workshop is to motivate the preparation of joint research proposals with researchers from both US and China.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Kahaner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David K Kahaner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kahaner@atip.or.jp</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5055635521</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000163740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Asian Technology Information Program</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871964510</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5058429020</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Central Ave SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 2000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>957677586</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASIAN TECHNOLOGY INFORMATION PROGRAM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Asian Technology Information Program]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871964510</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Central Ave SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7684</Code>
<Text>CESER-Cyberinfrastructure for</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7942</Code>
<Text>HIGH-PERFORMANCE COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~99489</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Arial;"><span style="font-size: 12pt;">There are many difficult problems associated with the development and use of high-performance computing (HPC). Important concerns include power, cost, programmability, and reliability, as well as the &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; requirement for highest performance. Recently, there has been a significant effort to utilize special purpose hardware which might be less expensive to purchase, operates at lower electrical costs, and performs better than more general purpose hardware. &nbsp;The most recent trend takes this a step further with the incorporation of GPUs, processors that were initially developed for graphics engines and game consoles. These make programming more challenging, but offer excellent cost benefit. Developing countries such as China are very strongly attracted to this approach and have considerable experience exploiting it. Finally, China recently developed an </span></span><span style="font-family: Arial;"><span style="font-size: 12pt;">energy efficient and low-cost </span></span><span style="font-family: Arial;"><span style="font-size: 12pt;">general-purpose processor that is being incorporated into Chinese domestic HPC systems. Since these scenarios present unique research challenges, it is particularly important for US researchers to hear about such developments in China and to determine whether there are opportunities to improve US domestic research. <br /> &nbsp;<br /> The Asian Technology Information Program (ATIP) held a US-China Workshop on High-Performance Computing (HPC) emphasizing specialized hardware, including a significant set of presentations, posters, and panels from a delegation of Chinese academic, research laboratory, and industry experts as well as graduate students. Participants spoke on topics such as Government support for the research, development, and utilization of special purpose hardware, including GPU and self-developed processors. Speakers from industry provided their perspective of the importance of such hardware for real applications. A panel of experts helped the audience identify topics suitable for collaborative (US-China) research and the mechanisms for developing those collaborations. </span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial;"><span style="font-size: 12pt;">A key outcome of the proposed Workshop was the interaction between the US research community and the top Chinese scientists. ATIP&rsquo;s workshop gave US scientists the opportunity to become acquainted with their Chinese colleagues, and encouraged the development of collaborations leading to joint research on especially difficult HPC problems of mutual interest. This approach is particularly important, because Chinese scientists are increasingly utilizing HPC while at the same time publishing only infrequently in English in international journals. &nbsp;Further, when viewed from a Chinese perspective, the travel costs associated with participation in international meetings are very high. As a result, only a small elite set of Chinese researchers has the opportunity to travel abroad to interact with recognized scientists outside of China. <br /> &nbsp;<br /> The workshop proceedings were made available on ATIP&rsquo;s website at <span style="color: #0000ff;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="http://atip.org">http://atip.org</a></span></span>, and ATIP also published a report summarizing the technical aspects of the workshop discussions along with analysis provided by ATIP&rsquo;s Senior HPC Advisor, Mr. Eietsu Tamura. This report was made available to the HPC research community in the US as well as other ATIP subscribers. &nbsp;In sum, ATIP&rsquo;s workshop outcomes included (a) an introduction of the US HPC research community to Chinese approaches to development and utilization of special purpose HPC hardware, (b) an opportunity for US and Chinese researchers to mee...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There are many difficult problems associated with the development and use of high-performance computing (HPC). Important concerns include power, cost, programmability, and reliability, as well as the "traditional" requirement for highest performance. Recently, there has been a significant effort to utilize special purpose hardware which might be less expensive to purchase, operates at lower electrical costs, and performs better than more general purpose hardware.  The most recent trend takes this a step further with the incorporation of GPUs, processors that were initially developed for graphics engines and game consoles. These make programming more challenging, but offer excellent cost benefit. Developing countries such as China are very strongly attracted to this approach and have considerable experience exploiting it. Finally, China recently developed an energy efficient and low-cost general-purpose processor that is being incorporated into Chinese domestic HPC systems. Since these scenarios present unique research challenges, it is particularly important for US researchers to hear about such developments in China and to determine whether there are opportunities to improve US domestic research.      The Asian Technology Information Program (ATIP) held a US-China Workshop on High-Performance Computing (HPC) emphasizing specialized hardware, including a significant set of presentations, posters, and panels from a delegation of Chinese academic, research laboratory, and industry experts as well as graduate students. Participants spoke on topics such as Government support for the research, development, and utilization of special purpose hardware, including GPU and self-developed processors. Speakers from industry provided their perspective of the importance of such hardware for real applications. A panel of experts helped the audience identify topics suitable for collaborative (US-China) research and the mechanisms for developing those collaborations.   A key outcome of the proposed Workshop was the interaction between the US research community and the top Chinese scientists. ATIPÆs workshop gave US scientists the opportunity to become acquainted with their Chinese colleagues, and encouraged the development of collaborations leading to joint research on especially difficult HPC problems of mutual interest. This approach is particularly important, because Chinese scientists are increasingly utilizing HPC while at the same time publishing only infrequently in English in international journals.  Further, when viewed from a Chinese perspective, the travel costs associated with participation in international meetings are very high. As a result, only a small elite set of Chinese researchers has the opportunity to travel abroad to interact with recognized scientists outside of China.      The workshop proceedings were made available on ATIPÆs website at http://atip.org, and ATIP also published a report summarizing the technical aspects of the workshop discussions along with analysis provided by ATIPÆs Senior HPC Advisor, Mr. Eietsu Tamura. This report was made available to the HPC research community in the US as well as other ATIP subscribers.  In sum, ATIPÆs workshop outcomes included (a) an introduction of the US HPC research community to Chinese approaches to development and utilization of special purpose HPC hardware, (b) an opportunity for US and Chinese researchers to meet and share ideas concerning HPC, and (c) motivation for the preparation of joint research proposals with researchers from both US and China.           Last Modified: 07/09/2012       Submitted by: David K Kahaner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
