<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ATOL: Collaborative Research: Assembling the Green Algal Tree of Life (GRAToL)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>606000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>657250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Green Algae Tree of Life (GRAToL) is a project involving the collaboration of five institutions to understand the evolutionary relationships of all of the major groups of green algae, a diverse group of more than 14,000 photosynthetic species worldwide.  Green algae are abundant and play important roles in a wide variety of terrestrial and aquatic habitats, including deserts, extremely salty ponds, and coral reefs, and several species are symbiotic partners with lichens and animals.  Thus, green algae are important primary producers in most ecosystems.  Green algae are diverse in form - from microscopic single cells to large seaweeds - and function as important primary producers in most ecosystems.  The project will employ DNA sequence data to assemble a tree of life reflecting the evolutionary history of the group.  This tree will be critical for an improved classification of known species of algae as well as species that are yet to be discovered.  The project will facilitate further studies of green algae genomics and evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will train 3-4 postdoctoral researchers, several graduate students, and numerous undergraduate students in basic research on algae and genomics.  New analytical tools will be developed for use by the broader scientific community.  A public exhibit on the GRAToL will be produced, along with a web site containing images and other information on evolution of the group that will be of interest to educators and the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036495</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Lopez-Bautista</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan M Lopez-Bautista</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlopez@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053481791</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000254544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[152 Rose Admin. / Box 870104]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045632635</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>808245794</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama Tuscaloosa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 University Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7689</Code>
<Text>ASSEMBLING THE TREE OF LIFE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7689</Code>
<Text>Assembling the Tree of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~406000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~6250</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~12500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~12500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~12500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Green Algae (Chlorophyta) is a group of mostly aquatic photosynthetic organisms that play important roles in our lives. They are consumed in salads, others are causing economic and ecological problems as &ldquo;green tides,&rdquo; and a few are agents of human diseases. They are also important in the understanding of evolution in our planet since they gave origin to the group of organisms that we call &ldquo;land plants.&rdquo; Land plants produce ca. 50% of the oxygen that we use, while the other 50%, is produced by green algae and other algae from marine and freshwater environments. The GRAToL project was born about this concern to advance our knowledge on this important group of organisms by exploring their systematics, evolution and biodiversity. In order to develop this program a group of scientists was formed from several institutions: Lopez-Bautista (UAlabama), Delwiche (UMaryland), Karol (NYBotanical Garden), Louise and Paul Lewis (UConnecticut), and McCourt (DrexelU). Specifically our laboratory was focusing on the Class Ulvophyceae (including major orders such as Ulvales, Dasycladales, Cladophorales, Trentepohliales, Bryopsidales, among others). Recently, with the technological advancement and cost-effective generation of genome sequencing and analyses, we have been adding a pipeline of phylogenomic analysis to our goals. We have generated a wealth of genetic information that represents the breadth of green algal diversity. Two of the most unexpected discoveries a new branch of the tree of life of green algae, the Palmophyllophyceae, that represents the oldest and deepest branch of the Tree of Life for green algae (Chlorophyta). Our second discovery was the novel architecture of a plastid genome in green algae from the order Cladophorales; most plastids genomes are circular but in this group of green algae the plastids genes have been a mystery for decades, our results indicate that the plastid genome is entirely fragmented in hairpin chromosomes. A chloroplast genome of this type is unprecedented among eukaryotes, and highlights unexpected variation in plastid genome architectures. These and other information have been published in scientific journals, presented in national and international conferences, and the genetic information obtained through this project has been deposited at the national NCBI repository for public access. A diverse group of individuals were trained in systematics and genomics, including undergraduate and graduate students, postdoctoral researchers and scientists that constitute a new generation of philologists using state of the art technology to implement new advances in several areas such as biotechnology, ecology and education.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2017<br>      Modified by: Juan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lopez-Bautista</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Green Algae (Chlorophyta) is a group of mostly aquatic photosynthetic organisms that play important roles in our lives. They are consumed in salads, others are causing economic and ecological problems as "green tides," and a few are agents of human diseases. They are also important in the understanding of evolution in our planet since they gave origin to the group of organisms that we call "land plants." Land plants produce ca. 50% of the oxygen that we use, while the other 50%, is produced by green algae and other algae from marine and freshwater environments. The GRAToL project was born about this concern to advance our knowledge on this important group of organisms by exploring their systematics, evolution and biodiversity. In order to develop this program a group of scientists was formed from several institutions: Lopez-Bautista (UAlabama), Delwiche (UMaryland), Karol (NYBotanical Garden), Louise and Paul Lewis (UConnecticut), and McCourt (DrexelU). Specifically our laboratory was focusing on the Class Ulvophyceae (including major orders such as Ulvales, Dasycladales, Cladophorales, Trentepohliales, Bryopsidales, among others). Recently, with the technological advancement and cost-effective generation of genome sequencing and analyses, we have been adding a pipeline of phylogenomic analysis to our goals. We have generated a wealth of genetic information that represents the breadth of green algal diversity. Two of the most unexpected discoveries a new branch of the tree of life of green algae, the Palmophyllophyceae, that represents the oldest and deepest branch of the Tree of Life for green algae (Chlorophyta). Our second discovery was the novel architecture of a plastid genome in green algae from the order Cladophorales; most plastids genomes are circular but in this group of green algae the plastids genes have been a mystery for decades, our results indicate that the plastid genome is entirely fragmented in hairpin chromosomes. A chloroplast genome of this type is unprecedented among eukaryotes, and highlights unexpected variation in plastid genome architectures. These and other information have been published in scientific journals, presented in national and international conferences, and the genetic information obtained through this project has been deposited at the national NCBI repository for public access. A diverse group of individuals were trained in systematics and genomics, including undergraduate and graduate students, postdoctoral researchers and scientists that constitute a new generation of philologists using state of the art technology to implement new advances in several areas such as biotechnology, ecology and education.          Last Modified: 12/16/2017       Submitted by: Juan M Lopez-Bautista]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
