<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building STEM Capacity for the Nation: A National Student Research Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1504307.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1805167</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) will organize the student conference for selected programs of the National Science Foundation (NSF) Human Resources Development (HRD) division in 2011 and 2012. The conference will include undergraduate and graduate students from the Historically Black Colleges and Universities -Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP), Tribal Colleges and Universities Programs (TCUP), Research in Disabilities Education (RDE), the Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP), and the Centers of Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each of the conferences will be planned with the NSF HRD Program Officers and awardees of the NSF HRD Programs. The final theme and title for each of the conferences will be decided with an advisory committee and will provide undergraduate and graduate students from the NSF HRD programs with the knowledge and skills needed to smoothly transition into graduate programs and/or the STEM workforce. The general conference format for the 2-1/2 day conference will include:&lt;br/&gt;- Undergraduate poster and oral presentations;&lt;br/&gt;- Graduate students oral and poster presentations;&lt;br/&gt;- Workshops focused on strategies for applying for and succeeding in graduate programs and finding funding for graduate school;&lt;br/&gt;- Career preparation workshops focused on employment searches and retention, and;&lt;br/&gt;- Workshops that highlight STEM in a global context and international research and education opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students and faculty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A networking session will be designed to connect undergraduate students with graduate students and graduate students with postdoctoral fellows. The conference will include plenary sessions, including one with policymakers on the importance of broadening participation in the STEM workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1036084</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yolanda</FirstName>
<LastName>George</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yolanda S George</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>YGeorge@aaas.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023266677</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000360941</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200053928</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023266400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 NEW YORK AVENUE, N.W.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077795672</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077795672</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Association for the Advancement of Science]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200053928</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 NEW YORK AVENUE, N.W.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>Centers for Rsch Excell in S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1504307</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~201200</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~99660</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) and the <a href="http://nsf.gov/div/index.jsp?div=HRD/t_blank">National Science Foundation (NSF) Division of Human Resource Development (HRD)</a>&nbsp;co-hosted the 2011, 2012, and 2013 Emerging Researchers National (ERN) Conference in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM).</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>The objective of the ERN Conference is to help undergraduate and graduate students enhance their science communication skills and to better understand how to prepare for science careers in a global workforce.</p> <p>The 2-1/2 day conferences were aimed at students who participate in programs funded by the NSF HRD Unit and the Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Programs, including underrepresented minorities and persons with disabilities. NSF HRD Programs include:</p> <p>***Alliance for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP);</p> <p>***Centers of Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST);</p> <p>***Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU?UP);</p> <p>***Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) and LSAMP Bridges to the Doctorate;</p> <p>***Research in Disabilities Education (RDE); and</p> <p>***Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP).</p> <p>Attendance for the 2011, 2012 and 2013 ERN Conferences was 760, 885, and 828, respectively. Attendees included students, faculty, administrators, and others.</p> <p>The number of institutions participating in the ERN Conference increased from 163 in 2011 to 218 in 2013, an increase of 55 institutions.</p> <p>The number of STEM students attending the 2011-13 ERN Conferences ranged between 586 and 621. For 2011-2013, students represented 66.6% to 75% of the ERN conference attendees.</p> <p>The number of student abstracts submitted for the ERN Conference grew from 542 to 639 in 2013, an increase of 97.</p> <p>Students classified as college seniors or juniors represented nearly 64% of all 2013 ERN Conference students. Graduate student participation in the ERN conference decreased from 112 in 2011 to 87 in 2013, a decrease of 25.</p> <p>Of the 607 students who reported their discipline for the 2013 ERN Conference, 224 or 36.9% were biology majors, 93 or 15.3% were technology and engineering majors, and 14.8% were chemistry majors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>In general the conference format is interactive, and sessions are designed to provide mentoring and coaching in scientific communication, as well as applying for and succeeding in STEM graduate programs and careers.</p> <p>On a scale of 1-5, with 5 being the highest rating, all the ERN Conferences plenary and poster and oral presentation sessions and workshops were rated in the very good range, with highest rating being the James Gates, University of Maryland 2013 Awards Banquet&nbsp;presentation (4.63). Only 3 sessions were rated below 4, with the lowest rating being 3.77.</p> <p>The 2011-2013 ERN Conferences and pre-conference activities ratings were in the very good range (on a scale of 1-5, with 5 being the highest rating) in terms of helping participants to better understand:</p> <p>***How to prepare and submit abstracts for STEM conference poster and oral presentations (4.03 &ndash; 4.20 ratings).</p> <p>***How to prepare posters (3.98 - .4.23 ratings).</p> <p>***How to prepare an oral presentation (4.06 &ndash; 4.22 ratings).</p> <p>***How to communicate science findings (4.01 &ndash; 4.26 ratings).</p> <p>***How to network with peers, faculty, and others (4.1 rating all the years).</p> <p>&nbsp;***Science in a global context (3.96 &ndash; 4.22 ratings).</p> <p>The 2011-2013 ERN Conferences were rated in the nearly very good to very good range (on a scale of 1-5, with 5 being the highest rating) in terms of helping students to identify:</p> <p>***Internship opportunities (3.81 &ndash; 4.09 ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) and the National Science Foundation (NSF) Division of Human Resource Development (HRD) co-hosted the 2011, 2012, and 2013 Emerging Researchers National (ERN) Conference in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM).  Intellectual Merit  The objective of the ERN Conference is to help undergraduate and graduate students enhance their science communication skills and to better understand how to prepare for science careers in a global workforce.  The 2-1/2 day conferences were aimed at students who participate in programs funded by the NSF HRD Unit and the Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Programs, including underrepresented minorities and persons with disabilities. NSF HRD Programs include:  ***Alliance for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP);  ***Centers of Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST);  ***Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU?UP);  ***Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) and LSAMP Bridges to the Doctorate;  ***Research in Disabilities Education (RDE); and  ***Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP).  Attendance for the 2011, 2012 and 2013 ERN Conferences was 760, 885, and 828, respectively. Attendees included students, faculty, administrators, and others.  The number of institutions participating in the ERN Conference increased from 163 in 2011 to 218 in 2013, an increase of 55 institutions.  The number of STEM students attending the 2011-13 ERN Conferences ranged between 586 and 621. For 2011-2013, students represented 66.6% to 75% of the ERN conference attendees.  The number of student abstracts submitted for the ERN Conference grew from 542 to 639 in 2013, an increase of 97.  Students classified as college seniors or juniors represented nearly 64% of all 2013 ERN Conference students. Graduate student participation in the ERN conference decreased from 112 in 2011 to 87 in 2013, a decrease of 25.  Of the 607 students who reported their discipline for the 2013 ERN Conference, 224 or 36.9% were biology majors, 93 or 15.3% were technology and engineering majors, and 14.8% were chemistry majors.     Broader Impacts  In general the conference format is interactive, and sessions are designed to provide mentoring and coaching in scientific communication, as well as applying for and succeeding in STEM graduate programs and careers.  On a scale of 1-5, with 5 being the highest rating, all the ERN Conferences plenary and poster and oral presentation sessions and workshops were rated in the very good range, with highest rating being the James Gates, University of Maryland 2013 Awards Banquet presentation (4.63). Only 3 sessions were rated below 4, with the lowest rating being 3.77.  The 2011-2013 ERN Conferences and pre-conference activities ratings were in the very good range (on a scale of 1-5, with 5 being the highest rating) in terms of helping participants to better understand:  ***How to prepare and submit abstracts for STEM conference poster and oral presentations (4.03 &ndash; 4.20 ratings).  ***How to prepare posters (3.98 - .4.23 ratings).  ***How to prepare an oral presentation (4.06 &ndash; 4.22 ratings).  ***How to communicate science findings (4.01 &ndash; 4.26 ratings).  ***How to network with peers, faculty, and others (4.1 rating all the years).   ***Science in a global context (3.96 &ndash; 4.22 ratings).  The 2011-2013 ERN Conferences were rated in the nearly very good to very good range (on a scale of 1-5, with 5 being the highest rating) in terms of helping students to identify:  ***Internship opportunities (3.81 &ndash; 4.09 ratings).  ***Graduate school opportunities (3.89 &ndash; 4.19 ratings).  ***Financial aid information for graduate school (3.62 &ndash; 3.91 ratings).  ***Career resources (3.64 &ndash; 4.00 ratings).  ***Employment opportunities (3.42 &ndash; 3.79 ratings).  ***Travel awards for professional meetings (3.44...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
