<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Sino-USA Summer School in Vision, Learning, Pattern Recognition VLPR 2010</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924768</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The recent decade has witnessed rapid advances in computer vision research, not only in its fundamental studies but also its emerging applications. This Sino-USA summer school in Vision, Learning and Pattern Recognition (VLPR 2010) is held in Xi'an City, China. It brings together a high-quality team of leading American and Chinese researchers in computer vision to offer a one-week educational program to students and junior scholars from both US and China. This education program provides an important opportunity to discuss recent advance in Perception, Motion and Events, and allows technical and culture exchanges between researchers from two countries. Such interactions are important for fostering new understanding and new collaborations in science, education, and culture. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Summer School web site: http://vlpr2010.eecs.northwestern.edu/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1037845</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Rehg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Rehg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rehg@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048949105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000257071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL PLAN &amp; WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <a href="http://vlpr2010.eecs.northwestern.edu/index.html">2010 Sino-USA Summer School in Vision, Learning, and Pattern Recognition</a> was held in Xian, China from July 18-26, 2010. The program consisted of presentations by distinguished researchers from US universities, including Georgia Tech, CMU, USC, Penn State, UCSB, Northwestern, and Texas A&amp;M. In addition, a workshop entitled <a href="http://vlpr2010.eecs.northwestern.edu/SummerSchool_IndustrialWorkshop.htm">From Academia to Industry: A Comprehensive View of Computer Vision</a> was held in conjunction with the summer school and featured presentations by senior researchers from industry and academia. A lively program of cultural events arranged by Xi'an Jiaotong University rounded out the meeting.</p> <p>The summer school was attended by graduate students from the US and China, who were selected through a competitive review process based on their accomplishments and research potential. The meeting afforded a unique opportunity for these students to advance their understanding of research issues and activities, and an opportunity make contacts with other students who share their interests. This conference played a key role in building ties between the computer vision research communities in the US and China, and will foster greater international collaboration in addressing key research questions.</p> <p>In recent years, advances in computer vision and pattern recognition have led to a broad range of new products and services, including medical imaging methods, content-based image search, driver assistance and automobile safety systems, smart phones and cameras, and a variety of industrial and security systems, to name just a few areas. The rapid advance of technology and the need for more innovations to address problems of societal importance make it more important than ever to build a global research community. This workshop was an important step towards this goal.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2012<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Rehg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2010 Sino-USA Summer School in Vision, Learning, and Pattern Recognition was held in Xian, China from July 18-26, 2010. The program consisted of presentations by distinguished researchers from US universities, including Georgia Tech, CMU, USC, Penn State, UCSB, Northwestern, and Texas A&amp;M. In addition, a workshop entitled From Academia to Industry: A Comprehensive View of Computer Vision was held in conjunction with the summer school and featured presentations by senior researchers from industry and academia. A lively program of cultural events arranged by Xi'an Jiaotong University rounded out the meeting.  The summer school was attended by graduate students from the US and China, who were selected through a competitive review process based on their accomplishments and research potential. The meeting afforded a unique opportunity for these students to advance their understanding of research issues and activities, and an opportunity make contacts with other students who share their interests. This conference played a key role in building ties between the computer vision research communities in the US and China, and will foster greater international collaboration in addressing key research questions.  In recent years, advances in computer vision and pattern recognition have led to a broad range of new products and services, including medical imaging methods, content-based image search, driver assistance and automobile safety systems, smart phones and cameras, and a variety of industrial and security systems, to name just a few areas. The rapid advance of technology and the need for more innovations to address problems of societal importance make it more important than ever to build a global research community. This workshop was an important step towards this goal.       Last Modified: 01/26/2012       Submitted by: James Rehg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
