<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>VetEngrProject</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>189876.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>189876</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donna Riley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This engineering education research project seeks to set a model for other institutions by developing and implementing an intensive "boot camp" based on cohorts to transition veterans to four year engineering degree programs.  A particular emphasis of the proposal is on providing needed skills in mathematics, to ensure those coming from military service are given the tools to succeed in engineering programs.  The proposed program is comprehensive, addressing elements such as internships with industry, mentoring, recruitment, and cultural orientation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project will be to develop, then test, a model to help transition veterans to engineering degree programs.  The overall goal of this project is to leverage the military service and experience of veterans to increase success in obtaining engineering degrees.  Should this project be successful, the knowledge gained and practices developed may help other engineering schools recruit and retain veteran students.  A particular feature of this project is the focus on support for veterans with a wide spectrum of disabilities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1037814</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Endicott-Popovsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Endicott-Popovsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>endicott@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2062846123</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amelia</FirstName>
<LastName>Phillips</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amelia Phillips</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aphillips@highline.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065793674</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000766972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~189876</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>VetEngr PROJECT </strong>EEC-1037814<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Transitioning America&rsquo;s Veterans to Science, Technology, </strong><strong>Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) Academic Programs</strong></p> <p><strong>PROJECT OUTCOMES REPORT</strong></p> <p>As a grateful nation repays transitioning veterans for their sacrifices through<br />the new GI Bill, there is a new call to duty these heroes can answer. We face a serious deficit in scientists, engineers and technologists. By using their<br />benefits for a STEM education, our veterans can serve the country yet again.</p> <p>Washington State has stepped up to lead in transitioning soldiers into academic STEM programs and in overcoming barriers identified in the NSF&rsquo;s &ldquo; Veteran&rsquo;s Education for Engineering and Science&rdquo; May2009 report. The region has 1) a significant concentration of transitioning military forces, 2) a nationally recognized National Guard Employment Enhancement Program (NGEEP) that assists veterans with transition into civilian life, 3) high tech industries (Boeing, Microsoft, PNNL, etc.) eager to support our returning vets, and 4) a will to collaborate among all of us to make this happen.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Inspired by an NSF Workshop &ldquo;Enhancing Post 9/11 Veterans Educational<br />Benefits&rdquo; (NSF <em>STEM</em> planning grant #0951441 to Mississippi State University), the University of Washington developed a pilot program, <em>VetsEngrProject</em>, to study the transition of a cohort of 10 veterans through their first year of academic studies, providing support for overcoming roadblocks to that transition. Further, we developed an effective math boot camp that boosts soldiers&rsquo; math confidence and ability to enter STEM programs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts:</strong> The PI provided NSF STEM planning grant #0951441 participants with reports on our findings and brought them to a business round table (November 2011) that recruited industry for internships and jobs. Further, we built a pipeline from the WNG through academics into jobs in cybersecurity ensuring our efforts are sustained beyond the V<em>etsEngr Project&nbsp;(Se</em>e images). We forged a partnership with the City of Seattle PRISEM alert system for internships in live fire incident response&mdash;preparation for job placement. We are scaling the program with successive cohorts of veterans and are pursuing funding for subsequent efforts. Publications are underway and publicity has been extensive.</p> <p>Plans are underway to spread our math bootcamps to other community colleges, including seeking funding for a train-the-trainers program. Publications are planned in journals and conferences that address a community college audience. &nbsp;</p> <p><em><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">PUBLIC ADDRESSES</span></strong></em></p> <p><em>Developing cyber defenders to protect the homeland: One university&rsquo;s approach</em>. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;May 19, 2011</p> <p>Cyber Physical Systems Day, Daegu<br />Gyeongbuk Institute of Science and Technology<br />(DGIST), Daegu, Korea<em>.</em></p> <p><br /><em>Transitioning America's veterans to STEM academic programs</em> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;March 15, 2011</p> <p>Veterans Education in Science and Engineering, National<br />Science Foundation, Reston, VA.</p> <div> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em><strong>MEDIA APPEARANCES</strong></em></span></p> </div> <p><em><span style="text...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ VetEngr PROJECT EEC-1037814   Transitioning AmericaÆs Veterans to Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) Academic Programs  PROJECT OUTCOMES REPORT  As a grateful nation repays transitioning veterans for their sacrifices through the new GI Bill, there is a new call to duty these heroes can answer. We face a serious deficit in scientists, engineers and technologists. By using their benefits for a STEM education, our veterans can serve the country yet again.  Washington State has stepped up to lead in transitioning soldiers into academic STEM programs and in overcoming barriers identified in the NSFÆs " VeteranÆs Education for Engineering and Science" May2009 report. The region has 1) a significant concentration of transitioning military forces, 2) a nationally recognized National Guard Employment Enhancement Program (NGEEP) that assists veterans with transition into civilian life, 3) high tech industries (Boeing, Microsoft, PNNL, etc.) eager to support our returning vets, and 4) a will to collaborate among all of us to make this happen.     Inspired by an NSF Workshop "Enhancing Post 9/11 Veterans Educational Benefits" (NSF STEM planning grant #0951441 to Mississippi State University), the University of Washington developed a pilot program, VetsEngrProject, to study the transition of a cohort of 10 veterans through their first year of academic studies, providing support for overcoming roadblocks to that transition. Further, we developed an effective math boot camp that boosts soldiersÆ math confidence and ability to enter STEM programs.     Broader impacts: The PI provided NSF STEM planning grant #0951441 participants with reports on our findings and brought them to a business round table (November 2011) that recruited industry for internships and jobs. Further, we built a pipeline from the WNG through academics into jobs in cybersecurity ensuring our efforts are sustained beyond the VetsEngr Project (See images). We forged a partnership with the City of Seattle PRISEM alert system for internships in live fire incident response&mdash;preparation for job placement. We are scaling the program with successive cohorts of veterans and are pursuing funding for subsequent efforts. Publications are underway and publicity has been extensive.  Plans are underway to spread our math bootcamps to other community colleges, including seeking funding for a train-the-trainers program. Publications are planned in journals and conferences that address a community college audience.    PUBLIC ADDRESSES  Developing cyber defenders to protect the homeland: One universityÆs approach.                           May 19, 2011  Cyber Physical Systems Day, Daegu Gyeongbuk Institute of Science and Technology (DGIST), Daegu, Korea.   Transitioning America's veterans to STEM academic programs                                                    March 15, 2011  Veterans Education in Science and Engineering, National Science Foundation, Reston, VA.   MEDIA APPEARANCES   Original Press  Adam Ashton. WA National Guard focusing on cyber security. Tacoma News Tribune. October 7, 2012.  Broadcast Interviews   Glen Farley. Cyberspace: The modern battlefield. KING 5 News, October 5, 2012   Intellectual merit: VetsEngrProject, as field research, conducted externally evaluated boot camps in math that significantly decreased studentsÆ math anxiety, preparing veterans for a range of STEM programs that require math backgrounds. Several innovations were introduced in these bootcamps including the emporium approach (one room school house with every level of math competence functioning at the same time) and the introduction of KINECT as a tool to engage students physically in the creation of graphs and formulas. We also evaluated the effectiveness of our cultural orientation programs, buddy system application and mentoring programs through an external evaluation that included individual interviews and focus group data.  Objectives of VetsEngrProject            ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
