<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  LiT:  Vulnerability of Tropical Ectotherms to Climate Warming</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>177742.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>177742</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kimberly Hammond</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Biological impacts of climate warming are well documented at mid- to high latitudes, where warming is relatively rapid. However, recent theoretical models predict that tropical coldblooded species (called ectotherms), such as plants, insects, reptiles, fish, are also vulnerable to warming, even though tropical warming is relatively slow. An immediate way to test whether tropical ectotherms are being affected involves comparing current physiological and ecological data with historical data gathered prior to recent warming. Thus, by replicating historical studies, physiological and ecological changes that may have already occurred in parallel with recent climate warming can be detected. Puerto Rico is the ideal venue for such comparisons. In the 1970s and 1980s (prior to recent warming), extensive baseline studies were made of the physiology, reproduction, and ecology of Anolis lizards. No comparable data sets exist for any tropical ectotherm. Puerto Rico has warmed since those baseline studies and is projected to warm more. Simulations predict that these warmer temperatures should have induced heat stress in forest Anolis populations in the summer, but actually increased reproduction during the winter. To test these predictions, baseline study sites will be revisited, and reproductive rates, body and environmental temperatures, and feeding success will be quantified and compared to parallel data collected 25-30 years ago. The investigators who did the original studies will replicate their own studies: thus comparisons between decades will not be influenced by between-investigator differences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of the Research: If these studies document that tropical ectotherms are indeed vulnerable to climate warming, the ecological, agricultural, and economic implications are serious because the tropics are the earth's center of biodiversity and its main engine of primary productivity. In many tropical habitats, reptiles and amphibians are key component of the food web and their loss may precipitate catastrophic changes in tropical communities. The project will provide training in field ecology and physiology to undergraduate and graduate students from five universities or colleges. Under-represented minorities will be recruited from the University&lt;br/&gt;of Puerto Rico (undergraduates, graduates) and from LaGuardia Community College (NYC), both of which enroll largely minority undergraduate populations. Undergraduate women will be recruited from Barnard College, a women's college. Outreach to pre-college teachers and students will be an important component of the project and will take place through established connections with organizations such as the New York State STEM Initiative, the Ohio State STEM Learning Network, and the American Museum of Natural History. A public symposium at the University of Puerto Rico will enable project researchers, Puerto Rican scientists, and students to interact and share research ideas and results. A new generation of field workers will be mentored: they can potentially replicate these studies in future decades and thus maintain this unique time series of physiological and ecological responses of tropical ectotherms to climate warming.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1038013</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bradford</FirstName>
<LastName>Lister</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bradford C Lister</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>listeb@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182762143</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000104410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrative Ecologi Physiology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7949</Code>
<Text>LIFE IN TRANSITION (LiT)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~177742</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Climate Warming Restructures a Rainforest Ecosystem</strong></p> <p>Brad Lister, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>While tropical rainforests harbor more than 50% of the world&rsquo;s species, comparatively little is known about the impact of climate warming on rainforest communities. One approach to enhancing our understanding is to compare current data with studies conducted in tropical forests before the rise in ambient temperature that has occurred over the past 30 years. As part of my NSF-funded research, I was able to repeat studies that I conducted during the 1970s in Puerto Rico&rsquo;s Luquillo rainforest. Since that time, average temperature within the forest has risen by more than two degrees Centigrade, one of the highest increases recorded for a tropical location. To determine the extent of change in food resources available to forest insectivores, we utilized sticky traps just as I had done in my previous research. We discovered that insect biomass was up to 50 times less than I had found during the 1970s.&nbsp;</p> <p>Several studies have predicted that tropical insects should be especially sensitive to increases in temperature, and we believe that this sensitivity is the primary mechanism driving the catastrophic decline in insects within the Luquillo forest. In theory, such a major disruption at the lower levels of the forest food web should precipitate bottom-up changes in the abundances of species occupying higher trophic levels. We censused insect eating forest lizards and found that, compared to my previous censuses within the same study area, two species had gone extinct, one formerly abundant species was now 10 to 20 times less abundant, and the density of the dominant species during the 1970s had decreased by 50%. We also analyzed long term data taken during the NSF sponsored Long Term Ecological Research project at Luquillo&rsquo;s El Verde research station, and found that declines in the abundances of insectivorous frogs and birds were as great, or greater, than those of the forest lizards, falling by 300-400% over the previous 25 years. We suspect that tropical forests around the world may be experiencing a similar collapse in their insect populations, with consequent bottom-up dismantling of their food webs. If this is the case, then the negative impact of climate warming on the structure and functioning of tropical ecosystems may be even greater than hitherto imagined.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Bradford&nbsp;C&nbsp;Lister</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Climate Warming Restructures a Rainforest Ecosystem  Brad Lister, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute      While tropical rainforests harbor more than 50% of the worldÆs species, comparatively little is known about the impact of climate warming on rainforest communities. One approach to enhancing our understanding is to compare current data with studies conducted in tropical forests before the rise in ambient temperature that has occurred over the past 30 years. As part of my NSF-funded research, I was able to repeat studies that I conducted during the 1970s in Puerto RicoÆs Luquillo rainforest. Since that time, average temperature within the forest has risen by more than two degrees Centigrade, one of the highest increases recorded for a tropical location. To determine the extent of change in food resources available to forest insectivores, we utilized sticky traps just as I had done in my previous research. We discovered that insect biomass was up to 50 times less than I had found during the 1970s.   Several studies have predicted that tropical insects should be especially sensitive to increases in temperature, and we believe that this sensitivity is the primary mechanism driving the catastrophic decline in insects within the Luquillo forest. In theory, such a major disruption at the lower levels of the forest food web should precipitate bottom-up changes in the abundances of species occupying higher trophic levels. We censused insect eating forest lizards and found that, compared to my previous censuses within the same study area, two species had gone extinct, one formerly abundant species was now 10 to 20 times less abundant, and the density of the dominant species during the 1970s had decreased by 50%. We also analyzed long term data taken during the NSF sponsored Long Term Ecological Research project at LuquilloÆs El Verde research station, and found that declines in the abundances of insectivorous frogs and birds were as great, or greater, than those of the forest lizards, falling by 300-400% over the previous 25 years. We suspect that tropical forests around the world may be experiencing a similar collapse in their insect populations, with consequent bottom-up dismantling of their food webs. If this is the case, then the negative impact of climate warming on the structure and functioning of tropical ecosystems may be even greater than hitherto imagined.          Last Modified: 01/14/2016       Submitted by: Bradford C Lister]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
