<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Development of an NMR Console for the 36 T Series Hybrid</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The development of a nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) console is essential to carry out the scientific program for which the Series Hybrid magnet at the NHMFL was funded.  The proposed console together with the new high homogeneity magnet will increase the available field for high-homogeneity NMR from 23 to 36 T and provide important scientific opportunities.  For the first time, scientists will be able to obtain chemically resolved spectra of strongly broadened isotopes.  These quadrupolar nuclei, which comprise most of the periodic table and which are important for catalysts, porous materials, batteries and fuel cells, are sensitive to the molecular electric field but are impractical to study by lower field NMR due to their extreme line broadening.  In addition, more than 25% of all biological macromolecules contain metals.  These nuclei  will also be newly accessible to NMR.   The quadrupolar species 17^O and 14^N are important sites of functional activity, and will be directly observable at 36 T.  The console will also facilitate development of new techniques for 1H NMR analysis of solid materials, in which the resonance lines are broadened by large spin interactions.  By combining very high field and very fast sample spinning, 1H solid state NMR spectroscopy promises to become a very sensitive tool with adequate spectral resolution for scientific challenges, ranging from functionalized silicate surfaces to macromolecular studies.  The user facility, providing high quality spectroscopy at up to 36 T, will allow the United States to stay at the forefront of solid state magnetic resonance for the foreseeable future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Analysis of the  weak magnetic signals from hydrogen led to the revolution in medicine that we know as MRI, or Magnetic Resonance Imaging.  Past developments in MRI and its first cousin nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), which uses the same signals for chemical analysis, have been significant enough to garner four Nobel prizes.  And yet, of all the elements, only a handful can be observed in conventional MRI scanners and NMR spectrometers.  Other elements, including most of those important to science and medicine, produce only poorly resolved signals in the magnets typically available in laboratories.   The proposed NMR/MRI scanner, together with a strong new NSF-supported magnet already under construction, will greatly extend the range of elements that can be studied by NMR to include most of the periodic table.   Analyzing the chemical configuration of these elements has the potential to improve many areas of life, such as the development of batteries and fuel cells, and of new catalysts.   The spectrometer is essential to carry out the scientific program of the NSF-funded series hybrid magnet, a new powered research magnet that uses less energy, and has a more uniform and constant field than previous powered magnets.   The innovative magnet and NMR spectrometer will become part of the Mag Lab's user program, allowing the U.S. to stay at the forefront of magnetic resonance research for the foreseeable future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1039938</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Cross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy A Cross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cross@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506440917</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000098951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Brey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William W Brey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wbrey@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506453293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000266356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Bird</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark D Bird</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bird@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506447789</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244210</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Grant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel C Grant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grantsa@eng.famu.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8504106158</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhehong</FirstName>
<LastName>Gan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhehong Gan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gan@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506444662</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516552</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has supported the development of a state-of-the-art NMR spectrometer to operate at 1H frequencies from 1000 to 1500 MHz to be used in conjunction with the 36 Tesla Series Connected Hybrid (SCH) magnet that is fully funded (DMR-0603042) and under construction at the NHMFL. This spectrometer&rsquo;s unique mission will be to perform potentially transformative science in an unexplored magnetic field range for a broad range of applications, from biological macromolecules to synthetic catalysts, and from battery materials to biological tissues. With today&rsquo;s commercially available superconducting magnets, these studies are limited to a 1H frequency of &le;1000 MHz (23.4 Tesla). The practical limit to these magnets based on metallic superconductors is at best about 25 T. Further increases in field strength are not expected until high temperature superconductor based magnets become available. The SCH represents an increase in field strength of more than 50%, equivalent to more than a two decade advance in superconductive magnet technology for arguably the most important tool in chemistry and biochemistry. This development will make many nuclei available for investigations with unprecedented sensitivity and spectral resolution. Quadrupolar isotopes such as <sup>17</sup>O that have been nearly unobservable by lower field NMR will yield unique chemical, structural and dynamic insights into novel materials and biological macromolecules. Access to a range of high fields will enable studies of field dependence and allow probe development in advance of the next generations of superconducting magnets. Our team worked collaboratively with commercial console vendor Bruker Biospin to develop an instrument having unique capabilities that will be accessible to students and visiting scientists, and that will allow investigators to focus on their science rather than on the magnet. The spectrometer will be made available to the scientific community with the administrative, technical and scientific support of the NHMFL DC and NMR user programs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2017<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;W&nbsp;Brey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has supported the development of a state-of-the-art NMR spectrometer to operate at 1H frequencies from 1000 to 1500 MHz to be used in conjunction with the 36 Tesla Series Connected Hybrid (SCH) magnet that is fully funded (DMR-0603042) and under construction at the NHMFL. This spectrometer?s unique mission will be to perform potentially transformative science in an unexplored magnetic field range for a broad range of applications, from biological macromolecules to synthetic catalysts, and from battery materials to biological tissues. With today?s commercially available superconducting magnets, these studies are limited to a 1H frequency of &le;1000 MHz (23.4 Tesla). The practical limit to these magnets based on metallic superconductors is at best about 25 T. Further increases in field strength are not expected until high temperature superconductor based magnets become available. The SCH represents an increase in field strength of more than 50%, equivalent to more than a two decade advance in superconductive magnet technology for arguably the most important tool in chemistry and biochemistry. This development will make many nuclei available for investigations with unprecedented sensitivity and spectral resolution. Quadrupolar isotopes such as 17O that have been nearly unobservable by lower field NMR will yield unique chemical, structural and dynamic insights into novel materials and biological macromolecules. Access to a range of high fields will enable studies of field dependence and allow probe development in advance of the next generations of superconducting magnets. Our team worked collaboratively with commercial console vendor Bruker Biospin to develop an instrument having unique capabilities that will be accessible to students and visiting scientists, and that will allow investigators to focus on their science rather than on the magnet. The spectrometer will be made available to the scientific community with the administrative, technical and scientific support of the NHMFL DC and NMR user programs.       Last Modified: 01/10/2017       Submitted by: William W Brey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
