<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: WSC-Category 3- Toward Sustainability of the High Plains Aquifer Region: Coupled Landscape, Atmosphere, and Socioeconomic Systems (CLASS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1224356.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1368128</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collaborative Research: WSC-Category 3 - Toward Sustainability of the High Plains Aquifer Region: Coupled Landscape, Atmosphere, and Socioeconomic Systems (CLASS)&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt; The High Plains region hosts some of the most productive irrigated agricultural land in the United States due to the vast Ogallala-High Plains aquifer (HPA) complex, but much of this system is on a fundamentally unsustainable path due to extensive groundwater withdrawals since the 1930s. The future of this region will be dictated by a range of state and local laws and regulations, complex economic drivers, variable soil productivity and saturated thicknesses, and a changing climate that is forecast to increase the severity of existing regional precipitation and evapotranspiration gradients. This interdisciplinary project examines the coupled landscape, atmospheric and socioeconomic systems (CLASS) associated with the HPA through linking process-based climate, hydrology, dynamic vegetation, and econometrics models. Exploiting data from decades of intense study of the region, the investigators are applying the CLASS modeling suite to better understand historical changes, system interactions, and the feedbacks among climate, hydrology, and agroecosystems. With insights from this historical context, the impacts of a range of possible future social, economic, climate, agroengineering, and land-management conditions on the sustainability of the region's hydrology and economy can be quantified. Diurnal processes are simulated over seasonal to century timescales to investigate the likely impacts of both short-term perturbations and long-term trends. &lt;br/&gt; This project broadly integrates across engineering and the physical, biological, and social sciences. It provides a newly-coupled set of physical process models that will together simulate the terrestrial and atmospheric hydrologic cycles. These physical models are coupled to a biological systems model describing the dynamic growth of both natural and managed agricultural vegetation, and how those biological systems respond to climatic or hydrologic variability. Models that simulate agroengineering decisions about irrigation, management practices, and crop rotations in response to social and economic drivers are then used to both drive the biophysical models and incorporate feedbacks among the systems.&lt;br/&gt; The research provides a powerful modeling system that can inform better management of regional water usage, yields, nutrients applications, and soil carbon sequestration, and offer transformative insights into the sustainability of one of the world's most important agricultural regions. The linked models also allow for better understanding and quantification of interactions among landscape, atmospheric, agroengineering, and socioeconomic systems over the HPA that will be relevant to irrigated agricultural systems worldwide. High resolution simulations will provide policy makers and managers with local information within a regional context. Results of the project will also help raise public awareness of critical links between climate change and biophysical, agroengineering, and socioeconomic systems. Summarized results will be presented to policy makers, planners, and the public via interactive web sites to inform policies that can improve the sustainability of the HPA and other aquifer systems. Students working on the project team will be embedded in science at the interface among multiple disciplines, providing them with both in-depth knowledge within their fields and an ability to work in broad interdisciplinary physical and social science teams. The models and linkages used here can be applied to agricultural systems worldwide and will be made freely available to the research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1039180</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Hyndman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Hyndman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hyndman@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173534442</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000411413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jinhua</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jinhua Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jzhao@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173539935</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489773</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan J Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>moorena@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5178840546</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000348115</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Kendall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony D Kendall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kendal30@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5176481511</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519194</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Gasteyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen P Gasteyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gasteyer@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173555040</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000561186</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7977</Code>
<Text>CR-Water Sustainability &amp; Clim</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8026</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Energy Pathways</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004Z</Code>
<Text>Innovations at the Nexus of Food-Energy-</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1224356</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~143772</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-d5c8a22c-37b8-f6bb-5f77-121bfe41f81d"> </span></p> <p>The High Plains Aquifer (HPA) hosts some of the most productive irrigated agricultural land in the United States, but much of this system is on a fundamentally unsustainable path due to extensive groundwater withdrawals since the 1930s. The future of this region will be dictated by the characteristics of the aquifer, climate conditions, economic drivers, policies, and resultant land uses and groundwater management practices. This project investigated the Coupled Landscape, Atmospheric, and Socioeconomic Systems (CLASS) associated with the HPA by linking climate, hydrology, vegetation, and economics models to examine historical changes and develop fundamental insights into system interactions and feedbacks.</p> <p>* <span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Drawdown of the HPA began earlier and is significantly greater than previously calculated. During recent droughts, these declines accelerated by a factor of four. There is a strong need for improved water management to preserve the useful life of the aquifer<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span><br />Although irrigation is the largest consumptive use of groundwater, it is often ignored or oversimplified in large scale studies of hydrology and land surface/climate interactions. Incorporating realistic and dynamic models of irrigation, driven by readily-available data, improves: a) commonly used satellite-based groundwater storage change estimates; b) regional climate models; and c) integrated surface water/groundwater models.</p> <p>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Crop yields have dramatically increased in the HPA over the last 40 years, and irrigated fields typically yield more than twice their rainfed counterparts. This yield incentive, along with increases in commodity prices, have driven irrigation expansion across the HPA. Satellite data, processed using modern cloud computing systems, can accurately reveal annual patterns in irrigation, enhancing data about this largely under-reported water use.</p> <p>* &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Newer, more efficient irrigation systems dramatically reduce water loss to wind-drift evaporation, which allow pumping from lower-yielding aquifer areas. As result of this and other factors, per-acre use of water is declining. However, farmer adoption of these technologies leads to a rebound effect, in which aquifer-wide water use increases.</p> <p>* &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Depletion of the HPA is ongoing, and accelerating. Projected declines in water levels affect nearly all of the Central and Southern HPA by the end of the century, and will likely lead to significant reductions in regional production of wheat and corn.</p> <p>* &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Analysis of water-level change versus water use led to development of a simple water-balance approach for assessing the sustainability of heavily-pumped regions of the HPA, which is now being used to improve policies.</p> <p>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The data, results, and findings of the project have been communicated to a wide range of scientific, agency, stakeholder, and public audiences through presentations, interviews, journal papers, a special conference session on the HPA, news publications, and computer media.</p> <p>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Improved modeling tools of landscape hydrology demonstrate that the bulk of annual groundwater recharge in the drier portions of the HPA come from localized playa lake sources. Yet managing the land use of the fields between the playas strongly affects their behavior. An important land use in the region, grassland management under the Conservation Reserve Program, leads to decreased groundwater recharge compared to dryland farming.</p> <p>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Projected changes in climate are likely to cause significant declines for both irrigated and rainfed corn yields. However, adaptation strategies can offset much of these yield declines.</p> <p>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Irrigation over large regions significantly impacts both local and downwind climate, particularly in dry years. The expected effects of surface cooling and enhanced atmospheric moisture are amplified by changes in regional atmospheric circulation that impact much of the Continental US.</p> <p>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Modeling tools, analytical methods, and data processing algorithms developed for this project in this relatively data-rich region are already beginning to be applied elsewhere across the US and globally, revealing in greater detail the physical mechanisms and socioeconomic interactions that control similar Coupled Landscape Atmospheric and Socioeconomic Systems.</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/17/2017<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;W&nbsp;Hyndman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The High Plains Aquifer (HPA) hosts some of the most productive irrigated agricultural land in the United States, but much of this system is on a fundamentally unsustainable path due to extensive groundwater withdrawals since the 1930s. The future of this region will be dictated by the characteristics of the aquifer, climate conditions, economic drivers, policies, and resultant land uses and groundwater management practices. This project investigated the Coupled Landscape, Atmospheric, and Socioeconomic Systems (CLASS) associated with the HPA by linking climate, hydrology, vegetation, and economics models to examine historical changes and develop fundamental insights into system interactions and feedbacks.  *  Drawdown of the HPA began earlier and is significantly greater than previously calculated. During recent droughts, these declines accelerated by a factor of four. There is a strong need for improved water management to preserve the useful life of the aquifer  Although irrigation is the largest consumptive use of groundwater, it is often ignored or oversimplified in large scale studies of hydrology and land surface/climate interactions. Incorporating realistic and dynamic models of irrigation, driven by readily-available data, improves: a) commonly used satellite-based groundwater storage change estimates; b) regional climate models; and c) integrated surface water/groundwater models.  *      Crop yields have dramatically increased in the HPA over the last 40 years, and irrigated fields typically yield more than twice their rainfed counterparts. This yield incentive, along with increases in commodity prices, have driven irrigation expansion across the HPA. Satellite data, processed using modern cloud computing systems, can accurately reveal annual patterns in irrigation, enhancing data about this largely under-reported water use.  *      Newer, more efficient irrigation systems dramatically reduce water loss to wind-drift evaporation, which allow pumping from lower-yielding aquifer areas. As result of this and other factors, per-acre use of water is declining. However, farmer adoption of these technologies leads to a rebound effect, in which aquifer-wide water use increases.  *      Depletion of the HPA is ongoing, and accelerating. Projected declines in water levels affect nearly all of the Central and Southern HPA by the end of the century, and will likely lead to significant reductions in regional production of wheat and corn.  *      Analysis of water-level change versus water use led to development of a simple water-balance approach for assessing the sustainability of heavily-pumped regions of the HPA, which is now being used to improve policies.  *      The data, results, and findings of the project have been communicated to a wide range of scientific, agency, stakeholder, and public audiences through presentations, interviews, journal papers, a special conference session on the HPA, news publications, and computer media.  *      Improved modeling tools of landscape hydrology demonstrate that the bulk of annual groundwater recharge in the drier portions of the HPA come from localized playa lake sources. Yet managing the land use of the fields between the playas strongly affects their behavior. An important land use in the region, grassland management under the Conservation Reserve Program, leads to decreased groundwater recharge compared to dryland farming.  *      Projected changes in climate are likely to cause significant declines for both irrigated and rainfed corn yields. However, adaptation strategies can offset much of these yield declines.  *      Irrigation over large regions significantly impacts both local and downwind climate, particularly in dry years. The expected effects of surface cooling and enhanced atmospheric moisture are amplified by changes in regional atmospheric circulation that impact much of the Continental US.  *      Modeling tools, analytical methods, and data processing algorithms developed for this project in this relatively data-rich region are already beginning to be applied elsewhere across the US and globally, revealing in greater detail the physical mechanisms and socioeconomic interactions that control similar Coupled Landscape Atmospheric and Socioeconomic Systems.         Last Modified: 07/17/2017       Submitted by: David W Hyndman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
