<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chandrasekhar Centennial Symposium; Chicago, IL; October 16-17, 2010</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports travel to a scientific symposium to be held October 16 - 17, 2010 at the University of Chicago in honor of the 100th anniversary of the birth of Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar. A Nobel Prize winner, Chandrasekhar is best known for his earliest work showing  that white dwarf stars cannot have a mass greater than the "Chandrasekhar limit," a result that plays a central role in current understanding of stellar evolution, supernovae, and gravitational  collapse.  After completing this work, Chandrasekhar went on, successively, to the analysis of stellar structure, stellar dynamics, radiative transfer, plasma physics, hydrodynamics and magnetohydrodynamics, and equilibrium solutions for rotating bodies in Newtonian gravity.  He  then devoted most of the last thirty-five years of his life to research in general relativity,  where he made major contributions to post-Newtonian analysis, the theory of black holes, and many  other areas. The symposium will bring together internationally leading physicists and astrophysicists to put his work in perspective and elucidate many of the ramifications of his work in current research.  The symposium should provide an excellent introduction to some key areas of research in general relativity and astrophysics for students and postdocs who participate. It may be a sufficiently "high profile" event to attract attention in the local, national, and international media, leading to greater interest by the broader public in the work of Chandrasekhar.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1039863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Wald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert M Wald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rmwa@midway.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737027765</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160039</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6054 South Drexel Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1244</Code>
<Text>Gravity Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">S. Chandrasekhar was one of the most distinguished physicists/astrophysicists of the 20th century. He  is probably best known for his earliest work showing that white dwarf stars cannot have a mass greater than the &ldquo;Chandrasekhar limit&rdquo; (approximately 1.4 solar masses), which plays a central role in our current understanding of stellar evolution, supernovae, and gravitational collapse. Chandrasekhar then went on to make major contributions to the theory of  stellar structure, stellar dynamics, radiative transfer, plasma physics, hydrodynamics and magnetohydrodynamics, and equilibrium solutions for rotating bodies in Newtonian gravity. He then devoted most of the last thirty-five years of his life to research in general relativity, where he made major contributions to the theory of black holes. Chandrasekhar also had a great personal impact on many researchers in the example he set of never resting on his laurels, always maintaining the highest standards of scholarship, and always having his research be motivated by deep scientific interest rather than popular fads</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   P { margin-bottom: 0.08in } --> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">October, 19, 2010 was the 100th anniversary of his birth, and we held a two-day Symposium to mark this occassion on the campus of the University of Chicago. The main purpose of the Symposium was to bring together leading researchers in broad areas of general relativity and astrophysics to talk about key issues in current research. The speakers included Freeman Dyson, Roger Penrose, Martin Rees, and Kip Thorne. The Symposium was broader in scope than most specialized meetings, we  believe that it provided a good opportunity for cross-fertilization and collaboration. We also believe that it also provided an excellent opportunity for graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty to get an introduction to current research on a broad range of topics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2011<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;M&nbsp;Wald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  S. Chandrasekhar was one of the most distinguished physicists/astrophysicists of the 20th century. He  is probably best known for his earliest work showing that white dwarf stars cannot have a mass greater than the "Chandrasekhar limit" (approximately 1.4 solar masses), which plays a central role in our current understanding of stellar evolution, supernovae, and gravitational collapse. Chandrasekhar then went on to make major contributions to the theory of  stellar structure, stellar dynamics, radiative transfer, plasma physics, hydrodynamics and magnetohydrodynamics, and equilibrium solutions for rotating bodies in Newtonian gravity. He then devoted most of the last thirty-five years of his life to research in general relativity, where he made major contributions to the theory of black holes. Chandrasekhar also had a great personal impact on many researchers in the example he set of never resting on his laurels, always maintaining the highest standards of scholarship, and always having his research be motivated by deep scientific interest rather than popular fads       October, 19, 2010 was the 100th anniversary of his birth, and we held a two-day Symposium to mark this occassion on the campus of the University of Chicago. The main purpose of the Symposium was to bring together leading researchers in broad areas of general relativity and astrophysics to talk about key issues in current research. The speakers included Freeman Dyson, Roger Penrose, Martin Rees, and Kip Thorne. The Symposium was broader in scope than most specialized meetings, we  believe that it provided a good opportunity for cross-fertilization and collaboration. We also believe that it also provided an excellent opportunity for graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty to get an introduction to current research on a broad range of topics.       Last Modified: 09/09/2011       Submitted by: Robert M Wald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
