<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a High-Resolution Positron Imaging System Dedicated to Plant Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1043197.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1043197</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation award funds the development of a novel positron emission tomography (PET) system for plant imaging using an innovative virtual pinhole detector geometry. The new PET system will provide sub-millimeter resolution PET imaging capability.  The system will be fully integrated into a plant growth chamber that is fitted with lighting, temperature, humidity and CO2 control so that the plant can be studied in a well controlled environment (including elevated CO2 concentrations).&lt;br/&gt;Radioactive gas delivery system and labeling apparatus will also be developed and integrated into the growth chamber to enable plant imaging using PET tracers under a controlled environment.  The system will enable several in planta molecular imaging research projects that may (1) understand how crop yields will be affected at elevated atmospheric CO2 level; (2) improve the yield and extend the shelf life of cassava to aid food shortage problem in Africa; (3) accelerate the selection of genetically modified crops by accurately predicting the yield without full scale field experiment; (4) better understand the effect of plant hormone for growth control and defending diseases.  The results of the research and development efforts will be broadly disseminated through abstracts and peer reviewed publications, as well as by active participation of students and faculty at professional meetings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1040498</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuan-Chuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Tai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuan-Chuan Tai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>taiy@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3147474134</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000523594</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[CAMPUS BOX 1054]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9184</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1043197</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Positron emission tomography (PET) scanner is a special kind of camera that can look into a living subject and provide three-dimensional images. It requires the use of specially labeled dyes to be injected or administered into an object. These special dyes will circulate in the object and may come out in different ways, depending on the type of dyes used and the functions that these dyes are designed to reveal. The most common clinical application of PET is to detect cancers and to reveal how extensive the cancer has spread out in the patient body. PET is also used to study new drugs in small animals in order to understand how these drugs might distribute and interact in the body. Although PET is now used widely in clinical diagnosis and pharmaceutical research using animals, it is rarely used to study plants. Part of the reason is the availability of the scanners that are specifically designed to accommodate plants of a wide range of shapes and sizes. Part of the reason is the availability of a cyclotron to produce radionuclides that are needed to produce the specially labeled dyes.</p> <p>In this NSF sponsored project, we developed a special PET scanner that can accommodate plants of different shapes and sizes to produce high-resolution PET images. The scanner is installed in the Washington University School of Medicine where there are 4 medical cyclotrons to produce a wide range of radionuclides to make the special dyes needed for PET imaging. One good example is C-11-labeled carbon dioxide that can be incorporated into plants by photosynthesis. Using this PET scanner, we can measure how carbon is absorbed, transported, and consumed in plants. We can also use N-13 labeled nitrite or nitrogen gas to study nitrogen utilization in plants. There are just some of the easiest-to-make dyes that are also extremely useful to study plants.</p> <p>This unique scanner, plus a wealth of resources at Washington University and Donald Danforth Plant Sciences Center, allows us to explore some of the most pressing challenges that we face. For example, how do plants utilize carbon and cope with global warming when the atmospheric carbon dioxide level continues to rise? How do we increase food and energy crop production in order to sustain the growing population and energy consumption on the earth?&nbsp; These challenges cannot be resolved without advanced plant sciences. What we can offer is another powerful research tool that can help to understand the most complicated biological processes that change dynamically and requires measurement in real-time.</p> <p>In short, the investment from NSF to establish this major research instrumentation has enabled the research community to study molecular processes in plants in real-time. New research collaborations have been stimulated among several universities and research centers. We anticipate exciting results will start to be revealed in the next few years.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Yuan-Chuan&nbsp;Tai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1040498/1040498_10030944_1432946541001_P4290573--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1040498/1040498_10030944_1432946541001_P4290573--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PlantPET"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1040498/1040498_10030944_1432946541001_P4290573--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PlantPET"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A maize plant being imaged ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Positron emission tomography (PET) scanner is a special kind of camera that can look into a living subject and provide three-dimensional images. It requires the use of specially labeled dyes to be injected or administered into an object. These special dyes will circulate in the object and may come out in different ways, depending on the type of dyes used and the functions that these dyes are designed to reveal. The most common clinical application of PET is to detect cancers and to reveal how extensive the cancer has spread out in the patient body. PET is also used to study new drugs in small animals in order to understand how these drugs might distribute and interact in the body. Although PET is now used widely in clinical diagnosis and pharmaceutical research using animals, it is rarely used to study plants. Part of the reason is the availability of the scanners that are specifically designed to accommodate plants of a wide range of shapes and sizes. Part of the reason is the availability of a cyclotron to produce radionuclides that are needed to produce the specially labeled dyes.  In this NSF sponsored project, we developed a special PET scanner that can accommodate plants of different shapes and sizes to produce high-resolution PET images. The scanner is installed in the Washington University School of Medicine where there are 4 medical cyclotrons to produce a wide range of radionuclides to make the special dyes needed for PET imaging. One good example is C-11-labeled carbon dioxide that can be incorporated into plants by photosynthesis. Using this PET scanner, we can measure how carbon is absorbed, transported, and consumed in plants. We can also use N-13 labeled nitrite or nitrogen gas to study nitrogen utilization in plants. There are just some of the easiest-to-make dyes that are also extremely useful to study plants.  This unique scanner, plus a wealth of resources at Washington University and Donald Danforth Plant Sciences Center, allows us to explore some of the most pressing challenges that we face. For example, how do plants utilize carbon and cope with global warming when the atmospheric carbon dioxide level continues to rise? How do we increase food and energy crop production in order to sustain the growing population and energy consumption on the earth?  These challenges cannot be resolved without advanced plant sciences. What we can offer is another powerful research tool that can help to understand the most complicated biological processes that change dynamically and requires measurement in real-time.  In short, the investment from NSF to establish this major research instrumentation has enabled the research community to study molecular processes in plants in real-time. New research collaborations have been stimulated among several universities and research centers. We anticipate exciting results will start to be revealed in the next few years.          Last Modified: 05/29/2015       Submitted by: Yuan-Chuan Tai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
