<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FIA: Collaborative Research: A Content and Service Friendly Architecture with Intrinsic Security and Explicit Trust</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6075001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6123001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darleen Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Today's Internet is under enormous pressure: there is a growing diversity of use models, an urgent need for trustworthy communication, and a growing set of stakeholders who must coordinate to provide Internet services.&lt;br/&gt;The project is developing the eXpressive Internet Architecture (XIA), a potential new network architecture that is built around several key principles. First, XIA represents a single network that offers inherent support for communication between diverse principals including hosts, content, services, and unknown future entities. For each type of principal, XIA defines a narrow waist that dictates the API for communication and the network communication mechanisms.  Second, XIA rests upon a foundation of intrinsic security in which the integrity and authenticity of communication is guaranteed using XIA's various self-certifying identifiers.  Third, XIA enables flexible context-dependent mechanisms for establishing trust between the communicating principals, bridging the gap between human and intrinsically secure identifiers. Finally, recognizing the Internet's central role in our society, economic, policy, and usability considerations play a major role in XIA's design.  The project includes user experiments to evaluate and refine the interface between the network and users, and studies that analyze the relationship between technical design decisions, and economic incentives and public policy.&lt;br/&gt;The outcome of the project will be knowledge about a potential future network architecture that is inherently trustworthy, supports long-term evolution of network use models and network technology, and provides explicit interfaces for interaction between network actors.  The architecture will also enable greater visibility and control for various stakeholders, including users, ISPs, and content owners.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1040801</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Peha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon M Peha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peha@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122687126</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000432516</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Steenkiste</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter A Steenkiste</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>prs@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122683261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000456370</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hui</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hui Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hzhang@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122688945</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165147</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Perrig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian Perrig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>perrig@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122682242</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225148</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Andersen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David G Andersen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dga@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122683064</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~3835185</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~2271816</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Internet has been widely successful and has become an integral part of our society.&nbsp; It is also facing a growing number of significant challenges, such as the security of both endpoints and the network infrastructure, user privacy, and the need to support increasingly diverse services and applications.&nbsp; These challenges are in part the result of a mismatch between the architecture of the Internet, which was developed 40 years ago to support a relatively small community of knowledgeable users running a small number of simple applications, and reality of today&rsquo;s internet, which is ubiquitous and plays a critical role in almost every aspect of our society.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has developed the eXpressive Internet Architecture (XIA), a new network architecture that is built around three key principles. First, XIA represents a single network that offers inherent support for communication between multiple types of endpoints, including hosts, content, services, and unknown future entities. For each type of endpoint, XIA defines the interface for communication and the network communication mechanisms.&nbsp; Second, XIA rests upon a foundation of intrinsic security in which the integrity and authenticity of communication is guaranteed using XIA's various self-certifying identifiers.&nbsp; Third, XIA enables flexible context-dependent mechanisms for establishing trust between the communicating principals, bridging the gap between human and intrinsically secure identifiers. Finally, recognizing the Internet's central role in our society, economic, policy, and usability considerations have played a major role in XIA.&nbsp; The project has for example conducted user experiments to evaluate and refine the interface between the network and users, and has analyzed the relationship between technical design decisions, and economic incentives and public policy.</p> <p>We have evaluated the XIA architecture by using its features to help address a number of network challenges, such as network mobility, incremental deployment of network features and architectures, and content and service network support.&nbsp; The project has also implemented a complete XIA protocol stack that enables the deployment of entire XIA networks can be used by applications.&nbsp; Such XIA deployments have played an important role in evaluating our research results and in assessing the viability of the XIA architecture as the basis operational network.</p> <p>The project has had significant broader impact.&nbsp; The project has high visibility in the networking research community and industry, and its research results are having an impact, both by helping establish an active future internet architecture research community, and by contributing specific concepts that have shown to improve network evolvability, customizability, and security.&nbsp; &nbsp;The project has also trained a large number undergraduate, MS, and PhD students and postdocs in the context of a unique project, that is not only interdisciplinary, but also focusses on ``big systems&rsquo;&rsquo; research and is very forward looking.&nbsp; Our broader impact also includes the development of a high-school curriculum in networking, outreach to policy makers in Washington on future internet issues.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2015<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;A&nbsp;Steenkiste</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Internet has been widely successful and has become an integral part of our society.  It is also facing a growing number of significant challenges, such as the security of both endpoints and the network infrastructure, user privacy, and the need to support increasingly diverse services and applications.  These challenges are in part the result of a mismatch between the architecture of the Internet, which was developed 40 years ago to support a relatively small community of knowledgeable users running a small number of simple applications, and reality of todayÆs internet, which is ubiquitous and plays a critical role in almost every aspect of our society.   The project has developed the eXpressive Internet Architecture (XIA), a new network architecture that is built around three key principles. First, XIA represents a single network that offers inherent support for communication between multiple types of endpoints, including hosts, content, services, and unknown future entities. For each type of endpoint, XIA defines the interface for communication and the network communication mechanisms.  Second, XIA rests upon a foundation of intrinsic security in which the integrity and authenticity of communication is guaranteed using XIA's various self-certifying identifiers.  Third, XIA enables flexible context-dependent mechanisms for establishing trust between the communicating principals, bridging the gap between human and intrinsically secure identifiers. Finally, recognizing the Internet's central role in our society, economic, policy, and usability considerations have played a major role in XIA.  The project has for example conducted user experiments to evaluate and refine the interface between the network and users, and has analyzed the relationship between technical design decisions, and economic incentives and public policy.  We have evaluated the XIA architecture by using its features to help address a number of network challenges, such as network mobility, incremental deployment of network features and architectures, and content and service network support.  The project has also implemented a complete XIA protocol stack that enables the deployment of entire XIA networks can be used by applications.  Such XIA deployments have played an important role in evaluating our research results and in assessing the viability of the XIA architecture as the basis operational network.  The project has had significant broader impact.  The project has high visibility in the networking research community and industry, and its research results are having an impact, both by helping establish an active future internet architecture research community, and by contributing specific concepts that have shown to improve network evolvability, customizability, and security.   The project has also trained a large number undergraduate, MS, and PhD students and postdocs in the context of a unique project, that is not only interdisciplinary, but also focusses on ``big systemsÆÆ research and is very forward looking.  Our broader impact also includes the development of a high-school curriculum in networking, outreach to policy makers in Washington on future internet issues.          Last Modified: 06/04/2015       Submitted by: Peter A Steenkiste]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
