<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spatial Intelligence and Learning Center (SILC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18306816</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Spatial Intelligence and Learning Center (SILC) was established in the fall of 2006 as one of three second-cohort Science of Learning Centers. SILC's purpose is to develop the new science of spatial learning and to use this knowledge to transform STEM educational practice. Spatial learning is the acquisition of spatial knowledge and skills, and the use of spatial knowledge and skills to facilitate learning in both spatial and non-spatial domains. It provides the foundation for a wide range of reasoning skills in STEM-based activities, from solving mathematical problems to engineering new products to understanding graphical depictions of complex systems. Previous research shows that spatial skills are a strong predictor of entry into STEM disciplines in college and into STEM careers, that substantial improvement of spatial learning is possible, and that this improvement matters to STEM success. SILC has brought together researchers from multiple lines of work on spatial cognition and education and from a variety of traditional disciplines (e. g., cognitive science, psychology, artificial intelligence, linguistics, education, STEM disciplines), integrating them to achieve new insights. SILC researchers are developing a set of powerful tools for spatial learning, honing them into effective, deployable educational techniques and practices for STEM learning, including advanced technology (e.g., intelligent educational software), effective curriculum units (e.g., in elementary school mathematics), engaging activities (e.g., in children's museums), and spatial assessment instruments (e.g., testing children's spatial skills, testing adults' STEM-relevant spatial skills). Several of the insights, tools and products from SILC's initial funding period already hold transformational potential for spatial learning. Research and translational activities in the second and last funding period, from 2011-2016, will continue the investment in the science of spatial learning, in order to allow the fulfillment of this promise.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1041707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldin-Meadow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan J Goldin-Meadow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sgm@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737022585</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000198358</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nora</FirstName>
<LastName>Newcombe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nora S Newcombe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>newcombe@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152046944</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000285523</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Levine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan C Levine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>s-levine@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737028844</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000117787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dedre</FirstName>
<LastName>Gentner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dedre Gentner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gentner@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474672035</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000426434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
<LastName>Hedges</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Larry V Hedges</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>l-hedges@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474918899</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000514339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1801 N. Broad Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7278</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF LEARN CTRS- CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8077</Code>
<Text>Science Across Virtual Instits</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5912</Code>
<Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5948</Code>
<Text>NETHERLANDS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7278</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF LEARN CTRS- CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8058</Code>
<Text>Science Across Virtual Instits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~3556816</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~3500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~3250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Spatial Intelligence and Learning Center (SILC), founded in 2006, united scientists, graduate students and post-doctoral fellows from Temple University, the University of Chicago, Northwestern University, the University of Pennsylvania and the Science Education Resource Center (SERC) at Carleton College, as well as individual researchers at other universities. SILC completed its 10-year funding cycle, plus an additional two no-cost extension years, in September of 2018. Nora S. Newcombe (Temple University) served as SILC's PI, along with co-PIs Susan C. Levine and Susan Goldin-Meadow (University of Chicago) and Dedre Gentner and Larry V. Hedges (Northwestern University).</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p>Many anecdotes have suggested that spatial thinking is at the heart of mathematical and scientific discovery, e.g., Francis Crick and James Watson envisioning the three-dimensional structure of DNA with the help of Rosalind Franklin's flat x-ray diffraction images, and John Snow's use of a map in his investigation of London's 19th century cholera epidemic. However, when SILC began in 2006, there was only scanty evidence to support the connection, and most of it was simply concurrent correlations, whose causal interpretation was unclear. In addition, in 2006, the National Academy report <em>Learning to Think Spatially</em> expressed skepticism that training would lead to durable improvements in spatial thinking that showed transfer to non-trained areas. SILC and SILC-inspired research transformed our understanding of spatial-STEM connections in the subsequent decade.</p> <ul> <li>First, we now know that there are longitudinal correlations between spatial and STEM skills and outcomes, using appropriate statistical controls, at a wide range of ages, strengthening the case for a causal arrow from spatial thinking to STEM Learning. </li> <li>Second, we discovered that training can lead to durable and transferable improvements in spatial thinking (Uttal, Meadow, Tipton, Hand, Alden, Warren &amp; Newcombe, 2013). </li> <li>Third, we began randomized control treatment studies of spatial training with the dependent variables tapping STEM learning, and inspired other investigators to join the enterprise, which is continuing. Evidence to date is encouraging (Newcombe, 2017). </li> <li>Fourth, we investigated cognitive mechanisms of the spatial-STEM linkage. One of SILC's achievements was to involve a broad range of researchers who could explore various learning techniques other than simple practice, including embodied experience, gesture, analogy, spatial language, sketching and effective use of diagrams and graphs. These studies also bridged to other SLCs, telling us about technology-supported learning, learning in informal environments, and learning in children who communicate using sign. </li> </ul> <p>SILC produced 283 peer-reviewed publications, as well as numerous additional conference presentations and talks to policy makers, educators, parents and the public.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></p> <p>SILC trained a next-generation of scientists and educators by working with 96 PhD students and 70 post-doctoral fellows, as well as numerous undergraduates and professional staff, many of whom continued in relevant careers. SILC's students and fellows now work in academia, industry, business, and government. Throughout the duration of SILC, investigators stayed in close contact with educators at levels from PreK to 16, especially in STEM. There are now clear indicators of SILC's impact on STEM education, in the use of its publications in workshops and manuals for STEM educators from PreK to 16. SILC planned or cooperated in conferences in Australia, Brazil, China, Germany and Italy, and established a Spatial Network of researchers across the world. We also sponsored 15 workshops on aspects of our work.</p> <p><span><span><span><span><span><span class="ComponentStyle_SpecialClear"><span><span id="_webr_EntityView"><span class="SF424Workspace_IDCell"><span id="__FundingProposal.ID_container"><span><span><span class="htmlPage"> </span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/05/2019<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;J&nbsp;Goldin-Meadow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Spatial Intelligence and Learning Center (SILC), founded in 2006, united scientists, graduate students and post-doctoral fellows from Temple University, the University of Chicago, Northwestern University, the University of Pennsylvania and the Science Education Resource Center (SERC) at Carleton College, as well as individual researchers at other universities. SILC completed its 10-year funding cycle, plus an additional two no-cost extension years, in September of 2018. Nora S. Newcombe (Temple University) served as SILC's PI, along with co-PIs Susan C. Levine and Susan Goldin-Meadow (University of Chicago) and Dedre Gentner and Larry V. Hedges (Northwestern University).  Intellectual Merit  Many anecdotes have suggested that spatial thinking is at the heart of mathematical and scientific discovery, e.g., Francis Crick and James Watson envisioning the three-dimensional structure of DNA with the help of Rosalind Franklin's flat x-ray diffraction images, and John Snow's use of a map in his investigation of London's 19th century cholera epidemic. However, when SILC began in 2006, there was only scanty evidence to support the connection, and most of it was simply concurrent correlations, whose causal interpretation was unclear. In addition, in 2006, the National Academy report Learning to Think Spatially expressed skepticism that training would lead to durable improvements in spatial thinking that showed transfer to non-trained areas. SILC and SILC-inspired research transformed our understanding of spatial-STEM connections in the subsequent decade.  First, we now know that there are longitudinal correlations between spatial and STEM skills and outcomes, using appropriate statistical controls, at a wide range of ages, strengthening the case for a causal arrow from spatial thinking to STEM Learning.  Second, we discovered that training can lead to durable and transferable improvements in spatial thinking (Uttal, Meadow, Tipton, Hand, Alden, Warren &amp; Newcombe, 2013).  Third, we began randomized control treatment studies of spatial training with the dependent variables tapping STEM learning, and inspired other investigators to join the enterprise, which is continuing. Evidence to date is encouraging (Newcombe, 2017).  Fourth, we investigated cognitive mechanisms of the spatial-STEM linkage. One of SILC's achievements was to involve a broad range of researchers who could explore various learning techniques other than simple practice, including embodied experience, gesture, analogy, spatial language, sketching and effective use of diagrams and graphs. These studies also bridged to other SLCs, telling us about technology-supported learning, learning in informal environments, and learning in children who communicate using sign.    SILC produced 283 peer-reviewed publications, as well as numerous additional conference presentations and talks to policy makers, educators, parents and the public.  Broader Impacts  SILC trained a next-generation of scientists and educators by working with 96 PhD students and 70 post-doctoral fellows, as well as numerous undergraduates and professional staff, many of whom continued in relevant careers. SILC's students and fellows now work in academia, industry, business, and government. Throughout the duration of SILC, investigators stayed in close contact with educators at levels from PreK to 16, especially in STEM. There are now clear indicators of SILC's impact on STEM education, in the use of its publications in workshops and manuals for STEM educators from PreK to 16. SILC planned or cooperated in conferences in Australia, Brazil, China, Germany and Italy, and established a Spatial Network of researchers across the world. We also sponsored 15 workshops on aspects of our work.          Last Modified: 02/05/2019       Submitted by: Susan J Goldin-Meadow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
