<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CI-TEAM Implementation Project:  The Virtual School of Computational Science and Engineering Network, a collaboration cyberinfrastructure for petascale computing education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>874475.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>874475</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sushil K Prasad</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Virtual School of Computational Science and Engineering (VSCSE) is a national-scale computational science and engineering research and education program that trains graduate students and postdoctoral researchers in research techniques for using leading-edge cyberinfrastructure resources. This program has in the past been challenged to keep up with increasing demand and faces an acute need for a collaboration cyberinfrastructure to support its growing portfolio of courses and community of students. In response to this need, the University of Michigan and the University of Illinois is implementing the Virtual School of Computational Science and Engineering Network, a collaboration cyberinfrastructure to provide the VSCSE with research-based socio-technical systems for conducting synchronous and asynchronous learning through integrated research and education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The VSCSE Network consists of a synchronous instruction environment called the Virtual Classroom, a HubZero-based online community and open educational resources repository and a Coordinating Center to provide staff support for network operations and outreach. This project is creating a set of ?Virtual Classrooms in a Box? to facilitate widespread adoption of the cyberinfrastructure.  The VSCSE Network is being  implemented iteratively, organized around annual Summer School courses. Each iteration features work to develop new capabilities to enhance the Network?s ability to support highly distributed, interactive, open and community-driven education, expanding the breadth, depth and openness of the VSCSE. This collaboration cyberinfrastructure facilitates the education and training of an entire generation of computational scientists and engineers able to exploit petascale computational power for scientific discovery and engineering innovation, enabled by 21st century cyberinfrastructure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is extending the reach of the VSCSE by providing sustainable models for petascale training and education among faculty, students, practitioners, and institutions by developing the necessary infrastructure, processes, and mechanisms for current and future generations and by rigorously evaluating and assessing this work. The elements of the infrastructure includes research-proven, pedagogically effective methods for delivering synchronous and asynchronous content to large, geographically-distributed audiences, mechanisms for handling student registrations, pedagogically effective techniques for transforming live content into on-line self-paced tutorials, on-line mentoring networks to support learning during and after scheduled events, searchable peer reviewed repository of petascale training and education materials, and a larger, more diverse human network of experts to engage in future efforts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This proposal is building on the successful foundations established by the VSCSE between 2008 and 2010 to accelerate national adoption of live petascale training to reach graduate and postdoctoral students at multiple sites across the country simultaneously by applying innovative and immersive collaboration technologies. Transforming the materials produced from live events into stand-alone, on-line, learning materials to support self-paced learning requires the creation of new, pedagogically-based techniques for packaging open education resources. The Network is supporting integrated research and education on petascale computing topics that include the hands on use of leading cyberinfrastructure resources, such as TeraGrid and Track 1 Petascale systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: To prepare significantly larger and more diverse generations of scientists, technologists, engineers and mathematicians to advance scientific discovery, the VSCSE Network is connecting students, faculty, and researchers at institutions across the country including top-tier research universities and institutions that serve historically underrepresented individuals. The VSCSE Network will create a rich repository of open educational resources that can be adopted and used in a wide variety of educational settings and will provide a mentorship network for matching new scholars and students with established experts. The VSCSE also plans to work with international organizations to provide additional depth of content in the materials and to advance international research and education collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1041313</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Dunning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas H Dunning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thdjr@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066169976</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000399097</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/25/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Finholt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Finholt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>finholt@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347646131</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Glotzer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon C Glotzer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sglotzer@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346156296</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472028</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Kramer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William T Kramer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wtkramer@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173336260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Hofer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik Hofer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ehofer@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346156502</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000260020</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7477</Code>
<Text>CI-TEAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7477</Code>
<Text>CI-TEAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~874475</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to implement a nation-wide collaboration and education network for developing skills in expertise in computational science and engineering techniques for faculty, students, and practitioners, called the Virtual School of Computational Science and Engineering, or VSCSE for short. The VSCSE successfully organized and delivered 11 Summer School courses on cutting-edge computational science and engineering topics from 2011-2015.</p> <p>These courses were led by leading topic experts from around the country, covering a wide variety of important and emerging topics in the computational sciences, such as scientific visualization, working with large scale supercomputers, approaches to working with &ldquo;big data,&rdquo; and using new forms of computing technologies in scientific computing. These courses were delivered by high-definition video conferencing to host sites across the U.S. to maximize access and to minimize travel expense, with 48 different institutions hosting students and trainees across the life of the project.&nbsp; These courses included both lecture components as well as hands-on exercises, some of which featured major supercomputers at U.S. labs and universities. During the project, 3,883 registrants took advantage of these course offerings.</p> <p>To assist with the delivery of these courses, the VSCSE also provided direct support for a small number of advanced students at each host site to help other trainees through questions and problems.</p> <p>In addition to these Summer School course offerings, the VSCSE produced a number of online webinars that made short seminars on advanced tools and topics available online. These topics ranged from tutorials on advanced computational science tools to discussions about innovations resulting from these techniques.</p> <p>Materials from the different VSCSE programs were published online at the VSCSE website, <a href="http://www.vscse.org">www.vscse.org</a>, so that anyone can take advantage of these materials and the training opportunities.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/25/2016<br>      Modified by: Erik&nbsp;Hofer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to implement a nation-wide collaboration and education network for developing skills in expertise in computational science and engineering techniques for faculty, students, and practitioners, called the Virtual School of Computational Science and Engineering, or VSCSE for short. The VSCSE successfully organized and delivered 11 Summer School courses on cutting-edge computational science and engineering topics from 2011-2015.  These courses were led by leading topic experts from around the country, covering a wide variety of important and emerging topics in the computational sciences, such as scientific visualization, working with large scale supercomputers, approaches to working with "big data," and using new forms of computing technologies in scientific computing. These courses were delivered by high-definition video conferencing to host sites across the U.S. to maximize access and to minimize travel expense, with 48 different institutions hosting students and trainees across the life of the project.  These courses included both lecture components as well as hands-on exercises, some of which featured major supercomputers at U.S. labs and universities. During the project, 3,883 registrants took advantage of these course offerings.  To assist with the delivery of these courses, the VSCSE also provided direct support for a small number of advanced students at each host site to help other trainees through questions and problems.  In addition to these Summer School course offerings, the VSCSE produced a number of online webinars that made short seminars on advanced tools and topics available online. These topics ranged from tutorials on advanced computational science tools to discussions about innovations resulting from these techniques.  Materials from the different VSCSE programs were published online at the VSCSE website, www.vscse.org, so that anyone can take advantage of these materials and the training opportunities.           Last Modified: 03/25/2016       Submitted by: Erik Hofer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
