<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CEDAR: A Novel Atomic Edge Filter Enabling Na Doppler Lidar for Simultaneous Wind and Temperature Measurements from Troposphere to Lower Thermosphere</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>271666.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>271666</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sunanda Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is to develop and deploy new lidar technology that would enable simultaneous observation of wind and temperature in the troposphere, stratosphere, and mesosphere.   Specifically, a sodium double-edge magneto-optical filter will be designed and integrated into the receiver of an existing sodium Doppler lidar.  This effort will extend current narrow-band resonance wind-temperature lidar capabilities, which are based on scattering by atomic constituents in the mesosphere, by accommodating scattering by aerosols and molecules at lower altitudes.  The new measurements of wind and temperature, extending from the ground to 50 km and from 80-105 km, will facilitate improved understanding of the structure and dynamical coupling between the lower and middle atmosphere.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1042257</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xinzhao</FirstName>
<LastName>Chu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xinzhao Chu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xinzhao.chu@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034923280</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000301664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ling</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ling Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lwang@gats-inc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7202744752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000176931</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wentao</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wentao Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wentao@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037351466</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000312231</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1323</Code>
<Text>SOLAR INFLUENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~90242</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~90572</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~90852</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The optical design of the sodium double-edge magneto-optical filter (Na-DEMOF) was substantially revised by Zemax modeling. By properly selecting key optical components and redesigning the layout, the optical throughput of the new Na-DEMOF reached over 95% after the fiber input port, which helped significantly improve the signal level. To address the stability issue, the heating and temperature controlling elements of the new Na-DEMOF were fully redesigned in order to reach 0.1&deg;C temperature stability. The filter functions of the new Na-DEMOF were tested to be fairly stable during a day and between days separated by a week. The signal level achieved using the new Na-DEMOF and the Na Doppler lidar transmitter at Boulder, CO, was improved about 20 times over the signal level reported in our 2009 field campaign at Colorado State University with old prototype. We were able to derive trustable wind and temperature to about 50 km with 0.5 hour temporal and 0.7-1.5 km vertical resolutions for the first time in our tests in 2013 rather than to about 35 km before. Calibration factors in lidar data analysis are derived by validating the vertical wind and temperature to zero mean vertical wind and radiosonde measurements. The calibrations turned out to be much stable over a night than what we found in 2009, which suggested the stability has improved substantially. However, the true origin of the calibration factors is still not very clear and under further investigation. The calibration method of switching the signals between two signal channels by rotating the quarter wave plate, which was explored as a potential calibration method just before this grant and investigated during this grant, turned out to introduce additional uncertainties and need to be further analyzed.</p> <p>The two-direction Na-DEMOF receiver was constructed and characterized. It is fully incorporated into our Na Doppler lidar for sky tests after we fully implemented the horizontal winds measurement capability of the lidar. A new method in aligning and verifying the pointing direction of the Na Doppler lidar was also developed during the process. With two fully functional Na-DEMOFs implemented for zonal and meridional wind measurements, we achieved trustable horizontal wind field and temperature measurements with 0.5 hour temporal and 0.7 km vertical resolutions with stable calibration factors in tests in 2015. However, we suffered from low transmitted lidar power and high background noise during the tests. We unfortunately were not able to identify neither coherent propagating gravity wave structures, nor tidal structures in the lower atmosphere from the wind and temperature fields, which is possibly due to small amplitudes of such perturbations during our tests and the large uncertainties in our data. Our Na Doppler lidar has recently been upgraded with a powerful new pump laser, which will significantly improve the transmitted laser power, thus the signal level for planned future tests. &nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, we have re-designed the optical, heating and electrical components of the Na-DEMOF, successfully constructed, characterized and tested two filters for simultaneously measuring the horizontal winds and temperature in the troposphere and stratosphere. The stability and the optical efficiency of the new receiver are significantly improved over the prototype. New calibration method has been developed, and good measurements have been made in our field tests. Unfortunately, we haven&rsquo;t been able to fully understand the calibration factors required for this technique, and haven&rsquo;t been able to track the gravity wave propagation and study the wave coupling between the stratosphere and mesosphere. We anticipate that better results will be achieved in planned future tests with recently upgraded lidar transmitter. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2015<br>      Mo...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The optical design of the sodium double-edge magneto-optical filter (Na-DEMOF) was substantially revised by Zemax modeling. By properly selecting key optical components and redesigning the layout, the optical throughput of the new Na-DEMOF reached over 95% after the fiber input port, which helped significantly improve the signal level. To address the stability issue, the heating and temperature controlling elements of the new Na-DEMOF were fully redesigned in order to reach 0.1&deg;C temperature stability. The filter functions of the new Na-DEMOF were tested to be fairly stable during a day and between days separated by a week. The signal level achieved using the new Na-DEMOF and the Na Doppler lidar transmitter at Boulder, CO, was improved about 20 times over the signal level reported in our 2009 field campaign at Colorado State University with old prototype. We were able to derive trustable wind and temperature to about 50 km with 0.5 hour temporal and 0.7-1.5 km vertical resolutions for the first time in our tests in 2013 rather than to about 35 km before. Calibration factors in lidar data analysis are derived by validating the vertical wind and temperature to zero mean vertical wind and radiosonde measurements. The calibrations turned out to be much stable over a night than what we found in 2009, which suggested the stability has improved substantially. However, the true origin of the calibration factors is still not very clear and under further investigation. The calibration method of switching the signals between two signal channels by rotating the quarter wave plate, which was explored as a potential calibration method just before this grant and investigated during this grant, turned out to introduce additional uncertainties and need to be further analyzed.  The two-direction Na-DEMOF receiver was constructed and characterized. It is fully incorporated into our Na Doppler lidar for sky tests after we fully implemented the horizontal winds measurement capability of the lidar. A new method in aligning and verifying the pointing direction of the Na Doppler lidar was also developed during the process. With two fully functional Na-DEMOFs implemented for zonal and meridional wind measurements, we achieved trustable horizontal wind field and temperature measurements with 0.5 hour temporal and 0.7 km vertical resolutions with stable calibration factors in tests in 2015. However, we suffered from low transmitted lidar power and high background noise during the tests. We unfortunately were not able to identify neither coherent propagating gravity wave structures, nor tidal structures in the lower atmosphere from the wind and temperature fields, which is possibly due to small amplitudes of such perturbations during our tests and the large uncertainties in our data. Our Na Doppler lidar has recently been upgraded with a powerful new pump laser, which will significantly improve the transmitted laser power, thus the signal level for planned future tests.    Overall, we have re-designed the optical, heating and electrical components of the Na-DEMOF, successfully constructed, characterized and tested two filters for simultaneously measuring the horizontal winds and temperature in the troposphere and stratosphere. The stability and the optical efficiency of the new receiver are significantly improved over the prototype. New calibration method has been developed, and good measurements have been made in our field tests. Unfortunately, we havenÆt been able to fully understand the calibration factors required for this technique, and havenÆt been able to track the gravity wave propagation and study the wave coupling between the stratosphere and mesosphere. We anticipate that better results will be achieved in planned future tests with recently upgraded lidar transmitter.            Last Modified: 12/29/2015       Submitted by: Wentao Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
