<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Instrumentation:  COCONet (Continuously Operating Caribbean GPS Observational Network) An Infrastructure Proposal for a Multi-hazard Tectonic and Weather Observatory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>815728.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>815728</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Russell Kelz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rkelz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924747</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative grant to UNAVCO, Inc., an EAR supported national geodetic support Facility (EAR-0735156), and the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research (UCAR), an AGS supported consortium that manages the National Center for Atmospheric Research Facilities (NCAR), supports a five year planned development of a plate-scale integrated geodetic and atmospheric/regional climate observational system in the pan-Caribbean region.   A goal of the Continuously Operating Caribbean GPS Observational Network (COCONet) is to add 50 new semi-permanently monumented, continuously operating, Global Positioning Satellite (cGPS) stations spanning multiple Caribbean and Caribbean bordering nations. COCONet goals also call for the integration of GPS data from up to 50 existing stations operating in the Caribbean.  The new cGPS stations will, in some cases, be co-located with existing tide gauges, thus supporting studies of sea level change in response to current global warming, and will be mated with surface meteorological observational equipment (Metpacks) to significantly expand spatiotemporal geodetic and atmospheric observational infrastructure in a region of complex tectonics with substantial earthquake, tsunami, volcanic, tropical storm and hurricane, flooding and landslide hazards.  COCONet will provide a backbone fiducial and meteorologic observational network and COCONet data and data products that will be freely available through the UNAVCO archive will be available to serve a broad range of basic tectonic and atmospheric research investigations and enable observations of immediate relevance for advancing understanding, mitigating and perhaps predicting regional geohazards.  Some specific questions that COCONet data could help to address include:  1) How rigid is the Caribbean plate?; 2)  What are the slip rates along active faults that bound the Caribbean plate?; 3)  How is stress released at convergent plate boundaries and how is stress transferred across plate boundaries?; and 4)  How can we better understand and assess hazards in the Caribbean and Central American regions?  Atmospheric questions that could be advanced by proposed GPS meteorological determinations and surface measurements of atmospheric physical properties include: 1)  How sensitive is tropospheric water vapor content to changes in sea surface temperatures?; and  2) How does the distribution of precipitable water vapor across the Caribbean region influence the genesis, intensification and vectoring of tropical storms and hurricanes?    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COCONet data will flow via the EarthScope Plate Boundary Observatory (PBO) data management system and be available via the Web-accessible UNAVCO data archive.  Low-latency data telemetry will be via cellular modem or through VSAT satellite communications to the PBO Network Operations Center in Boulder, Colorado.  These data will be processed into derived geodetic products, including combined GPS station position and velocity estimates, simplified position time series and velocity field estimates in multiple formats, at the existing PBO GPS Analysis Centers at Central Washington University and New Mexico Tech and the Analysis Center Coordinator at MIT.  In addition, UCAR will estimate tropospheric precipitable water vapor (PV) every 30 minutes from observations of GPS radio frequency signal propagation delays along the path length between the satellite transmitter and the receiver coupled with concurrent surface measurement of barometric pressure.  The PV observations will feed into operational numerical weather models run several times per day.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will engage Caribbean researchers, their students and governmental agency representatives with the goal of empowering these nations to utilize COCONet data for both scientific and socioeconomic purposes.  Real-time data from COCONet will be made available to the International GNSS Service (IGS) to help densify GPS observations in a region of the globe with few existing real-time data streams and thereby improve GPS satellite orbit calculations and help to refine the international terrestrial reference frame (ITRF).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1042909</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Braun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Mr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John J Braun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>braunj@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034978018</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 Center Green Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078339587</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078339587</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University Corporation For Atmospheric Res]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3090 Center Green Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6898</Code>
<Text>EAR-Earth Sciences Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~306727</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~164560</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~169240</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~175201</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the COCONet (Continuously Operating Caribbean GPS Observational Network) project was to increase both technical and human scientific capacity in the Caribbean region through the installation and operation of a network of continuously operating Global Positioning System (cGPS) stations for natural hazards research. Data collected from a cGPS station supports an array of earth and atmospheric scientific investigations. The precise positioning estimates provided by these instruments are useful in measuring the movement of the Earth&rsquo;s surface to support tectonic and earthquake hazard research. The data collected from these instruments can also be used to sense the amount of water vapor in the atmosphere above the site. These all-weather observations provide critical observations of Earth&rsquo;s most abundant greenhouse gas which are useful for a range of atmospheric process studies including hurricane research. The core COCONet network of stations that were installed includes 58 new sites, with an additional 60 contributing sites that were enhanced through equipment upgrades or through improvements in infrastructure. These stations are distributed throughout the Caribbean region.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>UCAR/COSMIC activities in support of this project have helped address the technical merit of the proposed work.&nbsp; UCAR played an important role in building COCONet by helping design, install, operate and maintain the GPS receivers in the network, as well as train local scientists how to operate the receivers.&nbsp; UCAR also performed the scientific data processing required to produce estimates of the site position and the total amount of water vapor above the site from more than 500 stations in the North American, Central American, and Caribbean regions. These data, both raw data and higher level products, were made available (via Unidata&rsquo;s Local Data Manager tool and through the Suominet web page, www.suominet.ucar.edu) to researchers, educators, students, and the private sector. An example of COCONet GPS water vapor data (as color-coded numbers) is shown in Figure 1 as Hurricane Isaac passed through the eastern Caribbean Sea in August, 2012. UCAR also conducted impactful scientific investigations with the COCONet water vapor data. One study included a comparison to NOAA&rsquo;s GFS (Global Forecast System) weather model that found the GFS analysis is slightly more moist than the COCONet data in lower water vapor environments, and conversely, is slightly more dry than COCONet data in higher water vapor environments. Research was also conducted by UCAR to determine the best sampling interval of the GPS water vapor products, which determined that a sampling interval of 10 minutes is best to capture significant changes in water vapor in the atmosphere above the site.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>UCAR/COSMIC COCONet activities also helped address the broader societal impacts of the proposed work, in particular building human scientific capacity in the geo and atmospheric sciences in the Caribbean region. In an effort to augment the education and outreach goals of COCONet, UCAR/COSMIC received funding from NSF (solicitation NSF 12&shy;535) to conduct a Pan American Advanced Studies Institute (PASI) on Atmospheric Processes of Latin America and the Caribbean: Observations, Analysis, and Impacts. This two&shy; week course was held at the Almirante Padilla Naval Academy in Cartagena, Colombia from May 27 &ndash; June 7, 2013. Thirty&shy;five participants gathered from twelve countries to listen, interact, and learn about atmospheric processes with nine lecturers from across the Americas. Another significant achievement by UCAR and the COCONet project was the historic installation of a GPS receiver in Cuba. This installation was seven years in the making, is providing valuable scientific data, and may also integrate Cuba more into the international scientific community. Figure 2 shows a photo of US and Cuban collaborators after the successful installation of the GPS site in Camaguey, Cuba.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/11/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Braun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1042909/1042909_10041361_1513015348251_IR_20120825_0515--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1042909/1042909_10041361_1513015348251_IR_20120825_0515--rgov-800width.jpg" title="COCONet PW and Hurricane Isaac (2012)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1042909/1042909_10041361_1513015348251_IR_20120825_0515--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="COCONet PW and Hurricane Isaac (2012)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: COCONet estimated water vapor overlaid upon a GOES-IR image taken on August 25, 2012 at 05:15 UTC. Hurricane Isaac is visible in the Central Caribbean.  The COCONet estimate of water vapor above each GPS site is shown as color-coded numbers (in millimeters).</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Braun (UCAR/COSMIC)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Braun</div> <div class="imageTitle">COCONet PW and Hurricane Isaac (2012)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1042909/1042909_10041361_1513015800065_IMG_9921--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1042909/1042909_10041361_1513015800065_IMG_9921--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GPS Station Installation in Camaguey, Cuba"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1042909/1042909_10041361_1513015800065_IMG_9921--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GPS Station Installation in Camaguey, Cuba"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: A photo of US and Cuban collaborators at the Camaguey Cuba station.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Braun (UCAR/COSMIC)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Braun</div> <div class="imageTitle">GPS Station Installation in Camaguey, Cuba</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the COCONet (Continuously Operating Caribbean GPS Observational Network) project was to increase both technical and human scientific capacity in the Caribbean region through the installation and operation of a network of continuously operating Global Positioning System (cGPS) stations for natural hazards research. Data collected from a cGPS station supports an array of earth and atmospheric scientific investigations. The precise positioning estimates provided by these instruments are useful in measuring the movement of the Earth?s surface to support tectonic and earthquake hazard research. The data collected from these instruments can also be used to sense the amount of water vapor in the atmosphere above the site. These all-weather observations provide critical observations of Earth?s most abundant greenhouse gas which are useful for a range of atmospheric process studies including hurricane research. The core COCONet network of stations that were installed includes 58 new sites, with an additional 60 contributing sites that were enhanced through equipment upgrades or through improvements in infrastructure. These stations are distributed throughout the Caribbean region.     UCAR/COSMIC activities in support of this project have helped address the technical merit of the proposed work.  UCAR played an important role in building COCONet by helping design, install, operate and maintain the GPS receivers in the network, as well as train local scientists how to operate the receivers.  UCAR also performed the scientific data processing required to produce estimates of the site position and the total amount of water vapor above the site from more than 500 stations in the North American, Central American, and Caribbean regions. These data, both raw data and higher level products, were made available (via Unidata?s Local Data Manager tool and through the Suominet web page, www.suominet.ucar.edu) to researchers, educators, students, and the private sector. An example of COCONet GPS water vapor data (as color-coded numbers) is shown in Figure 1 as Hurricane Isaac passed through the eastern Caribbean Sea in August, 2012. UCAR also conducted impactful scientific investigations with the COCONet water vapor data. One study included a comparison to NOAA?s GFS (Global Forecast System) weather model that found the GFS analysis is slightly more moist than the COCONet data in lower water vapor environments, and conversely, is slightly more dry than COCONet data in higher water vapor environments. Research was also conducted by UCAR to determine the best sampling interval of the GPS water vapor products, which determined that a sampling interval of 10 minutes is best to capture significant changes in water vapor in the atmosphere above the site.     UCAR/COSMIC COCONet activities also helped address the broader societal impacts of the proposed work, in particular building human scientific capacity in the geo and atmospheric sciences in the Caribbean region. In an effort to augment the education and outreach goals of COCONet, UCAR/COSMIC received funding from NSF (solicitation NSF 12&shy;535) to conduct a Pan American Advanced Studies Institute (PASI) on Atmospheric Processes of Latin America and the Caribbean: Observations, Analysis, and Impacts. This two&shy; week course was held at the Almirante Padilla Naval Academy in Cartagena, Colombia from May 27 &ndash; June 7, 2013. Thirty&shy;five participants gathered from twelve countries to listen, interact, and learn about atmospheric processes with nine lecturers from across the Americas. Another significant achievement by UCAR and the COCONet project was the historic installation of a GPS receiver in Cuba. This installation was seven years in the making, is providing valuable scientific data, and may also integrate Cuba more into the international scientific community. Figure 2 shows a photo of US and Cuban collaborators after the successful installation of the GPS site in Camaguey, Cuba.          Last Modified: 12/11/2017       Submitted by: John J Braun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
