<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NUE:Nanoengineering Education in an Under-Represented Minority University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199868.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199868</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Nanotechnology Undergraduate Education (NUE) in Engineering program at Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville (TAMUK) entitled "NUE: Nanoengineering Education in an Under-Represented Minority University", under the direction of Dr. Syed I. Omar, aims at developing an undergraduate nanotechnology education program in a minority serving institution that lacks access to some of the cutting-edge resources available at larger universities.  A nanotechnology education program in electrical engineering will be developed which will lay the foundation for a broader multidisciplinary nanotechnology education effort at the University level.  Specifically, 1)Development of a first course in nanoengineering, 2) Development of modules of elements of nanoengineering that will be incorporated into relevant courses, 3) Development of students' skills in nanoengineering design and development work and in research through senior level projects, and 4) development of sutiable metrics, concept inventories, and teaching methodology for an undergraduate nanotechnology course.     &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TAMUK, a Hispanic Serving Institution (HSI), recently ranked by ASEE as ninth in the country in producing Hispanic engineers, provides a unique opportunity to develop such a program. During this two year project it is anticipated that over 20 students from underrepresented groups will be directly affected and many of them may be encouraged to pursue a career in conducting research at the forefront of technology.  TAMUK will also work with other universities in South Texas to encourage development of a similar program and disseminate it to minority serving institutions across the U.S.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1042056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reza</FirstName>
<LastName>Nekovei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reza Nekovei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rnekovei@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3615932635</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amit</FirstName>
<LastName>Verma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amit Verma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amit.verma@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3615934012</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000346947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Stollberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Stollberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dstollbe@kennesaw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4044077384</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000077256</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Syed</FirstName>
<LastName>Omar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Syed I Omar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>siomar@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3615933219</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000529018</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Holton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas L Holton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dholton@floridapoly.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>1386243510</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville</Name>
<CityName>Kingsville</CityName>
<ZipCode>783638202</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3615933344</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Campus Box 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868154089</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY KINGSVILLE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville]]></Name>
<CityName>Kingsville</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>783638202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Campus Box 201]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7219</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY UNDERGRAD EDUCA</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>113E</Code>
<Text>ENG CURRICULUMN DEVELOPMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~199868</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>New NanoElectronics Courses To Train Future Researchers and Developers of Nanoscale Electronic Systems</p> <p>For nearly the last twenty years, nanotechnology has been advertised as the future of the Electronics industry.&nbsp; A sequence of two courses has been developed which can be used to train the manpower needed&nbsp;by this industry to do research and development work, thereby retaining the competitive edge.&nbsp; In addition, a Nanoelectronics Concept Inventory has been developed to assess student learning of fundamental concepts and to enhance pedagogical techniques employed.&nbsp; A literature survey indicated that ours is the first attempt at the development of a Nanoelectronics Concept Inventory.</p> <p>The sequence of the two new NanoElectronics courses has been taught at the Junior/Senior level to Electrical Engineering majors.&nbsp; The first course is modular in structure and incorporates computational nanotechnology and modeling and simulation using High Performance Computing Cluster.&nbsp; After completing the first course, the students were able to do research and development projects in NaoElectronics in the second course.</p> <p>To handle research and development problems in NanoElectronics, it is essential to have a good understanding of the principles of carrier transport at the nanoscale as well as to have&nbsp;the ability to apply them to real-world problems.&nbsp; Modeling and simulation provide tools for both understanding the principles and their application.&nbsp; These tools are all based on computational nanotechnology.</p> <p>Keeping these facts in view, the sequence of two courses was developed.&nbsp; The main objective of the first course is to provide a good understanding of the principles of carrier transport at the nanoscale.&nbsp; Two of the essential components of this course are basic computational nanotechnology and modeling and simulation using High Performance Computing Cluster.&nbsp; The second course is designed to provide experience in the application of principles to the solution of real-world problems.</p> <p>The Nanoelectronics Concept Inventory (NCI) was developed using two major steps: specification of fundamental concepts and development of multiple choice questions related to these concepts.&nbsp; The following three groups of concepts were considered to be fundamental to a nanoelectronics course: computational nanoelectronics concepts, nanoelectronics devices concepts, and nanoelectronics fabrication concepts.&nbsp; NCI has been administered and validated on a small scale.&nbsp; It will be, however, necessary to establish its reliability and validity more rigorously.</p> <p>The details of all the outcomes of the project are available in three peer-reviewed papers published in the proceedings of internationally recognized engineering education conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2015<br>      Modified by: Syed&nbsp;I&nbsp;Omar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ New NanoElectronics Courses To Train Future Researchers and Developers of Nanoscale Electronic Systems  For nearly the last twenty years, nanotechnology has been advertised as the future of the Electronics industry.  A sequence of two courses has been developed which can be used to train the manpower needed by this industry to do research and development work, thereby retaining the competitive edge.  In addition, a Nanoelectronics Concept Inventory has been developed to assess student learning of fundamental concepts and to enhance pedagogical techniques employed.  A literature survey indicated that ours is the first attempt at the development of a Nanoelectronics Concept Inventory.  The sequence of the two new NanoElectronics courses has been taught at the Junior/Senior level to Electrical Engineering majors.  The first course is modular in structure and incorporates computational nanotechnology and modeling and simulation using High Performance Computing Cluster.  After completing the first course, the students were able to do research and development projects in NaoElectronics in the second course.  To handle research and development problems in NanoElectronics, it is essential to have a good understanding of the principles of carrier transport at the nanoscale as well as to have the ability to apply them to real-world problems.  Modeling and simulation provide tools for both understanding the principles and their application.  These tools are all based on computational nanotechnology.  Keeping these facts in view, the sequence of two courses was developed.  The main objective of the first course is to provide a good understanding of the principles of carrier transport at the nanoscale.  Two of the essential components of this course are basic computational nanotechnology and modeling and simulation using High Performance Computing Cluster.  The second course is designed to provide experience in the application of principles to the solution of real-world problems.  The Nanoelectronics Concept Inventory (NCI) was developed using two major steps: specification of fundamental concepts and development of multiple choice questions related to these concepts.  The following three groups of concepts were considered to be fundamental to a nanoelectronics course: computational nanoelectronics concepts, nanoelectronics devices concepts, and nanoelectronics fabrication concepts.  NCI has been administered and validated on a small scale.  It will be, however, necessary to establish its reliability and validity more rigorously.  The details of all the outcomes of the project are available in three peer-reviewed papers published in the proceedings of internationally recognized engineering education conferences.                Last Modified: 09/07/2015       Submitted by: Syed I Omar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
