<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CubeSat: Cubesat investigating Atmospheric Density Response to Extreme driving (CADRE)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>875659.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>838668</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020204</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irfan S. Azeem</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a coordinated science program, whose main instrument is a 3-Unit (3U) CubeSat named Cubesat investigating Atmospheric Density Response to Extreme driving (CADRE). The planned science investigation addresses fundamental issues related to ion-neutral coupling, including neutral wind morphology and dynamics that are key to understanding how the thermosphere reacts to energy input and the role this plays in magnetosphere-ionosphere coupling. This project brings a unique and comprehensive set of new and existing measurements and modeling to bear on this problem. This includes in-situ measurements from the planned CubeSat of density, temperature, composition, neutral winds, and ion flows of the high-latitude thermosphere and top-side ionosphere, respectively. Very little such data currently exist and cannot be provided on large scale from ground-based instrumentation. Significant portions of the satellite design is based on the Radio Aurora eXplorer (RAX), the first of the NSF CubeSats, which was built at the University of Michigan by students and members of this project team. The advanced instrument payload is a new design that has been developed recently through a collaboration between NASA and the Naval Research Laboratory and will be provided to this project through very substantial leveraging of internal efforts at NRL and NASA Goddard Space Flight Center. The project adopts a comprehensive observational approach, incorporating a ground-based component that utilizes incoherent scatter radar data for small-scale investigations, SuperDARN radar and Assimilative Mapping of Ionospheric Electrodynamics (AMIE) patterns of the potential for large-scale context, Fabry Perot Interferometer measurements of the neutral winds and temperatures as well as all sky imagery to determine the auroral precipitation. Further, modeling and measurements from other satellite missions, such as Swarm and AMPERE, will be utilized in the interpretation of the data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is a collaboration between University of Michigan and Naval Research Laboratory. The latter will provide the science payload. CADRE is a student driven program, where undergraduate, Master's and Ph.D. students at UM work collaboratively to design, build, test, launch and operate the CubeSat. A full-time Ph.D. student will be involved in every aspect of the project, from the design, integration and testing to the data analysis. Efforts are also planned to reach out to K-12 schools to include them in many of the activities including a popular high altitude balloon program. The raw and processed data will be disseminated in a variety of formats as well as making software available for visualization of the data and the data will be archived at a national repository. The project will produce a wealth of high resolution, high fidelity measurements of the thermospheric neutral winds, temperature and composition that will constitute a valuable resource for the wider atmospheric and space science research community.  In addition, the results of the project will help improve space weather modeling and forecasting of neutral density distributions in the upper atmosphere, something that is crucial for accurate orbit determination as well as operational tracking of satellites and collision avoidance. The in-situ neutral winds measurements in question are difficult to obtain making this a high-risk effort but one with immensely high potential pay-off in providing a unique observational dataset of fundamental thermosphere parameters and related cutting-edge, potentially transformational scientific findings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1042815</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Ridley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron J Ridley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ridley@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347645727</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330122</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Cutler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James W Cutler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwcutler@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346157238</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000062678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Nicholas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Nicholas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrew.nicholas@nrl.navy.mil</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2027672441</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563820</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>4202</Code>
<Text>Upper Atmospheric Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5750</Code>
<Text>MAGNETOSPHERIC PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Space Weather Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~375533</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~184299</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~278836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The upper atmosphere of the Earth is a region of space that satellites and the international space station orbits through. &nbsp;It is important to understand this part of the atmosphere for the safety of our astronauts and&nbsp;to prevent collisions between objects that could be catastrophic financially. In order to do this, scientists create space weather models, which simulate the environment and its response to heating caused by the northern (and southern) lights (i.e., the aurora).&nbsp; We have built a small satellite called CADRE that will measure things like the temperature and winds in the upper atmosphere, allowing researchers to both better understand how the system behaves and validate models.&nbsp; The satellite is a CubeSat that is 4 inches by 4 inches by 12 inches in size, and is being deployed from the International Space Station the last week of January, 2016. Students at the University of Michigan (UM) built it, while the Naval Research Laboratory built the sensor.&nbsp; Over 50 students, including undergraduate, masters, and Ph.D. students worked on the design, build, integration, and testing of the CubeSat.&nbsp; The CubeSat is technologically much more challenging than any other that UM has built.&nbsp; Many small satellites don&rsquo;t need to know which direction they are pointing, since they have sensors that can take data in any direction (for example, radiation sensors can measure radiation from anywhere).&nbsp; CADRE needs to be pointed in a given direction extremely accurately, which was a huge challenge.&nbsp; Further, CADRE needs more power than any satellite that UM has produced, which meant putting a large number of solar cells on the satellite.&nbsp; This was also quite complicated, since it involved having folding panels, which UM had never done before.&nbsp; The satellite was delivered just after the project officially ended, and was launched into space in December 2015.&nbsp; It will be deployed from the international space station in late January 2016.&nbsp; Data will start being taken about two weeks after it is deployed.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/21/2016<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;J&nbsp;Ridley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1042815/1042815_10137804_1453389056065_IMG_0110--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1042815/1042815_10137804_1453389056065_IMG_0110--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Installing a Wing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1042815/1042815_10137804_1453389056065_IMG_0110--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Installing a Wing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students installing one of four wings on CADRE</div> <div class="imageCredit">UM-MXL</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;J&nbsp;Ridley</div> <div class="imageTitle">Installing a Wing</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1042815/1042815_10137804_1453389176680_IMG_0266--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1042815/1042815_10137804_1453389176680_IMG_0266--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Almost Finished!"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1042815/1042815_10137804_1453389176680_IMG_0266--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Almost Finished!"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CADRE almost fully inte...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The upper atmosphere of the Earth is a region of space that satellites and the international space station orbits through.  It is important to understand this part of the atmosphere for the safety of our astronauts and to prevent collisions between objects that could be catastrophic financially. In order to do this, scientists create space weather models, which simulate the environment and its response to heating caused by the northern (and southern) lights (i.e., the aurora).  We have built a small satellite called CADRE that will measure things like the temperature and winds in the upper atmosphere, allowing researchers to both better understand how the system behaves and validate models.  The satellite is a CubeSat that is 4 inches by 4 inches by 12 inches in size, and is being deployed from the International Space Station the last week of January, 2016. Students at the University of Michigan (UM) built it, while the Naval Research Laboratory built the sensor.  Over 50 students, including undergraduate, masters, and Ph.D. students worked on the design, build, integration, and testing of the CubeSat.  The CubeSat is technologically much more challenging than any other that UM has built.  Many small satellites donÆt need to know which direction they are pointing, since they have sensors that can take data in any direction (for example, radiation sensors can measure radiation from anywhere).  CADRE needs to be pointed in a given direction extremely accurately, which was a huge challenge.  Further, CADRE needs more power than any satellite that UM has produced, which meant putting a large number of solar cells on the satellite.  This was also quite complicated, since it involved having folding panels, which UM had never done before.  The satellite was delivered just after the project officially ended, and was launched into space in December 2015.  It will be deployed from the international space station in late January 2016.  Data will start being taken about two weeks after it is deployed.          Last Modified: 01/21/2016       Submitted by: Aaron J Ridley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
