<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Environmental and Social Impacts of the 2010 Eyjafjallajokull Eruption</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27720.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27720</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna M. Kerttula</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will use the once-in-a-generation opportunity provided by the 2010 eruption of Eyjafjallajökull (Ey 2010) to create a new model of volcanic ash layer formation within the geological record, and evaluate the ash-fall?s social and environmental impact. This could potentially transform our understanding of the environmental data preserved within volcanic ash layers, refine our knowledge of past eruptions and enhance our understanding of their impacts on society and landscape. In order to achieve this goal this project it is necessary to rapidly gather a suitable multinational (US-Icelandic-UK) interdisciplinary team of researchers, hold a workshop to establish appropriate and meaningful collaborations between both the academic and local community and establish a rigorous sampling protocol that can be carried out over the next 3-5 years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Ey 2010 eruption presents a unusual opportunity to understand more about thresholds of change related to volcanic ash-fall; under what circumstances do tipping points occur in relation to vegetation, geomorphology and land-use change? How does weather, vegetation, topography, land use affect the transformation of the ash layer? What is the effect of deposition over snow? When do volcanic ash layers remain the same, acquire or lose mass? What governs the timing of ash stabilisation and redistribution across landscape? If the ways in which volcanic ash layers become transformed are better understood then this could achieve four important goals: 1) we will be able to know more about the nature of the landscape onto which the ash fell and 2) the post depositional environmental processes operating on it; 3) we will be able to have a better idea of the nature of the initial ash fall and so 4) be able to better reconstruct the initial eruption.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the aftermath of the 2010 eruption the social and environmental impacts can be tracked in detail as they happen and it will be possible to discuss unfolding events and their consequences with the affected community. How does volcanic ash affect vegetation, water quality and drainage? What are the impacts on livestock? How does the ash-fall affect grazing, soil erosion and soil fertility? Where the ash was cleared, how was this done? What other impacts (negative and positive) has the eruption caused and how does this affect the viability of farming and other rural activities?</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1042951</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Dugmore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew J Dugmore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Andrew.Dugmore@ed.ac.uk</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128177523</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563758</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Graduate School University Center</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128177526</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>365 Fifth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128194</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Graduate School University Center]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[365 Fifth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~27720</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A field-based pilot study, three workshops and a field school have been supported with this grant. A multinational, trans-disciplinary research group has been assembled to assess tephra (volcanic ash) transformations with a tested research strategy, supported by a new research discussion group <em>Tephra in Quaternary Science</em>.&nbsp; An international conference presentation, workshop report and community statement have been published; a fully funded PhD studentship secured and 38 students have received field training.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The most important research finding to arise from this project is the discovery that although we do not understand in any detail how surface tephra deposits are transformed into layers within the stratigraphic record <em>we can use variations in tephra layer thickness as an early warning indicator of threshold-crossing events</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>When centimetre-scale depths of tephra fall across Iceland layer-thickness variability develops proportional to landscape instability; in stable, vegetated areas there is relatively little variation in tephra layer thickness and a comparatively uniform layer is rapidly incorporated into the stratigraphic record. In less stable areas tephra layers acquire greater variability, becoming partially-removed, patchy or very thick before their eventually burial. In unstable areas where critical thresholds between deposition and erosion have been crossed, tephra thickness becomes extremely variable and no long-term record is preserved. Observations of the 2010 tephra deposits have established systematic relationships between thickness variability and landscape instability, up to <em>and across</em> environmental thresholds. Thus the preserved physical features of a tephra layer - a &ldquo;memory&rdquo; of process - can be used to predict threshold-crossing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This understanding can now be developed and applied to the interpretation of thickness data from past tephra falls to quantify &lsquo;closeness to threshold&rsquo; for different times and places. This will allow us to identify &lsquo;near-misses&rsquo; when the landscape came close to, but did not cross, thresholds of change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to discovering a new early-warning indicator this project has highlighted critical limits to our present understanding. Where tephra layers vary in thickness we do not know for sure if the maximum thickness, minimum thickness or some thickness in between represents the original thickness of fallout at that site. This is an important issue because tephra layers are the principal record of the scale and nature of past explosive volcanism. Centimetre-thicknesses of tephra are globally significant having affected much of the earth and large areas of the United States. They form marker horizons of great use in environmental reconstruction and record extreme events that have affected people both directly and indirectly.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We can identify a range of natural and cultural impacts due to tephra fall, some positive and some negative; the types of volcanic impacts and their consequences are crucially dependant on context, as similar tephra&ndash;falls in different places and at different times can have very different effects. Although responses to volcanic impacts are many and diverse, they do follow identifiable trends and may be modelled.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Observations made in the course of this project highlight the varied interactions of tephra, snow and glacier ice which give complex responses in terms of meltwater production. Tephra resting on low-permeability glacier ice is rapidly removed by runoff. Tephra on permeable snow is more persistent as melt water drains through the snow pack so the insulating effect of an undisturbed tephra cover is prolonged. The development of tephra-snow-ice surfaces follows a sequence where rill incision s...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A field-based pilot study, three workshops and a field school have been supported with this grant. A multinational, trans-disciplinary research group has been assembled to assess tephra (volcanic ash) transformations with a tested research strategy, supported by a new research discussion group Tephra in Quaternary Science.  An international conference presentation, workshop report and community statement have been published; a fully funded PhD studentship secured and 38 students have received field training.      The most important research finding to arise from this project is the discovery that although we do not understand in any detail how surface tephra deposits are transformed into layers within the stratigraphic record we can use variations in tephra layer thickness as an early warning indicator of threshold-crossing events.     When centimetre-scale depths of tephra fall across Iceland layer-thickness variability develops proportional to landscape instability; in stable, vegetated areas there is relatively little variation in tephra layer thickness and a comparatively uniform layer is rapidly incorporated into the stratigraphic record. In less stable areas tephra layers acquire greater variability, becoming partially-removed, patchy or very thick before their eventually burial. In unstable areas where critical thresholds between deposition and erosion have been crossed, tephra thickness becomes extremely variable and no long-term record is preserved. Observations of the 2010 tephra deposits have established systematic relationships between thickness variability and landscape instability, up to and across environmental thresholds. Thus the preserved physical features of a tephra layer - a "memory" of process - can be used to predict threshold-crossing.     This understanding can now be developed and applied to the interpretation of thickness data from past tephra falls to quantify æcloseness to thresholdÆ for different times and places. This will allow us to identify ænear-missesÆ when the landscape came close to, but did not cross, thresholds of change.     In addition to discovering a new early-warning indicator this project has highlighted critical limits to our present understanding. Where tephra layers vary in thickness we do not know for sure if the maximum thickness, minimum thickness or some thickness in between represents the original thickness of fallout at that site. This is an important issue because tephra layers are the principal record of the scale and nature of past explosive volcanism. Centimetre-thicknesses of tephra are globally significant having affected much of the earth and large areas of the United States. They form marker horizons of great use in environmental reconstruction and record extreme events that have affected people both directly and indirectly.     We can identify a range of natural and cultural impacts due to tephra fall, some positive and some negative; the types of volcanic impacts and their consequences are crucially dependant on context, as similar tephra&ndash;falls in different places and at different times can have very different effects. Although responses to volcanic impacts are many and diverse, they do follow identifiable trends and may be modelled.     Observations made in the course of this project highlight the varied interactions of tephra, snow and glacier ice which give complex responses in terms of meltwater production. Tephra resting on low-permeability glacier ice is rapidly removed by runoff. Tephra on permeable snow is more persistent as melt water drains through the snow pack so the insulating effect of an undisturbed tephra cover is prolonged. The development of tephra-snow-ice surfaces follows a sequence where rill incision sets up rapid back wasting of 50-60 degree low-albedo ice walls, progressively removing the initial tephra-covered surface. This etching of the ice cap surface involves the growth of a slower melting, largely tephra free ice surface sever...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
