<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Augmenting the Ross Island-area automatic weather station network to develop a tropospheric ozone climatology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>219222.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>219222</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Polar tropospheric ozone concentrations exhibit strong seasonal variations and often just as strong anomalies, or ozone depletion events arising from spring destruction episodes.  Using the existing Automatic Weather Stations network in the McMurdo Ross Sea region, a number of photometric based ozone meters will be deployed, in order to establish a multi-season record of surface level ozone distributions in the McMurdo area. This in turn will allow a record of seasonal surface ozone variability in the Ross Sea region to be assembled. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A link between natural background processes  influencing tropospheric ozone  and any transported or local (McMurdo region, Ant)  pollution components (such as NOx) or naturally sourced halogens is to be better explained. The continued career development of  a post-doctoral associate, and also an undergraduate student involved in the proposal will be an aditional outcome of this work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1043478</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Lazzara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew A Lazzara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mattl@ssec.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082620436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~219222</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In contrast to the majority of the Earth&rsquo;s landmasses, Antarctica still remains a continent largely free from anthropogenic pollution and human influence.&nbsp;&nbsp; With the exception of a small number of areas influenced by permanent research stations, Antarctica provides a pristine laboratory for the study of naturally occurring processes in our environment.&nbsp;&nbsp; One of these processes is the seasonal cycle of surface level ozone, which follows a predictable cycle, with a mid-winter maximum followed by an episodic, and sometimes rapid, decrease at polar sunrise, reaching a minimum in late summer followed by a slow increase during the autumn.&nbsp;&nbsp; While the cycle is predictable, the mechanism behind it is not clearly understood, particularly the episodic ozone depletions that drive the overall spring time decrease in surface level ozone.&nbsp; This project established a small network of autonomous ozone sensors in the Ross Island region of Antarctica to obtain a record of surface level ozone away from the anthropogenic influence of McMurdo Station, the largest Antarctic research station.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The scientific goals of the project were threefold: to characterize the frequency and severity of spring time ozone depletion events in the Ross Island region, to examine the geographic extent of these events and their dependence on meteorology, and to establish a year round climatology of surface level ozone spanning several years.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the first year of the project, four Automatic Weather Stations (AWS) in the Ross Island region were instrumented with newly-developed, rugged, low power, ozone sensors.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; These sensors were developed specifically for this project, and designed to operate through the harsh Antarctic winters using renewable energy.&nbsp; These instruments were integrated with the existing AWS network that provide real-time meteorology, as well as leverage the existing AWS infrastructure including communications and energy systems.&nbsp; The instruments were installed during the austral summer of 2011-12, with a service and calibration visit in 2012-13.&nbsp;&nbsp; Two of the four instruments continued to operate through the winter of 2013, but without a service visit in 2013-14, mechanical component failures had impacted all instruments by 2014.&nbsp;&nbsp; Over the course of the project, over 100,000 measurements of ozone and associated meteorology were made.&nbsp;&nbsp; In parallel to the measurement campaign, meteorological data from the AWS system as well as the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System (AMPS) was archived for use in the analysis of observed ozone depletion events.&nbsp;&nbsp; A new diagnostic tool to produce high-resolution back trajectories specifically for the Antarctic was developed to trace the origin of ozone depleted air parcels.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Ozone depletion events were observed during both the austral spring of 2012 and 2013.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; These events were significantly more frequent and pronounced at the monitoring stations closest to spring time sea ice and summer time open water, with fewer distinct events observed at inland stations.&nbsp; This supports the currently held theory that the springtime ozone depletion events are associated with chemicals derived from sea ice, and are limited to coastal and sea ice locations. Furthermore, only a single ozone depletion event was conclusively identified at the higher altitude measurement site, even though the same annual cycle was observed.&nbsp;&nbsp; Surprisingly, a prominent ozone depletion event was observed at the coastal site during the late winter, before polar sunrise.&nbsp; In comparison to longer-term measurements from other coastal Antarctic research stations, ozone depletion events were less frequent and less severe in the Ross Island region.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As th...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In contrast to the majority of the EarthÆs landmasses, Antarctica still remains a continent largely free from anthropogenic pollution and human influence.   With the exception of a small number of areas influenced by permanent research stations, Antarctica provides a pristine laboratory for the study of naturally occurring processes in our environment.   One of these processes is the seasonal cycle of surface level ozone, which follows a predictable cycle, with a mid-winter maximum followed by an episodic, and sometimes rapid, decrease at polar sunrise, reaching a minimum in late summer followed by a slow increase during the autumn.   While the cycle is predictable, the mechanism behind it is not clearly understood, particularly the episodic ozone depletions that drive the overall spring time decrease in surface level ozone.  This project established a small network of autonomous ozone sensors in the Ross Island region of Antarctica to obtain a record of surface level ozone away from the anthropogenic influence of McMurdo Station, the largest Antarctic research station.    The scientific goals of the project were threefold: to characterize the frequency and severity of spring time ozone depletion events in the Ross Island region, to examine the geographic extent of these events and their dependence on meteorology, and to establish a year round climatology of surface level ozone spanning several years.     During the first year of the project, four Automatic Weather Stations (AWS) in the Ross Island region were instrumented with newly-developed, rugged, low power, ozone sensors.    These sensors were developed specifically for this project, and designed to operate through the harsh Antarctic winters using renewable energy.  These instruments were integrated with the existing AWS network that provide real-time meteorology, as well as leverage the existing AWS infrastructure including communications and energy systems.  The instruments were installed during the austral summer of 2011-12, with a service and calibration visit in 2012-13.   Two of the four instruments continued to operate through the winter of 2013, but without a service visit in 2013-14, mechanical component failures had impacted all instruments by 2014.   Over the course of the project, over 100,000 measurements of ozone and associated meteorology were made.   In parallel to the measurement campaign, meteorological data from the AWS system as well as the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System (AMPS) was archived for use in the analysis of observed ozone depletion events.   A new diagnostic tool to produce high-resolution back trajectories specifically for the Antarctic was developed to trace the origin of ozone depleted air parcels.     Ozone depletion events were observed during both the austral spring of 2012 and 2013.    These events were significantly more frequent and pronounced at the monitoring stations closest to spring time sea ice and summer time open water, with fewer distinct events observed at inland stations.  This supports the currently held theory that the springtime ozone depletion events are associated with chemicals derived from sea ice, and are limited to coastal and sea ice locations. Furthermore, only a single ozone depletion event was conclusively identified at the higher altitude measurement site, even though the same annual cycle was observed.   Surprisingly, a prominent ozone depletion event was observed at the coastal site during the late winter, before polar sunrise.  In comparison to longer-term measurements from other coastal Antarctic research stations, ozone depletion events were less frequent and less severe in the Ross Island region.         As the first distributed measurements of this type in the Ross Island region, this project has furthered our understanding of the frequency and geographic distribution of ozone depletion events, which is important for understanding the overall natural chemical cycle in Polar Regions.  This is ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
