<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Designing Interdisciplinary Tools to Assess Diverse Learners' Approaches to Problem-Solving: a Cross-State Collaboration in New Mexico</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Terry S. Woodin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project tests the adaptability and adoptability of on-line case studies as the basis for student groups to use Problem-based Learning to master complex concepts in biology and chemistry.  A group of faculty from the University of New Mexico has used this approach successfully in biochemistry courses there.  To learn whether the approach can be used at different types of institutions, they are collaborating with faculty at San Juan College to help them to develop and implement it among the San Juan students of introductory biology and chemistry.  San Juan College is a rural community college in northwestern New Mexico, and is a federally designated Native American Serving Non-Tribal Institution.  Its student population also includes a significant Hispanic presence.  Despite the significant physical and cultural distance between the two schools, the collaboration succeeds by the use of workshops for development of the case studies and ongoing support and mentoring of the San Juan faculty using electronic means of communication.  Groups of students working on the case studies also use electronic tools to investigate the cases and to respond to assessments designed to test their mastery in several different domains of learning.  When needed, faculty assistance can also be provided electronically.  Distance thus becomes far less an obstacle in development of this learning community.  Support for this project is provided by EHR/DUE and by the EPSCoR program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1043079</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcy</FirstName>
<LastName>Osgood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marcy Osgood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>MOsgood@salud.unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052728184</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Veronica</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Veronica Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Evansv@sanjuancollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5055663209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526417</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052726264</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>MSC09 5220</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 University of New Mexico]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>829868723</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[MSC09 5220]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~249998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of the UNM/SJC TUES Project was to introduce problem-based learning (PBL) strategies to community college faculty and students. This grant facilitated dissemination of problem-solving practice and assessment tools to San Juan College (SJC) science faculty through: 1) a three-workshop series that offered step-by-step training for the development and implementation of relevant On-Line Cases (OLCs) to be used in the SJC School of Science (SoS) classes in Biology, Chemistry, and General Science; 2) training for the development of corresponding Individual Problem-Solving Assessments (IPSAs); 3) ongoing support during implementation and&nbsp; subsequent improvement of these products; 4) creation of a complete online workshop and repository, offering trainings as well as fully developed, ready for use, OLCs and IPSAs.</p> <p>In addition, the project paved the way for institutional changes. The following specific examples of impact were identified by UNM/SJC TUES participants:</p> <ul> <li>Collaboration  <ul> <li>UNM/SJC TUES has resulted in more interaction among faculty at SJC, as well as between SJC and UNM educators</li> <li>Sharing materials, techniques, and experiences assisted faculty in curriculum development and delivery, and provided for more uniform delivery of the curriculum across courses</li> <li>SJC faculty began to seek collaborations with student support programs and curriculum development groups on campus; together faculty and programs are changing the way faculty teach at SJC</li> </ul> </li> <li>Increased Understanding and Implementation of PBL strategies  <ul> <li>There is increased awareness of the fact that students can benefit from these techniques</li> </ul> </li> <li>Increased Understanding of Student Barriers to Success  <ul> <li>There is increased awareness by faculty and administrators of barriers to student participation and success with online teaching approaches</li> <li>Faculty are getting involved in institution-wide efforts to address barriers to student success</li> </ul> </li> <li>Collective Vision  <ul> <li>Faculty are asking questions centering on how they can motivate students and increase student participation </li> <li>Faculty seem determined to develop techniques that help students learn</li> </ul> </li> <li>Impact Across Campus  <ul> <li>The project has resulted in other disciplinary faculty being introduced to and adopting PBL techniques.&nbsp; </li> <li>Additional instructors (in Biology) will be using fully developed OLCs and IPSAs in the Fall 2014 semester</li> <li>Training sessions offered to faculty across campus are utilizing PBL concepts </li> <li>Faculty are seeking exposure to and training in complementary new teaching approaches</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2014<br>      Modified by: Veronica&nbsp;Evans</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of the UNM/SJC TUES Project was to introduce problem-based learning (PBL) strategies to community college faculty and students. This grant facilitated dissemination of problem-solving practice and assessment tools to San Juan College (SJC) science faculty through: 1) a three-workshop series that offered step-by-step training for the development and implementation of relevant On-Line Cases (OLCs) to be used in the SJC School of Science (SoS) classes in Biology, Chemistry, and General Science; 2) training for the development of corresponding Individual Problem-Solving Assessments (IPSAs); 3) ongoing support during implementation and  subsequent improvement of these products; 4) creation of a complete online workshop and repository, offering trainings as well as fully developed, ready for use, OLCs and IPSAs.  In addition, the project paved the way for institutional changes. The following specific examples of impact were identified by UNM/SJC TUES participants:  Collaboration   UNM/SJC TUES has resulted in more interaction among faculty at SJC, as well as between SJC and UNM educators Sharing materials, techniques, and experiences assisted faculty in curriculum development and delivery, and provided for more uniform delivery of the curriculum across courses SJC faculty began to seek collaborations with student support programs and curriculum development groups on campus; together faculty and programs are changing the way faculty teach at SJC   Increased Understanding and Implementation of PBL strategies   There is increased awareness of the fact that students can benefit from these techniques   Increased Understanding of Student Barriers to Success   There is increased awareness by faculty and administrators of barriers to student participation and success with online teaching approaches Faculty are getting involved in institution-wide efforts to address barriers to student success   Collective Vision   Faculty are asking questions centering on how they can motivate students and increase student participation  Faculty seem determined to develop techniques that help students learn   Impact Across Campus   The project has resulted in other disciplinary faculty being introduced to and adopting PBL techniques.   Additional instructors (in Biology) will be using fully developed OLCs and IPSAs in the Fall 2014 semester Training sessions offered to faculty across campus are utilizing PBL concepts  Faculty are seeking exposure to and training in complementary new teaching approaches             Last Modified: 08/05/2014       Submitted by: Veronica Evans]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
