<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID Collaborative Proposal: Spatially-explicit, High-resolution Mapping and Modeling to Quantify Hypoxia and Oil Effects on the Living Resources of the Northern Gulf of Mexico</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>46981.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>46981</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>On April 22, 2010, the drill platform Deepwater Horizon sank in nearly 1,200 m of water in the northern Gulf of Mexico. Since this date various estimates of oil and added chemical dispersants have been released from the site with dispersion both at the surface and at depth. The transport of this oil and dispersants has been influenced by wind-driven currents over the shelf and by the Loop Current and its derivatives offshore. To date the exact amount and paths of movement of the Horizon spill remain speculative. Since 2003, with NOAA-CSCOR funding, this group of investigators has conducted 5 summer cruises in the northern Gulf of Mexico that used high-resolution sampling to define the spatially explicit relationships between physical structure to pelagic zooplankton and fish distributions.  Thus this group has one of the most comprehensive, synoptic data sets on temperature, salinity, oxygen, phytoplankton, zooplankton and fish in the northern Gulf of Mexico for conditions prior to the oil leak.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current RAPID award will allow this group to repeat their high-resolution mapping of hydrography, oxygen, plankton and fish in the northern Gulf of Mexico. The domain of interest will include the previous survey region in the hypoxic zone west of the Mississippi Delta but also the area east of the Mississippi where more oil transport from the spill has been suggested. The cruise will take place in the late summer period because the investigators have 5 years of ?baseline? data during this season to compare the results. The measures of species diversity and abundance, biomass size spectrum, fish diets, fish growth rate potential and ecosystem models will all be extremely useful to assess the possible effects of the oil spill on the living resources of the northern Gulf of Mexico. In addition to the rapid mapping cruise on the inner to mid-shelf, this group also will send scientists on the ORV Oceanus to conduct high resolution vertical zooplankton measurements (LOPC and TAPS) and MOCNESS zooplankton tows at deeper stations and broader mapping surveys to extend our spatial coverage of the affected area. They will coordinate our zooplankton and fish measurements with other investigators assessing the biogeochemical and biological impacts of the BP oil spill. Data from previous NOAA will be deposited in the BCODMO data management facility as well as current measurements and model products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. Given the economic importance of the Gulf of Mexico commercial fisheries (about 20% of the U.S. total landings representing about $991 million) and recreational fishing (generating ~30% of the nation?s saltwater fishing expenditures and supporting nearly 25% of the nation?s recreational saltwater jobs), it is imperative that knowledge of the effects of the BP oil spill on the pelagic ecosystem be assessed. The Horn Point Laboratory and Oregon State University are part of the National Science Foundation ? Center for Ocean Sciences Education Excellence (NSF-COSEE) and Experience for Undergraduates (REU) programs. Where possible in this NSF RAPID response grant, we will involve REU undergraduate students and teachers in our proposed research program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1043261</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Brandt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Brandt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stephen.brandt@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417373396</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527885</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5987</Code>
<Text>GULF OF MEXICO OIL SPILL-2010</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~46981</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Following the Deepwater Horizon Oil spill, in September 2010 our team conducted a 7 day cruise aboard the RV Pelican to the Louisiana shelf (Figure 1). We completed 12 cross-shelf transects, which included acoustic surveys for plankton and fish, and generated distribution maps of various physical properties, including dissolved oxygen, temperature, salinity, chlorophyll a fluorescence, and colored dissolved organic matter (CDOM). &nbsp;CDOM, which in some cases can be used as a proxy for oil, appeared to be associated with river flow from the Atchafalaya River and Mississippi River. Low dissolved oxygen was observed in patches, primarily in the deeper regions of transects in the middle and eastern portions of the Louisiana shelf. An additional vessel used trawls at discrete points along each transect to collect fish for species identification to verify acoustic surveys. &nbsp;</p> <p>This field work builds on 5 previous years of high-resolution mapping of hydrography, oxygen, plankton and fish in the northern Gulf of Mexico, including our previous survey region in the &ldquo;hypoxic zone&rdquo; west of the Mississippi Delta. Our &ldquo;metrics&rdquo; of species diversity and abundance, fish diets, fish growth rate potential and ecosystem models will all be extremely useful to assess the possible effects of the oil spill on the living resources of the northern Gulf of Mexico. Our team is comprised of partners from University of Maryland, Oregon State University, East Carolina University, Louisiana State University, NOAA Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory, University of Akron, and University of Michigan.</p> <p>Fish acoustic surveys from the 2010 cruise revealed interesting patterns in dissolved oxygen and fish response. We saw a &ldquo;double layer&rdquo; of low dissolved oxygen in portions of the water column, with DO sharply dropping below 15m depth, increasing to higher oxygen below 17m depth, and then gradually decreasing to the bottom of the water column. Acoustic surveys showed fish distributed themselves along oxygen gradients (Figure 2). Scattering strength, which serves as a proxy for fish abundance, revealed high densities of fish in both the eastern portion of our survey area in shallow nearshore areas, as well as in the western region a bit further offshore (Figure 3). Preliminary identification of fish species from trawling suggests that high numbers of croaker were caught throughout the survey area. These and other data are currently being incorporated into our ongoing living resource modeling efforts to provide spatially-explicit habitat assessment for fishes in areas of the northern Gulf of Mexico affected by low oxygen and the oil spill.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2011<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;Brandt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1043261/1043261_10016701_1323207492806_NSFRAPIDFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1043261/1043261_10016701_1323207492806_NSFRAPIDFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/1043261/1043261_10016701_1323207492806_NSFRAPIDFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The blue line represents the cruise track from our September 1-7, 2010 cruise in the northern Gulf of Mexico.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J.J. Pierson</div> <div class="imagePermisssio...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Following the Deepwater Horizon Oil spill, in September 2010 our team conducted a 7 day cruise aboard the RV Pelican to the Louisiana shelf (Figure 1). We completed 12 cross-shelf transects, which included acoustic surveys for plankton and fish, and generated distribution maps of various physical properties, including dissolved oxygen, temperature, salinity, chlorophyll a fluorescence, and colored dissolved organic matter (CDOM).  CDOM, which in some cases can be used as a proxy for oil, appeared to be associated with river flow from the Atchafalaya River and Mississippi River. Low dissolved oxygen was observed in patches, primarily in the deeper regions of transects in the middle and eastern portions of the Louisiana shelf. An additional vessel used trawls at discrete points along each transect to collect fish for species identification to verify acoustic surveys.    This field work builds on 5 previous years of high-resolution mapping of hydrography, oxygen, plankton and fish in the northern Gulf of Mexico, including our previous survey region in the "hypoxic zone" west of the Mississippi Delta. Our "metrics" of species diversity and abundance, fish diets, fish growth rate potential and ecosystem models will all be extremely useful to assess the possible effects of the oil spill on the living resources of the northern Gulf of Mexico. Our team is comprised of partners from University of Maryland, Oregon State University, East Carolina University, Louisiana State University, NOAA Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory, University of Akron, and University of Michigan.  Fish acoustic surveys from the 2010 cruise revealed interesting patterns in dissolved oxygen and fish response. We saw a "double layer" of low dissolved oxygen in portions of the water column, with DO sharply dropping below 15m depth, increasing to higher oxygen below 17m depth, and then gradually decreasing to the bottom of the water column. Acoustic surveys showed fish distributed themselves along oxygen gradients (Figure 2). Scattering strength, which serves as a proxy for fish abundance, revealed high densities of fish in both the eastern portion of our survey area in shallow nearshore areas, as well as in the western region a bit further offshore (Figure 3). Preliminary identification of fish species from trawling suggests that high numbers of croaker were caught throughout the survey area. These and other data are currently being incorporated into our ongoing living resource modeling efforts to provide spatially-explicit habitat assessment for fishes in areas of the northern Gulf of Mexico affected by low oxygen and the oil spill.       Last Modified: 12/06/2011       Submitted by: Stephen Brandt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
