<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:Rates and mechanisms controlling the microbial degradation of crude oil from the MC252 spill in Gulf of Mexico beach sands</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>169653.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>169653</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald L. Rice</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With funding through this Grant for Rapid Response Research (RAPID), scientists at the Florida State University will study the transport and biodegradation of Deepwater Horizon crude oil in Gulf beach sands.   The study will place emphasis on the sediment clogging caused by oil filtration and ensuing changes to the structure and function of indigenous microbial communities.  Although the process of oil contamination of beaches has been investigated in great detail, little is known about the effect of crude oil on beach filtration and the effect of oil-related reduction of beach pore water flows on oil transport and microbial degradation within the sandy sediment.  This filtration process, caused by wave set up and tidal water level changes, constitutes an effective pumping mechanism that can drive low-viscosity crude oil and detergent-oil mixtures deep into beach sediments.  Oil transport into deeper, anoxic layers may decrease oil degradation rates, thereby extending the period of toxin release to nearshore waters.  Goals of the project are to assess 1) how much and how deep oil is filtered into the beach, 2) how oil alters the beach filtration rate and thereby sediment oxygenation, 4) how oil contamination changes structure and function of the sand microbial community and 5) which factors regulate oil degradation by microbial communities in marine sands.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To quantify these processes, sets of sediment cores will be taken at time intervals along a short transect from the supralittoral to the sublittoral zone at a sandy beach in the Northeastern Gulf of Mexico.  The sediment will be analyzed for oil content (amount, composition and distribution), sediment characteristics (permeability, porosity, grain size spectrum, oxygen penetration), and the microbial community (composition and activity).  Oil will be characterized using a GC-MS.  Changes in microbial community composition and activity will be assessed using a combination of culture-based and cultivation-independent molecular techniques.  The results will quantify the uptake of oil and detergent-oil mixtures into Gulf sand beaches, the effect of these substances on sediment physical and biogeochemical properties, the response of the sedimentary microbial community, and oil degradation rates. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The sandy beaches of the Northeastern Gulf of Mexico are of high ecological and economical value as they are biotope, foraging and breeding area of a large number species, and present a main tourist attraction.  Tourism is Florida?s largest sector of the state economy with about 60 million visitors every year and a $57 billion impact.  The pollution of the beaches by crude oil thus presents a major threat to Florida?s economy.  Previous research indicates that oil can penetrate deep into sandy beaches, which may change microbial community activities and decrease the oil degradation rates.  Consequences include toxin release from such beaches extending over many years.  Understanding the uptake, transport and degradation of oil in sandy Gulf beaches is prerequisite for designing clean up and remediation procedures.  Research of this project focuses on pristine Gulf beaches for which no data on oil penetration and degradation exist and that now are threatened by the Deepwater Horizon disaster.  The project combines research with education and training of two graduate students.  Project results will be published in scientific journals, local outlets and the internet.  The data collected in this rapid response project will provide data for a proposal of a three year project focusing on transport and degradation of crude oil components in permeable shore sediments.  The project goal is to generate quantitative data that permit forecasting of the oil degradation process and optimization of bioremediation procedures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1044939</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kostka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel E Kostka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joel.kostka@biology.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043853325</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Markus</FirstName>
<LastName>Huettel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Markus H Huettel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mhuettel@fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506451394</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1389</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5987</Code>
<Text>GULF OF MEXICO OIL SPILL-2010</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~169653</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Crude oil released after the Deepwater Horizon to Gulf of Mexico was deposited during stormy days end of June 2010 onto the sandy beaches of the northeastern Gulf, from Dauphin Island to Panama City. This oil covered an approximately 10 m wide beach area along the water line, and sands subsequently deposited onto this area buried the oil and led to the formation of compressed tar layers found as deep as 75 cm in the beach sand. The fate of this buried oil and its environmental impact were unknown. Because as these beaches are a primary tourist destination, information on the degradation of these oil layers was needed. Supported by a grant from NSF, scientists and students from Florida State University and Georgia Institute of Technology investigated the decomposition of the oil deposited in Gulf sandy beaches and its impact on the sedimentary microbial community. The oil layers were found to be hot spots of microbial activity and sites of enhanced biogeochemical cycling. Parallel analysis of the sand microbial community with molecular biology techniques revealed a distinct enrichment of known hydrocarbon-degrading bacterial taxa where oil was present. By combining identification of oil hydrocarbons and microbial community analysis, it was possible to single out the predominant hydrocarbon-degrading microorganisms that are active in degrading various oil components in the sands. The microbial degradation process was reflected in the oxygen consumption rates and carbon dioxide production rates that both increased significantly in the sediment layers containing oil. These results revealed that the oil was decomposed by the microbial community at relatively high rates, which is attributed to the content of rapidly degradable hydrocarbons in the buried oil. The warm temperatures of the Gulf Coast supported the rapid degradation, and approximately half a year after the accident, the aerobic degradation rates showed a significant decline. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Biodegradation mediated by indigenous microorganisms is the main mechanism by which oil released to the marine environment may be naturally removed. Analysis of the factors that affect the transport and decomposition of the oil is prerequisite for a realistic prediction of the duration and impact of the oil contamination. The investigations conducted in this NSF-supported project elucidated the molecular fingerprint of oil compounds trapped in the beach sand, their change over time and that of the associated microbial community.&nbsp; The results identified microbial species in the beach sands that responded with growth to the oil contamination and that are critical for the degradation process. Quantitative determinations of the factors that affected the microbially-catalyzed biodegradation in this project will help coastal managers to assess the environmental impact of oil on the coast as well as to direct appropriate remediation efforts to oil spills. This research thereby helps to maintain the high ecological and economical value of the sandy Gulf beaches.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2012<br>      Modified by: Markus&nbsp;H&nbsp;Huettel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1044939/1044939_10017051_1342628957969_DSC01665--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1044939/1044939_10017051_1342628957969_DSC01665--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampling of oil layers buried in Florida beach sands"><img src="/por/images/Reports/P...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Crude oil released after the Deepwater Horizon to Gulf of Mexico was deposited during stormy days end of June 2010 onto the sandy beaches of the northeastern Gulf, from Dauphin Island to Panama City. This oil covered an approximately 10 m wide beach area along the water line, and sands subsequently deposited onto this area buried the oil and led to the formation of compressed tar layers found as deep as 75 cm in the beach sand. The fate of this buried oil and its environmental impact were unknown. Because as these beaches are a primary tourist destination, information on the degradation of these oil layers was needed. Supported by a grant from NSF, scientists and students from Florida State University and Georgia Institute of Technology investigated the decomposition of the oil deposited in Gulf sandy beaches and its impact on the sedimentary microbial community. The oil layers were found to be hot spots of microbial activity and sites of enhanced biogeochemical cycling. Parallel analysis of the sand microbial community with molecular biology techniques revealed a distinct enrichment of known hydrocarbon-degrading bacterial taxa where oil was present. By combining identification of oil hydrocarbons and microbial community analysis, it was possible to single out the predominant hydrocarbon-degrading microorganisms that are active in degrading various oil components in the sands. The microbial degradation process was reflected in the oxygen consumption rates and carbon dioxide production rates that both increased significantly in the sediment layers containing oil. These results revealed that the oil was decomposed by the microbial community at relatively high rates, which is attributed to the content of rapidly degradable hydrocarbons in the buried oil. The warm temperatures of the Gulf Coast supported the rapid degradation, and approximately half a year after the accident, the aerobic degradation rates showed a significant decline.       Biodegradation mediated by indigenous microorganisms is the main mechanism by which oil released to the marine environment may be naturally removed. Analysis of the factors that affect the transport and decomposition of the oil is prerequisite for a realistic prediction of the duration and impact of the oil contamination. The investigations conducted in this NSF-supported project elucidated the molecular fingerprint of oil compounds trapped in the beach sand, their change over time and that of the associated microbial community.  The results identified microbial species in the beach sands that responded with growth to the oil contamination and that are critical for the degradation process. Quantitative determinations of the factors that affected the microbially-catalyzed biodegradation in this project will help coastal managers to assess the environmental impact of oil on the coast as well as to direct appropriate remediation efforts to oil spills. This research thereby helps to maintain the high ecological and economical value of the sandy Gulf beaches.          Last Modified: 07/18/2012       Submitted by: Markus H Huettel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
