<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Process Oriented Guided Inquiry Learning (POGIL) in Computer Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>161367.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>161367</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie August</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Faculty are developing Process-Oriented Guided-Inquiry Learning materials (POGIL) to teach computer science topics:  software engineering and data structures &amp; algorithms.  POGIL is based on the biology of learning and has been developed and validated for over fifteen years.  Teams of learners work on scripted inquiry activities to help them construct their own knowledge.  The instructor serves as facilitator, not lecturer.  Ten student activities are being developed for software engineering topics including project management and the Unified Modeling Language.  Ten activities are being developed to support data structures &amp; algorithms topics including basic data structures, searching and sorting.  Materials include facilitator instructions, activity descriptions and supplemental information.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Four collaborators are developing and assessing materials at a variety of institutions including selective liberal arts colleges, a public university and an institute of technology.  The project leverages and extends the successful inquiry-based approach to a new subject and explores the use of computer tablets and web-based tools that could benefit the POGIL movement in general.  Faculty workshops during the third year are designed to raise awareness and adoption in the computer science education community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1044679</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R.</FirstName>
<LastName>Libby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>R. D Libby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rdlibby@chem.moravian.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6108611436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087092</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
<LastName>Salter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carl Salter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>csalter@moravian.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6108613927</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000352812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Clifton</FirstName>
<LastName>Kussmaul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Clifton L Kussmaul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>clif@kussmaul.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4848930255</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219181</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Muhlenberg College</Name>
<CityName>Allentown</CityName>
<ZipCode>181045586</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4846643673</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>24th and Chew Streets</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047352836</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MUHLENBERG COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>047352836</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Muhlenberg College]]></Name>
<CityName>Allentown</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>181045586</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[24th and Chew Streets]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~161367</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The CS-POGIL project produced classroom materials for <em>process-oriented guided-inquiry learning (POGIL)</em> in <em>computer science (CS)</em>, particularly for <em>software engineering (SE)</em> and <em>data structures &amp; algorithms (DS&amp;A)</em>. These materials have been used to raise the awareness of POGIL and related techniques among CS educators, and to foster a community to develop and refine POGIL materials and thereby transform CS education.&nbsp;</p> <p>POGIL is an evidence-based approach to learning in which student teams work during class on activities that are specifically designed to guide them to create their own understanding of key concepts and to practice and develop important process skills such as communication, teamwork, critical thinking, and problem solving.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>The CS-POGIL project developed, refined, validated, and disseminated over 80 POGIL activities for CS. Each activity is typically packaged as a set of handouts and worksheets for student teams, along with supporting information such as learning objectives, prerequisites, and suggestions for teachers. Assessment of POGIL activities has been mostly qualitative and informal.</p> <p>We surveyed the CS-POGIL Google Group on their use of POGIL. Responding faculty who had tried POGIL believed that it increases student engagement (92%) and encourages deeper understanding (84%). A majority perceived improvements in students&rsquo; effectiveness in working in small groups, communication skills, and positive peer-to-peer relationships. The greatest obstacle to adopting POGIL was time (both preparation time and classroom time). 71% believed that a closer community would be helpful to new adopters of POGIL, and for regular users of POGIL this percentage increases to 87%.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>The CS-POGIL project produced POGIL materials for adoption by other faculty to improve the quality of CS education. <a href="http://cspogil.org">http://cspogil.org</a> is the project website, using the TikiWiki platform, where faculty can search, upload, download, and comment on activities. The project also fostered a community of CS and SE educators to develop and refine POGIL materials, including a Google Group discussion forum. There are now ~200 publically available POGIL activities for CS, ~60 CS faculty who have attended 3-day POGIL workshops, and several hundred CS faculty who have attended shorter workshops, tutorials, or conference sessions. Faculty have developed, used, or plan to use POGIL activities for CS and related areas at a wide variety of other institutions, including high schools, community colleges, liberal arts colleges, comprehensive institutions, and research universities. Thus, POGIL is now recognized as one of several evidence-based pedagogies that are used in CS.</p> <p>The CS-POGIL project has provided or supported over 30 workshops and tutorials at a variety of professional meetings and other venues. The project has also supported ~40 trips to POGIL Regional Workshops, ~10 trips to POGIL National Meetings, 5 trips to POGIL Facilitator Training, a SIGCSE preconference event, and several project meetings.</p> <p>This project has also led to other significant developments, including: ongoing relationships with STEM faculty across south India; POGIL activities for the AP CS Principles course; the 2015 NSF IUSE OpenPath project to use POGIL to help students prepare to contribute to Humanitarian Free &amp; Open Source Software (HFOSS); and the 2017 NSF IUSE IntroCS-POGIL project to study factors that influence college teachers to adopt POGIL in introductory CS courses, and the resulting impacts on student learning and engagement.</p> <p>The CS-POGIL project is one of several initiatives to extend POGIL practices beyond chemistry, biology, and related disciplines, thereby helping to improve education practices across STEM disciplines. In particular, CS-POGIL activities involving estimation, new product development, and project management may be relatively easy to adapt to other STEM disciplines. We explored some related resources and approaches that may interest the broader POGIL community, and other people interested in related approaches. We developed a Google Doc add-on to generate student and teacher versions of an activity from a single master version. We developed a one page design canvas that gives activity authors an overview of the key elements of their new POGIL activity. We documented effective practices in POGIL as pedagogical patterns, which are general descriptions of effective practices that can facilitate higher-level analysis and discussion.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Clifton&nbsp;L&nbsp;Kussmaul</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The CS-POGIL project produced classroom materials for process-oriented guided-inquiry learning (POGIL) in computer science (CS), particularly for software engineering (SE) and data structures &amp; algorithms (DS&amp;A). These materials have been used to raise the awareness of POGIL and related techniques among CS educators, and to foster a community to develop and refine POGIL materials and thereby transform CS education.   POGIL is an evidence-based approach to learning in which student teams work during class on activities that are specifically designed to guide them to create their own understanding of key concepts and to practice and develop important process skills such as communication, teamwork, critical thinking, and problem solving.  Intellectual Merit  The CS-POGIL project developed, refined, validated, and disseminated over 80 POGIL activities for CS. Each activity is typically packaged as a set of handouts and worksheets for student teams, along with supporting information such as learning objectives, prerequisites, and suggestions for teachers. Assessment of POGIL activities has been mostly qualitative and informal.  We surveyed the CS-POGIL Google Group on their use of POGIL. Responding faculty who had tried POGIL believed that it increases student engagement (92%) and encourages deeper understanding (84%). A majority perceived improvements in students? effectiveness in working in small groups, communication skills, and positive peer-to-peer relationships. The greatest obstacle to adopting POGIL was time (both preparation time and classroom time). 71% believed that a closer community would be helpful to new adopters of POGIL, and for regular users of POGIL this percentage increases to 87%.   Broader Impacts  The CS-POGIL project produced POGIL materials for adoption by other faculty to improve the quality of CS education. http://cspogil.org is the project website, using the TikiWiki platform, where faculty can search, upload, download, and comment on activities. The project also fostered a community of CS and SE educators to develop and refine POGIL materials, including a Google Group discussion forum. There are now ~200 publically available POGIL activities for CS, ~60 CS faculty who have attended 3-day POGIL workshops, and several hundred CS faculty who have attended shorter workshops, tutorials, or conference sessions. Faculty have developed, used, or plan to use POGIL activities for CS and related areas at a wide variety of other institutions, including high schools, community colleges, liberal arts colleges, comprehensive institutions, and research universities. Thus, POGIL is now recognized as one of several evidence-based pedagogies that are used in CS.  The CS-POGIL project has provided or supported over 30 workshops and tutorials at a variety of professional meetings and other venues. The project has also supported ~40 trips to POGIL Regional Workshops, ~10 trips to POGIL National Meetings, 5 trips to POGIL Facilitator Training, a SIGCSE preconference event, and several project meetings.  This project has also led to other significant developments, including: ongoing relationships with STEM faculty across south India; POGIL activities for the AP CS Principles course; the 2015 NSF IUSE OpenPath project to use POGIL to help students prepare to contribute to Humanitarian Free &amp; Open Source Software (HFOSS); and the 2017 NSF IUSE IntroCS-POGIL project to study factors that influence college teachers to adopt POGIL in introductory CS courses, and the resulting impacts on student learning and engagement.  The CS-POGIL project is one of several initiatives to extend POGIL practices beyond chemistry, biology, and related disciplines, thereby helping to improve education practices across STEM disciplines. In particular, CS-POGIL activities involving estimation, new product development, and project management may be relatively easy to adapt to other STEM disciplines. We explored some related resources and approaches that may interest the broader POGIL community, and other people interested in related approaches. We developed a Google Doc add-on to generate student and teacher versions of an activity from a single master version. We developed a one page design canvas that gives activity authors an overview of the key elements of their new POGIL activity. We documented effective practices in POGIL as pedagogical patterns, which are general descriptions of effective practices that can facilitate higher-level analysis and discussion.          Last Modified: 05/08/2017       Submitted by: Clifton L Kussmaul]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
