<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Population ecology of Salpa thompsoni based on molecular indicators</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>776165.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>776165</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christian Fritsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed research targets the molecular genetics of salps, an increasingly important member of the zooplankton in Antarctic waters who's dominance appears to be related to climate warming and sea ice loss.  Specifically the research will examine genome-wide patterns of gene expression, target gene expression levels, and patterns of population genetic diversity and structure underlying the complex life history and population dynamics of S. thompsoni.  The P.I.s hypothesize that (1) deep analysis of the Salpa thompsoni transcriptome will reveal significant associations among selected set of differentially expressed genes and critical life history stages and events (e.g., ontogenetic maturation, sexual reproduction, senescence) of the salp; and 2) the species will show variable levels of clonal diversity and significant genetic differentiation among populations in different regions of the Southern Ocean.  Broader impacts include training of two graduate students; inclusion of undergraduates in research, and in a formal training workshop; development of a summer workshop for high school teachers in collaboration with Connecticut Sea Grant; and public outreach via postings on the Census of Marine Zooplankton homepage.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1044982</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>Bucklin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ann C Bucklin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ann.bucklin@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604059260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000334405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Neill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel J O'Neill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rachel.oneill@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604866031</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Payne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diana L Payne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>diana.payne@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604059248</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000081424</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[438 Whitney Road Ext.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5111</Code>
<Text>ANT Organisms &amp; Ecosystems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>High Risk/Reward Innovative Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~776165</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Overview</p> <p>The Southern Ocean salp, <em>Salpa thompsoni </em>(Tunicata, Thaliacea) is a pivotal species in the pelagic ecosystem of the Western Antarctic Peninsula (WAP), one of the fastest warming regions of the world oceans. This study produced the first reference genome and reference transcriptome for <em>S. thompsoni</em>. The genomic resources provide a significant step forward in the development of  the salp as a model species for studying urochordate evolution;  adaptation to a polar, planktonic environment; and the molecular  processes underlying organism-environment interactions of this species. The transcriptomic resources will allow improved mechanistic understanding and prediction of impacts and consequences of environmental variation and climate change on the population dynamics and adaptation potential of this key species in the Southern Ocean pelagic ecosystem. Overall, the <em>S. thompsoni</em> reference genome and transcriptome provide important reference points for the continued understanding of the adaptive evolution of polar and planktonic species, as well as the elucidation of the underlying biology of an important group of chordate-related organisms.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>We have also assembled the first draft genome sequence for <em>S. thompsoni,</em> as well as the first estimates of genome size and gene predictions for  this species. This assembly, while still in need of further study and  more data, was used to establish an extensive resource of gene,  repetitive element, and small RNA gene predictions. The genomic data  have established significant resources for both further phylogenomic and  population genetic studies. Patterns in protein divergence in S.  thompsoni appear to confirm the urochordate characteristic of elevated  rates of genome evolution, indicating that urochordates may be  particularly responsive to selective pressures. For instance, genome  size, repetitive element content and patterns of positive selection in  ribosomal genes indicate that expansion of rDNA gene families is  extensive in this species, and and may be related to metabolic  adaptations to polar environments. Additionally, the rapid evolution of  the variably expressed gene cyclophilin A supports the functional  importance of immune gene in urochordate biology, specifically the  unusual complex life history, with both solitary and colonial stages.  This rate of evolutionary change is also notable in the small RNA  repertoire of this species that is characterized by both conserved and  novel miRNAs implicated in embryonic development, as well as a possibly  novel piRNA biogenesis mechanism.</p> <p>The <em>S. thompsoni</em> reference transcriptome contains 216,931 sequences; 41,210 (18%) were associated with predicted, hypothetical, or known proteins; 13,058 (6%) were mapped and annotated. The new data will provide a foundation for  functional  analysis and identification of  molecular markers of  physiological  condition and life history events. Whole-transcriptome (RNA-seq) analysis of 39 samples collected during austral spring and summer 2011 in the WAP, and in summer 2009 in the Indian Sector revealed clustering of samples by regions, seasons, and areas. Patterns of differential gene expression revealed notable differences between salp samples collected from different regions, seasons, and areas of the Southern Ocean. A primary result was the finding of highest numbers of significantly differentially expressed genes between spring and summer 2011 collections from the Western Antarctic Peninsula (WAP) region. This difference was also reflected by high levels of differential expression for 77 genes associated with environmental stress response and 51 genes associated with sexual reproduction. Gene Ontology (GO) term enrichment analysis of salps collected during spring versus summer in the WAP showed 41 GO terms responsible for the changes in gene expression pattern between the spring and summer seasons.</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>Outreach and education activities included three experiential workshops for high school teachers (2012, 2013, 2015), which provided foundations for new learning goals and new curriculum elements related to the molecular analysis of marine organisms. Hands-on exercises included DNA barcoding and DNA sequence analysis; lectures and discussions focused on impacts of climate change, global warming, ocean acidification, and disruption of biological communities. A fourth workshop (2016) for high school students (accompanied by their teachers) was held to directly evaluate resulting curriculum modules. Our assessment process indicated that our workshops may have impacted 200 &ndash; 400 students, who were exposed to novel classroom, laboratory, and computer exercises in science education.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Ann&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bucklin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  The Southern Ocean salp, Salpa thompsoni (Tunicata, Thaliacea) is a pivotal species in the pelagic ecosystem of the Western Antarctic Peninsula (WAP), one of the fastest warming regions of the world oceans. This study produced the first reference genome and reference transcriptome for S. thompsoni. The genomic resources provide a significant step forward in the development of  the salp as a model species for studying urochordate evolution;  adaptation to a polar, planktonic environment; and the molecular  processes underlying organism-environment interactions of this species. The transcriptomic resources will allow improved mechanistic understanding and prediction of impacts and consequences of environmental variation and climate change on the population dynamics and adaptation potential of this key species in the Southern Ocean pelagic ecosystem. Overall, the S. thompsoni reference genome and transcriptome provide important reference points for the continued understanding of the adaptive evolution of polar and planktonic species, as well as the elucidation of the underlying biology of an important group of chordate-related organisms.   Intellectual Merit  We have also assembled the first draft genome sequence for S. thompsoni, as well as the first estimates of genome size and gene predictions for  this species. This assembly, while still in need of further study and  more data, was used to establish an extensive resource of gene,  repetitive element, and small RNA gene predictions. The genomic data  have established significant resources for both further phylogenomic and  population genetic studies. Patterns in protein divergence in S.  thompsoni appear to confirm the urochordate characteristic of elevated  rates of genome evolution, indicating that urochordates may be  particularly responsive to selective pressures. For instance, genome  size, repetitive element content and patterns of positive selection in  ribosomal genes indicate that expansion of rDNA gene families is  extensive in this species, and and may be related to metabolic  adaptations to polar environments. Additionally, the rapid evolution of  the variably expressed gene cyclophilin A supports the functional  importance of immune gene in urochordate biology, specifically the  unusual complex life history, with both solitary and colonial stages.  This rate of evolutionary change is also notable in the small RNA  repertoire of this species that is characterized by both conserved and  novel miRNAs implicated in embryonic development, as well as a possibly  novel piRNA biogenesis mechanism.  The S. thompsoni reference transcriptome contains 216,931 sequences; 41,210 (18%) were associated with predicted, hypothetical, or known proteins; 13,058 (6%) were mapped and annotated. The new data will provide a foundation for  functional  analysis and identification of  molecular markers of  physiological  condition and life history events. Whole-transcriptome (RNA-seq) analysis of 39 samples collected during austral spring and summer 2011 in the WAP, and in summer 2009 in the Indian Sector revealed clustering of samples by regions, seasons, and areas. Patterns of differential gene expression revealed notable differences between salp samples collected from different regions, seasons, and areas of the Southern Ocean. A primary result was the finding of highest numbers of significantly differentially expressed genes between spring and summer 2011 collections from the Western Antarctic Peninsula (WAP) region. This difference was also reflected by high levels of differential expression for 77 genes associated with environmental stress response and 51 genes associated with sexual reproduction. Gene Ontology (GO) term enrichment analysis of salps collected during spring versus summer in the WAP showed 41 GO terms responsible for the changes in gene expression pattern between the spring and summer seasons.  Broader Impacts  Outreach and education activities included three experiential workshops for high school teachers (2012, 2013, 2015), which provided foundations for new learning goals and new curriculum elements related to the molecular analysis of marine organisms. Hands-on exercises included DNA barcoding and DNA sequence analysis; lectures and discussions focused on impacts of climate change, global warming, ocean acidification, and disruption of biological communities. A fourth workshop (2016) for high school students (accompanied by their teachers) was held to directly evaluate resulting curriculum modules. Our assessment process indicated that our workshops may have impacted 200 &ndash; 400 students, who were exposed to novel classroom, laboratory, and computer exercises in science education.       Last Modified: 08/29/2016       Submitted by: Ann C Bucklin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
