<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Project PLURIS: Purposeful Learning in Undergraduate Research and Independent Studies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199841.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199841</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Zia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lzia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925140</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is creating a "brokering system" to mediate the interaction among faculty and students who want first to identify topics of mutual interest for independent study and/or research experiences, then to explore what questions to consider, and finally to negotiate a formal agreement on what the project would entail. The Purposeful Learning in Undergraduate Research and Independent Studies (PLURIS) system helps: i) to align individual student learning agendas with the goals of supervising faculty; ii) to clarify the intended student learning outcomes; iii) to monitor and document actual learning outcomes; and iv) to make public the learning achievements of the students. The intellectual merit of the project lies in its "community-based co-design" approach in which faculty and students are iteratively developing and testing components of this model system. This development approach carries into the way that PLURIS enables faculty and students to negotiate intended learning outcomes, reflecting the critical collaborative discourse essential to science. The project's broader impacts include: the modeling of collaboration among scientists, educators, and educational technology professionals that develops the science education expertise of STEM faculty, and the provision of a means for undergraduate, postdoctoral, and faculty researchers to think meta-cognitively about research experiences and learning in general. Furthermore, through its approach that links rich learning experiences of undergraduate independent research studies with specific measurable outcomes the project seeks to improve the cost-effectiveness and academic consistency of STEM independent study courses and research activities, so that larger and more diverse numbers of students may take advantage of these high-impact activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1044460</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathy</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathy S Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kathy.williams@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6195944358</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000377196</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brock</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brock S Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brock.allen@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6192823400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000503956</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073371346</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921151338</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5300 Campanile Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~199841</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PLURIS (Purposeful Learning for Undergraduate Research and Independent Studies) system is assisting faculty and students to design STEM undergraduate research and independent study experiences by building learning agendas that clarify purposeful and intentional learning. Learning agendas identify what needs to be learned before a project or task can be planned and implemented. By clarifying learning expectations, we expect to improve the cost-effectiveness, academic consistency, and auditability of these valuable courses and activities, so they can be offered to more students.</p> <p>The PLURIS system was designed to help (1) elucidate opportunities for learning in host projects and recruit students, (2) clarify intended student learning outcomes by students and faculty, (3) align individual student learning agendas with goals of supervising faculty, and (4) build a community of professionals engaged in high-impact learning activities (HILAs) for undergraduates, especially in STEM disciplines.</p> <p>Using focus groups of students and faculty to revise and improve the system, we developed an online survey instrument called the PLURIS Student Profile Builder. The online Profile Builder focused on engaging students in developing learning agendas as it leads them to purposefully identify and describe their learning goals, to contextualize their reasons for seeking a STEM undergraduate research or independent study experiences. In addition to soliciting basic information such as major and class standing, the Profile Builder challenges students to rank work-related values, interests, and activities, using about 60 items. Students rank values like efficiency, flexibility, innovation, teamwork, results, and personal learning. Other rankings are based on preferences for work activities such as processing information, making decisions, negotiating, coaching, building teams, controlling processes, or repairing and maintaining equipment. Students rank their perceived importance of these items and designate values and capacities they want to develop further. Then they are invited to explain highly ranked items. Another Profile Builder section challenges students to write examples of research questions they might like to discuss with prospective research mentors, graduate advisors, or employers. Ultimately, the Profile Builder guides students in authoring examples of specific learning outcomes they would like to pursue during HILAs such as research, internships, community service, or travel. Based on their declared major, the Profile Builder automatically links each student to appropriate listings in the Occupational Information Network (O*NET) database (US Department of Labor/Employment and Training Administration; onetonline.org), which lists thousands of occupation-related capacities associated with college majors. O*NET is the nation's primary source of occupational information and it allowed automating and increasing the capacities of the PLURIS process more than originally proposed.</p> <p>Once students complete a profile, the Profile Builder emails a report of their responses they can discuss with academic advisers, peers, or parents and use as a resource preparing for job and graduate school applications and interviews. In the local pilot, students could have profile information included in a database available to faculty or staff involved in finding or supervising research opportunities for undergraduates. This provides a unique set of relevant characteristics by which faculty can identify diverse students who might excel in supervised research that might not receive such opportunities if grades alone were used. This resulted in successful connections being made, and career centers may be able to deploy the system more widely.</p> <p>Participating faculty members (and in the future, campus partners such as employers or community services hosts) complete an abbreviated &ldquo;Faculty Profile Builder&rdquo; based on the types of students they are recruiting and types of opportunities they have to offer. Resulting faculty/host profiles may provide content for developing announcements for those opportunities, syllabi for those activities, and job descriptions.</p> <p>Finally, we tested a major prediction of this project &ndash; that students who clearly state their learning agendas when presenting research results will be perceived by experts as &ldquo;learning more&rdquo; than students with similar quality projects, but who only describe procedural activities conducted. Initial results from Honors freshmen supported that prediction, so we explored responses of faculty and graduate research supervisors. A team of student researchers helped develop and deploy an online survey to present similar research situations, differing only in student descriptions of results and learning gains from the experience. Responses from over 100 invited prospective/current mentors showed similar results &ndash; that mentors valued experiences more and perceived learning gains to be greater for students who described their experience in the context of learning agendas rather than procedural accomplishments.</p> <p>As the national movement towards outcomes-based assessment in higher education is promoted by accrediting and governmental agencies, we expect the general PLURIS paradigm to be widely adaptable to STEM internships, civic engagement projects, and international travel. Purposefully clarifying learning goals and explicating achievements from undergraduate research and independent studies is central to the PLURIS process, and these findings demonstrate the value of using the PLURIS process to help students and faculty gain recognition for the learning accomplished in many types of high-impact activities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Kathy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Williams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PLURIS (Purposeful Learning for Undergraduate Research and Independent Studies) system is assisting faculty and students to design STEM undergraduate research and independent study experiences by building learning agendas that clarify purposeful and intentional learning. Learning agendas identify what needs to be learned before a project or task can be planned and implemented. By clarifying learning expectations, we expect to improve the cost-effectiveness, academic consistency, and auditability of these valuable courses and activities, so they can be offered to more students.  The PLURIS system was designed to help (1) elucidate opportunities for learning in host projects and recruit students, (2) clarify intended student learning outcomes by students and faculty, (3) align individual student learning agendas with goals of supervising faculty, and (4) build a community of professionals engaged in high-impact learning activities (HILAs) for undergraduates, especially in STEM disciplines.  Using focus groups of students and faculty to revise and improve the system, we developed an online survey instrument called the PLURIS Student Profile Builder. The online Profile Builder focused on engaging students in developing learning agendas as it leads them to purposefully identify and describe their learning goals, to contextualize their reasons for seeking a STEM undergraduate research or independent study experiences. In addition to soliciting basic information such as major and class standing, the Profile Builder challenges students to rank work-related values, interests, and activities, using about 60 items. Students rank values like efficiency, flexibility, innovation, teamwork, results, and personal learning. Other rankings are based on preferences for work activities such as processing information, making decisions, negotiating, coaching, building teams, controlling processes, or repairing and maintaining equipment. Students rank their perceived importance of these items and designate values and capacities they want to develop further. Then they are invited to explain highly ranked items. Another Profile Builder section challenges students to write examples of research questions they might like to discuss with prospective research mentors, graduate advisors, or employers. Ultimately, the Profile Builder guides students in authoring examples of specific learning outcomes they would like to pursue during HILAs such as research, internships, community service, or travel. Based on their declared major, the Profile Builder automatically links each student to appropriate listings in the Occupational Information Network (O*NET) database (US Department of Labor/Employment and Training Administration; onetonline.org), which lists thousands of occupation-related capacities associated with college majors. O*NET is the nation's primary source of occupational information and it allowed automating and increasing the capacities of the PLURIS process more than originally proposed.  Once students complete a profile, the Profile Builder emails a report of their responses they can discuss with academic advisers, peers, or parents and use as a resource preparing for job and graduate school applications and interviews. In the local pilot, students could have profile information included in a database available to faculty or staff involved in finding or supervising research opportunities for undergraduates. This provides a unique set of relevant characteristics by which faculty can identify diverse students who might excel in supervised research that might not receive such opportunities if grades alone were used. This resulted in successful connections being made, and career centers may be able to deploy the system more widely.  Participating faculty members (and in the future, campus partners such as employers or community services hosts) complete an abbreviated "Faculty Profile Builder" based on the types of students they are recruiting and types of opportunities they have to offer. Resulting faculty/host profiles may provide content for developing announcements for those opportunities, syllabi for those activities, and job descriptions.  Finally, we tested a major prediction of this project &ndash; that students who clearly state their learning agendas when presenting research results will be perceived by experts as "learning more" than students with similar quality projects, but who only describe procedural activities conducted. Initial results from Honors freshmen supported that prediction, so we explored responses of faculty and graduate research supervisors. A team of student researchers helped develop and deploy an online survey to present similar research situations, differing only in student descriptions of results and learning gains from the experience. Responses from over 100 invited prospective/current mentors showed similar results &ndash; that mentors valued experiences more and perceived learning gains to be greater for students who described their experience in the context of learning agendas rather than procedural accomplishments.  As the national movement towards outcomes-based assessment in higher education is promoted by accrediting and governmental agencies, we expect the general PLURIS paradigm to be widely adaptable to STEM internships, civic engagement projects, and international travel. Purposefully clarifying learning goals and explicating achievements from undergraduate research and independent studies is central to the PLURIS process, and these findings demonstrate the value of using the PLURIS process to help students and faculty gain recognition for the learning accomplished in many types of high-impact activities.       Last Modified: 05/13/2018       Submitted by: Kathy S Williams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
