<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Evaluating how the sampling integration scale affects field estimates of groundwater transit time and nitrogen fluxes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>230998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>230998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030109</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The transit time of groundwater, from recharge at the water table to discharge at streams, is a fundamental aquifer characteristic relevant to rates of contaminant transport in groundwater and other aspects of water resource management.  The project goal is a rigorous quantitative comparison of three novel approaches for estimating each of three variables related to transit time and non-point-source nitrate contamination:  (a) the mean transit time (MTT) of groundwater in aquifers, (b) the magnitude of water and nitrate flux from aquifers to streams, and (c) the amount of nitrate degradation occurring in groundwater prior to seepage into streams.  Each of the three approaches is based on groundwater and stream hydrologic and tracer measurements, however, the data collection methods and analysis strategies differ greatly. A side-by-side evaluation of the approaches elucidating strengths and limitations does not exist and will be completed by this project in two streams in an agricultural region of the N.C. Coastal Plain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will take place in the Neuse River watershed, site of an ambitious basin-wide regulatory effort by the state of N.C. to reduce nitrogen (N) contamination and associated harmful algal blooms and fish kills in the Neuse River estuary.  Several years of effort have not reduced estuarine N input. Groundwater transit times for N, which can extend for decades, are potentially an important contributing factor.  By comparing three novel approaches to measuring MTT, nitrate flux, and nitrate degradation, this project will better define the pros and cons of the approaches.  The results will provide practical guidance to improve assessment strategies applicable to water resource and land management.  The project will provide advanced hydrologic training for students at two universities (N.C. State and the Univ. of Utah), and practical results and insight for state regulators dealing with non-point-source pollutants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1045134</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>D. Kip</FirstName>
<LastName>Solomon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>D. Kip Solomon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kip.solomon@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015817231</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423309</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/04/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75 S 2000 E]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~86900</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~87961</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~56137</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When precipitation infiltrates the land surface it can migrate downward to the water table and then move laterally towards springs and seeps and into streams.&nbsp; The elapsed time for this water to move from the water table to discharge into streams is known as the groundwater transit time.&nbsp; This transit is highly variable ranging from days to millennia.&nbsp; As a result, the movement of chemicals derived from agricultural and industrial activities that travel with this water is also highly variable.&nbsp; In this project we developed a practical method for estimating this travel time and in turn for evaluating the impacts of changing agricultural and industrial activities on the quality of stream flow.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We evaluated the groundwater transit time and its relationship to the transport of nitrogen in the coastal plain of North Carolina.&nbsp; Elevated concentrations of nitrate in streams have persisted in this region in spite of recent reductions in use of nitrogen-based fertilizers.&nbsp; We hypothesized that a lag between reductions in nitrogen application and decreases in stream concentrations is partly a result of the groundwater transit time.&nbsp; In order to understand the link between reductions in fertilizer application and improvements in the water quality of streams, we evaluated the average and the range of transit times using a variety of sampling methods that integrate (lump) over various spatial scales.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The mean transit time is a fundamental property of a groundwater flow system that is related to the rate of recharge and the volume of water stored within the aquifer.&nbsp; We employed groundwater age-dating technology that utilizes the concentration of trace substance present in all precipitation to estimate ages (transit times).&nbsp; We studied both the mean transit time and the range of transit times in West Bear Creek, North Carolina and in the surrounding shallow aquifer.&nbsp; Groundwater seepage to the stream was quantified using the dilution of an injected Br tracer, stream velocity measurements, seepage meters, and calculated using hydraulic data from discrete measuring points in the streambed.&nbsp; Seepage mats, a dilution flow meter, and a tube flow meter are all new technologies that were invented as part of our study.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Age-dating tracers (CFCs, SF<sub>6</sub>, <sup>3</sup>H-<sup>3</sup>He) were measured in multi-level monitoring wells, in streambed piezometers (wells), seepage meters, and stream samples. Discrete samples from streambed piezometers have concentrations from multiple age-dating tracers suggesting that mixing of a wide range of groundwater ages was not occurring as groundwater flow paths converged below the streambed.&nbsp; The mean transit time from streambed samples was 30 &plusmn; 5 years with more than 80% of the groundwater discharge having a transit time between 20 And 40 years.&nbsp; A very similar mean transit time was obtained from well samples and from stream water samples that are corrected for exchange with the atmosphere.&nbsp; Our findings suggest that only modest improvements in stream water quality can be expected within the first 20 years after reducing the amount of nitrogen fertilizers applied to the West Bear Creek watershed, but major improvements can be expected within 40 years.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our study has shown, for the first time, that the flow-weighted cumulative distribution of apparent ages from streambed samples can be modeled with a gamma distribution having a shape factor (&alpha;) that is greater than 1.&nbsp; Numerical modeling of some ideal cases indicates that spatial variations in recharge might be discerned from the cumulative transit time distribution with &alpha;&nbsp;&gt;1 for recharge concentrated away from a stream and &alpha;&nbsp;&lt; 1 for recharge concentrated near the stream.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>West Bear...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When precipitation infiltrates the land surface it can migrate downward to the water table and then move laterally towards springs and seeps and into streams.  The elapsed time for this water to move from the water table to discharge into streams is known as the groundwater transit time.  This transit is highly variable ranging from days to millennia.  As a result, the movement of chemicals derived from agricultural and industrial activities that travel with this water is also highly variable.  In this project we developed a practical method for estimating this travel time and in turn for evaluating the impacts of changing agricultural and industrial activities on the quality of stream flow.     We evaluated the groundwater transit time and its relationship to the transport of nitrogen in the coastal plain of North Carolina.  Elevated concentrations of nitrate in streams have persisted in this region in spite of recent reductions in use of nitrogen-based fertilizers.  We hypothesized that a lag between reductions in nitrogen application and decreases in stream concentrations is partly a result of the groundwater transit time.  In order to understand the link between reductions in fertilizer application and improvements in the water quality of streams, we evaluated the average and the range of transit times using a variety of sampling methods that integrate (lump) over various spatial scales.     The mean transit time is a fundamental property of a groundwater flow system that is related to the rate of recharge and the volume of water stored within the aquifer.  We employed groundwater age-dating technology that utilizes the concentration of trace substance present in all precipitation to estimate ages (transit times).  We studied both the mean transit time and the range of transit times in West Bear Creek, North Carolina and in the surrounding shallow aquifer.  Groundwater seepage to the stream was quantified using the dilution of an injected Br tracer, stream velocity measurements, seepage meters, and calculated using hydraulic data from discrete measuring points in the streambed.  Seepage mats, a dilution flow meter, and a tube flow meter are all new technologies that were invented as part of our study.     Age-dating tracers (CFCs, SF6, 3H-3He) were measured in multi-level monitoring wells, in streambed piezometers (wells), seepage meters, and stream samples. Discrete samples from streambed piezometers have concentrations from multiple age-dating tracers suggesting that mixing of a wide range of groundwater ages was not occurring as groundwater flow paths converged below the streambed.  The mean transit time from streambed samples was 30 &plusmn; 5 years with more than 80% of the groundwater discharge having a transit time between 20 And 40 years.  A very similar mean transit time was obtained from well samples and from stream water samples that are corrected for exchange with the atmosphere.  Our findings suggest that only modest improvements in stream water quality can be expected within the first 20 years after reducing the amount of nitrogen fertilizers applied to the West Bear Creek watershed, but major improvements can be expected within 40 years.     Our study has shown, for the first time, that the flow-weighted cumulative distribution of apparent ages from streambed samples can be modeled with a gamma distribution having a shape factor (&alpha;) that is greater than 1.  Numerical modeling of some ideal cases indicates that spatial variations in recharge might be discerned from the cumulative transit time distribution with &alpha; &gt;1 for recharge concentrated away from a stream and &alpha; &lt; 1 for recharge concentrated near the stream.     West Bear Creek appears to act as a flow weighted integrator of transit times and samples from the stream and streambed can provide fundamental information regarding properties of the contributing aquifer.  Our finding that age-dating tracers measured on stream samples can ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
