<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International: Research Experience for US Students at INRIA - REUSSI 2</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sol Greenspan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgreensp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927841</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The REUSSI-2 project funds US graduate student research internships at INRIA, the premier Computer Science research institute in France. The project is made possible by co-funding between the NSF Office of International Science and Engineering and the Directorate of Computer and Information Science and Engineering. The program will support 10 to 20 US student internships each year. Each selected student is expected to spend at least two summer months and at most six months working at INRIA.  INRIA pays each student a stipend and the INRIA scientists mentor and guide the student's research during the internship. INRIA also provides students with health insurance during their internships. NSF funds cover the travel costs and costs associated with getting students to the annual summer research colloquium held during the time they are in France. A call for internship applications is published in October of each year. The call is also sent via email to US universities with graduate research programs, including universities with a high proportion of students from under-represented groups. Each applicant has to contact the INRIA site that posted the internship opportunity prior to applying in order to obtain INRIA support for the application. Furthermore, each student applicant must be nominated by his/her adviser and must state how the visit will enhance his/her graduate work. Each application must include a brief description of the proposed internship work. The description must be developed in consultation with the INRIA scientists and must include a statement asserting that the INRIA scientists commit to mentoring the student during the internship period. Submitted applications are evaluated by the REUSSI-2 PI with the help of representatives from INRIA sites that the students apply to visit. Final selections will be made by the REUSSI-2 PI in consultation with the INRIA International Relations Office. Selected students and the respective INRIA teams will be informed in mid to late-December.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Computer Science projects currently covered by participating US institutions tackle complex problems in areas such as computer graphics, computational brain anatomy, rigorous modeling and analysis of critical software systems, computational MRI, next generation wireless networks, quantum computing, and ocean modeling. Participating students have the opportunity to develop international research links that can be further strengthened and leveraged in their research careers. These collaborations and student exchanges help to nurture a spirit of international cooperation which, through exchange of high quality ideas, can yield significant insights into some of the more challenging Computer Science research problems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1045885</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjay</FirstName>
<LastName>Rajopadhye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjay Rajopadhye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Sanjay.Rajopadhye@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704917323</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423826</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>France</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert B France</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>france@cs.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704916356</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000476127</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/09/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sudipto</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghosh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sudipto Ghosh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ghosh@cs.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704914608</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000392748</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S Howes St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7731</Code>
<Text>Other Global Learning &amp; Trng</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5918</Code>
<Text>FRANCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project funded US graduate student summer internships at INRIA, a premier European Computer Science Research institution in France distributed over multiple sites and with multiple research groups (called teams/projects). Students were selected from US institutions with research projects funded by INRIA's competitive Associated Team program, and also through an open call to US faculty with active collaborations with INRIA researchers.&nbsp;INRIA paid each student a stipend to patially cover lodging and boarding expenses, and NSF funds covered the travel costs. &nbsp;The French PIs mentored and guided the student's research during the internship. &nbsp;INRIA also provided students with health insurance during their internships. &nbsp;NSF funds covered the travel and some housing costs. &nbsp;In the final two years, the scope of the project was extended to support, in addition to the summer internships, travel by US graduate students to specialized spring/winter schools organized by INRIA affiliated researchers.</p> <p>A total of 27 student visits were supported by the program. &nbsp;Students from&nbsp;Carnegie Mellon University, Colorado State University, Florida International University, George Mason University, Georgia Institute of Technology, Harvard University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Northeastern University, Stanford University, University of California - San Diego, University of California - Santa Cruz, University of Chicago, University of Delaware, University of Florida, University of Minnesota, University of Texas, Dallas, University of Utah, and&nbsp;Wright State University, Dayton participated. They&nbsp;went to various INRIA centres: Grenoble, Sophia, Rennes, Rocquencourt, and Saclay.</p> <p>The results (intellectual merit) of the visits usually led to joint publications, and fostered collaborations between US and INRIA researchers. &nbsp;A majority of them were pre-existing collaborations, that REUSSI funds enhanced, while in a number of cases, new collaborations between US and INRIA groups developed as a result of the internships. Research topics were diverse, such as (1)&nbsp;depth perception in direct volumetric rendering, (2) design of super lenses, (3) logic, specification, reasoning, and theorem provers, and (4) polyhedral compilation.</p> <p>Interns had an opportunity to experience the French academic/research culture and get exposure to cutting edge French research groups (broader impact).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2017<br>      Modified by: Sanjay&nbsp;Rajopadhye</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project funded US graduate student summer internships at INRIA, a premier European Computer Science Research institution in France distributed over multiple sites and with multiple research groups (called teams/projects). Students were selected from US institutions with research projects funded by INRIA's competitive Associated Team program, and also through an open call to US faculty with active collaborations with INRIA researchers. INRIA paid each student a stipend to patially cover lodging and boarding expenses, and NSF funds covered the travel costs.  The French PIs mentored and guided the student's research during the internship.  INRIA also provided students with health insurance during their internships.  NSF funds covered the travel and some housing costs.  In the final two years, the scope of the project was extended to support, in addition to the summer internships, travel by US graduate students to specialized spring/winter schools organized by INRIA affiliated researchers.  A total of 27 student visits were supported by the program.  Students from Carnegie Mellon University, Colorado State University, Florida International University, George Mason University, Georgia Institute of Technology, Harvard University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Northeastern University, Stanford University, University of California - San Diego, University of California - Santa Cruz, University of Chicago, University of Delaware, University of Florida, University of Minnesota, University of Texas, Dallas, University of Utah, and Wright State University, Dayton participated. They went to various INRIA centres: Grenoble, Sophia, Rennes, Rocquencourt, and Saclay.  The results (intellectual merit) of the visits usually led to joint publications, and fostered collaborations between US and INRIA researchers.  A majority of them were pre-existing collaborations, that REUSSI funds enhanced, while in a number of cases, new collaborations between US and INRIA groups developed as a result of the internships. Research topics were diverse, such as (1) depth perception in direct volumetric rendering, (2) design of super lenses, (3) logic, specification, reasoning, and theorem provers, and (4) polyhedral compilation.  Interns had an opportunity to experience the French academic/research culture and get exposure to cutting edge French research groups (broader impact).       Last Modified: 11/23/2017       Submitted by: Sanjay Rajopadhye]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
