<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A Batteryless Wireless Impedance Sensor System For Gastroesophageal Reflux Diagnosis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project explores advanced technologies to develop a transformative miniature batteryless wireless impedance sensor that is suitable for endoscopic implantation through the mouth and esophagus for the comfort and convenience of patients in the diagnosis and prognosis of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD). An implantable miniature batteryless wireless device that does not require externally tethered connections and has the ability to detect acid and nonacid episodes is preferred for esophageal reflux monitoring by both patients and doctors. The proposed system consists of a miniature nanowire-based sensor which can be attached on esophagus wall for a long period of time and an external wearable reader. The impedance variations from the sensor can indicate episodes of reflux that are both acidic and non-acidic in nature. The intellectual merits in this project include the optimization of wireless power transfer efficiency for human implant applications, low-power circuitry design and miniature device fabrication/packaging, sensor surface modification with silicon nanowires, and characterization of the entire wireless sensor system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will enhance greatly the scientific and technological understanding of passive wireless communication for miniature medical implants, improve healthcare procedures, reduce healthcare costs, and enable accurate measurements for regular screening methods to prevent the occurrence of incurable esophageal cancers. The proposed system provides an innovative and practical solution for gastroesophageal reflux monitoring with advantages of batteryless operation, portable wireless communication, impedance sensing method, and miniature size enabling comfortable endoscopic implantation. With these advantages, clinicians can precisely diagnose reflux with electronic records showing quantitative data with cost-effective and out-patient procedures that can be used for large population and potentially periodic screening. With 19 million adults who have consistent reflux symptoms in US and the global aging population, the proposed system for diagnosis and prognosis will have a significant impact on healthcare procedures and costs. With improved comfort level and accuracy, the system will enable regular screening procedures in clinics which in return offer a great commercial potential with a sustainable market size. The technology development also addresses commercial potentials for applications and manufacturing of semiconductor chips in miniature medical implants and portable wireless electronics in body sensor networking</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1046488</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Smitha</FirstName>
<LastName>Rao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Smitha Rao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smithar@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873230</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000564976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Talus Atomics Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Grand Prairie</CityName>
<ZipCode>750508325</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9726027922</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2432 Kingsley Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>961435146</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TALUS ATOMICS CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Talus Atomics Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Grand Prairie</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750508325</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2432 Kingsley Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; DEVICE TEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7257</Code>
<Text>APPLICATS OF ADVANCED TECHNOLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9139</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This SBIR Phase I project explored advanced technologies to develop a transformative miniature batteryless wireless impedance sensor that is suitable for endoscopic implantation through the mouth and esophagus for the comfort and convenience of patients in the diagnosis and prognosis of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD). The Phase I project addressed critical engineering elements in the research and development of the proposed batteryless endoluminal sensing telemeter (BEST<sup>TM</sup>) system architecture. We have demonstrated the feasibility and performance of the implantable batteryless wireless impedance sensor system in the Phase I period. <strong>Intellectual Merits</strong> that have been accomplished in the Phase I include: optimization of wireless power transfer efficiency for human implant applications, low-power circuitry design and miniature device fabrication/packaging, fabrication and Integration of nanowire impedance electrodes, characterization of the entire sensor system, development of the signal driver circuitry and the implementation of wireless module hardware, programming of the user interface and microcontroller functionality, and characterization of the wireless modules. The tasks were all accomplished. The <strong>Broader Impacts </strong>include impacts on both the healthcare fields and sensor fields. The demonstrated system provides a unique and practical solution for gastroesophageal reflux monitoring with advantages of batteryless operation, portable wireless communication, impedance sensing method, and miniature size enabling comfortable endoscopic implantation. With these advantages, clinicians can precisely diagnose the reflux with electronic records showing quantitative data with cost-effective and out-patient procedures that can be used for large population and potentially periodic screening. As broader impacts for society, since GERD has been recognized as a prime risk factor for esophagus cancers which often are incurable, accurate and regular screening could identify early symptoms with proper treatment for GERD in order to prevent the development of cancers. The miniature devices and sensing systems address many market opportunities motivated by the national and international initiatives to reduce healthcare costs. The markets also include nonclinical sensors that could be used in defense and industrial applications.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2012<br>      Modified by: Smitha&nbsp;Rao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This SBIR Phase I project explored advanced technologies to develop a transformative miniature batteryless wireless impedance sensor that is suitable for endoscopic implantation through the mouth and esophagus for the comfort and convenience of patients in the diagnosis and prognosis of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD). The Phase I project addressed critical engineering elements in the research and development of the proposed batteryless endoluminal sensing telemeter (BESTTM) system architecture. We have demonstrated the feasibility and performance of the implantable batteryless wireless impedance sensor system in the Phase I period. Intellectual Merits that have been accomplished in the Phase I include: optimization of wireless power transfer efficiency for human implant applications, low-power circuitry design and miniature device fabrication/packaging, fabrication and Integration of nanowire impedance electrodes, characterization of the entire sensor system, development of the signal driver circuitry and the implementation of wireless module hardware, programming of the user interface and microcontroller functionality, and characterization of the wireless modules. The tasks were all accomplished. The Broader Impacts include impacts on both the healthcare fields and sensor fields. The demonstrated system provides a unique and practical solution for gastroesophageal reflux monitoring with advantages of batteryless operation, portable wireless communication, impedance sensing method, and miniature size enabling comfortable endoscopic implantation. With these advantages, clinicians can precisely diagnose the reflux with electronic records showing quantitative data with cost-effective and out-patient procedures that can be used for large population and potentially periodic screening. As broader impacts for society, since GERD has been recognized as a prime risk factor for esophagus cancers which often are incurable, accurate and regular screening could identify early symptoms with proper treatment for GERD in order to prevent the development of cancers. The miniature devices and sensing systems address many market opportunities motivated by the national and international initiatives to reduce healthcare costs. The markets also include nonclinical sensors that could be used in defense and industrial applications.       Last Modified: 01/30/2012       Submitted by: Smitha Rao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
