<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Acoustic Slurry Monitor</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase-I project is to develop an acoustic CMP (Chemical Mechanical Polishing) slurry monitor?a fully in-line, real-time, point of use instrument that will detect and disperse any and all large agglomerates in the nanofine slurries used in IC manufacture.  Left unchecked, these errant slurry particles/ agglomerates can "kill" (deeply scratch) a semiconductor wafer as it undergoes chemical mechanical planarizing or polishing.  CMP has become the method of choice for restoring the surface trueness of wafers at all stages of IC manufacture. This acoustic slurry monitor makes use of a novel technology?Acoustic Coaxing Induced Microcavitation (ACIM), a means of constructively controlling acoustic microcavitation.  It does so by facilitating controlled bubble nucleation preferentially on the large particle, in the midst of dense nano-fine slurry.  This research is thus aimed at investigating a new principle of bubble nucleation. In operation the slurry monitor will inspect a 100ml of the slurry charge at final dispense point just before the slurry is fed to the polishing pad.  It will complete the detection for large particles in fully dense CMP slurry in one minute.  This slurry monitor can be mounted on the existing CMP tools. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project are to enable improved yields in semiconductor manufacturing by making CMP processing scratch free. No method currently exists that can implement a CMP-safe slurry at the point of use. An advanced device wafer scratched at the final stages of manufacture is a direct loss of $250k or more.  Use of the Acoustic Slurry Monitor protects wafers and more than returns the $100k investment with the very first wafer it saves. The Slurry Monitor is a yield protecting tool reliably improving CMP performance. Ultimately, the principle of constructively controlled microcavitation, ACIM particle detection, relies on controlling the very fundamental process of phase change, the control of nucleation?the ability to convert a liquid into a gas in the vicinity of a solid phase. The study of this acoustically mediated nucleation control could form an active field/area of research and education. ACIM will be widely applicable in a variety of liquid-chemical processing, e.g. control of boiling processes in chemical and nuclear reactors, sonochemical synthesis, and bio-technology. This small business is a minority and woman-owned company that relies on diversity?ethnic, gender and age?for robust performance that is dedicated to training young researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1046659</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bingrong</FirstName>
<LastName>He</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bingrong He</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bingrong@uncopiers.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7857769990</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000408165</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Uncopiers, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Manhattan</CityName>
<ZipCode>665039123</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7852934917</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6923 Redbud Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080880557</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNCOPIERS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Uncopiers, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Manhattan</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>665039123</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6923 Redbud Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7257</Code>
<Text>APPLICATS OF ADVANCED TECHNOLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9139</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Acoustic Slurry Monitor</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The goal of this project was to evaluate the feasibility of developing an <strong>Acoustic</strong> <strong>CMP Slurry Monitor</strong>&mdash;a fully in-line, real-time, point of use instrument that will detect and disperse any and all large agglomerates in the nanofine slurries used in IC manufacture.&nbsp; Left unchecked, these errant slurry particles/agglomerates can "kill" (deeply scratch) a semiconductor wafer as it undergoes chemical mechanical planarizing or polishing (CMP).&nbsp; CMP has become the method of choice for restoring the surface trueness of wafers at all stages of IC manufacture.&nbsp; No method currently exists that can implement a CMP-safe slurry at the point of use.</p> <p>The <strong>Acoustic Slurry Monitor </strong>makes use of a novel technology of constructively controlling acoustic microcavitation.&nbsp; The slurry monitor detects large particles/agglomerates that compromise CMP slurry. The <strong>Slurry Monitor is a yield protecting tool</strong> reliably improving CMP performance.</p> <p><strong>Acoustic CMP Slurry Monitor</strong> is a new method of detecting in-slurry boulder/agglomerates relying on controlled nucleation. Ultimately, the principle of constructively controlled microcavitation&mdash;the ability to convert a liquid into a gas in the vicinity of a solid phase&mdash;will have rich applications in a variety of liquid-chemical processing, e.g. control of boiling processes in chemical and nuclear reactors, sonochemical synthesis, and bio-technology.&nbsp;</p> <p>Rejected wafers amount to a colossal waste of prime resources including energy, material, and productivity time; it further amounts to environmental degradation through the effluents and scrap generated.&nbsp; Use of <strong>Acoustic CMP Slurry Monitor </strong>to prevent such wafer loss directly benefits the society at large.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/21/2011<br>      Modified by: Bingrong&nbsp;He</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Acoustic Slurry Monitor     The goal of this project was to evaluate the feasibility of developing an Acoustic CMP Slurry Monitor&mdash;a fully in-line, real-time, point of use instrument that will detect and disperse any and all large agglomerates in the nanofine slurries used in IC manufacture.  Left unchecked, these errant slurry particles/agglomerates can "kill" (deeply scratch) a semiconductor wafer as it undergoes chemical mechanical planarizing or polishing (CMP).  CMP has become the method of choice for restoring the surface trueness of wafers at all stages of IC manufacture.  No method currently exists that can implement a CMP-safe slurry at the point of use.  The Acoustic Slurry Monitor makes use of a novel technology of constructively controlling acoustic microcavitation.  The slurry monitor detects large particles/agglomerates that compromise CMP slurry. The Slurry Monitor is a yield protecting tool reliably improving CMP performance.  Acoustic CMP Slurry Monitor is a new method of detecting in-slurry boulder/agglomerates relying on controlled nucleation. Ultimately, the principle of constructively controlled microcavitation&mdash;the ability to convert a liquid into a gas in the vicinity of a solid phase&mdash;will have rich applications in a variety of liquid-chemical processing, e.g. control of boiling processes in chemical and nuclear reactors, sonochemical synthesis, and bio-technology.   Rejected wafers amount to a colossal waste of prime resources including energy, material, and productivity time; it further amounts to environmental degradation through the effluents and scrap generated.  Use of Acoustic CMP Slurry Monitor to prevent such wafer loss directly benefits the society at large.       Last Modified: 07/21/2011       Submitted by: Bingrong He]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
