<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Four-way Catalytic Converter for Lean Burn Diesel Engines</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>148725.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>178168</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory T. Baxter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will demonstrate the technical and commercial viability of a novel four-way catalytic converter for lean burn diesel applications that is based on high-surface area nanomaterials applied directly to the inner walls of existing catalytic converter monoliths. While there is ongoing research to integrate diesel particulate filters and the oxidation catalyst, there is little research addressing the integration of all four components (oxidation of carbon monoxide, oxidation of hydrocarbons, capture and destruction of carbon particulate matter (PM) and reduction of NOx.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impacts of this research are that in 2013 strict requirements for diesel emissions standards will become law. These new regulations will effect carbon emissions both in terms of particle size and number of particles. While there are proposals to meet impending PM regulations, none actively integrate all the required functions of a catalytic converter. Therefore the potential U.S. commercial value of the catalytic converter structure from this project is significant. The European market opportunity may be larger since diesel engines are more prevalent in Europe.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1047410</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Giancarlo</FirstName>
<LastName>Corti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Giancarlo Corti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>corticlg@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135290747</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506202</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/12/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Yahvah</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Yahvah</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matt.yahvah@gonano-9.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2088922000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000608667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GoNano Technologies</Name>
<CityName>Moscow</CityName>
<ZipCode>838432386</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2088922000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>121 West Sweet Avenue #115</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808496009</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GONANO TECHNOLOGIES, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[GoNano Technologies]]></Name>
<CityName>Moscow</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>838432386</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[121 West Sweet Avenue #115]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL IMPLICATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9188</Code>
<Text>AIR QUALITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~178168</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Four-way Catalytic Converter for Lean Burn Diesel Engines</p> <p>NSF Award #: 1047410</p> <p>Project Outcomes Report</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>: Under the auspices of this NSF SBIR Phase I/IB funding, GoNano Technologies, Inc. has been working on determining the viability and commercial feasibility of incorporating the company's silica Nanospring<sup>&trade; </sup>material into catalytic converter (CC) applications. This report describes in detail the progress made in this application.</p> <p>The Nanospring mat provides a high surface area (~ 400m<sup>2</sup>/g) support for the active catalyst, which can be easily deposited using solution-based techniques such as wet impregnation. The Nanospring support is stable at high temperatures maintaining its morphology and retaining its surface area up to 1025<sup>&deg;</sup>C where it begins to sublime. The standard catalyst support in the CC industry is alumina, which has a surface area ~ 140m<sup>2</sup>/g, but when exposed to high temperatures over long periods of use it degrades and its surface area reduces eventually to ~ 20m<sup>2</sup>/g. During the period of this NSF award, GoNano Technologies was able to further analyze the practicality and develop some cost estimates regarding the deposition of Nanosprings inside CC cores.</p> <p>GoNano Technologies has worked on assessing the benefits of using Nanosprings in CC applications by first showing the ability of the silica Nanosprings to inhibit catalyst particle growth; a common problem seen when the catalyst is exposed to harsh environments over a long time. In previous work it was shown that the Nanosprings stabilized supported gold nanoparticles and prevented them from sintering even at elevated temperatures (600&deg;C in the case of Au). Under the auspices of this grant it was found that both platinum and palladium nanoparticles supported on silica Nanosprings were able to resist sintering under hydrothermal aging (800<sup>o</sup>C at 10% relative humidity) for 16 hours and remain catalytically active. This result not only shows that Nanosprings offer a significant benefit over existing oxide supports, but also that silica Nanosprings do not poison the precious metal catalyst, which is often observed when these metals are supported on other forms of silica.</p> <p>The initial studies conducted by GoNano Technologies demonstrated that&nbsp; Nanosprings are a viable catalyst support. Experiments done in-house demonstrated that the Nanosprings could add some stability to catalyst particles during aging conditions. Both platinum and palladium nanoparticles were found to ripen very little and experiments showed that they were not &ldquo;poisoned&rdquo; by the silica during aging.</p> <p>Stainless steel foil substrates were found to be rather simple to grow the Nanosprings on. The configuration of rolling up the steel foil to make monoliths meshed well with the established procedures used at GoNano Technologies. For this reason GoNano Technologies decided to use metallic substrates for most of its investigations. It is highly expected that the Nanospring growth process could be configured to a roll-to-roll process using this metal foil, such that any size core could be made.</p> <p>The external collaborators we engaged all had different ideas of the configurations in which they would like to evaluate the Nanosprings. Most companies desired to first compare the Nanosprings as a support in a diesel oxidation catalyst (DOC) configuration against the standard alumina washcoat. GoNano Technologies coated both ceramic materials and metal substrates with the Nanosprings and even various thicknesses of Nanosprings to satisfy these evaluations. Most of these companies have not yet completed their evaluations and have asked GoNano Technologies for variations in the Nanospring configuration or for more samples.</p> <p>GoNano Technologies identified the potential of Nanospring...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Four-way Catalytic Converter for Lean Burn Diesel Engines  NSF Award #: 1047410  Project Outcomes Report  Summary: Under the auspices of this NSF SBIR Phase I/IB funding, GoNano Technologies, Inc. has been working on determining the viability and commercial feasibility of incorporating the company's silica Nanospring&trade; material into catalytic converter (CC) applications. This report describes in detail the progress made in this application.  The Nanospring mat provides a high surface area (~ 400m2/g) support for the active catalyst, which can be easily deposited using solution-based techniques such as wet impregnation. The Nanospring support is stable at high temperatures maintaining its morphology and retaining its surface area up to 1025&deg;C where it begins to sublime. The standard catalyst support in the CC industry is alumina, which has a surface area ~ 140m2/g, but when exposed to high temperatures over long periods of use it degrades and its surface area reduces eventually to ~ 20m2/g. During the period of this NSF award, GoNano Technologies was able to further analyze the practicality and develop some cost estimates regarding the deposition of Nanosprings inside CC cores.  GoNano Technologies has worked on assessing the benefits of using Nanosprings in CC applications by first showing the ability of the silica Nanosprings to inhibit catalyst particle growth; a common problem seen when the catalyst is exposed to harsh environments over a long time. In previous work it was shown that the Nanosprings stabilized supported gold nanoparticles and prevented them from sintering even at elevated temperatures (600&deg;C in the case of Au). Under the auspices of this grant it was found that both platinum and palladium nanoparticles supported on silica Nanosprings were able to resist sintering under hydrothermal aging (800oC at 10% relative humidity) for 16 hours and remain catalytically active. This result not only shows that Nanosprings offer a significant benefit over existing oxide supports, but also that silica Nanosprings do not poison the precious metal catalyst, which is often observed when these metals are supported on other forms of silica.  The initial studies conducted by GoNano Technologies demonstrated that  Nanosprings are a viable catalyst support. Experiments done in-house demonstrated that the Nanosprings could add some stability to catalyst particles during aging conditions. Both platinum and palladium nanoparticles were found to ripen very little and experiments showed that they were not "poisoned" by the silica during aging.  Stainless steel foil substrates were found to be rather simple to grow the Nanosprings on. The configuration of rolling up the steel foil to make monoliths meshed well with the established procedures used at GoNano Technologies. For this reason GoNano Technologies decided to use metallic substrates for most of its investigations. It is highly expected that the Nanospring growth process could be configured to a roll-to-roll process using this metal foil, such that any size core could be made.  The external collaborators we engaged all had different ideas of the configurations in which they would like to evaluate the Nanosprings. Most companies desired to first compare the Nanosprings as a support in a diesel oxidation catalyst (DOC) configuration against the standard alumina washcoat. GoNano Technologies coated both ceramic materials and metal substrates with the Nanosprings and even various thicknesses of Nanosprings to satisfy these evaluations. Most of these companies have not yet completed their evaluations and have asked GoNano Technologies for variations in the Nanospring configuration or for more samples.  GoNano Technologies identified the potential of Nanosprings in DOC applications and realized that they should undertake some in-house experiments rather than rely on external partners to share all their data. GoNano Technologies coated 1" OD x 3" long metallic substrates (E...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
