<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Compact analyzer for trace ammonia in air</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will lead to a highly miniaturized trace gas analyzers that are useful for emissions monitoring and industrial safety application. The planned work is motivated by a need to detect ammonia in the air. Once released into the air, ammonia forms fine particles can impact the climate by affecting cloud formation, and are linked to cardiac and respiratory illness. Anticipated ammonia detection limits are between 1 and 10 parts per billion. The proposed technology will, if successful, lead to commercial ammonia analyzers that will fit into a shirt pocket. The planned six-month-duration Phase I project will identify the technical factors limiting measurement sensitivity, determine the changes in analyzer performance with changing sample pressure, and extrapolate results for ammonia to other gases of environmental, industrial, and biomedical importance. The Phase I project will end with a head-to-head comparison between the benchtop analyzer built during the project and a well-calibrated, open-path ammonia analyzer that has been deployed successfully for rapid measurements of ammonia in air.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is the development of new rapid, low cost, and inexpensive technology for analyzing trace gases in environmental monitoring, industrial workplace safety, and, perhaps, medical diagnostics through analysis of exhaled breath. The technology is part of the $250 to $350 million dollar a year market for gas sensors, detectors, and analyzers. Measurements of ammonia emissions and trace concentrations in air will have significant impact on atmospheric science and public health. It has been suggested that the most economical way to reduce the amount of fine particles in air over the eastern United States, is to control ammonia emissions instead of trying to limit oxides of nitrogen and sulfur. But, highly-portable, reasonably-priced ammonia analyzers that are needed to provide supporting data and to monitor ammonia distributions are not yet commercially available. The planned technology can also be applied to detection of compounds including carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide, hydrogen sulfide, methane, hydrogen chloride, nitric oxide, and ethylene. In the case of hydrogen sulfide detection for the petrochemical industry, the new technology offers significant advantages over existing methods for hydrogen sulfide monitoring at wellheads and in refineries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1047108</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Bomse</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Bomse</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dbomse@mesaphotonics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052165015</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000565945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/18/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mesa Photonics, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Santa Fe</CityName>
<ZipCode>875053914</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052165015</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1550 Pacheco St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>607619223</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MESA PHOTONICS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mesa Photonics, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Fe</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>875053914</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1550 Pacheco St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; DEVICE TEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7257</Code>
<Text>APPLICATS OF ADVANCED TECHNOLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9139</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Mesa Photonics, LLC, (Santa Fe, NM) successfully completed a Phase I SBIR project that will lead to development of a highly sensitive and low cost analyzers for ammonia in air.&nbsp; Detection limits will be better than 50 parts per billion and, likely, less than 10 parts per billion.</p> <p>Small amounts of ammonia can have big effects on health and on the atmosphere.&nbsp; The ammonia forms particles that are small enough to be inhaled deeply into our lungs leading to pulmonary inflammation.&nbsp; The same particles can affect climate by changing cloud formation dynamics.&nbsp; Scientists studying ammonia&rsquo;s effect on the atmosphere need accurate measurements of ammonia concentrations at low concentrations.&nbsp; But, there are large discrepancies among measurements made from satellites, measurements made at the earth&rsquo;s surface, and concentrations predicted using computer modeling.&nbsp; Commercial products based on Mesa Photonics&rsquo; technology will help resolve these discrepancies.&nbsp; The analyzers will be able to measure ammonia concentrations down to about 10 parts per billion, yet will be less than half the cost of competing products.&nbsp; Measurements will require only a few seconds.</p> <p>By the end of the six-month-long Phase I project, Mesa Photonics researchers demonstrated ammonia detection limits of 290 parts per billion.&nbsp; Significantly, we also identified improvements that will bring the detection limit to the targeted 10 ppb value.&nbsp; One of these improvements is a new invention that significantly speeds measurement rates.&nbsp; We plan to file a patent application covering the idea later this summer.&nbsp; Markets for sensors and analyzers are highly competitive.&nbsp; Patent protection provides an important advantage to commercialization of new technology.</p> <p>The ammonia analyzer technology is a non-contacting optical method based on the type of miniature, low-power lasers that are sold for telecommunications over optical fibers.&nbsp; The laser is smaller than a grain of rice and draws less electric power than an iPad.&nbsp; Laser light is contained within a glass fiber that is thinner than a human hair.&nbsp; The light is eye safe.&nbsp;</p> <p>Measuring ammonia at very low concentrations (below 1 part per million) is important for understanding atmospheric effects, as noted.&nbsp; Measurements of higher concentrations (above 1 part per million) are also important because ammonia irritates eyes and lungs.&nbsp; Our technology will also be able to monitor ammonia emissions leading to these health problems.&nbsp; Agriculture is the biggest source of ammonia emissions in the United States.&nbsp; Analyzers are needed for measurements around animal feed operations (AFOs), poultry and hog farms, waste lagoons, and cropland where ammonia is applied directly to the soil as a fertilizer.&nbsp; This market is significant: 70% of domestic ammonia emissions come from agriculture.&nbsp; There are, for example, 450,000 AFOs in the United States.&nbsp; Small size, low power requirement, and low cost make Mesa Photonics&rsquo; technology well-suited to the agricultural emissions market.</p> <p>Finally, we note that the gas analyzer technology tested during the Phase I project is also applicable to other gases.&nbsp; Hydrogen sulfide (H<sub>2</sub>S) detection is probably offers the best commercial opportunity.&nbsp; The gas is highly toxic and is ubiquitous in oil and gas operations.&nbsp; Existing electrochemical sensors can fail at extreme temperatures and require regular dosing with hydrogen sulfide to keep the electrolyte active.&nbsp; Mesa Photonics NSF-funded technology promises more reliable operation.&nbsp; A significant development effort will be needed, however, to obtain the price benefits of large volume production.</p> <p>For additional information, please contact David Bomse, PhD, at 505-216-5015 or dbomse@mesaphoton...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Mesa Photonics, LLC, (Santa Fe, NM) successfully completed a Phase I SBIR project that will lead to development of a highly sensitive and low cost analyzers for ammonia in air.  Detection limits will be better than 50 parts per billion and, likely, less than 10 parts per billion.  Small amounts of ammonia can have big effects on health and on the atmosphere.  The ammonia forms particles that are small enough to be inhaled deeply into our lungs leading to pulmonary inflammation.  The same particles can affect climate by changing cloud formation dynamics.  Scientists studying ammoniaÆs effect on the atmosphere need accurate measurements of ammonia concentrations at low concentrations.  But, there are large discrepancies among measurements made from satellites, measurements made at the earthÆs surface, and concentrations predicted using computer modeling.  Commercial products based on Mesa PhotonicsÆ technology will help resolve these discrepancies.  The analyzers will be able to measure ammonia concentrations down to about 10 parts per billion, yet will be less than half the cost of competing products.  Measurements will require only a few seconds.  By the end of the six-month-long Phase I project, Mesa Photonics researchers demonstrated ammonia detection limits of 290 parts per billion.  Significantly, we also identified improvements that will bring the detection limit to the targeted 10 ppb value.  One of these improvements is a new invention that significantly speeds measurement rates.  We plan to file a patent application covering the idea later this summer.  Markets for sensors and analyzers are highly competitive.  Patent protection provides an important advantage to commercialization of new technology.  The ammonia analyzer technology is a non-contacting optical method based on the type of miniature, low-power lasers that are sold for telecommunications over optical fibers.  The laser is smaller than a grain of rice and draws less electric power than an iPad.  Laser light is contained within a glass fiber that is thinner than a human hair.  The light is eye safe.   Measuring ammonia at very low concentrations (below 1 part per million) is important for understanding atmospheric effects, as noted.  Measurements of higher concentrations (above 1 part per million) are also important because ammonia irritates eyes and lungs.  Our technology will also be able to monitor ammonia emissions leading to these health problems.  Agriculture is the biggest source of ammonia emissions in the United States.  Analyzers are needed for measurements around animal feed operations (AFOs), poultry and hog farms, waste lagoons, and cropland where ammonia is applied directly to the soil as a fertilizer.  This market is significant: 70% of domestic ammonia emissions come from agriculture.  There are, for example, 450,000 AFOs in the United States.  Small size, low power requirement, and low cost make Mesa PhotonicsÆ technology well-suited to the agricultural emissions market.  Finally, we note that the gas analyzer technology tested during the Phase I project is also applicable to other gases.  Hydrogen sulfide (H2S) detection is probably offers the best commercial opportunity.  The gas is highly toxic and is ubiquitous in oil and gas operations.  Existing electrochemical sensors can fail at extreme temperatures and require regular dosing with hydrogen sulfide to keep the electrolyte active.  Mesa Photonics NSF-funded technology promises more reliable operation.  A significant development effort will be needed, however, to obtain the price benefits of large volume production.  For additional information, please contact David Bomse, PhD, at 505-216-5015 or dbomse@mesaphotonics.com          Last Modified: 07/07/2011       Submitted by: David S Bomse]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
