<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Improved Regional and Decadal Predictions of the Carbon Cycle</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>884194.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>884194</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anjuli Bamzai</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abamzai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928688</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual merit&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of this project is to improve the decadal and regional projections of the carbon cycle in the Community Earth System Model.  There currently is substantial spread in the predictions of atmospheric carbon among the full complexity climate-carbon models, even with the same anthropogenic forcings. This spread in predictions of the carbon uptake by the land and ocean result in large differences in climate forcing, and thus climate impacts. The next Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change is the first that will include the carbon cycle for all models, and thus the carbon cycle models have not yet been subject to the same rigorous analysis that the physical models have been exposed to. This project will jump-start the process of understanding and improving the carbon cycle in the Community Earth System Model.  The goal is to compile datasets, prepare methodologies for comparisons and develop metrics that will facilitate improvements in the models and reduce the uncertainty in future climate projections of the carbon cycle for earth system models. In addition, the PIs will use these datasets to answer fundamental questions about how the carbon cycle responds on regional and decadal scales, and how it will evolve in the future. This project includes experts in modeling and model/data comparisons for the land, ocean and atmosphere, which is required for the cross-disciplinary challenge of improving simulations of regional and decadal scale carbon fluxes.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts&lt;br/&gt;This project includes the compilation and publishing of important datasets and metrics that can be used to improve carbon flux predictions.  It will result in improvements in the publically available Community Earth System Model.  The project includes the education of 4 graduate students, and 2 undergraduate students in cross-disciplinary studies of the carbon cycle.  It also includes outreach programs targeted at temporary exhibits at museums, and K-12 teacher development programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1048890</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Randerson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James T Randerson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jranders@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498249030</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000450242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jefferson</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jefferson Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkmoore@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498245391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~884194</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this grant was to improve the decadal and regional projections of the carbon cycle in the Community Earth System Model (CESM).&nbsp; There currently is substantial spread in the predictions of atmospheric carbon among the full complexity climate-carbon models, even with the same anthropogenic forcings. This spread in predictions of the carbon uptake by the land and ocean result in large differences in climate forcing, and thus climate impacts. The IPCC 5th assessment was the first to include the carbon cycle for all IPCC models, and thus the carbon cycle models have not yet been subject to the same rigorous analysis that the physical models have been exposed to. This proposal sought to jump-start the process of understanding and improving the carbon cycle in CESMs.&nbsp; Our goal was to compile datasets, prepare methodologies for comparisons and develop metrics necessary to facilitate improvements in the models and reduce the uncertainty in future climate projections of the carbon cycle for the CCSM as well as other models. In addition, we used these datasets to answer fundamental questions about how the carbon cycle responds on regional and decadal scales, and how it will evolve in the future. The project included experts in modeling and model/data comparisons for the land, ocean and atmosphere, which is required for the cross-disciplinary challenge of improving simulations of regional and decadal scale carbon fluxes.&nbsp;</p> <p>At UCI Irvine, this EaSM project supported three major lines of effort. It supported development of the marine biogeochemistry submodel of the Community Earth System Model (CESM), with work led by Keith Moore. It supported the development of the International Land Model Benchmarking System (ILAMB), with work led by Jim Randerson. It also supported analysis and evaluation of the representation of different ecosystem and carbon cycle processes within CESM and other earth system models, with Randerson and Moore collaborating with other team members at NCAR, Woods Hole Research Center, and Cornell. Fourteen papers were published with UCI personnel leading the activity. Many other papers were published in which UCI contributed to efforts being led by team members at other institutions.</p> <p>Several important specific project objectives included:</p> <p>&nbsp;1) Developing new ways to use contemporary atmospheric CO2 observations to reduce uncertainties in future projections. Work in this area led to the development of a new 'emergent constraint' that can help explain model-to-model differences in their future projections of CO2. Much of the spread in future model projections of atmospheric CO2 can be traced back to model biases observed during the last decade from comparisons with observations at Mauna Loa and other monitoring stations.</p> <p>2) Improving our understanding of how differences in tree species composition and plant traits in boreal forests contribute to continental differences in fire-climate feedbacks.</p> <p>&nbsp;3) Understanding how climate-carbon cycle feedbacks may evolve beyond 2100. In this work, we were able to show that ocean contributions to climate-carbon feedbacks grow considerably after 2100, making it difficult to stabilize atmospheric CO2 levels.</p> <p>4) Assessing the role of fire-emitted aerosols and trace gases in influencing radiation and climate. To address this objective, we wrote papers looking at the changing role of fires in influencing radiative forcing as well as analysis of fire impacts on precipitation and surface temperature.</p> <p>5) Quantifying how changes in ocean oxygen content are likely to evolve in response to sustained, long-term impacts of climate warming.</p> <p>This grant supported the training of several early career scholars. Brendan Rogers received his Ph.D. working on this project, as is now a postdoctoral scholar at Woods Hole Research Center. Postdoctoral sc...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this grant was to improve the decadal and regional projections of the carbon cycle in the Community Earth System Model (CESM).  There currently is substantial spread in the predictions of atmospheric carbon among the full complexity climate-carbon models, even with the same anthropogenic forcings. This spread in predictions of the carbon uptake by the land and ocean result in large differences in climate forcing, and thus climate impacts. The IPCC 5th assessment was the first to include the carbon cycle for all IPCC models, and thus the carbon cycle models have not yet been subject to the same rigorous analysis that the physical models have been exposed to. This proposal sought to jump-start the process of understanding and improving the carbon cycle in CESMs.  Our goal was to compile datasets, prepare methodologies for comparisons and develop metrics necessary to facilitate improvements in the models and reduce the uncertainty in future climate projections of the carbon cycle for the CCSM as well as other models. In addition, we used these datasets to answer fundamental questions about how the carbon cycle responds on regional and decadal scales, and how it will evolve in the future. The project included experts in modeling and model/data comparisons for the land, ocean and atmosphere, which is required for the cross-disciplinary challenge of improving simulations of regional and decadal scale carbon fluxes.   At UCI Irvine, this EaSM project supported three major lines of effort. It supported development of the marine biogeochemistry submodel of the Community Earth System Model (CESM), with work led by Keith Moore. It supported the development of the International Land Model Benchmarking System (ILAMB), with work led by Jim Randerson. It also supported analysis and evaluation of the representation of different ecosystem and carbon cycle processes within CESM and other earth system models, with Randerson and Moore collaborating with other team members at NCAR, Woods Hole Research Center, and Cornell. Fourteen papers were published with UCI personnel leading the activity. Many other papers were published in which UCI contributed to efforts being led by team members at other institutions.  Several important specific project objectives included:   1) Developing new ways to use contemporary atmospheric CO2 observations to reduce uncertainties in future projections. Work in this area led to the development of a new 'emergent constraint' that can help explain model-to-model differences in their future projections of CO2. Much of the spread in future model projections of atmospheric CO2 can be traced back to model biases observed during the last decade from comparisons with observations at Mauna Loa and other monitoring stations.  2) Improving our understanding of how differences in tree species composition and plant traits in boreal forests contribute to continental differences in fire-climate feedbacks.   3) Understanding how climate-carbon cycle feedbacks may evolve beyond 2100. In this work, we were able to show that ocean contributions to climate-carbon feedbacks grow considerably after 2100, making it difficult to stabilize atmospheric CO2 levels.  4) Assessing the role of fire-emitted aerosols and trace gases in influencing radiation and climate. To address this objective, we wrote papers looking at the changing role of fires in influencing radiative forcing as well as analysis of fire impacts on precipitation and surface temperature.  5) Quantifying how changes in ocean oxygen content are likely to evolve in response to sustained, long-term impacts of climate warming.  This grant supported the training of several early career scholars. Brendan Rogers received his Ph.D. working on this project, as is now a postdoctoral scholar at Woods Hole Research Center. Postdoctoral scholar Gretchen Keppel Aleks also received support from this project, and is now an assistant professor at University of Michigan. Ph.D....]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
