<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF/DOE Thermoelectrics Partnership, Collaborative Proposal: Project SEEBECK - Saving Energy Effectively By Engaging in Collaborative research and sharing Knowledge</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>517568.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>388549</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruey-Hung Chen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1048622 / 1048621 / 1048728&lt;br/&gt;Heremans / Lu / Kanatzidis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves researchers from Ohio State University, Northwestern University, and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, with input from industries. Working together, the researchers hope to solve major scientific barriers to commercializing thermoelectric waste heat recovery technology.  The goal of project is the creation of a viable system to convert automotive waste heat into usable electrical power using thermoelectric (TE) devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The research proposed here will advance work in TE by focusing on five key elements. Materials research (led by OSU and NU) will develop advanced TE materials made from earth-abundant, geographically dispersed elements and compounds, specifically PbSe and Mg2Si-Mg2Sn. Thermal management system design (led by BSST) will create new thermal designs to minimize losses by minimizing the number of interfaces, minimizing the amount of TE material used; these designs will maximize the durability of the product. Work on interfaces, led by VPI&amp;SU and ZTPlus, will focus on the metallization of the TE materials and device interconnection and the flexible bonding of the metallized elements to the heat spreaders to increase durability and reduce device level performance losses. The team will expand capabilities in metrology to measure electrical and thermal contact resistances, and develop a comprehensive and redundant measurement loop system with self-consistent error checking. Durability will be the inherent design criterion in every invention.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has the potential to transform progress in TE materials. We will improve the fundamental understanding of the effect of resonant levels on the transport properties of solids, and make it applicable to large classes of semiconductors. The development of matrix encapsulation techniques for Mg2X will expand the repertoire of creative solid-state chemistry approaches in creating nanostructured thermoelectrics. New strong and flexible high-temperature bonding techniques will impact the assembly of semiconductor die. The project will advance understanding on the efficiency of TE generators, TE material durability at high temperatures, and cycle life durability of TE materials, all of which are critical to successful commercialization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project will create potentially transformative research that promises to save up to 800,000 barrels of oil daily and reduce carbon emissions. Results of the research will be incorporated into classes taught by project investigators in the physics of transport phenomena, materials synthesis and electronic component assembly. The academic PI's will also integrate this research into participation in multidisciplinary collaborative groups. The significance of energy efficiency and usage that this research addresses will be integrated into the well established outreach programs at all three universities. Involvement of corporate partners ensures large scale commercialization, as BSST is the world leader in commercial applications of TE's in automotive and other key industries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1048728</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mercouri</FirstName>
<LastName>Kanatzidis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mercouri G Kanatzidis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>m-kanatzidis@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474671541</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000391785</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 N. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8008</Code>
<Text>NSF/DOE Thermoelectric Partner</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J429</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>KX51</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>LX31</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>065E</Code>
<Text>Radiation heat transfer</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>099E</Code>
<Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>104E</Code>
<Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1761</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~126403</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~387057</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~0</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~133127</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol">&nbsp; <p>The goal of this research was to advance work in the thermoelectric (TE) field by focusing on (a) materials research (led by OSU and NU) to develop advanced TE materials made from earth-abundant, geographically dispersed elements and compounds. (b) thermal management system design (led by BSST) to minimize losses by minimizing the number of interfaces, minimizing the amount of TE material used and maximize the durability of the product. (c) work on interfaces, led by VPI&amp;SU and ZTPlus, that focuses on the metallization of the TE materials and device interconnection and the flexible bonding of the metallized elements to the heat spreaders to increase durability and reduce device level performance losses. In this context the team at Northwestern University chose to work on PbS as one of the most attractive materials. The Northwestern team investigated the PbS system as an example of low cost materials composed of earth abundant elements. During the duration of the project we succeeded in producing high thermoelectric performance in nanostructured n- and p-type PbS, a material consisting of highly earth abundant and inexpensive elements. This was done by exploring the addition of second phases in PbS and measuring the thermoelectric properties of the materials. &nbsp;The program succeeded in accomplishing its goals which were to produce high performance low cost materials composed of earth abundant elements. Our efforts in this project allowed us to show that vast improvements in <em>ZT</em> can also be achieved in p-type PbS materials. We showed that the thermoelectric performance of the PbS system and by extension other systems can be enhanced by means of a closely coupled phonon-blocking/electron-transmitting approach through embedding nanostructured second phases.&nbsp; The work on PbS showed that the figure of merit <em>ZT </em>can be increased to the record high value of ~1.3 at 923 K with second phase nanostructures. The project contributed significantly on our understanding of how to start with low cost poor of modest thermoelectric materials (containing earth abundant element such as PbS).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2015<br>      Modified by: Mercouri&nbsp;G&nbsp;Kanatzidis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The goal of this research was to advance work in the thermoelectric (TE) field by focusing on (a) materials research (led by OSU and NU) to develop advanced TE materials made from earth-abundant, geographically dispersed elements and compounds. (b) thermal management system design (led by BSST) to minimize losses by minimizing the number of interfaces, minimizing the amount of TE material used and maximize the durability of the product. (c) work on interfaces, led by VPI&amp;SU and ZTPlus, that focuses on the metallization of the TE materials and device interconnection and the flexible bonding of the metallized elements to the heat spreaders to increase durability and reduce device level performance losses. In this context the team at Northwestern University chose to work on PbS as one of the most attractive materials. The Northwestern team investigated the PbS system as an example of low cost materials composed of earth abundant elements. During the duration of the project we succeeded in producing high thermoelectric performance in nanostructured n- and p-type PbS, a material consisting of highly earth abundant and inexpensive elements. This was done by exploring the addition of second phases in PbS and measuring the thermoelectric properties of the materials.  The program succeeded in accomplishing its goals which were to produce high performance low cost materials composed of earth abundant elements. Our efforts in this project allowed us to show that vast improvements in ZT can also be achieved in p-type PbS materials. We showed that the thermoelectric performance of the PbS system and by extension other systems can be enhanced by means of a closely coupled phonon-blocking/electron-transmitting approach through embedding nanostructured second phases.  The work on PbS showed that the figure of merit ZT can be increased to the record high value of ~1.3 at 923 K with second phase nanostructures. The project contributed significantly on our understanding of how to start with low cost poor of modest thermoelectric materials (containing earth abundant element such as PbS).             Last Modified: 01/13/2015       Submitted by: Mercouri G Kanatzidis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
