<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop Proposal: West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25440.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25440</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julie Palais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The WAIS (West Antarctic Ice Sheet) meetings have been held annually since 1994. This award supports the 17th annual WAIS meeting at the Pennsylvania State University. The intellectual merit of this award is that there are currently large uncertainties in sea-level rise estimates over the next century that are cause for concern for policymakers and the public.  Projections of sea-level rise for the next century implicate the large polar ice sheets (in particular, marginal melt of the Greenland Ice Sheet and of the Antarctic Peninsula and the Amundsen Sea sector of West Antarctica) as the major contributors, but with significant uncertainty on the magnitude and timing of those contributions. Obtaining better constraints on those uncertainties requires better ice-sheet models and better inputs to the ice-sheet models, and a concerted, interdisciplinary effort including ice sheet modelers, ocean modelers, and observational efforts. Over the last two decades, the role of the Polar ice sheets has grown in importance with regards to global environmental and societal concerns. The WAIS community consists of glaciologists, geologists, atmospheric- and earth-scientists, oceanographers, and others.  This workshop award supports a meeting that will examine these questions and will formulate a community strategy for the future. The particular science topics to be addressed are: 1) Ocean &amp; Ice interactions: how important and how well-understood?;  2) Basal properties: mm to km scale importance; heat flow; 3) Ice sheet models: recent advances and future prospects; 4) Observations: satellites, airplanes, skidoos, and crampons; 5) History of the ice sheet: ice cores, ocean-bottom features, geology. In order to encourage a broad representation of early career scientists and scientists who might not have attended WAIS previously, this award provides funding for participant support that will lower the cost of attendance for many of the attendees. The broader impacts of this award are that priority for support will be given to early-career scientists, scientists from underrepresented groups, students, and scientists from science disciplines of importance to WAIS who have been absent in the past.The meeting will be held in  central Pennsylvania in late September, 2010.  WAIS is strongly interdisciplinary and high-visibility meeting. Students and researchers mingle in an informal setting that encourages the free exchange of ideas.  WAIS meetings bring together scientists from many fields with a central focus on understanding ice sheets and sea level interactions, which as yet have large uncertainties.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1048878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sridhar</FirstName>
<LastName>Anandakrishnan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sridhar Anandakrishnan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sak@essc.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148636742</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000477864</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5112</Code>
<Text>ANT Earth Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5116</Code>
<Text>ANT Glaciology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5292</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~25440</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the last two decades, the role of the Polar ice sheets has grown in importance with regards to global environmental and societal concerns. &nbsp;The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) research community consists of glaciologists, geologists, atmospheric- and earth-scientists, oceanographers, and others.&nbsp;The work of the WAIS community has, in part, lead to the re-assessment of the importance and impact of Polar ice sheets. &nbsp;It is incumbent on that community to continue and expand that work to the next level: quantifying the scale and timing of the contributions of the Polar ice sheets to sea level in a warming world.</p> <p>The WAIS meeting was held at the Lake Raystown Resort in central PA on Sep 23-25, 2010. &nbsp;The meeting was well-attended, with over 80 participants. &nbsp;The interactions between research scientists and with students was dynamic, spirited, valuable for all, and went on far into the night. &nbsp;Many students, postdocs, and early career scientists commented that they valued their experience and the opportunity to engage with extraordinary scientists. &nbsp;They also found the opportunity to network among themselves valuable.Of the 82 participants, 29 were students (most grad students, with 3 undergrads from Penn State - undergrads who all had posters on their summer research projects). &nbsp;There were an additional 10-12 early-career scientists (postdocs or pre-tenure faculty) who attended. There were 6 international participants. &nbsp;The gender ratio was good.</p> <p>Sessions on oceanography, basal processes, hydrology, and satellite remote sensing were followed by long discussions in which ideas could be exchanged and debated. &nbsp;The interactions of oceans and glaciers was a particularly engaging and lively area of discussion.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2011<br>      Modified by: Sridhar&nbsp;Anandakrishnan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the last two decades, the role of the Polar ice sheets has grown in importance with regards to global environmental and societal concerns.  The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) research community consists of glaciologists, geologists, atmospheric- and earth-scientists, oceanographers, and others. The work of the WAIS community has, in part, lead to the re-assessment of the importance and impact of Polar ice sheets.  It is incumbent on that community to continue and expand that work to the next level: quantifying the scale and timing of the contributions of the Polar ice sheets to sea level in a warming world.  The WAIS meeting was held at the Lake Raystown Resort in central PA on Sep 23-25, 2010.  The meeting was well-attended, with over 80 participants.  The interactions between research scientists and with students was dynamic, spirited, valuable for all, and went on far into the night.  Many students, postdocs, and early career scientists commented that they valued their experience and the opportunity to engage with extraordinary scientists.  They also found the opportunity to network among themselves valuable.Of the 82 participants, 29 were students (most grad students, with 3 undergrads from Penn State - undergrads who all had posters on their summer research projects).  There were an additional 10-12 early-career scientists (postdocs or pre-tenure faculty) who attended. There were 6 international participants.  The gender ratio was good.  Sessions on oceanography, basal processes, hydrology, and satellite remote sensing were followed by long discussions in which ideas could be exchanged and debated.  The interactions of oceans and glaciers was a particularly engaging and lively area of discussion.       Last Modified: 08/30/2011       Submitted by: Sridhar Anandakrishnan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
