<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SI2-SSE: Software Infrastructure For Partitioning Sparse Graphs on Existing and Emerging Computer Architectures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499784.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499784</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sol Greenspan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgreensp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927841</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Algorithms that find good partitionings of large, sparse, and unstructured graphs represent an important technique for developing effective and computationally efficient approaches for problems that need to process and analyze such graphs. As a result, they have found extensive applications in many diverse areas such as high-performance computing, scientific computing, VLSI design, data mining, pattern recognition, computer graphics, network analysis, database and geographical information systems, operations research, optimization, and scheduling. This project will develop and make available a software infrastructure that provides a broad range of graph partitioning tools for large, sparse, and unstructured graphs. This infrastructure will be built using modern object-oriented software engineering principles that will facilitate their modularity, user-extensibility, maintainability, and community development; and incorporate novel graph partitioning algorithms that can scale to graphs containing billions of nodes and facilitate the partitioning of different types of graphs on different computing architectures. This software infrastructure will enable the efficient execution of scientific numerical simulations on parallel systems containing tens of thousands of processing nodes and billions of mesh elements, the development of divide-and-conquer approaches for synthesizing very large VLSI circuits on different chip architectures, the clustering and analysis of very large graphs and networks, and the solution of a wide-range of partitioning problem instances involving different objectives and constraints.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This will positively impact numerous science &amp; engineering disciplines, commercial companies, non-profit organizations, and individuals that benefit from the results of the computations that are enabled and facilitated by the various application domains that rely on graph partitioning. Finally, the project integrates the research with an educational plan focused on undergraduate and graduate education and mentoring through courses, software engineering projects, summer institutes, and research opportunities; and a community development and an outreach plan designed to promote broad adoption of the resulting software infrastructure by providing extensive documentation, online tutorials, and organizing meetings at relevant conferences and workshops.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1048018</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Karypis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George Karypis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>karypis@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126267524</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000386588</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Whalen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael W Whalen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>whalen@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126254002</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000564513</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~499784</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sparse and unstructured graphs arise in many application domains including data mining, social network analysis, scientific computing, and VLSI design. Graph partitioning and clustering is an important technique for facilitating the development of effective and computationally efficient approaches for processing and analyzing large, sparse, and unstructured graphs.</p> <p>This project has developed new algorithms for partitioning and clustering different types of graphs that take advantage of the multiple cores available in today's computers. These algorithms, by exploiting thread-level parallelism can quickly process extremely large graphs and obtain high-quality partitioning and clustering solutions. The research led to the development of fundamental mechanisms to enable the decomposition of the key operations associated with multilevel graph partitioning and clustering, which reduces the frequency by which the different threads need to synchronize and thus allows them to effectively take advantage of computer systems with large number of processing cores.</p> <p>These algorithms have been implemented in general-purpose and easy-to-use software packages (Metis, mt-Metis, &amp; Nerstrand) and have been released to the community under open source licenses. These software packages are used extensively by researchers in various academic, government, and industrial laboratories and are incorporated in commercial software tools in the fields of computer aided engineering and manufacturing, computational simulation, and data analytics. Finally, the project provided training to Ph.D. students in areas related to parallel processing, graph theory, combinatorial optimization, and data science, and many of the algorithmic innovations have been incorporated in undergraduate- and graduate-level courses.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2015<br>      Modified by: George&nbsp;Karypis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sparse and unstructured graphs arise in many application domains including data mining, social network analysis, scientific computing, and VLSI design. Graph partitioning and clustering is an important technique for facilitating the development of effective and computationally efficient approaches for processing and analyzing large, sparse, and unstructured graphs.  This project has developed new algorithms for partitioning and clustering different types of graphs that take advantage of the multiple cores available in today's computers. These algorithms, by exploiting thread-level parallelism can quickly process extremely large graphs and obtain high-quality partitioning and clustering solutions. The research led to the development of fundamental mechanisms to enable the decomposition of the key operations associated with multilevel graph partitioning and clustering, which reduces the frequency by which the different threads need to synchronize and thus allows them to effectively take advantage of computer systems with large number of processing cores.  These algorithms have been implemented in general-purpose and easy-to-use software packages (Metis, mt-Metis, &amp; Nerstrand) and have been released to the community under open source licenses. These software packages are used extensively by researchers in various academic, government, and industrial laboratories and are incorporated in commercial software tools in the fields of computer aided engineering and manufacturing, computational simulation, and data analytics. Finally, the project provided training to Ph.D. students in areas related to parallel processing, graph theory, combinatorial optimization, and data science, and many of the algorithmic innovations have been incorporated in undergraduate- and graduate-level courses.       Last Modified: 10/31/2015       Submitted by: George Karypis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
