<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Towards a molecular-scale understanding of flow-induced gelation in rodlike micelle solutions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174992.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174992</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eddie Chang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0853735&lt;br/&gt;Sureshkumar&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite substantial progress achieved in understanding the microstructural basis of transport and rheology in many classes of complex fluids, including polymers, colloids, glasses, liquidcrystals and others, the flow behavior of one of the most important classes of complex fluids, surfactant solutions, remains mysterious. In particular, it has been known for at least two decades that translucent solutions of thread/rod like surfactant micelles undergo a phase transition to form viscoelastic gels under sufficiently strong shear or extensional flows. Lacking an understanding even of what these structures are, they are simply given the name Flow Induced Structures, or FIS. While progress has been made towards simulating thread/rod like(nanoscale) micelles at the molecular level, and towards simulating the macroscopic consequences of the presence of FIS, such as banded structures in the shear flow, there is an almost complete lack of theoretical connection between molecular structures and the possibility and conditions under which such nano structures might manifest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. This is a collaborative investigation between two universities to help close gaps in understanding through both experiments and a multi scale set of simulations encompassing length and time scales ranging from atomic (and nano) to continuum. A set of experiments exploring the regimes of transient and novel permanent flow-induced structures, induced by extensional deformation in micro channels, will be carried out. In parallel, the project  proposes four different simulation methods. 1) Atomistic Molecular Dynamic Simulations. These can capture the structure and interactions of one or two thread like micelle fragments in a periodic box roughly 10 nm on a side, at the atomic level on timescales of 10 nanoseconds. This is long enough and big enough to determine ionic effects on micellar structure and intermicellar interactions. 2) Coarse Grained (CG) Molecular Dynamics Simulations. Using the Marrink MARTINI model that lumps around four heavy atoms into each bead, a 1000 fold speed up relative to atomistic simulations is attained, reaching nearly to the millisecond time scale, while preserving molecular scale properties through suitably chosen CG potentials. The CG model will allow for the determination of micelle persistence lengths and the stability of thread like micelles as a function of salt concentration. 3) Brownian Dynamics Simulations using pearl necklace micelle model. This model, pioneered by Ryckaert and coworkers, treats the wormlike micelle as a string of beads that can break and fuse end-to-end, and is fast enough to allow for the equilibration of micelle length distributions, with and without flow. The PI's will incorporate into this model the potential for micelle junctions or cross links, and bundling, thereby allowing for the first time a molecular scale simulation of flow induced gel formation. 4) Kinetic Model and Constitutive Equation. The PI's will attempt to draw from the simulations the ingredients necessary to build a kinetic model and, if possible, a full nonlinear constitutive equation for flow of thread like micelles. Through this set of interlocking simulations, each aimed at different length and time scales, complemented by experiments, the investigators have developed a roadmap to bridge between molecular properties and macroscopic flow effects such as flow induced gelation and shear banding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts include a collaboration with scientists at Proctor and Gamble, whose nterest is in understanding, modeling, and controlling the properties of thread like micellar solutions. They plan annual meetings between P&amp;G scientists and our team of graduate and undergraduate students and faculty as well as month long student interships at P&amp;G. This will lead to fruitful exchange of ideas, bringing practical commercial concerns to the attention of students, and carrying novel fundamental ideas and new modeling methods into the corporate world. They plan to  also recruit UG (REU) as well as school students including minority students (through STARS program at Washington University) and involve them in developing modules driven by fast GROMACS and MARTINI engines with coarse grained potentials to help learn self assembly in surfactant solutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1049454</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Radhakrishna</FirstName>
<LastName>Sureshkumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Radhakrishna Sureshkumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rsureshk@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154433194</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000188980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1414</Code>
<Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>051E</Code>
<Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>056E</Code>
<Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~63492</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~54983</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~56517</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Surfactants are ubiquitous &ldquo;soapy&rdquo; materials. They are present in almost every walk of life and technology: in laundry detergents and shampoos, lungs to ensure normal alveolar function, emulsions, therapeutics, cosmetics, fire fighting chemicals and fluid mixtures used in enhanced oil recovery. Their chemical structure is quite unique. A surfactant molecule is typically made up of two parts: a water-loving (hydrophilic) head and an oily (hydrophobic) tail. In an aqueous solvent, surfactants can assemble into spherical, cylindrical (rodlike), vesicular or lamellar shapes, known as <em>micelles</em>, such that the hydrophilic heads are exposed to the surrounding water molecules while the oily tail groups lie hidden from the solvent. Spherical and rodlike micelles are nano-scale objects since their diameters are on the order of a few billionth of a meter (or a few nanometers). Efficient means have been sought to pack micellar rods into 3-D architectures which have nano-sized holes and channels. Such nanogels offer great potential as templates for synthesizing new materials for sensing, cellular delivery, catalysis and photonics. For instance, in NSF-supported interdisciplinary research we discovered a robust flow-assisted technique to irreversibly assemble rodlike micelles into permanent nanostructured gels (Vasudevan et al., <em>Nature Materials</em>, 9: 436-441 (2010)).</p> <p>Surfactants also have the ability to self assemble with nanoparticles to form a corona or a double-layer vesicular structure. Such structures, upon further interaction with wormlike micelle fragments, could form micelle-nanoparticle networks. Micelle-metal NP complexes are the fundamental structural units of many active nanofluids that exhibit tunable optical/magnetic properties. Rational design and manufacturing of such fluids is of critical importance to optofluidics and light trapping/guiding in photoelectric devices including thin film solar cells.</p> <p>Amongst micellar structures, cylindrical or wormlike micelles are known to exhibit rich rheological behavior because microstructural changes such as length or entanglement can be induced in micellar phases by altering surfactant and salt concentration, salt hydrophobicity, temperature/pH, and importantly by flow deformation. Specifically, depending on the surfactant concentration, chemical environment that has a pronounced influence on the underlying&nbsp; electrostatic interactions and shear rate, cylindrical micelle solutions could exhibit Newtonian, shear thinning, i.e., decrease of shear viscosity with increasing shear rate, shear induced structure formation that manifests as shear thickening or shear banding .While phenomenological, kinetic-theory inspired and continuum-level constitutive&nbsp; models&nbsp; have been developed to study the dynamics and rheology of cylindrical micelles, molecular-level explorations of flow-structure coupling in micelle solutions has been lacking.</p> <p>Based on the above background and motivation, the major research goals of the project were as follows.</p> <ol> <li>Develop faithful simulations to explore the molecular mechanisms of self-assembly in surfactant solutions and determine the effect of added salt on the binary interaction between self-assembled objects.</li> <li>Study the effect of flow shear on cylindrical micelles and binary interactions between cylindrical micelles using molecular dynamics simulations to understand the mechanisms of shear-induced structure formation in micelle solutions.</li> <li>Study the self-assembly of micelles and metal nanoparticles leading to the formation of plasmonic nanogels with tunable optical properties. </li> <li>Explore the use of surfactant stabilized nanoparticle solutions in manufacturing metal nanoparticle interfaces capable of efficient light trapping in thin film solar cells.</li> </ol> <p>The project served as a mechanism to nucleate, ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Surfactants are ubiquitous "soapy" materials. They are present in almost every walk of life and technology: in laundry detergents and shampoos, lungs to ensure normal alveolar function, emulsions, therapeutics, cosmetics, fire fighting chemicals and fluid mixtures used in enhanced oil recovery. Their chemical structure is quite unique. A surfactant molecule is typically made up of two parts: a water-loving (hydrophilic) head and an oily (hydrophobic) tail. In an aqueous solvent, surfactants can assemble into spherical, cylindrical (rodlike), vesicular or lamellar shapes, known as micelles, such that the hydrophilic heads are exposed to the surrounding water molecules while the oily tail groups lie hidden from the solvent. Spherical and rodlike micelles are nano-scale objects since their diameters are on the order of a few billionth of a meter (or a few nanometers). Efficient means have been sought to pack micellar rods into 3-D architectures which have nano-sized holes and channels. Such nanogels offer great potential as templates for synthesizing new materials for sensing, cellular delivery, catalysis and photonics. For instance, in NSF-supported interdisciplinary research we discovered a robust flow-assisted technique to irreversibly assemble rodlike micelles into permanent nanostructured gels (Vasudevan et al., Nature Materials, 9: 436-441 (2010)).  Surfactants also have the ability to self assemble with nanoparticles to form a corona or a double-layer vesicular structure. Such structures, upon further interaction with wormlike micelle fragments, could form micelle-nanoparticle networks. Micelle-metal NP complexes are the fundamental structural units of many active nanofluids that exhibit tunable optical/magnetic properties. Rational design and manufacturing of such fluids is of critical importance to optofluidics and light trapping/guiding in photoelectric devices including thin film solar cells.  Amongst micellar structures, cylindrical or wormlike micelles are known to exhibit rich rheological behavior because microstructural changes such as length or entanglement can be induced in micellar phases by altering surfactant and salt concentration, salt hydrophobicity, temperature/pH, and importantly by flow deformation. Specifically, depending on the surfactant concentration, chemical environment that has a pronounced influence on the underlying  electrostatic interactions and shear rate, cylindrical micelle solutions could exhibit Newtonian, shear thinning, i.e., decrease of shear viscosity with increasing shear rate, shear induced structure formation that manifests as shear thickening or shear banding .While phenomenological, kinetic-theory inspired and continuum-level constitutive  models  have been developed to study the dynamics and rheology of cylindrical micelles, molecular-level explorations of flow-structure coupling in micelle solutions has been lacking.  Based on the above background and motivation, the major research goals of the project were as follows.  Develop faithful simulations to explore the molecular mechanisms of self-assembly in surfactant solutions and determine the effect of added salt on the binary interaction between self-assembled objects. Study the effect of flow shear on cylindrical micelles and binary interactions between cylindrical micelles using molecular dynamics simulations to understand the mechanisms of shear-induced structure formation in micelle solutions. Study the self-assembly of micelles and metal nanoparticles leading to the formation of plasmonic nanogels with tunable optical properties.  Explore the use of surfactant stabilized nanoparticle solutions in manufacturing metal nanoparticle interfaces capable of efficient light trapping in thin film solar cells.   The project served as a mechanism to nucleate, support and nurture a number of bright individuals including three post-doctoral fellows, five graduate students and two undergraduate scholars. Our principal accomplishments a...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
