<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Acquisition of a new noble gas mass spectrometer and extraction system for the University of Michigan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>577010.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>652010</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support the acquisition of a new noble gas mass spectrometer and construction of two new extraction lines ? one for crustal fluids and one for rocks and minerals in the Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences at the University of Michigan. Current equipment at the University of Michigan is old and is now taking a toll in terms of measurement efficiency as well as its ability to reach greater levels of accuracy made possible with more modern equipment. As the PI and co-PIs?s research interests have also expanded, the current MAP215 and extraction system have been pressed into service analyzing samples that are far more challenging than the originally planned freshwater samples. Pursuing new directions of research requires new and more robust extraction and purification noble gas lines as well as a new, more capable mass spectrometer which will enable the analysis of a wider variety of samples. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual achievements made possible through the acquisition of a new mass spectrometer as well as the construction of two new extraction systems are multiple. For example, it will allow us to conduct routine studies of noble gases in old fluids in cratonic regions to further investigate their potential in holding and preserving solar noble gas signatures. It will also lead to an improved understanding of noble gas behavior in the unsaturated zone and thus, improved noble gas temperature models and more accurate paleoclimate reconstructions in continental areas. Acquisition of this new equipment will also lead to a better understanding of noble gases behavior in ice and glaciers allowing us to place constraints in the temporal evolution of covered ice lakes (e.g., in Antarctica) and thus, on the past climate in the region. Furthermore, analyses of noble gas isotopes in mantle rocks will allow new insights into mantle geochemistry.   Overall, the improved precision and enhanced output resulting from this award will have a major positive impact on multiple fields, from Mantle Geochemistry to Paleoclimatology, Hydrogeology and the Environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1049822</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Youxue</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Youxue Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>youxue@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347630947</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000226809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chris M Hall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmhall@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347646391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000319595</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M. Clara</FirstName>
<LastName>Castro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>M. Clara Castro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mccastro@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346153812</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000178559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7977</Code>
<Text>CR-Water Sustainability &amp; Clim</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~301807</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~350203</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The stable noble gases (helium, neon, argon, krypton and xenon) are chemically inert elements that play a vital role in tracing the history of many processes above, below and upon the earth&rsquo;s surface. They can be used to pinpoint the origin of rocks and fluids using a host of isotopes that indicate whether a gas derived from radioactive decay within the crust, or came from primordial fluids in the mantle, or even if they originated from the atmosphere. Our objective was to create a new modern noble gas laboratory that could routinely measure noble gas concentrations and isotopic ratios quickly and with high precision from a variety of sample materials. This has been accomplished using a totally automated system employing two mass spectrometers, a cryogenic noble gas separation bench, a fluid noble gas extraction bench and an extraction bench dedicated to handling rock samples. The automation software can routinely handle a wide range of sample types and sizes without user intervention and acquire data on all five stable noble gases within about 4.5 hours. Volume estimates are highly reproducible, with most gas concentrations measured at the percent level of precision and reproducibility is often better. Isotope ratio measurements for fluid samples typically have precision at roughly the ~0.1% level, but for samples with nearly atmospheric Ne and Ar isotopic ratios, we can usually achieve precision at the 0.01-0.02 % level. This level of precision has allowed us to detect extremely subtle signs of isotope separation that can shed light on the detailed mechanisms of noble gas transport, especially between the liquid and gas phases.</p> <p>&nbsp;Examples of the applications of the new laboratory include:</p> <ul> <li>Characterizing the noble gas      signatures of natural gas from both conventional and enhanced gas recovery      fields. This is vital in the study of the possible effects of hydraulic      fracturing on domestic drinking water supply.</li> <li>Measuring the effects of the      exclusion of heavy noble gases in perennially ice-covered Antarctic Lakes      (e.g., Bonney, Hoare and Fryxell), which reveals the history of the      thickness and depth of the lakes&rsquo; ice cover and, indirectly, the evolution      of past climate in the region.</li> <li>Characterizing the mechanisms      of the incorporation of noble gases within snow crystals, which verified      that melting snow within storms is a viable cause of the previously      discovered enrichment of He and the depletion of heavy noble gases within      rain water.</li> <li>Measurement of noble gases in      meltwater from the termini of two glaciers, one continental and the other      alpine. Noble gases were able to constrain the source altitude of the      meltwater and the buildup of radiogenic He was used to estimate possible      water residence times.</li> <li>Measurement of noble gases      within Mexico geothermal fields and in one case, it was shown that,      contrary to previous estimates, a field that was assumed to be regularly      recharged with modern meteoric water appears to need artificial recharge      in order to remain viable.</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2018<br>      Modified by: M. Clara&nbsp;Castro</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The stable noble gases (helium, neon, argon, krypton and xenon) are chemically inert elements that play a vital role in tracing the history of many processes above, below and upon the earth?s surface. They can be used to pinpoint the origin of rocks and fluids using a host of isotopes that indicate whether a gas derived from radioactive decay within the crust, or came from primordial fluids in the mantle, or even if they originated from the atmosphere. Our objective was to create a new modern noble gas laboratory that could routinely measure noble gas concentrations and isotopic ratios quickly and with high precision from a variety of sample materials. This has been accomplished using a totally automated system employing two mass spectrometers, a cryogenic noble gas separation bench, a fluid noble gas extraction bench and an extraction bench dedicated to handling rock samples. The automation software can routinely handle a wide range of sample types and sizes without user intervention and acquire data on all five stable noble gases within about 4.5 hours. Volume estimates are highly reproducible, with most gas concentrations measured at the percent level of precision and reproducibility is often better. Isotope ratio measurements for fluid samples typically have precision at roughly the ~0.1% level, but for samples with nearly atmospheric Ne and Ar isotopic ratios, we can usually achieve precision at the 0.01-0.02 % level. This level of precision has allowed us to detect extremely subtle signs of isotope separation that can shed light on the detailed mechanisms of noble gas transport, especially between the liquid and gas phases.   Examples of the applications of the new laboratory include:  Characterizing the noble gas      signatures of natural gas from both conventional and enhanced gas recovery      fields. This is vital in the study of the possible effects of hydraulic      fracturing on domestic drinking water supply. Measuring the effects of the      exclusion of heavy noble gases in perennially ice-covered Antarctic Lakes      (e.g., Bonney, Hoare and Fryxell), which reveals the history of the      thickness and depth of the lakes? ice cover and, indirectly, the evolution      of past climate in the region. Characterizing the mechanisms      of the incorporation of noble gases within snow crystals, which verified      that melting snow within storms is a viable cause of the previously      discovered enrichment of He and the depletion of heavy noble gases within      rain water. Measurement of noble gases in      meltwater from the termini of two glaciers, one continental and the other      alpine. Noble gases were able to constrain the source altitude of the      meltwater and the buildup of radiogenic He was used to estimate possible      water residence times. Measurement of noble gases      within Mexico geothermal fields and in one case, it was shown that,      contrary to previous estimates, a field that was assumed to be regularly      recharged with modern meteoric water appears to need artificial recharge      in order to remain viable.        Last Modified: 06/04/2018       Submitted by: M. Clara Castro]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
