<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Environmental Bioaerosol Generation and Potential Environmental Health Risks with Hydrocarbon Weathering on Oil-Spill Impacted Shoreline</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>168886.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>168886</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This rapid response project will collect long-term composite aerosol samples from pristine and oil-impacted shorelines under various weather conditions through the warmest (most biologically active) months.  This study will examine the microbiological and chemical composition of airborne particulate matter proximal to clean-up operations.  Additionally, toxicological properties of the aerosols will be analyzed for potential health impacts associated with respiratory exposure routes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1049388</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernard</FirstName>
<LastName>Singleton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernard Singleton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bsingleton@dillard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5048164308</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000079494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Hernandez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Hernandez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mark.hernandez@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034925991</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000568032</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Environmental Forensics LLC</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803056649</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3035033518</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4355 Butler Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[University of Colorado]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>016334634</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ENVIRONMENTAL FORENSICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Environmental Forensics LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803056649</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4355 Butler Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5987</Code>
<Text>GULF OF MEXICO OIL SPILL-2010</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~168886</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There is a growing body of evidence suggesting that both biogenic and inorganic pools of airborne particles can act as potent adjuvants that sensitize lungs and mucosal membranes to air pollution.&nbsp; This sensitization manifests through a broad spectrum of serious health effects, some of which are well known infectious diseases, but many of which fall into generic respiratory diseases including, but not limited to, allergenic, hypersensitivity and toxigenic responses which can often present as asthma.&nbsp; With the rapid growth of respiratory illnesses over the last generation come their association with poor air quality from large-scale disasters: floods, storms, terrorist activities and earthquakes.&nbsp; However, there is relatively little information regarding aerosol exposures to petroleum products outside occupational exposures, and regulatory criteria for oil spills have not been defined from an epidemiological perspective appropriate for clean-up operations.</p> <p>The primary scientific goal of this study was to comprehensively characterize and compare biological aerosol loads from oil-polluted beaches to those of pristine environments from the same region: biochemically, ecologically and toxicologically. &nbsp;Popular recreational beaches in the proximity of Dillard University and Houston, served as field sites for this demonstration study.&nbsp; Dillard is a historically black college in New Orleans, which maintains an active environmental microbiology and public health program.&nbsp; Mentoring from the University of Colorado&rsquo;s graduate bioaerosol research group was formally extended to Dillard&rsquo;s students, who were trained in modern (bio)aerosol assessment techniques through intra-company and university exchanges.</p> <p><br /><strong><em>The intrinsic scientific merits</em></strong><em> </em>of this study manifest in establishing a robust suite of fundamental aerobiological characterization tools for ambient aerosols, to include biochemical and toxicological indices which have never collectively been used in a remedial atmospheric environment before. <strong><em>Broader reaching impacts</em></strong> stem from a discovery-driven partnership between a start-up company, an &ldquo;R1&rdquo; University with extensive bioaerosol and environmental engineering expertise, and an Historically Black college recovering from Hurricane Katrina.&nbsp; This project enhanced Dillard&rsquo;s educational infrastructure and brought modern industrial hygiene training capabilities to underrepresented students in a region that because of Katrina, no longer has Environmental Engineering programs (Tulane has closed its program following Katrina).</p> <p>While gaseous air pollutants have received much attention following oil spills, the biological <em>content </em>as well as the biological <em>activity</em> of aerosols (collectively termed "bioaerosols") generated by weathering oil has largely been ignored by the regulatory community &mdash; most notably in the context of the potential environmental health risks associated with coastal clean up operations.&nbsp; In response, this work adapted quantitative biochemistry and molecular biology methods for use in coastal atmospheric environments, with the express purpose of assessing the composition and toxicological properties of bioaerosols above oil-impacted beaches during clean-up<br />operations.</p> <p>The outcomes of this work demonstrated, for the first time, how a suite<br />of ambient air samples can be recovered with common aerosol collection<br />equipment, and analyzed for converging lines of evidence which suggest the following: there can be (i) a significant local enrichment of bioaerosols; and (ii) such (bio)aerosols may carry potential toxicological activity in the<br />vicinity of coastal weathering (spilled) oil.&nbsp; This work demonstrated a fundamental basis for a regulatory suite of air quality indices to include more robust bioaerosol analyses in the future, for the express purpose of linking biological characterization of atmospheric environments with remedial practices.&nbsp; This work also served as a novel educational model for industrial-university cooperation applicable to both "start-ups" and mature companies: Dillard&rsquo;s microbiology division now has proficiency in this emerging area of industrial hygiene, and this aspect of their environmental science program is now self-funded and engaged in longer-term bioaerosol monitoring/research of these, and other polluted environments in the Gulf region.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/11/2012<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Hernandez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1049388/1049388_10020388_1326313656426_DSC00540--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1049388/1049388_10020388_1326313656426_DSC00540--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Aerosol Sampling during Oil Spill Clean Up Operations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1049388/1049388_10020388_1326313656426_DSC00540--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Aerosol Sampling during Oil Spill Clean Up Operations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">University of Colorado PhD Candidate Jane Turner, teaching Dillard University student teams how to sample biological aerosols using state of the art collection equipment during the clean-up of weathering oil washed ashore on Grand Isle State Beach, LA</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alison Ling</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;Hernandez</div> <div class="imageTitle">Aerosol Sampling during Oil Spill Clean Up Operations</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There is a growing body of evidence suggesting that both biogenic and inorganic pools of airborne particles can act as potent adjuvants that sensitize lungs and mucosal membranes to air pollution.  This sensitization manifests through a broad spectrum of serious health effects, some of which are well known infectious diseases, but many of which fall into generic respiratory diseases including, but not limited to, allergenic, hypersensitivity and toxigenic responses which can often present as asthma.  With the rapid growth of respiratory illnesses over the last generation come their association with poor air quality from large-scale disasters: floods, storms, terrorist activities and earthquakes.  However, there is relatively little information regarding aerosol exposures to petroleum products outside occupational exposures, and regulatory criteria for oil spills have not been defined from an epidemiological perspective appropriate for clean-up operations.  The primary scientific goal of this study was to comprehensively characterize and compare biological aerosol loads from oil-polluted beaches to those of pristine environments from the same region: biochemically, ecologically and toxicologically.  Popular recreational beaches in the proximity of Dillard University and Houston, served as field sites for this demonstration study.  Dillard is a historically black college in New Orleans, which maintains an active environmental microbiology and public health program.  Mentoring from the University of Colorado?s graduate bioaerosol research group was formally extended to Dillard?s students, who were trained in modern (bio)aerosol assessment techniques through intra-company and university exchanges.   The intrinsic scientific merits of this study manifest in establishing a robust suite of fundamental aerobiological characterization tools for ambient aerosols, to include biochemical and toxicological indices which have never collectively been used in a remedial atmospheric environment before. Broader reaching impacts stem from a discovery-driven partnership between a start-up company, an "R1" University with extensive bioaerosol and environmental engineering expertise, and an Historically Black college recovering from Hurricane Katrina.  This project enhanced Dillard?s educational infrastructure and brought modern industrial hygiene training capabilities to underrepresented students in a region that because of Katrina, no longer has Environmental Engineering programs (Tulane has closed its program following Katrina).  While gaseous air pollutants have received much attention following oil spills, the biological content as well as the biological activity of aerosols (collectively termed "bioaerosols") generated by weathering oil has largely been ignored by the regulatory community &mdash; most notably in the context of the potential environmental health risks associated with coastal clean up operations.  In response, this work adapted quantitative biochemistry and molecular biology methods for use in coastal atmospheric environments, with the express purpose of assessing the composition and toxicological properties of bioaerosols above oil-impacted beaches during clean-up operations.  The outcomes of this work demonstrated, for the first time, how a suite of ambient air samples can be recovered with common aerosol collection equipment, and analyzed for converging lines of evidence which suggest the following: there can be (i) a significant local enrichment of bioaerosols; and (ii) such (bio)aerosols may carry potential toxicological activity in the vicinity of coastal weathering (spilled) oil.  This work demonstrated a fundamental basis for a regulatory suite of air quality indices to include more robust bioaerosol analyses in the future, for the express purpose of linking biological characterization of atmospheric environments with remedial practices.  This work also served as a novel educational model for industrial-university cooperation applicable to both "start-ups" and mature companies: Dillard?s microbiology division now has proficiency in this emerging area of industrial hygiene, and this aspect of their environmental science program is now self-funded and engaged in longer-term bioaerosol monitoring/research of these, and other polluted environments in the Gulf region.       Last Modified: 01/11/2012       Submitted by: Mark Hernandez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
