<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Type 1- L02170391: Collaborative Research:  Atmosphere-Ocean Coupling Causing Ice Shelf Melt in Antarctica (ACCIMA)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>374811.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>374811</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) represents about 10% of the entire Antarctic ice sheet. The WAIS is currently losing mass due to several of its outlet glaciers draining into the Amundsen Sea. The rate of this mass loss, over natural accretion through snowfall, has also been increasing in recent years. One possible reason for this is increased basal melt of the seaward floating ice shelves of the region's terminal glaciers. This can result from a change in either the temperature, or circulation patterns, of the relatively warm Circumpolar Deep Water (CDW) that enters the subglacial zone,  providing heat to increase the basal melt rate. Because much of the WAIS bed lies well below sea-level and is therefore theoretically unstable, there is considerable interest in its stability and mobility of the WAIS ice shelves in a warming ocean.  Complete disintegration of the WAIS could in principle raise global sea levels by as much as 4.8 m. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the coupling of large scale atmospheric circulation patterns such as the El-Nino Southern Oscillation (ENSO) and the Southern Annular Mode (SAM), changes in ocean temperature and current regimes, along with the complexity of glacial bed physics and importantly the timescales over which these components interact is a challenging modeling and computational task. A team of researchers from Ohio State, Old Dominion University and NYU will develop and couple components of an earth systems model for the Southern Ocean with a regional emphasis on the West Antarctic. The component system models to be coupled include the polar-optimized version of the Weather Research and Forecasting model (Polar WRF) for the atmosphere. The ocean component will be the Regional Ocean Modeling System (ROMS), and the sea ice component will be the Los Alamos sea ice model (CICE). Retrospective decadal simulations will be done to understand recent past variability. Downscaled future projections for Antarctica will be driven by the global National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Community Climate Model (CCSM or its equivalent), which is also being used for the IPCC 5th Assessment simulations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is a responsive submission to the CRI-EaSM solicitation with goals to maximize the utility of available observational and model data for impact assessments through scaling activities and to effectively translate model results and associated uncertainties into the scientific basis for well-informed human adaptation to and management decisions for climate change, specifically addressing the risk of significant sea-level rise in the next century.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1049081</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Holland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Holland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmh4@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129983245</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000153243</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/07/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~374811</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 8pt;"><span style="font-family: Calibri;"><span style="font-size: small;">Understanding heat and freshwater content change in the Antarctic continental shelf areas is important for understanding the basal melting of ice shelves, an important component of understanding glacier drawdown and sea-level rise.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">This project analyzed the heat and freshwater budgets using a coupled climate model, which was built for a domain including the Antarctic shelves and the bulk of the Southern Ocean.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">A new technique that utilizes passive tracers was introduced to track the oceanic transport across the Antarctic continental shelf break.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">Compared to an existing technique, this tracer-based estimate provides additional information on horizontal and vertical structure of the oceanic transport with minimal expenses in accuracy.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">For the entire Antarctic shelf seas, it is found that while the surface exchange with the atmosphere and sea ice explains the most of the annual cycle in total heat and freshwater content change, the oceanic transport constantly provides heat and freshwater onto the shelf, and balances out the surface exchange.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">Two distinct annual cycles, one in the upper layer (0-300 m) and the other in the lower layer (300 m and below) are found for the Antarctic shelf seas.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">Unlike the upper layer, which is dominated by the surface processes, in the lower layer, the oceanic transport plays an important role in the heat and freshwater change. </span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-size: small;">For local shelf seas, except the Amundsen-Bellingshausen shelf sea, positive on-shelf heat and freshwater transport by the ocean are found.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">For the Amundsen-Bellingshausen shelf sea, the ocean instead takes freshwater away from the shelf, indicating flooding of warm Circumpolar Deep Water is dominant for this region.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-size: small;">Combined with the fact that remote sensing has shown that glaciers in this area are undergoing the most dramatic change in all of Antarctica, this finding provides computational evidence that the ocean is driving this change.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/07/2015<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Holland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Understanding heat and freshwater content change in the Antarctic continental shelf areas is important for understanding the basal melting of ice shelves, an important component of understanding glacier drawdown and sea-level rise.  This project analyzed the heat and freshwater budgets using a coupled climate model, which was built for a domain including the Antarctic shelves and the bulk of the Southern Ocean.  A new technique that utilizes passive tracers was introduced to track the oceanic transport across the Antarctic continental shelf break.  Compared to an existing technique, this tracer-based estimate provides additional information on horizontal and vertical structure of the oceanic transport with minimal expenses in accuracy.  For the entire Antarctic shelf seas, it is found that while the surface exchange with the atmosphere and sea ice explains the most of the annual cycle in total heat and freshwater content change, the oceanic transport constantly provides heat and freshwater onto the shelf, and balances out the surface exchange.  Two distinct annual cycles, one in the upper layer (0-300 m) and the other in the lower layer (300 m and below) are found for the Antarctic shelf seas.  Unlike the upper layer, which is dominated by the surface processes, in the lower layer, the oceanic transport plays an important role in the heat and freshwater change.  For local shelf seas, except the Amundsen-Bellingshausen shelf sea, positive on-shelf heat and freshwater transport by the ocean are found.  For the Amundsen-Bellingshausen shelf sea, the ocean instead takes freshwater away from the shelf, indicating flooding of warm Circumpolar Deep Water is dominant for this region.   Combined with the fact that remote sensing has shown that glaciers in this area are undergoing the most dramatic change in all of Antarctica, this finding provides computational evidence that the ocean is driving this change.             Last Modified: 05/07/2015       Submitted by: David M Holland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
