<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computational Studies of Folding and Dynamics of Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>861203.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1091317</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaroslaw Majewski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmajewsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927278</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The mechanism of folding of proteins to their native structure is a subject of significant interest in biology. Proteins perform most of the molecular level functions in the cell. In addition, proteins are nanoscale molecular machines that can perform tasks important for biotechnology applications.  It is well known that the marginal stability of proteins can be altered by changing solvent conditions, such as application of pressure, or addition of co-solvents. Computer simulations can provide an atomic level picture of the mechanisms by which solvent (mostly water), co-solvents, and physical effects, such as pressure and temperature, affect protein stability. The combined use of enhanced sampling methods and parallel computing enable the study of protein folding/unfolding equilibrium and dynamics. The objective of this project is to study the folding/unfolding equilibrium and kinetics of model proteins with increased degree of complexity. The simulations will explore the effects of co-solvents and hydrostatic pressure on the transition states and will help understand the effect of solvent in determining the transition state of proteins and will provide a measure of the folding/unfolding activation volumes. These calculations will be done on model proteins that fold in the microsecond timescale and for which there is ample kinetics and thermodynamics experimental data available. In addition to folding, this project will explore the functional dynamics of the proteins - that is, correlate the existence of sub-states in the energy landscape with functional states of the proteins.  The overall goal is to examine the equilibrium folding/unfolding, the energy landscape, the folding kinetics and dynamics of protein domains involved in protein-protein interactions and switching. These proteins fold in the microsecond to 100 microsecond timescales. The kinetics and functional dynamics of these proteins will be studied using Markov state models built from a very large number of independent simulations. Theories related to the allosteric effect in proteins will be tested. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is interdisciplinary in nature and includes the use of physical and computational methods to describe basic steps in the functioning of biological models. An important element of this project is the training of scientists with expertise in physics, biology and computational methods.  This training will be done with students at various levels of education - including high school, undergraduate and graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows. Another equally important element of this research is the commitment to enhance participation of underrepresented groups in research. The PI's laboratory has continuously hosted and will continue to host minority and women undergraduates doing research in the group. Many of these students have now obtained PhDs or are pursuing graduate studies.  This project is jointly supported by Molecular Biophysics in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences in the Directorate for Biological Sciences and the Physics of Living Systems Program in the Division of Physics in the Mathematical and Physical Sciences Directorate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1050966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angel</FirstName>
<LastName>Garcia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angel E Garcia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>angel@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182764206</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000479209</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/11/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Royer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A Royer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>royerc@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182763796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1164</Code>
<Text>MOLECULAR BIOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~666317</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project we studied the structure and dynamics of model proteins and nucleic acids (RNA) by molecular dynamics computer simulations. We emphasized the effects of temperature, pressure, and solution conditions on the stability and dynamics of biomolecules. The computer simulations were combined, when possible, with thermodynamics and structural experimental validation. The results obtained in our project are important for determining, from first principles, the factors that affect the structure and function of biomolecules and their possible relevance for developing new therapeutics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Of particular importance were the studies of co-solvents on biomolecular stability. The use of co-solvents is important in industry applications in which proteins used as therapeutics are preserved by the presence osmolytes. We found that TMAO and urea, a typical osmolytes found in nature, can be used to tune up or down the stability of proteins. We studied the reversible folding/unfolding thermodynamics of a model protein, trp-cage, under a broad range of temperature, pressure, and co-solvent conditions. We found that urea destabilize proteins by preferentially interacting with the protein sidechains over the protein backbone, in agreement with recent experimental work. The interaction of urea with protein sidechains favors the interaction of urea with the unfolded state over the folded state. We also found that TMAO stabilize proteins by excluding the osmolyte from the protein surface, thus stabilizing the folded state over the unfolded state. Interestingly, the effect of these two co-solutes balance each other, and the stability of proteins can be modulated by combining both stabilizing and denaturing osmolytes. This effect has been observed in deep see animals, like sharks. Comparison of the high pressure effects on trp cage with high pressure NMR revealed a novel folded conformation of this peptide, which is highly used for benchmarking in simulations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also studied the effect of high hydrostatic pressure on protein dynamics. We were able to describe, both computationally and by novel high-pressure NMR experiments, how pressure modulates the energy landscape and dynamics of proteins in ways that are very different from denaturants, osmolytes and temperature.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also studied the interaction of signaling proteins, e.g., G-protein coupling receptors (GPCR) with the lipid membrane environment. GPCR is a large family of proteins involved in cell signaling. Multiple drugs currently in the market interact with GPCRs. The structure of GPCRs and their interactions with G-proteins have been recently obtained by x-ray crystallography, and led to the Novel Prize in Chemistry in 2012. However, the dynamics and interactions of GPCR are not well understood. We studied the interactions of a GPCR with lipids and found that lipids can bind to GPCR and maintain the active state conformation in absence of the G-protein. This work has implications in the design of chemicals that can modulate the function of specific GPCRs and serve as drugs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Another important kind of molecules involved in regulation of biological functions are RNA molecules. The computer simulations of RNA molecules have been limited by the accuracy of the energy models (force fields) used to describe their interactions. In this project we developed a new model for RNA interactions. With this model we were able to describe accurately the structure of small RNA structural motifs called tetraloops. Our methods were able to reproduce the structure of all hyperstable tetraloop families. Using high performance computer simulations we were able to study the reversible folding/unfolding equilibrium of these structures. We also studied the effect of a co-solute, urea, and hydrostatic pressure on changing the free energy landscape of RN tetraloops. Future work will include the characterization of the effect of stabilizing osmolytes (e.g., TMAO) on RNA. Finally, preliminary work on high pressure NMR studies on RNA to compare to the theoretical results was carried out.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Royer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1050966/1050966_10066041_1488229059103_Kitazawa_et_al_Figure_8--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1050966/1050966_10066041_1488229059103_Kitazawa_et_al_Figure_8--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Novel high pressure conformation of Trp Cage"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1050966/1050966_10066041_1488229059103_Kitazawa_et_al_Figure_8--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Novel high pressure conformation of Trp Cage"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Main centroid structure for each state of the Tc5b native state ensemble. Overlapped structures represent the different simulation conditions. Colors correspond to the conditions, with blue, red, black, and green representing low density 297.6K, low density 285K, high density 297.K and high density</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kitazawa et al. J Chem Phys B Figure 8</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Royer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Novel high pressure conformation of Trp Cage</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project we studied the structure and dynamics of model proteins and nucleic acids (RNA) by molecular dynamics computer simulations. We emphasized the effects of temperature, pressure, and solution conditions on the stability and dynamics of biomolecules. The computer simulations were combined, when possible, with thermodynamics and structural experimental validation. The results obtained in our project are important for determining, from first principles, the factors that affect the structure and function of biomolecules and their possible relevance for developing new therapeutics.     Of particular importance were the studies of co-solvents on biomolecular stability. The use of co-solvents is important in industry applications in which proteins used as therapeutics are preserved by the presence osmolytes. We found that TMAO and urea, a typical osmolytes found in nature, can be used to tune up or down the stability of proteins. We studied the reversible folding/unfolding thermodynamics of a model protein, trp-cage, under a broad range of temperature, pressure, and co-solvent conditions. We found that urea destabilize proteins by preferentially interacting with the protein sidechains over the protein backbone, in agreement with recent experimental work. The interaction of urea with protein sidechains favors the interaction of urea with the unfolded state over the folded state. We also found that TMAO stabilize proteins by excluding the osmolyte from the protein surface, thus stabilizing the folded state over the unfolded state. Interestingly, the effect of these two co-solutes balance each other, and the stability of proteins can be modulated by combining both stabilizing and denaturing osmolytes. This effect has been observed in deep see animals, like sharks. Comparison of the high pressure effects on trp cage with high pressure NMR revealed a novel folded conformation of this peptide, which is highly used for benchmarking in simulations.     We also studied the effect of high hydrostatic pressure on protein dynamics. We were able to describe, both computationally and by novel high-pressure NMR experiments, how pressure modulates the energy landscape and dynamics of proteins in ways that are very different from denaturants, osmolytes and temperature.     We also studied the interaction of signaling proteins, e.g., G-protein coupling receptors (GPCR) with the lipid membrane environment. GPCR is a large family of proteins involved in cell signaling. Multiple drugs currently in the market interact with GPCRs. The structure of GPCRs and their interactions with G-proteins have been recently obtained by x-ray crystallography, and led to the Novel Prize in Chemistry in 2012. However, the dynamics and interactions of GPCR are not well understood. We studied the interactions of a GPCR with lipids and found that lipids can bind to GPCR and maintain the active state conformation in absence of the G-protein. This work has implications in the design of chemicals that can modulate the function of specific GPCRs and serve as drugs.     Another important kind of molecules involved in regulation of biological functions are RNA molecules. The computer simulations of RNA molecules have been limited by the accuracy of the energy models (force fields) used to describe their interactions. In this project we developed a new model for RNA interactions. With this model we were able to describe accurately the structure of small RNA structural motifs called tetraloops. Our methods were able to reproduce the structure of all hyperstable tetraloop families. Using high performance computer simulations we were able to study the reversible folding/unfolding equilibrium of these structures. We also studied the effect of a co-solute, urea, and hydrostatic pressure on changing the free energy landscape of RN tetraloops. Future work will include the characterization of the effect of stabilizing osmolytes (e.g., TMAO) on RNA. Finally, preliminary work on high pressure NMR studies on RNA to compare to the theoretical results was carried out.       Last Modified: 02/27/2017       Submitted by: Catherine A Royer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
