<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   Signaling and regulation of vegetative incompatibility in the plant pathogen Cryphonectria parasitica.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>447610.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>447610</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070700</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The recognition events that lead to cell fusion are crucial steps in many important biological processes. In the Fungal Kingdom, cell recognition events are well understood for such processes as mating in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (a budding yeast.) In filamentous fungi, a recognition system is also used to control vegetative fusion (anastomosis) of the hyphae. These fusion events permit the development of large networked colonies in which the older hyphae are greatly interconnected. This allows for rapid distribution of nutrients to different parts of the colony. The benefits of cell fusion also extend to the joining of two distinct colonies of the same species. Stable colonies formed by the fusion of two partners will contain two different sets of genes, one from each partner, thus producing novel genetic combinations. In addition such fusions permit more efficient foraging, since the nutritional and metabolic resources of both colonies can be pooled. However, there are inherent risks associated with this process. Viruses that infect fungi exploit these cell fusion events in order to spread from one host to another. To counteract the inherent risk of transmitting viral infection, fungi have evolved a complex genetic mechanism, called vegetative incompatibility. This permits self-fusion but prevents the fusion of two unrelated fungal colonies.  Cryphonectria parasitica, the plant pathogen responsible for the blight of the American chestnut, is a fungus that can be infected by RNA viruses that reduce the ability of the fungus to cause disease. This project will address 1) the nature of the recognition events that lead to fungal colony fusion and the transmission of the virus from one colony to another and 2) the signals that cause the fungal cells to die if the interaction is genetically incompatible. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;C. parasitica is an excellent system for integrating students into research because this fungus is simple to grow and manipulate, but at the same time it can be coupled to powerful technologies. In this collaborative project there will be opportunities for the cooperative training of undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in a minority serving institution and a research university. The integrative nature of the project will enable a high degree of interaction between the two research teams. Contributions will be made to the fields of fungal development, plant pathology and host-virus interactions. There is potential for improving virus-based biological control strategies for chestnut blight and other fungal diseases. In addition, this project will enhance undergraduate student education by integrating the research into the classroom, and it will allow graduate and undergraduate researchers to participate in scientific meetings. The results of the project will be made available in publicly accessible databases and through distribution of the data by publication, web site dissemination, and participation in scientific meetings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1051331</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Nuss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald Nuss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dnuss@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567545</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~75533</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~123476</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~122463</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~126138</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Collaborative Research: Signaling and regulation of vegetative incompatibility in the plant pathogen <em>Cryphonectria parasitica</em>.&nbsp; </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Scientific Merit</strong>:&nbsp; Non-self recognition genetic systems operate widely in filamentous fungi and are thought to limit the transmission of deleterious genetic elements.&nbsp; Interactions between genetically distinct individuals of the same fungal species result in incompatible reactions that trigger localized cell death along the zone of contact, thereby restricting the transmission of viruses and other cytoplasmic elements.&nbsp; These incompatible reactions, termed vegetative incompatibility, have significant consequences for the transmission of virulence-reducing mycoviruses that provide potential for biological control of their plant pathogenic fungal hosts.&nbsp; A major goal of this collaborative grant with Drs. Angus Dawe [New Mexico State University (NMSU)] and Donald Nuss [University of Maryland (UMD)] was to complete the molecular identification of the six genetically defined vegetative incompatibility (<em>vic</em>) loci in the chestnut blight fungus <em>Cryphonectira parasitica</em> that restrict transmission of virulence-attenuating hypoviruses.&nbsp;&nbsp; This objective was completed in full by using a novel comparative genomics approach that can be applied to other important fungi.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A second major goal was to test the hypothesis that the identified <em>vic</em> components participate in the vegetative incompatibility pathway by creating gene deletions and substitutions.&nbsp; A total of 14 genes contained within the six <em>vic</em> loci were deleted and shown to contribute to the incompatible reactions, fully completing this objective</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:&nbsp;</strong>The project provided postdoctoral fellow and graduate student exchanges between NMSU and the Institute for Bioscience and Biotechnology Research at UMD.&nbsp; Opportunities were provided for NMSU graduate students to work with postdoctoral fellows and scientists at a major university research institute and for postdoctoral fellows to observe numerous classes in graduate and undergraduate level courses and to create and deliver lectures.&nbsp; Both undergraduate students from NMSU and postdoctoral fellows from IBBR gained experience in manuscript preparation and presented at national scientific meetings.&nbsp; The identification and characterization of the <em>C. parasitica vic</em> loci provides a solid foundation for future detailed elucidation of the mechanisms underlying the initiation and regulation of fungal non-self incompatibility reaction.&nbsp; The results of this study also provide the means for manipulating the newly identified <em>vic</em> components to engineer fungal strains with enhanced ability to transmit virulence-attenuating mycoviruses. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2015<br>      Modified by: Donald&nbsp;Nuss</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Collaborative Research: Signaling and regulation of vegetative incompatibility in the plant pathogen Cryphonectria parasitica.       Scientific Merit:  Non-self recognition genetic systems operate widely in filamentous fungi and are thought to limit the transmission of deleterious genetic elements.  Interactions between genetically distinct individuals of the same fungal species result in incompatible reactions that trigger localized cell death along the zone of contact, thereby restricting the transmission of viruses and other cytoplasmic elements.  These incompatible reactions, termed vegetative incompatibility, have significant consequences for the transmission of virulence-reducing mycoviruses that provide potential for biological control of their plant pathogenic fungal hosts.  A major goal of this collaborative grant with Drs. Angus Dawe [New Mexico State University (NMSU)] and Donald Nuss [University of Maryland (UMD)] was to complete the molecular identification of the six genetically defined vegetative incompatibility (vic) loci in the chestnut blight fungus Cryphonectira parasitica that restrict transmission of virulence-attenuating hypoviruses.   This objective was completed in full by using a novel comparative genomics approach that can be applied to other important fungi.              A second major goal was to test the hypothesis that the identified vic components participate in the vegetative incompatibility pathway by creating gene deletions and substitutions.  A total of 14 genes contained within the six vic loci were deleted and shown to contribute to the incompatible reactions, fully completing this objective  Broader Impacts: The project provided postdoctoral fellow and graduate student exchanges between NMSU and the Institute for Bioscience and Biotechnology Research at UMD.  Opportunities were provided for NMSU graduate students to work with postdoctoral fellows and scientists at a major university research institute and for postdoctoral fellows to observe numerous classes in graduate and undergraduate level courses and to create and deliver lectures.  Both undergraduate students from NMSU and postdoctoral fellows from IBBR gained experience in manuscript preparation and presented at national scientific meetings.  The identification and characterization of the C. parasitica vic loci provides a solid foundation for future detailed elucidation of the mechanisms underlying the initiation and regulation of fungal non-self incompatibility reaction.  The results of this study also provide the means for manipulating the newly identified vic components to engineer fungal strains with enhanced ability to transmit virulence-attenuating mycoviruses.            Last Modified: 09/21/2015       Submitted by: Donald Nuss]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
