<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Evolution of the pheromone signaling system of Spodoptera frugiperda and Heliothis virescens</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>465000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>465000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjawor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927887</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Research on insect pheromones has enabled their use in ecologically-sound pest control in agricultural and public health systems. Pheromonal communication has also served as an important model for our understanding of the mechanisms of signal diversification and speciation in animals. However, most research has focused on female-emitted pheromones, largely ignoring close-range male-produced pheromones which are important for species-recognition and female mate choice. This project addresses two major questions: (1) How does natural variation in close-range male sexual signals affect female choice? (2) What are the evolutionary consequences if the production of male sexual signals is biochemically and genetically linked to production of female signals? Specifically, this project will chemically identify the close-range male pheromones in two moth species using a combination of behavioral and analytical approaches, quantify the magnitude of intraspecific variation in the male pheromones, and evaluate what features of the male pheromone contribute to female mate choice. The comparative project will concentrate on two ecologically and agriculturally important species, Spodoptera frugiperda (Fall Armyworm) and Heliothis virescens (Tobacco Budworm). A unique asset is that each species consists of two strains with distinct female pheromone blends. Results of this investigation will be critical not only for understanding the roles of reciprocal signaling and mate choice in the evolution of sexual communication systems in animals, but will also lead to a better understanding of how the evolution of mating preferences can lead to premating isolation among populations, and ultimately to the origin of new species. With additional support from NSF's Office of International Science and Engineering, this project will train a postdoctoral researcher, a graduate student, and undergraduate students in a unique international collaborative project with the Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology in Jena, Germany. These trainees will participate in community science education outreach programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1052238</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Coby</FirstName>
<LastName>Schal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Coby Schal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>coby_schal@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195151821</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000120614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Astrid</FirstName>
<LastName>Groot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Astrid T Groot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>astrid_groot@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195151651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000253488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2601 Wolf Village Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~172000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~113000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>The overall goal of this proposal was to address several major questions in an animal chemical communication system where the female and male pheromones chemically resemble each other: (a) What are the complete chemical signals that the female and males use? (b) What features of close-range male sexual signals affect female mate choice? and (c) Is the production of female and male sexual signals genetically and biochemically linked? Answers to these questions are critical not only for understanding the roles of reciprocal signaling and mate choice in the evolution of sexual communication systems in animals, but will also lead to a better understanding of how the evolution of mate preferences can lead to isolation among populations, and ultimately to the origin of new species. Moreover, because moths are major crop pests, understanding the chemistry of courtship signals and their behavioral effects is essential for controlling pest populations.</p> <p>We collected moths representing the natural variation in pheromone communication in agricultural fields in North Carolina. We optimized moth rearing and conducted artificial selection of lines of <em>Heliothis virescens</em> with excellent divergence of two pheromone phenotypes: One that produces high amounts of the major female pheromone (Z11-16:Ald) and another that makes instead a large amount of a related compound (16:Ald) but little Z11-16:Ald. Genetic analysis revealed that a mutation in an important gene (delta-11-desaturase) made this gene non-functional. These lines serve as an important resource because they inform us of the linkage between male and female pheromones. Indeed, genetically selected lines with low-Z11-16:Ald in the female pheromone gland also produce low-Z11-16:OAc in the male&rsquo;s pheromone gland, as we predicted.</p> <p>We also developed and optimized procedures for identifying new compounds in females and males. By coupling a gas chromatograph (GC) to an insect antenna, and electrophysiologically recording from the antenna (<span style="text-decoration: underline;">E</span>lectro<span style="text-decoration: underline;">A</span>ntennographic <span style="text-decoration: underline;">D</span>etection = EAD; hence, GC-EAD), we identified several new male compounds that elicit strong responses from female antennae. Unexpectedly, some of the new male compounds appear to be of plant origin. We documented the sequestration patterns from plant leaves and from sugar solutions and also examined the role of one of these plant compounds as a male nuptial contribution to the female.</p> <p>We conducted field studies to assess sexual selection gradients on <em>Heliothis virescens</em> female pheromones. To our knowledge, such an approach has never been implemented on an insect pheromone communication system. We recovered stabilizing selection on major pheromone components, indicating that the ratio of major components is important for attracting males. We are employing similar theory and techniques with male pheromones to pinpoint the most behaviorally important male components.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>This project produced over a dozen peer-reviewed publications and more than 30 professional presentations. Some of our research results were highlighted in the popular media. <em>Heliothis virescens</em> is a major pest of soybean, cotton and many other agricultural crops. Therefore, a better understanding of the chemistry of attraction and courtship signals and their respective behavioral effects is essential for controlling pest populations.</p> <p>Twelve undergraduates trained in our lab on this project, including several underrepresented students. In addition, one graduate student trained on this project before transitioning to an NSF-funded predoctoral fellowship. This project trained four postdoctoral researchers, two of whom moved on to independent positions in sc...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  The overall goal of this proposal was to address several major questions in an animal chemical communication system where the female and male pheromones chemically resemble each other: (a) What are the complete chemical signals that the female and males use? (b) What features of close-range male sexual signals affect female mate choice? and (c) Is the production of female and male sexual signals genetically and biochemically linked? Answers to these questions are critical not only for understanding the roles of reciprocal signaling and mate choice in the evolution of sexual communication systems in animals, but will also lead to a better understanding of how the evolution of mate preferences can lead to isolation among populations, and ultimately to the origin of new species. Moreover, because moths are major crop pests, understanding the chemistry of courtship signals and their behavioral effects is essential for controlling pest populations.  We collected moths representing the natural variation in pheromone communication in agricultural fields in North Carolina. We optimized moth rearing and conducted artificial selection of lines of Heliothis virescens with excellent divergence of two pheromone phenotypes: One that produces high amounts of the major female pheromone (Z11-16:Ald) and another that makes instead a large amount of a related compound (16:Ald) but little Z11-16:Ald. Genetic analysis revealed that a mutation in an important gene (delta-11-desaturase) made this gene non-functional. These lines serve as an important resource because they inform us of the linkage between male and female pheromones. Indeed, genetically selected lines with low-Z11-16:Ald in the female pheromone gland also produce low-Z11-16:OAc in the maleÆs pheromone gland, as we predicted.  We also developed and optimized procedures for identifying new compounds in females and males. By coupling a gas chromatograph (GC) to an insect antenna, and electrophysiologically recording from the antenna (ElectroAntennographic Detection = EAD; hence, GC-EAD), we identified several new male compounds that elicit strong responses from female antennae. Unexpectedly, some of the new male compounds appear to be of plant origin. We documented the sequestration patterns from plant leaves and from sugar solutions and also examined the role of one of these plant compounds as a male nuptial contribution to the female.  We conducted field studies to assess sexual selection gradients on Heliothis virescens female pheromones. To our knowledge, such an approach has never been implemented on an insect pheromone communication system. We recovered stabilizing selection on major pheromone components, indicating that the ratio of major components is important for attracting males. We are employing similar theory and techniques with male pheromones to pinpoint the most behaviorally important male components.  Broader Impacts:  This project produced over a dozen peer-reviewed publications and more than 30 professional presentations. Some of our research results were highlighted in the popular media. Heliothis virescens is a major pest of soybean, cotton and many other agricultural crops. Therefore, a better understanding of the chemistry of attraction and courtship signals and their respective behavioral effects is essential for controlling pest populations.  Twelve undergraduates trained in our lab on this project, including several underrepresented students. In addition, one graduate student trained on this project before transitioning to an NSF-funded predoctoral fellowship. This project trained four postdoctoral researchers, two of whom moved on to independent positions in science research and STEM education. This project was an international collaboration with Dr. Astrid Groot, at the University of Amsterdam in The Netherlands. Dr. Groot is also affiliated with the Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology (MPICE) in Jena, Germany and North Carolina Sta...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
