<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Elucidating Roles of the Haloacid Dehalogenase-Superfamily Phosphatases in Plant Cytosol</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>896821.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>896821</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070700</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>All organisms require inorganic phosphate (Pi) as a key component of nucleic acids, phosphorylated sugars, phospholipids, and phosphate-containing cofactors. Pi is also a participant in signal transduction cascades, and a regulator of many enzyme activities through phosphorylation. Soils generally contain limited amounts of Pi in forms available for uptake by plant roots. Phosphate fertilizers have been used on a mass scale to combat limited crop productivity caused by low Pi availability, but raw materials to produce those fertilizers are expected to soon run out. In addition, over-fertilization of soils has caused environmental damage. Thus, plants with improved phosphate use efficiency would benefit the society by enabling a more productive agriculture while protecting the environment. The proposed study is expected to advance the knowledge of phosphate metabolism, needed to create such plants. The objective of this application is to biochemically characterize a set of phosphatases from Arabidopsis, and to uncover their roles in homeostasis, which refers to the ability to maintain an internal equilibrium by adjusting physiological processes. The project will test the central hypothesis that these enzymes are cytosolic phosphatases that participate in adjusting cellular levels of Pi and organic phosphoesters in response to developmental programs and external stimuli in plants. The project will test this hypothesis by (1) determining biochemical properties, subcellular localization, and expression patterns of these enzymes; and (2) determining the roles of these enzymes in phosphate homeostasis in plants using genetic approaches. The expected outcome of this study is knowledge of the contributions of cytosolic phosphatases to the overall homeostasis of Pi and organic phosphoesters, which is an uninvestigated aspect of phosphate metabolism in plants. This knowledge is expected to have a significant impact on the overall understanding of the metabolism of Pi and organic phosphoesters because the knowledge of how individual enzymes on metabolic pathways participate in regulating intra-cellular pool sizes of Pi and organic phosphoesters is particularly scarce, and is lagging behind that of the roles of signal transduction networks and transporters. The knowledge gained in this study is expected to be relevant to future attempts at optimizing phosphate use by plant tissues and organs, which would be beneficial because phosphate is a limiting nutrient added during fertilization, and we are expected to run out of the phosphate rock used to manufacture the fertilizer supplies in as little as 50 years. Reduced use of phosphate fertilizers in agriculture would also benefit the environment by reducing pollution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participation in this project will provide an opportunity for multidisciplinary training of postdoctoral research associates, graduate, and undergraduate students in plant biochemistry, molecular biology, and metabolism. A strong effort will be made to recruit members of underrepresented groups into the postdoctoral, graduate, and undergraduate student positions. An Associate Professor of Biology at Pacific Lutheran University, a predominantly undergraduate training institution, will participate in the project and apply the new knowledge gained towards updating and developing courses she teaches, and towards helping the participating undergraduate students from Pacific Lutheran University continue some of their research at their home institution, thus directly benefiting a larger group of undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1052492</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanja</FirstName>
<LastName>Roje</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanja Roje</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sanja@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5093353008</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482780</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington State University</Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 641060]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington State University]]></Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[280 Lighty]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~213571</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~220471</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~227653</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~235126</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong> Our long-term goal is to advance the understanding of plant metabolism, and we are particularly interested in studying metabolic processes having potential to affect plant nutrient composition, as well as growth and development. We are also interested in finding out how nutrient availability and environmental factors affect these metabolic processes at cellular level. While studying flavin nucleotide metabolism in plants, we discovered a group of phosphatases belonging to the HAD superfamily of enzymes, expected to hydrolyze organic phosphoesters including phosphorylated sugars, glycolytic intermediates, purines, pyrimidines, and phosphate-containing cofactors. Previously published work demonstrated that phosphatases of this family could have narrow or broad substrate specificities. The objective of this application was to determine substrate specificities of five putatively cytosolic members of this group, and to uncover their physiological roles. To accomplish this objective, we assayed the recombinant enzymes in the presence of a panel of physiologically relevant substrates and determined their substrate specificity, confirmed their subcellular localization, and determined the expression patterns using promoter-GUS fusions. We also produced T-DNA insertional mutants and overexpressor lines for those enzymes. We found that one of the enzymes we characterized biochemically and with respect to its physiological role, localized in plastids, is the phosphatase that was the last missing enzyme on the riboflavin biosynthesis pathway in all organisms. Of the remaining five enzymes, one was found to be involved in the metabolism of sugar phosphates, and four in the metabolism of nucleotide phosphates. The insertional mutants for the enzymes hydrolyzing nucleotide phosphates have no phenotype, so we have expanded the original objectives of the proposal and created double, triple, and quadruple mutants for these enzymes. The ongoing mutant analyses are expected to reveal the physiological role of these enzymes.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts.</strong> The project provided training opportunities for students at all levels. Two postdocs and two graduate students were directly involved with conducting the research. Three undergraduate students from WSU were trained during the academic year, and two undergraduate students from Pacific Lutheran University (PLU) participated in a 10-week summer research program in my laboratory annually. Dr. Mary Ellard-Ivey (associate Professor, PLU) mediated the interactions with the students at PLU, and helped select the candidates for the summer research program. Furthermore, Dr. Ellard-Ivey spent one month in the laboratory at WSU every summer; during this period, she learned new experimental techniques and applied them towards updating the courses she teaches at PLU. In addition, one high school senior student participating in the Upward Bound Program was trained in the laboratory for four weeks each summer for the last three years of the project. Summer research projects for the undergraduate students were tailored based on the background and specific interests of the participants, and the ongoing research activities in my laboratory. Activities included construction of plasmids for expression of the recombinant cDNAs in plants, and transformation of <em>Arabidopsis</em> by vacuum infiltration; screening of the transgenic <em>Arabidopsis</em> plants by antibodies or PCR; or extraction and quantification of metabolites from plant extracts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Sanja&nbsp;Roje</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit. Our long-term goal is to advance the understanding of plant metabolism, and we are particularly interested in studying metabolic processes having potential to affect plant nutrient composition, as well as growth and development. We are also interested in finding out how nutrient availability and environmental factors affect these metabolic processes at cellular level. While studying flavin nucleotide metabolism in plants, we discovered a group of phosphatases belonging to the HAD superfamily of enzymes, expected to hydrolyze organic phosphoesters including phosphorylated sugars, glycolytic intermediates, purines, pyrimidines, and phosphate-containing cofactors. Previously published work demonstrated that phosphatases of this family could have narrow or broad substrate specificities. The objective of this application was to determine substrate specificities of five putatively cytosolic members of this group, and to uncover their physiological roles. To accomplish this objective, we assayed the recombinant enzymes in the presence of a panel of physiologically relevant substrates and determined their substrate specificity, confirmed their subcellular localization, and determined the expression patterns using promoter-GUS fusions. We also produced T-DNA insertional mutants and overexpressor lines for those enzymes. We found that one of the enzymes we characterized biochemically and with respect to its physiological role, localized in plastids, is the phosphatase that was the last missing enzyme on the riboflavin biosynthesis pathway in all organisms. Of the remaining five enzymes, one was found to be involved in the metabolism of sugar phosphates, and four in the metabolism of nucleotide phosphates. The insertional mutants for the enzymes hydrolyzing nucleotide phosphates have no phenotype, so we have expanded the original objectives of the proposal and created double, triple, and quadruple mutants for these enzymes. The ongoing mutant analyses are expected to reveal the physiological role of these enzymes.          Broader Impacts. The project provided training opportunities for students at all levels. Two postdocs and two graduate students were directly involved with conducting the research. Three undergraduate students from WSU were trained during the academic year, and two undergraduate students from Pacific Lutheran University (PLU) participated in a 10-week summer research program in my laboratory annually. Dr. Mary Ellard-Ivey (associate Professor, PLU) mediated the interactions with the students at PLU, and helped select the candidates for the summer research program. Furthermore, Dr. Ellard-Ivey spent one month in the laboratory at WSU every summer; during this period, she learned new experimental techniques and applied them towards updating the courses she teaches at PLU. In addition, one high school senior student participating in the Upward Bound Program was trained in the laboratory for four weeks each summer for the last three years of the project. Summer research projects for the undergraduate students were tailored based on the background and specific interests of the participants, and the ongoing research activities in my laboratory. Activities included construction of plasmids for expression of the recombinant cDNAs in plants, and transformation of Arabidopsis by vacuum infiltration; screening of the transgenic Arabidopsis plants by antibodies or PCR; or extraction and quantification of metabolites from plant extracts.              Last Modified: 05/02/2016       Submitted by: Sanja Roje]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
