<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conditions of Melt Generation Associated with the  Colorado Plateau</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>146937.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>146937</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>greander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924693</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical description: USArray data are significantly advancing knowledge of the structure and physical properties of the upper mantle beneath the southwestern US. For the Colorado Plateau (CP), there is evidence that the upper mantle may be substantially modified by gravitational destabilization of dense domains as drips/delaminations and/or by thermal rejuvenation +/- melt invasion of the lithosphere where it is juxtaposed against the asthenosphere. This project is focused on evaluating these scenarios by determining conditions of melt generation and segregation associated with lithosphere destabilization across the north- and southwestern transition zones of the Colorado Plateau. The overarching goals of this study are (1) providing intensive parameters for melting conditions and (2) gaining insights into the lithologic heterogeneity in zones of melting. New data being acquired in this study include: (1) estimates of magmatic water contents from analyses of nominally anhydrous clinopyroxene and melt inclusions in olivine and; (2) pressures and temperatures of melting and clinopyroxene crystallization; (3) estimates of source oxygen fugacity; and (4) limits on the role of lithologic heterogeneities in the mantle from minor element characteristics of olivine and from trace element and isotopic characteristics of whole rocks (especially Hf and Os isotopes). These data are being considered along with seismic anisotropy observations from USArray to evaluate scenarios for the dynamics of melting beneath the CP and for the structure and evolution of lithosphere beneath the Colorado Plateau and its transition zones. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact and significance: Just as seismic waves can reveal heterogeneities in the physical properties of Earth's interior, compositional features of volcanic rocks can reveal heterogeneities in its chemical properties. From these twin approaches, insights into the interdependence and evolution of the physical and chemical properties are possible. This project is using the chemistry of lavas and minerals associated with profound changes in the Earth's outer shell to learn about the pressures, temperatures, and chemical compositions - especially fluids - of magma sources responsible for enigmatic volcanism. The results are helping to elucidate the origin of continental melting and to better interpret seismic models for the structure and dynamics of the North American plate. The project is providing professional training for two graduate students in the collection and interpretation of novel high quality geochemical data. It is also fostering collaborations between the principal investigator and scientists at three other universities. The results of this study will be shared professionally at national and international conferences as well as in peer-reviewed publications. Insights into the origin of CP-related volcanism will also be disseminated to naturalists at Sunset Crater and El Malpais National Monuments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1053616</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Reid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary R Reid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mary.reid@nau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9285237200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000426571</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Arizona University</Name>
<CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
<ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9285230886</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ARD Building #56, Suite 240</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1395 South Knoles Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHERN ARIZONA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northern Arizona University]]></Name>
<CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ARD Building #56, Suite 240]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~146937</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An area in the southwestern US known as the Colorado Plateau has anomalously high elevation compared to its surroundings, and is associated with relatively long-lived volcanism. This project investigated the origin of that volcanism in Utah and Arizona, including the ~1100-year old Sunset Crater cinder cone. A relatively novel combination of geochemical and seismic approaches was employed.</p> <p>Our investigations revealed the following: (1) melts responsible for volcanism were derived from depths that generally correspond to the base of the North American tectonic plate; (2) melting occurs near the margin of the Colorado Plateau, where the North American plate thickens dramatically; (3) melting occurs as mantle below the North American rises upwards, possibly driven by instabilities at the step-like change in plate thickness; and (4) the base of the tectonic plate is being thinned because of the ongoing mantle upwelling and volcanism. Volcanism is therefore predicted to continue its trend of migrating towards the center of the Colorado Plateau over time.</p> <p>Our chemical results showed that (5) the sources of melts are rich in the mineral olivine as opposed to the mineral pyroxene, a distinction that is important for understanding melting conditions since they melt at different temperatures; (6) the source is nevertheless heterogeneous and often in ways that correlate with geography; (7) sources may contain contributions, especially water, that were added to the mantle during an earlier period when the subducted oceanic plate was at a shallow depth; and (8) there is a distinctive and ubiquitous chemical signature found in all basalts that had not been recognized before. The unusual chemical signature may be the most compelling chemical effect of shallow subduction but additional work is needed to test this hypothesis.</p> <p>We also (9) broadly correlated geochemical signatures in the western USA with features identified in seismic models developed as part of a USA-wide campaign of seismic investigation and found that ages of the crust vary with thickness of the crust and, unexpectedly, that certain chemical signatures correlate in unexpected ways with specific seismic characteristics. These correlations are proposed to reveal broad tectonic processes in ways that are difficult to achieve on the basis of geologic outcrops alone.</p> <p>The project provided professional training for four M.S. students at Northern Arizona University, and research opportunities for three undergraduates. Results have been presented at international conferences and in three articles in international journals; an additional two papers are in preparation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Mary&nbsp;R&nbsp;Reid</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An area in the southwestern US known as the Colorado Plateau has anomalously high elevation compared to its surroundings, and is associated with relatively long-lived volcanism. This project investigated the origin of that volcanism in Utah and Arizona, including the ~1100-year old Sunset Crater cinder cone. A relatively novel combination of geochemical and seismic approaches was employed.  Our investigations revealed the following: (1) melts responsible for volcanism were derived from depths that generally correspond to the base of the North American tectonic plate; (2) melting occurs near the margin of the Colorado Plateau, where the North American plate thickens dramatically; (3) melting occurs as mantle below the North American rises upwards, possibly driven by instabilities at the step-like change in plate thickness; and (4) the base of the tectonic plate is being thinned because of the ongoing mantle upwelling and volcanism. Volcanism is therefore predicted to continue its trend of migrating towards the center of the Colorado Plateau over time.  Our chemical results showed that (5) the sources of melts are rich in the mineral olivine as opposed to the mineral pyroxene, a distinction that is important for understanding melting conditions since they melt at different temperatures; (6) the source is nevertheless heterogeneous and often in ways that correlate with geography; (7) sources may contain contributions, especially water, that were added to the mantle during an earlier period when the subducted oceanic plate was at a shallow depth; and (8) there is a distinctive and ubiquitous chemical signature found in all basalts that had not been recognized before. The unusual chemical signature may be the most compelling chemical effect of shallow subduction but additional work is needed to test this hypothesis.  We also (9) broadly correlated geochemical signatures in the western USA with features identified in seismic models developed as part of a USA-wide campaign of seismic investigation and found that ages of the crust vary with thickness of the crust and, unexpectedly, that certain chemical signatures correlate in unexpected ways with specific seismic characteristics. These correlations are proposed to reveal broad tectonic processes in ways that are difficult to achieve on the basis of geologic outcrops alone.  The project provided professional training for four M.S. students at Northern Arizona University, and research opportunities for three undergraduates. Results have been presented at international conferences and in three articles in international journals; an additional two papers are in preparation.       Last Modified: 12/19/2016       Submitted by: Mary R Reid]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
