<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Pedogenic fractionation of Fe and Mo isotopes: The role of soil redox status, organic matter and Fe-(oxyhydr)oxide composition</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>159978.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>159978</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030205</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebarrera@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927780</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project investigates the behavior of the natural isotopes of iron (Fe) and molybdenum (Mo) in soils. Differences in the mass of individual isotopes of Fe and Mo confer small variations in their behavior. Laboratory experiments suggest the direction and magnitude of these variations in isotope behavior in soils are tied to specific biogeochemical processes associated with the presence of soil organic matter, the composition of Fe minerals in the soil, and the soil oxygen status. However, field measurements of these isotopes are extremely limited in soils and this knowledge gap is a key barrier for developing them as diagnostic indicators of soil biogeochemical processes in ways similar to how carbon, oxygen, and nitrogen isotopes are commonly used. For instance, Fe and Mo isotopes hold great promise for determining past responses of soils to changes in climate, vegetation type, and water content. Our field measurements will be made across well-constrained gradients in soil age and climate that naturally exist across the Hawaiian Islands (Hawaiian Climate-Age Matrix). The Hawaiian Islands are an ideal natural laboratory for soil research because of their extreme isolation and a similar basaltic soil parent material across all the islands. In this research project we will: (1) establish the range of Fe and Mo isotopic variation across the Hawaiian Climate-Age Matrix; (2) characterize the composition of Fe minerals using advanced molecular-scale techniques; and (3) establish the relative influence of organic matter, Fe minerals and soil redox status (water and oxygen content) on Fe and Mo isotopic variation. In addition to developing a new isotopic probe of key soil processes, our work will provide detailed knowledge of the Fe solid-phase composition of the Hawaiian Climate-Age Matrix sites, which will benefit ongoing ecological and earth science research at those sites. It will also provide constraints on the baseline isotopic composition of Fe and Mo efflux from terrestrial weathering to rivers and oceanic sediments, which is critical for the use of these isotopes to interpret the past redox status of ancient marine sediments. Lastly, this work will train two graduate students and two undergraduate students over the three-year grant period as well as provide summer research experiences for three students each year from disadvantaged high schools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1053470</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aaront@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7064101293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000522064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Tucker Hall Room 409]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004315578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~159978</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Soils host biogeochemical reactions at the interface of ecosystems, rocks, water, and the atmosphere. Within soils, reactions between iron-bearing minerals and other elements have particularly important implications for the storage and cycling of carbon, nutrient availability to plants, and the behavior of trace metals in the environment. Fluctuating oxygenation conditions in soil are thought to be a key control on the reactions between iron minerals and other elements in soil, but current understanding redox fluctuations and their biogeochemical implications in field settings is limited.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Iron (Fe) and molybdenum (Mo) isotopic tracers show great promise for elucidating complex soil biogeochemical reactions and redox conditions. The power of these isotopic systems rests in their response to changing redox conditions in the soil. Fe isotopic fractionation responds directly to changes in redox during reductive dissolution of Fe minerals and potential re-precipitation; Mo isotopes may respond indirectly if they are bound to the Fe minerals that dissolve or are re-precipitated. Central to both of these isotopic systems is a solid understanding of the redox conditions across the landscape and the composition of the Fe minerals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our study established a threshold for iron reduction processes in upland soils as a function of rainfall across the Hawaiian Islands that can be extrapolated to other ecosystems. At very low rainfall, no iron reduction is expected and at high rainfall iron reduction should be extensive. We verified this using steel rods coated with easily reducible iron. We also identified the threshold rainfall/evaporation zone in intermediately moist soils where iron reduction becomes prominent. An important outcome of this work is our extension of this research to other environments where we are testing this threshold concept for iron reduction. We have also shown that above this threshold, Fe reduction events can mobilize colloidal carbon. This indicates that carbon mobilization (and perhaps loss) is strongly tied to shifts in redox in basalt-derived soils because these soils are rich in clay sized mineral-organic assemblages. Our study also made important conclusions regarding changes in iron mineral composition during weathering. We found that basalt-derived Fe is released from basaltic glass and forms secondary Fe phases much more rapidly than previously assumed under dry climates. In fact, by examining soils above and below the Fe reduction rainfall threshold on very young soils (&lt;1000 yrs), we find the more crystalline Fe(III) phases at the wettest sites than at the drier sites; an observation that becomes inverted as soils age.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Molybdenum (Mo) is a redox sensitive trace element that has proven to be a valuable tracer of oxygenation conditions in ocean environments, and Mo isotope measurements in ancient ocean sediments have contributed greatly to our understanding of early Earth&rsquo;s history.&nbsp; In this project, we proposed that Mo isotope analyses in soils may provide similarly powerful information about redox cycling and element mobilization in terrestrial environments.&nbsp; We designed our study to carefully examine the likely potential controls on Mo isotopes behavior in soil.&nbsp; Our approach independently examined the role of soil age and soil climate across well-constrained soil transects, and combined Mo isotope analyses with iron mineral characterization through M&ouml;ssbauer spectroscopy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our study results show that, while iron minerals play an important role, soil organic matter content appears to play an even larger role in controlling soil Mo content, Mo availability, and Mo isotope values. In analyzing data across a wide range of soil types, Mo loss from soil does not appear to be a simple function of increasing precipitation or soil age or weathering status, as is often the case for base cation and major elements. Instead, we found that Mo in soils is often substantially augmented by additions from precipitation, and potentially anthropogenic inputs of Mo, and that retention of these inputs within soils is controlled by Mo<strong>&ndash;</strong>organic matter interactions. We conclude that atmospheric inputs may be a significant source of micronutrient Mo to forest ecosystems, and that strong Mo retention by soil organic matter limits ecosystem Mo loss via dissolution and leaching pathways. Across diverse landscapes, we observed a wide range of Mo isotope values, both heavier and lighter than underlying bedrock. Overall, these patterns illustrated the potential for Mo isotopes as a tracer of atmospheric inputs and pedogenic processes in soils.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our research advanced understanding of how coupled reactions between soil organic matter and iron minerals controls the retention and mobility of other elements in soil. Our research also impacted a number of young scientists by providing interdisciplinary training including cutting-edge geochemical methods. This project served as the central research experience for three undergraduate students and two Ph.D. students. We also engaged in outreach, including radio programs about the molybdenum research designed to introduce high school students to STEM careers, and we created an exhibit at the Oregon Museum of Science illustrating how molybdenum is used to determine Earth&rsquo;s oxygenation history.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2017<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;Thompson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Soils host biogeochemical reactions at the interface of ecosystems, rocks, water, and the atmosphere. Within soils, reactions between iron-bearing minerals and other elements have particularly important implications for the storage and cycling of carbon, nutrient availability to plants, and the behavior of trace metals in the environment. Fluctuating oxygenation conditions in soil are thought to be a key control on the reactions between iron minerals and other elements in soil, but current understanding redox fluctuations and their biogeochemical implications in field settings is limited.     Iron (Fe) and molybdenum (Mo) isotopic tracers show great promise for elucidating complex soil biogeochemical reactions and redox conditions. The power of these isotopic systems rests in their response to changing redox conditions in the soil. Fe isotopic fractionation responds directly to changes in redox during reductive dissolution of Fe minerals and potential re-precipitation; Mo isotopes may respond indirectly if they are bound to the Fe minerals that dissolve or are re-precipitated. Central to both of these isotopic systems is a solid understanding of the redox conditions across the landscape and the composition of the Fe minerals.     Our study established a threshold for iron reduction processes in upland soils as a function of rainfall across the Hawaiian Islands that can be extrapolated to other ecosystems. At very low rainfall, no iron reduction is expected and at high rainfall iron reduction should be extensive. We verified this using steel rods coated with easily reducible iron. We also identified the threshold rainfall/evaporation zone in intermediately moist soils where iron reduction becomes prominent. An important outcome of this work is our extension of this research to other environments where we are testing this threshold concept for iron reduction. We have also shown that above this threshold, Fe reduction events can mobilize colloidal carbon. This indicates that carbon mobilization (and perhaps loss) is strongly tied to shifts in redox in basalt-derived soils because these soils are rich in clay sized mineral-organic assemblages. Our study also made important conclusions regarding changes in iron mineral composition during weathering. We found that basalt-derived Fe is released from basaltic glass and forms secondary Fe phases much more rapidly than previously assumed under dry climates. In fact, by examining soils above and below the Fe reduction rainfall threshold on very young soils (&lt;1000 yrs), we find the more crystalline Fe(III) phases at the wettest sites than at the drier sites; an observation that becomes inverted as soils age.     Molybdenum (Mo) is a redox sensitive trace element that has proven to be a valuable tracer of oxygenation conditions in ocean environments, and Mo isotope measurements in ancient ocean sediments have contributed greatly to our understanding of early Earth?s history.  In this project, we proposed that Mo isotope analyses in soils may provide similarly powerful information about redox cycling and element mobilization in terrestrial environments.  We designed our study to carefully examine the likely potential controls on Mo isotopes behavior in soil.  Our approach independently examined the role of soil age and soil climate across well-constrained soil transects, and combined Mo isotope analyses with iron mineral characterization through M&ouml;ssbauer spectroscopy.     Our study results show that, while iron minerals play an important role, soil organic matter content appears to play an even larger role in controlling soil Mo content, Mo availability, and Mo isotope values. In analyzing data across a wide range of soil types, Mo loss from soil does not appear to be a simple function of increasing precipitation or soil age or weathering status, as is often the case for base cation and major elements. Instead, we found that Mo in soils is often substantially augmented by additions from precipitation, and potentially anthropogenic inputs of Mo, and that retention of these inputs within soils is controlled by Mo&ndash;organic matter interactions. We conclude that atmospheric inputs may be a significant source of micronutrient Mo to forest ecosystems, and that strong Mo retention by soil organic matter limits ecosystem Mo loss via dissolution and leaching pathways. Across diverse landscapes, we observed a wide range of Mo isotope values, both heavier and lighter than underlying bedrock. Overall, these patterns illustrated the potential for Mo isotopes as a tracer of atmospheric inputs and pedogenic processes in soils.     Our research advanced understanding of how coupled reactions between soil organic matter and iron minerals controls the retention and mobility of other elements in soil. Our research also impacted a number of young scientists by providing interdisciplinary training including cutting-edge geochemical methods. This project served as the central research experience for three undergraduate students and two Ph.D. students. We also engaged in outreach, including radio programs about the molybdenum research designed to introduce high school students to STEM careers, and we created an exhibit at the Oregon Museum of Science illustrating how molybdenum is used to determine Earth?s oxygenation history.       Last Modified: 03/03/2017       Submitted by: Aaron Thompson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
