<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Group II-VI Semiconductor Vapor Phase Epitaxy Guided by Kinetically Active Surface Agents</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449699.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>449699</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tania M. Paskova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical: The research component of this CAREER award aims to provide a comprehensive understanding of the role that chemically inert species play in the evolution of thin films and nanostructures for the heteroepitaxial deposition of the II-VI semiconductor materials. It tests the hypothesis that an inert gas is able to induce a surfactant-like effect by kinetically disrupting adatom motion such that the thermodynamically preferred island growth mode is inhibited in favor of one that proceeds in a layer-by-layer manner. It investigates, through the use of analytical techniques and device fabrication, whether these growth modes give rise to superior material properties that are of relevance to photovoltaic applications.&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of materials science with high technological relevance. The fundamental research, if successful, could help further development of thin-film photovoltaic materials for energy harvesting. Education and outreach activities, geared towards the implementation of engineering solutions that promote sustainability through the use of renewable energy and nanotechnologies, will provide society with engineers equipped with the knowledge, training, and social consciousness needed to realize a sustainable urban environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1053416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Svetlana</FirstName>
<LastName>Neretina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Svetlana Neretina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sneretina@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746316127</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539836</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1801 N. Broad Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~89064</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~89490</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~89927</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~90377</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~90841</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Modern technologically driven societies could not exist in their current form if it were not for a great many materials science discoveries reliant on solution-based chemistry and substrate-based epitaxy. In terms of generating nanomaterials, substrate-based techniques have undeniably given rise to an impressive collection of materials, but where the scope and scale of this success is dwarfed by the many impressive accomplishments of solution-based chemistry. The work carried out in this CAREER award began with the vision of creating a synthetic platform which combines these two approaches in a manner yielding unprecedented synthetic flexibility. The approach is unique in that it combines solution-based synthetic techniques, which are largely the domain of chemists, with the substrate-based routes typically used by material scientists and engineers, but which are rarely practiced by a single investigator. The work targeted plasmonic nanostructures, a class of nanomaterials formed predominantly from noble metals, which derive their significance from the intense interactions they have in response to an incident electromagnetic wave (i.e., light). The goal was to devise inexpensive synthetic routes able to form organized patterns of plasmonic nanostructures with functionalities unrealizable through other means. This goal was met and, in the process, led to significant intellectual merit while having an impact on students at the graduate, undergraduate, and high school levels.</p> <p>The major outcomes of the award were to: (i) devise a lithography-free fabrication route able to define periodic arrays of substrate-based noble metal nanostructures, (ii) develop a series of synthetic protocols able to transform the arrayed structures into more intricate nanostructures using vapor phase techniques, (iii) validate the synthetic approach which combines liquid- and substrate-based techniques in a manner yielding substrate-based nanostructure architectures with unprecedented complexity, (iv) establish the chemistry and physics which underpin the devised synthetic routes, and (v) demonstrate the potential of these nanostructures as hydrogen gas sensors, catalysts, photocatalysts, and photoactive materials. This work has been disseminated in high impact factor journals and at prominent international conferences of the Materials Research Society and the American Chemical Society. The devised synthetic strategy is now being practiced by other researchers and is being advanced as a nanomanufacturing platform through NSF&rsquo;s Nanomanufacturing Program. The work is also of high relevance to the much broader audience carrying out similar reactions on solution-dispersed templates because the substrate-based platform has led to mechanistic findings not readily achievable using solution-based syntheses. Because this strategy has only been applied to plasmonic nanomaterials there is now the potential to adapt it to a broad range of nanomaterials with diverse functionalities.</p> <p>This CAREER award has also contributed to the training and professional development of graduate and undergraduate students, the matriculation of women into the engineering profession, and provided high-school students with research experiences aimed at giving them a decisive advantage as they embark on STEM-related careers. The award has resulted in the graduation of three Ph.D. students, one is now a postdoctoral researcher at the Georgia Institute of Technology while the other two are employed in the electronics and pharmaceutical industries. A total of 19 undergraduate students participated in this research through undergraduate summer internships or as part of an engineering senior design team. The matriculation of women into the engineering profession has been promoted through the Women&rsquo;s Engineering Exploration outreach program directed toward high school students interested in pursuing careers ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Modern technologically driven societies could not exist in their current form if it were not for a great many materials science discoveries reliant on solution-based chemistry and substrate-based epitaxy. In terms of generating nanomaterials, substrate-based techniques have undeniably given rise to an impressive collection of materials, but where the scope and scale of this success is dwarfed by the many impressive accomplishments of solution-based chemistry. The work carried out in this CAREER award began with the vision of creating a synthetic platform which combines these two approaches in a manner yielding unprecedented synthetic flexibility. The approach is unique in that it combines solution-based synthetic techniques, which are largely the domain of chemists, with the substrate-based routes typically used by material scientists and engineers, but which are rarely practiced by a single investigator. The work targeted plasmonic nanostructures, a class of nanomaterials formed predominantly from noble metals, which derive their significance from the intense interactions they have in response to an incident electromagnetic wave (i.e., light). The goal was to devise inexpensive synthetic routes able to form organized patterns of plasmonic nanostructures with functionalities unrealizable through other means. This goal was met and, in the process, led to significant intellectual merit while having an impact on students at the graduate, undergraduate, and high school levels.  The major outcomes of the award were to: (i) devise a lithography-free fabrication route able to define periodic arrays of substrate-based noble metal nanostructures, (ii) develop a series of synthetic protocols able to transform the arrayed structures into more intricate nanostructures using vapor phase techniques, (iii) validate the synthetic approach which combines liquid- and substrate-based techniques in a manner yielding substrate-based nanostructure architectures with unprecedented complexity, (iv) establish the chemistry and physics which underpin the devised synthetic routes, and (v) demonstrate the potential of these nanostructures as hydrogen gas sensors, catalysts, photocatalysts, and photoactive materials. This work has been disseminated in high impact factor journals and at prominent international conferences of the Materials Research Society and the American Chemical Society. The devised synthetic strategy is now being practiced by other researchers and is being advanced as a nanomanufacturing platform through NSFÆs Nanomanufacturing Program. The work is also of high relevance to the much broader audience carrying out similar reactions on solution-dispersed templates because the substrate-based platform has led to mechanistic findings not readily achievable using solution-based syntheses. Because this strategy has only been applied to plasmonic nanomaterials there is now the potential to adapt it to a broad range of nanomaterials with diverse functionalities.  This CAREER award has also contributed to the training and professional development of graduate and undergraduate students, the matriculation of women into the engineering profession, and provided high-school students with research experiences aimed at giving them a decisive advantage as they embark on STEM-related careers. The award has resulted in the graduation of three Ph.D. students, one is now a postdoctoral researcher at the Georgia Institute of Technology while the other two are employed in the electronics and pharmaceutical industries. A total of 19 undergraduate students participated in this research through undergraduate summer internships or as part of an engineering senior design team. The matriculation of women into the engineering profession has been promoted through the WomenÆs Engineering Exploration outreach program directed toward high school students interested in pursuing careers in science and engineering. The mentorship of 9 high-school science fair projects has ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
