<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Exploring the Underexplored: A Fundamental Study of Optimal Resource Allocation and Low-Complexity Algorithms in Multi-Radio Multi-Channel Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The multi-radio multi-channel (MR-MC) networking provides a generic computing platform for a wide range of next-generation wireless networks. However, the capacity of MR-MC networking has been underexplored, due to the lack of effective computing methodologies to address the complex multi-dimensional resource allocation. The current state of the art of MR-MC network capacity analysis is limited to heuristic algorithms and loose capacity bound analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project targets at breakthrough studies on optimal resource allocation and low-complexity algorithm development for MR-MC networks. The proposed research activities weave up optimization theory, graph theory, stochastic control, and asymptotic scaling law analysis, to reveal the underpinning factors that distinguish the MR-MC network optimization from the single-radio single-channel (SR-SC) counterpart, develop low-complexity algorithms with theoretically provable performance, and exploit the particular advantages of MR-MC networking in incorporating new techniques for further capacity enhancement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a set of novel theoretical tools to fundamentally address the capacity optimization and computational complexity in a multi-dimensional resource space. On the education front, this interdisciplinary research will not only provide various training projects to undergraduate and graduate students, but also inspire students (particularly PhD students) to pursue high-quality research with a creative, open-minded, and cross-disciplinary perspective. On the industry front, the capacity planning and dynamic network control techniques developed in this project are of critical importance to practical wireless network design, and have the potential to be transformed into practical network protocols with low complexity and provable efficiency.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1053777</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yu Cheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cheng@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3125677996</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000070889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 7D71]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Illinois Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10 West 35th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has contributed a set of theoretical tools that fundamentally address the capacity optimization and computational complexity in multi-radio multi-channel (MR-MC) wireless networks. Some important insights have been revealed: MR-MC wireless network optimization can be addressed in the linear programming domain (instead of mixed integer programming domain as known in the literature), facilitated by the multi-dimensional modeling tools developed in this project; the underpinning factors that distinguish the MR-MC network optimization from the single-radio single-channel (SR-SC) counterpart is the network geometric property; low-complexity algorithms with guaranteed performance for optimizing MR-MC networks can be developed in a systematic manner based on the delayed column generation (DCG) method. Specifically, the findings from this project have fundamentally advanced the state of the art of MR-MC networking from three aspects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; An innovative multi-dimensional tuple based modeling framework has been developed, which transforms an MR-MC network node into multiple node-radio-channel (NRC) tuples, and thus the original MR-MC network into a virtual SR-SC network. Such a framework in principles allows extending all those optimization techniques for SR-SC networks to the MR-MC context; and in particular facilitates the derivation of a tuple-based back-pressure algorithm for throughput-optimal control in MR-MC wireless networks and enables a systematic study of various scheduling algorithms with guaranteed performance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A critical insight revealed through this project is that the optimal resource allocation over a wireless network can fundamentally be expressed as an independent set (IS) based scheduling, and the convex hull over all the possible ISs defines the space of resource allocation. Although there are exponentially many possible ISs, only a small number of ISs, which are defined as critical IS set in this project, are used in the optimal scheduling. It is further revealed that such critical IS set can be searched (at the same time, the network optimization problem can be solved) by the delayed column generation (DCG) method. A significant theoretical result is that the approximation ratio associated with the MWIS approximation algorithm involved in DCG is a lower-bound approximation ratio of the network capacity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This project has also demonstrated how NRC tuple based modeling can be extendable to include new dimension of resource into network capacity or energy efficiency optimization formulation. Specifically, the NRC tuple has been extended to incorporate resource dimensions of power and antenna direction to study energy-efficient networking in the MR-MC context with directional antenna; such a study was impossible with existing methods in the literature.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project seamlessly integrates studies in the areas of optimization, stochastic control, graph theory, scaling law analysis, and wireless networking. This interdisciplinary research have provided many training projects to IIT undergraduate and graduate students, students from Spain and France through IIT exchange program, and Brazil undergraduate students through the Brazil Scientific Mobility Program (BSMP) at IIT.&nbsp; Especially, this project inspired students (particularly PhD students) to pursue high-quality research with a creative, open-minded, and cross-disciplinary perspective. A few students involved in this project have obtained R&amp;D jobs in Qualcomm, InterDigital, and United Technology Research center after graduation, respectively. The postdoc fellow supported by this project joined Southeastern University, China as an associated professor in August 2015. Two more PhD students are going to graduate in Spring 2017.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The outcomes from this project have been published in top-tier IEEE or ACM conference proceedings and journals, including the Best Paper Runner-Up Award at the prestigious conference ACM MobiHoc 2014. &nbsp;The publications have been timely listed in the PI&rsquo;s webpage. The outcomes have also been disseminated to community through community outreach activities, a dozen of seminar talks in both universities and industry, and through IEEE Distinguished Lecturer talks. The research results have also been leveraged to enhance the PI&rsquo;s course materials at IIT. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2017<br>      Modified by: Yu&nbsp;Cheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has contributed a set of theoretical tools that fundamentally address the capacity optimization and computational complexity in multi-radio multi-channel (MR-MC) wireless networks. Some important insights have been revealed: MR-MC wireless network optimization can be addressed in the linear programming domain (instead of mixed integer programming domain as known in the literature), facilitated by the multi-dimensional modeling tools developed in this project; the underpinning factors that distinguish the MR-MC network optimization from the single-radio single-channel (SR-SC) counterpart is the network geometric property; low-complexity algorithms with guaranteed performance for optimizing MR-MC networks can be developed in a systematic manner based on the delayed column generation (DCG) method. Specifically, the findings from this project have fundamentally advanced the state of the art of MR-MC networking from three aspects.     1)            An innovative multi-dimensional tuple based modeling framework has been developed, which transforms an MR-MC network node into multiple node-radio-channel (NRC) tuples, and thus the original MR-MC network into a virtual SR-SC network. Such a framework in principles allows extending all those optimization techniques for SR-SC networks to the MR-MC context; and in particular facilitates the derivation of a tuple-based back-pressure algorithm for throughput-optimal control in MR-MC wireless networks and enables a systematic study of various scheduling algorithms with guaranteed performance.     2)            A critical insight revealed through this project is that the optimal resource allocation over a wireless network can fundamentally be expressed as an independent set (IS) based scheduling, and the convex hull over all the possible ISs defines the space of resource allocation. Although there are exponentially many possible ISs, only a small number of ISs, which are defined as critical IS set in this project, are used in the optimal scheduling. It is further revealed that such critical IS set can be searched (at the same time, the network optimization problem can be solved) by the delayed column generation (DCG) method. A significant theoretical result is that the approximation ratio associated with the MWIS approximation algorithm involved in DCG is a lower-bound approximation ratio of the network capacity.     3)            This project has also demonstrated how NRC tuple based modeling can be extendable to include new dimension of resource into network capacity or energy efficiency optimization formulation. Specifically, the NRC tuple has been extended to incorporate resource dimensions of power and antenna direction to study energy-efficient networking in the MR-MC context with directional antenna; such a study was impossible with existing methods in the literature.     This project seamlessly integrates studies in the areas of optimization, stochastic control, graph theory, scaling law analysis, and wireless networking. This interdisciplinary research have provided many training projects to IIT undergraduate and graduate students, students from Spain and France through IIT exchange program, and Brazil undergraduate students through the Brazil Scientific Mobility Program (BSMP) at IIT.  Especially, this project inspired students (particularly PhD students) to pursue high-quality research with a creative, open-minded, and cross-disciplinary perspective. A few students involved in this project have obtained R&amp;D jobs in Qualcomm, InterDigital, and United Technology Research center after graduation, respectively. The postdoc fellow supported by this project joined Southeastern University, China as an associated professor in August 2015. Two more PhD students are going to graduate in Spring 2017.     The outcomes from this project have been published in top-tier IEEE or ACM conference proceedings and journals, including the Best Paper Runner-Up Award at the prestigious conference ACM MobiHoc 2014.  The publications have been timely listed in the PI?s webpage. The outcomes have also been disseminated to community through community outreach activities, a dozen of seminar talks in both universities and industry, and through IEEE Distinguished Lecturer talks. The research results have also been leveraged to enhance the PI?s course materials at IIT.            Last Modified: 01/05/2017       Submitted by: Yu Cheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
