<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CCS Workshops Organization Supplement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeremy Epstein</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jepstein@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928338</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The award is to support the series of workshops on security in emerging areas that are affiliated with the 2010 ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), and will be held on October 4 to 8, 2010 in Chicago, IL. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The annual ACM Computer and Communications Security Conference is a leading international forum for information security researchers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore cutting-edge ideas and results, and to exchange techniques, tools and experiences. Since year 2001, CCS started accommodating series of workshops to explore security issues in a variety of emerging areas. CCS workshops quickly become active forums for researchers to form focus groups, discuss and collaborate on emerging and critical security problems, and disseminate fresh, revolutionary (and sometimes even controversial) ideas. These workshops also serve as natural venues to bring together researchers from multiple disciplines to address security issues in specific domains, such as health care, cloud computing and national critical infrastructures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1054001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ninghui</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ninghui Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ninghui@cs.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654966756</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000166436</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7795</Code>
<Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~27000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant is for supporting workshops associated with the ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS) in 2010 and 2011. &nbsp;The annual ACM CCS Conference is a leading international forum for information security researchers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore cutting-edge ideas and results, and to exchange techniques, tools and experiences. Since year 2001, CCS started accommodating series of workshops to explore security issues in a variety of emerging areas. CCS workshops quickly become active forums for researchers to form focus groups, discuss and collaborate on emerging and critical security problems, and disseminate fresh, revolutionary (and sometimes even controversial) ideas. These workshops also serve as natural venues to bring together researchers from multiple disciplines to address security issues in specific domains, such as cloud computing, privacy, mobile devices, health care, and national critical infrastructures.</p> <p>The bulk of the money is used to support graduate students enrolled in US education institutions to attend the workshops. &nbsp;A small portion of the fund was used to support researchers who participate in panels in the workshops. &nbsp;This grant has supported 34 students and 6 panel members to attend these workshops. &nbsp;The financial support helped improve the quality and attendance of the workshops, helped attendants of the workshops to gain better knowledge and understanding of the field, indirectly helping their research.&nbsp; The grant helped graduate students attending the workshops, promoting training and learning.&nbsp; Increased attendance of the workshops also helps improve networking, idea exchanging, and partnerships for all attendants of the workshop.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2012<br>      Modified by: Ninghui&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant is for supporting workshops associated with the ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS) in 2010 and 2011.  The annual ACM CCS Conference is a leading international forum for information security researchers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore cutting-edge ideas and results, and to exchange techniques, tools and experiences. Since year 2001, CCS started accommodating series of workshops to explore security issues in a variety of emerging areas. CCS workshops quickly become active forums for researchers to form focus groups, discuss and collaborate on emerging and critical security problems, and disseminate fresh, revolutionary (and sometimes even controversial) ideas. These workshops also serve as natural venues to bring together researchers from multiple disciplines to address security issues in specific domains, such as cloud computing, privacy, mobile devices, health care, and national critical infrastructures.  The bulk of the money is used to support graduate students enrolled in US education institutions to attend the workshops.  A small portion of the fund was used to support researchers who participate in panels in the workshops.  This grant has supported 34 students and 6 panel members to attend these workshops.  The financial support helped improve the quality and attendance of the workshops, helped attendants of the workshops to gain better knowledge and understanding of the field, indirectly helping their research.  The grant helped graduate students attending the workshops, promoting training and learning.  Increased attendance of the workshops also helps improve networking, idea exchanging, and partnerships for all attendants of the workshop.       Last Modified: 09/06/2012       Submitted by: Ninghui Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
