<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Slab structure and dynamics of arcuate shaped subduction zones</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>527388.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>533912</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030204</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin Reichlin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rreichli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928556</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the intriguing features of plate tectonics is that many active and ancient subduction zones have a pronounced arc-shaped morphology, with their topographic expressions stretching over hundreds to thousands of kilometers in length.  Studying subduction, in general, is essential to understanding the evolution of the planet.  More fully understanding the structure and dynamics of lithosphere, the relatively rigid outer shell of the Earth, subducting along highly arcuate plate boundaries will aid in constraining geologically recorded tectonic events, global plate motions, plate boundary deformation, and the role of subducted oceanic lithosphere in mantle convection.  The overarching research goal of this CAREER award is development of an improved understanding of the structural and morphological evolution of arcuate shaped convergent margins through the study of four active arcs: the Mariana, Antilles, Betic-Rif, and Banda arcs, using a range of tools, including seismological imaging and geodynamic modeling.  The expected findings will provide an important contribution to basic research on plate tectonics, an improved understanding of the structure and evolution of the tectonic plate boundaries, and the nature of seismicity in these regions.  The educational goal is to train and prepare undergraduate graduate students as the next generation of geoscientists who are able to understand and effectively utilize both geophysical and geological data from subduction zones.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award will investigate, in detail, the origin and evolution of the deep Earth structure of four target arcs.  Improved imaging and modeling of these arcs will provide a way to test geodynamic hypotheses, for example, that curved subduction zones have evolved into their current configuration due to interactions of cold, dense oceanic lithosphere with positively buoyant features, such as oceanic plateaus or continental lithosphere, resulting in curved morphology as a result of trench rollback and slab fragmentation.  Each of the four arc systems, have different length scales and topographic expressions, unique individual tectonic histories and plate configurations, yet they all exhibit highly arcuate convergent boundary structures and are bounded by buoyant crustal and lithospheric bodies at their cusps.  This project proposes to examine these similarities and differences in order to better understand the geodynamic evolution and mantle structure at tightly curved convergent boundaries in terms of rollback, mantle flow, and the influence of buoyant "pinning" features at the ends of the arcs.  This award will also fund development of an integrated education and research program based on understanding of seismicity, volcanism, mantle convection, plate tectonics, and geologic processes from both field and classroom based learning. The field component of the new Tectonophysics course will include deployment and collection of broadband seismic data along the several of the Antilles Islands and in northern Morocco, plus regional geologic mapping and sampling along portions of the active arcs.  Both undergraduates and graduate students will participate in the course and other teaching modules developed through this award and will be part of USC's Problems Without Passports program that combine inquiry-based learning exercises with research in a foreign country.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1054638</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meghan</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meghan S Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>msmiller@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137406308</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485263</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Park]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6898</Code>
<Text>EAR-Earth Sciences Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7731</Code>
<Text>Other Global Learning &amp; Trng</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~410486</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~123426</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This CAREER award project was awarded to a female early career geophysicist to investigate, in detail, the origin and evolution of the boundaries of tectonic plates.&nbsp; The project primarily focused on studying subduction zones, where oceanic plates are descending into the Earth&rsquo;s deep interior, which are critical to the advance of knowledge in the field, but are still relatively poorly understood.&nbsp;&nbsp;These are regions where tectonic activity, as observed in seismicity and volcanism, is localized, making them natural targets of high scientific and societal relevance.</p> <p>This project funded PI Miller and her team of students at the University of Southern California to use and develop novel techniques, collect new data in regions where none are available, and integrate other disparate geologic and geophysical data, to solve outstanding questions in plate tectonics and how the Earth evolves.&nbsp; The project involved collecting new seismic data by deploying seismographs in Africa and Asia, together with mining the wide range of earthquake data that is available through the NSF-funded IRIS consortium and active participation in national and international collaborations.</p> <p>The award had a substantial educational component, part of which included teaching a field-based course for undergraduates in Morocco to learn both about field-based seismology and learn about the amazing geology there.&nbsp; The location of the experiment and course was picked because it extends across the Strait of Gibraltar, which is the boundary between the Eurasian and African plates, to into the interior of the African continent.&nbsp; One important result of this study revealed the extent to which&nbsp;the Atlas Mountains of Morocco&nbsp;is an incredibly unusual mountain belt with a peak elevation of ~4km was previously unexplained.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Many students and early career researchers were trained through this project.&nbsp; Undergraduate students at the University of Southern California participated in international geophysical fieldwork, summer internship projects, and even wrote academic papers with funding from this project.&nbsp; In addition, three postdocs were employed through this grant and two PhD students were funded as research assistants.&nbsp; Finally, the PI Miller was an early career researcher and achieved tenure during the project, which was enabled through the research and educational components of the project.</p> <p>Over all the funds from this award were used to fund science that produced 27 peer-reviewed publications, including two in Nature and one in Nature Geoscience.&nbsp; The funds enabled the PI and her research group to give dozens of presentations at international scientific conferences and for the PI to give many invited lectures at universities around the world.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Meghan&nbsp;S&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This CAREER award project was awarded to a female early career geophysicist to investigate, in detail, the origin and evolution of the boundaries of tectonic plates.  The project primarily focused on studying subduction zones, where oceanic plates are descending into the Earth?s deep interior, which are critical to the advance of knowledge in the field, but are still relatively poorly understood.  These are regions where tectonic activity, as observed in seismicity and volcanism, is localized, making them natural targets of high scientific and societal relevance.  This project funded PI Miller and her team of students at the University of Southern California to use and develop novel techniques, collect new data in regions where none are available, and integrate other disparate geologic and geophysical data, to solve outstanding questions in plate tectonics and how the Earth evolves.  The project involved collecting new seismic data by deploying seismographs in Africa and Asia, together with mining the wide range of earthquake data that is available through the NSF-funded IRIS consortium and active participation in national and international collaborations.  The award had a substantial educational component, part of which included teaching a field-based course for undergraduates in Morocco to learn both about field-based seismology and learn about the amazing geology there.  The location of the experiment and course was picked because it extends across the Strait of Gibraltar, which is the boundary between the Eurasian and African plates, to into the interior of the African continent.  One important result of this study revealed the extent to which the Atlas Mountains of Morocco is an incredibly unusual mountain belt with a peak elevation of ~4km was previously unexplained.    Many students and early career researchers were trained through this project.  Undergraduate students at the University of Southern California participated in international geophysical fieldwork, summer internship projects, and even wrote academic papers with funding from this project.  In addition, three postdocs were employed through this grant and two PhD students were funded as research assistants.  Finally, the PI Miller was an early career researcher and achieved tenure during the project, which was enabled through the research and educational components of the project.  Over all the funds from this award were used to fund science that produced 27 peer-reviewed publications, including two in Nature and one in Nature Geoscience.  The funds enabled the PI and her research group to give dozens of presentations at international scientific conferences and for the PI to give many invited lectures at universities around the world.          Last Modified: 02/03/2019       Submitted by: Meghan S Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
