<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Generalizing Planar Algorithms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>401169.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>427569</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jack S. Snoeyink</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsnoeyin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computational topology is an exciting new area, emerging at the intersection of computer science and mathematics.  The most simple topological setting is the plane (or two-dimensional Euclidean space).  Developing fast algorithms for planar objects is vital for many applications, including road networks, integrated circuit design, and motion planning.  Generalizing these planar algorithms so that they will run quickly in other topological settings allows one to extend to an even larger domain of applications, including shape modeling in graphics, medical imaging, finding low-dimensional spans for high-dimensional data in statistical analysis, shape description and detection, computing similarity measures between curves or surfaces, and flow and routing problems in graphs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will develop faster algorithms for fundamental problems in graphs on surfaces and in minor free graphs, which are both natural generalizations of planar graphs that provide extra topological structure.  More specifically, the PI will work on problems such as finding shortest paths and cycles on surfaces, computing maximum flows in surfaces and minor free flows, and computing similarity measures between curves.  In addition to designing faster algorithms, the PI will also implement the first code for several of these algorithms for practical settings, particularly in the area of computing similarity measures between curves on non-planar surfaces.  Much of this work is at the intersection of math and computer science, and so will lead to interdisciplinary collaboration between the PI's research group and other researchers in both areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaboration and interdisciplinary work also provide the framework for advances in computer science education and community outreach.  The PI's active interdisciplinary research group will provide an ideal forum to mentor undergraduate students, particularly those from underrepresented groups.  Undergraduate research will in turn draw talented students to graduate school in computer science.  In addition, the PI has redesigned several of the computer science courses to incorporate a large active learning component.  The PI will continue this research on pedagogical methods for active learning and its effect on the recruitment and retention of students in computer science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1054779</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Chambers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erin W Chambers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>erin.chambers@slu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173697138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000080572</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/29/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Saint Louis University</Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3149773925</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>221 N. Grand Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050220722</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAINT LOUIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050220722</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Saint Louis University]]></Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[221 N. Grand Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7929</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL GEOMETRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~71588</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~94227</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~82407</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~83243</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~96104</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Objects from the real world such as road networks and electrical circuits are often represented as graphs or geometric objects in the plane; given these representations, there are a wide range of fast algorithms which can be implemented to analyze and compute their structural properites. &nbsp;However, in the presence of noise or when the input is more complex, solving problems and designing algorithms becomes much more difficult. &nbsp;Topology is the branch of mathematics concerned with investigating fundamental connections and shape information of these more complex objects. &nbsp;This project explored computational problems on such structures, in the new and emerging area of computational topology. &nbsp;The main overarching theme of the project was to find faster algorithms for these types of objects when they generalize beyond the plane. &nbsp;For example, there are fast algorithms for the maximum flow algorithm in a planar graph: so on a road network where roads cross only at intersections, it is possible to find bottlenecks that limit the number of vehicles that can be routed through the graph. &nbsp;However, as soon as there is any additional complexity, such as inserting bridge or putting the graph on a more complex shape like a donut, the algorithm no longer has the same performance guarantees, even though it is still relatively simple from a topological viewpoint. &nbsp;Work on this project generalized this type of planar algorithm to a variety of more complex settings, including meshes and minor free families of graphs. &nbsp;Generalizations to meshes have practical applications in areas such as computer graphics or medical imaging; generalizations to minor free graphs help further develop the theory by showing the strong role that graph decompositions can play in finding fast practical algorithms or showing strong structural or hardness results. &nbsp;Finally, a component of this grant was also applying these algorithms and structural results to problems in more applied domains such as map matching, trajectory analysis, and graph drawing. &nbsp;</p> <p>This work lies at the intersection of mathematics and computer science, and resulted in interdisciplinary publications that appeare both in mathematics journals and computer science conferences or journals. &nbsp;Talks were given at a number of CS and mathematics venues both in the US and internationally, including Dagstuhl, Oberwolfach, and many conferences or workshops.&nbsp;</p> <p>The grant also funded 3 graduate students in applied mathematics and 6 undergraduates from mathematics and computer science, all of whom have continued to work in the mathematical or computer science industries. &nbsp;Besides dissemination in journals and conferences, the PI has also presented several aspects of this work to local high school and grade school students in order to create wider interest in computing and mathematics as a career choice.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Erin&nbsp;W&nbsp;Chambers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Objects from the real world such as road networks and electrical circuits are often represented as graphs or geometric objects in the plane; given these representations, there are a wide range of fast algorithms which can be implemented to analyze and compute their structural properites.  However, in the presence of noise or when the input is more complex, solving problems and designing algorithms becomes much more difficult.  Topology is the branch of mathematics concerned with investigating fundamental connections and shape information of these more complex objects.  This project explored computational problems on such structures, in the new and emerging area of computational topology.  The main overarching theme of the project was to find faster algorithms for these types of objects when they generalize beyond the plane.  For example, there are fast algorithms for the maximum flow algorithm in a planar graph: so on a road network where roads cross only at intersections, it is possible to find bottlenecks that limit the number of vehicles that can be routed through the graph.  However, as soon as there is any additional complexity, such as inserting bridge or putting the graph on a more complex shape like a donut, the algorithm no longer has the same performance guarantees, even though it is still relatively simple from a topological viewpoint.  Work on this project generalized this type of planar algorithm to a variety of more complex settings, including meshes and minor free families of graphs.  Generalizations to meshes have practical applications in areas such as computer graphics or medical imaging; generalizations to minor free graphs help further develop the theory by showing the strong role that graph decompositions can play in finding fast practical algorithms or showing strong structural or hardness results.  Finally, a component of this grant was also applying these algorithms and structural results to problems in more applied domains such as map matching, trajectory analysis, and graph drawing.    This work lies at the intersection of mathematics and computer science, and resulted in interdisciplinary publications that appeare both in mathematics journals and computer science conferences or journals.  Talks were given at a number of CS and mathematics venues both in the US and internationally, including Dagstuhl, Oberwolfach, and many conferences or workshops.   The grant also funded 3 graduate students in applied mathematics and 6 undergraduates from mathematics and computer science, all of whom have continued to work in the mathematical or computer science industries.  Besides dissemination in journals and conferences, the PI has also presented several aspects of this work to local high school and grade school students in order to create wider interest in computing and mathematics as a career choice.       Last Modified: 08/29/2017       Submitted by: Erin W Chambers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
