<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Forecasting Climate Change Impacts on Plant Communities? When Do Species Interactions Matter?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>573401.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>716669</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The impact of climate change on an individual species depends both on how that species responds directly to alterations in precipitation and temperature, and on how its predators or competitors are affected by the change in climate. While scientists have documented examples of these species interactions overwhelming the direct effects of altered climate variables, it remains impossible to predict how common such situations may be or when and where they will occur. The proposed research combines long-term observational data, mathematical models, and field experiments to test general predictions about how, when and where species interactions will mediate the ecological impacts of climate change and variability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research may be of value to government land managers, who are under increasing pressure to consider climate change impacts in land-use planning. However, managers lack practical access to relevant scientific information. Therefore, the research will be complemented by an education program to improve communication between researchers and land managers. A series of coordinated graduate seminars at multiple universities will bring faculty, students and agency personnel together to synthesize existing climate change science in the Intermountain West. The seminars will build new relationships between researchers and managers and the resulting summary reports will inform decision-making.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1054040</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Adler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter B Adler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.adler@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357971021</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000422289</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1415 Old Main Hill ~ Room 64]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~180201</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~334897</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~201571</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~0</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="margin-bottom: 0in;" lang="en-US"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: transparent;"><span style="font-style: normal;"><span style="text-decoration: none;">An urgent challenge for ecologists is predicting how species will respond to climate change.</span></span><span style="font-style: normal;"><span style="text-decoration: none;"> Climate change may directly affect species by altering their physiological and demographic rates, but it may also exert indirect effects by altering species interactions. For example, warmer temperatures might have negative direct effects on a cold-adapted plant species, but if that species' competitors suffer even more under warming, then the overall effect of warming on the focal species may be positive. The </span></span><span style="font-style: normal;"><span style="text-decoration: none;">primary research </span></span><span style="font-style: normal;"><span style="text-decoration: none;">goal of this project was to use ecological theory to determine when such indirect effects might be strong and important to include in predictive models, and when they might be weak enough to be safely ignored in favor of a simpler, single-species modeling approach. We advanced this goal</span></span><span style="font-style: normal;"><span style="text-decoration: none;"> by combining long-term observational data, statistical and simulation models, theory, and field experiments.</span></span><span style="font-style: normal;"> </span></span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;" lang="en-US">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;" lang="en-US"><span style="font-size: small;">Our most important empirical finding in the semiarid plant communities we studied is that niche overlap is low: intraspecific (within species) limitations were much stronger than interspecific (between species) limitations. This pattern is important because it leads to very stable coexistence and very weak indirect effects of climate change among competing plant species. More generally, it implies that much of the variation in species abundances reflects variation in the strength of intraspecific density dependence, since interspecific density dependence was generally quite weak. Plant community ecologists have traditionally focused more on understanding competition between than within species; our results suggest that these priorities should be reconsidered. </span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;" lang="en-US">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;" lang="en-US"><span style="font-size: small;">Some of our results suggest that simple models can work as well as complex models for forecasting the ecological impacts of climate change. For example, in plant communities where niche overlap is low, and interspecific interactions are weak, single species models should work well. Furthermore, models built using population-level data can predict as well as models based on individual-level demographic data. These results give cause for optimism.</span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;" lang="en-US">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in; font-style: normal; font-weight: normal; text-decoration: none;" lang="en-US"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: transparent;">On the other hand, we are learning that predicting the direct effects of precipitation and temperature on demographic rates and population dynamics is much more difficult than we expected. In both experimental tests of models based on observational data and cross-validation tests with long-term data, we can only make skillful forecasts for half of the species we have studied, and our criteria for "skillful" is low (outperforming a null model assuming no effects of climate variables). We are now planning future work to identify why this problem is so difficult and to identify strategies most likely to improve forecast skill.</span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in; font-style: normal; font-weight: normal; text-decoration: none;" lang="en-US">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in; font-style: normal; font-weight: normal; text-decoration: none;" lang="en-US"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: transparent;">The project also included an outreach and education goal to improve communication between researchers and land managers through a series of distributed graduate courses focused on climate change vulnerability assessment in the Intermountain West. The course, taught in 2012 and 2013, involved 8 instructors and over 40 graduate students from 6 universities. Products included a series of "fact sheets" about climate change impacts on sagebrush steppe ecosystems, now available on the internet, and a symposium at the 2015 annual Society for Range Management meeting in February, 2015. The course also led to new research, funded by the US Fish and Wildlife Service and USGS, which used a model-comparison approach to show that climate change will have negative impacts on sagebrush cover only in the hottest portion of the Intermountain West; in cooler locations, warming appears likely to have weak or even positive effects on sagebrush cover. </span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in; font-style: normal; font-weight: normal; text-decoration: none;" lang="en-US">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in; font-style: normal; font-weight: normal; text-decoration: none;" lang="en-US"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: transparent;">In addition to the distributed graduate course, the project provided one-on-one research training for two post-doctoral fellows, four graduate students, two undergraduate researchers, and seven undergraduate research technicians. These students gained experience with quantitative techniques including database management, programming, and statistical and mathematical modeling.</span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;B&nbsp;Adler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[An urgent challenge for ecologists is predicting how species will respond to climate change. Climate change may directly affect species by altering their physiological and demographic rates, but it may also exert indirect effects by altering species interactions. For example, warmer temperatures might have negative direct effects on a cold-adapted plant species, but if that species' competitors suffer even more under warming, then the overall effect of warming on the focal species may be positive. The primary research goal of this project was to use ecological theory to determine when such indirect effects might be strong and important to include in predictive models, and when they might be weak enough to be safely ignored in favor of a simpler, single-species modeling approach. We advanced this goal by combining long-term observational data, statistical and simulation models, theory, and field experiments.    Our most important empirical finding in the semiarid plant communities we studied is that niche overlap is low: intraspecific (within species) limitations were much stronger than interspecific (between species) limitations. This pattern is important because it leads to very stable coexistence and very weak indirect effects of climate change among competing plant species. More generally, it implies that much of the variation in species abundances reflects variation in the strength of intraspecific density dependence, since interspecific density dependence was generally quite weak. Plant community ecologists have traditionally focused more on understanding competition between than within species; our results suggest that these priorities should be reconsidered.    Some of our results suggest that simple models can work as well as complex models for forecasting the ecological impacts of climate change. For example, in plant communities where niche overlap is low, and interspecific interactions are weak, single species models should work well. Furthermore, models built using population-level data can predict as well as models based on individual-level demographic data. These results give cause for optimism.   On the other hand, we are learning that predicting the direct effects of precipitation and temperature on demographic rates and population dynamics is much more difficult than we expected. In both experimental tests of models based on observational data and cross-validation tests with long-term data, we can only make skillful forecasts for half of the species we have studied, and our criteria for "skillful" is low (outperforming a null model assuming no effects of climate variables). We are now planning future work to identify why this problem is so difficult and to identify strategies most likely to improve forecast skill.   The project also included an outreach and education goal to improve communication between researchers and land managers through a series of distributed graduate courses focused on climate change vulnerability assessment in the Intermountain West. The course, taught in 2012 and 2013, involved 8 instructors and over 40 graduate students from 6 universities. Products included a series of "fact sheets" about climate change impacts on sagebrush steppe ecosystems, now available on the internet, and a symposium at the 2015 annual Society for Range Management meeting in February, 2015. The course also led to new research, funded by the US Fish and Wildlife Service and USGS, which used a model-comparison approach to show that climate change will have negative impacts on sagebrush cover only in the hottest portion of the Intermountain West; in cooler locations, warming appears likely to have weak or even positive effects on sagebrush cover.    In addition to the distributed graduate course, the project provided one-on-one research training for two post-doctoral fellows, four graduate students, two undergraduate researchers, and seven undergraduate research technicians. These students gained experience with quantitative techniques including database management, programming, and statistical and mathematical modeling.             Last Modified: 02/18/2017       Submitted by: Peter B Adler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
