<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Deconvoluting Fibroblast Mechanobiology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>416500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Fyhrie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dfyhrie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to clarify fibroblast mechanobiology by examining cellular response from mechanical stimuli, through intracellular mechanotransduction, and finally to changes in phenotype and function of the cell. Fibroblasts are ubiquitous cells found in most tissues and are primarily driven by mechanical cues with the goal of providing structural support to these tissues. To accomplish this, the following objectives are proposed: 1) develop a novel, combined system for applying well-defined strain regimes to cultured fibroblasts while assessing their response with atomic force microscopy and fluorescence microscopy, 2) examine fibroblasts under strain regimes mimicking growth, injury, and disease, and 3) expose fibroblasts that have selectively inhibited mechanotransductive elements (via genetic deletion or pharmacological inhibition) to strain regimes in a combinatorial fashion to reveal their interdependence in the mechanotransduction of extracellular forces to the nucleus of the cell. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The impact of this award will lead to innovations for the field of tissue engineering, which heavily relies on cell response to in vitro training regimes. Further, the outreach and educational component of this award is centered on the message that Engineering Innovation and will be targeted to minority and underrepresented middle and high school students, teachers, and counselors. Specifically, an interactive presentation will be developed for middle and high school students describing how biology is one of the next frontiers for engineers by beginning with the question: how does a cell know when it has been stretched? This presentation will incorporate biology, chemistry, medicine, and engineering to demonstrate how engineers innovatively solve complex problems, often at the interface between fields. The expectation is that this program will open the door of engineering to students, who because of their environment, may have never known that engineering was a possible, desirable, or exciting career.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1055384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Merryman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William D Merryman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.merryman@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153227219</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000564440</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs Administratio]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7479</Code>
<Text>BMMB-Biomech &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~16500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of this award are focused on elucidating the various molecular signaling pathways that are activated during fibroblast to myofibroblast conversion, which occurs in fibrotic disease. The primary focus of this work was on:</p> <p>1. How cells sense neighboring cells via cadherin bonds. In this area we focused our work on cadherin-11, which is a robust cell-cell junction and appears after myofibroblast differentation.&nbsp;</p> <p>2. How the cytoskeleton protein, smooth muscle alpha actin, is expressed due to mechanical stimuli, such as substrate stiffness or applied strain.&nbsp;</p> <p>3. Which focal adhesions protein kinases are responsible for transmitting the outside-in signal that leads to changes in fibroblasts.&nbsp;</p> <p>Within these contexts, we focused our research on general fibroblasts (mouse embryonic fibroblasts) and tissue-specific fibroblasts (heart valve, cardiac, pulmonary, etc). These results were published in multiple articles and were also used to generate new hypotheses about the role of fibroblast mechanobiology in various diseases.&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, these research areas were integrated into multiple teaching and outreach activities, such as:</p> <p>1. A three week short course on cardiac mechanobiology and engineering was taught at a local all-girls HS to 15 9th grade girls.&nbsp;</p> <p>2. Two teachers joined our laboratory over the summer for an RET to learn bench-top techniques that they took back to their schools with them.&nbsp;</p> <p>3. We produced a short video on the message that Engineering is Innovation that can be accessed here: https://vimeo.com/87062863&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2016<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;D&nbsp;Merryman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of this award are focused on elucidating the various molecular signaling pathways that are activated during fibroblast to myofibroblast conversion, which occurs in fibrotic disease. The primary focus of this work was on:  1. How cells sense neighboring cells via cadherin bonds. In this area we focused our work on cadherin-11, which is a robust cell-cell junction and appears after myofibroblast differentation.   2. How the cytoskeleton protein, smooth muscle alpha actin, is expressed due to mechanical stimuli, such as substrate stiffness or applied strain.   3. Which focal adhesions protein kinases are responsible for transmitting the outside-in signal that leads to changes in fibroblasts.   Within these contexts, we focused our research on general fibroblasts (mouse embryonic fibroblasts) and tissue-specific fibroblasts (heart valve, cardiac, pulmonary, etc). These results were published in multiple articles and were also used to generate new hypotheses about the role of fibroblast mechanobiology in various diseases.   Additionally, these research areas were integrated into multiple teaching and outreach activities, such as:  1. A three week short course on cardiac mechanobiology and engineering was taught at a local all-girls HS to 15 9th grade girls.   2. Two teachers joined our laboratory over the summer for an RET to learn bench-top techniques that they took back to their schools with them.   3. We produced a short video on the message that Engineering is Innovation that can be accessed here: https://vimeo.com/87062863        Last Modified: 11/01/2016       Submitted by: William D Merryman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
