<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Using hydroclimatic thresholds and changing baselines to develop decision tools for adaptive water use policy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>406551.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>452688</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927066</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1055934 (Jain) The research objective of this CAREER proposal is to deliver a comprehensive decision tool to analyze hydrologic changes and quantify impacts on humans and ecosystems and test and assess the adequacy of policy in the face of changing climate and uncertain forecasts. The project would use downscaled GCM output to drive a land surface/watershed model capable of predicting policy relevant metrics such as flow duration curves and indicators of hydrologic alteration which would then be used to determine adaptive water use policy that would help to meet targets under current and future climate conditions.  The research methodology to be applied, in collaboration with the Maine Department of Environmental Protection and a broad range of water-related stakeholder groups, uses a systems modeling approach complemented by a research-stakeholder collaborative.  This award's educational component complements the research activities, seeking to redress perceived gaps in the present Environmental Science and Engineering curriculum relative to sustainability of water infrastructure. The data, models, methodologies, and case studies emanating from research will be integrated with teaching and outreach activities throughout the K-20 educational system and in informal education settings by: (a) development of programmable media-based watershed models for the Penobscot River Watershed?integrating K-12 science, geography and culture into active storytelling and sharing, (b) collaborative work with University of Maine?s Wabanaki Center to develop a sustained engagement on watershed sustainability education with students and teachers from the Penobscot and Passamaquoddy Indian schools, and (c) creating and revising undergraduate and graduate level courses focusing on interdisciplinary watershed sustainability topics.  The integrated research and educational plan represents a first step towards a long-term commitment to develop the capacity for innovative environmental solutions guided by principles of sustainability. Long-term benefits include not only the scientific and technical knowledge necessary to identify and develop effective environmental solutions but also generation of citizens equipped to grasp the challenges and respond to the imperative of environmental sustainability in a changing climate.  Ascertaining flexibility, probability of surprises, and determining courses of action (flexibility in policy) demand deep engagement of the researcher-agency-stakeholder collective. Participation of Maine?s Passamaquoddy and Penobscot middle-school students extends a unique opportunity to this traditionally underrepresented group to aspire to higher levels of learning and education. The partnership with the University?s Wabanaki Center will help ensure long-term engagement and assimilation of new knowledge regarding effective models of STEM outreach throughout the state and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1055934</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shaleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Jain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shaleen Jain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shaleen.jain@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812420</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000493310</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186875787</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071750426</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5717 Corbett Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>145E</Code>
<Text>Water sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~403255</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~49431</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Water allocation to meet human needs while maintaing the integrity of ecosystems is a major challenge around the world. In this project, Shaleen Jain and students at the University of Maine pursued analysis and modeling of watersheds in New England to understand the recent changes in streamflow, how water withdrawals may impact river flow regime, and the nature and impact of early ice-out in Maine lakes. They found that large-scale climatic phenomenon named El Nino influences the timing of lake ice out and also affects high river flows in the winter seasons. These results highlight the prospect of season-ahead forecasts of early lake ice out, with the potential to inform recreational use of lakes, water quality and ecosystem-related concerns. Students are developing computer-based decision tools to investigate the manner in which a sustainable water policy can benefit communities, and at the same time understand trade-offs linked to rising water demands and uncertain water supplies.&nbsp;</p> <p>A linked effort involved the development of learning modules focused on water movement and use, using the Scratch computing environment. Jain and student researchers presented the tools at a local school, developed a workshop for middle school students, and explored the ways in which computer programming and visualization and environmental education can be melded in an effective manner.&nbsp;</p> <p>Jain introduced environmental sustainability concepts in a first-year introductory engineering course at the University of Maine, and also developed a new gradaute course titled, "Water Resources Sustainability."</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Shaleen&nbsp;Jain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539351454203_Jain1055934Image02--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539351454203_Jain1055934Image02--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Building environmental models from Scratch"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539351454203_Jain1055934Image02--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Building environmental models from Scratch"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Travis Hall, a teacher at Holbrook Middle School in Holden, Maine works with a student at the Northern Maine Children's Water Festival. Mr. Hall noted, "These kids link into computers well, so this is a phenomenal situation for them to use computers in a real-world sense." University of Maine</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Maine</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shaleen&nbsp;Jain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Building environmental models from Scratch</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539350894637_Jain1055934Image01--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539350894637_Jain1055934Image01--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Scratch-based Environmental Models"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539350894637_Jain1055934Image01--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Scratch-based Environmental Models"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Regina Smith, an undergraduate researcher at the University of Maine working with a middle school student at the Northern Maine Children's Water Festival. Students manipulated the water model variables, added new components to the computer code and explored the role and impact of visualizations.</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Maine</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shaleen&nbsp;Jain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Scratch-based Environmental Models</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539350510099_TiminBudapest--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539350510099_TiminBudapest--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Scratch-based Environmental Education Module"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1055934/1055934_10096826_1539350510099_TiminBudapest--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Scratch-based Environmental Education Module"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tim Baker, a University of Maine graduate student developed simplified water cycle models as a means to engage middle-school students. The initial model instance was remixed by students to express their own perspectives and also explore various scenarios--from floods to droughts.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shaleen Jain</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shaleen&nbsp;Jain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Scratch-based Environmental Education Module</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Water allocation to meet human needs while maintaing the integrity of ecosystems is a major challenge around the world. In this project, Shaleen Jain and students at the University of Maine pursued analysis and modeling of watersheds in New England to understand the recent changes in streamflow, how water withdrawals may impact river flow regime, and the nature and impact of early ice-out in Maine lakes. They found that large-scale climatic phenomenon named El Nino influences the timing of lake ice out and also affects high river flows in the winter seasons. These results highlight the prospect of season-ahead forecasts of early lake ice out, with the potential to inform recreational use of lakes, water quality and ecosystem-related concerns. Students are developing computer-based decision tools to investigate the manner in which a sustainable water policy can benefit communities, and at the same time understand trade-offs linked to rising water demands and uncertain water supplies.   A linked effort involved the development of learning modules focused on water movement and use, using the Scratch computing environment. Jain and student researchers presented the tools at a local school, developed a workshop for middle school students, and explored the ways in which computer programming and visualization and environmental education can be melded in an effective manner.   Jain introduced environmental sustainability concepts in a first-year introductory engineering course at the University of Maine, and also developed a new gradaute course titled, "Water Resources Sustainability."          Last Modified: 10/12/2018       Submitted by: Shaleen Jain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
