<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Cleaner Water Through Microbial Stress: An Integrated Research and Education Plan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Trace organic compounds (TOrCs) in surface and groundwater present human and ecological health concerns at parts-per-trillion concentrations.  Recent water surveys have revealed that TOrC contamination is widespread, and this threat to potable water is expected to grow through increased demands on finite water supplies in arid regions.  Since remediation of contaminated waters is challenging and expensive, the goal of this research is to gain a fundamental understanding of how microbial stress can impact the natural degradation of TOrCs. Results from this study should have application to treatment in managed natural systems.  Objectives of this research plan are to A) determine the correlation between enzyme expression, microbial stress, and TOrC degradation using nitrosamines as a model compound, B) explore the relevance of these findings toward indigenous microbial assemblages in soil barriers and C) investigate the broader role of microbial stress in biodegradation of other TOrCs.  Objectives will be addressed through a suite of interdisciplinary experiments that will be scaled from fundamental pure strain studies to more heterogeneous and biodiverse soil systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of the broader impacts, research efforts will be coupled with an educational plan designed to increase the engagement and diversity of students in environmental science and engineering.  The objectives of the educational plan are to improve learning outcomes of undergraduate environmental engineering students through ?client? interactions with a local nonprofit watershed group and to deliver modules that engage at-risk middle school students with K-12 teachers and scientific researchers in projects relating to environmental water quality.  A nontraditional, field-based undergraduate course that focuses on the assessment and remediation of abandoned mining operations will enable students to become involved in solutions to regional environmental problems and see the implementation of their findings.  Similarly, interactive K-12 teacher-driven modules will engage at-risk youth with collegiate researchers while integrating regional water quality themes into curricular requirements. Student tracking and a multi-faceted assessment of educational activities that involve students, instructors, external educators, and nonprofit organizations will be conducted.   Advancing our fundamental understanding of the biodegradation of TOrCs benefits society by furthering the development of a new generation of managed natural treatment technologies.  This work may lead to novel processes for the enhancement of natural biodegradation of extremely low concentrations of organic pollutants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1055396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan O Sharp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsharp@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3032733473</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536642</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE COLORADO SCHOOL OF MINES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado School of Mines]]></Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 Illinois]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>015E</Code>
<Text>Pollutant fate and transport</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Project Outcomes Report - NSF Award # 1055396</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>CAREER: Cleaner Water Through Microbial Stress: An Integrated Research and Education Plan</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Jonathan O. Sharp, Associate Professor of Civil and Environmental Engineering</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Colorado School of Mines, Golden, CO</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;While we often associate microorganisms with disease, there is an ever-growing understanding of their beneficial value for human health and engineering applications. This grant supported research investigations into the role of microbial metabolic processes to improve water quality using sustainable alternatives to more traditional engineered water treatment. We applied this theme to both passive (managed aquifer recharge, riverbank filtration, engineered wetlands) and engineered water treatment infrastructure (biofiltration) to understand the attenuation of water pollutants such as nutrients, pharmaceuticals and personal care products whose removal is traditionally energy and cost intensive. In the case of managed aquifer recharge and riverbank filtration, we found that pharmaceutical and disinfection byproduct attenuation is most pronounced when there is sufficient bioavailable organic carbon to support core respiratory processes but limited enough to push metabolism toward these emerging water pollutants. In essence, this represents a sort of starvation stress diet that drives microorganisms to consume these less desirable substrates when there is a modest quantity of desirable organics to sustain the community. This concept of a microbial &ldquo;sweet spot&rdquo; for contaminant attenuation also extended to engineered wetlands that were colonized by photosynthetic biofilms. Specifically, vertical gradients established within these biofilm created ideal zones for enhanced nitrate and pharmaceutical attenuation. Rates of removal rivaled, and in many cases exceeded, those of more traditional engineered wetlands, which could help decrease the footprint and increase the reliability of these designs for water treatment. We also explored the capabilities of biologically activated carbon as an alternative to traditional filtration in water treatment plants. Consistent with our prior work in aquifer recharge, bioreactor depth was found to exert selective pressures on contaminant biotransformation and microbial ecology. These findings help system-specific design to ensure adequate depth and retention for desirable biodegradation process while also mitigating the transient formation of toxic intermediates.</p> <p>&nbsp;The impact of this award was not limited to these scientific and engineering insights. In addition to supporting several PhD graduate student researchers directly involved in the project, more than five undergraduates were involved in various stages of research inquiry. Collectively this enabled the training of a new generation of college-educated scientists and engineers ready to tackle our society&rsquo;s water challenges. Another hallmark of this CAREER Young Investigator award was to foster the development of place-based, hands-on undergraduate learning. Over the course of this award, I led a novel field-based course where undergraduate environmental engineers (~150 over 5 years) addressed the environmental impact of orphaned and abandoned mines in the region. A hallmark of this course involved close collaboration with a local nonprofit who negotiated our access to these sites so that we could conduct environmental site assessments and develop low-cost best practice solutions to limit the impacts of legacy mining on regional water quality. Both student and accreditor feedback highlighted this course as a unique and valuable approach to education. Scientific outreach was further extended to K-12 students through community and school science fairs and exhibitions, classroom environmental learning for the future module delivery, and by collaborating with 6<sup>th</sup> grade teachers to develop age appropriate standards-based lesson plans for their classrooms as part of a Research Experiences for Teachers summer program. Specifically, four of these teachers were co-hosted in our laboratory over two summers and a total of five different environmental microbiology modules were extended to other K-12 teachers within the program.&nbsp; Collectively, this grant had impact on a new generation of citizens across the kindergarten to postgraduate spectrum that now have an increased understanding of the importance of, and familiarity with, novel and sustainable engineering solutions to water challenges of the future. &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;O&nbsp;Sharp</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Project Outcomes Report - NSF Award # 1055396  CAREER: Cleaner Water Through Microbial Stress: An Integrated Research and Education Plan Jonathan O. Sharp, Associate Professor of Civil and Environmental Engineering Colorado School of Mines, Golden, CO   While we often associate microorganisms with disease, there is an ever-growing understanding of their beneficial value for human health and engineering applications. This grant supported research investigations into the role of microbial metabolic processes to improve water quality using sustainable alternatives to more traditional engineered water treatment. We applied this theme to both passive (managed aquifer recharge, riverbank filtration, engineered wetlands) and engineered water treatment infrastructure (biofiltration) to understand the attenuation of water pollutants such as nutrients, pharmaceuticals and personal care products whose removal is traditionally energy and cost intensive. In the case of managed aquifer recharge and riverbank filtration, we found that pharmaceutical and disinfection byproduct attenuation is most pronounced when there is sufficient bioavailable organic carbon to support core respiratory processes but limited enough to push metabolism toward these emerging water pollutants. In essence, this represents a sort of starvation stress diet that drives microorganisms to consume these less desirable substrates when there is a modest quantity of desirable organics to sustain the community. This concept of a microbial "sweet spot" for contaminant attenuation also extended to engineered wetlands that were colonized by photosynthetic biofilms. Specifically, vertical gradients established within these biofilm created ideal zones for enhanced nitrate and pharmaceutical attenuation. Rates of removal rivaled, and in many cases exceeded, those of more traditional engineered wetlands, which could help decrease the footprint and increase the reliability of these designs for water treatment. We also explored the capabilities of biologically activated carbon as an alternative to traditional filtration in water treatment plants. Consistent with our prior work in aquifer recharge, bioreactor depth was found to exert selective pressures on contaminant biotransformation and microbial ecology. These findings help system-specific design to ensure adequate depth and retention for desirable biodegradation process while also mitigating the transient formation of toxic intermediates.   The impact of this award was not limited to these scientific and engineering insights. In addition to supporting several PhD graduate student researchers directly involved in the project, more than five undergraduates were involved in various stages of research inquiry. Collectively this enabled the training of a new generation of college-educated scientists and engineers ready to tackle our society?s water challenges. Another hallmark of this CAREER Young Investigator award was to foster the development of place-based, hands-on undergraduate learning. Over the course of this award, I led a novel field-based course where undergraduate environmental engineers (~150 over 5 years) addressed the environmental impact of orphaned and abandoned mines in the region. A hallmark of this course involved close collaboration with a local nonprofit who negotiated our access to these sites so that we could conduct environmental site assessments and develop low-cost best practice solutions to limit the impacts of legacy mining on regional water quality. Both student and accreditor feedback highlighted this course as a unique and valuable approach to education. Scientific outreach was further extended to K-12 students through community and school science fairs and exhibitions, classroom environmental learning for the future module delivery, and by collaborating with 6th grade teachers to develop age appropriate standards-based lesson plans for their classrooms as part of a Research Experiences for Teachers summer program. Specifically, four of these teachers were co-hosted in our laboratory over two summers and a total of five different environmental microbiology modules were extended to other K-12 teachers within the program.  Collectively, this grant had impact on a new generation of citizens across the kindergarten to postgraduate spectrum that now have an increased understanding of the importance of, and familiarity with, novel and sustainable engineering solutions to water challenges of the future.               Last Modified: 12/28/2017       Submitted by: Jonathan O Sharp]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
