<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Bifocal Modeling: A New Famework for the Learning of Advanced STEM Content in High-school</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>628883.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>628883</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregg Solomon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gesolomo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928333</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI proposes to advance the idea of "bifocal modeling" to promote understanding of how and why things work. In bifocal modeling, learners build a model of a device or phenomenon in the real world and attach sensors to it, and they build a virtual model (on the computer) of the same device or phenomenon using one of several modeling platforms. They run both models, and explore and investigate the function and behavior of the device or phenomenon using both models. The approach is designed to help learners construct explanatory mental models of phenomena and devices they encounter. The need to reconcile the differences between the models focuses learners on details they might not have noticed if working with just one model. As they engage in bifocal modeling activities, learners encounter issues concerning the purpose and veracity of models, human error, sensors, and science practice. Thus, in addition to facilitating learning of the science behind the phenomenon they are exploring, learners have opportunities to learn about the roles of models in science and how to design, construct, and use models scientifically.  Engaging for a sustained period of time is necessary for such learning, and the approach has learners engage in bifocal modeling in the context of exploring phenomena and devices that they have grown curious about in the context of science or technology activities. The approach has potential to be used in school or out of school, and it might be used to cover targeted science or to supplement classroom activities. The project has phases that include investigating the efficacy and feasibility of bifocal modeling in a variety of circumstances, identifying the ways it might be productively used in school and to supplement school, understanding how learning happens when learning in the context of bifocal modeling, iteratively designing curriculum modules based on findings (and testing them), and iteratively refining the software and hardware that goes with those curriculum models so as to come to better understand of how to use them to promote learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work has potential to help young people (and perhaps others) learn the science behind phenomena of interest and become better scientific reasoners. Citizens who understand the roles of models in science and who can design, construct, and/or use them to reason scientifically will be able to take part in the discussions of our democracy and be ready to prepare for scientific careers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1055130</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paulo</FirstName>
<LastName>Blikstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paulo Blikstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paulob@tc.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8475714538</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000547976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~87807</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~254627</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~149310</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~137139</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h2>Goals</h2> <p><em>The Bifocal Modeling Framework (BMF) is an inquiry-based approach for science learning that challenges students to design, compare, and examine the relationships between lab experiments and computer models connected in real-time </em>(this dual focus motivates the <strong>bifocal</strong>&nbsp;designation.) In a typical Bifocal Modeling activity, students explore a phenomenon by designing and interacting with a physical experiment (often equipped with electronic sensors) and a computer model of the same phenomenon, comparing them in real-time. The aim is to emphasize the relationship between the theorized behavior represented in the computer model, and the real-world data stream coming from the experiment. The original proposal had two main research foci. The first was around the understanding of the learning, cognitive, and epistemological aspects of Bifocal Modeling. The second focus was about the dynamics of classroom implementations, determining the supports required to make this project implementable in classrooms, especially in public schools.</p> <h2>Three cycles of studies and development</h2> <p>The project had <em>three cycles of iterations, </em>based on the tenets of Design-Based Research (DBR). At each cycle, based on multiple research studies, we refined the design, tools, and methodologies, in order to inform the subsequent cycle.</p> <p><strong>1. Pilot studies and preparing the infrastructure</strong></p> <p>The first cycle was focused on preparing the framework for research and enactment of the approach in a classroom setting. It included the following:</p> <ul> <li> Design and development of research tools, such as surveys, semi-structured interviews and observation protocols.</li> <li>Pilot lab studies to understand the potential and requirements for future classroom studies.</li> <li>Development of sensor and computer modeling technologies (GoGo Board, sensor conversion hardware, NetLogo extension for the GoGo Board)</li> </ul> <p>Findings suggested that as students compared their virtual models with physical experiments, they encountered <strong>discrepant events</strong>&nbsp;that contradicted their existing conceptions and elicited cognitive disequilibrium. This experience of conflict encouraged students to further examine their ideas and seek more accurate explanations, improving the design of their computer models. In addition, students showed more attention to issues of scientific precision, intrinsic measurement error, and to the differences between real and ideal systems. Data also suggested that students were more confident in their abilities as scientists in the classroom context when they came to understand that the work of scientists is often imprecise and that scientific laws are only approximations of the real phenomena. Other studies showed that students who participated in Bifocal Modeling activities demonstrate a better understanding of the target content and their meta?modeling knowledge, with stronger effects when the treatment group designed their own models instead of just interaction with pre-made models. These initial studies suggested that implementation choices (e.g., model design versus no design) significantly impacted learning gains.</p> <p><strong><em>2. Developing the content and curricula</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>Te main objective of this component was to investigate supports required to make Bifocal Modeling implementable by teachers and sustainable in schools for diverse populations. This step included:</p> <ul> <li> Studies in several diverse classrooms.</li> <li>Development of tools and instruments for data analysis: developing rubrics and coding schemes, as well as data analysis frameworks.</li> <li>Development of several curricular units investigating different implementation modes for Bifocal Modeling.</li> </ul> <p>According to studies conducted in this phase, participating in Bifocal Modeling activities which were focused on designing (instead of only manipulating) models encouraged students to further examine their hypothesis, seek more accurate explanations of the observed phenomena, and improve the design of their computer models. Results show a statistically significant gain in both content and meta-modeling knowledge (24% (p&lt;0.0001), and 17% (p&lt;0.02) respectively.) In a different study, we were able to demonstrate a significant increase in content knowledge as well as improved modeling and question-asking skills. In addition, in implementation studies with teachers, we traced roadmaps for classroom deployment and determined preconditions and infrastructures needed for teachers to run Bifocal Modeling activities themselves.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>3. Implementation and scaling up</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>This phase focused on disseminating and scaling up the Bifocal Modeling framework and curricula. The idea was to lay out the foundation for sustainable and broad implementation. It included four main activities:</p> <ul> <li>Professional development activities for teachers, such as workshops, residencies, and a co-design program.</li> <li>Development &amp; enactment of full units after co-design with teachers, with the goal of disseminating the curricula into formal education.</li> <li>Implementation and scale-up in schools in the US and internationally (Brazil, Italy, Hong Kong).</li> </ul> <h2>Conclusion</h2> <p>In conclusion, we were able to create a new type of activity for Science classrooms, in which students design and compare experiments and computer models in real time, and were able to work with several teachers in order to develop units and implementation guides for public schools. Several of the teachers from our first cohorts still deliver the Bifocal units even after the research team has left the school, and new groups of teachers are now joining the project in Brazil, Hong Kong, and Italy.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="color: #158155; font-size: 16px;">Resources:&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><a href="https://tltlab.org/portfolio_page/bifocal-modeling/">https://tltlab.org/portfolio_page/bifocal-modeling/</a></p> <p><a href="https://tltlab.org/portfolio_page/bifocal-modeling/">https://bifocalmodeling.stanford.edu</a></p> <p><a href="http://tltl.stanford.edu/projects/bifocal-modeling">http://tltl.stanford.edu/projects/bifocal-modeling</a></p> <p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5&amp;q=bifocal+modeling&amp;btnG=http://tltl.stanford.edu/projects/bifocal-modeling">https://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5&amp;q=bifocal+modeling&amp;btnG=http://tltl.stanford.edu/projects/bifocal-modeling</a></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658041583_Figure1.BifocalFramework--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658041583_Figure1.BifocalFramework--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bifocal Modeling Framework"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658041583_Figure1.BifocalFramework--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bifocal Modeling Framework"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Bifocal Modeling Framework: real data from experiments, simulated data from computer models, and comparison in real time.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paulo Blikstein</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bifocal Modeling Framework</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658528347_Figure5.Bacterialgrowthstudy-comparingphysicalexperimentwithcomputermodel--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658528347_Figure5.Bacterialgrowthstudy-comparingphysicalexperimentwithcomputermodel--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example of Bacterial Growth Experiment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658528347_Figure5.Bacterialgrowthstudy-comparingphysicalexperimentwithcomputermodel--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example of Bacterial Growth Experiment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example of Bacterial Growth Experiment and computer model, side by side.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paulo Blikstein</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example of Bacterial Growth Experiment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658631344_Figure6.Osmosis&amp;Diffusionstudy-comparingphysicalexperimentwithcomputermodel--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658631344_Figure6.Osmosis&amp;Diffusionstudy-comparingphysicalexperimentwithcomputermodel--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Osmosis and Diffusion study"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658631344_Figure6.Osmosis&amp;Diffusionstudy-comparingphysicalexperimentwithcomputermodel--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Osmosis and Diffusion study"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Osmosis and Diffusion study, in which students compare the data from the physical experiment with a "naked egg" and the corresponding NetLogo computer model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paulo Blikstein</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</div> <div class="imageTitle">Osmosis and Diffusion study</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658732234_Figure4.BifocalModelingunitsdesignedbystudentsB--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658732234_Figure4.BifocalModelingunitsdesignedbystudentsB--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Examples of Bifocal Modeling Units (2)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658732234_Figure4.BifocalModelingunitsdesignedbystudentsB--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Examples of Bifocal Modeling Units (2)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of Bifocal Modeling units, with their physical experiments and computer models side-by-side. From top left, clockwise: (1) Diffusion, (2) Gas Laws, (3) Climate Change and Greenhouse Effect, (4) Oil Spill.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paulo Blikstein</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</div> <div class="imageTitle">Examples of Bifocal Modeling Units (2)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658841596_Bifocalunits2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658841596_Bifocalunits2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="List of Bifocal Modeling Units"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658841596_Bifocalunits2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="List of Bifocal Modeling Units"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">List of Bifocal Modeling units developed during the project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paulo Blikstein</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</div> <div class="imageTitle">List of Bifocal Modeling Units</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658085123_Figure3.BifocalModelingunitsdesignedbystudents--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658085123_Figure3.BifocalModelingunitsdesignedbystudents--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Examples of Bifocal Modeling Units"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1055130/1055130_10105431_1562658085123_Figure3.BifocalModelingunitsdesignedbystudents--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Examples of Bifocal Modeling Units"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of Bifocal Modeling units, with their physical experiments and computer models side-by-side. From top left, clockwise: (1) and (2) Heat transfer, (3) Waves, (4) Human biology and blood transport, (5) Newtonian physics in a roller coaster, (6) Buoyancy</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paulo Blikstein</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paulo&nbsp;Blikstein</div> <div class="imageTitle">Examples of Bifocal Modeling Units</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Goals  The Bifocal Modeling Framework (BMF) is an inquiry-based approach for science learning that challenges students to design, compare, and examine the relationships between lab experiments and computer models connected in real-time (this dual focus motivates the bifocal designation.) In a typical Bifocal Modeling activity, students explore a phenomenon by designing and interacting with a physical experiment (often equipped with electronic sensors) and a computer model of the same phenomenon, comparing them in real-time. The aim is to emphasize the relationship between the theorized behavior represented in the computer model, and the real-world data stream coming from the experiment. The original proposal had two main research foci. The first was around the understanding of the learning, cognitive, and epistemological aspects of Bifocal Modeling. The second focus was about the dynamics of classroom implementations, determining the supports required to make this project implementable in classrooms, especially in public schools. Three cycles of studies and development  The project had three cycles of iterations, based on the tenets of Design-Based Research (DBR). At each cycle, based on multiple research studies, we refined the design, tools, and methodologies, in order to inform the subsequent cycle.  1. Pilot studies and preparing the infrastructure  The first cycle was focused on preparing the framework for research and enactment of the approach in a classroom setting. It included the following:   Design and development of research tools, such as surveys, semi-structured interviews and observation protocols. Pilot lab studies to understand the potential and requirements for future classroom studies. Development of sensor and computer modeling technologies (GoGo Board, sensor conversion hardware, NetLogo extension for the GoGo Board)   Findings suggested that as students compared their virtual models with physical experiments, they encountered discrepant events that contradicted their existing conceptions and elicited cognitive disequilibrium. This experience of conflict encouraged students to further examine their ideas and seek more accurate explanations, improving the design of their computer models. In addition, students showed more attention to issues of scientific precision, intrinsic measurement error, and to the differences between real and ideal systems. Data also suggested that students were more confident in their abilities as scientists in the classroom context when they came to understand that the work of scientists is often imprecise and that scientific laws are only approximations of the real phenomena. Other studies showed that students who participated in Bifocal Modeling activities demonstrate a better understanding of the target content and their meta?modeling knowledge, with stronger effects when the treatment group designed their own models instead of just interaction with pre-made models. These initial studies suggested that implementation choices (e.g., model design versus no design) significantly impacted learning gains.  2. Developing the content and curricula   Te main objective of this component was to investigate supports required to make Bifocal Modeling implementable by teachers and sustainable in schools for diverse populations. This step included:   Studies in several diverse classrooms. Development of tools and instruments for data analysis: developing rubrics and coding schemes, as well as data analysis frameworks. Development of several curricular units investigating different implementation modes for Bifocal Modeling.   According to studies conducted in this phase, participating in Bifocal Modeling activities which were focused on designing (instead of only manipulating) models encouraged students to further examine their hypothesis, seek more accurate explanations of the observed phenomena, and improve the design of their computer models. Results show a statistically significant gain in both content and meta-modeling knowledge (24% (p&lt;0.0001), and 17% (p&lt;0.02) respectively.) In a different study, we were able to demonstrate a significant increase in content knowledge as well as improved modeling and question-asking skills. In addition, in implementation studies with teachers, we traced roadmaps for classroom deployment and determined preconditions and infrastructures needed for teachers to run Bifocal Modeling activities themselves.    3. Implementation and scaling up   This phase focused on disseminating and scaling up the Bifocal Modeling framework and curricula. The idea was to lay out the foundation for sustainable and broad implementation. It included four main activities:  Professional development activities for teachers, such as workshops, residencies, and a co-design program. Development &amp; enactment of full units after co-design with teachers, with the goal of disseminating the curricula into formal education. Implementation and scale-up in schools in the US and internationally (Brazil, Italy, Hong Kong).  Conclusion  In conclusion, we were able to create a new type of activity for Science classrooms, in which students design and compare experiments and computer models in real time, and were able to work with several teachers in order to develop units and implementation guides for public schools. Several of the teachers from our first cohorts still deliver the Bifocal units even after the research team has left the school, and new groups of teachers are now joining the project in Brazil, Hong Kong, and Italy.   Resources:   https://tltlab.org/portfolio_page/bifocal-modeling/  https://bifocalmodeling.stanford.edu  http://tltl.stanford.edu/projects/bifocal-modeling  https://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5&amp;q=bifocal+modeling&amp;btnG=http://tltl.stanford.edu/projects/bifocal-modeling       Last Modified: 07/09/2019       Submitted by: Paulo Blikstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
