<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Federal Policy and Scientific Research on American Physique</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kelly Moore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project examines how the U.S. federal government invested in and used science to create specific kinds of standards.  While the focus on fitness and health seem like contemporary concerns, they actually date back to the calorie experiments of 19th century Agricultural Experiment Stations, the 1920s nutrition advice of the Home Economics Bureau, and the 1950s fitness projects of the President's Commission on Physical Fitness.  Although the impact of such projects has been extraordinary, these multiple agencies and bureaus have never been understood as critical stakeholders in a continuous discussion of good citizens or fit bodies. Political historians have largely avoided the seemingly cultural domain of physique (weight, size, musculature), while cultural historians have tended to overlook the political and scientific aspects of fitness. This research offers a corrective, bringing the state's investment and the role of science in definitions of normal bodies to the fore.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the different government agencies and types of scientific expertise and government agencies involved in changes in weight and musculature standards. The research centers on three main questions. First, how did physique become legitimized as a concern of the U.S. federal government? Second, how were decisions about physical measurements made, and how were physiological standards set? How and why did these standards change over time?  Third, what were the political implications of these changing body standards? That is, did these standards simultaneously include and exclude individuals as normal citizens? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators' methodology is based in extensive archival work. Documents and materials are examined through qualitative study, consisting primarily of critical textual analysis. Such historical scholarship offers insight into the complexity of state agencies and forms of scientific expertise, and provides an analytical framework to study contemporary debates about health and fitness. The project uncovers and theorizes a largely forgotten history in a way that promises to impact policy studies, anthropological and sociological studies of the body, and the history of science. It also brings attention to some understudied federal archive collections such as the Home Economics Bureau and the President's Commission on Physical Fitness. Its subject matter is of great contemporary interest, as it provides needed historical context for current debates over government intervention in American standards for weight and fitness.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1057527</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
<LastName>Eghigian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Greg A Eghigian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gae2@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148659022</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000188877</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Moran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel L Moran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rachel.moran@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9403695120</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1353</Code>
<Text>Hist &amp; Philosophy of SET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8815</Code>
<Text>Studies of Policy Sci Eng Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes for the General Public<br /><span>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Federal Policy and Scientific Research on American Physique</span></p><p>Today, the federal government is regularly called to sort out the political problems of American bodies. The apparent obesity of citizens is frequently attributed to government decisions such as subsidies for the production of high fructose corn syrup and the underfunding of public school lunch programs.&nbsp; City, state and federal governments are nonetheless often considered the logical channels to fix the crisis, perhaps through taxes on sodas, legislation mandating calories on restaurant menus, or the banning of trans fats. &nbsp;First Lady Michelle Obama has taken up this public concern through her &ldquo;Let's Move&rdquo; initiative. The political nature of these concerns is often justified through estimated costs of obesity to Medicare and Medicaid, as well as the percentage of GDP such medical interventions represent.&nbsp; While opposition to these centralized health and welfare measures can be vocal, most notable is simply that concerns over body weight and physique represent a national, highly-political issue.</p><p>This project uses extensive original research in archives to contextualize contemporary tensions. We examines how and why weight and physique became issues of substantial concern to the federal government, from the late 19<sup>th</sup>-century up through the present.&nbsp; The research, including month of work at the National Archives, the National Library of Medicine, and the archives of the National Academy of Sciences, was funded by this award and conducted by the CO-PI. The research quickly explodes the myth that government interest in weight is a product of modern &ldquo;obesity epidemic&rdquo; circumstances.&nbsp;</p><p>Our research examines the transformation of the body as an object of government interest. We find that federal policy-making was critical to the federally-funded nutrition science at the turn-of the century, and to the attempts of the Bureau of Home Economics and the Children&rsquo;s Bureau to increase children&rsquo;s weights in the 1920s. Elements of the federal government were also at the core of the obsession with male citizens&rsquo; musculature in the Civilian Conservation Corps and up through the WWII draft, as well as its aftermath. Throughout the first half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century, long before subsidized high fructose corn syrup or White House organic gardens, weight and physique were well established federal concerns. The larger historical import of this political concern with the body rests in the <em>approaches</em> taken in shaping citizen bodies. I reveal agencies fascinated with what we might call a &ldquo;big government&rdquo; project, but save for a little experimentation in the 1930s, willing to address their concerns only through &ldquo;small government&rdquo; mechanisms. Policy makers relied on partnerships with public schools, civic and voluntary organizations, and, by mid-century, corporate collaboration. The research illustrates a long but limp-armed state. We argue that while wide-spread and relatively influential, the lack of financial support or legislative mandate accompanying federal programming relegated American fitness to the realm of political fantasy, not reality. As the contemporary obesity crisis threatens American health, we believe it is critical to look back at the way weight and body policy has taken shape, and the ways in which we can learn from some of these mistakes and develop stronger and more successful health programs.</p><p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/26/2012<br>      Modified by: Rachel&nbsp;Moran</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div> <div class="porColContainerHR"> <div class="porContentCol"> <h2>Addendum # 1</h2><p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p><p>Establishing a historical ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes for the General Public Doctoral Dissertation Research: Federal Policy and Scientific Research on American Physique Today, the federal government is regularly called to sort out the political problems of American bodies. The apparent obesity of citizens is frequently attributed to government decisions such as subsidies for the production of high fructose corn syrup and the underfunding of public school lunch programs.  City, state and federal governments are nonetheless often considered the logical channels to fix the crisis, perhaps through taxes on sodas, legislation mandating calories on restaurant menus, or the banning of trans fats.  First Lady Michelle Obama has taken up this public concern through her "Let's Move" initiative. The political nature of these concerns is often justified through estimated costs of obesity to Medicare and Medicaid, as well as the percentage of GDP such medical interventions represent.  While opposition to these centralized health and welfare measures can be vocal, most notable is simply that concerns over body weight and physique represent a national, highly-political issue. This project uses extensive original research in archives to contextualize contemporary tensions. We examines how and why weight and physique became issues of substantial concern to the federal government, from the late 19th-century up through the present.  The research, including month of work at the National Archives, the National Library of Medicine, and the archives of the National Academy of Sciences, was funded by this award and conducted by the CO-PI. The research quickly explodes the myth that government interest in weight is a product of modern "obesity epidemic" circumstances.  Our research examines the transformation of the body as an object of government interest. We find that federal policy-making was critical to the federally-funded nutrition science at the turn-of the century, and to the attempts of the Bureau of Home Economics and the ChildrenÆs Bureau to increase childrenÆs weights in the 1920s. Elements of the federal government were also at the core of the obsession with male citizensÆ musculature in the Civilian Conservation Corps and up through the WWII draft, as well as its aftermath. Throughout the first half of the 20th century, long before subsidized high fructose corn syrup or White House organic gardens, weight and physique were well established federal concerns. The larger historical import of this political concern with the body rests in the approaches taken in shaping citizen bodies. I reveal agencies fascinated with what we might call a "big government" project, but save for a little experimentation in the 1930s, willing to address their concerns only through "small government" mechanisms. Policy makers relied on partnerships with public schools, civic and voluntary organizations, and, by mid-century, corporate collaboration. The research illustrates a long but limp-armed state. We argue that while wide-spread and relatively influential, the lack of financial support or legislative mandate accompanying federal programming relegated American fitness to the realm of political fantasy, not reality. As the contemporary obesity crisis threatens American health, we believe it is critical to look back at the way weight and body policy has taken shape, and the ways in which we can learn from some of these mistakes and develop stronger and more successful health programs.         Last Modified: 03/26/2012       Submitted by: Rachel Moran Broader Impacts: Establishing a historical baseline for the nature and scope of the government's interest in citizen weight and physique should benefit policymakers concerned with contemporary fitness concerns (like the obesity crisis).   First, this research disproves the myth that federal involvement with weight or physique is "un-American" or otherwise beyond the scope of the American state. While citizens should debate and discuss whether specifi...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
