<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Coherent and Incoherent Energy Transfer in Conjugated Molecules</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program of the Division of Chemistry, supports Valeria Kleiman from the University of Florida to investigate energy migration in conjugated model systems, the material of choice for organic solar cells. The scientific goals will be achieved through the combination of phase sensitive transient techniques with computational tools to investigate excited state electronic coupling in conjunction with nuclear motion. Materials under investigation will include building blocks for conjugated macromolecules and chemically modified dendritic structures with variable band gap energies which can be used for solar energy conversion. A broad impact in the community is expected through a strong educational effort intended to yield highly educated scientists, well versed on the latest tools of state of the art spectroscopy and theoretical calculations regarding light harvesting materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Solar energy conversion has the potential to provide enough energy to fuel the planet, but it requires an understanding of the fundamental properties to be able to create efficient and economic solar energy conversion devices. This proposal addresses these goals by focusing on the initial light harvesting step.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058638</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valeria</FirstName>
<LastName>Kleiman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valeria D Kleiman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kleiman@chem.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523924656</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315251</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was designed&nbsp;to understand and elucidate the mechanisms of excited state energy transfer through the use of time-resolved, phase-sensitive spectroscopy techniques. The program was enhanced by a collaboration with a group of theoreticians who developed new tools&nbsp;to analyzed solution based ensemble-samples of light-harvesting materials. &nbsp;</p> <p>One of the crucial issues on energy transfer in antennae dendrimers is an initial process of spatial localization of the wavepacket. Through the collaboration we embarked in combined experimental- theoretical studies elucidating ultrafast, unidirectional, electronic energy-transfer on complex molecules designed to spatially focus&nbsp;the initial&nbsp;excitation onto an energy-sink. &nbsp;We investigated the interplay between atomic motions, excited-state populations, and localization/delocalization of excitations. &nbsp;We were able to experimentally observe and computationally confirm the presence of multiple pathways for energy transfer in conjugated dendrimers. &nbsp;The time-resolved experiments also revealed energy<em>-</em>transfer mechanisms governed by the degree of flexibility of the backbone and surface charge density. &nbsp;</p> <p>To expand the investigation on the initial mechanism of energy transfer, we extended our experiments to measure the photophysics of transition metal-based monomers and oligomers. Through the use of similar time-resolved techniques we explored electron and energy- transfer in Ru-based light-harvesters.&nbsp; Whereas in the case of organic dendrimers a step-wise process driven by the energy-gradient leads to efficient vectorial energy transfer, a delocalization of the hole in the metal centers seems to be the source of efficient long range transfer in the inorganic compounds. &nbsp;</p> <p>The goal of our program was to educate the next generation of scientists. We are proud to host a diverse group of young minds that come to the University of Florida to learn science and appreciate the research environment.&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>The active mentoring of</em>&nbsp;students and postdocs fomented a productive environment for all to appreciate the wonders of academic life. &nbsp;Students and postdocs attended national and international conferences and interacted with other scientists. &nbsp;The established strong international collaboration exposed students to world-class research laboratories.&nbsp;Graduate, undergraduate students and postdocs had the opportunity to interact with international collaborators, even travelling to Argentina to perform some of the related research and to learn new techniques.&nbsp;</p> <p>The scientific results discovered within this program have been disseminated in the top journals in our field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Valeria&nbsp;D&nbsp;Kleiman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was designed to understand and elucidate the mechanisms of excited state energy transfer through the use of time-resolved, phase-sensitive spectroscopy techniques. The program was enhanced by a collaboration with a group of theoreticians who developed new tools to analyzed solution based ensemble-samples of light-harvesting materials.    One of the crucial issues on energy transfer in antennae dendrimers is an initial process of spatial localization of the wavepacket. Through the collaboration we embarked in combined experimental- theoretical studies elucidating ultrafast, unidirectional, electronic energy-transfer on complex molecules designed to spatially focus the initial excitation onto an energy-sink.  We investigated the interplay between atomic motions, excited-state populations, and localization/delocalization of excitations.  We were able to experimentally observe and computationally confirm the presence of multiple pathways for energy transfer in conjugated dendrimers.  The time-resolved experiments also revealed energy-transfer mechanisms governed by the degree of flexibility of the backbone and surface charge density.    To expand the investigation on the initial mechanism of energy transfer, we extended our experiments to measure the photophysics of transition metal-based monomers and oligomers. Through the use of similar time-resolved techniques we explored electron and energy- transfer in Ru-based light-harvesters.  Whereas in the case of organic dendrimers a step-wise process driven by the energy-gradient leads to efficient vectorial energy transfer, a delocalization of the hole in the metal centers seems to be the source of efficient long range transfer in the inorganic compounds.    The goal of our program was to educate the next generation of scientists. We are proud to host a diverse group of young minds that come to the University of Florida to learn science and appreciate the research environment.  The active mentoring of students and postdocs fomented a productive environment for all to appreciate the wonders of academic life.  Students and postdocs attended national and international conferences and interacted with other scientists.  The established strong international collaboration exposed students to world-class research laboratories. Graduate, undergraduate students and postdocs had the opportunity to interact with international collaborators, even travelling to Argentina to perform some of the related research and to learn new techniques.   The scientific results discovered within this program have been disseminated in the top journals in our field.             Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Valeria D Kleiman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
