<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Low-cost Long-life Diamond Electrodes for Wastewater Treatment using Advanced Electrochemical Oxidation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499939.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>985933</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will employ the boron-doped ultrananocyrstalline diamond (BD-UNCD) electrodes developed during the Phase I project to fabricate and characterize electrochemical cells and systems for the on-site generation (OSG) of advanced oxidants (chlorine-based mixed oxidants - hydrogen peroxide combined with hypochlorite - and sodium persulfate) and apply them to targeted water treatment applications.  The primary research objectives are to determine the optimal conditions to generate oxidants and to establish the projected lifetime of the electrodes.  BD-UNCD cells will demonstrate higher rates of oxidant production at lower costs and with greater energy efficiency than competing electrodes due to higher current densities and over-potentials for O2 and H2 evolution at the anode and cathode. The known difficulties with existing approaches of disinfection, such as the inadequate destruction of pathogens (Cryptosporidium), ineffective operation below 10°C, generation of large quantities of O2 and H2, and electrode fouling are expected to be mitigated substantially through use of BD-UNCD electrodes. Sodium persulfate (SPS) has been used as a highly effective oxidant capable of oxidative destruction of recalcitrant organics such as in oil-contaminated sea water.  BD-UNCD technology will dramatically reduce the cost and increase flexibility of OSG water treatment using SPS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is the development of a safer, cheaper, more environmentally friendly technology to generate "green" oxidants using diamond electrodes that can be used for a number of water treatment applications including purification, disinfection, and remediation. The market for chlorine-based disinfection systems alone is $20 billion with a correspondingly large impact on human health and national security issues associated with transporting vast quantities of hazardous materials.  Overcoming technical barriers that have prevented diamond from being used for oxidant generation will require advances in the synthesis and large-scale manufacturing of diamond thin films that will impact other applications of this material. The electrochemistry of diamond is not well understood in the conditions needed for OSG. Better understanding of these reactions and the technological trade-offs between cell design and electrode geometry will impact related applications including the development of compact systems for third-world potable water generation, small scale desalination, the energy efficient electrochemical synthesis of new materials and other point-of-use applications of advanced oxidants.  Large scale on-site generation of persulfates will enable highly effective treatment of refractory organics found in oil contaminated sea water and waste water associated with bitumen refining.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058505</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlisle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John A Carlisle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carlisle@thindiamond.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8152723969</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000370798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/16/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ADVANCED DIAMOND TECHNOLOGIES</Name>
<CityName>Romeoville</CityName>
<ZipCode>604461764</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8152930900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>48 E Belmont Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>143371388</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADVANCED DIAMOND TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ADVANCED DIAMOND TECHNOLOGIES]]></Name>
<CityName>Romeoville</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>604461764</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[48 E Belmont Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1984</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS SYNTHESIS &amp; PROCESSN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9163</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~486112</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~499821</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary focus of this NSF Phase II project was to improve the durability and economics of diamond electrodes for their application in various electrochemical water treatment technologies. Conducting diamond materials are attractive since they have electrochemical properties that enable the synthesis of higher-order oxidants (such as hydroxyl radicals, ozone, and peroxide). These oxidants in turn can be used to remove contaminants from water that are difficult or impossible to remove using conventional technologies. Advanced Diamond Technologies (ADT) is the world leader in UNCD&reg; (ultrananocrystalline diamond) technology, which is thin, smooth, diamond coatings that are superior to conventional CVD diamond materials for many applications. UNCD technology has lead to orders of magnitude improvements in the lifetime, performance, and economics of diamond electrodes for a number of electrochemical water treatment technologies, including advanced oxidation processes (AOPs), on-site generation of mixed oxidants, and for point-of-use ozonated water generation. The commercial name for this new technology is Diamonox&reg;.</p> <p>During the active period of execution of the project, ADT successfully commercialized the Diamonox OSG (on-site generation) for cooling tower applications, which eliminates the need for and handling of hazardous chemicals to prevent legionella outbreaks in these facilities. ADT also demonstrated the application of Diamonox for oil &amp; gas, ballast water, and mining applications. ADT continues to support its industrial partners as they work to win adoption of their products that incorporate Diamonox with end-customers.</p> <p>Following the successful completion of the Phase IIB work, ADT has focused on expanding opportunities for Diamonox specifically for liquid ozone applications. ADT conducted a market analysis of ozone and concluded that roughly $20M in near-term sales opportunities existed for POU (point of use) ozonated water technologies that currently could not be addressed using conventional UV &amp; corona discharge technologies. ADT is currently in early stage discussions with about five other companies regarding other potential applications of point-of-use ozonated water. ADT is also developing a more generalized product aimed directly at end-customer applications such as commercial pools/spas, cooling towers, food processing, and other applications for which the technology can be retrofitted.</p> <p>ADT also continues to work with potential customers interested in other applications of Diamonox technology, for oil &amp; gas injected water and wastewater treatment as well as for ballast water treatment. ADT is also currently working with the EPA to explore setting up a field trial of its EAOP technology to remove estrogens and other toxic organic chemicals from municipal drinking water (supported by an EPA Phase II SBIR grant).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2015<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Carlisle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary focus of this NSF Phase II project was to improve the durability and economics of diamond electrodes for their application in various electrochemical water treatment technologies. Conducting diamond materials are attractive since they have electrochemical properties that enable the synthesis of higher-order oxidants (such as hydroxyl radicals, ozone, and peroxide). These oxidants in turn can be used to remove contaminants from water that are difficult or impossible to remove using conventional technologies. Advanced Diamond Technologies (ADT) is the world leader in UNCD&reg; (ultrananocrystalline diamond) technology, which is thin, smooth, diamond coatings that are superior to conventional CVD diamond materials for many applications. UNCD technology has lead to orders of magnitude improvements in the lifetime, performance, and economics of diamond electrodes for a number of electrochemical water treatment technologies, including advanced oxidation processes (AOPs), on-site generation of mixed oxidants, and for point-of-use ozonated water generation. The commercial name for this new technology is Diamonox&reg;.  During the active period of execution of the project, ADT successfully commercialized the Diamonox OSG (on-site generation) for cooling tower applications, which eliminates the need for and handling of hazardous chemicals to prevent legionella outbreaks in these facilities. ADT also demonstrated the application of Diamonox for oil &amp; gas, ballast water, and mining applications. ADT continues to support its industrial partners as they work to win adoption of their products that incorporate Diamonox with end-customers.  Following the successful completion of the Phase IIB work, ADT has focused on expanding opportunities for Diamonox specifically for liquid ozone applications. ADT conducted a market analysis of ozone and concluded that roughly $20M in near-term sales opportunities existed for POU (point of use) ozonated water technologies that currently could not be addressed using conventional UV &amp; corona discharge technologies. ADT is currently in early stage discussions with about five other companies regarding other potential applications of point-of-use ozonated water. ADT is also developing a more generalized product aimed directly at end-customer applications such as commercial pools/spas, cooling towers, food processing, and other applications for which the technology can be retrofitted.  ADT also continues to work with potential customers interested in other applications of Diamonox technology, for oil &amp; gas injected water and wastewater treatment as well as for ballast water treatment. ADT is also currently working with the EPA to explore setting up a field trial of its EAOP technology to remove estrogens and other toxic organic chemicals from municipal drinking water (supported by an EPA Phase II SBIR grant).          Last Modified: 07/11/2015       Submitted by: John A Carlisle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
