<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Bayesian Information Fusion for Robust Classification and Quantification of ill-defined Biosamples with Applications to Studies of Microalgae</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>404559.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404559</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924956</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Professor Frank Vogt of the University of Tennessee Knoxville is supported by the Chemical Measurement and Imaging (CMI) Program in the Division of Chemistry to develop chemometric methods for the qualitative and quantitative analysis of complex chemical and biological samples. The specific objective is to develop "Bayesian Information Fusion," a novel chemometric concept which merges different types of information from complementary sources for sample classification. To further enhance the accuracy of the classification and the quantification, a novel "Plausibility Analysis" software will be developed and incorporated. As a proof-of-principle, these novel chemometric methodologies will be applied to FTIR spectroscopic data obtained from microalgae samples with the goal to utilize them as environmental bioprobes.&lt;br/&gt;The analysis of complex chemical and biological samples is extremely challenging because of the large number of analytes present and their wide range of concentrations, and chemometric data analysis is increasingly becoming an invaluable analytical chemistry tool for improved classification and quantification of such samples.&lt;br/&gt;The project results will be integrated in classroom material  by means of the cyber-enabled and interactive software package "Virtual Chemometrics Laboratory."</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058695</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Vogt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank Vogt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fvogt@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1331 CIR PARK DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7752</Code>
<Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~285669</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~118890</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fundamental challenges in analyzing chemically complex samples like biological materials arise from the sheer number of possible analytes which may prevent calibration models from being comprehensive. Moreover, calibration models deduced from data acquired from biosamples often feature nonlinear relations between a sample&rsquo;s chemical parameters of interest and these data. The <em>overall objective</em> of this project was to develop innovative, <em>robust</em>, and <em>nonlinear</em> data modeling methodologies (chemometrics) that (i) are based on fusing additional information to support chemical analyses and that (ii) can incorporate nonlinearities and thus overcome the limitations conventional chemometrics. It has been <em>hypothesized</em> that incorporating different types of information into novel chemometric calibrations excludes those models which are acceptable based on measured data but are implausible chemically. Moreover, nonlinear models were expected to be more realistic for describing real-world systems namely biological materials. The <em>rationale</em> for expanding conventional, linear chemometric modeling has been to improve the accuracy and precision of chemical analyses. Moreover, these modeling approaches were shown to gain an in-depth understanding of chemical processes defining the measured data. The PI has invited researchers to utilize the resulting cyber-enabled software package &lsquo;<em>Virtual Chemometrics Lab</em>&rsquo; (<em>VCL</em>) and remains interested in new collaborations. As a Broader Impact, a scaled-down version of the VCL has been implemented in the PI&rsquo;s Instrumental Analysis Lab (Chem329) and has enabled his students to design their own analyzer in form of semester projects (see Fig.&nbsp;1).</p> <p>As <em>proof-of-principle application</em>, microalgae have been investigated regarding their chemical adaptation to environmental conditions. Since ubiquitous microalgae sequester large quantities of inorganic compounds out of their environment and transformation them into microalgal biomass, they carry a high environmental relevance. From an analytical chemistry perspective, chemical sensing of microalgal biomass has been envisioned as innovative, embedded environmental monitor. Moreover, knowing microalgae&rsquo;s responses to ambient conditions enables driving microalgal biomass production towards a wanted chemical composition. For experimental studies utilizing FTIR spectroscopy and microscopy, a steady supply of microalgae grown under well-known conditions has been generated by means of a culturing facility developed in the PI&rsquo;s lab (Fig.&nbsp;2).</p> <p>The chemical composition of microalgae cells has been shown to be influenced by the cells&rsquo; environment in a strongly nonlinear way (Fig&nbsp;3 left). Thus, without considering the samples&rsquo; context (environment), incorrect quantitative analyses would result (Fig.&nbsp;3 right). Thus, this project&rsquo;s Intellectual Merit regarding improving quantitation by means of nonlinear chemometrics (&lsquo;Predictor Surface&rsquo;) has been clearly demonstrated. However, for applying said Predictor Surface methodology, the species need to be identified in order to apply the correct Predictor Surface. Different species&rsquo; chemical signature can be very similar. In order to enhance species identification, cells size distributions (Fig.&nbsp;4) have been derived from microscopy data and were combined with IR-spectroscopic measurements. In conclusion, this project&rsquo;s chemometric innovations applied to chemical analyses of and with microalgae have opened new pathways for environmental analytical chemistry and for investigating consequences of chemical shifts for marine ecosystems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Frank&nbsp;Vogt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galConte...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fundamental challenges in analyzing chemically complex samples like biological materials arise from the sheer number of possible analytes which may prevent calibration models from being comprehensive. Moreover, calibration models deduced from data acquired from biosamples often feature nonlinear relations between a sampleÆs chemical parameters of interest and these data. The overall objective of this project was to develop innovative, robust, and nonlinear data modeling methodologies (chemometrics) that (i) are based on fusing additional information to support chemical analyses and that (ii) can incorporate nonlinearities and thus overcome the limitations conventional chemometrics. It has been hypothesized that incorporating different types of information into novel chemometric calibrations excludes those models which are acceptable based on measured data but are implausible chemically. Moreover, nonlinear models were expected to be more realistic for describing real-world systems namely biological materials. The rationale for expanding conventional, linear chemometric modeling has been to improve the accuracy and precision of chemical analyses. Moreover, these modeling approaches were shown to gain an in-depth understanding of chemical processes defining the measured data. The PI has invited researchers to utilize the resulting cyber-enabled software package æVirtual Chemometrics LabÆ (VCL) and remains interested in new collaborations. As a Broader Impact, a scaled-down version of the VCL has been implemented in the PIÆs Instrumental Analysis Lab (Chem329) and has enabled his students to design their own analyzer in form of semester projects (see Fig. 1).  As proof-of-principle application, microalgae have been investigated regarding their chemical adaptation to environmental conditions. Since ubiquitous microalgae sequester large quantities of inorganic compounds out of their environment and transformation them into microalgal biomass, they carry a high environmental relevance. From an analytical chemistry perspective, chemical sensing of microalgal biomass has been envisioned as innovative, embedded environmental monitor. Moreover, knowing microalgaeÆs responses to ambient conditions enables driving microalgal biomass production towards a wanted chemical composition. For experimental studies utilizing FTIR spectroscopy and microscopy, a steady supply of microalgae grown under well-known conditions has been generated by means of a culturing facility developed in the PIÆs lab (Fig. 2).  The chemical composition of microalgae cells has been shown to be influenced by the cellsÆ environment in a strongly nonlinear way (Fig 3 left). Thus, without considering the samplesÆ context (environment), incorrect quantitative analyses would result (Fig. 3 right). Thus, this projectÆs Intellectual Merit regarding improving quantitation by means of nonlinear chemometrics (æPredictor SurfaceÆ) has been clearly demonstrated. However, for applying said Predictor Surface methodology, the species need to be identified in order to apply the correct Predictor Surface. Different speciesÆ chemical signature can be very similar. In order to enhance species identification, cells size distributions (Fig. 4) have been derived from microscopy data and were combined with IR-spectroscopic measurements. In conclusion, this projectÆs chemometric innovations applied to chemical analyses of and with microalgae have opened new pathways for environmental analytical chemistry and for investigating consequences of chemical shifts for marine ecosystems.       Last Modified: 02/16/2016       Submitted by: Frank Vogt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
