<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Experimental and Theoretical Study of Ligand Steric Effects in Homogeneous Catalysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>348000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy Patten</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tpatten@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation supports Professor Kevin Shaughnessy of the University of Alabama, for a combined experimental and theoretical investigation of the ligand structural effects on the performance of Pd catalysts for coupling reactions.  The goal of this work is to understand the balance of steric and electronic properties of the ligands, typically phosphines, that make one catalyst operate at a faster rate or with higher turnover numbers than another. The Pd catalyst systems to be investigated here are popular reagents due to their high functional group compatibility and ease of use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research are centered in the combination of experimental and theoretical approaches to the problem of catalyst structure/reactivity relationships. The systematic approach applied through this collaboration will expose students to both techniques simultaneously, making it an excellent training ground for young scientists. The potential for rational design of new catalyst systems with improved performance is important for conservation of natural resources and the construction of "atom economical" manufacturing processes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058984</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Dixon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Dixon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dadixon@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053488441</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000117633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Shaughnessy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin H Shaughnessy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kshaughn@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053484435</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000403993</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[152 Rose Admin. / Box 870104]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045632635</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>808245794</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama Tuscaloosa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 University Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~232000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~116000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objectives of this proposal were to use theoretical and experimental studies to explore the effects of ligand properties on late-transition metal-catalyzed bond-forming reactions. These reactions play critical roles in all phases of modern organic chemistry from fundamental academic research; to research and development of new pharmaceuticals, agricultural chemicals, and electronic materials; and ultimately the manufacture of these materials.&nbsp; Theoretical approaches were applied to understanding the structure and electronic properties of metal-ligand complexes. These results were correlated with catalyst performance in an effort to understand how structure affects performance. Of particularly interest, were conformationally flexible ligand substituents that were found to have subtle but important impacts on catalyst performance.&nbsp; This research has resulted in a number of novel observations that have provided new ways to control the coupling of organic fragments.&nbsp; These methodologies are of interest in the synthesis of new pharmaceuticals and agricultural chemicals.&nbsp; Industrial researchers are currently evaluating the methods developed under this proposal for commercial applications.</p> <p>This grant has had a significant impact on the education of post-doctoral, graduate, and undergraduate students. A total of two post-doctoral associates, five graduate students, thirty undergraduate researchers and one high school student participated in research on this project. Of these students, 50% were female and 10% were underrepresented racial minorities . Each of the papers published to date on this work have included graduate and undergraduate co-authors with nine undergraduate co-authors to date. All students participating in this project have presented their research at professional meetings.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2015<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Shaughnessy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objectives of this proposal were to use theoretical and experimental studies to explore the effects of ligand properties on late-transition metal-catalyzed bond-forming reactions. These reactions play critical roles in all phases of modern organic chemistry from fundamental academic research; to research and development of new pharmaceuticals, agricultural chemicals, and electronic materials; and ultimately the manufacture of these materials.  Theoretical approaches were applied to understanding the structure and electronic properties of metal-ligand complexes. These results were correlated with catalyst performance in an effort to understand how structure affects performance. Of particularly interest, were conformationally flexible ligand substituents that were found to have subtle but important impacts on catalyst performance.  This research has resulted in a number of novel observations that have provided new ways to control the coupling of organic fragments.  These methodologies are of interest in the synthesis of new pharmaceuticals and agricultural chemicals.  Industrial researchers are currently evaluating the methods developed under this proposal for commercial applications.  This grant has had a significant impact on the education of post-doctoral, graduate, and undergraduate students. A total of two post-doctoral associates, five graduate students, thirty undergraduate researchers and one high school student participated in research on this project. Of these students, 50% were female and 10% were underrepresented racial minorities . Each of the papers published to date on this work have included graduate and undergraduate co-authors with nine undergraduate co-authors to date. All students participating in this project have presented their research at professional meetings.           Last Modified: 12/22/2015       Submitted by: Kevin H Shaughnessy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
