<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chemical Triggers for Spin-State Switching: Fundamental Studies Toward Anion Receptors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>383000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>383000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanism Program of the Chemistry Division, Matthew Shores of Colorado State University will combine synthetic and measurement techniques to control electron spin in molecular species via non-covalent interactions. Fe(II) coordination complexes will be probed by solution methods to understand - at the microscopic level - how their spin states are influenced by outer sphere interactions with anions. These insights will inform the exploration of metal-ligand architectures where, in polar solvents, a change in complex spin state robustly signals the presence of an anionic species. Among the broader impacts of the research, diverse training in synthesis, spectroscopy, X-ray crystallography, and magnetometry will be offered; a new class of colorimetric sensors for anions of biological and/or environmental significance will be developed; and research opportunities for undergraduate students will be enhanced by close association with and support of the CSU chemistry REU program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project intends to expand the methods by which colorless anions can be detected, by taking advantage of the propensity of certain metal complexes to switch their color and  magnetic and physical properties as a result of small environmental changes. Sensing of anions under controlled, anaerobic conditions has been developed. This research aims to achieve robust sensing in water, a key goal in this field. A direct result of the research and educational activities will be manifested in the quality of training that graduate and undergraduate students obtain in the synthesis and characterization of compounds. More generally, the research will aid in developing fundamental understandings of molecular switching, and will contribute to improved imaging, data storage, and display devices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058889</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Shores</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Shores</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matthew.shores@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704917235</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000386527</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S Howes St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~383000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanism Program of the Chemistry Division, Matthew Shores&rsquo; chemistry research group at Colorado State University combined chemical synthesis and measurement techniques to probe and manipulate magnetic property switching as a function of charged (anionic) guest inclusion. Molecular-scale switches could have diverse applications in memory, display and sensor devices. A key challenge to overcome is to understand and manage the small energies associated with the switching event.</p> <p>The original target in this project was the control of spin-state switching in solution, toward the development of colorimetric sensors for anions. Anions are often colorless, whereas spin-crossover compounds have very different colors depending on whether they are found in the high- or low-spin state. Creating spin-crossover-capable compounds with anion-binding groups could lead to a new class of chemosensors, and would provide a synthetically-tunable platform for understanding the pathway(s) by which host-guest interaction information is transmitted to the spin-crossover center.</p> <p>The Shores group&rsquo;s efforts in completing the original objective resulted in the syntheses and characterizations of several families of iron and cobalt coordination complex salts, each featuring novel magnetic property responses to anion identity. To promote complex stability in polar solvents, a chelating ligand was used to encapsulate the metal ion and shield it from direct interactions with solvent and/or anions. Anion binding groups were placed at several locations on the periphery of the ligand so as to systematically influence steric and electronic effects. The electronic properties of the ligand were tuned further by changing the relative oxidation states of the donor atoms. Such ligand tunability required the development of new chemical synthesis methods.</p> <p>Iron complexes prepared from the ligand family described above showed a variety of anion-dependent magnetism behaviors, which were correlated to structural changes in the ligands. Most relevant to the original objective, an iron(II) complex was discovered in which binding of chloride anions in polar (acetonitrile) solution at ambient temperatures causes the equilibrium of high- and low-spin states to shift toward the high-spin state. This represents the first observation of &ldquo;turn-on&rdquo; sensing via spin-state switching. This proof-of-principle result requires further elaboration; notwithstanding, switching from diamagnetic to paramagnetic states could find use in areas as diverse as chemical separations of gases and magnetic resonance contrast agents.</p> <p>Cobalt analogues of the iron complexes were expected to show spin-crossover properties, however all species isolated were high spin. Nevertheless, a family of these compounds showed anion-selective &ldquo;turn-on&rdquo; of magnetic response to switching (ac) magnetic fields. The slow relaxation of magnetization observed is a hallmark of single-molecule magnetism. Although this is (currently) a low-temperature phenomenon, and thus not immediately practical for chemical sensing, being able to control this phenomenon with host-guest chemistry adds to the list of external controls for magnetic property management at the molecular level.</p> <p>As part of this project, 4 graduate students, 1 postdoc and 4 undergraduate students were trained in air- and moisture-sensitive inorganic synthesis techniques, X-ray crystallography, spectroscopic characterization methods, and magnetometry. The PI and research group also contributed to the mentoring and professional development activities of the long-running CSU Chemistry REU program. The results from this project were disseminated in several papers (with several manuscripts in preparation) and through student and PI presentations at multiple seminars, including two international conferences. Three PhD dissertations and one BS senior thesis are linked to the project. An ongoing theory-experiment collaboration with computational chemistry Prof. Tony Rapp&eacute; (CSU) was strengthened: development of accurate computations and deeper theoretical understanding will benefit from the ability to simultaneously control structure and magnetism at a more granular level. &nbsp;</p> <p>As part of the broadening and outreach activities associated with this project, five collaborations with research groups across the country (Boston University, Purdue, CU Boulder, UC Irvine and Oregon) were established. Magnetic measurements performed by the Shores group contributed to the understanding of electronic structure in a wide range of inorganic and molecular materials provided by the collaborators. In turn, the researchers in the Shores group gained valuable experience with a diverse set of materials, and were exposed to &ndash; and contributed to &ndash; new examples of redox non-innocence, spin crossover, single-molecule magnetism, and single-chain magnetism.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/06/2016<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;Shores</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanism Program of the Chemistry Division, Matthew Shores? chemistry research group at Colorado State University combined chemical synthesis and measurement techniques to probe and manipulate magnetic property switching as a function of charged (anionic) guest inclusion. Molecular-scale switches could have diverse applications in memory, display and sensor devices. A key challenge to overcome is to understand and manage the small energies associated with the switching event.  The original target in this project was the control of spin-state switching in solution, toward the development of colorimetric sensors for anions. Anions are often colorless, whereas spin-crossover compounds have very different colors depending on whether they are found in the high- or low-spin state. Creating spin-crossover-capable compounds with anion-binding groups could lead to a new class of chemosensors, and would provide a synthetically-tunable platform for understanding the pathway(s) by which host-guest interaction information is transmitted to the spin-crossover center.  The Shores group?s efforts in completing the original objective resulted in the syntheses and characterizations of several families of iron and cobalt coordination complex salts, each featuring novel magnetic property responses to anion identity. To promote complex stability in polar solvents, a chelating ligand was used to encapsulate the metal ion and shield it from direct interactions with solvent and/or anions. Anion binding groups were placed at several locations on the periphery of the ligand so as to systematically influence steric and electronic effects. The electronic properties of the ligand were tuned further by changing the relative oxidation states of the donor atoms. Such ligand tunability required the development of new chemical synthesis methods.  Iron complexes prepared from the ligand family described above showed a variety of anion-dependent magnetism behaviors, which were correlated to structural changes in the ligands. Most relevant to the original objective, an iron(II) complex was discovered in which binding of chloride anions in polar (acetonitrile) solution at ambient temperatures causes the equilibrium of high- and low-spin states to shift toward the high-spin state. This represents the first observation of "turn-on" sensing via spin-state switching. This proof-of-principle result requires further elaboration; notwithstanding, switching from diamagnetic to paramagnetic states could find use in areas as diverse as chemical separations of gases and magnetic resonance contrast agents.  Cobalt analogues of the iron complexes were expected to show spin-crossover properties, however all species isolated were high spin. Nevertheless, a family of these compounds showed anion-selective "turn-on" of magnetic response to switching (ac) magnetic fields. The slow relaxation of magnetization observed is a hallmark of single-molecule magnetism. Although this is (currently) a low-temperature phenomenon, and thus not immediately practical for chemical sensing, being able to control this phenomenon with host-guest chemistry adds to the list of external controls for magnetic property management at the molecular level.  As part of this project, 4 graduate students, 1 postdoc and 4 undergraduate students were trained in air- and moisture-sensitive inorganic synthesis techniques, X-ray crystallography, spectroscopic characterization methods, and magnetometry. The PI and research group also contributed to the mentoring and professional development activities of the long-running CSU Chemistry REU program. The results from this project were disseminated in several papers (with several manuscripts in preparation) and through student and PI presentations at multiple seminars, including two international conferences. Three PhD dissertations and one BS senior thesis are linked to the project. An ongoing theory-experiment collaboration with computational chemistry Prof. Tony Rapp&eacute; (CSU) was strengthened: development of accurate computations and deeper theoretical understanding will benefit from the ability to simultaneously control structure and magnetism at a more granular level.    As part of the broadening and outreach activities associated with this project, five collaborations with research groups across the country (Boston University, Purdue, CU Boulder, UC Irvine and Oregon) were established. Magnetic measurements performed by the Shores group contributed to the understanding of electronic structure in a wide range of inorganic and molecular materials provided by the collaborators. In turn, the researchers in the Shores group gained valuable experience with a diverse set of materials, and were exposed to &ndash; and contributed to &ndash; new examples of redox non-innocence, spin crossover, single-molecule magnetism, and single-chain magnetism.       Last Modified: 10/06/2016       Submitted by: Matthew Shores]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
