<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Technocratic Expertise and the Government of Catastrophic Risk in the United States, 1950 - 2010</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>129436.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129436</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technocratic Expertise and the Government of Catastrophic Risk in the United States, 1950 ? 2010&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stephen J. Collier (The New School) and Andrew Lakoff (University of Southern California)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the last two decades a series of events in the United States has focused public attention on the government?s role in anticipating and managing catastrophic events. In the wake of terrorist attacks, major natural disasters, pandemic influenza, and financial crises, planners and policy-makers have been criticized for their failure to prepare adequately for potential catastrophes. The problem of catastrophic risk has become a critical arena in which government is expected to manage risks to collective wellbeing.  This project approaches the government of catastrophic risk from the vantage of science and technology studies: it asks how the category of catastrophic risk is constituted as an object of knowledge and intervention at the interface of potentially disruptive events, on the one hand, and the agencies and experts charged with managing them, on the other. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project investigates the historical emergence of distinctive ?styles of reasoning? about catastrophic risk, and associated knowledge practices such as catastrophe modeling, vulnerability assessment, and simulation exercises. Many of these practices were initially developed in the context of the Cold War military confrontation, and then migrated to other areas, including natural disaster response, public health, and terrorism preparedness. The project traces critical moments when experts developed tools to manage events whose catastrophic potential outstripped the capacities of government agencies charged with protecting wellbeing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Findings from the investigation will be significant for several areas of scholarship and policy. These findings indicate that contemporary controversies over risk governance can be understood in terms of conflicting styles of reasoning that cannot be adjudicated by reference to common standards for validating truths. For policy-makers and risk analysts, the project?s findings will be of interest in that they shed new light on the sources of conflict among experts and officials over how to understand and mitigate the risk of potentially catastrophic events.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058882</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Collier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen J Collier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stephenjcollier@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9176930911</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000056211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The New School</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100118603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2122295600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>66 W 12TH ST RM 800</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071030969</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW SCHOOL, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071030969</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The New School]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100118603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[66 W 12TH ST RM 800]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8815</Code>
<Text>Studies of Policy Sci Eng Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~108686</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~20750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml> <w:WordDocument> <w:View>Normal</w:View> <w:Zoom>0</w:Zoom> <w:TrackMoves /> <w:TrackFormatting /> <w:PunctuationKerning /> <w:ValidateAgainstSchemas /> <w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid> <w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent> <w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText> <w:DoNotPromoteQF /> <w:LidThemeOther>EN-US</w:LidThemeOther> <w:LidThemeAsian>X-NONE</w:LidThemeAsian> <w:LidThemeComplexScript>X-NONE</w:LidThemeComplexScript> <w:Compatibility> <w:BreakWrappedTables /> <w:SnapToGridInCell /> <w:WrapTextWithPunct /> <w:UseAsianBreakRules /> <w:DontGrowAutofit /> <w:SplitPgBreakAndParaMark /> <w:DontVertAlignCellWithSp /> <w:DontBreakConstrainedForcedTables /> <w:DontVertAlignInTxbx /> <w:Word11KerningPairs /> <w:CachedColBalance /> </w:Compatibility> <w:BrowserLevel>MicrosoftInternetExplorer4</w:BrowserLevel> <m:mathPr> <m:mathFont m:val="Cambria Math" /> <m:brkBin m:val="before" /> <m:brkBinSub m:val=" " /> <m:smallFrac m:val="off" /> <m:dispDef /> <m:lMargin m:val="0" /> <m:rMargin m:val="0" /> <m:defJc m:val="centerGroup" /> <m:wrapIndent m:val="1440" /> <m:intLim m:val="subSup" /> <m:naryLim m:val="undOvr" /> </m:mathPr></w:WordDocument> </xml><![endif]--></p> <p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml> <w:LatentStyles DefLockedState="false" DefUnhideWhenUsed="true"   DefSemiHidden="true" DefQFormat="false" DefPriority="99"   LatentStyleCount="267"> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Normal" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="heading 1" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 2" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 3" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 4" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 5" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 6" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 7" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 8" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 9" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 1" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 2" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 3" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 4" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 5" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 6" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 7" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 8" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 9" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" Name="annotation text" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="35" QFormat="true" Name="caption" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" Name="annotation reference" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="10" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Title" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" Name="Default Paragraph Font" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="11" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtitle" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="22" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Strong" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="20" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Emphasis" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="59" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Table Grid" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Placeholder Text" /> <w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" SemiHidden="false"    UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat=...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Normal 0     false false false  EN-US X-NONE X-NONE              MicrosoftInternetExplorer4                                                                                                                                                                 In the last two decades a series of events in the United States has focused public attention on the governmentÆs role in anticipating and managing emergencies. In the wake of terrorist attacks, major natural disasters, pandemic influenza, and financial crises, planners and policy-makers have been criticized for their failure to prepare adequately for potential catastrophes. They face intense pressure to improve preparedness, to reduce vulnerabilities, and to increase response capacity. The problem of emergency has thus become a critical arena in which government is expected to manage risks to collective wellbeing. Our project on "Technocratic Expertise and the Politics of Emergency" examined how expert communities have shaped understandings of emergencies, and the political contexts in which they have worked.  NSF funds were used to support a number of activities that were critical to this project, including:     Archival research in the National Archives and Records Administration Archival research at the Air Force Historical Research Agency  Collaborative work among the co-PIs and with MA and PhD students at Columbia University, The New School, and the University of Southern California Organization of a collaborative issue of a scholarly magazine on "systemic risk" Research in secondary sources on specific topics that were relevant to the project, including New Deal economics, strategic bombing theory, and Cold War non-military preparedness      This research traced current institutions for governing emergencies in the United States to the Cold War. Over the course of the decades following World War II, experts in think tanks and government agencies shaped the knowledge practices and institutional mechanisms of a "political technology of emergency." We examined how these tools were then extended to non-military emergencies such as natural disasters in the 1960s and the 1970s and, more recently, to the development of "critical infrastructure protection" in response to the threat of terrorism or technological accidents, and the rise of "public health preparedness" as a response to the specter of catastrophic infectious disease.  The project has resulted in a number of publications that are either in preparation, in production, or already published. Among these are:     The Government of Emergency (with co-PI Andrew Lakoff) &ndash; a major academic press publication, currently in preparation. "Neoliberalism and Natural Disaster" &ndash; an article submitted for review at the Journal of Cultural Economy. "Vital Systems Security" (with co-PI Andrew Lakoff) &ndash; an article accepted for publication in Theory, Culture, and Society "Limn 1: Systemic Risk," an issue of the scholarly magazine Limn devoted to "systemic risk" &ndash; a concept that has recently become central to many domains of emergency management, including finance and Critical Infrastructure Protection (http://limn.it/issue/01/). The co-PIs contributed an article titled "System Vulnerability and the Problem of National Survival."  Results from the project have also been presented at at numerous universities in the United States and in other countries, including the University of California, San Diego; The New School; Durham University (U.K.); the University of Helsinki; the Goethe University of Frankfurt; and the University of Hamburg.    TNSCollier13       Last Modified: 06/04/2013       Submitted by: Stephen J Collier]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
