<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pyridine-bis(oxazoline) derivatives for enhanced Ln(III) emission in aqueous systems and in the solid state</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>384000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>391766</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ricjohns@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Synthesis Program is funding Professor Ana de Bettencourt-Dias at the University of Nevada-Reno to synthesize and study the photophysics of new derivatized pyridine-bis(oxazoline) (Pybox) lanthanide complexes.  While Pybox ligands have been extensively used in transition-metal catalyzed organic synthesis, it was only recently that their ability to efficiently sensitize lanthanide ion luminescence was reported.  In particular, the project seeks to establish a structure-function relationship of Pybox ligands with respect to sensitization of lanthanide ion luminescence.  Moreover, water-soluble complexes are being targeted for use in bioluminescence, as are complexes that can be incorporated into polymers,  for solid state lighting applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As noted above, this project has potential long-term scientific broader impacts in the areas of bioimaging and solid state materials. Moreover, research in lanthanide ion chemistry is potentially connected with the chemistry of actinides, as lanthanide complexes are sometimes used as surrogates to mimic the chemistry of the radioactive actinides.  Educational broader impacts include the training of undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral co-workers in a multidisciplinary environment, including elements of synthetic organometallic chemistry and ofabsorption, excitation and emission spectroscopy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058805</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ana</FirstName>
<LastName>de Bettencourt-Dias</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ana de Bettencourt-Dias</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abd@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7753272363</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488789</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects / MS 325]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>146515460</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1664 North Virginia Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6878</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1948</Code>
<Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~148000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~236000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~7766</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Lanthanides are capable of light emission, which is sensitized through appended ligands. During the course of this project we synthesized and characterized new water-soluble complexes of lanthanides with ligands capable of sensitizing this luminescence. The resulting complexes display emission in water and in one case, the complex transfect the cell membrane of specific cancer cells and allows for fluorescence imaging of these cells, while displaying moderate cytotoxicity towards these same cancer cells, but no cytotoxicity towards healthy cells.</p> <p>We also isolated ligands capable of capping nanoparticles of ZnS, and preliminary results, indicate that lanthanides can bind to these capping ligands and energy transfer occurs from the nanoparticles to the lanthanides, followed by lanthanide-centered light emission.</p> <p>Finally, we isolated several ligands capable of binding lanthanide ions and of being polymerized. The resulting polymers, while insoluble, display the characteristic lanthanide-centered emission (see attached figures); in fact, with judicious choice of amount and nature of the lanthanide ions incorporated into the polymers, materials with variable and controllable emission color were obtained.</p> <p>During the course of the project several students at the undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral level were trained in the synthesis and spectroscopic characterization techniques pertinent to this research in lanthanide chemistry. They attended conferences were they presented their research results and were involved in writing the manuscripts for publication of these research results.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/26/2015<br>      Modified by: Ana&nbsp;De Bettencourt-Dias</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1058805/1058805_10134285_1432241775144_PolymerPowderAdBD_May2015--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1058805/1058805_10134285_1432241775144_PolymerPowderAdBD_May2015--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poly(styrene)Eu"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1058805/1058805_10134285_1432241775144_PolymerPowderAdBD_May2015--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poly(styrene)Eu"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Poly(styrene)-based polymers with different proportions of metal ion, displaying red europium emission</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Jeffrey S.K. Rossini</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ana&nbsp;De Bettencourt-Dias</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poly(styrene)Eu</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1058805/1058805_10134285_1432568185753_RedGreenEmission--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1058805/1058805_10134285_1432568185753_RedGreenEmission--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poly(norbornene) Eu and Tb"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1058805/1058805_10134285_1432568185753_RedGreenEmission--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poly(norbornene) Eu and Tb"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Red (left) and green (right) emission from poly(norbornene) doped withe Eu (left) and Tb (right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Jeffrey S.K. Rossini</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ana&nbsp;De Bettencourt-Dias</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poly(norbornene) ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Lanthanides are capable of light emission, which is sensitized through appended ligands. During the course of this project we synthesized and characterized new water-soluble complexes of lanthanides with ligands capable of sensitizing this luminescence. The resulting complexes display emission in water and in one case, the complex transfect the cell membrane of specific cancer cells and allows for fluorescence imaging of these cells, while displaying moderate cytotoxicity towards these same cancer cells, but no cytotoxicity towards healthy cells.  We also isolated ligands capable of capping nanoparticles of ZnS, and preliminary results, indicate that lanthanides can bind to these capping ligands and energy transfer occurs from the nanoparticles to the lanthanides, followed by lanthanide-centered light emission.  Finally, we isolated several ligands capable of binding lanthanide ions and of being polymerized. The resulting polymers, while insoluble, display the characteristic lanthanide-centered emission (see attached figures); in fact, with judicious choice of amount and nature of the lanthanide ions incorporated into the polymers, materials with variable and controllable emission color were obtained.  During the course of the project several students at the undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral level were trained in the synthesis and spectroscopic characterization techniques pertinent to this research in lanthanide chemistry. They attended conferences were they presented their research results and were involved in writing the manuscripts for publication of these research results.           Last Modified: 05/26/2015       Submitted by: Ana De Bettencourt-Dias]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
