<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: RAPID: Taxonomic and metagenetic analysis of species distributions for marine meiofauna from the Gulf of Mexico</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38784.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38784</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Lydeard</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Oceanic sediments harbor most of the world's biodiversity, primarily comprised of minute organisms that perform key ecological functions such as nutrient cycling, critical to the biodegradation of hydrocarbons. Unfortunately, knowledge of these communities of organisms in the Gulf of Mexico is sparse, thus precluding informed mitigation and remediation of the BP Deepwater Horizon oil spill. Knowledge-based action requires that three key questions be addressed: 1) How unique are the sediment communities in the Gulf? 2) How structured are the sediment communities within the Gulf? and 3) What has been the effect of anthropogenic disturbance on these communities? Cutting-edge, high-throughput DNA sequencing technologies will be employed, together with traditional taxonomic methods to assay the diversity of virtually all complex organisms from sediment samples collected prior to the April 2010 spill, representing diverse habitats across the Gulf of Mexico. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BP Deepwater Horizon oil spill represents a dramatic anthropogenic event of historic proportions. It will both require and inspire the interest of future biologists for decades. This funding will specifically provide new opportunities for student engagement in the long-term characterization of biodiversity, using new tools to understand the response of organisms to environmental change and the consequences, mitigation and remediation of such an environmental disturbance. Training will include support for undergraduate students to attend a workshop in Gulf of Mexico biodiversity assessment as well as graduate and postdoctoral training. In all cases participation by underrepresented groups in science will be actively encouraged. Most importantly, all data collected will be made openly accessible to the public and scientific communities to facilitate ongoing research and maximize the engagement of all stakeholders.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1058489</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Halanych</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth M Halanych</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ken@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348443222</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000232375</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Auburn University</Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<ZipCode>368320001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>VPRED, Research &amp; Innovation Ctr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[540 Devall Drive, Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066470972</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AUBURN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066470972</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Auburn University]]></Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>368320001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[VPRED, Research &amp; Innovation]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7978</Code>
<Text>Global Systems Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY SURVEYS &amp; INVENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5987</Code>
<Text>GULF OF MEXICO OIL SPILL-2010</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~38784</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Scientific Merit:&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>This proposal funded assessment of meiofaunal diversity in the Gulf of Mexico (GOM) in the wake of the BP Deepwater Horizon oil spill. Meiofaunal communities comprise the vast majority of the eukaryotic biodiversity in benthic marine habitats and perform key ecosystem functions such as nutrient cycling and sediment stability. Knowledge of biogeographic patterns or community structure in the GOM, was lacking prior to this study. Key questions were: 1) How unique are the meiofaunal communities in the GOM? 2) How structured are meiofaunal communities within the GOM? Addressing these two fundamental questions will allow us to better evaluate the effect of the anthropogenic disturbance on the benthic meiofaunal communities. To address these questions, we applied metagenetic and traditional taxonomic methods of analysis that assay diversity of virtually all eukaryotic organisms from critical samples collected prior to the spill and selected from diverse habitats in the GOM.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>This project focused on a meta-genomic analysis on the meiofauna that may have been impacted by the BP oil spill. This grant was augmented by similar work that was funded (several months after the RAPID) by the Marine Environmental Research Consortium in Alabama. Thus we have built a much bigger collection of samples than originally expected. Field collection activities (including an occasional undergraduate participation) was a considerable activity during the award.We have been working through these samples to extract DNA (mostly) and some RNA. We have received data for several samples and have many more that are still in the pipeline (either awaiting Illumina Sequencing or about to undergo PCR for metagenomics). The initial results of this project are in the from of a submitted manuscript (accepted pending revision at the time of this writing) that was first authored by Holly Bik at University of New Hampshire. These results reveal a dramatic shift in the meiofauna community between May 2010 (before the spill hit the Alabama shoreline) and Sept 2010. Samples for this work were from near shore subtidal areas on the Alabama coast. The shift was from an expected/typical invertebrate meiofaunal compliment to a community very poor in invertebrates and dominated by fungal species. Some of the fungal representatives recovered were genetical very identical with species known to be associated with hydrocarbon release.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Broader Impacts:&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Together with our collaborators a meiofaunal workshop was held at Auburn University in March 31 until April 3rd. This workshop introduced students to both genomic and morphological aspects of meiofauna and the potential impacts of the oil spill. The work shop was attended by 11 students (including a balance of females and males, and underrepresented groups - 3 latinos). The workshop was an intensive 2.5 day effort and the assessment of student responses indicated several of our goals were successfully met. Additionally, Halanych has been very active in a number of presentations in the Alabama region. This work has been presented in at several formal or informal talks. These have ranged from K-12, to lay public (eg Audubon Society in Columbus Georgia) to more scientifically oriented communities. Finally, the focus of this proposal was the immediate assessment of meiofaunal community structure in the GOM; however, the samples were collected to support future research, specifically critical voucher samples will be collected to allow linking of taxonomies to the metagenetic assessment, and we collected total DNA and RNA in parallel to allow metagenomic and metatranscriptomic analysis of ecosystem function, including the associated microbial fauna.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Scientific Merit:      This proposal funded assessment of meiofaunal diversity in the Gulf of Mexico (GOM) in the wake of the BP Deepwater Horizon oil spill. Meiofaunal communities comprise the vast majority of the eukaryotic biodiversity in benthic marine habitats and perform key ecosystem functions such as nutrient cycling and sediment stability. Knowledge of biogeographic patterns or community structure in the GOM, was lacking prior to this study. Key questions were: 1) How unique are the meiofaunal communities in the GOM? 2) How structured are meiofaunal communities within the GOM? Addressing these two fundamental questions will allow us to better evaluate the effect of the anthropogenic disturbance on the benthic meiofaunal communities. To address these questions, we applied metagenetic and traditional taxonomic methods of analysis that assay diversity of virtually all eukaryotic organisms from critical samples collected prior to the spill and selected from diverse habitats in the GOM.      This project focused on a meta-genomic analysis on the meiofauna that may have been impacted by the BP oil spill. This grant was augmented by similar work that was funded (several months after the RAPID) by the Marine Environmental Research Consortium in Alabama. Thus we have built a much bigger collection of samples than originally expected. Field collection activities (including an occasional undergraduate participation) was a considerable activity during the award.We have been working through these samples to extract DNA (mostly) and some RNA. We have received data for several samples and have many more that are still in the pipeline (either awaiting Illumina Sequencing or about to undergo PCR for metagenomics). The initial results of this project are in the from of a submitted manuscript (accepted pending revision at the time of this writing) that was first authored by Holly Bik at University of New Hampshire. These results reveal a dramatic shift in the meiofauna community between May 2010 (before the spill hit the Alabama shoreline) and Sept 2010. Samples for this work were from near shore subtidal areas on the Alabama coast. The shift was from an expected/typical invertebrate meiofaunal compliment to a community very poor in invertebrates and dominated by fungal species. Some of the fungal representatives recovered were genetical very identical with species known to be associated with hydrocarbon release.     Broader Impacts:   Together with our collaborators a meiofaunal workshop was held at Auburn University in March 31 until April 3rd. This workshop introduced students to both genomic and morphological aspects of meiofauna and the potential impacts of the oil spill. The work shop was attended by 11 students (including a balance of females and males, and underrepresented groups - 3 latinos). The workshop was an intensive 2.5 day effort and the assessment of student responses indicated several of our goals were successfully met. Additionally, Halanych has been very active in a number of presentations in the Alabama region. This work has been presented in at several formal or informal talks. These have ranged from K-12, to lay public (eg Audubon Society in Columbus Georgia) to more scientifically oriented communities. Finally, the focus of this proposal was the immediate assessment of meiofaunal community structure in the GOM; however, the samples were collected to support future research, specifically critical voucher samples will be collected to allow linking of taxonomies to the metagenetic assessment, and we collected total DNA and RNA in parallel to allow metagenomic and metatranscriptomic analysis of ecosystem function, including the associated microbial fauna.          Last Modified: 12/27/2011       Submitted by: Kenneth M Halanych]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
