<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>II-New:  A Compute and Storage Cluster for Multidisciplinary Research on Computer Systems and Scientific Simulations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399647.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399647</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Almadena Chtchelkanova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>achtchel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927498</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is carried out by a team of scientific computing researchers, computer systems researchers, and computer science educators.  A cutting-edge compute and storage cluster is built to enable multidisciplinary research on computer systems and scientific simulations. This cluster consists of a stable compute partition with GPGPU processors for scientific computing and an experimental storage partition for computer systems research. Leading groups at Auburn University in the areas of computational atomic physics, climate and ecosystem modeling, and computer science plan to use this computing infrastructure in their research. &lt;br/&gt;This research infrastructure strengthens computer science research on parallel programming models, parallel I/O, file systems, storage, and data-intensive analytics.  In addition, it cultivates new multidisciplinary research projects on computational climate modeling, computational atomic physics, and applied computer science.  Furthermore, it allows better pedagogical methods and education activities to attract more students, particularly from underrepresented groups, for computing careers.  The project's research is expected to result in optimized scientific codes, fine-grained ecosystem simulations, and accurate environmental change predictions.  Research results will be published in computational and computer science journals and international conferences. Open source software packages from this project will be released for community services.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1059376</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Pindzola</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael S Pindzola</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pindzola@physics.auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348444127</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000346271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hanqin</FirstName>
<LastName>Tian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hanqin Tian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tianhan@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348441059</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000119910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Seals</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheryl D Seals</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sealscd@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348446319</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000360696</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weikuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Yu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weikuan Yu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yuw@cs.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506445442</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492930</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Auburn University</Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<ZipCode>368320001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>VPRED, Research &amp; Innovation Ctr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[540 Devall Drive, Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066470972</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AUBURN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066470972</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Auburn University]]></Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>368320001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[VPRED, Research &amp; Innovation]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~399647</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Report of Outcomes for CNS-1059376</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the past four years of this project, our team has planned, acquired and deployed a cutting-edge compute and storage cluster to enable multidisciplinary research on computer systems and scientific simulations. This cluster consists of a stable compute partition with GPGPU processors for scientific computing and an experimental storage partition for computer systems research. Its intellectual merits are listed below.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <ol> <li>[<strong>A 52-node GPU+CPU Cluster] </strong>Enabled by the project, a 52-node heterogeneous cluster has been deployed at Auburn University since 2011. It has a peak computing power of 35 TeraFlops. The cluster has been used to enable many computing research and interdisciplinary collaborative research activities.</li> <li>&nbsp;[<strong>Research Publications] </strong>Enabled by the CRI cluster, the team has published more than 30 research papers to major HPC conferences ICS'15, Sigmetrics'14, IPDPS'14, IPDPS'15, DATE'15, Cluster'15, Mascots'15, PACT&rsquo;13, IPDPS&rsquo;13, SC&rsquo;13, CCGrid&rsquo;13, Cluster&rsquo;13, USENIX ICAC&rsquo;13, MASCOTS&rsquo;12, IPDPS&rsquo;12, HPDC&rsquo;12, SC&rsquo;12, SC&rsquo;11, ICPP&rsquo;11, CCGrid&rsquo;11, and Cluster&rsquo;11, as well as major journals such as IEEE Transactions on Computers, IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems, Journal of Computers and Electrical Engineering, International Journal of Parallel Programming, and Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing.</li> <li>&nbsp;[<strong>George Michael Fellowship]: </strong>Ph.D. Advisee Xinyu Que was selected as one of the two awardees for 2011 George Michael Fellowship. Xinyu Que received travel support to attend both SC11 and SC12 conferences, besides a $5000 monetary award through this fellowship. His research on scalable run-time system techniques was enabled by the CRI cluster.</li> <li>[<strong>First Place in 2012 ACM SRC Grand Finals]: </strong>Partly enabled by the CRI cluster, Ph.D. student Yuan Tian is selected as the First Prize Winner of the ACM Student Research Competition Grand Finals, for her research on system-aware I/O organization for scientific analytics. Both Yuan and Dr. Yu were invited to the 2012 ACM Award Ceremony at San Francisco in June 2012.</li> <li>[<strong>2<sup>nd</sup> Place Graduate Research Award at College of Engineering]: </strong>Enabled by the CRI cluster, Xinyu Que&rsquo;s research on scalable programming models for computation and big data analytics has been selected by Samuel Ginn College of Engineering as the 2<sup>nd</sup> place winner in the 2012 Graduate Research Competition. </li> <li>[<strong>College of Engineering Outstanding International Student]: </strong>For his research enabled by the CRI cluster, Yandong Wang has won the recognition as a 2013 outstanding international student recognition by the College of Engineering, Auburn University. </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, this research infrastructure has broader impact in a number of aspects.&nbsp; It strengthens computer science research on parallel programming models, parallel I/O, file systems, storage, and data-intensive analytics.&nbsp; In addition, it cultivates new multidisciplinary research projects on computational climate modeling, computational atomic physics, and applied computer science. Open source software packages from this project are released for community services. These broader impacts are listed in more detail as follows.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <ol> <li>[<strong>Graduated Ph.D. and Master students] </strong>Enabled by the CRI cluster, Yuan Tian, Xinyu Que, Yandong Wang, Zhuo Liu, and Cong Xu have finished their doctoral thesis dissertation and joined prestigious organizations such as Oak Ridge National Lab, IBM T.J. Watson, Yahoo and Intel. Patrick Carpenter and Xiaobing Li have finished their mas...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Report of Outcomes for CNS-1059376     During the past four years of this project, our team has planned, acquired and deployed a cutting-edge compute and storage cluster to enable multidisciplinary research on computer systems and scientific simulations. This cluster consists of a stable compute partition with GPGPU processors for scientific computing and an experimental storage partition for computer systems research. Its intellectual merits are listed below.  Intellectual Merit:  [A 52-node GPU+CPU Cluster] Enabled by the project, a 52-node heterogeneous cluster has been deployed at Auburn University since 2011. It has a peak computing power of 35 TeraFlops. The cluster has been used to enable many computing research and interdisciplinary collaborative research activities.  [Research Publications] Enabled by the CRI cluster, the team has published more than 30 research papers to major HPC conferences ICS'15, Sigmetrics'14, IPDPS'14, IPDPS'15, DATE'15, Cluster'15, Mascots'15, PACTÆ13, IPDPSÆ13, SCÆ13, CCGridÆ13, ClusterÆ13, USENIX ICACÆ13, MASCOTSÆ12, IPDPSÆ12, HPDCÆ12, SCÆ12, SCÆ11, ICPPÆ11, CCGridÆ11, and ClusterÆ11, as well as major journals such as IEEE Transactions on Computers, IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems, Journal of Computers and Electrical Engineering, International Journal of Parallel Programming, and Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing.  [George Michael Fellowship]: Ph.D. Advisee Xinyu Que was selected as one of the two awardees for 2011 George Michael Fellowship. Xinyu Que received travel support to attend both SC11 and SC12 conferences, besides a $5000 monetary award through this fellowship. His research on scalable run-time system techniques was enabled by the CRI cluster. [First Place in 2012 ACM SRC Grand Finals]: Partly enabled by the CRI cluster, Ph.D. student Yuan Tian is selected as the First Prize Winner of the ACM Student Research Competition Grand Finals, for her research on system-aware I/O organization for scientific analytics. Both Yuan and Dr. Yu were invited to the 2012 ACM Award Ceremony at San Francisco in June 2012. [2nd Place Graduate Research Award at College of Engineering]: Enabled by the CRI cluster, Xinyu QueÆs research on scalable programming models for computation and big data analytics has been selected by Samuel Ginn College of Engineering as the 2nd place winner in the 2012 Graduate Research Competition.  [College of Engineering Outstanding International Student]: For his research enabled by the CRI cluster, Yandong Wang has won the recognition as a 2013 outstanding international student recognition by the College of Engineering, Auburn University.       In addition, this research infrastructure has broader impact in a number of aspects.  It strengthens computer science research on parallel programming models, parallel I/O, file systems, storage, and data-intensive analytics.  In addition, it cultivates new multidisciplinary research projects on computational climate modeling, computational atomic physics, and applied computer science. Open source software packages from this project are released for community services. These broader impacts are listed in more detail as follows.  Broader Impacts:  [Graduated Ph.D. and Master students] Enabled by the CRI cluster, Yuan Tian, Xinyu Que, Yandong Wang, Zhuo Liu, and Cong Xu have finished their doctoral thesis dissertation and joined prestigious organizations such as Oak Ridge National Lab, IBM T.J. Watson, Yahoo and Intel. Patrick Carpenter and Xiaobing Li have finished their master theses and joined Amazon and LogicMonitor Inc, respectively. Several more students are graduating soon in 2015. [Hadoop Acceleration in the Industry] Hadoop Acceleration project, as enabled by the CRI cluster, has been integrated into several main distributions of Hadoop including Cloudera, Horton Networks and Haoop Mainline. A source code patch is also released from a group project website: http://pasl.eng.auburn.edu/doku/dok...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
