<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Basalt-Hosted Biosphere at North Pond: A Subseafloor Mid-Atlantic Ridge-Flank Microbial</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>165078.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>248065</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040204</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Janecek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit &lt;br/&gt;North Pond, the target for drilling based on IODP 677-Full in 2011, is a shallow sediment pondon the western flank of the mid Atlantic ridge. Prior drilling and study of North Pond revealed youngocean crust (7-8 m.y.) with active, low temperature fluids vigorously advecting through basement. Thethermal and hydrologic state of North Pond are characteristic of large portions of the global ridge flank system, where a significant fraction of lithospheric heat is lost via hydrothermal processes, and theassociated fluid-rock reactions significantly alter the composition of ocean and crust. Petrographicobservations of certain textural features in the alteration rind of basaltic glass that have been retrieved at many (other) sites suggest that microbes may play an important role in alteration of ocean crust in ridge flank settings. However, this hypothesis has not been confirmed and indeed, we lack robust molecular, biochemical, or physiological data that might inform our understanding of the very nature of microbes in the lithosphere. The principal motivation for the North Pond project is to address these questions through systematic empirical and experimental study. The fundamental scientific questions that motivate the drilling and observatory program at North Pond include: 1) What is the nature of microbial communities harbored in young ridge flanks and what is their role in ocean crust alteration? 2) Are these communities unique, particularly incomparison with seafloor and sedimentary communities? 3) Where do deep-seated microbial communities come from (sediment, rock, seawater?)? While some of these questions can be addressed through sampling with ?typical? IODP recovery and analysis of sediment and rock, progress at the heart of questions that relate to active processes such as crustal alteration, microbial colonization, fluid dynamics, and transience, require time-series observation and experiments, coupled with contextual data concerning chemical, physical, and hydrodynamics of the system as a whole. In a sense, this is taking an Earth systems science approach to solving problems in the environmental life sciences. To achieve this approach IODP will establish three long-term subseafloor microbial observatories in North Pond in order to identify indigenous ridge flank microbes and delineate the role that they play in oxidative alteration. A major portion of the infrastructural needs for this project have already been supported, enabling preparations, which are now well underway for deployment in 2011 with the IODP. This includes the design, fabrication, and purchasing of hardware, down hole samplers, instruments, and experimental materials. This proposal requests ROV dives shortly after the IODP expedition to initiate the observatory and populate it with a variety of samplers and experiments and to collect supporting material (sediments,water, rocks) from the surround area to elucidate sources for the subsurface biome that will be sampled within borehole observatories. We also seek ROV time one year later to monitor how fast these boreholes recover from drilling operations and gauge future operations and direction. The experiments at North Pond will also provide an excellent comparison for ongoing studies on the eastern flank of the Juan de Fuca Ridge, which is chemically, thermally, and hydrologically distinct. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts &lt;br/&gt;We propose to bring three professionals (videographers and science writers) on board the IODP cruise and the two cruises proposed herein. These individuals will work with ship-board scientists and shore-based liaisons associated with COSSEE-West and Ocean Leadership. Our objectives are to link teachers and classrooms with these liaisons in real-time, establish new educational programs in drilling related science, and create new products for broader public outreach. For example, through the creation of a variety of media products, from blogs, vignettes, and online media, we will develop a documentary that focuses on life below the bottom of the ocean. Another important broader impact of this project is in the establishment of long-term infrastructure for community wide study of this environment. Observatories are a community resource, and over the next decade many dozens of diverse researchers will participate in scientific study at North Pond. Indeed, scientists have recognized the importance of this site as a key reference system and have engaged in scientific study of it since the mid 1970?s. This project marks the beginning of a new era of observing science for the community at North Pond, through the establishment of a 3-D array of instrumented modern borehole observatories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1060855</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keir</FirstName>
<LastName>Becker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keir Becker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbecker@rsmas.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3054214661</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000134360</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Miami</Name>
<CityName>Key Biscayne</CityName>
<ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3054214089</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4600 RICKENBACKER CSWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>152764007</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004146619</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami]]></Name>
<CityName>Key Biscayne</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4600 RICKENBACKER CSWY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5720</Code>
<Text>OCEAN DRILLING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5720</Code>
<Text>OCEAN DRILLING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~171611</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~11288</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~65166</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was part of a collaborative effort among investigators at the University of Southern California, Moss Landing Marine Lab, and the University of Miami Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Science (RSMAS).&nbsp; The goal of the collaboration was to conduct two submersible cruises in 2012 and 2014 for data recovery and formation fluid sampling from three deep-sea sealed-hole observatories called &ldquo;CORKs&rdquo; that had been installed during a 2011 expedition of the Integrated Ocean Drilling Program (IODP) in an isolated sediment pond (&ldquo;North Pond&rdquo;) in young oceanic crust west of the Mid-Atlantic Ridge.&nbsp; The overall goal of the borehole observatory program was to understand subseafloor hydrogeology of the setting and determine the nature of the largely unknown subseafloor microbial ecosystems hosted in that hydrogeological regime.&nbsp;</p> <p>The specific objective of this project was to record seafloor and formation pressure and temperature data from the CORK observatories and conduct initial interpretation of those data to understand the natural hydrogeological regime there.&nbsp; Previous work had suggested there is vigorous lateral flow of formation fluids in the permeable oceanic basement beneath the less permeable sediments of North Pond.&nbsp; Primary objectives of the pressure monitoring were to determine the formation pressure differentials driving this flow, and also to interpret the hydrological properties of the basement from its response to external pressure loading signals such as the ocean tidal variation registered on the seafloor.</p> <p>The pressure instrumentation had been acquired with prior NSF support (OCE-0946795) to the PI of this project.&nbsp; The design of the CORK observatories provides for submersible connection to transfer formation pressure data recorded at two-minute intervals by data loggers mounted on the wellheads.&nbsp; Pressure data from all three CORKs were successfully transferred during two research cruises in spring of 2012 and spring of 2014, using the US remotely operated vehicle (ROV) Jason from the German research vessel Maria S. Merian.&nbsp; The PI of this project acted as ROV chief scientist for the 2014 cruise.&nbsp; On the other hand, the downhole temperatures are recorded in individual memory data loggers that are attached to sensor strings suspended down in the holes.&nbsp; These sensor strings must be recovered onto an oceanographic ship before the temperature data can be accessed.&nbsp; That is planned for spring of 2017, with a final phase of NSF support to the collaborating group including the PI of this project.</p> <p>The pressure data recovered in 2012 and 2014 form 2-1/2 year time series that document the formation pressure state and responses to external loads like the oceanographic tides.&nbsp; They support the earlier inference of extensive flow of formation fluids in a highly permeable oceanic crust beneath the less permeable sediment layer.&nbsp; The pressure data clearly show slight overpressures (about 1-2 psi) of the oceanic crust beneath the sediments.&nbsp; This was initially interpreted as a result of the thermally insulating effects of the impermeable sediments, producing slightly warmer and less dense formation fluids beneath the sediment pond relative to the surrounding region.&nbsp; The formation fluids in the surrounding unsedimented crust are cooler and denser at a given depth and therefore &lsquo;squeeze&rsquo; the formation fluids confined beneath the sediment pond, raising their pressures slightly.&nbsp; Final verification of this hypothesis must await 2017 recovery of the downhole temperature data, because the equilibrium temperature state controls the background density of the fluid column and therefore defines the hydrostatic reference for determination of the magnitude of the over-pressures.</p> <p>The pressure-logging systems and CORK observat...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was part of a collaborative effort among investigators at the University of Southern California, Moss Landing Marine Lab, and the University of Miami Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Science (RSMAS).  The goal of the collaboration was to conduct two submersible cruises in 2012 and 2014 for data recovery and formation fluid sampling from three deep-sea sealed-hole observatories called "CORKs" that had been installed during a 2011 expedition of the Integrated Ocean Drilling Program (IODP) in an isolated sediment pond ("North Pond") in young oceanic crust west of the Mid-Atlantic Ridge.  The overall goal of the borehole observatory program was to understand subseafloor hydrogeology of the setting and determine the nature of the largely unknown subseafloor microbial ecosystems hosted in that hydrogeological regime.   The specific objective of this project was to record seafloor and formation pressure and temperature data from the CORK observatories and conduct initial interpretation of those data to understand the natural hydrogeological regime there.  Previous work had suggested there is vigorous lateral flow of formation fluids in the permeable oceanic basement beneath the less permeable sediments of North Pond.  Primary objectives of the pressure monitoring were to determine the formation pressure differentials driving this flow, and also to interpret the hydrological properties of the basement from its response to external pressure loading signals such as the ocean tidal variation registered on the seafloor.  The pressure instrumentation had been acquired with prior NSF support (OCE-0946795) to the PI of this project.  The design of the CORK observatories provides for submersible connection to transfer formation pressure data recorded at two-minute intervals by data loggers mounted on the wellheads.  Pressure data from all three CORKs were successfully transferred during two research cruises in spring of 2012 and spring of 2014, using the US remotely operated vehicle (ROV) Jason from the German research vessel Maria S. Merian.  The PI of this project acted as ROV chief scientist for the 2014 cruise.  On the other hand, the downhole temperatures are recorded in individual memory data loggers that are attached to sensor strings suspended down in the holes.  These sensor strings must be recovered onto an oceanographic ship before the temperature data can be accessed.  That is planned for spring of 2017, with a final phase of NSF support to the collaborating group including the PI of this project.  The pressure data recovered in 2012 and 2014 form 2-1/2 year time series that document the formation pressure state and responses to external loads like the oceanographic tides.  They support the earlier inference of extensive flow of formation fluids in a highly permeable oceanic crust beneath the less permeable sediment layer.  The pressure data clearly show slight overpressures (about 1-2 psi) of the oceanic crust beneath the sediments.  This was initially interpreted as a result of the thermally insulating effects of the impermeable sediments, producing slightly warmer and less dense formation fluids beneath the sediment pond relative to the surrounding region.  The formation fluids in the surrounding unsedimented crust are cooler and denser at a given depth and therefore æsqueezeÆ the formation fluids confined beneath the sediment pond, raising their pressures slightly.  Final verification of this hypothesis must await 2017 recovery of the downhole temperature data, because the equilibrium temperature state controls the background density of the fluid column and therefore defines the hydrostatic reference for determination of the magnitude of the over-pressures.  The pressure-logging systems and CORK observatories were designed with lifetimes and battery capabilities of 10-20 years.  Thus, these installations will remain as viable infrastructure for future investigations related to hydrogeology and the subs...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
