<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fostering Science and Math Scholars in Rural North Carolina</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>575000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>575000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is providing scholarships plus comprehensive academic and social support to talented, but financially challenged students, who wish to pursue careers in biology, chemistry, mathematics or biotechnology. Serving a student population composed of 45% Native American, 28% African American, and 24% White with 72% women and 28% men, the project is increasing the: &lt;br/&gt;1) number of students enrolled in mathematics and science/curriculum transfer programs; &lt;br/&gt;2) number of students receiving assistance from Student Support Services programs; &lt;br/&gt;3) retention of students to transfer or degree achievement; and, &lt;br/&gt;4) graduation rate of African American, Native American and female students in mathematics and science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project is developing the support network necessary for student achievement through a campus-wide effort. Academic performance is being supported through student learning communities, facilitated study sessions, one-on-one tutoring, faculty mentoring, counseling, and support through Student Support Services and electronic communities. Internships, job shadowing and/or faculty-led research opportunities are available to enhance learning and achievement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The project impact is significant through incorporation of existing resources with newly developed activities to address the unique needs of rural, predominantly minority students. Research with trained professionals or introductions to science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) professionals in business and industry is advancing discovery and understanding and leading to greater achievement and degree attainment. Students are being prepared for successful transitions to work or baccalaureate degree programs, resulting in highly qualified candidates for jobs including jobs as public school science and mathematics teachers. Additionally, the opportunity to transfer scholarship funding to the university is a unique feature of the program. The project is establishing a model for achievement that can be replicated in many other disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1060551</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nirupama</FirstName>
<LastName>Mohapatra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nirupama Mohapatra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nmohapatra@robeson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9102723382</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000142021</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/12/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cassandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cassandra Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cjohnson@robeson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9102723240</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544338</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cassandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cassandra Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cjohnson@robeson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9102723240</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544338</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/11/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
<LastName>McIntyre</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louis F McIntyre</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcintyrel5511@rockinghamcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3363424261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536579</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/11/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Robeson Community College</Name>
<CityName>Lumberton</CityName>
<ZipCode>283591420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9102723675</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5160 Fayetteville Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P O Box 1420]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>099813479</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROBESON COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>099813479</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Robeson Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Lumberton</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>283591420</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5160 Fayetteville Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~59250</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~515750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>NSF S-STEM OUTCOMES REPORT</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Robeson Community College</strong></p> <p>The Robeson Community College Fostering Science and Math in Rural North Carolina Scholars Program was a National Science Foundation funded project that provided scholarships for financially needy community college students. The scope of the project involved providing financial assistance, supplemental support and extra-curricular engagement for underrepresented groups of economically disadvantaged students pursuing associate in science degrees, leading to transfer to a 4-year university. The project goal was to provide 20 scholarships per year, and this was accomplished by providing scholarships to a total of 82 students, comprised of 24 females and 58 males receiving funding.</p> <p>The success of the project is also evidenced in its support of 83% of the FMSRNC Scholars completing associate degrees. Some of these students earned multiple degrees: 33% earned an Associate in Science, 31% earned an Electrical Systems Technology degree, 16% earned an Industrial Systems Technology degree, and 16% earned a Computer Information Technology degree. Four percent of students were partially funded as Associate in Science major but concluded their academic path earning an Associate in Arts degree.</p> <p>Of the associate degree earning students, 37% transferred to a 4-year institution, 4% pursued a graduate degree and 56% transitioned into the STEM workforce after the completion of an associate degree, bachelor&rsquo;s degree or STEM Certificate; two of which are high school math teachers. Thus, for the transferring scholars the portability component of the initiative was a vital part of the program and contributed to their successful pursuit of a 4-year degree. The unique demographics of Robeson County provided an opportunity to serve the underrepresented populations in rural NC in that the students served represented 41% American Indian, 24% African American, 10% Hispanic/Other, and 24% White. The average GPA of the FSMRNC Scholars was 3.33 and contributed to the successful matriculation into and completion of their involvement in the STEM initiative.</p> <p>Scholars not only benefitted from the financial support provided by the project, as they were also provided with faculty mentors, institutionally supported student support services, as well as opportunities to engage in extracurricular interventions <em>(e.g. internships, site visits both corporate &amp; educational),</em> and peer tutoring. Additionally, a major capacity building aspect of the project involved the STEM scholars&rsquo; involvement in the colleges&rsquo; outreach efforts <em>(Open House, New Student Orientations, site visits within the local education agencies, etc.)</em> to promote, the value of attending community college.&nbsp; FSMRNC scholars were also effective with promoting STEM awareness in the secondary education environment as well as local community by organizing science fairs and participating in career day events.</p> <p>STEM capacity building was affected by the project providing opportunities for the project management (PI &amp; Co-PI) to give presentations at regional and national conferences, to participate on steering committees and advisory boards at North Carolina institutions of Higher Education, as well as North Carolina STEM initiatives. This funded initiative was an excellent opportunity for the college to support economically disadvantaged students in Robeson County with their STEM education, while also having a positive impact on STEM academics and careers for underrepresented groups in Robeson County.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Cassandra&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[NSF S-STEM OUTCOMES REPORT Robeson Community College  The Robeson Community College Fostering Science and Math in Rural North Carolina Scholars Program was a National Science Foundation funded project that provided scholarships for financially needy community college students. The scope of the project involved providing financial assistance, supplemental support and extra-curricular engagement for underrepresented groups of economically disadvantaged students pursuing associate in science degrees, leading to transfer to a 4-year university. The project goal was to provide 20 scholarships per year, and this was accomplished by providing scholarships to a total of 82 students, comprised of 24 females and 58 males receiving funding.  The success of the project is also evidenced in its support of 83% of the FMSRNC Scholars completing associate degrees. Some of these students earned multiple degrees: 33% earned an Associate in Science, 31% earned an Electrical Systems Technology degree, 16% earned an Industrial Systems Technology degree, and 16% earned a Computer Information Technology degree. Four percent of students were partially funded as Associate in Science major but concluded their academic path earning an Associate in Arts degree.  Of the associate degree earning students, 37% transferred to a 4-year institution, 4% pursued a graduate degree and 56% transitioned into the STEM workforce after the completion of an associate degree, bachelor?s degree or STEM Certificate; two of which are high school math teachers. Thus, for the transferring scholars the portability component of the initiative was a vital part of the program and contributed to their successful pursuit of a 4-year degree. The unique demographics of Robeson County provided an opportunity to serve the underrepresented populations in rural NC in that the students served represented 41% American Indian, 24% African American, 10% Hispanic/Other, and 24% White. The average GPA of the FSMRNC Scholars was 3.33 and contributed to the successful matriculation into and completion of their involvement in the STEM initiative.  Scholars not only benefitted from the financial support provided by the project, as they were also provided with faculty mentors, institutionally supported student support services, as well as opportunities to engage in extracurricular interventions (e.g. internships, site visits both corporate &amp; educational), and peer tutoring. Additionally, a major capacity building aspect of the project involved the STEM scholars? involvement in the colleges? outreach efforts (Open House, New Student Orientations, site visits within the local education agencies, etc.) to promote, the value of attending community college.  FSMRNC scholars were also effective with promoting STEM awareness in the secondary education environment as well as local community by organizing science fairs and participating in career day events.  STEM capacity building was affected by the project providing opportunities for the project management (PI &amp; Co-PI) to give presentations at regional and national conferences, to participate on steering committees and advisory boards at North Carolina institutions of Higher Education, as well as North Carolina STEM initiatives. This funded initiative was an excellent opportunity for the college to support economically disadvantaged students in Robeson County with their STEM education, while also having a positive impact on STEM academics and careers for underrepresented groups in Robeson County.       Last Modified: 10/15/2018       Submitted by: Cassandra Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
