<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Eddy Correlation and chamber measurements of benthic oxygen fluxes in permeable sediments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>343385.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>343385</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald L. Rice</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project will investigate the measurement of oxygen flux across the sediment water interface using the eddy correlation technique, which is an in situ approach for continuous measurement. Obtaining such fluxes will increase the ability to measure accurately benthic oxygen fluxes in sediments. This project will further the development of the eddy correlation technique and compare these results with advection chambers and with the perfusion method, both of which are currently used, to validate the eddy correlation approach and show its broad applicability. A process-based mathematical model will also be developed and used, with the flux measurements and porewater data, to validate the technique and will also be used to interpret and synthesize the results. The scientific merit of this research is that oxygen fluxes are the main proxy for assessing carbon cycling rates in sediments and are used widely in carbon budget estimates. The project will therefore help improve such estimates by increasing the database on oxygen fluxes for permeable shelf sediments, and by providing an increased understanding of the controlling variables.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop an outreach program in conjunction with the Virginia Coast Reserve LTER, one of the locations of this project, which has an active outreach program to K-12 schools, with a strong impact on minority groups. The project will also involve graduate and undergraduate education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1061110</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Markus</FirstName>
<LastName>Huettel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Markus H Huettel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mhuettel@fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506451394</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~343385</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project focused on further developing the aquatic eddy covariance technique in order to improve our ability to measure, understand, and predict oxygen fluxes between the water column and marine sandy sediments. Both PIs have pioneered novel flux methods specifically for permeable sands, and by comparing results from parallel deployments of both approaches, benthic chamber incubations and eddy covariance measurements, the project shed light on the conditions under which these methods produce trustworthy flux estimates. This effort added valuable data to the sparsely populated global database of oxygen fluxes for permeable sediments. Detailed modeling of the transport of water borne constituents, and its interactions with inhomogeneous bottoms, improved our interpretations of measured flux data. The eddy covariance data showed the temporal variability of the oxygen fluxes and how these are influenced by bottom currents, light and temperature. In contrast to the eddy covariance technique that integrates fluxes over an area that can be more than hundred meters long an a couple meters wide, the benthic chambers measure fluxes for a specific flow setting and for a small confined sediment area. The fluxes thus are not directly comparable, however, the ranges of the fluxes agreed between the two techniques. The two techniques complement each other as the eddy covariance can capture flux changes caused by flow and light variations, while the chambers can record a large number of different fluxes (oxygen, carbon dioxide, nutrients, dissolved metals etc.) simultaneously, which is helpful for the interpretation of the oxygen fluxes measured by the eddy covariance instrument.</p> <p>Submerged permeable sandy sediments are found everywhere along our shorelines. Due to the porous structure of sands, current and wave motions can induce extensive exchange of water and water borne constituents between bottom water and the pore space in the upper sand layers. This exchange largely controls how organic matter is transported into the sand from the water above, how it is then broken down, and how the bi-products are released again. Traditional underwater flux methods have difficulties capturing this exchange under natural field conditions and thus, fluxes measured by these techniques may be biased. Because sands are found everywhere, this uncertainty affects carbon budget estimates on both local and global scales, and ultimately adds uncertainly to our model predictions of carbon cycling and global warming.</p> <p>In this project, graduate students were trained and workshops were hosted for new users of state-of-the-art flux methods for permeable sediments. Project results were presented in scientific publications and at two special sessions chaired by the PIs at international conferences. Further information about this project is available at the project websites: <a href="http://faculty.virginia.edu/berg/">http://faculty.virginia.edu/berg/</a> (University of Virginia) and <a href="http://myweb.fsu.edu/mhuettel/Projects/NSF_Eddy.html">http://myweb.fsu.edu/mhuettel/Projects/NSF_Eddy.html</a> (Florida State University).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/18/2015<br>      Modified by: Markus&nbsp;H&nbsp;Huettel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1061110/1061110_10078824_1432001545261_6Benthicchambers--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Report...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project focused on further developing the aquatic eddy covariance technique in order to improve our ability to measure, understand, and predict oxygen fluxes between the water column and marine sandy sediments. Both PIs have pioneered novel flux methods specifically for permeable sands, and by comparing results from parallel deployments of both approaches, benthic chamber incubations and eddy covariance measurements, the project shed light on the conditions under which these methods produce trustworthy flux estimates. This effort added valuable data to the sparsely populated global database of oxygen fluxes for permeable sediments. Detailed modeling of the transport of water borne constituents, and its interactions with inhomogeneous bottoms, improved our interpretations of measured flux data. The eddy covariance data showed the temporal variability of the oxygen fluxes and how these are influenced by bottom currents, light and temperature. In contrast to the eddy covariance technique that integrates fluxes over an area that can be more than hundred meters long an a couple meters wide, the benthic chambers measure fluxes for a specific flow setting and for a small confined sediment area. The fluxes thus are not directly comparable, however, the ranges of the fluxes agreed between the two techniques. The two techniques complement each other as the eddy covariance can capture flux changes caused by flow and light variations, while the chambers can record a large number of different fluxes (oxygen, carbon dioxide, nutrients, dissolved metals etc.) simultaneously, which is helpful for the interpretation of the oxygen fluxes measured by the eddy covariance instrument.  Submerged permeable sandy sediments are found everywhere along our shorelines. Due to the porous structure of sands, current and wave motions can induce extensive exchange of water and water borne constituents between bottom water and the pore space in the upper sand layers. This exchange largely controls how organic matter is transported into the sand from the water above, how it is then broken down, and how the bi-products are released again. Traditional underwater flux methods have difficulties capturing this exchange under natural field conditions and thus, fluxes measured by these techniques may be biased. Because sands are found everywhere, this uncertainty affects carbon budget estimates on both local and global scales, and ultimately adds uncertainly to our model predictions of carbon cycling and global warming.  In this project, graduate students were trained and workshops were hosted for new users of state-of-the-art flux methods for permeable sediments. Project results were presented in scientific publications and at two special sessions chaired by the PIs at international conferences. Further information about this project is available at the project websites: http://faculty.virginia.edu/berg/ (University of Virginia) and http://myweb.fsu.edu/mhuettel/Projects/NSF_Eddy.html (Florida State University).             Last Modified: 05/18/2015       Submitted by: Markus H Huettel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
