<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Practices of Record Production and their Impact on the Administration of American Indian and Migrant Populations in the United States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>289617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>289617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Gould</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research team investigate the manner in which individuals interact with official documents to construct official versions of their identity and status in response to regulatory requirements. The research examines two groups: 1) immigrants preparing naturalization documents, and 2) indigenous individuals preparing federal tribal recognition documents. The research offers insights into the practices that constitute state power and define its boundaries; citizenship; the role of regulation in identity-formation; and the cultural production of knowledge. The research plan involves participant observation, archival research and interviews at three selected sites of official documents in California. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will highlight the ways that, in response to legal requirements, individuals use official documents to construct versions of their own identity that will help them secure their place in society -- a process that is especially important for those with marginalized status.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1061063</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Coutin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan B Coutin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scoutin@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498241447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000277904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Coutin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan B Coutin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scoutin@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498241447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000277904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/19/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Richland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin B Richland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbrich@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498245756</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/19/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~289617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Although Native Americans and immigrants may be seen as disparate, even opposite groups (the former lived in the territory that is now the United States before the country was founded, the latter are recent arrivals), legally, these two populations have much in common.&nbsp; Both Native Americans and immigrants are members of multiple nations, both are governed by the Plenary Powers doctrine of the U.S. Constitution, which gives Congress and Federal authorities considerable discretion in devising policies, and both groups have faced challenges in being able to gather the documents needed to prove their status &ndash; whether as a tribe or as legal immigrants.&nbsp; Our research set out to examine these commonalities, in order to better understand the ways that that indigenous and immigrant groups obtain the records that they need to submit to U.S. authorities, as well as the particular evidentiary challenges that they face.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Research funding allowed us to conduct ethnographic research in two Southern California settings:&nbsp; among members of a Native American band that is petitioning the U.S. government for Federal Recognition as a tribe, and within a Southern California nonprofit agency that assists Spanish-speaking immigrants in applying for legal status.&nbsp; We were able to shadow legal service providers, audio-record tribal council meetings, observe as immigrants and Native Americans compiled documents for their immigration or federal recognition cases, familiarize ourselves with a range of forms and documents pertinent to these cases, collect examples of these forms and documents, travel to archives from which immigrants and Native Americans retrieve records, and conduct interviews with Native Americans, immigrants, and legal services providers regarding these processes. We also did historical research, examining court opinions from earlier decades as well as earlier versions of key immigration forms.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Our results indicate that there are important intersections in the ways that immigrants and the indigenous are positioned in relation to U.S. law.&nbsp; For example, historically, the U.S. government&rsquo;s ability to move indigenous groups to reservations was cited as a precedent for deporting immigrants to other countries, suggesting that indigenous and immigrant populations were seen as occupying similar legal positions despite their very different histories.&nbsp; The high level of discretion that the government enjoys regarding the treatment of these two groups continues to shape the everyday lives and practices of immigrant and the indigenous today.&nbsp; &nbsp;Our observations indicate that immigrants and the indigenous face continual uncertainty regarding the standards of proof that they need to meet, the forms of evidence that will be deemed acceptable, and even whether or not particular programs and policies will remain in existence.&nbsp; This uncertainty produces an awareness of documents and their importance.&nbsp; Many immigrants, for example, develop a habit of saving all sorts of records (receipts, bank statements, check stubs) in case they will be of use in a future immigration case.&nbsp; Such repurposing of documents (that is, using records produced in one context as evidence in another context) can also create challenges, however, given that records might or might not contain the information required for a particular legal proceeding.&nbsp; For instance, federal regulations mandate that petitioners seeking federal recognition as a tribe provide documentary evidence of descent from a &ldquo;known Indian,&rdquo; yet the historical records on which such claims are based date from time periods when individuals may have had to hide t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             Although Native Americans and immigrants may be seen as disparate, even opposite groups (the former lived in the territory that is now the United States before the country was founded, the latter are recent arrivals), legally, these two populations have much in common.  Both Native Americans and immigrants are members of multiple nations, both are governed by the Plenary Powers doctrine of the U.S. Constitution, which gives Congress and Federal authorities considerable discretion in devising policies, and both groups have faced challenges in being able to gather the documents needed to prove their status &ndash; whether as a tribe or as legal immigrants.  Our research set out to examine these commonalities, in order to better understand the ways that that indigenous and immigrant groups obtain the records that they need to submit to U.S. authorities, as well as the particular evidentiary challenges that they face.              Research funding allowed us to conduct ethnographic research in two Southern California settings:  among members of a Native American band that is petitioning the U.S. government for Federal Recognition as a tribe, and within a Southern California nonprofit agency that assists Spanish-speaking immigrants in applying for legal status.  We were able to shadow legal service providers, audio-record tribal council meetings, observe as immigrants and Native Americans compiled documents for their immigration or federal recognition cases, familiarize ourselves with a range of forms and documents pertinent to these cases, collect examples of these forms and documents, travel to archives from which immigrants and Native Americans retrieve records, and conduct interviews with Native Americans, immigrants, and legal services providers regarding these processes. We also did historical research, examining court opinions from earlier decades as well as earlier versions of key immigration forms.              Our results indicate that there are important intersections in the ways that immigrants and the indigenous are positioned in relation to U.S. law.  For example, historically, the U.S. governmentÆs ability to move indigenous groups to reservations was cited as a precedent for deporting immigrants to other countries, suggesting that indigenous and immigrant populations were seen as occupying similar legal positions despite their very different histories.  The high level of discretion that the government enjoys regarding the treatment of these two groups continues to shape the everyday lives and practices of immigrant and the indigenous today.   Our observations indicate that immigrants and the indigenous face continual uncertainty regarding the standards of proof that they need to meet, the forms of evidence that will be deemed acceptable, and even whether or not particular programs and policies will remain in existence.  This uncertainty produces an awareness of documents and their importance.  Many immigrants, for example, develop a habit of saving all sorts of records (receipts, bank statements, check stubs) in case they will be of use in a future immigration case.  Such repurposing of documents (that is, using records produced in one context as evidence in another context) can also create challenges, however, given that records might or might not contain the information required for a particular legal proceeding.  For instance, federal regulations mandate that petitioners seeking federal recognition as a tribe provide documentary evidence of descent from a "known Indian," yet the historical records on which such claims are based date from time periods when individuals may have had to hide their identities as Native American.  As a result, that information may not be recorded.  Additionally, immigrants and the indigenous may face evidentiary challenges due to errors introduced by others.  A common example in the case of immigrants occurs when names or birthdates were recorded incorrectly on a birth cer...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
