<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: An International Professional-Development Workshop in Dendrochronology: North American Dendroecological Fieldweek (NADEF)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>206422.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>206422</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The North American Dendroecological Fieldweek (NADEF) has been providing advanced education in tree-ring research through project-based learning for 20 years.  The current project will provide funding for the next five years to acquire state-of-the-art equipment and includes funds to offset participant fees to students to make attendance easier for undergraduate and graduate students.  Tree-ring research (or dendrochronology) uses the annual growth of trees to record environmental variables such as climate, fires, or insect outbreaks.   Anything that affects tree-growth could potentially be dated using tree rings.  The fieldweek teaches the skills of crossdating (matching the pattern of wide and narrow rings to apply exact dates to every ring) and the statistical techniques necessary to interpret what is affecting tree growth by using hands-on teaching techniques that enable learners to understand the process more fully and to comprehend the practice of dendrochronology on a research project from start to finish.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NADEF is a nine-day workshop that has approximately 40 participants. The participants choose to become a member of the research team on one of five original research projects that are conducted during the fieldweek under the guidance of experienced dendrochronologists.  Participants are divided into groups on fire history, climate reconstruction, stand-age structure, insect outbreak histories, dating archaeological dwellings, among other activities. With respect to broader impacts, the fieldweeks have given researchers as well as undergraduate and graduate students the opportunity to interact and network with others. Furthermore, the research that is completed each year contributes to the local resource management knowledge base and can grow into long-term research agendas. Past fieldweek projects have also been the kernel for further work on a thesis or dissertation and have become published papers.  As the fieldweek comes to an end, participants from each group present their findings back to the whole group and turn in a short research paper describing their methods and findings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1061808</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Speer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James H Speer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jim.speer@indstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8122373011</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485070</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter M Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pmb@rmtrr.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9702299557</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000421353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana State University</Name>
<CityName>TERRE HAUTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>478091902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8122373088</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 N 7TH STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075953448</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INDIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075953448</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TERRE HAUTE</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>478091902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 N 7TH STREET]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1397</Code>
<Text>Cross-Directorate  Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1303</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE MODELING &amp; PREDICTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1324</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY AND PREDICTABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~62418</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~37102</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~72244</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~34658</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The North American Dendroecological Fieldweek (NADEF) has completed six years of research under this grant proposal from five years of funding and one year with a no-cost extension. We have also received a previous five year grant from NSF as well dating from 2006-2010 and the current grant ran from 2011-2016. Dendrochronology is the field of using tree rings to reconstruct environmental variables with annual resolution. We use hands-on training and experiential learning as our main teaching methods. By engaging the students in original research projects whose outcomes will be directly transferred to local land managers for forestry applications the participants deeply understand the utility of this research and become more engaged in their education through these projects. The fieldweek enables these students to excel in the techniques of dendrochronology applied to earth systems science, natural resources, forestry, and life sciences issues. We use a similar technique as the National Science Foundation (NSF) funded Science Education for New Civic Engagements and Responsibilities (SENCER) teaching model which uses hands-on inquiry based education around important real-world civic issues that engage students. This teaching model and our own is influenced by the National Research Council of the National Academies publications on <em>How People Learn</em> (Bransford <em>et al.</em> 1999) and <em>How Students Learn Science in the Classroom</em> (Donovan and Bransford 2005) which shows that the learning must have meaning to the students and they must be active participants in the process of discovery. NADEF fulfills four main goals:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Educate the participants in the methods of dendrochronology and application of the scientific method to fully execute a research project.</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Offer valuable leadership opportunities for graduate students who are encouraged to serve as group leaders with the introductory group and through the Graduate Research Fellowship program.</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Expand and promote the methods of dendrochronology at the frontiers of the science including applications in marine and freshwater science (sclerochronology) and multi-proxy reconstructions.</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Provide local land managers with a wealth of scientific information about the ecosystems they manage.</p> <p>In the last 6 years research from 17 fieldweek projects has been presented at national or international conferences, 5 projects have been published in peer-reviewed journals, and 4 thesis or dissertations have been completed on fieldweek data (4 more in progress). Local land managers have gained a wealth of information from the products of the fieldweek. Local land managers are always invited into the process as we are planning the research projects for each year so that we can provide data that they need on their forests. We often focus the five research projects during the fieldweek in one location so that local managers can benefit from climate reconstructions, fire histories, insect outbreak reconstructions, and stand-age structure studies from a specific area. The managers are invited to the final talks at the end of the fieldweek and are presented with the final report summarizing the findings each year. We also provide surfaced and dated cross sections from their management areas as educational and interpretive tools that make a lasting impact in that management area.</p> <p>Numerous broader impacts are achieved through the fieldweek. Most of these are explicit and many collateral benefits are gained as well. The fieldweek:</p> <ul> <li>Enables networking of graduate students and professors from different institutions.</li> <li>Allows participants and group leaders to experience dendrochronological techniques from different labs and perspectives.</li> <li>Allows group leaders to try novel research approaches in new environments, possibly expanding their research agendas to new tools and new locations.</li> <li>Provides outreach opportunities for the dendrochronological community, where local land managers gain the benefit of intensive tree-ring research.</li> <li>Engages graduate and undergraduate students that would otherwise not have access to courses in dendrochronology.</li> <li>Provides teaching opportunities for advanced dendrochronology graduate students.</li> <li>Engages graduate and undergraduate students in the scientific method and skills of group research by conducting a self-contained research project.</li> </ul> <p>With the importance of environmental change issues in today&rsquo;s society, the need for high resolution proxy records of climate and ecological variables is quickly growing. Dendrochronology is an active field, but most practitioners work alone in their academic programs and do not have the opportunity to interact with other dendrochronologists. The fieldweeks give these researchers as well as undergraduate and graduate students the opportunity to interact with others in the field and network with university faculty and professional foresters. Many of the undergraduates and graduate students that come to the fieldweeks have learned about dendrochronology through brief mention of tree-ring research in their classes. The fieldweeks are generally the best opportunity for these students to take an intensive course in dendrochronology. The fieldweek enables these students to excel in the techniques of dendrochronology applied to Earth system science, natural resources, forestry, and life sciences issues.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/28/2017<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681662957_IMGP8955--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681662957_IMGP8955--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NADEF 2014 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681662957_IMGP8955--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NADEF 2014 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group Photo at the 2014 North American Dendroecological Fieldweek at The Northwest College, A.L. Mickelson Field Station near Cody, Wyoming.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James H. Speer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</div> <div class="imageTitle">NADEF 2014 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681154855_IMGP9994--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681154855_IMGP9994--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NADEF 2012 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681154855_IMGP9994--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NADEF 2012 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participants of the 2012 North American Dendroecological Fieldweek at Valles Caldera National Preserve, NM.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James H. Speer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</div> <div class="imageTitle">NADEF 2012 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681561315_IMGP1077--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681561315_IMGP1077--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NADEF 2013 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681561315_IMGP1077--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NADEF 2013 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The fieldweek group for 2013 during an introductory lecture before we go into the field at Black Rock Forest near Cornwall, NY.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James H. Speer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</div> <div class="imageTitle">NADEF 2013 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498680970795_GroupPhoto1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498680970795_GroupPhoto1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NADEF 2011 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498680970795_GroupPhoto1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NADEF 2011 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participants of the 2011 North American Dendroecological Fieldweek held at The Mountain Lake Biological Station in Pembroke, Virginia.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James H. Speer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</div> <div class="imageTitle">NADEF 2011 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681798067_RIMG5590--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681798067_RIMG5590--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NADEF 2015 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681798067_RIMG5590--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NADEF 2015 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group Photo for 2015 of the North American Dendroecological Fieldweek at The Schoodic Institute, Acadia National Park, Maine.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James H. Speer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</div> <div class="imageTitle">NADEF 2015 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681936759_IMGP1704--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681936759_IMGP1704--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NADEF 2016 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1061808/1061808_10079010_1498681936759_IMGP1704--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NADEF 2016 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group photo from the 2016 North American Dendroecological Fieldweek at Mount Rainier National Park, WA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James H. Speer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Speer</div> <div class="imageTitle">NADEF 2016 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The North American Dendroecological Fieldweek (NADEF) has completed six years of research under this grant proposal from five years of funding and one year with a no-cost extension. We have also received a previous five year grant from NSF as well dating from 2006-2010 and the current grant ran from 2011-2016. Dendrochronology is the field of using tree rings to reconstruct environmental variables with annual resolution. We use hands-on training and experiential learning as our main teaching methods. By engaging the students in original research projects whose outcomes will be directly transferred to local land managers for forestry applications the participants deeply understand the utility of this research and become more engaged in their education through these projects. The fieldweek enables these students to excel in the techniques of dendrochronology applied to earth systems science, natural resources, forestry, and life sciences issues. We use a similar technique as the National Science Foundation (NSF) funded Science Education for New Civic Engagements and Responsibilities (SENCER) teaching model which uses hands-on inquiry based education around important real-world civic issues that engage students. This teaching model and our own is influenced by the National Research Council of the National Academies publications on How People Learn (Bransford et al. 1999) and How Students Learn Science in the Classroom (Donovan and Bransford 2005) which shows that the learning must have meaning to the students and they must be active participants in the process of discovery. NADEF fulfills four main goals:  1)      Educate the participants in the methods of dendrochronology and application of the scientific method to fully execute a research project.  2)      Offer valuable leadership opportunities for graduate students who are encouraged to serve as group leaders with the introductory group and through the Graduate Research Fellowship program.  3)      Expand and promote the methods of dendrochronology at the frontiers of the science including applications in marine and freshwater science (sclerochronology) and multi-proxy reconstructions.  4)      Provide local land managers with a wealth of scientific information about the ecosystems they manage.  In the last 6 years research from 17 fieldweek projects has been presented at national or international conferences, 5 projects have been published in peer-reviewed journals, and 4 thesis or dissertations have been completed on fieldweek data (4 more in progress). Local land managers have gained a wealth of information from the products of the fieldweek. Local land managers are always invited into the process as we are planning the research projects for each year so that we can provide data that they need on their forests. We often focus the five research projects during the fieldweek in one location so that local managers can benefit from climate reconstructions, fire histories, insect outbreak reconstructions, and stand-age structure studies from a specific area. The managers are invited to the final talks at the end of the fieldweek and are presented with the final report summarizing the findings each year. We also provide surfaced and dated cross sections from their management areas as educational and interpretive tools that make a lasting impact in that management area.  Numerous broader impacts are achieved through the fieldweek. Most of these are explicit and many collateral benefits are gained as well. The fieldweek:  Enables networking of graduate students and professors from different institutions. Allows participants and group leaders to experience dendrochronological techniques from different labs and perspectives. Allows group leaders to try novel research approaches in new environments, possibly expanding their research agendas to new tools and new locations. Provides outreach opportunities for the dendrochronological community, where local land managers gain the benefit of intensive tree-ring research. Engages graduate and undergraduate students that would otherwise not have access to courses in dendrochronology. Provides teaching opportunities for advanced dendrochronology graduate students. Engages graduate and undergraduate students in the scientific method and skills of group research by conducting a self-contained research project.   With the importance of environmental change issues in today?s society, the need for high resolution proxy records of climate and ecological variables is quickly growing. Dendrochronology is an active field, but most practitioners work alone in their academic programs and do not have the opportunity to interact with other dendrochronologists. The fieldweeks give these researchers as well as undergraduate and graduate students the opportunity to interact with others in the field and network with university faculty and professional foresters. Many of the undergraduates and graduate students that come to the fieldweeks have learned about dendrochronology through brief mention of tree-ring research in their classes. The fieldweeks are generally the best opportunity for these students to take an intensive course in dendrochronology. The fieldweek enables these students to excel in the techniques of dendrochronology applied to Earth system science, natural resources, forestry, and life sciences issues.       Last Modified: 06/28/2017       Submitted by: James H Speer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
