<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Idealized simulations of turbulence advected by surface waves: Implications for interpreting turbulence measurements in shallow water</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>184988.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184988</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric C. Itsweire</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In shallow water  such as the inner shelf, bays, and estuaries, turbulence measurements are often made with fixed sensors. Surface waves, which are ubiquitous in these environments, confound turbulence measurement because wave orbital velocities are typically two orders of magnitude larger than turbulent fluctuations and they also advect turbulent eddies are advected past sensors. Turbulent flux measurements are usually biased by wave velocities and spectra are difficult to interpret because energy is distributed differently in frequency space than when turbulence is advected by a current alone. Methods that fit spectral shapes to frequency spectra to estimate turbulent fluxes, turbulent kinetic energy, and turbulent length scales are presently limited to conditions where wave orbital velocities are less than or equal to currents.&lt;br/&gt;In this study a series of idealized simulations will be performed to develop spectral fitting methods suitable for situations where wave orbital velocities exceed currents. Theoretical and semi-empirical turbulence wavenumber spectra from the literature, as well as fields from high resolution simulations of turbulence will be converted to frequency spectra that would be observed if the eddies were advected past a fixed location sensor by waves and a current. Preliminary idealized simulations of 1D advection of isotropic turbulence and anisotropic boundary-layer turbulence by monochromatic waves provide a framework for synthesizing the proposed simulations, as well as measurements and methods in the literature, in terms of important dimensionless parameters that relate advection of turbulence by waves to advection by currents. Idealized simulations will be extended to 2D (horizontal and vertical advection by waves) and 3D (waves propagating at an angle to the current), and to narrow- and broad-banded wave conditions typical of those on the inner shelf. Simulation results will be compared with existing laboratory and field measurements collected previously by the PI to assess the validity of model spectra (which were developed for turbulence in steady flows) for turbulence beneath waves, potentially providing new insights into wave-current boundary layers. The results of idealized simulations, along with the existing laboratory and field measurements, will be used to develop new tools that employ spectral fitting to estimate turbulence parameters and their uncertainties from fixed sensor measurements when wave orbital velocities exceed currents.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;There has been much interest recently in measuring turbulent momentum and scalar fluxes beneath surface waves using fixed location sensors; however, these measurements can be difficult to interpret. The proposed work will improve understanding of the issues involved with making turbulence measurements beneath waves when wave orbital velocities exceed currents, and develop methods for estimating turbulence parameters and their uncertainties in these conditions that will be valuable to scientists studying the physics and chemistry of a range of shallow water environments. The synthesis of previous work in the context of idealized simulations will help guide the analysis of turbulence measurements from fixed sensors in wavy environments. A library of idealized simulation results, available on a website, will allow scientists to put their measurements in the context of a broad parameter space without repeating the simulations themselves. Matlab scripts for performing idealized simulations and applying new methods developed in this study will also be made available on the project website. This grant will provide salary support and a computer workstation for one early career scientist.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1061108</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Johanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Johanna H Rosman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrosman@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2527266841</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000562084</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~184988</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Turbulence controls the mixing of dissolved and particulate materials (e.g., nutrients, contaminants, sediment, larvae) in natural water bodies. Quantifying and predicting transport of these materials therefore requires a good understanding of turbulence that can be used as the basis for models that predict mixing rates. Turbulence measurements from a range of environments and conditions are needed to develop this understanding and test these models. Turbulence is usually understood and quantified by considering its spatial structure; specifically, how the turbulent energy is distributed among eddies with different sizes. In shallow water, sensors are typically placed at fixed locations and eddies are moved past the sensors by the background water motion. Surface waves move eddies backward and forward past these stationary sensors and complicate the interpretation of turbulence measurements. This project has improved understanding of how to interpret observations of turbulence made from stationary sensors in the presence of waves, and methods to extract information about turbulence from measurements have been developed and tested.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In the first part of the project, we used data from three contrasting field sites to evaluate two major classes of methods for estimating turbulence parameters from measurements beneath waves, one that relies on differencing measurements from adjacent sensors and one that relies on fitting theoretical spectrum shapes to observations. We conclude that spectral fitting methods reduce the impact of measurement noise on estimates of turbulence properties, but existing spectral fitting methods can only be used in situations where wave motion is small relative to currents, which is severely limiting in the coastal ocean. Meanwhile, differencing methods can be used in a wider range of conditions but have limited utility if data is noisy. Therefore, there is strong motivation to (1) refine differencing methods to reduce the effects of noise and (2) extend spectral fitting methods to a larger range of wave conditions.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In the second part of the project we focused on the second of these goals: developing an understanding of the shape of the observed turbulence spectrum for a range of different wave and current conditions with the goal of expanding spectral fitting methods to situations where wave motion is large compared with currents. We approached this problem using both theoretical analyses and data from computer simulations of turbulence. Using both approaches, we illustrated that, for the same turbulence, the turbulent energy appears at higher frequencies in the presence of waves and current than in the presence of just a current. We derived equations that describe the shapes of turbulence spectra under waves and showed that the shapes of these spectra depend on two main parameters, the ratio of wave orbital velocity to current speed and the ratio of wave orbital excursion to largest turbulent eddy size. The spectral shapes derived in the project could be fit to data to estimate turbulence properties when wave motion is large compared with currents.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Thirdly, we applied methods derived and evaluated in the project to field measurements to quantify turbulent mixing in a shallow, wind-driven estuary, the Neuse River Estuary. Turbulence quantities were calculated from the data and their uncertainties were carefully quantified. We then investigated the relationship between mixing rates and the properties of the turbulence, background current (shear), and density stratification. We observed a wide range of turbulence states in the estuary, from growing (shear-dominated) turbulence for which energy was being transferred from the mean flow to the turbulence, to decaying (buoyancy-dominated) turbulence in which eddies were suppressed by stratification, to turbulence not directly affected by shear or stratification. The most efficient mixing appeared to be associated with buoyancy-dominated turbulence. Observed mixing efficiencies agreed reasonably well with relationships that have been proposed previously based solely on numerical simulations. &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The project resulted in some important advances toward better measurement, understanding and prediction of mixing in the coastal ocean. Improved understanding and prediction of turbulent mixing are important for a wide variety of environmmental problems that require assessment of transport of dissolved and particulate materials in natural water bodies.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span style="white-space: pre;">&nbsp;</span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>One graduate student and two undergraduate students were involved in the project and trained in techniques for measuring, analyzing, and understanding turbulence in coastal water bodies. The grant also enabled an early career researcher to initiate her research group. At the end of the grant, work done in the project had appeared in four scientific journal articles, one additional journal article in review, and five conference presentations. Another two papers describing results from the project were in preparation. During the project, public lectures and hands-on demonstrations were performed at two workshops attended by more than 200 K-12 teachers and four summer camps reaching about 350 children.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2016<br>      Modified by: Johanna&nbsp;H&nbsp;Rosman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit   Turbulence controls the mixing of dissolved and particulate materials (e.g., nutrients, contaminants, sediment, larvae) in natural water bodies. Quantifying and predicting transport of these materials therefore requires a good understanding of turbulence that can be used as the basis for models that predict mixing rates. Turbulence measurements from a range of environments and conditions are needed to develop this understanding and test these models. Turbulence is usually understood and quantified by considering its spatial structure; specifically, how the turbulent energy is distributed among eddies with different sizes. In shallow water, sensors are typically placed at fixed locations and eddies are moved past the sensors by the background water motion. Surface waves move eddies backward and forward past these stationary sensors and complicate the interpretation of turbulence measurements. This project has improved understanding of how to interpret observations of turbulence made from stationary sensors in the presence of waves, and methods to extract information about turbulence from measurements have been developed and tested.   In the first part of the project, we used data from three contrasting field sites to evaluate two major classes of methods for estimating turbulence parameters from measurements beneath waves, one that relies on differencing measurements from adjacent sensors and one that relies on fitting theoretical spectrum shapes to observations. We conclude that spectral fitting methods reduce the impact of measurement noise on estimates of turbulence properties, but existing spectral fitting methods can only be used in situations where wave motion is small relative to currents, which is severely limiting in the coastal ocean. Meanwhile, differencing methods can be used in a wider range of conditions but have limited utility if data is noisy. Therefore, there is strong motivation to (1) refine differencing methods to reduce the effects of noise and (2) extend spectral fitting methods to a larger range of wave conditions.   In the second part of the project we focused on the second of these goals: developing an understanding of the shape of the observed turbulence spectrum for a range of different wave and current conditions with the goal of expanding spectral fitting methods to situations where wave motion is large compared with currents. We approached this problem using both theoretical analyses and data from computer simulations of turbulence. Using both approaches, we illustrated that, for the same turbulence, the turbulent energy appears at higher frequencies in the presence of waves and current than in the presence of just a current. We derived equations that describe the shapes of turbulence spectra under waves and showed that the shapes of these spectra depend on two main parameters, the ratio of wave orbital velocity to current speed and the ratio of wave orbital excursion to largest turbulent eddy size. The spectral shapes derived in the project could be fit to data to estimate turbulence properties when wave motion is large compared with currents.   Thirdly, we applied methods derived and evaluated in the project to field measurements to quantify turbulent mixing in a shallow, wind-driven estuary, the Neuse River Estuary. Turbulence quantities were calculated from the data and their uncertainties were carefully quantified. We then investigated the relationship between mixing rates and the properties of the turbulence, background current (shear), and density stratification. We observed a wide range of turbulence states in the estuary, from growing (shear-dominated) turbulence for which energy was being transferred from the mean flow to the turbulence, to decaying (buoyancy-dominated) turbulence in which eddies were suppressed by stratification, to turbulence not directly affected by shear or stratification. The most efficient mixing appeared to be associated with buoyancy-dominated turbulence. Observed mixing efficiencies agreed reasonably well with relationships that have been proposed previously based solely on numerical simulations.        Broader Impacts   The project resulted in some important advances toward better measurement, understanding and prediction of mixing in the coastal ocean. Improved understanding and prediction of turbulent mixing are important for a wide variety of environmmental problems that require assessment of transport of dissolved and particulate materials in natural water bodies.    One graduate student and two undergraduate students were involved in the project and trained in techniques for measuring, analyzing, and understanding turbulence in coastal water bodies. The grant also enabled an early career researcher to initiate her research group. At the end of the grant, work done in the project had appeared in four scientific journal articles, one additional journal article in review, and five conference presentations. Another two papers describing results from the project were in preparation. During the project, public lectures and hands-on demonstrations were performed at two workshops attended by more than 200 K-12 teachers and four summer camps reaching about 350 children.       Last Modified: 10/24/2016       Submitted by: Johanna H Rosman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
