<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Individual Decisions and Emergent Aggregate Patterns: Kin Co-residence among Hadza Hunter-Gatherers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249635.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249635</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Comparative work in cultural anthropology has shown that marriage, kinship systems, and marital residence patterns vary according to the ecological conditions. In this project, Dr. James Holland Jones and Dr. Brian Wood, both at Stanford University, will  investigate the individual and family-level decisions that lead to emergent patterns of kin coresidence among Hadza hunter-gatherers of northern Tanzania. The Hadza are an ideal population with whom to perform this research, because they exhibit a high degree of variation in their residential arrangements, across individuals, families, and seasons. As the last group of hunter-gatherers in east Africa, they also provide a rare chance to examine the demography and residential arrangements of a foraging population. This work will improve the theoretical and methodological foundations for understanding how individual decisions, cascading through a population, lead to aggregate patterns in residential groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will test theoretically grounded hypotheses about the formation of residential groups by examining variation between and within Hadza residential groups.  Their hypotheses address questions of how demographic, economic, and ecological factors contribute to variation in social structure, through both time and space. To test these largely adaptive hypotheses, the investigators will develop rigorous counterfactual demographic null hypotheses and test these using both demographic microsimulation and agent-based models constructed specifically for this project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project also will forge new international research alliances with the University of Dar Es Salaam, and local capacity building through workshops and student training. In cooperation with Tanzanian colleagues, the demographic information being collected for basic science research questions also will be made available to those seek to improve the health and welfare of the Hadza community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1062879</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James H Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhj1@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507212484</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000094389</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5247</Code>
<Text>POST DOC/TRAVEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~129635</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px 'Helvetica Neue Light'} p.p2 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px 'Helvetica Neue Light'; min-height: 15.0px} --> <p class="p1">Kinship and residence are two of the fundamental ways that people organize their societies. The people you live with determine, to a greater or lesser degree, with whom you share food or go to war, or who is likely to introduce them to a future spouse. A long-standing and central debate in anthropology is what the ancestral form of human residential system. Do people generally live with their mother&rsquo;s or their father&rsquo;s kin. Powerful arguments exist for why either would be more advantageous. Living with male kin, for example, may make it easier to organize war parties for raiding or defense, whereas living with maternal kin may increase overall cooperation because the average relatedness of maternal kin is higher than it is for paternal kin.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">Human life histories &ndash; i.e., the age-patterns of the major events of the life cycle &ndash; are unusual in a number of respects. Humans exhibit a pattern of extended post-reproductive survival, short inter-birth intervals, extremely high levels of parental investment, and extensively overlapping periods of parental investment. An important hypothesis that explains many of these unusual features is known as the &lsquo;Grandmother Hypothesis&rsquo; and suggests that it is the investment of older mothers in their daughters&rsquo; offspring that leads to the relatively high fertility of humans compared to our closest primate relatives, the great apes, in conjunction with the massive amounts of economic investment that human parents typically lavish on their offspring. If Grand-maternal investment is central to human reproductive strategies, residence with maternal kin would clearly be favored since elder women&rsquo;s shared residence with their daughters would facilitate direct investment in grandchildren.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The social organization, kinship systems, and residential patterns of hunter-gatherers is of particular interest since humans have spent the majority of our history living as hunter-gatherers. The Hadza of northern Tanzania are the only population in East Africa that continues to rely extensively on hunting and gathering for their subsistence. The Hadza are also extremely flexible in their social organization and residential patterns. In our project, we tested the preferences for residential location while controlling for features such as the size and composition of local populations that are clearly important but have not previously been considered.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">Based on a complete census of the Hadza, we found that husbands are, on average, four years older than their wives. Because of this &ndash; and the fact that men&rsquo;s mortality rates are higher than women&rsquo;s &ndash; women have more living kin on average. As a result, we would expect families to live more frequently with maternal kin simply by default. However, we find that husbands and wives are nearly equally likely to live with their siblings or parents. Our census data show that husbands had fewer living siblings and parents than their wives, but co-resided with such kin at a remarkably similar level as their wives. This pattern suggests either a revealed preference for couple's co-residence with husbands' kin, or more conservatively, an indifference towards matrilocal or patrilocal residence.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2017<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Jones</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Kinship and residence are two of the fundamental ways that people organize their societies. The people you live with determine, to a greater or lesser degree, with whom you share food or go to war, or who is likely to introduce them to a future spouse. A long-standing and central debate in anthropology is what the ancestral form of human residential system. Do people generally live with their mother?s or their father?s kin. Powerful arguments exist for why either would be more advantageous. Living with male kin, for example, may make it easier to organize war parties for raiding or defense, whereas living with maternal kin may increase overall cooperation because the average relatedness of maternal kin is higher than it is for paternal kin.   Human life histories &ndash; i.e., the age-patterns of the major events of the life cycle &ndash; are unusual in a number of respects. Humans exhibit a pattern of extended post-reproductive survival, short inter-birth intervals, extremely high levels of parental investment, and extensively overlapping periods of parental investment. An important hypothesis that explains many of these unusual features is known as the ?Grandmother Hypothesis? and suggests that it is the investment of older mothers in their daughters? offspring that leads to the relatively high fertility of humans compared to our closest primate relatives, the great apes, in conjunction with the massive amounts of economic investment that human parents typically lavish on their offspring. If Grand-maternal investment is central to human reproductive strategies, residence with maternal kin would clearly be favored since elder women?s shared residence with their daughters would facilitate direct investment in grandchildren.   The social organization, kinship systems, and residential patterns of hunter-gatherers is of particular interest since humans have spent the majority of our history living as hunter-gatherers. The Hadza of northern Tanzania are the only population in East Africa that continues to rely extensively on hunting and gathering for their subsistence. The Hadza are also extremely flexible in their social organization and residential patterns. In our project, we tested the preferences for residential location while controlling for features such as the size and composition of local populations that are clearly important but have not previously been considered.   Based on a complete census of the Hadza, we found that husbands are, on average, four years older than their wives. Because of this &ndash; and the fact that men?s mortality rates are higher than women?s &ndash; women have more living kin on average. As a result, we would expect families to live more frequently with maternal kin simply by default. However, we find that husbands and wives are nearly equally likely to live with their siblings or parents. Our census data show that husbands had fewer living siblings and parents than their wives, but co-resided with such kin at a remarkably similar level as their wives. This pattern suggests either a revealed preference for couple's co-residence with husbands' kin, or more conservatively, an indifference towards matrilocal or patrilocal residence.          Last Modified: 10/31/2017       Submitted by: James H Jones]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
