<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Information and Governance: Experimental Evidence from India</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425642.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>425642</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia Kosmopoulou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gkosmopo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>India is the world's largest democracy and home to roughly one-third of the world's poor. However, like many low-income democracies, the quality of social service delivery remains poor, and India typically scores quite high on indices designed to measure corruption by public officials. The goal of the proposed research is to understand the role of information in improving the governance of low-income democracies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We propose two projects that examine these issues.  The first builds on a field experiment conducted during the February 2010 on village council elections in the Indian state of Rajasthan. A randomly selected set of citizens were given different types of information, and the results of the elections were compared. This proposal will support the collection and analysis of follow-up survey data and subsequent decisions by elected officials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second involves a multi-year experiment in Delhi where citizens are again provided with different information on the performance record of local councilors. We will follow citizens and officials for two years, and examine the impact of information on performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will generate rigorous empirical evidence on the ways that providing information can affect both citizens and elected officials behavior. It will provide important new insights into the political economy of development economics and developing economies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1063693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abhijit</FirstName>
<LastName>Banerjee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abhijit V Banerjee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>banerjee@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172538855</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107908</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rohini</FirstName>
<LastName>Pande</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rohini Pande</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rohini.pande@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173845267</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000645827</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL BUREAU OF ECONOMIC RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~425642</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research is to understand the role of information in improving the governance of low-income democracies. We are studying the impact of voter and citizen information campaigns, one in Rajasthan in early 2010 and on in Delhi in 2012. Our research focuses on the impact of information on electoral returns and public service delivery. Information can impact governance outcomes through multiple channels: informed voters choose better candidates to represent them; informed citizens petition their legislators for better services; politicians react to more transparent, high-information environments by providing public service more effectively. Our analysis tests the hypothesis that information matters, and the evaluations are designed to disentangle these channels. In order to measure the effect of each channel on governance outcomes, we collected a variety of data on motivations for political participation (as voters, citizens and candidates), electoral results and quality of public services.</p> <p>Overall, these studies point to the fact that an incumbent&rsquo;s decision to re-run and his or her performance are sensitive to information provision. India has already implemented a strong Right to Information Act; however, there has been less emphasis on pro-active disclosures. A first policy dialogue that we hope to initiate is identifying what forms of pro-active disclosures should be encouraged and what are the appropriate mechanisms for it. Should media play an ongoing role, should non-governmental organisations (NGOs) be deputed to take the message to villages or should government agencies be directly required to make this information publicly available? In March 2013 we had a first meeting on this with our Delhi NGO partner Satark Nagrik Sangathan (SNS) and we intend to continue these dialogues.</p> <p>Second, the Rajasthan study raised important questions on how do we balance broadening representation with ensuring that those with political experience continue to remain politically active. Again, this raises questions on whether information campaigns should be ongoing during entire election period or before elections. Here, it is relevant to note that our results confirm that exposure to female leaders thanks to mandatory reservation significantly improves future electoral prospects of female candidates. They also suggest that short-run gender specific awareness campaigns cannot be substitutes for actual exposure.</p> <p>Our Delhi results show that publishing report cards in the newspaper has positive incentive effects for the politicians, so the key is to move towards potentially publishing mid-term report cards. Having a report card published in the newspaper also increased spending on areas that slumdwellers care about.</p> <p>Our Delhi audits results show that providing information on public facilities has had limited impact. For example, we find that some toilets are closed, but others are opened. However, these changes are not associated with increased quality of public toilets. While the experiment was not designed to examine the influence of forms of delivery, two features of the results are worth noting. First, private contracting alone clearly does not solve the underlying problems of delivery&mdash;the descriptive data from the baseline survey reveals typically low levels of service. Second, politicians appear to have only limited influence over the behaviour of private contractors, at least on some activities. Again, how should public service audits be designed and who should implement them need further discussion.</p> <p>Overall, the findings suggest there is a greater role for information provision in reducing information asymmetries between politicians and their constituents.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/03/2015<br>      Modified by: Rohini&nbsp;Pande</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research is to understand the role of information in improving the governance of low-income democracies. We are studying the impact of voter and citizen information campaigns, one in Rajasthan in early 2010 and on in Delhi in 2012. Our research focuses on the impact of information on electoral returns and public service delivery. Information can impact governance outcomes through multiple channels: informed voters choose better candidates to represent them; informed citizens petition their legislators for better services; politicians react to more transparent, high-information environments by providing public service more effectively. Our analysis tests the hypothesis that information matters, and the evaluations are designed to disentangle these channels. In order to measure the effect of each channel on governance outcomes, we collected a variety of data on motivations for political participation (as voters, citizens and candidates), electoral results and quality of public services.  Overall, these studies point to the fact that an incumbentÆs decision to re-run and his or her performance are sensitive to information provision. India has already implemented a strong Right to Information Act; however, there has been less emphasis on pro-active disclosures. A first policy dialogue that we hope to initiate is identifying what forms of pro-active disclosures should be encouraged and what are the appropriate mechanisms for it. Should media play an ongoing role, should non-governmental organisations (NGOs) be deputed to take the message to villages or should government agencies be directly required to make this information publicly available? In March 2013 we had a first meeting on this with our Delhi NGO partner Satark Nagrik Sangathan (SNS) and we intend to continue these dialogues.  Second, the Rajasthan study raised important questions on how do we balance broadening representation with ensuring that those with political experience continue to remain politically active. Again, this raises questions on whether information campaigns should be ongoing during entire election period or before elections. Here, it is relevant to note that our results confirm that exposure to female leaders thanks to mandatory reservation significantly improves future electoral prospects of female candidates. They also suggest that short-run gender specific awareness campaigns cannot be substitutes for actual exposure.  Our Delhi results show that publishing report cards in the newspaper has positive incentive effects for the politicians, so the key is to move towards potentially publishing mid-term report cards. Having a report card published in the newspaper also increased spending on areas that slumdwellers care about.  Our Delhi audits results show that providing information on public facilities has had limited impact. For example, we find that some toilets are closed, but others are opened. However, these changes are not associated with increased quality of public toilets. While the experiment was not designed to examine the influence of forms of delivery, two features of the results are worth noting. First, private contracting alone clearly does not solve the underlying problems of delivery&mdash;the descriptive data from the baseline survey reveals typically low levels of service. Second, politicians appear to have only limited influence over the behaviour of private contractors, at least on some activities. Again, how should public service audits be designed and who should implement them need further discussion.  Overall, the findings suggest there is a greater role for information provision in reducing information asymmetries between politicians and their constituents.       Last Modified: 06/03/2015       Submitted by: Rohini Pande]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
