<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRES: U.S.-India Summer Research Experience in Nondestructive Evaluation Technologies for Michigan State University Students at the Indian Institute of Technology-Madras, Chennai.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>145856.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>145856</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdudka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>OISE-1064641&lt;br/&gt;Lalita Udpa  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This International Research Experience for Students (IRES) award to US PI Lalita Udpa, Michigan State University (MSU) is for international research collaborations in electrical, computer, and mechanical engineering with Professors Kavitha Arunachalam and Krishnan Balasubramaniam, Indian Institute of Technology-Madras (IITM), Chennai, India.  The research focuses on the assessment of infrastructure integrity or Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) using cutting-edge technologies in Non-Destructive Evaluation (NDE).  The IITM houses an NDE Center with state-of-the art facilities for research using advanced ultrasonic, electro-magnetic, radiography, thermal and optical tools that will be available to MSU graduate and undergraduate students to conduct hypotheses-driven, multidisciplinary research in NDE.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NDE techniques are used to inspect and assess the structural integrity of a variety of systems such as nuclear power plants, natural gas pipelines, aircraft, bridges, dams and other segments of the civilian and defense infrastructure.  As many of these are known to have far exceeded their designed lifetime, there is increasing demand for reliable and accurate assessments of their structural integrity.  Monitoring is accomplished using a variety of modalities that rely on different energy sources such as electromagnetic, ultrasound, thermal, and x-ray.  The underlying physics of each inspection technology is diverse as are the methods for analyzing the data.   Consequently, NDE provides a rich area for student research that will focus on novel developments in computational modeling, signal processing, machine learning algorithms for solving the inverse problem, and development of novel NDE sensors and systems.  Projects in multiple NDE modalities of mutual interest to MSU and IITM will be selected with the goal of developing new technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award offers opportunities for US students to work in an international research environment in collaboration with leading Indian scientists.  They will also have access to the research laboratories of General Electric and General Motors in Bangalore, where they will learn about   global operations of US companies and the advantages of international collaboration.  This project will attract high caliber domestic students who will be encouraged to do graduate studies and doctoral degrees.  Special outreach will be made to recruit minority and underrepresented students thru MSU and national programs.  A number of student theses and dissertations are anticipated from these projects plus numerous journal articles and joint presentations at scientific meetings and conferences.  This experience will expand students? academic horizons and encourage engagement in global collaboration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1064641</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lalita</FirstName>
<LastName>Udpa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lalita Udpa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>udpal@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173559261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417718</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Satish</FirstName>
<LastName>Udpa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Satish S Udpa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>udpa@vpfo.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173555014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>McGough</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert J McGough</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcgough@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174323333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000353352</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5919</Code>
<Text>INDIA (COOPERATIVE SCIENCE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7639</Code>
<Text>IRES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~145856</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nondestructive Evaluation (NDE) is an important research area that comprises development of technologies and methodologies for assessing the structural integrity of critical materials, components and structures. Research in NDE typically focuses on three primary areas, namely, design and development of new sensors and systems, computational modeling for solving the forward problem and development of signal processing and data analysis algorithms for solving the inverse problem. The IRES exploited the wealth of research topics and projects in the rich and multidisciplinary area of NDE.</p> <p>Five different groups of undergraduate and graduate students were selected from a pool of applicants from Michigan State University, University of Colorado, Denver, Iowa State University and Georgia Tech. A total of 15 undergraduate and 8 graduate students including 25% from underrepresented groups participated in the internship. These students spent around 7 weeks in June and July at the Center for Nondestructive Evaluation in Indian Institute of Technology &ndash; Madras (IIT-M) in Chennai, India.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The research and educational objectives<strong> </strong>of the IRES program were accomplished by means of the work conducted in the three broad projects on microwave, x-ray and ultrasonic guided wave technologies with application to inspection of composites. The projects represented novel contributions that addressed major challenges in the field of NDE. Consequently, the research resulted in several joint papers presented by the students at conferences in NDE and also published in peer reviewed journals. These papers are listed below.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Joint Publications</strong></p> <ol> <li>Panda R.S., Karpenko O., Udpa L., Haq, M., Rajagopal P. and Balasubramaniam K., &ldquo;Rapid Non-Contact Inspection of Ailerons using Air-Coupled Ultrasound&rdquo;, in Review of Progress in Quantitative Non-Destructive Evaluation,&nbsp;AIP Proceedings, AIP Conf. Proc.&nbsp;1706, 080002&nbsp;(2016), <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.4940534">http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.4940534</a></li> <li>Dib, G., J. Padiyar, J. Xin, L. Udpa, and K. Balasubramaniam. "High performance wireless sensors system for structural health monitoring." In AIP Conference Proceedings, vol. 1430, p. 1583. 2012.</li> <li>G. Dib, L. Mhamdi, T. Khan, L. Udpa, N. Lajnef, J.W. Hong, S. Udpa1, P. Ramuhalli, and K. Balasubramaniam,&rdquo; Wireless Sensors System for Continuous Monitoring &ldquo;, AIP Conf. Proc. 1335, pp. 1758-1765; Also appears in Review of Progress in QNDE, Vol. 30A, July 2011</li> <li>S. Reyes?Rodr&iacute;guez, C. Bardel, N. Lei. P. Roy, L. Udpa, S. S. Udpa, K. Arunachalam, K. Balasubramaniam, and C. V. Krishnamurthy &ldquo;Solution of Inverse Problem Using Time Reversal Techniques,&rdquo; AIP Conf. Proc. 1335, pp. 623-630, Also appears in Review of Progress in QNDE, Vol. 30A, July 2011</li> <li>G. Dib, J. Padiyar, L. Mhamdi, N. Lajnef, T. Khan. J. Hong, L. Udpa,&nbsp; K. Balasubramaniam, &ldquo;High Performance Wireless Sensor System for Structural Health Monitoring&rdquo;, Minerals and Materials Society conference, TMS2011, San Diego, CA.</li> </ol> <ol> <li>Saikiran N.T., David D.R., Karpenko O.,      Koricho E.G., Khomenko A., Haq M., <strong>Udpa      L</strong>., Udpa S., Rajagopal P., and Balasubramaniam K., &ldquo;Self-Sensing      Characteristics of Carbon Fiber Reinforced Composites using Electrical      Resistance Measurements and Guided Waves,&rdquo; Abstracts of 15th Annual      Society of Plastic Engineers (SPE) and Automotive Composites Conference      &amp; Exhibition (ACCE), 9-11 September 2015, Novi, MI, USA, 2015, (Best      poster award, 2nd place)</li> <li>David D.R., Saikiran N.T., Karpenko O.,      Koricho E.G., Khomenko A., Haq M., <strong>Udpa      L.</strong>, Udpa S., Rajagopal P., and Balasubramaniam K., &ldquo;Robust, Rapid      Measurements of Interlaminar Crack Growth in Composites,&rdquo; Abstracts of      15th Annual Society of Plastic Engineers (SPE) and Automotive Composites Conference &amp;      Exhibition (ACCE), 9-11 September 2015, Novi, MI, USA, (2015).</li> </ol> <p>Besides the considerable research productivity of this partnership between MSU and IIT-M, a major outcome of this project is that the global research experience further encouraged undergraduate students to pursue graduate program and stay involved in research. Around 50% of the undergraduate students who participated in the internship are now pursuing graduate studies. All 8 graduate students who participated in the program continue to be engaged in research and 7 of them are looking into a career in Academia. This was one of the missions of the IRES program and we can certainly say that that project achieved its goals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Lalita&nbsp;Udpa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495117614236_GroupPicture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495117614236_GroupPicture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Group of Interns at IIT-M"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495117614236_GroupPicture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Group of Interns at IIT-M"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ryan Lattrell ? Junior, Electrical engineering, MSU Jarvis Hill ? Ph.D. student, Electrical Engineering, University of Colorado, DenverJanardhan Padiyar  -Ph.D. student, IIT-MCharles Maines ? Senior, Mechanical Engineering, MSUFlorian Cherdron ? Junior, Mechanical Engineering, MSU</div> <div class="imageCredit">Interns in the NDE Lab at the Indian Institute of Technology ?Madras, in Chennai, India</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lalita&nbsp;Udpa</div> <div class="imageTitle">Group of Interns at IIT-M</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495117884744_JarvisHill--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495117884744_JarvisHill--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF IRES participant at IIT-M"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495117884744_JarvisHill--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF IRES participant at IIT-M"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Jarvis Hill  traveled to IIT-M on the internship and worked with Professors at IIT-M on computational model-based studies for optimizing a microwave imaging system</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jarvis Hill, MS student from University of Colorado, Denver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lalita&nbsp;Udpa</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF IRES participant at IIT-M</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495118015432_RyanLattrell--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495118015432_RyanLattrell--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF IRES student at IIT-M"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1064641/1064641_10088444_1495118015432_RyanLattrell--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF IRES student at IIT-M"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ryan Lattrell, Undergraduate student in Electrical Engineering from MSU,  working on a wireless ultrasonic sensor node for Structural Health monitoring applications</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan Lattrell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lalita&nbsp;Udpa</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF IRES student at IIT-M</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nondestructive Evaluation (NDE) is an important research area that comprises development of technologies and methodologies for assessing the structural integrity of critical materials, components and structures. Research in NDE typically focuses on three primary areas, namely, design and development of new sensors and systems, computational modeling for solving the forward problem and development of signal processing and data analysis algorithms for solving the inverse problem. The IRES exploited the wealth of research topics and projects in the rich and multidisciplinary area of NDE.  Five different groups of undergraduate and graduate students were selected from a pool of applicants from Michigan State University, University of Colorado, Denver, Iowa State University and Georgia Tech. A total of 15 undergraduate and 8 graduate students including 25% from underrepresented groups participated in the internship. These students spent around 7 weeks in June and July at the Center for Nondestructive Evaluation in Indian Institute of Technology &ndash; Madras (IIT-M) in Chennai, India.     The research and educational objectives of the IRES program were accomplished by means of the work conducted in the three broad projects on microwave, x-ray and ultrasonic guided wave technologies with application to inspection of composites. The projects represented novel contributions that addressed major challenges in the field of NDE. Consequently, the research resulted in several joint papers presented by the students at conferences in NDE and also published in peer reviewed journals. These papers are listed below.     Joint Publications  Panda R.S., Karpenko O., Udpa L., Haq, M., Rajagopal P. and Balasubramaniam K., "Rapid Non-Contact Inspection of Ailerons using Air-Coupled Ultrasound", in Review of Progress in Quantitative Non-Destructive Evaluation, AIP Proceedings, AIP Conf. Proc. 1706, 080002 (2016), http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.4940534 Dib, G., J. Padiyar, J. Xin, L. Udpa, and K. Balasubramaniam. "High performance wireless sensors system for structural health monitoring." In AIP Conference Proceedings, vol. 1430, p. 1583. 2012. G. Dib, L. Mhamdi, T. Khan, L. Udpa, N. Lajnef, J.W. Hong, S. Udpa1, P. Ramuhalli, and K. Balasubramaniam," Wireless Sensors System for Continuous Monitoring ", AIP Conf. Proc. 1335, pp. 1758-1765; Also appears in Review of Progress in QNDE, Vol. 30A, July 2011 S. Reyes?Rodr&iacute;guez, C. Bardel, N. Lei. P. Roy, L. Udpa, S. S. Udpa, K. Arunachalam, K. Balasubramaniam, and C. V. Krishnamurthy "Solution of Inverse Problem Using Time Reversal Techniques," AIP Conf. Proc. 1335, pp. 623-630, Also appears in Review of Progress in QNDE, Vol. 30A, July 2011 G. Dib, J. Padiyar, L. Mhamdi, N. Lajnef, T. Khan. J. Hong, L. Udpa,  K. Balasubramaniam, "High Performance Wireless Sensor System for Structural Health Monitoring", Minerals and Materials Society conference, TMS2011, San Diego, CA.   Saikiran N.T., David D.R., Karpenko O.,      Koricho E.G., Khomenko A., Haq M., Udpa      L., Udpa S., Rajagopal P., and Balasubramaniam K., "Self-Sensing      Characteristics of Carbon Fiber Reinforced Composites using Electrical      Resistance Measurements and Guided Waves," Abstracts of 15th Annual      Society of Plastic Engineers (SPE) and Automotive Composites Conference      &amp; Exhibition (ACCE), 9-11 September 2015, Novi, MI, USA, 2015, (Best      poster award, 2nd place) David D.R., Saikiran N.T., Karpenko O.,      Koricho E.G., Khomenko A., Haq M., Udpa      L., Udpa S., Rajagopal P., and Balasubramaniam K., "Robust, Rapid      Measurements of Interlaminar Crack Growth in Composites," Abstracts of      15th Annual Society of Plastic Engineers (SPE) and Automotive Composites Conference &amp;      Exhibition (ACCE), 9-11 September 2015, Novi, MI, USA, (2015).   Besides the considerable research productivity of this partnership between MSU and IIT-M, a major outcome of this project is that the global research experience further encouraged undergraduate students to pursue graduate program and stay involved in research. Around 50% of the undergraduate students who participated in the internship are now pursuing graduate studies. All 8 graduate students who participated in the program continue to be engaged in research and 7 of them are looking into a career in Academia. This was one of the missions of the IRES program and we can certainly say that that project achieved its goals.          Last Modified: 05/18/2017       Submitted by: Lalita Udpa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
