<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Microstructure and Rheology of Highly-concentrated Emulsions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>338067.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>338067</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Award: 1064132&lt;br/&gt;PI: Zinchenko&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Emulsion flows occur in polymer blending, mass-transfer equipment, food and beverage processing, oil recovery and other applications. Describing these flows is made difficult by complex rheological features of the emulsions (drop deformation and interactions, surfactant elasticity, etc.). The problem is even more difficult when the flow is through narrow channels or a porous medium such as a packed bed. &lt;br/&gt;This project is focused on the development of a comprehensive modeling strategy for the rheology of highly-concentrated emulsions based on rigorous microstructural dynamical simulations. Realistic features affecting the rheological behavior are included, such as an arbitrary type of macroscopic flow, three-dimensionality, random arrangement, drop deformation, hydrodynamical interactions, the presence of surfactants, and the possibility of dynamical phase transition to a partially-ordered state. The specific tasks of the project are:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(i) Prediction of the rheology of concentrated emulsions in extensional flows. A new algorithm for many drops is based on a combination of highly-efficient, 3D multipole-accelerated boundary-integral tools with periodic conditions to predict the average stress tensor in planar-extensional flows and its dependence on drop volume fraction, deformability and viscosity ratio. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;(ii)  Determination of the effect of surfactants on the emulsion rheology. A model of an insoluble surfactant is incorporated into 3D simulations for many deformable drops to study the additional effect of surfactant elasticity on the emulsion rheology. At high drop volume fractions, a prominent effect of surfactants is expected near the jamming limit, where the drops become less deformable and the role of interactions and surface mobility greatly increases. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(iii) Construction of a constitutive equation for a concentrated emulsion. A novel constitutive model from this work is based on matching a generalized Oldroyd-type rheological equation to shear and planar-extension simulations. The resulting constitutive equation, with parameters based exclusively on microstructural modeling,  incorporates the effects of drop volume fraction, deformability, viscosity ratio and surfactant elasticity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(iv) Simulations of emulsion flow through a packed bed. The microstructure-based constitutive equations are employed in a novel, multipole-accelerated boundary-integral algorithm to study 3D viscoelastic flow of a concentrated emulsion through a randomly packed bed. When the drops are comparable in size with the particles, so that the drop and continuous phases have different permeabilities and must be treated separately, a complementary, fully-microstructural approach is used for comprehensive modeling based on multidrop-multiparticle simulations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The project provides substantially new information about the rheology of realistic, concentrated emulsions obtained by rigorous simulations from first principles. The new approach to constitutive modeling, not limited to emulsions, is expected to apply for broad classes of flows. The novel method for emulsion flow through packed beds bridges emulsion rheology and non-Newtonian hydrodynamics; the algorithm for the solution is not be limited to emulsions and can accommodate any constitutive equation of differential type. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: An important feature of the project is the development of interactive eduational modules to provide animations for multiphase flow through porous media. The web-based modules can be distributed to K-12 students via the TeachEngineering digital library and via NSF Graduate K-12 Fellows to the University of Colorado and local schools, in partnership with the Integrated Teaching and Learning Program at the University of Colorado. The project also provides training for at least one graduate student and three undergraduates through the research and module work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1064132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert H Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.davis@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034927314</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000466005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Zinchenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Z Zinchenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alexander.zinchenko@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034927471</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000415948</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>056E</Code>
<Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~116761</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~109363</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~111943</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Emulsions are composed of drops or capsules of one liquid dispersed in a second liquid. They are encountered in a variety of natural and industrial applications, including enhanced oil recovery, food and pharmaceutical processing, polymer blending, and blood flow. This project developed computer simulations of emulsion flows.</p> <p>&nbsp;A key result is the determination of coefficients in a constitutive equation that governs the rheological behavior of emulsions so that it can be used to model complex flows in practice. Boundary-integral simulations of single drops in shear and extensional flows were used to determine these coefficients for dilute emulsions. A visco-elastic constitutive equation was used, as emulsions experience viscous resistance to flow, and they also exhibit elastic recoil after the flow is turned off &ndash; due to interfacial tension that causes the deformed drops to relax back to spherical shape. The novel approach has also been extended to suspensions of small, nonspherical particles.</p> <p>A second key outcome is new understanding of the flow behavior of concentrated emulsions. Here, multipole-accelerated boundary-integral simulations of 100 or more deformable emulsion drops in a periodic box were performed to determine the desired rheological functions and coefficients. This work was then extended to emulsions containing surfactants, which are large molecules that reside on the drop interfaces and tend to stabilize the drops against coalescence as well as modify the drop deformation and flow behavior.</p> <p>&nbsp;A third key outcome is a novel description of emulsion flow through packed beds or other porous media. This work is particularly important for enhanced-oil recovery, catalytic packed-bed reactors, and multiphase contactors. In addition to determining the relationship between flow rate and pressure drop for both the drop phase and the surrounding fluid, conditions for drop trapping in the pores as well as drop breakup were identified.</p> <p>&nbsp;Finally, an education module was developed to illustrate the concept of drop trapping within pores and drop squeezing through the pores. It is based on computer simulations that allow the user to vary the drop and pore sizes, as well as the interfacial tension, fluid viscosity, and flow rate to demonstrate when trapping will occur and when squeezing will occur.</p> <p>The primary intellectual merit of this work is that, for the first time, the novel approach provides a closed-form expression for a constitutive equation governing emulsion flows, with the coefficients found by exact computer simulations. The broader impacts include student training, dissemination of the findings at conferences and in journals, and availability of the educational module for student use. The resulting products include new simulation software, graphs of the coefficients in the constitutive equation, and a website containing the educational model (<a href="http://www.dropsimulation.com">www.dropsimulation.com</a>).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Zinchenko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1064132/1064132_10080531_1438145787534_Figab--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1064132/1064132_10080531_1438145787534_Figab--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Emulsion flow through a granular material with multiple drop breakup"><img src="/po...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Emulsions are composed of drops or capsules of one liquid dispersed in a second liquid. They are encountered in a variety of natural and industrial applications, including enhanced oil recovery, food and pharmaceutical processing, polymer blending, and blood flow. This project developed computer simulations of emulsion flows.   A key result is the determination of coefficients in a constitutive equation that governs the rheological behavior of emulsions so that it can be used to model complex flows in practice. Boundary-integral simulations of single drops in shear and extensional flows were used to determine these coefficients for dilute emulsions. A visco-elastic constitutive equation was used, as emulsions experience viscous resistance to flow, and they also exhibit elastic recoil after the flow is turned off &ndash; due to interfacial tension that causes the deformed drops to relax back to spherical shape. The novel approach has also been extended to suspensions of small, nonspherical particles.  A second key outcome is new understanding of the flow behavior of concentrated emulsions. Here, multipole-accelerated boundary-integral simulations of 100 or more deformable emulsion drops in a periodic box were performed to determine the desired rheological functions and coefficients. This work was then extended to emulsions containing surfactants, which are large molecules that reside on the drop interfaces and tend to stabilize the drops against coalescence as well as modify the drop deformation and flow behavior.   A third key outcome is a novel description of emulsion flow through packed beds or other porous media. This work is particularly important for enhanced-oil recovery, catalytic packed-bed reactors, and multiphase contactors. In addition to determining the relationship between flow rate and pressure drop for both the drop phase and the surrounding fluid, conditions for drop trapping in the pores as well as drop breakup were identified.   Finally, an education module was developed to illustrate the concept of drop trapping within pores and drop squeezing through the pores. It is based on computer simulations that allow the user to vary the drop and pore sizes, as well as the interfacial tension, fluid viscosity, and flow rate to demonstrate when trapping will occur and when squeezing will occur.  The primary intellectual merit of this work is that, for the first time, the novel approach provides a closed-form expression for a constitutive equation governing emulsion flows, with the coefficients found by exact computer simulations. The broader impacts include student training, dissemination of the findings at conferences and in journals, and availability of the educational module for student use. The resulting products include new simulation software, graphs of the coefficients in the constitutive equation, and a website containing the educational model (www.dropsimulation.com).       Last Modified: 07/29/2015       Submitted by: Alexander Z Zinchenko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
