<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>HCC: Medium: Hardware and Software Architectures for Next-Generation Mobile Platforms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>698941.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>698941</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>tao li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In his visionary 1991 article "The Computer for the 21st Century", Mark Weiser described a world in which people interact with smart information appliances, and where one would routinely have over a hundred such devices per room. He also described some of the key technologies needed to realize this vision, including devices where "a small battery will provide several days of continuous use." Since then, many of Weiser's predictions about the advent of ubiquitous computing have come to pass or have been exceeded. The capabilities of modern computing systems have far exceeded the requirements for Weiser's vision in terms of capacity and performance.&lt;br/&gt;However, truly ubiquitous computing still eludes us because the combination of increasing energy requirements and (relatively) slow progress in battery technology limits the lifetime of battery-powered devices. The goal of this project is to create hardware and software solutions to enable long-lifetime mobile information appliances.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The emergence of non-volatile memory technologies (e.g. magnetic random access memory) and bi-stable displays (e.g. e-Ink) significantly alter the energy signature of mobile devices by enabling near-zero quiescent power for the main memory and display. This project alters the energy signature for the microprocessor by tailoring its performance and energy to the requirements of typical user interaction patterns in the information appliance context. These patterns include viewing/reading the display (no computation), interacting with the display (minimal computation), and requesting a task that requires significant computation such as rendering a new screen. The processor architecture operates in high-performance mode with an energy signature resembling a modern embedded processor, low performance mode with an energy signature resembling a microcontroller, and ultra low power idle mode with extremely fast switching times between the different modes so as to provide the illusion of a single high-performance processor. This project creates the software interfaces necessary to exploit the low power properties of the new microprocessor thus simplifying application development for low power information appliances. The final goal of the project is to demonstrate the new concepts in a prototype e-book reader that is also a hardware testbed for the evaluation of the energy requirements of mobile information appliances.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will create enabling technologies for the development of mobile computing devices whose battery life can be measured in months, rather than days. The results of this project will be disseminated via research publications, by making a prototype mobile platform available to the research community, and by training undergraduate and graduate students in the design and implementation of energy-efficient mobile appliances.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the billions of mobile devices currently in use worldwide, a significant reduction in the energy requirements for mobile platforms could lead to a reduction in the energy consumed by the world's information technology infrastructure. Mobile devices that do not need to be re-charged on a daily basis would help us truly realize Mark Weiser's vision of ubiquitous computing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1065307</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Albonesi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David H Albonesi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>albonesi@csl.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072545473</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000108311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajit</FirstName>
<LastName>Manohar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajit Manohar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rajit.manohar@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034327040</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487009</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francois</FirstName>
<LastName>Guimbretiere</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francois V Guimbretiere</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>francois@cs.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555925</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000177407</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7941</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~698941</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our world is being increasingly instrumented with electronic devices that include some combination of computing, communication, sensing, and actuation. Mobile platforms like smartphones are ubiquitous. However, the power consumption of these battery-powered devices imposes a limit on their utility, since device lifetime is a major consideration in any mobile system. Recent progress in display technology and memory technology provide a path toward significant reduction in the power consumption of those two aspects of mobile platforms.</p> <p>The goal of this research was to examine the key contributors to power consumption in mobile platforms in the context of this recent progress in display and memory technology, and to develop solution on the hardware and software side that enable long-lifetime mobile systems. One of the key aspects of our research was to conduct user studies to understand how users interact with mobile platforms, and use those results to guide the design of hardware and software that minimizes the power consumption of the system. The work has resulted in a number of studies and new ideas for processor design that advance the field of mobile processor development, especially in the context where user interactions might be guided by modern deep learning techniques for facial recognition or speech recognition as other interaction modalities. The work has brought together researchers in three different areas, including chip/VLSI design, computer architecture, and human-computer interaction. These three components have provided a solid foundation for conducting this research.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: The proposed work researched new principles and techniques for mobile processor design driven by typical user interaction modalities. The user-focused perspective has led to some new research directions in the space of mobile processor design, and more recently in ideas for adaptive arithmetic for data-intensive computations such as face detection and recognition. The work has been extensively published and enhances the understanding of hardware design for interactive mobile systems.</p> <p>Broader Impact: The systems and techniques developed in the course of this research can benefit a significant number of important applications, since mobile platforms are ubiquitous in modern society. The work has had a significant educational component, in that it has involved synergistic development, combining different domains of knowledge and thus training the graduate students involved in interdisciplinary work, leading to new, creative solutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Key Words: Mobile computing; e-book readers; hybrid processor architecture; low power computing; asynchronous computing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Rajit&nbsp;Manohar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our world is being increasingly instrumented with electronic devices that include some combination of computing, communication, sensing, and actuation. Mobile platforms like smartphones are ubiquitous. However, the power consumption of these battery-powered devices imposes a limit on their utility, since device lifetime is a major consideration in any mobile system. Recent progress in display technology and memory technology provide a path toward significant reduction in the power consumption of those two aspects of mobile platforms.  The goal of this research was to examine the key contributors to power consumption in mobile platforms in the context of this recent progress in display and memory technology, and to develop solution on the hardware and software side that enable long-lifetime mobile systems. One of the key aspects of our research was to conduct user studies to understand how users interact with mobile platforms, and use those results to guide the design of hardware and software that minimizes the power consumption of the system. The work has resulted in a number of studies and new ideas for processor design that advance the field of mobile processor development, especially in the context where user interactions might be guided by modern deep learning techniques for facial recognition or speech recognition as other interaction modalities. The work has brought together researchers in three different areas, including chip/VLSI design, computer architecture, and human-computer interaction. These three components have provided a solid foundation for conducting this research.  Intellectual Merit: The proposed work researched new principles and techniques for mobile processor design driven by typical user interaction modalities. The user-focused perspective has led to some new research directions in the space of mobile processor design, and more recently in ideas for adaptive arithmetic for data-intensive computations such as face detection and recognition. The work has been extensively published and enhances the understanding of hardware design for interactive mobile systems.  Broader Impact: The systems and techniques developed in the course of this research can benefit a significant number of important applications, since mobile platforms are ubiquitous in modern society. The work has had a significant educational component, in that it has involved synergistic development, combining different domains of knowledge and thus training the graduate students involved in interdisciplinary work, leading to new, creative solutions.     Key Words: Mobile computing; e-book readers; hybrid processor architecture; low power computing; asynchronous computing.                Last Modified: 09/29/2017       Submitted by: Rajit Manohar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
