<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Development of song culture in zebra finches - vocal and sensory changes over generations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/10/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>330000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjawor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927887</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Culture consists of traits transmitted through social learning. One example for social learning is the acquisition of song by songbirds: During a sensitive period early in life, young males learn to imitate their father's song. Songbirds provide tractable models of culture: Members of a species show individual variation in song, and geographically separated groups have local song dialects, i.e., a local song culture. How does song culture develop over multiple generations? In zebra finches, birds kept isolated during the sensitive period develop an abnormal (isolate) song. Interestingly, in an isolated colony founded by an isolate, "normal" songs with species-typical features emerge within 3-4 generations, due to biased imitation that gradually transforms the isolate song into the species-typical song. Understanding how song develops in individual birds and how song culture develops in a community might require knowledge not only about the vocal, but also about the sensory-perceptual development across generations, as well as the social interactions which accompany it. This project is a combined study of social, vocal, and sensory aspects of song development. The investigators will design controlled social environments to examine dynamically how song is acquired and how song culture emerges. They will combine the continuous analysis of vocal changes and social interactions with non-invasive functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) of the brain to investigate how auditory brain responses to songs develop, and how they drive cultural changes. Moreover, these researchers will test if developmental changes in brain architecture correlate with observed vocal and/or sensory changes using diffusion tensor imaging (DTI). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will provide a bridge between studies of vocal and sensory changes and ethology studies of cultural changes in vocal communication.  This project will contribute to the training of three graduate students, and provide scientific education and research training to undergraduate students as well as middle and high school students in the community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1065678</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Santosh</FirstName>
<LastName>Helekar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Santosh A Helekar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sahelekar@tmhs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7134414389</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000077037</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Methodist Hospital Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770302703</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7134417885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6565 Fannin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MGJ4-024]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>185641052</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>METHODIST HOSPITAL, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>074172719</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Methodist Hospital Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770302703</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6565 Fannin]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~330000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Learned birdsong produced by songbirds such as zebra finches is recognized as a model of speech. Studies on the brain mechanisms of vocal learning in these birds therefore offer insights into the development of speech and language, as well as into speech motor control disorders such as developmental stuttering. An important focus of these studies is to understand how experience causes the brain to develop and change as it relates to song learning, perception and production. The just completed project undertaken by my laboratory in a joint effort with the laboratories of Ofer Tchernichovski at Hunter College and Henning Voss at Weill Medical College of Cornell University was aimed at studying how social interactions affected the learning of song by juvenile zebra finches from their adult tutors, and how the development of the ability of the brain to process vocal sounds impacts the development of songs produced by these birds. My laboratory contributed to this effort by helping in developing methods and procedures to detect responses to vocal sounds in different areas of the brain, and the changes that occur in these responses over short periods of time. One method developed for this purpose was functional magnetic resonance imaging in awake sedated or anesthetized birds. The second method called Balloon Bird recording involved recording of the electrical activity of small groups of nerve cells in different brain areas, wirelessly, while the bird was able to move about or perch comfortably. This was achieved by lightening the wireless transmitter on its head with a helium balloon attached to it.</p> <p>The first method allows us to track non-invasively how the brain of an individual bird processes songs over short or long periods of time. Our brain imaging experiments with this method showed that in young zebra finches the highest detectable levels of neuronal activation in response to birdsong sounds were seen in the main auditory areas of the brain, and these neuronal responses became more intense over short periods of time after repeated exposure to these sounds. The increase in responses was more pronounced when a bird was exposed to a new song. It was further accentuated if the song contained abnormal repetitions of a song component. We found that the brain responses to tutor&rsquo;s song were significantly weaker in birds (repeater birds) producing the latter type of abnormal songs that were superficially similar to stuttered speech. We also found that the strength of the response to tutor&rsquo;s song in repeater birds correlated with the degree of similarity of this song to the bird&rsquo;s own song. This led to the hypothesis that the weakness in response to the tutor&rsquo;s song was due to a difference in the ability of the brains of these repeater birds to undergo a change in responsiveness after repeated exposure to birdsong sounds. However, the results of completed experiments in five repeater birds did not confirm this hypothesis.</p> <p>The second method enabled us to record responses (called local field potentials) of groups of nerve cells in 4 different areas of the brain in an awake bird, to not only the sounds produced by a bird, but also to videos of a bird producing these sounds. The findings of these experiments lead us to conclude that one of these areas, called entopallium, might be a site of integration of sound and visual image information, and that the responses to sounds in two auditory areas are modified by visual information. The differences between sounds of bird calls appear to be reflected in the shapes of the responses and their spatial pattern of distribution across the different brain areas.</p> <p>In addition to these experiments, we also devised and constructed a setup to automatically measure the perceptual preferences of songbirds to sounds with different perceived features and to bird calls with contrasting significance from...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Learned birdsong produced by songbirds such as zebra finches is recognized as a model of speech. Studies on the brain mechanisms of vocal learning in these birds therefore offer insights into the development of speech and language, as well as into speech motor control disorders such as developmental stuttering. An important focus of these studies is to understand how experience causes the brain to develop and change as it relates to song learning, perception and production. The just completed project undertaken by my laboratory in a joint effort with the laboratories of Ofer Tchernichovski at Hunter College and Henning Voss at Weill Medical College of Cornell University was aimed at studying how social interactions affected the learning of song by juvenile zebra finches from their adult tutors, and how the development of the ability of the brain to process vocal sounds impacts the development of songs produced by these birds. My laboratory contributed to this effort by helping in developing methods and procedures to detect responses to vocal sounds in different areas of the brain, and the changes that occur in these responses over short periods of time. One method developed for this purpose was functional magnetic resonance imaging in awake sedated or anesthetized birds. The second method called Balloon Bird recording involved recording of the electrical activity of small groups of nerve cells in different brain areas, wirelessly, while the bird was able to move about or perch comfortably. This was achieved by lightening the wireless transmitter on its head with a helium balloon attached to it.  The first method allows us to track non-invasively how the brain of an individual bird processes songs over short or long periods of time. Our brain imaging experiments with this method showed that in young zebra finches the highest detectable levels of neuronal activation in response to birdsong sounds were seen in the main auditory areas of the brain, and these neuronal responses became more intense over short periods of time after repeated exposure to these sounds. The increase in responses was more pronounced when a bird was exposed to a new song. It was further accentuated if the song contained abnormal repetitions of a song component. We found that the brain responses to tutorÆs song were significantly weaker in birds (repeater birds) producing the latter type of abnormal songs that were superficially similar to stuttered speech. We also found that the strength of the response to tutorÆs song in repeater birds correlated with the degree of similarity of this song to the birdÆs own song. This led to the hypothesis that the weakness in response to the tutorÆs song was due to a difference in the ability of the brains of these repeater birds to undergo a change in responsiveness after repeated exposure to birdsong sounds. However, the results of completed experiments in five repeater birds did not confirm this hypothesis.  The second method enabled us to record responses (called local field potentials) of groups of nerve cells in 4 different areas of the brain in an awake bird, to not only the sounds produced by a bird, but also to videos of a bird producing these sounds. The findings of these experiments lead us to conclude that one of these areas, called entopallium, might be a site of integration of sound and visual image information, and that the responses to sounds in two auditory areas are modified by visual information. The differences between sounds of bird calls appear to be reflected in the shapes of the responses and their spatial pattern of distribution across the different brain areas.  In addition to these experiments, we also devised and constructed a setup to automatically measure the perceptual preferences of songbirds to sounds with different perceived features and to bird calls with contrasting significance from the standpoint of social interactions between the birds. Using this approach we have tested several con...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
