<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International: A US-Germany Research Collaboration on Systems for Computer-Integrated Healthcare</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>147320.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>147320</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maija Kukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkukla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924940</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computer-Integrated Medicine (CIM) is a new and rapidly growing area with high global appeal. Work in CIM is multi-national and inter-disciplinary. International research exchange is thus essential in creating state-of-the-art CIM systems, and in supporting CIM research programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this International Research Experiences for Students project is to create a bilateral international research exchange program on computer-integrated medicine (CIM) between the Technical University of Munich (TUM) Graduate School in Information Science and Health (GSISH) and the Johns Hopkins University (JHU) Center for Computer-Integrated Surgical Systems and Technology (CISST-ERC). Our vision is to develop a joint research and education activity that merges team research projects with cohort-focused education and organized cultural and socialization experiences, thereby creating a wide-ranging and long-term collaborative research program between our institutions. Both the TUM and JHU are national leaders in CIM, with networks of research collaborations that span their respective continents.  The proposed IRES support will provide the ?missing link? in our existing faculty interactions and unilateral student exchange, to bind the networks of the two institutions into one larger transatlantic network on a more systematic and sustainable level. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We have developed the exchange to focus on the development of a cohort experience for students with an innovative educational and research mentoring environment. Our collaboration will focus on four research projects that exploit the inherent synergies of JHU and TUM. They are: 1) Automated surgical skill modeling and workflow analysis; 2) Video reconstruction and registration for advanced surgical visualization; 3) Software systems for information-enhanced surgery; and 4) Medical robotics devices and systems for microsurgery. Each of these projects is led by both TUM and JHU faculty, and takes advantage of complementary skills at each institution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our project will emphasize the development of research networks that the students will be able to take advantage of after the exchange ends, leading to long-term international cooperation. The focus on graduate students in the exchange provides a longer time horizon for the networks, and the eventual inclusion of undergraduates in the exchange will cement the transatlantic research community in this growing area of important interdisciplinary research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by NSF's Office of International Science and Engineering (OISE) and the NSF Directorate for Computer &amp; Information Science and Engineering (CISE), Divisions of Information and Intelligent Systems (IIS) and Robust Intelligence (RI).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1065092</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Hager</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory D Hager</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hager@cs.jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105165521</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000385453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite B001]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1101 E 33rd St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7639</Code>
<Text>IRES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~147320</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this international research exchange was to create a bilateral collaboration on computer-integrated medicine between the Technical University of Munich Graduate School in Information Science and Health and the Johns Hopkins University Center for Computer-integrated Surgery. &nbsp;The long term goal of the program was to catalyze a joint research and education activity that merges team research projects with cohort-focused education and organized cultural and socialization experiences, thereby creating a wide-ranging and long-term collaborative research program between our institutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the course of this project, we supported twelve exchange visits on several topics ranging from biomedical imaging to healthcare informatics, to surgical workflow analysis and robotic surgery. Several of these visits resulted in longer-term collaborative activities among the faculty and students, and many of the students are continuing to collaborate with their counterparts in Germany.&nbsp; These collaborations have led to five joint publications to date, and have catalyzed the development of three collaborative research proposals among JHU and TUM faculty. One of the exchange participants is now spending a year in Germany with joint support from both German and US sides, and his dissertation will be jointly supervised.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As a result of this exchange program, we have substantially broadened the network of research and education activities that students and faculty at JHU and TUM have access to. This has allowed us to both leverage and accelerate research, thus improving the training and productivity of the students who participated in this exchange.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;D&nbsp;Hager</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1065092/1065092_10083738_1470430043041_IMG_3388--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1065092/1065092_10083738_1470430043041_IMG_3388--rgov-800width.jpg" title="JHU-TUMExchangeMeeting2015"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1065092/1065092_10083738_1470430043041_IMG_3388--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="JHU-TUMExchangeMeeting2015"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Members of the JHU exchange held a retreat in 2015 with their TU Munich counterparts in the Computer Science Department.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Greg Hager</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gregory&nbsp;D&nbsp;Hager</div> <div class="imageTitle">JHU-TUMExchangeMeeting2015</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this international research exchange was to create a bilateral collaboration on computer-integrated medicine between the Technical University of Munich Graduate School in Information Science and Health and the Johns Hopkins University Center for Computer-integrated Surgery.  The long term goal of the program was to catalyze a joint research and education activity that merges team research projects with cohort-focused education and organized cultural and socialization experiences, thereby creating a wide-ranging and long-term collaborative research program between our institutions.     During the course of this project, we supported twelve exchange visits on several topics ranging from biomedical imaging to healthcare informatics, to surgical workflow analysis and robotic surgery. Several of these visits resulted in longer-term collaborative activities among the faculty and students, and many of the students are continuing to collaborate with their counterparts in Germany.  These collaborations have led to five joint publications to date, and have catalyzed the development of three collaborative research proposals among JHU and TUM faculty. One of the exchange participants is now spending a year in Germany with joint support from both German and US sides, and his dissertation will be jointly supervised.     As a result of this exchange program, we have substantially broadened the network of research and education activities that students and faculty at JHU and TUM have access to. This has allowed us to both leverage and accelerate research, thus improving the training and productivity of the students who participated in this exchange.          Last Modified: 08/05/2016       Submitted by: Gregory D Hager]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
