<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Planning Visit: Robotic Exploration of the Mersa/Wadi Gawasis, Hurghada, Egypt</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9658.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9658</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Osman Shinaishin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>OISE-1066733  &lt;br/&gt;Choset&lt;br/&gt;Summary:  The proposal is for support of a planning visit to develop a project on: Robotic Exploration of Mersa/Wadi Gawasis Archeological Sites, Hurghada, Egypt.   The PI seeks to establish a long-term collaboration with Dr. Mohamed Abd El-Maguid, marine archeologist at the Egyptian Supreme Council of Antiquities, to use robots to inspect regions of archeological interest that are too dangerous for people to enter. The specific area of interest lies in the Mersa/Wadi Gawasis region that contains many man-made caves that were used to store pieces of ancient ships. This region has now gained considerable interest by Egyptologists. Dr. Kathryn Bard of Boston University and Rodolfo Fattovich of the University of Naples "l'Orientale" are active in this area, and Abd El-Maguid has joined with them to assist in excavations and in determining historical significance. They have identified two specific caves that contain artifacts of great interest and are looking at another location for a man-made storage facility. These areas are not safe for people to enter. The PI has developed robots, called snake robots, because they articulate and maneuver through cluttered spaces, much in the same ways biological snakes do. They are to be explored for use in these sites.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: Snake robots are expected to identify and even retrieve items from archeological caves. This trip will allow the PI to inspect the cave entrances which hopefully will be followed up by an expedition with the robots. The PI also will work with Dr. Majd Sakr, another Carnegie Mellon faculty, using efforts in cloud computing to disseminate the results of their excavations with the robots. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The PI and his Egyptian collaborator expect this work to lead to future expeditions of robotics in archeology in confined spaces. Already, robots have been used once in the great pyramid and under water. In this new field of robotics, archaeologists can use robots as tools to explore and investigate important archaeological sites without disturbing the surrounding areas, which often happens when people enter such locations. While exploring such regions, the robot is able to construct a map of the site, which in turn can be viewed by others. This map will provide a three-dimensional view of the location, allowing anyone, both archaeologist and non-specialist alike, to remotely and virtually visit a location of great national interest. The PI plans to visit schools around Pittsburgh to talk about robotics, drawing on the application of archeology for subject matter. Snake robots looking for artifacts of historical significance is one of the more compelling stories one can tell a middle school student to raise interest in science and engineering.  Choset will also develop lab modules for the undergraduate robotics with the theme of looking for artifacts in dangerous environments. This project is funded by the Division of Information and Intelligent Systems and the Office of International Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1066733</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Choset</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard M Choset</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>choset@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122682495</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000167332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5944</Code>
<Text>EGYPT (COOP SCIENCE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~9658</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The long-term goal of this work is to help support the efforts of archeologists looking for ancient Egyptian artifacts which are concealed in caves off of the coat of the Red Sea. These artifacts are pieces of ships and support technology that the ancient Egyptians used to sail to the legendary city of Punt. Unfortuanately, the caves are sometimes not stable or too small for people ot enter.</p> <p>This work supported a planning trip to Egypt to establish the relationship between the American and Egyptian PI in using robots to search of artifacts in the caves. We brought our robots to better understand the logistics isssues of travel into and within Egypt with the robots and those associated with deploying our robots in the field. We also had the opportunity to meet and work with the archeological team.</p> <p>Based on what we learned, we were supposed to return at the beginning of 2012 with a team of students and the robots to map out and search these caves, as well as meet other local Egyptian researchers. Unfortuantely, it was not possible to visit this year, but we hope to return in 2013.</p> <p>This is work done in collaboration with Mohamed El-Maguid, now at the Supreme Council of Antiquities, in Egypt, and Kathryn Bard, a Professor of Archeology at Boston University.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/07/2012<br>      Modified by: Howard&nbsp;M&nbsp;Choset</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The long-term goal of this work is to help support the efforts of archeologists looking for ancient Egyptian artifacts which are concealed in caves off of the coat of the Red Sea. These artifacts are pieces of ships and support technology that the ancient Egyptians used to sail to the legendary city of Punt. Unfortuanately, the caves are sometimes not stable or too small for people ot enter.  This work supported a planning trip to Egypt to establish the relationship between the American and Egyptian PI in using robots to search of artifacts in the caves. We brought our robots to better understand the logistics isssues of travel into and within Egypt with the robots and those associated with deploying our robots in the field. We also had the opportunity to meet and work with the archeological team.  Based on what we learned, we were supposed to return at the beginning of 2012 with a team of students and the robots to map out and search these caves, as well as meet other local Egyptian researchers. Unfortuantely, it was not possible to visit this year, but we hope to return in 2013.  This is work done in collaboration with Mohamed El-Maguid, now at the Supreme Council of Antiquities, in Egypt, and Kathryn Bard, a Professor of Archeology at Boston University.          Last Modified: 03/07/2012       Submitted by: Howard M Choset]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
