<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI:  Mapping of Charge Distribution on a Non-Uniformly Changed Toner Particle for Determining Fundamental Contributors of Adhesion Force</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1066877&lt;br/&gt;PI: Cetinkaya&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Handling micron-sized particles in bulk and depositing a large number of them onto a substrate in a controllable manner in the presence of electrostatic effects is a critical, general process step in various industries such as printing and copying, pharmaceutics, food processing, powder metallurgy and electronics and semiconductor manufacturing. Experiments show that there is considerable variation in particle-substrate adhesion force among particles prepared in an identical manner. It has been hypothesized that this variation results from non-uniform charge distribution on the surface of individual particles. To verify this hypothesis, and to understand the underlying mechanisms responsible for non-uniform charge distribution, it is necessary as a first step to determine charge distribution on the surface of individual particles. This project will develop techniques for determining charge distribution on individual toner particles under controlled conditions. Force required to roll a single particle will be determined by two techniques: one based on the Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM) and the other based on acoustics. The measured force will be used to estimate charge distribution under varying conditions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; New knowledge generated in this research program will be useful in the design and production of novel classes of energy-efficient emulsion aggregation toner and associated powder handling/deposition systems. Reduction in cost, energy consumption and environmental impact through the utilization of this technology in toner design and development phases are among the chief benefits of the program to society at large. The emulsion aggregation technology offers 60-70% energy savings per printed page in comparison to the conventional pulverized toner. It is projected that its adoption will result in substantial reductions in toner material usage, toner waste and greenhouse gas emissions. This project also includes a strong education component. The program will enhance undergraduate and graduate curricula at Clarkson by providing industrial internships and will support a state-funded K-12 teacher summer training program for increasing nanotechnology awareness. Students and participating teachers will have opportunities to interact and work with researchers from Clarkson and Xerox in fundamental research problems of practical relevance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1066877</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Goodarz</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahmadi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Goodarz Ahmadi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ahmadi@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152682322</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000359096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cetin</FirstName>
<LastName>Cetinkaya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cetin Cetinkaya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pharmacoustics01@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152768051</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314747</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiqiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Ding</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weiqiang Ding</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wding@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3046851938</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/04/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kock-Yee</FirstName>
<LastName>Law</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kock-Yee Law</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>klaw@xeroxlabs.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854225229</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502019</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clarkson University</Name>
<CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
<ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3152686475</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8 Clarkson Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041590993</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLARKSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041590993</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clarkson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8 Clarkson Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>149E</Code>
<Text>Granular systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Adhesion plays a central role in microscale particles involved in a wide spectrum of industrial processes and natural phenomena. Handling micro-particles in bulk and depositing a large number of them onto a substrate in a controllable manner under electrostatic effects is a critical, generic process step. Thus, accurate understanding of adhesion is a critical requirement for various industries such as additive&nbsp;manufacturing,&nbsp;printing/copying, pharmaceutics, food processing, powder metallurgy and electronics/semiconductor manufacturing.</p> <p>An&nbsp;experimental investigation&nbsp;was proposed to provide a fundamental understanding of the effect of a distributed electrostatic charge on the surface of a micro-particle on its adhesion properties, and &nbsp;to identify and experimentally quantify the contributors of the adhesive force between such a charged particle and a substrate.</p> <p><span>The significant results of this project are summarized as follows:</span></p> <p>1. A non-contact practical method for single particle adhesion characterization has been developed and demonstrated.&nbsp;</p> <p>2. A technique for determining critical particle leaning angles prior to free-rolling has been introduced. Critical leaning angle is a key parameter in particle handling systems used in various industries such as&nbsp;pharmaceuticals and food processing.</p> <p>3. An experimental method for determining the amount of electrical charge on a single microparticle has been presented and demonstrated. Electrical charge on toner microparticles and their accurate determination is a critical factor determining the print quality in a copying/printing machine.</p> <p>4. A unique method for mapping the adhesion distribution on a single microparticle in a non-contact/non-invasive manner has been developed and published for the first time. Such maps play an important role designing advanced toner particles for&nbsp;copying/printing machines.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Cetin&nbsp;Cetinkaya</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Adhesion plays a central role in microscale particles involved in a wide spectrum of industrial processes and natural phenomena. Handling micro-particles in bulk and depositing a large number of them onto a substrate in a controllable manner under electrostatic effects is a critical, generic process step. Thus, accurate understanding of adhesion is a critical requirement for various industries such as additive manufacturing, printing/copying, pharmaceutics, food processing, powder metallurgy and electronics/semiconductor manufacturing.  An experimental investigation was proposed to provide a fundamental understanding of the effect of a distributed electrostatic charge on the surface of a micro-particle on its adhesion properties, and  to identify and experimentally quantify the contributors of the adhesive force between such a charged particle and a substrate.  The significant results of this project are summarized as follows:  1. A non-contact practical method for single particle adhesion characterization has been developed and demonstrated.   2. A technique for determining critical particle leaning angles prior to free-rolling has been introduced. Critical leaning angle is a key parameter in particle handling systems used in various industries such as pharmaceuticals and food processing.  3. An experimental method for determining the amount of electrical charge on a single microparticle has been presented and demonstrated. Electrical charge on toner microparticles and their accurate determination is a critical factor determining the print quality in a copying/printing machine.  4. A unique method for mapping the adhesion distribution on a single microparticle in a non-contact/non-invasive manner has been developed and published for the first time. Such maps play an important role designing advanced toner particles for copying/printing machines.       Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Cetin Cetinkaya]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
