<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Experimental and Computational Studies on CO2 Photoreduction to Fuels by Nanostructured Catalysts</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>176730.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>176730</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Rorrer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Institution:  University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee / Arizona State University&lt;br/&gt;Title:  Collaborative Research: Experimental and Computational Studies on CO2 Photoreduction to Fuels by Nanostructured Catalysts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Carbon dioxide (CO2) from the atmosphere is a potentially sustainable source of carbon for the production of renewable fuels.  The photocatalytic conversion of CO2 and water to hydrocarbons is a particularly attractive route, as it uses solar energy as the source of reducing electrons to drive this conversion process.  However, the photocatalytic reduction of CO2 is an extremely challenging task due to the stable thermodynamic properties of CO2. The low yield of CO2 conversion calls for more efficient photocatalysts, but the development of efficient photocatalysts requires understanding of CO2?catalyst interactions and electron transfer pathways deduced from computational studies at the molecular level. The overall objective of the proposed research is to use solar radiation to photocatalytically reduce CO2 to fuels (CO, methane, methanol, and other hydrocarbons) at high conversion efficiency through manipulation of catalyst composition and nanostructure. Toward this end, the proposed research has three objectives.  The first objective is to fabricate nanostructured photocatalysts, specifically brookite-containing mixed-phase TiO2 nanoparticles with controlled phase contents such as lattice-doped iodine and surface Cu clusters, to achieve visible light responsiveness and facilitate charge separation.   The second objective is to develop a fundamental understanding of the catalyst properties and charge separation mechanism at the mixed-phase (e.g., anatase-brookite) nanocrystalline interfaces through closely coupled experiments and computational chemistry (density functional theory) modeling.  The third objective is to optimize catalyst composition and nanostructure (e.g., TiO2 phase composition, crystal size, surface structures, dopant concentration, etc.) to synergistically improve CO2 photoreduction efficiency.  In this regard, the proposed research will integrate experimental and computational approaches to evaluate brookite-based catalyst activity toward CO2 photoreduction, and will advance fundamental understanding in the multidisciplinary areas of material science, surface chemistry, photocatalysis, and nanotechnology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Processes for photoreduction of CO2 and water to hydrocarbon fuels tackle the simultaneous challenges of greenhouse gas management and renewable fuels production.  The educational and outreach activities will be in the context of the proposed research. Topics related to CO2 reduction and solar fuels will be incorporated into solar engineering, chemical reactor design, and air quality engineering courses at Arizona State University (ASU) and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (UWM).    Outreach activities at ASU sponsored though the Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering (IAFSE) will provide hands-on experiences in solar fuels to students from underrepresented groups as well as local teachers.  An animated educational module on CO2 conversion by sunlight will also be created to engage students and the general public. This module will be posted on the websites of the principal investigators as well as on the ASU IAFSE outreach website.  Complimentary outreach activities at UWM will be coordinated through the Urban Ecology Center (UEC) in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, who has partnerships with forty-four inner-city elementary and high schools and provides ?outdoor classrooms? in science education for urban youth.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1067340</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>Andino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean M Andino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jean.andino@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809650199</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179075</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ORSPA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>146E</Code>
<Text>Solar energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~176730</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Interest in controlling carbon dioxide emissions has increased over the years due to the correlation that has been shown to exist between climate change and carbon dioxide levels. One approach to controlling carbon dioxide levels is to chemically recycle the gas to useful chemicals. This carbon recycling and reuse (CRR) approach has the potential to be far superior to traditional techniques for carbon control that have been used by the scientific community and industries (e.g. carbon capture and sequestration) since the CRR approach creates products that can act as starting chemicals for other products, may be used as fuels, or may increase the operating efficiencies of stationary sources (e.g. power plants). Moreover, the CRR approach has the potential to substantially improve the profitability of businesses while simultaneously improving environmental stewardship. As such, research in the area of carbon dioxide recycling and reuse is exceptionally important.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong></p> <p>The investment provided by the National Science Foundation in this collaborative research project has assisted in (a) enhancing understanding of the light-initiated conversion of carbon dioxide in the presence of water vapor over novel solid catalytic surfaces, (b) sparking new technology development that has the potential to be beneficial to the public, and (c) engaging and training diverse groups.</p> <p>The project examined the conversion of carbon dioxide and water vapor over novel brookite (TiO<sub>2</sub>) surfaces using both computational and experimental approaches. Five peer-reviewed papers and additional extended, archived conference abstracts have been produced already, and additional results remain to be published. One of the published papers, Liu et al., <em>ACS Catalysis</em>, 2, 1817-1828 (2012) received a &ldquo;highly cited&rdquo; designation by Essential Science Indicators of Thompson Reuters in May/June 2015, falling in the top 1% of the field based on the number of citations. Thus, the work that was produced through this project has made a significant impact.</p> <p>The general, major conclusions that were obtained from the work include the following: (1) the brookite form of TiO<sub>2</sub>, and particularly the oxygen deficient form of this photocatalytic material, was useful for the light-initiated conversion of carbon dioxide and water vapor to carbon monoxide and methane; (2) nitric oxide (NO), an air pollutant that is routinely found in combustion systems, affected carbon dioxide conversion over the catalytic material, but the NO could also be reduced over the surface. The conclusions were arrived at through a series of experiments employing electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy, gas chromatography, or Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy, as well as computational chemistry studies that modeled the interactions of the gases on the surfaces.</p> <p>The work confirmed previous computational and experimental work with carbon dioxide, and extended the knowledge to the understanding of how water vapor, methane, and carbon monoxide interacted with the surfaces, particularly the brookite surface. Work with the brookite surface had not previously been conducted, either experimentally or computationally, for the carbon dioxide photoreduction reaction. The results suggested that the brookite surface was significantly more effective- as compared to other titania polymorphs- at converting carbon dioxide to other materials.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong></p> <p>The project has several broader impacts. In addition to expanding the scientific community&rsquo;s understanding of how the brookite surface led to a significant increase in the light-assisted conversion of carbon dioxide to other materials, the project sparked interest in the control of another critically important air pollutant: nitric oxide (NO).&nbsp...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Interest in controlling carbon dioxide emissions has increased over the years due to the correlation that has been shown to exist between climate change and carbon dioxide levels. One approach to controlling carbon dioxide levels is to chemically recycle the gas to useful chemicals. This carbon recycling and reuse (CRR) approach has the potential to be far superior to traditional techniques for carbon control that have been used by the scientific community and industries (e.g. carbon capture and sequestration) since the CRR approach creates products that can act as starting chemicals for other products, may be used as fuels, or may increase the operating efficiencies of stationary sources (e.g. power plants). Moreover, the CRR approach has the potential to substantially improve the profitability of businesses while simultaneously improving environmental stewardship. As such, research in the area of carbon dioxide recycling and reuse is exceptionally important.  Intellectual Merit:   The investment provided by the National Science Foundation in this collaborative research project has assisted in (a) enhancing understanding of the light-initiated conversion of carbon dioxide in the presence of water vapor over novel solid catalytic surfaces, (b) sparking new technology development that has the potential to be beneficial to the public, and (c) engaging and training diverse groups.  The project examined the conversion of carbon dioxide and water vapor over novel brookite (TiO2) surfaces using both computational and experimental approaches. Five peer-reviewed papers and additional extended, archived conference abstracts have been produced already, and additional results remain to be published. One of the published papers, Liu et al., ACS Catalysis, 2, 1817-1828 (2012) received a "highly cited" designation by Essential Science Indicators of Thompson Reuters in May/June 2015, falling in the top 1% of the field based on the number of citations. Thus, the work that was produced through this project has made a significant impact.  The general, major conclusions that were obtained from the work include the following: (1) the brookite form of TiO2, and particularly the oxygen deficient form of this photocatalytic material, was useful for the light-initiated conversion of carbon dioxide and water vapor to carbon monoxide and methane; (2) nitric oxide (NO), an air pollutant that is routinely found in combustion systems, affected carbon dioxide conversion over the catalytic material, but the NO could also be reduced over the surface. The conclusions were arrived at through a series of experiments employing electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy, gas chromatography, or Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy, as well as computational chemistry studies that modeled the interactions of the gases on the surfaces.  The work confirmed previous computational and experimental work with carbon dioxide, and extended the knowledge to the understanding of how water vapor, methane, and carbon monoxide interacted with the surfaces, particularly the brookite surface. Work with the brookite surface had not previously been conducted, either experimentally or computationally, for the carbon dioxide photoreduction reaction. The results suggested that the brookite surface was significantly more effective- as compared to other titania polymorphs- at converting carbon dioxide to other materials.     Broader Impacts:   The project has several broader impacts. In addition to expanding the scientific communityÆs understanding of how the brookite surface led to a significant increase in the light-assisted conversion of carbon dioxide to other materials, the project sparked interest in the control of another critically important air pollutant: nitric oxide (NO).  Preliminary work suggested that the catalysts that were employed for carbon dioxide control could simultaneously be used for the control of NO in flue gas. This work is highly significant in that it ma...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
