<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Rapid, Scalable Method for Plant-Made Production of Cellulases</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>550000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Friedrich Srienc</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This NSF award by the Biotechnology, Biochemical and Biomass Engineering program supports the development of technologies and processes for efficient, rapid and scalable production of cellulase enzymes in plant tissues. To meet the requirements of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007, conversion of cellulosic biomass into advanced biofuels will require a significant amount of cellulose degrading enzymes at a low cost. Current methods for production of cellulose and hemicellulose degrading enzymes rely primarily on submerged fungal fermentation and are expensive, energy intensive, generate carbon dioxide, and consume cellulosic feedstock for growth of the production microorganisms. In this project, multiple thermostable cell wall degrading enzymes will be produced in Nicotiana benthamiana (a relative of tobacco) plants and harvested leaves, utilizing novel transient expression systems. Advantages of the transient approach over in-planta production of enzymes in stably transformed plants are that it is rapid, can utilize wild type (non-transgenic) plant biomass, and that the plant growth and enzyme production stages are decoupled and can be separately optimized.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: This research project will improve fundamental bioprocess engineering understanding of transient agroinfiltration processes, plant viral amplicon expression systems, recovery and characterization of plant-made enzymes, scale-up considerations in transient agroinfiltration processes, and techno-economic and environmental assessment of alternative bioprocessing strategies for production of cellulase enzymes.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact: The benefits of the proposed research to society are 1) cost-effective, energyefficient and environmentally-sound technologies that will not only be useful for the production of cellulase and hemicellulase enzymes to meet the U.S biofuels mandates but also lead to "greener" and more efficient bioproduction technologies for the industrial enzyme industry, 2)enhanced fundamental process understanding of recombinant protein production using transient agroinfiltration in plants which will accelerate growth of companies utilizing similar technologies for vaccine and therapeutics production, 3) broadening participation of women and underrepresented minorities through proactive recruitment and interdisciplinary research and educational training opportunities at the interface of plant science, biotechnology and bioprocess engineering, and 4) broad curricular impact by incorporating research findings into existing and new lecture and laboratory courses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1067432</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abhaya</FirstName>
<LastName>Dandekar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abhaya M Dandekar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amdandekar@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307527784</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000478023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>McDonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen A McDonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kamcdonald@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7075488314</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460334</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryce</FirstName>
<LastName>Falk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryce W Falk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bwfalk@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307520302</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000451539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OR/Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>002E</Code>
<Text>Bio-energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>009E</Code>
<Text>Metabolic engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~200388</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~221989</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~127623</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching goal of this project is to reduce the cost of cellulosic biofuel production.&nbsp; The specific goal of this project was to develop biotechnologies, bioprocesses and improved fundamental understanding of plant-based processes for the transient production of multiple plant-cell wall degrading enzymes, specifically in harvested leaves of <em>Nicotiana benthamiana</em>, a relative of tobacco and sunflower, an agricultural waste product.&nbsp; The plant-based production of recombinant thermostable cellulase and hemicellulose enzymes can be used to initiate thermally activated self-deconstruction of plant cell walls in the host plant or as an alternative source of cellulase enzymes to be used as additives to other pretreated biomass, or a combination of the two since the spent biomass that produces the enzymes can also serve as a source of cellulose.&nbsp; Potential advantages of plant-based production of these enzymes over microbial fermentation which is typically carried out in large scale expensive stainless steel bioreactors, include use of sunlight/photosynthesis for the generation of the host biomass and consumption of CO<sub>2</sub> as the energy and carbon source for host cell growth, lower capital and enzyme production costs (resulting in lower costs of cellulosic biofuels), easier scale up, and ability to glycosylate enzymes which may be important for activity for some cellulases.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The outcomes in terms of <strong>intellectual merits</strong> of the project were that we successfully demonstrated the transient production of five functional thermostable cell wall degrading enzymes in harvested <em>Nicotiana benthamiana</em>, including endoglucanase E1 and xylanase Xyl from <em>Acidothermus cellulolyticus</em>, betaxylosidase (BXyl) and betaglucosidase (BglB) from <em>Thermatoga martima</em>, and cellobiohydrolase I (CBHI) from <em>Thermoascus aurantiacus</em>.&nbsp; &nbsp;Production kinetics for these systems were determined under various bioprocessing conditions for different expression systems, including novel plant viral expression systems developed in the project.&nbsp; We used a <em>Cucumber mosaic virus</em>-based expression system (<em>CMVar</em>) to simultaneously express two enzymes in <em>N. benthamiana</em> plants, even in the same cell.&nbsp; This is an important requirement to achieve thermally activated self-deconstruction of the host plant cell walls since these enzymes work in synergy and need to be physically co-located in the apoplast (<em>i.e.</em> cell wall matrix outside of the membrane). &nbsp;&nbsp;Enzymes were purified and characterized to determine their activities on model substrates as a function of pH and temperature.&nbsp; The production of thermostable E1 and Xyl was also demonstrated in harvest sunflower leaves and bioprocessing methods to increase the production of active enzymes were developed including the addition of plant hormones in the agroinfiltration buffer and the optimization of the temperature profile during post-infiltration incubation the sunflower leaves which increased the production over 4-fold. Scale up of recombinant agrobacteria cultures to the 100L scale was used to determine growth kinetics, nutrient uptake and oxygen uptake rates in defined medium; these data provided important parameters for technoeconomic models that were developed for the transient plant-based production platform.</p> <p>The outcomes in terms of <strong>broader impacts</strong> are 1) the development of cost-effective, energy-efficient and environmentally-sound technologies that will not only be useful for the production of cellulase and hemicellulase enzymes to meet the U.S biofuels mandates but also lead to &ldquo;greener&rdquo; and more efficient bioproduction technologies for the industrial enzyme industry in general, 2) fundamental process understanding and engineering applications of recombinant prot...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching goal of this project is to reduce the cost of cellulosic biofuel production.  The specific goal of this project was to develop biotechnologies, bioprocesses and improved fundamental understanding of plant-based processes for the transient production of multiple plant-cell wall degrading enzymes, specifically in harvested leaves of Nicotiana benthamiana, a relative of tobacco and sunflower, an agricultural waste product.  The plant-based production of recombinant thermostable cellulase and hemicellulose enzymes can be used to initiate thermally activated self-deconstruction of plant cell walls in the host plant or as an alternative source of cellulase enzymes to be used as additives to other pretreated biomass, or a combination of the two since the spent biomass that produces the enzymes can also serve as a source of cellulose.  Potential advantages of plant-based production of these enzymes over microbial fermentation which is typically carried out in large scale expensive stainless steel bioreactors, include use of sunlight/photosynthesis for the generation of the host biomass and consumption of CO2 as the energy and carbon source for host cell growth, lower capital and enzyme production costs (resulting in lower costs of cellulosic biofuels), easier scale up, and ability to glycosylate enzymes which may be important for activity for some cellulases.    The outcomes in terms of intellectual merits of the project were that we successfully demonstrated the transient production of five functional thermostable cell wall degrading enzymes in harvested Nicotiana benthamiana, including endoglucanase E1 and xylanase Xyl from Acidothermus cellulolyticus, betaxylosidase (BXyl) and betaglucosidase (BglB) from Thermatoga martima, and cellobiohydrolase I (CBHI) from Thermoascus aurantiacus.   Production kinetics for these systems were determined under various bioprocessing conditions for different expression systems, including novel plant viral expression systems developed in the project.  We used a Cucumber mosaic virus-based expression system (CMVar) to simultaneously express two enzymes in N. benthamiana plants, even in the same cell.  This is an important requirement to achieve thermally activated self-deconstruction of the host plant cell walls since these enzymes work in synergy and need to be physically co-located in the apoplast (i.e. cell wall matrix outside of the membrane).   Enzymes were purified and characterized to determine their activities on model substrates as a function of pH and temperature.  The production of thermostable E1 and Xyl was also demonstrated in harvest sunflower leaves and bioprocessing methods to increase the production of active enzymes were developed including the addition of plant hormones in the agroinfiltration buffer and the optimization of the temperature profile during post-infiltration incubation the sunflower leaves which increased the production over 4-fold. Scale up of recombinant agrobacteria cultures to the 100L scale was used to determine growth kinetics, nutrient uptake and oxygen uptake rates in defined medium; these data provided important parameters for technoeconomic models that were developed for the transient plant-based production platform.  The outcomes in terms of broader impacts are 1) the development of cost-effective, energy-efficient and environmentally-sound technologies that will not only be useful for the production of cellulase and hemicellulase enzymes to meet the U.S biofuels mandates but also lead to "greener" and more efficient bioproduction technologies for the industrial enzyme industry in general, 2) fundamental process understanding and engineering applications of recombinant protein production using transient agroinfiltration in plants which will accelerate growth of companies utilizing similar technologies for vaccine and therapeutics production, 3) human resource development, including training of six graduate students, including 3 women engine...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
