<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Janus Particles as Tunable Emulsion Stabilizers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>330000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Award:1067501&lt;br/&gt;PI: Kretzschmar&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The scientific goal of this project is to explore the effect of heterogeneous surface functionality on emulsion formation and stability using Janus particles with well-defined surface compositions. Emulsions are ubiquitous in industrial processes, ranging from cosmetics to petrochemicals, and the fundamental understanding of emulsion behavior has been the subject of over a century of research. Traditional emulsification processes apply molecular amphiphiles to stabilize the oil-water interface. Similarly, homogenous particles are capable of adsorbing to oil-water interfaces to stabilize emulsion droplets. Yet in many industrial and natural systems, the adsorbing particles are not homogenous in shape or surface chemistry, and, while a number of theoretical studies have predicted the behavior of surface anisotropic particles, few experiments have been conducted to quantify the influence of heterogeneities on the interface.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is carried out in three parallel steps. First, the coalescence of emulsions is examined, using both homogenous and heterogeneous particles. Second, interfacial structure and rheology of surfaces stabilized by homogeneous particles is probed, focusing on the quantification of interfacial properties as a function of particle size and concentration. And third, interfacial structure and rheology of surfaces stabilized by Janus particles are probed, focusing on the role of interfacial order in the mechanics of the surface. Taken together, these studies allow us to understand fundamental aspects of the effect of surface heterogeneities on emulsion stability and engineer optimized systems for stabilizing multiphase systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: A major goal of the research is to advance the understanding of the effect of spatially heterogenous surface chemistry of micron-sized particles on emulsion stabilization. The results of this project are likely to impact a wide range of industries, including crude oil exploration and separation processes, water purification, and next-generation pharmaceutical/personal care products. The PIs have research experience in asymmetric particle surface modification, emulsion preparation, and characterization of interfacial properties.  Further, the PIs have access to (i) surface characterization instruments such as scanning electron and atomic force microscopy, (ii) emulsion, rheology, and stability equipment, and (iii) surface visualization tools. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The importance of emulsions and emulsion-based processes in industry cannot be overstated. A range of students from the high school to the graduate level are trained in both the fundamental and the applied aspects of emulsion technology. Moreover, an international component enables the training of CCNY students locally and abroad (Colombia, England, and Sweden). CCNY students typically come from a diverse background, and the PIs have a long history of training a cadre of students with wide ranging backgrounds. CCNY is a recognized minority serving institution, which serves a diverse undergraduate student body of Hispanic (36%), African American (30%), Asian (23%), and White (11%) students. Further, individual mentoring will provide female and minority students with a mentoring network early on in their careers. Research findings will be broadly disseminated using journal publications, conferences, and websites and will be used to develop hands-on experiences for high school and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1067501</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ilona</FirstName>
<LastName>Kretzschmar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ilona Kretzschmar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kretzschmar@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126506769</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000108038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
<LastName>Tu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raymond Tu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tu@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126507031</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482796</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Harbottle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Harbottle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daveharbottle@googlemail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Convent Ave at 138th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~330000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report for </strong><strong>Grant #:1067501</strong></p> <p>The research goal of the NSF-CBET 1067501 grant was to show that anisotropic modification of particle surfaces enables stabilization of emulsions with micrometer-sized particles and adds addressability to the particle function beyond that of a simple surfactant. The educational goal evolved around offering of educational opportunities that increase the participation and competitiveness of students from underrepresented groups at the City College of New York (CCNY) and the City University of New York (CUNY) and provide international research experiences for students.</p> <p>For the accomplishment of these goals, three objectives were identified: (1) Ability to enhance the stability of a water-in-oil emulsion through the addition of Janus particles, (2) Ability to probe interfacial structure and rheology of surfaces stabilized by homogeneous particles, and (3) Ability to probe interfacial structure and rheology of surfaces stabilized by <strong><em>Janus </em></strong>particles.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">New Instrumentation and Techniques:</span> A molecular dynamics (MD) code has been developed that enables us to study the behavior of single and multiple plain and Janus particles at fluid/fluid interfaces. A holographic microscopy technique has been developed that allows the tracking of the position and orientation of Janus particles with respect to liquid/liquid interfaces. In addition, a Langmuir trough technique has been developed that enables the measurement of the mechanical and rheological properties of the particle layers as a function of particle surface modification.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Research Findings and Outcomes:</span> Our modeling approach has revealed the existence of a capillary bridge that is formed when particles interact with a fluid/fluid interface. Further, molecular dynamics simulations have shown that this capillary bridge is asymmetric in the case of a Janus particle and that Janus particles carry a solvent cap after transitioning through a fluid/fluid interface. An extension of our MD code to include particles with asymmetric surface features (i.e., a ridge) has enabled the study of the impact of surface features on a particle&rsquo;s stability at the interface, which is an important parameter in the preparation of reactive emulsions. Our holographic microscopy experiments have revealed that Janus particles align prior to transitioning into the fluid/fluid interface, but retain a certain amount of orientational freedom at the interface that is strongly dependent on the roughness and amphiphilicity of the Janus particle. Langmuir trough experiments have underscored the impact of particle-particle interaction on the orientation of particles at interface and the dependence of the mechanical stability and rheological properties of such particle layers at the air/water interface on the particle surface modification. A general outcome of the study is that whereas Janus particles have amphiphilicity analogous to surfactant molecules, they show distinctly different behaviors at fluid/fluid interfaces.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Educational Impact:</span> The grant provided research opportunities for eight undergraduate, five MS, and six PhD students in the Chemical Engineering program at the City College of New York. Support of this project provided a year-round mentoring program for CCNY undergraduate and MS students from underrepresented groups. 13 students (six summer students) from underrepresented groups met with the PI on a weekly basis to discuss academic progress, career plans, graduate school applications and research opportunities. Eight undergraduate students and five MS students participated in the mentoring program of whom ~30% have moved on into MS and PhD programs and ~25% hav...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for Grant #:1067501  The research goal of the NSF-CBET 1067501 grant was to show that anisotropic modification of particle surfaces enables stabilization of emulsions with micrometer-sized particles and adds addressability to the particle function beyond that of a simple surfactant. The educational goal evolved around offering of educational opportunities that increase the participation and competitiveness of students from underrepresented groups at the City College of New York (CCNY) and the City University of New York (CUNY) and provide international research experiences for students.  For the accomplishment of these goals, three objectives were identified: (1) Ability to enhance the stability of a water-in-oil emulsion through the addition of Janus particles, (2) Ability to probe interfacial structure and rheology of surfaces stabilized by homogeneous particles, and (3) Ability to probe interfacial structure and rheology of surfaces stabilized by Janus particles.  New Instrumentation and Techniques: A molecular dynamics (MD) code has been developed that enables us to study the behavior of single and multiple plain and Janus particles at fluid/fluid interfaces. A holographic microscopy technique has been developed that allows the tracking of the position and orientation of Janus particles with respect to liquid/liquid interfaces. In addition, a Langmuir trough technique has been developed that enables the measurement of the mechanical and rheological properties of the particle layers as a function of particle surface modification.  Research Findings and Outcomes: Our modeling approach has revealed the existence of a capillary bridge that is formed when particles interact with a fluid/fluid interface. Further, molecular dynamics simulations have shown that this capillary bridge is asymmetric in the case of a Janus particle and that Janus particles carry a solvent cap after transitioning through a fluid/fluid interface. An extension of our MD code to include particles with asymmetric surface features (i.e., a ridge) has enabled the study of the impact of surface features on a particleÆs stability at the interface, which is an important parameter in the preparation of reactive emulsions. Our holographic microscopy experiments have revealed that Janus particles align prior to transitioning into the fluid/fluid interface, but retain a certain amount of orientational freedom at the interface that is strongly dependent on the roughness and amphiphilicity of the Janus particle. Langmuir trough experiments have underscored the impact of particle-particle interaction on the orientation of particles at interface and the dependence of the mechanical stability and rheological properties of such particle layers at the air/water interface on the particle surface modification. A general outcome of the study is that whereas Janus particles have amphiphilicity analogous to surfactant molecules, they show distinctly different behaviors at fluid/fluid interfaces.  Educational Impact: The grant provided research opportunities for eight undergraduate, five MS, and six PhD students in the Chemical Engineering program at the City College of New York. Support of this project provided a year-round mentoring program for CCNY undergraduate and MS students from underrepresented groups. 13 students (six summer students) from underrepresented groups met with the PI on a weekly basis to discuss academic progress, career plans, graduate school applications and research opportunities. Eight undergraduate students and five MS students participated in the mentoring program of whom ~30% have moved on into MS and PhD programs and ~25% have or will be applying for MS and PhD programs.  Dissemination Efforts  Peer-reviewed publications: 5 published, 4 in preparation  Invited and Conference Talks: 20  Conference Posters: 7  Human Resource Development (brackets indicate students from underrepresented groups)  PhD students involved in researc...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
