<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Four Corners Undergraduate STEM Success (FOCUSS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>444757.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>444757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Four Corners STEM Success (FOCUSS) is a collaborative project between Fort Lewis College (a four-year public liberal arts college in Durango, Colorado) and San Juan College (a two-year community college in Farmington, New Mexico), designed to increase the number of students in the Four Corners area who graduate with STEM degrees. San Juan College and Fort Lewis College are geographically close to one another (51 miles apart) and attract many of their students from the same region (western Colorado, northwestern New Mexico, and adjacent parts of Arizona and Utah). Furthermore, Fort Lewis College, which has a tuition waiver for all Native American students, is an excellent transfer destination for the large number of Native American students at San Juan College.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. The project consists of four activities: (1) a joint seminar series that brings career-oriented speakers to both institutions; (2) visits by Fort Lewis College STEM faculty and students to San Juan College, to encourage students at San Juan College to continue their education by transferring to Fort Lewis College; (3) an early undergraduate research program run jointly by both institutions; and (4) a tutor/mentor program for Fort Lewis College sophomores and new transfer students, designed to improve retention between first-year courses and upper-level courses at Fort Lewis College. These activities complement existing programs aimed at retaining first-year students and providing support to Native American and Hispanic students at both institutions, and providing undergraduate research experiences to junior and senior STEM majors at Fort Lewis College. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact.  The project is increasing the number of STEM students who continue from San Juan College to four-year programs, and is increasing the number of STEM majors who graduate from Fort Lewis College. At the same time, the project is increasing the number of underrepresented minorities who graduate with STEM degrees because both San Juan College and Fort Lewis College are designated Native American-Serving, Non-Tribal Institutions by the Department of Education, and serve student bodies that are 27% and 20% Native American, respectively.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1068342</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Veronica</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Veronica Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Evansv@sanjuancollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5055663209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526417</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Juan College</Name>
<CityName>Farmington</CityName>
<ZipCode>874020000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5055663253</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4601 College Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>102794005</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN JUAN COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>102794005</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Juan College]]></Name>
<CityName>Farmington</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>874020000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4601 College Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1796</Code>
<Text>STEP-STEM Talent Expansn Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~356355</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~88402</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;The Four Corners Undergraduate STEM Success (FOCUSS) project was a collaboration between San Juan College (SJC), a community college in northwestern New Mexico and Fort Lewis College (FLC), a liberal arts college in Durango, Colorado. This project aimed to increase STEM student graduation at FLC by supporting STEM student transfer from SJC and supporting student success in the FLC STEM disciplines.&nbsp; During the duration of the FOCUSS project, students enrolled in biology, chemistry, physics, geosciences, math, and engineering programs at SJC transferred at a higher rate than before the project initiated. Additionally, students at FLC majoring in these disciplines graduated at a higher rate with four year degrees.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Three strategies were used to achieve these goals.&nbsp; First, in order to support STEM student transfer from SJC to FLC, FLC faculty and students visited the SJC campus to recruit SJC students. These visits were a unique opportunity for SJC STEM students to learn about FLC STEM programs and ask questions about transfer topics.&nbsp; The second strategy was to sponsor an undergraduate summer research program in which students could work at either the FLC or SJC campuses. This research program aimed to support thirteen students each summer, eight from SJC and five from FLC.&nbsp; Participating students shared their experiences with their peers at poster sessions hosted at both SJC and FLC campuses.&nbsp; The SJC students that participated in this high impact strategy transferred to four year institutions at a much higher rate than their classmates.&nbsp; Over 50% of participating SJC students transferred during this project, compared to 15% of nonparticipating SJC STEM students.&nbsp; Students who remained at SJC after participating in the research program often took on leadership roles within the department, like becoming peer mentors in the Tutoring Center, serving as student senators or in student clubs, or working as student laboratory technicians demonstrating a gain in their self-efficacy as they reported in surveys.&nbsp; Finally, this program supported a tutor-mentor program at FLC to support student success in STEM courses. As a result of these efforts, there was a steady but modest increase in STEM student transfer from SJC to FLC during the duration of the project.&nbsp; Seven STEM students from SJC transferred to FLC in 2010, before the initiation of the FOCUSS project, while 10, 16, 9, 16 transferred in 2011 &ndash; 2015, respectively.&nbsp; Because the SJC and FLC campuses are located close to several Native American Reservations including the Navajo, Southern and Mountain Ute, Jicarilla Apache and Hopi, and because Fort Lewis College offers a Native American tuition waiver to students affiliated with a Native American tribe, this program had a high impact on Native American students.&nbsp; Over 30% of San Juan College STEM students report that they are Native American, and over 50% of the San Juan College participants in the undergraduate summer research program were Native American.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;This program resulted in lasting changes.&nbsp; Importantly, the articulation agreement between SJC and FLC was revised and relationships were built between STEM faculty of the two institutions to facilitate future revisions. These relationships will also support planned future recruiting visits, research collaborations, and equipment sharing. Finally, this program allowed the SJC faculty research mentors to direct students toward potential careers in science and research and gain a better understanding of what students will need to pursue a graduate degree in a STEM field.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Veronica&nbsp;Evans</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      The Four Corners Undergraduate STEM Success (FOCUSS) project was a collaboration between San Juan College (SJC), a community college in northwestern New Mexico and Fort Lewis College (FLC), a liberal arts college in Durango, Colorado. This project aimed to increase STEM student graduation at FLC by supporting STEM student transfer from SJC and supporting student success in the FLC STEM disciplines.  During the duration of the FOCUSS project, students enrolled in biology, chemistry, physics, geosciences, math, and engineering programs at SJC transferred at a higher rate than before the project initiated. Additionally, students at FLC majoring in these disciplines graduated at a higher rate with four year degrees.       Three strategies were used to achieve these goals.  First, in order to support STEM student transfer from SJC to FLC, FLC faculty and students visited the SJC campus to recruit SJC students. These visits were a unique opportunity for SJC STEM students to learn about FLC STEM programs and ask questions about transfer topics.  The second strategy was to sponsor an undergraduate summer research program in which students could work at either the FLC or SJC campuses. This research program aimed to support thirteen students each summer, eight from SJC and five from FLC.  Participating students shared their experiences with their peers at poster sessions hosted at both SJC and FLC campuses.  The SJC students that participated in this high impact strategy transferred to four year institutions at a much higher rate than their classmates.  Over 50% of participating SJC students transferred during this project, compared to 15% of nonparticipating SJC STEM students.  Students who remained at SJC after participating in the research program often took on leadership roles within the department, like becoming peer mentors in the Tutoring Center, serving as student senators or in student clubs, or working as student laboratory technicians demonstrating a gain in their self-efficacy as they reported in surveys.  Finally, this program supported a tutor-mentor program at FLC to support student success in STEM courses. As a result of these efforts, there was a steady but modest increase in STEM student transfer from SJC to FLC during the duration of the project.  Seven STEM students from SJC transferred to FLC in 2010, before the initiation of the FOCUSS project, while 10, 16, 9, 16 transferred in 2011 &ndash; 2015, respectively.  Because the SJC and FLC campuses are located close to several Native American Reservations including the Navajo, Southern and Mountain Ute, Jicarilla Apache and Hopi, and because Fort Lewis College offers a Native American tuition waiver to students affiliated with a Native American tribe, this program had a high impact on Native American students.  Over 30% of San Juan College STEM students report that they are Native American, and over 50% of the San Juan College participants in the undergraduate summer research program were Native American.       This program resulted in lasting changes.  Importantly, the articulation agreement between SJC and FLC was revised and relationships were built between STEM faculty of the two institutions to facilitate future revisions. These relationships will also support planned future recruiting visits, research collaborations, and equipment sharing. Finally, this program allowed the SJC faculty research mentors to direct students toward potential careers in science and research and gain a better understanding of what students will need to pursue a graduate degree in a STEM field.           Last Modified: 11/28/2016       Submitted by: Veronica Evans]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
