<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI -- Further Optical Charge Studies with the Trinity University Kelvin Probe</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>126599.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>126599</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO) is most sensitive to gravitational waves at signal frequencies near 100 Hz. One potential noise source at these frequencies is the motion of surface charge on optics, which can be generated through abrasive contact with dust, contact with other materials, or possibly from polarization by an electrostatic drive. Charge contributes noise by interfering with the position control of optics, attracting dust to the optical surface, and generating fluctuating electric fields. The noise contribution depends on the charge magnitude and the correlation time for charge motion. Reasonable values for these quantities suggest that charging might be a limiting noise source for Advanced LIGO. This award supports a research program with the goal of exploring the underlying physics of dielectric charging  and methods to mitigate its impact on Advanced LIGO. The laboratory at Trinity University developed by the PI through prior NSF support will be used for a number of experiments including various ways Advanced LIGO components might produce electrostatic charging, testing methods to mitigate the charging, and studying how charging actually produces noise in gravitational wave detectors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research could be of crucial importance to Advanced LIGO, due to the charge noise witnessed at LIGO Livingston Observatory in 2006 and the recent discovery of charging from exposure to an electrode similar to one of those in Advanced LIGO. The research is also important for other existing, future, and envisioned ground-based gravitational wave interferometers in order to reduce noise in their most sensitive frequency range. In addition, continued charging research at Trinity University provides a real-word research experience to undergraduates in a cutting-edge field; over a dozen Trinity students have participated in LIGO-related projects and theses, have been published authors, have presented their results at state and national meetings, have won awards for their accomplishments, and have moved on to successful physics-related careers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1068760</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>Ugolini</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis W Ugolini</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dugolini@trinity.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2109997890</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000295878</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trinity University</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782127200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2109997246</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Trinity Place</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>008133456</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRINITY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>008133456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trinity University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782127200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Trinity Place]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1252</Code>
<Text>LIGO RESEARCH SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~126599</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO) is designed to measure gravitational-waves, tiny perturbations of spacetime caused by the motion of massive astronomical bodies.&nbsp; Observation of gravitational waves will open a new avenue of study for objects such as black holes, supernovae, pulsars, and possibly unexpected sources.&nbsp; The sensitivity of the experimental may be limited by the motion of surface charge on the interferometer optics.&nbsp; A new element of the Advanced LIGO mirror suspension, the electrostatic drive (ESD), may exacerbate this problem by inducing an uneven charge distribution.&nbsp;</p> <p>The goal of this project has been to better understand and mitigate the effects of charging noise in Advanced LIGO.&nbsp; Accomplishments include:</p> <ul> <li>Developing an in-vacuum testbed in which an optic can be exposed to an ESD, then moved via remote control to a probe that measures a two-dimension map of surface charge.</li> <li>Verifying that the ESD produces charging noise that increases linearly with time.</li> <li>Disproving the suggestion that repeatedly pumping down to vacuum can result in excess charging from dust abrasion (because even if it did, the charge sparks toward conductors in a certain pressure range).</li> <li>Investigating several methods of charge removal, resulting in the rejection of some (such as a UV LED-based electron gun) and the acceptance of one (a stream of ionized nitrogen pumped across the optical surface).</li> <li>Testing the final Advanced LIGO charge removal system (in which nitrogen is ionized with high voltage needles), and showing that the efficiency increases with the surface area of the high voltage surfaces.</li> <li>Measuring the charge buildup and dissipation rates as a function of optical cleaning technique.</li> <li>Initiating tests of the charging behavior of next-generation optical coatings and substrates, toward the eventual goal of making a choice of optical materials for future experiments that minimizes charging noise.</li> </ul> <p>Results from this work were shared within the LIGO Scientific Collaboration (LSC) through phone meetings and internal notes, through presentations at LSC meetings and conferences of the Texas Section of the American Physical Society, and through a publication in Review of Scientific Instruments in 2014.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this work is improved understanding of the noise generated by charge motion and techniques to supress it.&nbsp; This is of value not just for gravitational wave detection, but for other experiments limited by charging noise such as measurements of the gravitational inverse-square law.&nbsp; The broader impacts of the work include training for five Trinity University undergraduates in vacuum hardware, software packages such as LabView and Matlab, experimental techniques, and responsible conduct of research.&nbsp; NSF support has also allowed the principal investigator to pursue an outreach program that includes talks for university physics departments and the general public, and regular participation in the USA Science and Engineering Festival in Washington, DC.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Dennis&nbsp;W&nbsp;Ugolini</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO) is designed to measure gravitational-waves, tiny perturbations of spacetime caused by the motion of massive astronomical bodies.  Observation of gravitational waves will open a new avenue of study for objects such as black holes, supernovae, pulsars, and possibly unexpected sources.  The sensitivity of the experimental may be limited by the motion of surface charge on the interferometer optics.  A new element of the Advanced LIGO mirror suspension, the electrostatic drive (ESD), may exacerbate this problem by inducing an uneven charge distribution.   The goal of this project has been to better understand and mitigate the effects of charging noise in Advanced LIGO.  Accomplishments include:  Developing an in-vacuum testbed in which an optic can be exposed to an ESD, then moved via remote control to a probe that measures a two-dimension map of surface charge. Verifying that the ESD produces charging noise that increases linearly with time. Disproving the suggestion that repeatedly pumping down to vacuum can result in excess charging from dust abrasion (because even if it did, the charge sparks toward conductors in a certain pressure range). Investigating several methods of charge removal, resulting in the rejection of some (such as a UV LED-based electron gun) and the acceptance of one (a stream of ionized nitrogen pumped across the optical surface). Testing the final Advanced LIGO charge removal system (in which nitrogen is ionized with high voltage needles), and showing that the efficiency increases with the surface area of the high voltage surfaces. Measuring the charge buildup and dissipation rates as a function of optical cleaning technique. Initiating tests of the charging behavior of next-generation optical coatings and substrates, toward the eventual goal of making a choice of optical materials for future experiments that minimizes charging noise.   Results from this work were shared within the LIGO Scientific Collaboration (LSC) through phone meetings and internal notes, through presentations at LSC meetings and conferences of the Texas Section of the American Physical Society, and through a publication in Review of Scientific Instruments in 2014.  The intellectual merit of this work is improved understanding of the noise generated by charge motion and techniques to supress it.  This is of value not just for gravitational wave detection, but for other experiments limited by charging noise such as measurements of the gravitational inverse-square law.  The broader impacts of the work include training for five Trinity University undergraduates in vacuum hardware, software packages such as LabView and Matlab, experimental techniques, and responsible conduct of research.  NSF support has also allowed the principal investigator to pursue an outreach program that includes talks for university physics departments and the general public, and regular participation in the USA Science and Engineering Festival in Washington, DC.       Last Modified: 10/28/2015       Submitted by: Dennis W Ugolini]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
