<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Central Pattern Generator (CPG) Control of Locomotion for Adaptive Gait Generation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This basic research aims to establish a general theory for designing feedback control mechanisms to drive robotic systems that swim like fishes or crawl like snakes. The design method will enable propulsion with agility and energy efficiency. The control algorithm is inspired by the central pattern generator (CPG) --- neuronal circuits that command muscle contractions to achieve rhythmic body movements during animal locomotion. The CPG is an interconnection of multiple neurons with simple individual dynamics, exhibiting a collective behavior perceived as a pattern. What makes CPGs an attractive object for engineering applications is its ability to adaptively choose the pattern of body oscillation appropriate for varying environments. This exploratory research will investigate the potential of the CPG architecture to provide a viable foundation for a new system design methodology to achieve coordinated oscillations of mechanical systems by feedback control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding of the mechanisms underlying emergent behaviors of CPGs could provide a central idea for innovative design of engineered systems with new functionalities. A theory that relates local interactions to the resulting global pattern would help identify, predict, or avoid, for instance, traffic congestion and instability in power grids. Synergistic effects between neuroscience and control engineering will be exploited in both research and education. The educational goal of this project is to provide students with a broad dynamical systems view point that applies not only to the design of engineered machines but also to understanding of biological phenomena. The goal will be approached through multidisciplinary training of graduate and undergraduate students in a teamwork environment, and by incorporating research findings into control engineering courses. The results will be broadly disseminated to both neuroscience and control communities through conference presentations, journal publications, invited seminars, and tutorial workshops, to enhance cross-cultural fertilizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1068997</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tetsuya</FirstName>
<LastName>Iwasaki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tetsuya Iwasaki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tiwasaki@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102062533</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396080</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 Wilshire Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1632</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Locomotion is a means for transportation used by animals. While there are many forms of locomotion, including walking, running, crawling, flying, and swimming, the underlying principle is the same; the body parts go through rhythmic motions and interact with the environment (ground, air, water) to generate thrust for moving forward. The efficiency and effectiveness of locomotion depend critically on the gait -- the periodic body oscillation with a particular pace, shape, and coordination. The gait is set and adjusted by neuronal control circuits called the central pattern generator (CPG), which resides in the central nervous system separately from the brain. The CPG is a biological control system that can achieve various functionalities, not achievable by currently available engineered control technologies, such as real-time adjustment of the oscillation pattern adapting to varying environmental conditions.</p> <p>This project examined the potential of the CPG architecture as a basis for a novel control technology to achieve coordinated oscillations with stability and adaptivity. Exploiting mathematical models of CPGs already available in the literature, the Principal Investigator (PI) and his students established a theoretical framework for systematically designing a feedback controller that makes the body oscillate with a prescribed frequency, amplitude, and timing. A major challenge in adopting the CPG control architecture is the neuronal dynamics that are nonlinear and complicate the design, yet are essential for achieving stable oscillations. They showed how to approximate the neuronal property and identified a fundamental mathematical problem, called an eigenstructure assignment, to which the control design problem reduces. A complete solution to the eigenstructure assignment was given, revealing exactly when the problem is solvable, and providing a parameterization of all solutions.</p> <p>The broader impacts of the eigenstructure assignment theory established by this project go beyond the CPG inspired control design for gait generation. In fact, the theoretical framework encompasses general pattern formation problems, where a number of "agents" form a global pattern through local distributed interactions. In the context of the CPG control, each neuron acts as an "agent" and their synaptic interconnections allow them to exchange information to form neural computing circuits that stimulate various muscles with specific timing to yield a patterned body oscillation. Analogous situations may be found in other contexts; motion coordination of mobile robots for certain operational tasks, formation flight of aircrafts for efficient long-range flight (as in a V-shaped group of migrating birds), etc. In the general context, the "agents" do not have to be neurons, but can be robots, vehicles, animals, molecules, genes, planets, stars, or any members of a group exhibiting a collective behavior. The project contributed to laying a theoretical foundation for understanding and/or achieving pattern formations of multiple dynamical agents.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/24/2015<br>      Modified by: Tetsuya&nbsp;Iwasaki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Locomotion is a means for transportation used by animals. While there are many forms of locomotion, including walking, running, crawling, flying, and swimming, the underlying principle is the same; the body parts go through rhythmic motions and interact with the environment (ground, air, water) to generate thrust for moving forward. The efficiency and effectiveness of locomotion depend critically on the gait -- the periodic body oscillation with a particular pace, shape, and coordination. The gait is set and adjusted by neuronal control circuits called the central pattern generator (CPG), which resides in the central nervous system separately from the brain. The CPG is a biological control system that can achieve various functionalities, not achievable by currently available engineered control technologies, such as real-time adjustment of the oscillation pattern adapting to varying environmental conditions.  This project examined the potential of the CPG architecture as a basis for a novel control technology to achieve coordinated oscillations with stability and adaptivity. Exploiting mathematical models of CPGs already available in the literature, the Principal Investigator (PI) and his students established a theoretical framework for systematically designing a feedback controller that makes the body oscillate with a prescribed frequency, amplitude, and timing. A major challenge in adopting the CPG control architecture is the neuronal dynamics that are nonlinear and complicate the design, yet are essential for achieving stable oscillations. They showed how to approximate the neuronal property and identified a fundamental mathematical problem, called an eigenstructure assignment, to which the control design problem reduces. A complete solution to the eigenstructure assignment was given, revealing exactly when the problem is solvable, and providing a parameterization of all solutions.  The broader impacts of the eigenstructure assignment theory established by this project go beyond the CPG inspired control design for gait generation. In fact, the theoretical framework encompasses general pattern formation problems, where a number of "agents" form a global pattern through local distributed interactions. In the context of the CPG control, each neuron acts as an "agent" and their synaptic interconnections allow them to exchange information to form neural computing circuits that stimulate various muscles with specific timing to yield a patterned body oscillation. Analogous situations may be found in other contexts; motion coordination of mobile robots for certain operational tasks, formation flight of aircrafts for efficient long-range flight (as in a V-shaped group of migrating birds), etc. In the general context, the "agents" do not have to be neurons, but can be robots, vehicles, animals, molecules, genes, planets, stars, or any members of a group exhibiting a collective behavior. The project contributed to laying a theoretical foundation for understanding and/or achieving pattern formations of multiple dynamical agents.       Last Modified: 09/24/2015       Submitted by: Tetsuya Iwasaki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
