<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Top-Quark Pair Production Beyond NLO</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professor Andrea Ferroglia at the New York City College of Technology (CUNY). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The beginning of operations at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN is very likely to coincide with the beginning of a new chapter in the history of particle physics.  One of the primary goals of the LHC is to study the phenomena which lead to the breaking of the electroweak symmetry, and therefore to search for the Higgs boson.  In order to extract the most information from the data that the LHC will be providing, it is important to be able to obtain theoretical predictions which are at least as accurate as the expected experimental measurements.  The main objective of Professor Ferroglia's research is to contribute to the calculation of the top-quark pair production beyond next-to-leading order (NLO). In particular, Professor Ferroglia plans to calculate two-loop matrix elements for the gluon-fusion and quark-annihilation channels, and study the resummation of large logarithmic corrections at next-to-next-to-leading logarithmic accuracy by applying a recently developed resummation procedure based on soft-collinear effective theory. These results will enable scientists to obtain precise theoretical predictions for some important top-quark observables that will be measured at the LHC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is also envisioned to have significant broader impacts.  The proposed research plan will be carried out at New York City College of Technology (CUNY). This college plays a leading role in the education of minorities underrepresented in the sciences and engineering. Professor Ferroglia plans to contribute to the efforts of the college by mentoring groups of students who have an interest in particle physics. The goal of this activity will be to provide the students with a non-technical but logically coherent view of the current status of particle physics. The students will present the result of their work to the college community at large in dedicated events. Professor Ferroglia's research activities will also contribute to the development of the recently established Center for Theoretical Physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1068317</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferroglia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Ferroglia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aferroglia@citytech.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7182605603</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY New York City College of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<ZipCode>112012902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7182605560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Jay Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>611930657</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY New York City College of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112012902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Jay Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';"><span>The research activity supported by this award focused on the study of the production &nbsp;of top-quark pairs at hadron colliders. The top quark is the heaviest elementary particle in the Standard Model of particle physics. Currently, large numbers of top-antitop pairs are produced at the Large Hadron Collider, which is operating at CERN in Geneva, Switzerland. Due to its large mass, the top-quark is the Standard Model particle which interacts most strongly with the Higgs boson. As such, the study of the top quark and its properties can provide valuable information about the electroweak symmetry breaking sector of the Standard Model.</span></span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">Due to the precision already reached by experiments at the LHC, precise predictions for the physical observables related to top-quark pair production are of crucial importance. In the work supported by this grant, we contributed to the study of top-quark production with two different approaches:</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">i) Study of the soft emission corrections by means of Soft Collinear Effective Theory (SCET) methods, and</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">ii) Analytic evaluation of sets of two-loop diagrams for top-quark pair production.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">The results achieved and documented in several peer-reviewed publications are the following:</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">1) Calculation of the top-quark forward backward asymmetry measured at the Tevatron by including soft emission corrections up to next-to-next-to-leading logarithmic (NNLL) accuracy.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">2) Study of the factorization properties of the top pair production partonic cross section in the double soft emission and small mass limit. This kinematic region allows for the description of events in which the top quarks are "boosted", i.e. the partonic center of mass energy is much larger than the top-quark mass. Within this framework, the PI and his collaborators &nbsp;obtained &nbsp;improved approximate next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) formulas for the total cross section, for the pair invariant mass distribution, and for the top-quark transverse momentum distribution.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">3) Calculation of the cross section for the production of pairs of supersymmetric partners of the top quark (top squarks or "stops") at approximate NNLO and at NNLL accuracy. These calculations were carried out by employing the SCET methods previously applied to top pair production.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">4) Calculation of all of the two loop diagrams which include a closed light-quark loop in the gluon fusion channel for the production of a top pair. Our calculations are analytical and were carried out by using a method which allows one to rewrite the squared amplitude as a linear combination of a set of master integrals. The final result for the squared amplitude was written in terms of generalized harmonic polylogarithms.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">5) A pedagogical introduction to SCET was written. This work is suitable for advanced graduate students starting their research career. A special emphasis was given to applications of SCET to hadron collider processes.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: 'Liberation Serif';">A series of ancillary projects, related either to SCET or to precision electroweak physics, in which the top quark plays a crucial role, also led to publications:</span><...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The research activity supported by this award focused on the study of the production  of top-quark pairs at hadron colliders. The top quark is the heaviest elementary particle in the Standard Model of particle physics. Currently, large numbers of top-antitop pairs are produced at the Large Hadron Collider, which is operating at CERN in Geneva, Switzerland. Due to its large mass, the top-quark is the Standard Model particle which interacts most strongly with the Higgs boson. As such, the study of the top quark and its properties can provide valuable information about the electroweak symmetry breaking sector of the Standard Model. Due to the precision already reached by experiments at the LHC, precise predictions for the physical observables related to top-quark pair production are of crucial importance. In the work supported by this grant, we contributed to the study of top-quark production with two different approaches: i) Study of the soft emission corrections by means of Soft Collinear Effective Theory (SCET) methods, and ii) Analytic evaluation of sets of two-loop diagrams for top-quark pair production. The results achieved and documented in several peer-reviewed publications are the following: 1) Calculation of the top-quark forward backward asymmetry measured at the Tevatron by including soft emission corrections up to next-to-next-to-leading logarithmic (NNLL) accuracy. 2) Study of the factorization properties of the top pair production partonic cross section in the double soft emission and small mass limit. This kinematic region allows for the description of events in which the top quarks are "boosted", i.e. the partonic center of mass energy is much larger than the top-quark mass. Within this framework, the PI and his collaborators  obtained  improved approximate next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) formulas for the total cross section, for the pair invariant mass distribution, and for the top-quark transverse momentum distribution. 3) Calculation of the cross section for the production of pairs of supersymmetric partners of the top quark (top squarks or "stops") at approximate NNLO and at NNLL accuracy. These calculations were carried out by employing the SCET methods previously applied to top pair production. 4) Calculation of all of the two loop diagrams which include a closed light-quark loop in the gluon fusion channel for the production of a top pair. Our calculations are analytical and were carried out by using a method which allows one to rewrite the squared amplitude as a linear combination of a set of master integrals. The final result for the squared amplitude was written in terms of generalized harmonic polylogarithms. 5) A pedagogical introduction to SCET was written. This work is suitable for advanced graduate students starting their research career. A special emphasis was given to applications of SCET to hadron collider processes. A series of ancillary projects, related either to SCET or to precision electroweak physics, in which the top quark plays a crucial role, also led to publications: a) The hard functions for all of the 2 to 2 scattering processes in massless QCD were evaluated up to NNLO. These hard functions are needed if one desires to implement resummation up to NNNLL for these processes. b) An historical overview on radiative corrections on precision electroweak physics was written. c) A calculation of the muon decay including the complete dependence on the muon and electron mass was carried out. This study allowed us to correct an error in the published literature. The tools developed during the completion of this grant will be applied to other processes of interest for the Large Hadron Collider physics program. For example, a study of the associated production of a top pair and a Higgs boson to approximate NNLO has already begun. This grant provided partial support for one of the students at the CUNY Graduate Center, Mr. Zhibai Zhang. Two of the publications supported by this grant were coa...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
