<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Low Temperature Transcriptional Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4738001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4738001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dokamuro@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924508</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI:  M. Thomashow (Michigan State University)&lt;br/&gt;CoPIs:  C. Chan (Michigan State University) and T. Chen (Oregon State University; subawardee)&lt;br/&gt;Collaborator:  S.-H. Shiu (Michigan State University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long range goals of the project are to gain a systems level understanding of plant responses to abiotic stress and to use the first principles gained to develop novel strategies to improve the stress tolerance of agriculturally important crops.  These goals are important as abiotic stresses limit the geographical locations where crops can be grown and account for the majority of losses in yield on an annual basis.  The overall objective is to identify the low temperature transcriptional networks that plants have evolved to survive freezing.  As there is a direct link between freezing and dehydration injury, the results should also provide further insights into the nature of gene modules that impart tolerance to drought and other dehydration stresses.  The specific aims of the project are two-fold.  The first is to develop a detailed understanding of the low temperature transcriptional network of Arabidopsis and determine which components contribute to freezing tolerance.  This will be accomplished by identifying transcription factors and other regulatory proteins that have key roles in configuring the low temperature transcriptome; identifying the cis-acting DNA regulatory elements through which these regulatory proteins function; and identifying the regulatory programs and gene modules that contribute to freezing tolerance (and potentially tolerance to drought and other abiotic stresses).  The second aim of this project is to determine whether the low temperature transcriptional networks and gene modules that impart freezing tolerance in Arabidopsis are conserved in plants that cold acclimate (i.e., increase in freezing tolerance in response to low non-freezing temperatures) and whether "deficiencies" in these networks and modules contribute to the freezing sensitivity of those plants that do not cold acclimate.  This aim will be accomplished through comparative genomic analysis of three closely related Solanum species which differ in cold tolerance: S. commersonii, potato and tomato.  Together, the proposed studies incorporate the determination of gene expression at a genome level, a comparative genomic analysis of model and crop species, and the integration of computational analysis and empirical testing to reconstruct and model transcriptional regulatory networks that are fundamental to plant life and have importance in agriculture.     &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Improving the abiotic stress tolerance of crops is crucial to meeting future demands for food and fiber.  In addition, it is a key component of an emerging national vision to produce sufficient biomass per year in the U.S. to replace significant percentages of petroleum-based transportation fuels with biofuels produced from renewable resources.  The studies proposed here directly relate to these important areas as they will provide a deeper understanding of the genomic mechanisms that plants have evolved to cope with abiotic stress and have the potential to provide genetic tools to improve the abiotic stress tolerance of plants.  Microarray data generated in the course of these studies will be available through a project website (http://aztec.stanford.edu/cold/index.html) and through GEO and ArrayExpress.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will also contribute to the training of a next generation of scientists who are experienced in bringing genomic, bioinformatic and computational approaches to bear on fundamental questions in biology.  Finally, the project includes a summer undergraduate education and research training program which will target inclusion of underrepresented groups of our society.  The goal is to provide the students with opportunities to learn more about different areas of genomic research and to discuss broadly and informally issues that relate to pursuing careers in science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0701709</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomashow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael F Thomashow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michael.thomashow@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173532270</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449086</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tony</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tony H Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chent@hort.oregonstate.edu.</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417375444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Chan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christina Chan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krischan@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174324530</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000187768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~908897</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~904141</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~1921322</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1003641</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our long-term objective is to understand at a molecular level, how plants respond to abiotic stresses such as extremes in temperature, drought and high salinity, and to develop a set of &ldquo;first principles&rdquo; that can be used to improve the stress tolerance of agriculturally important crops for food, and potentially, renewable sources of bioenergy.&nbsp; The fundamental goal of this particular project was to learn more about the regulatory pathways that contribute to plant freezing tolerance.&nbsp; Improved crop freezing tolerance could greatly expand the regions where freezing sensitive crops are currently grown and increase crop yield on an annual basis.</p> <p>&nbsp;The results that we obtained in this project provide valuable new insights into the pathways that contribute to plant freezing tolerance.&nbsp; In previous work funded by NSF, we discovered the CBF pathway, which has been shown by us and others to have a major role in freezing (and drought) tolerance and to be highly conserved in plants that can cold acclimate; i.e., increase in freezing tolerance in response to low non-freezing temperatures.&nbsp; In this project, we identified six regulatory proteins that control the expression of the CBF pathway in response to either low temperature, the time of day, or the length of day, and contribute to plant freezing tolerance.&nbsp; The identification of these regulatory proteins open up new lines of investigation that have the potential to lead to the development of novel approaches to improve plant stress tolerance.&nbsp; In addition, we have identified new DNA regulatory elements that impart stress-regulated gene expression and provide insights into the evolution of stress tolerance pathways.&nbsp; We have also developed new computational approaches to identify genes that are regulated in response to environmental and physiological inputs, approaches that go beyond plant biology and can be used in molecular medicine studies centered on improving human health.&nbsp; To date, our findings have resulted in the publication of 13 primary peer-reviewed research articles in high quality scholarly journals including three in the <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</em>&nbsp; In addition, we have deposited raw gene expression data in public databases and have made our regulatory analysis algorithms available on the Web.</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em>In addition to valuable research findings, our project contributed to the training of young&nbsp; &ldquo;next generation&rdquo; scientists and provided lab research opportunities for undergraduates considering &ldquo;STEM&rdquo; (science, technology, engineering and math)-related careers.&nbsp; Specifically, our project provided research training for seven postdocs (four women), five graduate students (all women), and thirteen undergraduate students (eleven women including two who are African American and one Hispanic).&nbsp; One post-doc, Dr. Cheng Zou, decided that she needed to improve her statistical skills and went back to graduate school and now has an M.S. in statistics.&nbsp; Two of the graduate students, Colleen Doherty and Malia Dong, received NSF Postdoctoral Fellowships to continue their research training at UCSD and the Danforth Plant Science Center, respectively. &nbsp;Dr. Doherty recently accepted an Assistant Professor faculty position at North Carolina State University, and Marcela Carvallo, who was a graduate student on the project, now has a Research Scientist III position at Life Technologies. &nbsp;Katherine Pillman and Xuewei Wang, who were postdocs on the project, are now, respectively a Research Scientist at the Center for Cancer Biology in Adelaide, Australia, and a Research Scientist at Thomson Reuters. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2013<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;F&nbsp;Thomashow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our long-term objective is to understand at a molecular level, how plants respond to abiotic stresses such as extremes in temperature, drought and high salinity, and to develop a set of "first principles" that can be used to improve the stress tolerance of agriculturally important crops for food, and potentially, renewable sources of bioenergy.  The fundamental goal of this particular project was to learn more about the regulatory pathways that contribute to plant freezing tolerance.  Improved crop freezing tolerance could greatly expand the regions where freezing sensitive crops are currently grown and increase crop yield on an annual basis.   The results that we obtained in this project provide valuable new insights into the pathways that contribute to plant freezing tolerance.  In previous work funded by NSF, we discovered the CBF pathway, which has been shown by us and others to have a major role in freezing (and drought) tolerance and to be highly conserved in plants that can cold acclimate; i.e., increase in freezing tolerance in response to low non-freezing temperatures.  In this project, we identified six regulatory proteins that control the expression of the CBF pathway in response to either low temperature, the time of day, or the length of day, and contribute to plant freezing tolerance.  The identification of these regulatory proteins open up new lines of investigation that have the potential to lead to the development of novel approaches to improve plant stress tolerance.  In addition, we have identified new DNA regulatory elements that impart stress-regulated gene expression and provide insights into the evolution of stress tolerance pathways.  We have also developed new computational approaches to identify genes that are regulated in response to environmental and physiological inputs, approaches that go beyond plant biology and can be used in molecular medicine studies centered on improving human health.  To date, our findings have resulted in the publication of 13 primary peer-reviewed research articles in high quality scholarly journals including three in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.  In addition, we have deposited raw gene expression data in public databases and have made our regulatory analysis algorithms available on the Web.   In addition to valuable research findings, our project contributed to the training of young  "next generation" scientists and provided lab research opportunities for undergraduates considering "STEM" (science, technology, engineering and math)-related careers.  Specifically, our project provided research training for seven postdocs (four women), five graduate students (all women), and thirteen undergraduate students (eleven women including two who are African American and one Hispanic).  One post-doc, Dr. Cheng Zou, decided that she needed to improve her statistical skills and went back to graduate school and now has an M.S. in statistics.  Two of the graduate students, Colleen Doherty and Malia Dong, received NSF Postdoctoral Fellowships to continue their research training at UCSD and the Danforth Plant Science Center, respectively.  Dr. Doherty recently accepted an Assistant Professor faculty position at North Carolina State University, and Marcela Carvallo, who was a graduate student on the project, now has a Research Scientist III position at Life Technologies.  Katherine Pillman and Xuewei Wang, who were postdocs on the project, are now, respectively a Research Scientist at the Center for Cancer Biology in Adelaide, Australia, and a Research Scientist at Thomson Reuters.            Last Modified: 11/18/2013       Submitted by: Michael F Thomashow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
