<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Elwha Science Education Project (ESEP):   Increasing the Representation in the Geosciences by Native American Youth Through Participation in Environmental Restoration Projects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1216688.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1506494</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06000001</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jill L. Karsten</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Native Americans are poorly represented in all science, technology, engineering, and mathematics fields. This under representation results from numerous cultural, economic, and historical factors.  The broad goal of the Elwha Science Education Project (ESEP) is to develop a network of partners delivering culturally-integrated, geoscience education to Native American young people in grades 6-12 in the northern Olympic Peninsula of Washington while ultimately increasing the number of these students that pursue a geoscience career and/or geoscience degree by creating a pipeline of interested high school graduates into our higher education partners.  The ESEP will develop unique approaches to informal geoscience education using environmental restoration as a consequence of dam removal as a centerpiece.   Hands-on, geoscience education activities will be delivered in a culturally integrated manner.  Tribal elders and educators will participate in all phases of the project.  Local school districts will be involved during the academic year.  All student participants will have access to year-round mentors and activities.  Technical expertise will be provided by the PI; access to land and data related to the planned Elwha River Restoration Project will be provided by Olympic National Park; and educational activities will be carried out by the non-profit, Olympic Park Institute.  Additional partners include the Lower Elwha Klallam Tribe, Port Angeles (WA) School District and Crescent (WA) School District.  It is estimated that the project will directly involve 80 Native American students, 10 local science teachers, and indirectly, 600-700 Olympic Peninsula young people.   Broader impacts of the ESEP are realized by the development of a culture-based model for investing an entire Native American community in the geoscience education of their young people.  This project is the continuation of a successful two-year pilot.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0703676</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert S Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ryoung@wcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8282273822</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243442</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Carolina University</Name>
<CityName>Cullowhee</CityName>
<ZipCode>287239022</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8282273174</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>440 HFR Admin Bldg</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WCU]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066300039</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN CAROLINA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Carolina University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cullowhee</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>287239022</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[440 HFR Admin Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1697</Code>
<Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7622</Code>
<Text>GEO-LSAMP LINKAGES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1697</Code>
<Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~323558</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~569887</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~301211</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~311838</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Native Americans are poorly represented in all science, technology and  engineering fields. This under-representation results from numerous  cultural, economic, and historical factors. The Elwha Science Education  Project (ESEP), initiated in 2007 and funded initially by the National  Science Foundation, strives to construct a culturally-integrated and  place-based geoscience education program for Native American young  people through engagement of the entire tribal community. The ESEP has  developed a unique approach to informal geoscience education, using the  Elwha River Restoration Project as a centerpiece. Environmental  restoration is an increasingly important goal for tribes. By integrating  geoscience activities with community tradition and history, project  stakeholders hope to show students the relevance of science to their  day-to-day lives. The ESEP's strength lies in its participatory  structure and unique network of partners, which include Olympic National  Park; the non-profit, educational center Naturebridge; a geologist  providing oversight and technical expertise; and the Lower Elwha Klallam  Tribe (LEKT). Lower Elwha tribal elders and educators share in all  phases of the project, from planning and implementation to recruitment  of students and discipline. The project works collaboratively with  tribal scientists and cultural educators, along with science educators  to develop curriculum and best practices for this group of students. Use  of hands-on, place-based outdoor activities engage students and connect  them with the science outside their back doors. Project evaluation  results indicate that most (75% or more) students were highly engaged  approximately 90% of the time during science instruction. Recruitment of  students has been particularly successful, due to a high degree of  community involvement. Preliminary evaluations of the ESEP's outcomes  indicate success in improving the outlook of the tribe's youth towards  the geosciences and science, in general. The project has also helped to  raise the high school graduation rate for LEKT young people to record  levels. Perhaps the greatest success of the project is the fact that  funding has been secured to continue work for three years AFTER the NSF  funding has ended and our tribal partners are now leading the project.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/10/2015<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;S&nbsp;Young</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Native Americans are poorly represented in all science, technology and  engineering fields. This under-representation results from numerous  cultural, economic, and historical factors. The Elwha Science Education  Project (ESEP), initiated in 2007 and funded initially by the National  Science Foundation, strives to construct a culturally-integrated and  place-based geoscience education program for Native American young  people through engagement of the entire tribal community. The ESEP has  developed a unique approach to informal geoscience education, using the  Elwha River Restoration Project as a centerpiece. Environmental  restoration is an increasingly important goal for tribes. By integrating  geoscience activities with community tradition and history, project  stakeholders hope to show students the relevance of science to their  day-to-day lives. The ESEP's strength lies in its participatory  structure and unique network of partners, which include Olympic National  Park; the non-profit, educational center Naturebridge; a geologist  providing oversight and technical expertise; and the Lower Elwha Klallam  Tribe (LEKT). Lower Elwha tribal elders and educators share in all  phases of the project, from planning and implementation to recruitment  of students and discipline. The project works collaboratively with  tribal scientists and cultural educators, along with science educators  to develop curriculum and best practices for this group of students. Use  of hands-on, place-based outdoor activities engage students and connect  them with the science outside their back doors. Project evaluation  results indicate that most (75% or more) students were highly engaged  approximately 90% of the time during science instruction. Recruitment of  students has been particularly successful, due to a high degree of  community involvement. Preliminary evaluations of the ESEP's outcomes  indicate success in improving the outlook of the tribe's youth towards  the geosciences and science, in general. The project has also helped to  raise the high school graduation rate for LEKT young people to record  levels. Perhaps the greatest success of the project is the fact that  funding has been secured to continue work for three years AFTER the NSF  funding has ended and our tribal partners are now leading the project.       Last Modified: 02/10/2015       Submitted by: Robert S Young]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
