<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cosmic Beginnings and Cosmic Fate: Confronting Inflation and the Dark Sector with Observations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>847283.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>616423</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nigel Sharp</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nsharp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>AST-0708849&lt;br/&gt;Wandelt&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a broad and ambitious program of research and education related to precision cosmology, focusing on the dual quests to determine the initial conditions of the Universe and to discover the physical properties of dark energy.  New statistical techniques for Bayesian covariance analysis can take full advantage of the information contained in the cosmic microwave background and other cosmological probes.  Applying these techniques will allow this project to close in on an understanding of how the cosmos began, and what constitutes the dark energy that so dominates it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The associated education program capitalizes on existing infrastructure at the University of Illinois.  An exciting new "Einstein's Physics" one-week curriculum will partner with the Colleges of Engineering and Education, and the university's office of Women in Engineering, as part of a camp for high school girls.  Support for these activities is part of this award.  The research project also enhances graduate and postdoctoral education through an international component associated with the Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics in Munich.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the WMAP satellite produces new data, the Planck satellite launches in 2007, the South Pole Telescope comes online, and other cosmological data become available, the present program of research and education will uncover the initial conditions of the Universe, place strong constraints on the physical properties of dark energy, and open new avenues for the involvement of women and under-represented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0708849</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wandelt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin D Wandelt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bwandelt@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173339374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000194498</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~71855</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~239638</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~230860</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~74070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Studying cosmic beginnings and cosmic fate first requires developing the right tools to allow a detailed quantitative comparison of astronomical data sets with theory. This project delivered a broad set of mathematical, statistical and computational tools to probe deeper into the mysteries of the beginning of the cosmos and the expansion history of the universe since those beginnings &nbsp;than was possible at any time before. Through these tools the award resulted in a vast array of new science, culminating in&nbsp;<span>&nbsp;"constraints [that] represent the highest precision tests to date of physical mechanisms for the origin of cosmic structure." (from the abstract of the 2013 paper&nbsp;co-led by PI Wandelt on primordial non-Gaussianity from the Planck space mission).</span></span></p> <p>Some of the publications resulting from this award number amongst the most highly cited papers in astrophysics. Some sparked off new research directions, such as the development of new techniques to understand the observed distribution of galaxies in current galaxy redshift surveys. One technique teaches the computer all there is to know about gravity and then shows it the observed distribution of galaxies. The algorithm can then infer histories of gravitational evolution of the universe from its primordial state until now that are consistent wtih the data. This detailed information suggests new, and unprecedentedly precise ways of testing the current theoretical paradigm against future observations.</p> <p>Along the way we developed new methods for handling data sets on the sphere, machine learning tools to extract precision information on the composition, geometry, and initial conditions of the universe, accelerating computations by orders of magnitude without loss of accuracy, and new techniques for solving millions of simultaneous equations that allow us optimally to probe the statistics of the cosmic density field.</p> <p>This project provided research and educational opportunities for graduate students, prepared postdocs for their careers in cosmology and in the private sector.&nbsp;and reached out to tens of thousands of participants actively supporting the online participatory research project cosmologyathome.org.</p> <p>Taking a larger perspective, this award helped define and make feasilbe the field of principled cosmostatistics - the careful application of statistical techniques to a wide array of fundamental problems in cosmology. One example, is the direct observation of the physical effect dark energy has on binding energy of matter concentrations through measuring higher-order correlation functions, now observed in the Planck data.</p> <p>The benefit of this award will be felt in the field of cosmology for years to come. Many new investigations were sparked by the work we began here. We now use the results obtained in this award to study in unprecedented detail&nbsp;the cosmic web of clumps, filaments and sheets of matter surrounding underdense regions, discovering new ways to learn about the mysterious dark energy that is driving cosmic acceleration, and to learn even more details about the physical initial conditions of the universe from the observed galaxy distribution.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2015<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;D&nbsp;Wandelt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Studying cosmic beginnings and cosmic fate first requires developing the right tools to allow a detailed quantitative comparison of astronomical data sets with theory. This project delivered a broad set of mathematical, statistical and computational tools to probe deeper into the mysteries of the beginning of the cosmos and the expansion history of the universe since those beginnings  than was possible at any time before. Through these tools the award resulted in a vast array of new science, culminating in  "constraints [that] represent the highest precision tests to date of physical mechanisms for the origin of cosmic structure." (from the abstract of the 2013 paper co-led by PI Wandelt on primordial non-Gaussianity from the Planck space mission).  Some of the publications resulting from this award number amongst the most highly cited papers in astrophysics. Some sparked off new research directions, such as the development of new techniques to understand the observed distribution of galaxies in current galaxy redshift surveys. One technique teaches the computer all there is to know about gravity and then shows it the observed distribution of galaxies. The algorithm can then infer histories of gravitational evolution of the universe from its primordial state until now that are consistent wtih the data. This detailed information suggests new, and unprecedentedly precise ways of testing the current theoretical paradigm against future observations.  Along the way we developed new methods for handling data sets on the sphere, machine learning tools to extract precision information on the composition, geometry, and initial conditions of the universe, accelerating computations by orders of magnitude without loss of accuracy, and new techniques for solving millions of simultaneous equations that allow us optimally to probe the statistics of the cosmic density field.  This project provided research and educational opportunities for graduate students, prepared postdocs for their careers in cosmology and in the private sector. and reached out to tens of thousands of participants actively supporting the online participatory research project cosmologyathome.org.  Taking a larger perspective, this award helped define and make feasilbe the field of principled cosmostatistics - the careful application of statistical techniques to a wide array of fundamental problems in cosmology. One example, is the direct observation of the physical effect dark energy has on binding energy of matter concentrations through measuring higher-order correlation functions, now observed in the Planck data.  The benefit of this award will be felt in the field of cosmology for years to come. Many new investigations were sparked by the work we began here. We now use the results obtained in this award to study in unprecedented detail the cosmic web of clumps, filaments and sheets of matter surrounding underdense regions, discovering new ways to learn about the mysterious dark energy that is driving cosmic acceleration, and to learn even more details about the physical initial conditions of the universe from the observed galaxy distribution.        Last Modified: 12/23/2015       Submitted by: Benjamin D Wandelt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
