<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Microbial Inventory Research Across Diverse Aquatic LTERs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>840000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>854998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Lydeard</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will establish a Microbial Biodiversity Survey and Inventory across all 13 of the major aquatic (marine and freshwater) Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) sites established by the NSF US LTER Program. The long-term objective of the study is to document and describe baseline diversity and relative abundance data for both common and rare members of microbial communities located in aquatic LTER sites and to relate this diversity to the underlying physical and chemical environment. The project employs a new, high-volume DNA sequencing technology based on the sequencing of small ribosomal RNA regions that are especially variable, which will allow for discovery of novel microbial diversity in the bacterial, archaeal and eukaryal domains of life. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biodiversity in general, and microbial biodiversity in particular is important because microorganisms help shape Earth's habitability by orchestrating the major carbon transformations, biogeochemical cycles, and input into atmospheric composition. Radical fluctuations in microbial populations caused by changes in the environment pose irreversible threats to our quality of life and the entire biosphere. The resulting data will directly benefit participating LTERs that actively communicate results to policy makers, natural resource managers, the broader scientific community and the general public. Podcasts are planned to be coordinated with the Schoolyard LTER program.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0717390</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Amaral Zettler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda A Amaral Zettler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amaral@mbl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082897259</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marine Biological Laboratory</Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082897243</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7 M B L ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001933779</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARINE BIOLOGICAL LABORATORY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marine Biological Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7 M B L ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7187</Code>
<Text>MICROBIAL GENOME SEQUENCING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY SURVEYS &amp; INVENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~207500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~7498</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The MIRADA-LTERS (Microbial Inventory Research Across Diverse Aquatic Long Term Ecological Sites) was a large-scale microbial biodiversity survey and inventory across all 13 aquatic (marine and freshwater) LTER sites established by the NSF LTER Program. Our primary objective was to collaborate with existing sampling and research efforts within LTER sites to describe microbial (bacterial, archaeal and eukaryal) diversity and abundance primarily using next generation DNA sequencing approaches. Additionally, we assessed and documented the local physical and geochemical conditions corresponding to each microbial sample taken. This study identified both the common and rare members of the microbial populations in their environmental context, which can provide valuable baseline data for studying the interactions of population structure and ecosystem change, as well as describing microbially-mediated trophic dynamics and local biogeochemical processes.</p> <p>Our objectives were to: (1) use molecular approaches to document and describe baseline microbial diversity and relative abundance at aquatic LTER sites; (2) determine which microbial species are common to freshwater and marine LTERS; (3) determine whether diverse aquatic LTER sites possess &ldquo;signature&rdquo; assemblages characterized by location, season and environmental parameters; (4) discover new microbial species that represent novel microorganisms; and (5) explore large-scale patterns in microbial biogeography.</p> <p>Sampling, DNA sequencing, and recovery of environmental contextual data are complete for the project. Analyses are completed or underway on local datasets (lead by LTER PIs, postdoctoral students, graduate students or honors undergraduates) and for the cross-site syntheses led by the Amaral-Zettler laboratory. This study generated over 3.68 million DNA reads from bacterial, archaeal and eukaryotic community members from &gt;200 samples and &gt;600 datasets.&nbsp; The project has resulted in 7 publications to date with several in progress. Graduate and postdoctoral students are taking the lead on preparing manuscripts for their LTERS. We are anticipating manuscripts from the majority of participating LTERS in addition to the cross-site comparative manuscripts. A total of 12 graduate students, 8 postdoctoral scientists and 3 undergraduates have participated in the MIRADA effort to date. Information and data from the project are being posted at:&nbsp; <a href="http://vamps.mbl.edu/portals/mirada/mirada.php">http://vamps.mbl.edu/portals/mirada/mirada.php</a>) via our standard guest login (username: guest; password: guest).</p> <p>The amount of new information gained from this study will eclipse what we currently know about the numbers of different kinds of microbes at the LTER locations and in aquatic systems in general by many orders of magnitude. The strategy we have taken has unveiled novel taxa that may be of economic or medical importance that can be further pursued by researchers and students studying at the given LTERs. Our study is very much in line with the goals of the LTER program because it: 1) enabled a cross-site study of a diverse array of ecosystems at multiple spatial and temporal scales; 2) contributed to our understanding of microbial biogeography by providing empirical data to enhance existing models; 3) provided databases that will make data available to the broader scientific community, as well as natural resource managers, policy makers and the general public; 4) provided archived samples for future research projects; and 5) provided undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral students an opportunity to participate in different phases of the research through participating LTERs by either sample collection and/or data analysis and synthesis. Because some LTERs have foci that are less oriented towards molecular microbial ecological approaches, the work has further served to enhanc...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The MIRADA-LTERS (Microbial Inventory Research Across Diverse Aquatic Long Term Ecological Sites) was a large-scale microbial biodiversity survey and inventory across all 13 aquatic (marine and freshwater) LTER sites established by the NSF LTER Program. Our primary objective was to collaborate with existing sampling and research efforts within LTER sites to describe microbial (bacterial, archaeal and eukaryal) diversity and abundance primarily using next generation DNA sequencing approaches. Additionally, we assessed and documented the local physical and geochemical conditions corresponding to each microbial sample taken. This study identified both the common and rare members of the microbial populations in their environmental context, which can provide valuable baseline data for studying the interactions of population structure and ecosystem change, as well as describing microbially-mediated trophic dynamics and local biogeochemical processes.  Our objectives were to: (1) use molecular approaches to document and describe baseline microbial diversity and relative abundance at aquatic LTER sites; (2) determine which microbial species are common to freshwater and marine LTERS; (3) determine whether diverse aquatic LTER sites possess "signature" assemblages characterized by location, season and environmental parameters; (4) discover new microbial species that represent novel microorganisms; and (5) explore large-scale patterns in microbial biogeography.  Sampling, DNA sequencing, and recovery of environmental contextual data are complete for the project. Analyses are completed or underway on local datasets (lead by LTER PIs, postdoctoral students, graduate students or honors undergraduates) and for the cross-site syntheses led by the Amaral-Zettler laboratory. This study generated over 3.68 million DNA reads from bacterial, archaeal and eukaryotic community members from &gt;200 samples and &gt;600 datasets.  The project has resulted in 7 publications to date with several in progress. Graduate and postdoctoral students are taking the lead on preparing manuscripts for their LTERS. We are anticipating manuscripts from the majority of participating LTERS in addition to the cross-site comparative manuscripts. A total of 12 graduate students, 8 postdoctoral scientists and 3 undergraduates have participated in the MIRADA effort to date. Information and data from the project are being posted at:  http://vamps.mbl.edu/portals/mirada/mirada.php) via our standard guest login (username: guest; password: guest).  The amount of new information gained from this study will eclipse what we currently know about the numbers of different kinds of microbes at the LTER locations and in aquatic systems in general by many orders of magnitude. The strategy we have taken has unveiled novel taxa that may be of economic or medical importance that can be further pursued by researchers and students studying at the given LTERs. Our study is very much in line with the goals of the LTER program because it: 1) enabled a cross-site study of a diverse array of ecosystems at multiple spatial and temporal scales; 2) contributed to our understanding of microbial biogeography by providing empirical data to enhance existing models; 3) provided databases that will make data available to the broader scientific community, as well as natural resource managers, policy makers and the general public; 4) provided archived samples for future research projects; and 5) provided undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral students an opportunity to participate in different phases of the research through participating LTERs by either sample collection and/or data analysis and synthesis. Because some LTERs have foci that are less oriented towards molecular microbial ecological approaches, the work has further served to enhance the breadth of research that scientists can partake in at a given LTER.       Last Modified: 12/12/2011       Submitted by: Linda A Amaral Zettler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
