<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Community responses to river drying in an arid-land ecosystem: a field and experimental study</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>373414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rivers that flow through arid lands provide a limiting resource for human population and economic growth while simultaneously supporting a diverse community of plants and animals.  Consequently, these rivers are often targets of intensive restoration activities based, perhaps erroneously, on concepts developed for mesic (wetter) rivers.  Arid-land systems differ from mesic counterparts in that they experience enormous variability in flows that range from high floods to being nearly dry.  Low flows and river intermittency are common occurrences, and drying events may be important for enhancing species diversity by allowing coexistence of organisms that specialize on high- and low-flow conditions, respectively.  However, actual effects of seasonal variability in discharge, especially low flows, on aquatic communities remain largely unknown.  &lt;br/&gt; To address this gap in knowledge, a field and experimental study will be conducted on the Rio Grande in New Mexico.  Changes biomass and nutrient composition of the algae, invertebrates, and fishes that make up the river?s food web will be tracked.  Macronutrients, such as carbon, nitrogen, and phosphorus, will be used as tracers to understand the dynamics of community changes associated with flow variability and drying in natural river environments.  Finally, an experimental study will manipulate key variables that appear to strongly affect species abundance and diversity in drying river environments.  The outcomes of this study will aid development of scientifically defensible restoration policies and establishment of minimum flows in arid-land rivers.  Development of such policies is of paramount economic importance to arid and semi-arid regions worldwide. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0717047</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas F Turner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>turnert@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052777541</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000280935</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868853094</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~102401</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~127308</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~136205</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Rivers that flow through&nbsp;arid lands&nbsp;provide a critical resource for human population and economic growth while simultaneously supporting a diverse community of plants and animals.&nbsp; Consequently, dryland rivers are often targets of intensive restoration activities based, perhaps erroneously, on concepts developed for rivers where water is more abundant.&nbsp; Dryland systems differ from wetter counterparts in that they experience enormous variability in flows that range from high floods to nearly complete drying. Low flows and river intermittency are common occurrences, and drying events may be important for enhancing species diversity by allowing coexistence of organisms that specialize on high- and low-flow conditions, respectively.&nbsp; However, actual effects of seasonal variability in discharge, especially low flows, on biodiversity and abundance of aquatic organisms remain largely unknown.&nbsp;</p> <p>To address this gap in knowledge, our research group at the University of New Mexico (composed of 5 senior scientists, 4 graduate students, and 11 undergraduate students) conducted field and experimental studies of the Rio Grande in New Mexico from 2006 to 2011.&nbsp;&nbsp;We tracked changes abundance, biodiversity (e.g., the number of species), and nutrient composition of algae, detritus, invertebrates, and fishes that make up the river food web.&nbsp;&nbsp;We used&nbsp;biogeochemical tracers&nbsp;to understand how nutrients are transferred from organism to organism in the food web and how&nbsp;nutrient flow was&nbsp;affected by floods and drying.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;We employed the same methods in an experimental mesocosm (i.e., cattle tank) study that simulated river drying where we manipulated the amount and kind of nutrients available and the presence and absence of fish.&nbsp; &nbsp;We wanted to know whether nutrient availability or predation or both regulated invertebrate and algal species diversity and abundance in these harsh aquatic environments.</p> <p>Our data showed that algae and aquatic plants are the primary energy source for fishes under most flow conditions, but that invertebrates got their energy from both instream and terrestrial (e.g., tree leaves) sources, the amount of each depending on the river reach, overbank flooding, and flow patterns during the year.&nbsp; Our mesocosm studies showed that decomposing leaves can be an important source of carbon for the entire food web (including larval fishes), but its effects are not realized until several weeks after flooding.&nbsp; During early weeks, water column nutrients are locked up in leaves and only liberated for use by other organisms approximately two to four weeks after flooding when they begin to decompose.&nbsp;&nbsp; Extreme drying events strongly affect feeding relationships that permeate through the food web.&nbsp; Convergence of biogeochemical tracer data between invertebrates and fishes indicated overlapping resource use and food limitation during extended drying events.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our study has, and will continue to contribute to development of scientifically defensible restoration policies and establishment of minimum flows in the Rio Grande. &nbsp;&nbsp;For example, in order to gain nutrients from leaf litter in the floodplain that can be used by organisms, it is necessary to flood these areas for several weeks to allow decomposition.&nbsp; Also, drying and river pooling can increase local abundance and diversity of algae and invertebrates (through effects on light availability and temperature), but can severely deplete diversity and abundance of fishes.&nbsp; Our data further support the idea that water management strategies that mimic the natural hydrograph are likely to best maintain both diversity and abundance of aquatic organisms.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our research&nbsp;team&nbsp;participates in the&nbsp;Middle Rio Grande Collaborative Workgroup that brings stakeholder...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rivers that flow through arid lands provide a critical resource for human population and economic growth while simultaneously supporting a diverse community of plants and animals.  Consequently, dryland rivers are often targets of intensive restoration activities based, perhaps erroneously, on concepts developed for rivers where water is more abundant.  Dryland systems differ from wetter counterparts in that they experience enormous variability in flows that range from high floods to nearly complete drying. Low flows and river intermittency are common occurrences, and drying events may be important for enhancing species diversity by allowing coexistence of organisms that specialize on high- and low-flow conditions, respectively.  However, actual effects of seasonal variability in discharge, especially low flows, on biodiversity and abundance of aquatic organisms remain largely unknown.   To address this gap in knowledge, our research group at the University of New Mexico (composed of 5 senior scientists, 4 graduate students, and 11 undergraduate students) conducted field and experimental studies of the Rio Grande in New Mexico from 2006 to 2011.  We tracked changes abundance, biodiversity (e.g., the number of species), and nutrient composition of algae, detritus, invertebrates, and fishes that make up the river food web.  We used biogeochemical tracers to understand how nutrients are transferred from organism to organism in the food web and how nutrient flow was affected by floods and drying.   We employed the same methods in an experimental mesocosm (i.e., cattle tank) study that simulated river drying where we manipulated the amount and kind of nutrients available and the presence and absence of fish.   We wanted to know whether nutrient availability or predation or both regulated invertebrate and algal species diversity and abundance in these harsh aquatic environments.  Our data showed that algae and aquatic plants are the primary energy source for fishes under most flow conditions, but that invertebrates got their energy from both instream and terrestrial (e.g., tree leaves) sources, the amount of each depending on the river reach, overbank flooding, and flow patterns during the year.  Our mesocosm studies showed that decomposing leaves can be an important source of carbon for the entire food web (including larval fishes), but its effects are not realized until several weeks after flooding.  During early weeks, water column nutrients are locked up in leaves and only liberated for use by other organisms approximately two to four weeks after flooding when they begin to decompose.   Extreme drying events strongly affect feeding relationships that permeate through the food web.  Convergence of biogeochemical tracer data between invertebrates and fishes indicated overlapping resource use and food limitation during extended drying events.   Our study has, and will continue to contribute to development of scientifically defensible restoration policies and establishment of minimum flows in the Rio Grande.   For example, in order to gain nutrients from leaf litter in the floodplain that can be used by organisms, it is necessary to flood these areas for several weeks to allow decomposition.  Also, drying and river pooling can increase local abundance and diversity of algae and invertebrates (through effects on light availability and temperature), but can severely deplete diversity and abundance of fishes.  Our data further support the idea that water management strategies that mimic the natural hydrograph are likely to best maintain both diversity and abundance of aquatic organisms.  Our research team participates in the Middle Rio Grande Collaborative Workgroup that brings stakeholders together to develop policy to simultaneously provide water to users and endangered aquatic species.  This is of paramount economic importance to dryland regions here in the southwestern US.  Finally, as a direct result of support from this award, t...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
