<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: NeTS-NOSS: Sensor Network Synthesis - Opening the Use of Wireless Sensor Networks to Application Experts</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>474000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wireless sensor networks have the potential to revolutionize research areas and&lt;br/&gt;industries that require the distributed collection and aggregation of data,&lt;br/&gt;e.g., civil engineering, biology, and geology.  However, to date their impact&lt;br/&gt;has fallen short of this potential.  This is not surprising; wireless sensor&lt;br/&gt;networks are difficult to design and program.  Experts in application domains&lt;br/&gt;such as biology and civil engineering have neither the training in embedded&lt;br/&gt;system programming and design required to develop adequate wireless sensor&lt;br/&gt;networks, nor the time or inclination to become embedded systems designers.&lt;br/&gt;For wireless sensor networks to live up to their potential, they must be easy&lt;br/&gt;for application experts to design and program instead of requiring embedded&lt;br/&gt;systems design expertise.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to put wireless sensor network design and deployment within&lt;br/&gt;the reach of applications experts.  This project will identify a small set of&lt;br/&gt;application archetypes, described in terms meaningful to application&lt;br/&gt;developers, that capture the most common application structures.  Each&lt;br/&gt;archetype will be backed by a compilable specification written in a simple&lt;br/&gt;high-level archetype-specific language. After customization, a specification&lt;br/&gt;will be passed to a synthesis algorithm to produce a working hardware-software&lt;br/&gt;system.  Synthesis of efficient wireless sensor networks would be intractable&lt;br/&gt;without an appropriate hardware-software platform.  Therefore, this project&lt;br/&gt;will also determine the particular types of hardware and software components&lt;br/&gt;necessary to enable support for wide range of archetypes.  A configurable&lt;br/&gt;hardware-software platform will be developed based on these findings.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0721978</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Henschen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence J Henschen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>henschen@ece.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913338</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316522</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Dowding</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Dowding</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>c-dowding@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474914338</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416843</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Dinda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter A Dinda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdinda@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474677859</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000341788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Dinda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter A Dinda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdinda@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474677859</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000341788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/27/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Dick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert P Dick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dickrp@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474672298</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000167402</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/27/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 N. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7390</Code>
<Text>NETWORKING OF SENSOR SYSTEMS (NOSS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~162000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Wireless sensor networks hold considerable promise for observation and control within science and engineering. &nbsp;For example, structural cracks in infrastructure such as buildings and bridges could be be monitored by sensor networks that call attention to acute problems. &nbsp; However, building, programming, and deploying sensor network applications currently requires deep embedded systems expertise. &nbsp;This limits where sensor networks can be used today. &nbsp;The overall goal of our project was to expand the use of sensor networks to those without embedded systems expertise. &nbsp; The project results demonstrate that it is feasible to do so, and provide a set of tools and techniques, supported by experiment and simulation studies, that enable this.</p> <p>Our project focused on this goal through three threads of resarch. &nbsp;The first thread was in the design, implementation, and evaluation of programming&nbsp;languages and systems geared toward application domain experts. &nbsp; We developed several languages for expressing sensor network applications that, through careful user studies, were shown to enable non-experts to build single node, and whole-network applications. &nbsp; These languages were implemented and incorporated into a web-based system.</p> <p>The second thread of our project was in the design of synthesis toolchains, meaning software that transforms&nbsp;the high-level descriptions given in these&nbsp;languages into effective implementations, including&nbsp;specialized hardware and deployment guidance, under cost,&nbsp;accuracy, and other constraints. &nbsp; We developed a prototype synthesis toolchain that compiled a high-level description from one of the languages we designed to produce a deployable sensor network application. &nbsp; We also developed specialized hardware, including a low power board to wake up a sensor node on an interesting event, and a board for configurable power harvesting.&nbsp;</p> <p>The third thread of research was in applications, where we applied what we learned to&nbsp;example applications and domains, and tried to find new ones. &nbsp;Here, we were largely driven by structural monitoring applications, as described above.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project helped to train four Ph.D. students, two M.S. students, and seven undergraduates, and helped to inform the creation of a sensor networks class at Northwestern. &nbsp; Many parts of our toolchain are available from the project web site, http://absynth-project.org, as are the hardware designs, which we have made open source.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2012<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;A&nbsp;Dinda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wireless sensor networks hold considerable promise for observation and control within science and engineering.  For example, structural cracks in infrastructure such as buildings and bridges could be be monitored by sensor networks that call attention to acute problems.   However, building, programming, and deploying sensor network applications currently requires deep embedded systems expertise.  This limits where sensor networks can be used today.  The overall goal of our project was to expand the use of sensor networks to those without embedded systems expertise.   The project results demonstrate that it is feasible to do so, and provide a set of tools and techniques, supported by experiment and simulation studies, that enable this.  Our project focused on this goal through three threads of resarch.  The first thread was in the design, implementation, and evaluation of programming languages and systems geared toward application domain experts.   We developed several languages for expressing sensor network applications that, through careful user studies, were shown to enable non-experts to build single node, and whole-network applications.   These languages were implemented and incorporated into a web-based system.  The second thread of our project was in the design of synthesis toolchains, meaning software that transforms the high-level descriptions given in these languages into effective implementations, including specialized hardware and deployment guidance, under cost, accuracy, and other constraints.   We developed a prototype synthesis toolchain that compiled a high-level description from one of the languages we designed to produce a deployable sensor network application.   We also developed specialized hardware, including a low power board to wake up a sensor node on an interesting event, and a board for configurable power harvesting.   The third thread of research was in applications, where we applied what we learned to example applications and domains, and tried to find new ones.  Here, we were largely driven by structural monitoring applications, as described above.   The project helped to train four Ph.D. students, two M.S. students, and seven undergraduates, and helped to inform the creation of a sensor networks class at Northwestern.   Many parts of our toolchain are available from the project web site, http://absynth-project.org, as are the hardware designs, which we have made open source.       Last Modified: 10/02/2012       Submitted by: Peter A Dinda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
