<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Terahertz Response of Unique Composite Metamaterials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>GEORGE HADDAD</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;ECCS -0725764&lt;br/&gt;Weili Zhang, Oklahoma State University &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Metamaterials, with both negative permittivity and negative permeability, have opened up an entirely new world of devices that may lead to breakthrough applications in a broad range of disciplines. This project focuses on investigation of composite subwavelength-structured metamaterials using techniques of terahertz spectroscopy. The longer-term goal of this program is to develop integrated and efficient terahertz circuit elements capable of being integrated into compact platforms for applications in aerospace communications and surveillance systems, optoelectronics, and biosensing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed program encompasses multiple research efforts to develop metamaterials functioning at terahertz frequencies. The state-of-the-art terahertz spectroscopy technology will be used to characterize the electrical and magnetic properties of terahertz metamaterials. Novel metamaterial configurations with enhanced magnetic response and low loss will be explored to establish negative index of refraction in the terahertz regime. A proof-of-concept examination of potential use of metamaterials in biosensing will be undertaken. The PIs also propose to explore unique semiconductor metamaterials that exhibit instantaneous electric and magnetic response to electromagnetic radiation. Additionally, magnetic terahertz surface plasmons will be investigated at the surface of two-dimensional metamaterials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The proposed program will enable development of terahertz technology and new generation integrated optoelectronic devices that will impact a broad range of disciplines, particularly aerospace communications, biosensing, and terahertz imaging. The PIs would continue their collaboration with industry in developing terahertz components and microsensors. A new graduate level course, introduction to metamaterials, will be developed for photonics students. New topics in metamaterials will be implemented in an ongoing ?cleanroom open house? program offered to high school students, particularly the Oklahoma Native Americans. The PIs will also team up with other colleagues to develop programs in optical science for K-12 students. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0725764</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xincheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Xie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xincheng Xie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xie@solid.phy.okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4057445813</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000237359</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weili</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weili Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>weili.zhang@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4057447297</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000364856</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 WHITEHURST HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>109E</Code>
<Text>Sys theory in biology &amp; medicine</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~270000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Metamaterials, with negative permittivity, negative permeability, or both, are promising in developing unique photonic devices for applications in a broad range of disciplines. This project focuses on investigations of the unique terahertz (THz) responses of composite metamaterials using the state-of-the-art techniques of THz spectroscopy, cleanroom microelectronic processing, and numerical simulations. The research findings and accomplishments resulting from this project are described in the following sequence: unique response of planar THz metamaterials and negative index of refraction, chiral THz metamaterials, metamaterial-induced transparency, proof-of-concept sensing with THz metamaterials, and three-dimensional (3D) THz cloaking.</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em><em>1) Unique responses of planar THz metamaterials and negative index of refraction. </em>Systematic investigations have been carried out to study electromagnetic properties of planar metamaterials at THz frequencies. Using highly reproducible subwavelength resonators, we showed that the inductive-capacitive (LC) resonance could be developed in planar metamaterials made from both generally good and poor metals with either optically thick or optically thin thicknesses. We also demonstrated superconducting THz metamaterials (Fig. 1a), random metamaterials, spiral metamaterial antennas, and resonant properties of metallic split-ring resonators (SRRs) at oblique incidence, cryo-temperature, and with breaking symmetry. The LC resonance was found to exhibit strong dependence on the permittivity of metals at THz frequencies; it was enhanced with a higher ratio of the real to the imaginary parts of the permittivity. We have also observed THz negative index of refraction in a freestanding metamaterial fabricated by use of a unique double-layer, self-aligned photolithography. Such flexible texture, straightforward fabrication process, and interesting resonant properties are promising in developing 3D THz metamaterials and metamaterial-based THz components. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<em>2) Chiral THz metamaterials. </em>Chirality and asymmetric THz transmission have been studied in various unique metamaterials. A 3D chiral metamaterial with strong chirality and negative index of refraction was demonstrated at THz frequencies. Composed of more than a hundred thousand 40 &micro;m &times; 40 &micro;m gold unit cells, the chiral metamaterial revealed a negative index in the frequency range of 1.06-1.27 THz, as shown in Fig. 1b. Different from the Veselago metamaterials, the chirality, as opposed to mirror symmetry, enabled the creation of a negative index of refraction while it did not require the permittivity and permeability to be simultaneously negative. The realization of THz chiral negative-index metamaterials offers opportunities for investigations of their novel electromagnetic properties, such as negative refraction and reflection, as well as important THz device applications. In addition, we have also observed chiral behaviors and asymmetric THz transmission in planar chiral (Fig. 1c) and non-chiral metamaterials.</p> <p>&nbsp;<em>3)&nbsp; Metamaterial-induced transparency. </em>The coupling or interference effect in certain metamaterials may lead to narrow, low-loss, and strong dispersive resonances that could mimic the well-known quantum phenomenon, electromagnetically induced transparency (EIT). Our recent THz time-domain spectroscopy (THz-TDS) and numerical studies have shown that specially designed planar metamaterials resonating at THz frequencies can exhibit spectral response that resembled the EIT effect. In Fig. 1d &nbsp;we show the spectral coupling between a dark and a bright eigenmode in a metamaterial with broken symmetry. For normal incidence and a fixed polarization, both eigenmodes can be excited with one of them regarded as dark state since coupling was prohibited due to symmetry constraints. Similar tran...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Metamaterials, with negative permittivity, negative permeability, or both, are promising in developing unique photonic devices for applications in a broad range of disciplines. This project focuses on investigations of the unique terahertz (THz) responses of composite metamaterials using the state-of-the-art techniques of THz spectroscopy, cleanroom microelectronic processing, and numerical simulations. The research findings and accomplishments resulting from this project are described in the following sequence: unique response of planar THz metamaterials and negative index of refraction, chiral THz metamaterials, metamaterial-induced transparency, proof-of-concept sensing with THz metamaterials, and three-dimensional (3D) THz cloaking.   1) Unique responses of planar THz metamaterials and negative index of refraction. Systematic investigations have been carried out to study electromagnetic properties of planar metamaterials at THz frequencies. Using highly reproducible subwavelength resonators, we showed that the inductive-capacitive (LC) resonance could be developed in planar metamaterials made from both generally good and poor metals with either optically thick or optically thin thicknesses. We also demonstrated superconducting THz metamaterials (Fig. 1a), random metamaterials, spiral metamaterial antennas, and resonant properties of metallic split-ring resonators (SRRs) at oblique incidence, cryo-temperature, and with breaking symmetry. The LC resonance was found to exhibit strong dependence on the permittivity of metals at THz frequencies; it was enhanced with a higher ratio of the real to the imaginary parts of the permittivity. We have also observed THz negative index of refraction in a freestanding metamaterial fabricated by use of a unique double-layer, self-aligned photolithography. Such flexible texture, straightforward fabrication process, and interesting resonant properties are promising in developing 3D THz metamaterials and metamaterial-based THz components.     2) Chiral THz metamaterials. Chirality and asymmetric THz transmission have been studied in various unique metamaterials. A 3D chiral metamaterial with strong chirality and negative index of refraction was demonstrated at THz frequencies. Composed of more than a hundred thousand 40 &micro;m &times; 40 &micro;m gold unit cells, the chiral metamaterial revealed a negative index in the frequency range of 1.06-1.27 THz, as shown in Fig. 1b. Different from the Veselago metamaterials, the chirality, as opposed to mirror symmetry, enabled the creation of a negative index of refraction while it did not require the permittivity and permeability to be simultaneously negative. The realization of THz chiral negative-index metamaterials offers opportunities for investigations of their novel electromagnetic properties, such as negative refraction and reflection, as well as important THz device applications. In addition, we have also observed chiral behaviors and asymmetric THz transmission in planar chiral (Fig. 1c) and non-chiral metamaterials.   3)  Metamaterial-induced transparency. The coupling or interference effect in certain metamaterials may lead to narrow, low-loss, and strong dispersive resonances that could mimic the well-known quantum phenomenon, electromagnetically induced transparency (EIT). Our recent THz time-domain spectroscopy (THz-TDS) and numerical studies have shown that specially designed planar metamaterials resonating at THz frequencies can exhibit spectral response that resembled the EIT effect. In Fig. 1d  we show the spectral coupling between a dark and a bright eigenmode in a metamaterial with broken symmetry. For normal incidence and a fixed polarization, both eigenmodes can be excited with one of them regarded as dark state since coupling was prohibited due to symmetry constraints. Similar transparency resonance was also observed in another metamaterial made from unit cells consisting of a SRR surrounded by a larger closed ring.  4) Proo...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
