<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Benthic Dinoflagellate Migration (BenDiM):  Occurrence and Processes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>560000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>560000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040301</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most applications of the standardized dinoflagellate diel vertical migration (DVM) hypothesis consider a surface goal in daylight and a subsurface nutrient goal at night because of the visibility of surface blooms. The sub-surface nutrient source, however, can be so deep that dinoflagellates are unable to reach the surface during a 12 h ascent. At least three literature reports document a sediment-oriented expression of an alternative DVM pattern characteristic of continental boundaries with wider, more gently sloping shelves that can yield high biomass, near-bottom dinoflagellate accumulations. The targeted dinoflagellate niche, here termed ''Benthic Dinoflagellate Migration'' or ''BenDiM'', is influenced by light and nutrient gradients but is unique in that a DVM exists between a nutrient source near or at the sediment-sea interface and a light intensity in the lower euphotic zone that supports a net increase in population size. The project specifically deal with: 1) the different dinoflagellate species that occupy the BenDiM niche on the continental shelf off Panama City, FL between the 60 m and 20 m contours between May and Nov; 2) the light acclimation, the nutrient uptake capabilities, and the behavioral patterns required of different dinoflagellate species that occupy the BenDiM niche; and, 3) the effect of representative physical water motion on the formation, transport and fate of the different BenDiM dinoflagellate species populations. The study includes: 1) a pelagic/benthic field program with three 7-day cruises during different months between May and Oct in 2008 and Jul-Aug 2009; 2) laboratory studies on the light, nutrient, and behavioral characteristics of BenDiM dinoflagellates that allow successful competition with near-bottom pelagic diatoms and the microphytobenthos; and 3) a physical-biological modeling study to plan, integrate and extend the field and laboratory results. The cruise program applies standard UNOLS ship capabilities extended with instrumentation that includes: 1) an Acrobat undulating system instrumented with SeaBird CTD-O2 system, Biospherical PAR, SeaPoint Chlorophyll and CDOM Fluorometers, Seapoint Turbidity, Satlantic ISUS Nitrate Sensor, Brooke-Oceans Laser Optical Plankton Counter, and General Oceanics Flow Meter with integrated GPS and echo sounding location system and a real-time graphical display of the collected data, 2) the FlowCAM, and 3) the autonomous vertical profiler (AVP). The laboratory effort applies a proven motion analysis system for studying dinoflagellate behavior and a well-developed mesocosm capability for studying dinoflagellate physiology, biochemistry, and behavior. The modeling effort builds on an existing, biologically intense modeling approach that incorporates parameterization of dinoflagellate physiology, biochemistry and behavior in a representative physical field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit directly applies to "stealthy" bloom initiation since the developing BenDiM biomass generally is unseen because it occurs below the first optical depth of satellite detection. BenDiM also is implicated in improved estimates of carbon export since this biomass may be missed during routine euphotic zone surveys and in trophic relationships since this biomass may benefit or harm grazers depending on the dinoflagellate species that dominates the niche at a given place and time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts include: NCSU and UNCW graduate and undergraduate education; high school teacher education through COSEE; information transfer to colleagues at national/international meetings; and, information transfer to the public through a COSEE facilitated DVD on the cruise effort.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0726271</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Morrison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>morrisonj@uncw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9109622333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerald</FirstName>
<LastName>Janowitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerald S Janowitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>janowitz@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195157837</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180433</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kamykowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Kamykowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dan_kamykowski@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195157894</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000310743</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cjthomas@unity.ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195157839</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000296390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2>Admin. III, STE 240</StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0204000</Code>
<Name>Oceanography</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~560000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
