<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PIRE The Spin Triangle - Athens, Ohio; Hamburg, Germany; and Buenos Aires, Argentina:  Advancing Nanospintronics and Nanomagnetism</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2160000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2501950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Tsapogas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Smith 0730257&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PIRE The Spin Triangle - Athens, Ohio; Hamburg, Germany; and Buenos Aires, Argentina:  Advancing Nanospintronics and Nanomagnetism&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this Partnerships for International Research and Education award, Ohio University will develop a 3-way international collaboration involving the Nanoscale and Quantum Phenomena Institute at Ohio University; the Institute of Applied Physics at the University of Hamburg in Germany; and the condensed matter theory research groups at the Universidad de Buenos Aires and Centro Atomico Constituyentes Buenos Aires in Argentina.  They will form a focused, integrated, and complementary collaboration to lead nanoscale spintronics research on the global stage.  The U.S. team will collaborate with the scanning probe methods group in Hamburg specializing in spin-polarized scanning probe microscopy, led by Professor Roland Wiesendanger, and with the condensed matter theory group in Buenos Aires specializing in ab-initio calculations, led by Professors Ana Maria Llois, Andrea Barral, and Mariana Weissmann.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will help to train the next generation of globally engaged scientists and engineers, as approximately ten physics undergraduate students, ten physics graduate students, and four postdoctoral researchers will be funded to conduct research abroad with the German and Argentinean partners over the five-year course of the award.  Ohio University will develop an Undergraduate Certificate in International Nanoscience Research and a Graduate Certificate in International Nanoscience Research to document the training that these students will receive.  In addition, the project will also involve ten science journalism students, who will each perform one-year internships in which they will gain unique international science exposure.  The project overall is designed to broaden students' perspectives through an active international collaboration that includes both experiment and theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanospintronics and nanomagnetism promise to revolutionize the electronics/computer industry.  Smaller yet more powerful and energy efficient electronic devices are expected to be fabricated by exploiting electron spin in the near future.  To achieve this, one must understand the fundamental science underlying spintronics at the nanoscale.  Thus, the ultimate scientific goal of the project is to control and manipulate the electron spin for novel device functionalities as well as to achieve fundamental understanding.  To this end, one needs to understand how electron spin is distributed or screened in extended systems, how spins are transported, and subsequently how spin can be controlled and manipulated. Direct imaging of spins at the atomic limit using spin-polarized scanning tunneling microscopy is one of the first steps toward control, manipulation, and engineering of spintronic structures. The molecular beam epitaxy technique allows 'natural' engineering of various spintronic structures from 2D extended layers (atomic sheets) to the formation of localized 2D islands, 1D (chains), and 0D (dot) nanostructures. On the other hand, atom/molecule manipulation using scanning tunneling microscopy allows 'controlled' engineering (including shape, size, and composition) of spintronic nanostructures. The combination of these techniques will thus provide a powerful experimental approach to spintronic nanostructure fabrication and investigation.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project receives support from NSF's Office of International Science and Engineering and Division of Materials Research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0730257</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergio</FirstName>
<LastName>Ulloa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergio E Ulloa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ulloa@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405931729</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000119845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arthur Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smitha2@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405972576</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416363</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Saw-Wai</FirstName>
<LastName>Hla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Saw-Wai Hla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hla@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405931727</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000278066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Sandler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy P Sandler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sandler@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405939434</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308839</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio University</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio University]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[108 CUTLER HL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7742</Code>
<Text>PIRE- Prtnrshps Inter Res &amp; Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5911</Code>
<Text>ARGENTINA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7504</Code>
<Text>NSF-INTERNAT COOP IN MATERIALS RES-OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7566</Code>
<Text>PIRE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7574</Code>
<Text>CYBER INFRA FOR MATERIALS RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~641950</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~260000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PIRE Spin Triangle project was carried out from 2007 till 2013. Over this 6-year period, with the sustained efforts of the 4 PIRE faculty PI&rsquo;s and their international partners, and having the enthusiasm of many students who participated, numerous and significant outcomes were achieved &ndash; 1) intellectual outcomes, with regard to the scientific research, publications, and professional presentations that were made, and 2) educational outcomes, as demonstrated by the large number of undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral participants that have developed into aspiring young scientists and science journalists.</p> <p>The PIRE Spin Triangle program established scientific collaborations with two international partners:&nbsp; the University of Hamburg, Germany, primarily for experimental activities, and the Atomic Energy Commission/University of Buenos Aires, Argentina (also, Bariloche, Argentina), primarily for theoretical activities. Two corresponding international Study Abroad programs were consequently established at Ohio University, one for Germany, one for Argentina.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectually, the PIRE Spin Triangle program was aimed at advancing the fields of nanospintronics and nanomagnetism, areas of current high interest both scientifically and technologically. For the purposes of enabling the future paradigm of advanced computational devices which will increasingly rely on the spin of the electron for their functionality, and not just the charge, this project explored the properties and effects of magnetic atoms embedded in zero-, one-, two-, and three-dimensional materials including both atomic and molecular systems. The main experimental tools of interest included molecular beam deposition methods for sample synthesis, and for sample analysis, scanning and spin-polarized tunneling microscopy &ndash; methods in which complete electronic characterization and magnetic properties of structures at surfaces can be explored down to the single atomic scale. Theoretically, the main tools included numerical <em>ab-initio</em> methods as well as analytic techniques based on group theory and field theoretic approaches.</p> <p>These scientific tools were used, in collaboration with the international partners, to investigate such physical systems as single magnetic atoms arranged into linear constructions, magnetic molecules ordered into extended magnetic arrays, two-dimensional magnetic sheets at surfaces and within semiconductor host material, and magnetic pyramid structures. Furthermore, research included a full description of magnetic interactions within various nanostructures including, for example, quantum dots, quantum point contacts, and graphene. Phenomena of interest included Kondo physics such as &nbsp;Kondo resonance splitting due to specific features in the host density of states, spin-polarization, magnetic spin rotation, magnetic anisotropy, magnetic ordering, charge transfer between different system components, and the role of Coulomb interactions and quantum size effect. Results have been widely disseminated in numerous high level scientific journals including, for example, Physical Review Letters, Applied Physics Letters, Nature Nanotechnology, Physical Review B, and Nano Letters. In total, there have been 57 publications, over 130 invited presentations, and over 160 contributed presentations (mostly by students and postdocs) at scientific conferences and workshops.</p> <p>One of the most important aspects of the PIRE Spin Triangle project was the education and training of future scientists. PIRE students received at least 1 year of scientific training at Ohio University (1 &frac12; years for graduate students) before being sent abroad for immersive scientific and cultural experiences at the host institutions. These students were integrated into the hosts&rsquo; laboratories and research environments for periods of 10 to 12 wee...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PIRE Spin Triangle project was carried out from 2007 till 2013. Over this 6-year period, with the sustained efforts of the 4 PIRE faculty PIÆs and their international partners, and having the enthusiasm of many students who participated, numerous and significant outcomes were achieved &ndash; 1) intellectual outcomes, with regard to the scientific research, publications, and professional presentations that were made, and 2) educational outcomes, as demonstrated by the large number of undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral participants that have developed into aspiring young scientists and science journalists.  The PIRE Spin Triangle program established scientific collaborations with two international partners:  the University of Hamburg, Germany, primarily for experimental activities, and the Atomic Energy Commission/University of Buenos Aires, Argentina (also, Bariloche, Argentina), primarily for theoretical activities. Two corresponding international Study Abroad programs were consequently established at Ohio University, one for Germany, one for Argentina.   Intellectually, the PIRE Spin Triangle program was aimed at advancing the fields of nanospintronics and nanomagnetism, areas of current high interest both scientifically and technologically. For the purposes of enabling the future paradigm of advanced computational devices which will increasingly rely on the spin of the electron for their functionality, and not just the charge, this project explored the properties and effects of magnetic atoms embedded in zero-, one-, two-, and three-dimensional materials including both atomic and molecular systems. The main experimental tools of interest included molecular beam deposition methods for sample synthesis, and for sample analysis, scanning and spin-polarized tunneling microscopy &ndash; methods in which complete electronic characterization and magnetic properties of structures at surfaces can be explored down to the single atomic scale. Theoretically, the main tools included numerical ab-initio methods as well as analytic techniques based on group theory and field theoretic approaches.  These scientific tools were used, in collaboration with the international partners, to investigate such physical systems as single magnetic atoms arranged into linear constructions, magnetic molecules ordered into extended magnetic arrays, two-dimensional magnetic sheets at surfaces and within semiconductor host material, and magnetic pyramid structures. Furthermore, research included a full description of magnetic interactions within various nanostructures including, for example, quantum dots, quantum point contacts, and graphene. Phenomena of interest included Kondo physics such as  Kondo resonance splitting due to specific features in the host density of states, spin-polarization, magnetic spin rotation, magnetic anisotropy, magnetic ordering, charge transfer between different system components, and the role of Coulomb interactions and quantum size effect. Results have been widely disseminated in numerous high level scientific journals including, for example, Physical Review Letters, Applied Physics Letters, Nature Nanotechnology, Physical Review B, and Nano Letters. In total, there have been 57 publications, over 130 invited presentations, and over 160 contributed presentations (mostly by students and postdocs) at scientific conferences and workshops.  One of the most important aspects of the PIRE Spin Triangle project was the education and training of future scientists. PIRE students received at least 1 year of scientific training at Ohio University (1 &frac12; years for graduate students) before being sent abroad for immersive scientific and cultural experiences at the host institutions. These students were integrated into the hostsÆ laboratories and research environments for periods of 10 to 12 weeks at a time. Undergraduates went abroad once, whereas graduate students went typically two or three times. These students...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
