<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research in IPY: Abrupt Environmental Change in the Larsen Ice Shelf System, a Multidisciplinary Approach - Marine Ecosystems.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>285103.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>382264</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lisa Clough</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lclough@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924746</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0732983 - Vernet, Maria - Scripps Institute of Oceanography&lt;br/&gt;0732450 - Van Dover, Cindy - Duke University&lt;br/&gt;0732711 - Smith, Craig - University of Hawaii&lt;br/&gt;0732917 - McCormick, Michael - Hamilton College&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaborative Research in IPY: Abrupt Environmental Change in the&lt;br/&gt;Larsen Ice Shelf System, a Multidisciplinary Approach - Marine&lt;br/&gt;Ecosystems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A profound transformation in ecosystem structure and function is occurring in coastal waters of the western Weddell Sea, with the collapse of the Larsen B ice shelf. This transformation appears to be yielding a redistribution of energy flow between chemoautotrophic and photosynthetic production, and to be causing the rapid demise of the extraordinary seep ecosystem discovered beneath the ice shelf.  This event provides an ideal opportunity to examine fundamental aspects of ecosystem transition associated with climate change. We propose to test the following hypotheses to elucidate the transformations occurring in marine ecosystems as a consequence of the Larsen B collapse: (1) The biogeographic isolation and sub-ice shelf setting of the Larsen B seep has led to novel habitat characteristics, chemoautotrophically dependent taxa and functional adaptations. (2)  Benthic communities beneath the former Larsen B ice shelf are fundamentally different from assemblages at similar depths in the Weddell sea-ice zone, and resemble oligotrophic deep-sea communities. Larsen B assemblages are undergoing rapid change. (3) The previously dark, oligotrophic waters of the Larsen B embayment now support a thriving phototrophic community, with production rates and phytoplankton composition similar to other productive areas of the Weddell Sea. To document rapid changes occurring in the Larsen B ecosystem, we will use a remotely operated vehicle, shipboard samplers, and moored sediment traps.  We will characterize microbial, macrofaunal and megafaunal components of the seep community; evaluate patterns of surface productivity, export flux, and benthic faunal composition in areas previously covered by the ice shelf, and compare these areas to the open sea-ice zone.  These changes will be placed within the geological, glaciological and climatological context that led to ice-shelf retreat, through companion research projects funded in concert with this effort.  Together these projects will help predict the likely consequences of ice-shelf collapse to marine ecosystems in other regions of Antarctica vulnerable to climate change.  The research features international collaborators from Argentina, Belgium, Canada, Germany, Spain and the United Kingdom.  The broader impacts include participation of a science writer; broadcast of science segments by members of the Jim Lehrer News Hour (Public Broadcasting System); material for summer courses in environmental change; mentoring of graduate students and postdoctoral fellows; and showcasing scientific activities and findings to students and public through podcasts. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0732711</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig R Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>craigsmi@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089567776</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000331858</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2440 Campus Road, Box 368]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0311000</Code>
<Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5111</Code>
<Text>ANT Organisms &amp; Ecosystems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5292</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5295</Code>
<Text>IPY (GENERAL)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5383</Code>
<Text>HUMAN &amp;/OR BIOLOGICAL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~136710</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~97736</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~50657</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~97161</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Antarctic Peninsula is warming as rapidly as anywhere on Earth over the past few decades, resulting in ice-shelf collapse, glacial retreat, and rising ocean temperatures. The major goal of this project has been to&nbsp; evaluate biodiversity and ecosystem function in the unique seafloor animal communities along the Antarctic Peninsula, and then work with in interdisciplinary team to assess the response and sensitivities of Antarctic marine ecosystems to rapid climate change. Project outcomes include important contributions in following areas.</p> <p>The cold water on the Antarctic shelf has long formed a temperature barrier to cold-intolerant, predacious king crabs, preventing crab dispersal from the warmer deep sea into colder, shallow Antarctic waters. Using an underwater robot called a Remotely Operated Vehicle, we showed that a large, reproductive population of king crabs has crossed the Antarctic shelf into the Palmer Deep in the last 10,000 y. The king crab population (estimated at ~1.6 million individuals) appears to have dramatically altered seafloor biodiversity and ecosystem function in this deep near-shore basin (see pictures 1 and 2). Recent warming trends of shelf waters along the Antarctic Peninsula suggest that, if these king crabs are indeed excluded by cold temperatures, predacious crabs may disperse broadly into shallow Antarctic Peninsula shelf waters within a few decades, potentially causing major diversity loss in the long-isolated, evolutionarily novel Antarctic shelf communities. Our work has stimulated healthy scientific debate on the effects of temperature on Southern Ocean king crabs, and their potential to invade and alter ecosystem structure in Antarctic near-shore waters. Our crab discovery has also elicited extensive press coverage and has highlighted the need to better understand the potential impacts of climate warming on the unique biodiversity of the Antarctic region.</p> <p>To explore the influence of glacier melting on Antarctic seafloor communities, we conducted the first studies of productivity and biodiversity along transects from the open continental shelf deep into glacier-hosting Antarctic fjords. Unexpectedly, we found that glacier-hosting fjords along the Antarctic Peninsula are extraordinary hotspots of seafloor productivity and biodiversity (see pictures 3, 4, and 5). These Antarctic fjords provide habitat and foraging areas for Antarctic krill and baleen whales, enhance regional seafloor biodiversity, and attract substantial tourist activity along the Antarctic Peninsula. Our studies suggest that productivity/biodiversity hotspots are maintained in these fjords because the fjord glaciers are still in early stages of melting. Our studies also suggest that climate warming may &ldquo;snuff out&rdquo; these extraordinary hotspots of Antarctic biodiversity by increasing glacial melt and releasing large amounts of glacial sediments into the fjords.</p> <p>We have found that the warmer west side of the Antarctic Peninsula harbors much different seafloor communities than the east side, where bottom waters are substantially colder. &nbsp;In fact, the most abundant sediment dwelling species on the west side of the Peninsula appears to be absent from colder waters on the east side.&nbsp;These results indicate strong, temperature related regional differences in seafloor biodiversity around the Antarctic Peninsula, and suggest that ocean warming by a few degrees might cause dramatic shifts in seafloor communities. &nbsp;</p> <p>We have found that seafloor animal communities vary substantially along a transect spanning a large range in time (15 &ndash; 170 years) since overlying ice-shelf breakout in the Larsen A Embayment (see picture 6).&nbsp; We are now analyzing these patterns to help predict how further ice-shelf loss might influence marine ecosystems around Antarctica.</p> <p>Finally, our project has contributed substantia...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Antarctic Peninsula is warming as rapidly as anywhere on Earth over the past few decades, resulting in ice-shelf collapse, glacial retreat, and rising ocean temperatures. The major goal of this project has been to  evaluate biodiversity and ecosystem function in the unique seafloor animal communities along the Antarctic Peninsula, and then work with in interdisciplinary team to assess the response and sensitivities of Antarctic marine ecosystems to rapid climate change. Project outcomes include important contributions in following areas.  The cold water on the Antarctic shelf has long formed a temperature barrier to cold-intolerant, predacious king crabs, preventing crab dispersal from the warmer deep sea into colder, shallow Antarctic waters. Using an underwater robot called a Remotely Operated Vehicle, we showed that a large, reproductive population of king crabs has crossed the Antarctic shelf into the Palmer Deep in the last 10,000 y. The king crab population (estimated at ~1.6 million individuals) appears to have dramatically altered seafloor biodiversity and ecosystem function in this deep near-shore basin (see pictures 1 and 2). Recent warming trends of shelf waters along the Antarctic Peninsula suggest that, if these king crabs are indeed excluded by cold temperatures, predacious crabs may disperse broadly into shallow Antarctic Peninsula shelf waters within a few decades, potentially causing major diversity loss in the long-isolated, evolutionarily novel Antarctic shelf communities. Our work has stimulated healthy scientific debate on the effects of temperature on Southern Ocean king crabs, and their potential to invade and alter ecosystem structure in Antarctic near-shore waters. Our crab discovery has also elicited extensive press coverage and has highlighted the need to better understand the potential impacts of climate warming on the unique biodiversity of the Antarctic region.  To explore the influence of glacier melting on Antarctic seafloor communities, we conducted the first studies of productivity and biodiversity along transects from the open continental shelf deep into glacier-hosting Antarctic fjords. Unexpectedly, we found that glacier-hosting fjords along the Antarctic Peninsula are extraordinary hotspots of seafloor productivity and biodiversity (see pictures 3, 4, and 5). These Antarctic fjords provide habitat and foraging areas for Antarctic krill and baleen whales, enhance regional seafloor biodiversity, and attract substantial tourist activity along the Antarctic Peninsula. Our studies suggest that productivity/biodiversity hotspots are maintained in these fjords because the fjord glaciers are still in early stages of melting. Our studies also suggest that climate warming may "snuff out" these extraordinary hotspots of Antarctic biodiversity by increasing glacial melt and releasing large amounts of glacial sediments into the fjords.  We have found that the warmer west side of the Antarctic Peninsula harbors much different seafloor communities than the east side, where bottom waters are substantially colder.  In fact, the most abundant sediment dwelling species on the west side of the Peninsula appears to be absent from colder waters on the east side. These results indicate strong, temperature related regional differences in seafloor biodiversity around the Antarctic Peninsula, and suggest that ocean warming by a few degrees might cause dramatic shifts in seafloor communities.    We have found that seafloor animal communities vary substantially along a transect spanning a large range in time (15 &ndash; 170 years) since overlying ice-shelf breakout in the Larsen A Embayment (see picture 6).  We are now analyzing these patterns to help predict how further ice-shelf loss might influence marine ecosystems around Antarctica.  Finally, our project has contributed substantially to the development of human scientific resources, providing Antarctic field and research experience for three undergraduate s...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
