<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Downscaling global climate projections to the ecosystems of the  Bering Sea with nested biophysical models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>206037.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246678</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William J. Wiseman, Jr.</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Funds are provided to model the physics and ecosystem structure of the Bering Sea.  Change in climate forcing will be determined from coupled atmosphere-ocean general circulation model (GCM) simulations made for the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Fourth Assessment Report (AR4).  The twentieth century hindcasts from these models differ in terms of their ability to replicate past observed conditions; a subset of the better models will be used to project the trends, variability and uncertainty of the climate of the Bering Sea through the first half of the 21st century.  This ensemble of GCM model results will be used primarily for dynamical downscaling, i.e., as initial and boundary conditions for high-resolution ocean model experiments with the Regional Ocean Modeling System (ROMS).  The ROMS simulations are designed to properly handle physical processes known to be important on the Bering Sea shelf, such as sea ice, tides, and cross-shelf exchange; these results will form the direct input for embedded spatially-explicit nutrient-phytoplankton-zooplankton (NPZ) and food web model experiments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is part of a larger program designed to develop understanding of the integrated ecosystem of the eastern Bering Sea shelf, a highly productive region of US coastal waters.  This ecosystem is home to a major portion of the commercial fisheries of the US and also provides significant resources to subsistence hunters and fisherman of Alaska.  The model will help to synthesize our current and developing understanding of how this system functions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0732431</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Enrique</FirstName>
<LastName>Curchitser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Enrique N Curchitser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>enrique@marine.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7329327889</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000129332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[33 Knightsbridge Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5286</Code>
<Text>BEST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~51639</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~49882</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~94268</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~50889</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The project entitled &ldquo;Downscaling global climate projections to the ecosystems of the Bering sea with nested biophysical models&rdquo; consisted of four main components: climate forcing, numerical ocean modeling, lower-trophic modeling, and linking the models to an upper-trophic level model.&nbsp;</span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>For the climate forcing portion,&nbsp;the effort had two primary thrusts: (1) determining how to best synthesize the multiple simulations from the variety general circulation models (GCMs) carried out for the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), and (2) using the output from these models and empirical techniques to begin making projections of the populations of a variety of fish species in the Bering Sea.&nbsp;A variety of research was carried out on the evaluation and use of IPCC-class GCMs, with a focus on the Bering Sea and other high-latitude ocean regions. The recommendations of Overland et al. (2011), along with those from a number of other publications, indicate that the protocol should probably be application-dependent, i.e., no single method is best. There is a strong consensus that a multi-model ensemble approach is preferred if at all possible.&nbsp;</p> <p>For the physical modeling part of the research a coupled ocean/sea ice model was implemented and used to simulate the 1958-2008 period. &nbsp;Overall, the simulations showed the models ability to reproduce conspicuous features of the Bering Sea Circulation, including ice extent, tidal flows, bottom cold pool and a complex, seasonally- and interannualy-varying water column structure.</p> <p>A Bering Sea specific lower trophic level biological model was developed and implemented together with the physical model. &nbsp; The&nbsp;study explored the influence of temperature on the lower trophic level Bering Sea ecosystem only within the range of historic temperature variability and present ecosystem structure. &nbsp;Extensive sensitivity analysis was carried out to address uncertainty in ecosystem model outputs due to numerical uncertainty in the parameter values. The coupled&nbsp;model results indicate temperature alone could account for ~20-40% of the variation in euphausiid production; including primary production into the explanatory model increased the percentage of euphausiid production that could be accounted for up to 90%. The influence of the environment on the primary production varied by region and by phytoplankton type, but up to 81% of its inter-annual variability could be explained by variability in either temperature, mixed layer depth and/or ice cover.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, progress was achieved in linking the physics and lower trophic level models to an upper trophic level model that&nbsp;includes 14 fish species which have two-way interactions with five groups from the NPZ module. Predation is length based and species dynamics are modeled at three levels of detail: age and length, length only and biomass pool. Both temperature and advection from physical model are used inl terms involving bioenergetics and movement for the fish.&nbsp;</p> <p>Significant broader implacts of the project included interaction by the PI's with native Alaskan communities and the training of both graduate students and post-doctoral fellows in the integrated science of the Bering Sea.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/26/2013<br>      Modified by: Enrique&nbsp;N&nbsp;Curchitser</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The project entitled "Downscaling global climate projections to the ecosystems of the Bering sea with nested biophysical models" consisted of four main components: climate forcing, numerical ocean modeling, lower-trophic modeling, and linking the models to an upper-trophic level model.      For the climate forcing portion, the effort had two primary thrusts: (1) determining how to best synthesize the multiple simulations from the variety general circulation models (GCMs) carried out for the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), and (2) using the output from these models and empirical techniques to begin making projections of the populations of a variety of fish species in the Bering Sea. A variety of research was carried out on the evaluation and use of IPCC-class GCMs, with a focus on the Bering Sea and other high-latitude ocean regions. The recommendations of Overland et al. (2011), along with those from a number of other publications, indicate that the protocol should probably be application-dependent, i.e., no single method is best. There is a strong consensus that a multi-model ensemble approach is preferred if at all possible.   For the physical modeling part of the research a coupled ocean/sea ice model was implemented and used to simulate the 1958-2008 period.  Overall, the simulations showed the models ability to reproduce conspicuous features of the Bering Sea Circulation, including ice extent, tidal flows, bottom cold pool and a complex, seasonally- and interannualy-varying water column structure.  A Bering Sea specific lower trophic level biological model was developed and implemented together with the physical model.   The study explored the influence of temperature on the lower trophic level Bering Sea ecosystem only within the range of historic temperature variability and present ecosystem structure.  Extensive sensitivity analysis was carried out to address uncertainty in ecosystem model outputs due to numerical uncertainty in the parameter values. The coupled model results indicate temperature alone could account for ~20-40% of the variation in euphausiid production; including primary production into the explanatory model increased the percentage of euphausiid production that could be accounted for up to 90%. The influence of the environment on the primary production varied by region and by phytoplankton type, but up to 81% of its inter-annual variability could be explained by variability in either temperature, mixed layer depth and/or ice cover.   Finally, progress was achieved in linking the physics and lower trophic level models to an upper trophic level model that includes 14 fish species which have two-way interactions with five groups from the NPZ module. Predation is length based and species dynamics are modeled at three levels of detail: age and length, length only and biomass pool. Both temperature and advection from physical model are used inl terms involving bioenergetics and movement for the fish.   Significant broader implacts of the project included interaction by the PI's with native Alaskan communities and the training of both graduate students and post-doctoral fellows in the integrated science of the Bering Sea.             Last Modified: 02/26/2013       Submitted by: Enrique N Curchitser]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
