<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: AFTOL: Resolving the Evolutionary History of the Fungi</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>361994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399919</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Mindell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will support a team of investigators who seek to resolve evolutionary relationships within the fungi.  The research will enhance understanding of the ancient evolutionary diversification of the fungi by addressing evolutionary relationships among the major groups of fungi. This study will develop integrated molecular and morphological datasets, which will be freely accessible on the Web. Molecular data will include sequences from a target set of 76 genes that were identified from analyses of known fungal genomes. Morphological data will include characters associated with nuclear and cellular division and the morphological organization of hyphae. In addition the study will develop ontologies for morphological characters to promote further sampling and analytical integration across disparate organisms.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fungi make up one of the major groups of life, with an estimated diversity of approximately 1.5 million species. These organisms play crucial ecological roles as decomposers, beneficial mutualists, and parasites and pathogens, including pathogens of humans. The economic significance of fungi is almost incalculable as they perform essential ecological functions and impact diverse applied disciplines, including agriculture, medicine, and drug discovery. A better understanding of the early evolutionary history of the Fungi is necessary to expand our knowledge of the history of life of Earth and the evolution of its ecosystems. Phylogenomic analyses and databases for fungi will transform the field of comparative fungal biology and will benefit all fields of fungal biology that rely on an accurate understanding of evolutionary relationships and diversity of Fungi.  The bioinformatics tools for managing and analyzing phylogenomic data that will be developed will be broadly applicable across the Tree of Life.  Training and outreach activities will include graduate and post-doctoral training, undergraduate training, and outreach to K-12 educators.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0732550</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>McLaughlin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David J McLaughlin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>davem@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126255736</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000108795</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7689</Code>
<Text>ASSEMBLING THE TREE OF LIFE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7689</Code>
<Text>Assembling the Tree of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9232</Code>
<Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~191645</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~23500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~91914</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~92860</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Our contribution to the Assembling the Fungal Tree of Life (AFTOL) project was designed to provide structural data for unstudied and understudied groups of kingdom Fungi to complement the molecular phylogenetic data from other laboratories and test a number of hypotheses on fungal evolution. Structural (subcellular) characters observed with the electron microscope have been important historically in understanding the relationships among fungi, and some of these characters have broad implications in biology. For example, we have looked at (1) septal pore structures, which are important in cell growth, (2) nuclear division and spindle pole body structures, which are important in cell replication, and (3) organization of the growing apex of fungal filaments (hyphae), which controls hyphal growth and determines how fungi interact with other organisms. These structures allow us to understand fungal diversity and the evolution of characters. These data also provide information important for cell biologists and are potentially important for applied scientists.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To bring together subcellular data from previous studies covering about 50 years with recent data, we have compiled the information into a database, the AFTOL Structural and Biochemical Database (SBD), so that precise comparisons of subcellular characters can be made across Fungi and gaps in our knowledge can be identified. The SBD reveals that structural data cannot be generalized from one or a few studies to all species in a phylum, subphylum, class or order, as there may be significant variation among subcellular characters within taxonomic groups. Our studies of eight species in four phyla/subphyla reveal a new type of spindle pole body (the structure at the poles of dividing nuclei) in one subphylum (Kickxellomycotina, <em>Coemansia reversa</em>), new septal pore types in two phyla (Ascomycota, <em>Neolecta vitellina</em>, <em>Orbilia</em> species; Basidiomycota, two <em>Helicogloea</em> species, <em>Wallemia sebi</em>), and the hyphal tip organization in a third phylum (Glomeromycota, three <em>Gigaspora</em> species). These characters support several hypotheses but refute one hypothesis. For example, our results in <em>Coemansia reversa</em> support the hypothesis that the spindle pole body, which is characteristic of derived fungi, has evolved multiple times from the centriole-containing spindle pole bodies in basal fungi. Our results refute the hypothesis that the Glomeromycota are more closely related to the advanced Dikarya than to the zygomycetous fungi based on the organization of the hyphal apex.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In the Glomeromycota we have characterized the growing hyphal tip of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi for the first time. These fungi are important symbionts with herbaceous and woody plants, and they play important roles in agriculture and natural ecosystems through their beneficial interactions with their host plants. They only grow in association with a living plant, which has made them difficult to study. We have developed the methods for studying this group cytologically, which will set the stage for cell biological studies to understand the role of several types of organelles in hyphal growth.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Another area where cell biological study is clearly needed is in the unusual septal pore structures observed in <em>Neolecta vitellina</em>. In the growing fruiting body the pores between adjacent cells are plugged by membranous structures with a unique morphology. These structures resemble transfer cells in some fungi and plants that are involved in movement of nutrients between adjacent cells. Comparable structures may have been independently evolved in derived Ascomycota as suggested by our results in <em>Orbilia</em>...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[          Our contribution to the Assembling the Fungal Tree of Life (AFTOL) project was designed to provide structural data for unstudied and understudied groups of kingdom Fungi to complement the molecular phylogenetic data from other laboratories and test a number of hypotheses on fungal evolution. Structural (subcellular) characters observed with the electron microscope have been important historically in understanding the relationships among fungi, and some of these characters have broad implications in biology. For example, we have looked at (1) septal pore structures, which are important in cell growth, (2) nuclear division and spindle pole body structures, which are important in cell replication, and (3) organization of the growing apex of fungal filaments (hyphae), which controls hyphal growth and determines how fungi interact with other organisms. These structures allow us to understand fungal diversity and the evolution of characters. These data also provide information important for cell biologists and are potentially important for applied scientists.           To bring together subcellular data from previous studies covering about 50 years with recent data, we have compiled the information into a database, the AFTOL Structural and Biochemical Database (SBD), so that precise comparisons of subcellular characters can be made across Fungi and gaps in our knowledge can be identified. The SBD reveals that structural data cannot be generalized from one or a few studies to all species in a phylum, subphylum, class or order, as there may be significant variation among subcellular characters within taxonomic groups. Our studies of eight species in four phyla/subphyla reveal a new type of spindle pole body (the structure at the poles of dividing nuclei) in one subphylum (Kickxellomycotina, Coemansia reversa), new septal pore types in two phyla (Ascomycota, Neolecta vitellina, Orbilia species; Basidiomycota, two Helicogloea species, Wallemia sebi), and the hyphal tip organization in a third phylum (Glomeromycota, three Gigaspora species). These characters support several hypotheses but refute one hypothesis. For example, our results in Coemansia reversa support the hypothesis that the spindle pole body, which is characteristic of derived fungi, has evolved multiple times from the centriole-containing spindle pole bodies in basal fungi. Our results refute the hypothesis that the Glomeromycota are more closely related to the advanced Dikarya than to the zygomycetous fungi based on the organization of the hyphal apex.           In the Glomeromycota we have characterized the growing hyphal tip of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi for the first time. These fungi are important symbionts with herbaceous and woody plants, and they play important roles in agriculture and natural ecosystems through their beneficial interactions with their host plants. They only grow in association with a living plant, which has made them difficult to study. We have developed the methods for studying this group cytologically, which will set the stage for cell biological studies to understand the role of several types of organelles in hyphal growth.           Another area where cell biological study is clearly needed is in the unusual septal pore structures observed in Neolecta vitellina. In the growing fruiting body the pores between adjacent cells are plugged by membranous structures with a unique morphology. These structures resemble transfer cells in some fungi and plants that are involved in movement of nutrients between adjacent cells. Comparable structures may have been independently evolved in derived Ascomycota as suggested by our results in Orbilia, but in neither group is the function known.              The SBD is both a research and a teaching tool. It is an online resource for researchers to compile and analyze subcellular and biochemical characters phylogenetically. It also is an important resource for teaching mycology. Character lists serve ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
