<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Connection One-Communication Circuits and Systems Research Center Phase II</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>415000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Raffaella Montelli</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The existing Industry/University Cooperative Research Center for Circuits and Systems (Connection One) will continue to receive NSF support for the second five year of their live cycle.  The focus of the center is on Communication Circuits and Systems for the advancement of the next generation of wireless and wireline system systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The center has had a broad impact on communication, semiconductor, and electronics industry.  The research has benefited the wireless industry to develop smaller, more compact, low-power fully integrated new wireless models.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0742547</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sayfe</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiaei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sayfe Kiaei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sayfe.kiaei@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807277761</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000099294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ORSPA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0400000</Code>
<Name>Industry University - Co-op</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>122E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8043</Code>
<Text>System Design and Simulation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8808</Code>
<Text>Veterans Research Supplements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~166000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~3000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~133000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~83000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~83000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes:</p> <p>There are number of new projects supported by the center IAB including projects related to:</p> <p>1-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Power Management</p> <p>2-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Radio Frequency Circuits</p> <p>3-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Antennas</p> <p>4-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 4G and 5G wireless system</p> <p>5-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Wireless Transceivers</p> <p>6-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Bio-Electronics, and related areas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The center has established monthly seminars with the IAB, including visits to the IAB members and discussing the projects at their site. Overall, including the IAB membership, the center funding is well over $4M with funds from 23 IAB members, NSF, DOD, and related funding agencies.&nbsp; There were over 20 graduate students working at Member industry&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Center Impact and Outcomes&nbsp;</p> <p>New Technologies: the center has developed new technologies in wireless sensors, implanted medical devices, digital hearing aids, wireless HTMI at 60GHZ, and power management system for photo voltaic and mobile device.</p> <p>In these area, the center:</p> <p>Sensors and sources: This work has resulted in a new company startup by Dr. Remis Gaska and Dr. Shur at RPI on deep UV LEDs. This company has over 60 employees with contacts from DOD, and other sources and is now the only commercial supplier of deep UV LEDs. The company received PRISM Award in 2009 for the best photonic product of the year, was cited as "DARPA success story", and received South Carolina technology Awards.&nbsp; Others work at Ohio State and Arizona State has resulted in new circuits, and simulation tools that are being adopted by several industrial members resulting in new products. The net results of work in the center in this area is added work force of 20-30 new employees, and 3-5 Million in new revenues.</p> <p>Implanted medical devices: Connection One team has been working closely with Medtronic and they are developing a new implanted device to control defibrillators, and other monitoring devices. This technology could results in new products in excess of 10 Million dollars annual sales.</p> <p>Digital Hearing Aid: this work was funded by NSF under GOALI with connection one. This work has resulted in a new MEMS type microphone and speakers for the hearing aid and KNOWL is using the MEMS technology to enter the market place with sales over 5-10 Million.</p> <p>Power Management: Texas Instrument, Intel, Qualcomm, and Cirrus Logic are using the technology developed in connection one in this area. This work support several products in wireless, mobile, and portable devices. The net impact of the technology developed by the center is hard to estimate but the sales of new products in this field can be multiple million dollars.</p> <p>Mr. Gutin and Dr. Shur of RPI were funded by the NSF under the auspices of the NSF ICORP program to commercialize Terahertz On Si Chip Array (TOSCA) technology.</p> <p>Patents: The center has disclosed and applied for 4 patents. 3 of them are currently being issued.</p> <p>Interns and hires: Overall, the center placed over 10 Interns in the Connection One companies. The C1 companies also hired 6 PhD students who were funded by C1.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Membership over 15 Members</p> <p>2-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; New Projects in Bio sensors, THZ Circuits, and materials and communications.&nbsp;</p> <p>3-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The&nbsp;overall funding, including related projects outside at ASU is over $3M. &nbsp;</p> <p>4-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Graduated over 20 students working at Member industry &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact of the center:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>New materials, Circuits and Systems have been developed in the center impacting new technologies in wireless systems, RFIC, circuits and power management. We have also developed educational progra...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes:  There are number of new projects supported by the center IAB including projects related to:  1-    Power Management  2-    Radio Frequency Circuits  3-    Antennas  4-    4G and 5G wireless system  5-    Wireless Transceivers  6-    Bio-Electronics, and related areas.     The center has established monthly seminars with the IAB, including visits to the IAB members and discussing the projects at their site. Overall, including the IAB membership, the center funding is well over $4M with funds from 23 IAB members, NSF, DOD, and related funding agencies.  There were over 20 graduate students working at Member industry         Center Impact and Outcomes   New Technologies: the center has developed new technologies in wireless sensors, implanted medical devices, digital hearing aids, wireless HTMI at 60GHZ, and power management system for photo voltaic and mobile device.  In these area, the center:  Sensors and sources: This work has resulted in a new company startup by Dr. Remis Gaska and Dr. Shur at RPI on deep UV LEDs. This company has over 60 employees with contacts from DOD, and other sources and is now the only commercial supplier of deep UV LEDs. The company received PRISM Award in 2009 for the best photonic product of the year, was cited as "DARPA success story", and received South Carolina technology Awards.  Others work at Ohio State and Arizona State has resulted in new circuits, and simulation tools that are being adopted by several industrial members resulting in new products. The net results of work in the center in this area is added work force of 20-30 new employees, and 3-5 Million in new revenues.  Implanted medical devices: Connection One team has been working closely with Medtronic and they are developing a new implanted device to control defibrillators, and other monitoring devices. This technology could results in new products in excess of 10 Million dollars annual sales.  Digital Hearing Aid: this work was funded by NSF under GOALI with connection one. This work has resulted in a new MEMS type microphone and speakers for the hearing aid and KNOWL is using the MEMS technology to enter the market place with sales over 5-10 Million.  Power Management: Texas Instrument, Intel, Qualcomm, and Cirrus Logic are using the technology developed in connection one in this area. This work support several products in wireless, mobile, and portable devices. The net impact of the technology developed by the center is hard to estimate but the sales of new products in this field can be multiple million dollars.  Mr. Gutin and Dr. Shur of RPI were funded by the NSF under the auspices of the NSF ICORP program to commercialize Terahertz On Si Chip Array (TOSCA) technology.  Patents: The center has disclosed and applied for 4 patents. 3 of them are currently being issued.  Interns and hires: Overall, the center placed over 10 Interns in the Connection One companies. The C1 companies also hired 6 PhD students who were funded by C1.        1-    Membership over 15 Members  2-    New Projects in Bio sensors, THZ Circuits, and materials and communications.   3-    The overall funding, including related projects outside at ASU is over $3M.    4-    Graduated over 20 students working at Member industry             Broader Impact of the center:     New materials, Circuits and Systems have been developed in the center impacting new technologies in wireless systems, RFIC, circuits and power management. We have also developed educational programs where K-12 and undergrad students visited the centers and did internships. The center in phase II had over 20 interns go to companies and the industry members hired over 40 of the center graduates.             Last Modified: 10/31/2014       Submitted by: Sayfe Kiaei]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
