<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Phylogeography of Non-vagile Coastal Isopods and the Controversial History of the Megadiverse Gulf of California-Baja Peninsula Region</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>570000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>613500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;The proposed study is aimed at improving our understanding on the controversial geological and biogeographic history of the Gulf of California and Baja California Peninsula; a region that encompasses one of the most biodiverse and productive ocean basins, and one of the most unique and biodiverse desert ecosystems in the world. The complex geological history of this region is regarded as essential to the origin of its extraordinary biodiversity and without a reliable geological framework, interpretation of evolutionary and biogeographic patterns can be misleading. The proposed project will examine phylogeographic patterns (genealogy coupled with biogeography) of five coastal intertidal isopod taxa, using mitochondrial and nuclear genes. These isopods have a high probability of preserving in their genealogies, signatures of geological events that occurred during the formation of this region. Their patterns of evolution will be used to build a consensus on the geological and biogeographical history of the Gulf of California.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this study will have a broad impact on the diverse scientific community working in this region, including biologists, geologists, paleontologists, oceanographers, and conservationists. The project will help also to uncover the biodiversity of a poorly studied taxonomic group and the data collected will be important for conservation agencies to design strategies to protect the fragile rocky shore ecosystem of the Gulf of California-Baja Peninsula and California. This study will foster collaborations of the PIs with scientists from Mexican research institutions, scientists from other disciplines, and conservation agencies. A subset of the specimens collected will be deposited in a US museum collection. Others will be used in a pilot US-Mexico collaborative project to study the effects of sea level rise and pollution on rocky intertidal communities of the Gulf of California and California. Undergraduate and graduate students will be trained on different aspects of the project and will present their research at scientific meetings. Both PIs are Hispanic (including one woman) and will seek the participation of students from groups traditionally underrepresented in the biological sciences. Results will be broadly disseminated through peer-reviewed scientific publications, participation in meetings, invited talks, and collection information will be made available on the laboratory website.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0743782</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mariana</FirstName>
<LastName>Mateos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mariana Mateos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmateos@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9156138874</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000188995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>Hurtado-Clavijo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luis Hurtado-Clavijo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lhurtado@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798479463</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000195135</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078592789</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078592789</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1174</Code>
<Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1174</Code>
<Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~188000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~228000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~190000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><br /></strong></p> <p><strong>INTELLECTUAL MERIT:&nbsp;</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The Pacific region between southern California and central Mexico, including the Gulf of California, provides a remarkable setting to study biological diversification of coastal organisms with poor dispersal potential. A complex and controversial geological history coupled with the Quaternary&rsquo;s cyclical pattern of rising and falling global temperatures and transgressing and regressing seas in this region, provided ample opportunities for range expansions/contractions, vicariance and allopatric genetic differentiation of organisms with limited dispersal potential. &nbsp;Phylogeographic patterns of three non-vagile intertidal isopods widely distributed in this region were unraveled and examined in relation to competing geological hypotheses on the origin of the Gulf of California.&nbsp; Two of these isopods are restricted to the supralittoral, although one is associated with rocky beaches (<em>Ligia</em>), and the other with sandy beaches (<em>Tylos</em>).&nbsp; The third isopod, <em>Excirolana mayana</em>, is found lower in the intertidal.&nbsp; As expected from their limited dispersal potential, the three isopods exhibit high levels of isolation among populations and cryptic diversity, with separate populations often consisting of highly divergent lineages. &nbsp;However, phylogeographic patterns among these three isopods were in general incongruent, although some similarities were found.&nbsp; <em>Ligia</em> shows phylogeographic patterns congruent with aspects of controversial hypotheses on the origin of the Gulf of Califonia, whereas the other two did not show such concordance.&nbsp; Differences in their biology and the extension and connectivity of the habitats they occupy likely contribute to their contrasting phylogeographic patterns.&nbsp; Although <em>Tylos</em> and <em>Ligia</em> avoid the open water, habitat connectivity for <em>Tylos</em> is greater than for <em>Ligia</em>, because continuous sandy stretches are more widespread than the relatively discrete rocky supralittoral patches occupied by <em>Ligia</em>.&nbsp; <em>Excirolana</em>, in turn, is distributed lower in the intertidal and can swim, thus, it has the highest probability of experiencing eventual long distance dispersal.&nbsp; Phyloegographic patterns of <em>Ligia</em> in other regions examined indicate that oceanic environmental factors and passive overwater dispersal have been also important factors in shaping evolutionary histories of members of this genus.&nbsp; Passive overwater dispersal may also be important for <em>Tylos</em> over relatively short distances, but tectonic events rather than trans-oceanic dispersal appear to explain the distribution of <em>Tylos</em> on different continents.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>BROADER IMPACTS:</strong></p> <p>The project significantly helped to increase representation of minority groups in science.&nbsp; Both PIs (Hispanic, one woman) achieved tenure at Texas A&amp;M University, and the grant and associated publications contributed to this accomplishment.&nbsp; A Hispanic participant obtained his PhD and will begin a faculty tenure-track position in Fall 2016.&nbsp; Two female participants completed their MSc; one works as a researcher and the other continued PhD studies.&nbsp; The project also trained 20 undergraduate students, most of them women and/or members of underrepresented groups in science, several of whom went to graduate school.&nbsp; The results of the project have been widely disseminated at local, national and international meetings within the US and overseas.&nbsp; Some meetings were targeted at underrepresented groups in science.&nbsp; PIs also presented results or used the data of the project in graduate and undergraduate courses in genetics, ecology, evolution, and phylogenetics.&nbsp; Results have ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    INTELLECTUAL MERIT:    The Pacific region between southern California and central Mexico, including the Gulf of California, provides a remarkable setting to study biological diversification of coastal organisms with poor dispersal potential. A complex and controversial geological history coupled with the QuaternaryÆs cyclical pattern of rising and falling global temperatures and transgressing and regressing seas in this region, provided ample opportunities for range expansions/contractions, vicariance and allopatric genetic differentiation of organisms with limited dispersal potential.  Phylogeographic patterns of three non-vagile intertidal isopods widely distributed in this region were unraveled and examined in relation to competing geological hypotheses on the origin of the Gulf of California.  Two of these isopods are restricted to the supralittoral, although one is associated with rocky beaches (Ligia), and the other with sandy beaches (Tylos).  The third isopod, Excirolana mayana, is found lower in the intertidal.  As expected from their limited dispersal potential, the three isopods exhibit high levels of isolation among populations and cryptic diversity, with separate populations often consisting of highly divergent lineages.  However, phylogeographic patterns among these three isopods were in general incongruent, although some similarities were found.  Ligia shows phylogeographic patterns congruent with aspects of controversial hypotheses on the origin of the Gulf of Califonia, whereas the other two did not show such concordance.  Differences in their biology and the extension and connectivity of the habitats they occupy likely contribute to their contrasting phylogeographic patterns.  Although Tylos and Ligia avoid the open water, habitat connectivity for Tylos is greater than for Ligia, because continuous sandy stretches are more widespread than the relatively discrete rocky supralittoral patches occupied by Ligia.  Excirolana, in turn, is distributed lower in the intertidal and can swim, thus, it has the highest probability of experiencing eventual long distance dispersal.  Phyloegographic patterns of Ligia in other regions examined indicate that oceanic environmental factors and passive overwater dispersal have been also important factors in shaping evolutionary histories of members of this genus.  Passive overwater dispersal may also be important for Tylos over relatively short distances, but tectonic events rather than trans-oceanic dispersal appear to explain the distribution of Tylos on different continents.     BROADER IMPACTS:  The project significantly helped to increase representation of minority groups in science.  Both PIs (Hispanic, one woman) achieved tenure at Texas A&amp;M University, and the grant and associated publications contributed to this accomplishment.  A Hispanic participant obtained his PhD and will begin a faculty tenure-track position in Fall 2016.  Two female participants completed their MSc; one works as a researcher and the other continued PhD studies.  The project also trained 20 undergraduate students, most of them women and/or members of underrepresented groups in science, several of whom went to graduate school.  The results of the project have been widely disseminated at local, national and international meetings within the US and overseas.  Some meetings were targeted at underrepresented groups in science.  PIs also presented results or used the data of the project in graduate and undergraduate courses in genetics, ecology, evolution, and phylogenetics.  Results have also been disseminated through outreach activities at local schools with a large population of Hispanics and economically disadvantaged individuals.  These include presentations in Spanish to 3rd grade classes of the Dual Language Program, and presentations in English and Spanish at elementary school annual science fairs for children and their families.  Results of the project have been published in peer-reviewe...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
