<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Physiology and Molecular Evolution of Photoprotection in Allopolyploids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>362324.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>362324</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Scott Heckathorn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Polyploidy is the multiplication of the entire genome beyond the diploid level. It is a particularly important genetic process in flowering plants, and many cultivated plants (e.g., wheat, maize, cotton, soybean) are polyploid. Polyploidy can lead to profound genomic changes, even beyond duplicating all of the genes in the genome. Polyploidy has long been known to affect physiology, anatomy, and biochemistry, but few studies have sought to connect phenotype with changes at the molecular level to understand how plants achieve an integrated response to polyploidy in natural populations. Such investigations hold the key to understanding why polyploids are so prevalent among plants, and why polyploids often have been considered more adaptable or more successful than their diploid progenitors.&lt;br/&gt;This project will study photoprotection - an important physiological process by which plants avoid damage from excess light energy - in several recently formed polyploid species of Glycine, the genus that includes the cultivated soybean. These species formed by hybridization and genome doubling (allopolyploidy) within the last 50,000 years. The diploid species that gave rise to them have been identified. Chlorophyll fluorescence assays will be used to compare photoprotection in the polyploid species with their diploid progenitors. At the molecular level, it will be determined how the gene copies contributed by the two diploid progenitors have changed in sequence and expression in the polyploidy species since their formation, and whether changes in DNA sequence, dosage, and/or expression patterns correlate with photoprotection phenotype.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. This project is of broad significance and impact because it will elucidate the effects of a ubiquitous genetic phenomenon, polyploidy, on a physiological process essential to plant fitness, and will connect this to changes in the genes underlying photoprotection. In addition, the project involves training graduate and undergraduate students and is linked to an ongoing high-school teacher outreach program at Cornell.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0744306</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Doyle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey J Doyle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jjd5@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072557972</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Owens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas G Owens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tgo2@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000146485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010</Name>
<CityName>Ithica</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithica</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~232904</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~129420</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A defining characteristic of plant evolution is the recurrence of polyploidy or whole genome duplication (a doubling of the amount of DNA per nucleus). How polyploidy has contributed to the success of flowering plants has been identified as one of the most important questions facing plant science research. Among the wild relatives of the cultivated soybean are several recently formed polyploid species, as well as their non-duplicated diploid progenitors, providing an ideal system for studying the effects of polyploidy on plant traits. Using this system, we examined the effects of polyploidy on several traits relating to photosynthesis, a key determinant of plant productivity and fitness.</p> <p>We showed that one polyploid species was transgressive (more extreme than either diploid progenitor) for 17 of 21 photosynthesis-related phenotypes, including a near doubling of photosynthetic capacity per cell. Using gene expression profiling, we demonstrated that this polyploid exhibits a wholesale upregulation of the Calvin cycle, the central metabolic network of photosynthesis.&nbsp; Given the rate limiting role of this network under the growth and measurement conditions used in this study, the increase in expression across the Calvin cycle gene network is a strong candidate to explain the observed increase in photosynthetic capacity.</p> <p>In the process of photosynthesis, all plants absorb more energy from sunlight than can be used for carbon fixation. If not effectively dissipated, this excess energy causes severe damage to photosynthetic tissues (analogous to sunburn and its associated negative health consequences). Plants dissipate excess light energy in a process called &ldquo;nonphotochemical quenching&rdquo; or &ldquo;NPQ&rdquo;, which, to extend the analogy, can be considered a sort of plant sunscreen. We showed that three polyploid species possess enhanced NPQ capacity relative to their diploid progenitors. Gene expression profiling identified three gene networks that are upregulated in one of these polyploids relative to its progenitors: carotenoid biosynthesis, the water-water cycle, and cyclic electron flow around photosystem I. Each of these networks is known to function in dissipating excess light energy as heat. Two of these gene networks (the water-water cycle, and cyclic electron flow around photosystem I) are also upregulated in a second polyploid species exhibiting enhanced capacity for NPQ, suggesting that common molecular mechanisms underlie this trait in independent polyploid species. Intriguingly, however, none of these pathways is upregulated in the third polyploid examined, suggesting that polyploidy can also produce common phenotypes via distinct molecular pathways&mdash;a general phenomenon we term &ldquo;phenotypic convergence&rdquo;.</p> <p>These findings shed light on the molecular mechanisms underlying traits altered by polyploidy, and help to explain the apparent success of polyploidy in flowering plants. This work also offers insights into how to improve both primary productivity and stress tolerance in cultivated crop species, many of which are also polyploids. Finally, we have generated gene expression profiling datasets for multiple accessions of each of seven species (three polyploid and four diploid), and two light intensities (low intensity limiting to photosynthesis and high intensity in excess of a plant&rsquo;s capacity for utilization by photosynthesis). These datasets are publically available through the NCBI Short Read Archive.</p> <p>Broader impacts of the project included the training of undergraduate and graduate students, including members of groups under-represented in science, as well as postdoctoral fellows. In addition, K-12 teachers learned about polyploidy through the Cornell Institute for Biology Teachers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/21/2012<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;J&nbsp;Doyle</p> </div> <...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A defining characteristic of plant evolution is the recurrence of polyploidy or whole genome duplication (a doubling of the amount of DNA per nucleus). How polyploidy has contributed to the success of flowering plants has been identified as one of the most important questions facing plant science research. Among the wild relatives of the cultivated soybean are several recently formed polyploid species, as well as their non-duplicated diploid progenitors, providing an ideal system for studying the effects of polyploidy on plant traits. Using this system, we examined the effects of polyploidy on several traits relating to photosynthesis, a key determinant of plant productivity and fitness.  We showed that one polyploid species was transgressive (more extreme than either diploid progenitor) for 17 of 21 photosynthesis-related phenotypes, including a near doubling of photosynthetic capacity per cell. Using gene expression profiling, we demonstrated that this polyploid exhibits a wholesale upregulation of the Calvin cycle, the central metabolic network of photosynthesis.  Given the rate limiting role of this network under the growth and measurement conditions used in this study, the increase in expression across the Calvin cycle gene network is a strong candidate to explain the observed increase in photosynthetic capacity.  In the process of photosynthesis, all plants absorb more energy from sunlight than can be used for carbon fixation. If not effectively dissipated, this excess energy causes severe damage to photosynthetic tissues (analogous to sunburn and its associated negative health consequences). Plants dissipate excess light energy in a process called "nonphotochemical quenching" or "NPQ", which, to extend the analogy, can be considered a sort of plant sunscreen. We showed that three polyploid species possess enhanced NPQ capacity relative to their diploid progenitors. Gene expression profiling identified three gene networks that are upregulated in one of these polyploids relative to its progenitors: carotenoid biosynthesis, the water-water cycle, and cyclic electron flow around photosystem I. Each of these networks is known to function in dissipating excess light energy as heat. Two of these gene networks (the water-water cycle, and cyclic electron flow around photosystem I) are also upregulated in a second polyploid species exhibiting enhanced capacity for NPQ, suggesting that common molecular mechanisms underlie this trait in independent polyploid species. Intriguingly, however, none of these pathways is upregulated in the third polyploid examined, suggesting that polyploidy can also produce common phenotypes via distinct molecular pathways&mdash;a general phenomenon we term "phenotypic convergence".  These findings shed light on the molecular mechanisms underlying traits altered by polyploidy, and help to explain the apparent success of polyploidy in flowering plants. This work also offers insights into how to improve both primary productivity and stress tolerance in cultivated crop species, many of which are also polyploids. Finally, we have generated gene expression profiling datasets for multiple accessions of each of seven species (three polyploid and four diploid), and two light intensities (low intensity limiting to photosynthesis and high intensity in excess of a plantÆs capacity for utilization by photosynthesis). These datasets are publically available through the NCBI Short Read Archive.  Broader impacts of the project included the training of undergraduate and graduate students, including members of groups under-represented in science, as well as postdoctoral fellows. In addition, K-12 teachers learned about polyploidy through the Cornell Institute for Biology Teachers.       Last Modified: 05/21/2012       Submitted by: Jeffrey J Doyle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
