<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Regioregular Poly(3-alkylthiophene) Supramolecular Structures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>435000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>441000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070012</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;Conductive polymers have been widely used in organic electronic devices such as field-effect transistors (FETs) and photovoltaic devices (OPVs) where the polymer charge mobility and morphology play an important role in obtaining high device efficiency. With the support of this CAREER award, Professor Zhai's research group at University of Central Florida will 1) fabricate regiorecular poly(alkylthiophene)(rrPAT) ordered nanowire structures via perylene diimide ending group functionalization, 2) fabricate rrPAT nanocolumnar structures via a living polymerization from triphenylene, 3) build freestanding rrPAT nanofilms via the self-assembly of rrPATs with oligopeptides connected through photolabile links, 4) fabricate rrPAT/carbon nanotube composites by the dispersion of carbon nanotubes using various block copolymers comprised of rrPAT and nonconjugated polymer segments, and 5) study the electrical properties of rrPAT supramolecular structures and rrPAT/carbon nanotube composites. This research will bring about a deeper understanding of the relationship between molecular structures, solid assemblies and electrical properties, provide rational and predictable design rules for fabricating conductive polymer structures with desired properties for organic electronics, and realize efficient FETs and OPVs. This program will offer interdisciplinary research opportunities for graduate, undergraduate and high school students. It is critical that multidisciplinary training is expanded in our educational system to prepare future engineers and scientists for our society. A nanoscience and technology educational module will also be established at the NanoScience Technology Center at UCF that will introduce nanoscience to college and K-12 students as well as the general audience. Extra effort will be taken to reach minority and underrepresented groups through the educational module.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;Conductive polymers, i.e. plastics that can conduct electricity, have been proved to be very promising in replacing inorganic materials such as silicon in electronics. Polymers are light, flexible and ease to process, which allow for the fabrication of flexible electronic devices including large area flexible displays and solar cells. This CAREER award will support the research that will investigate how to increase the efficiency of organic electronics by building ordered polymeric structures. The success of the program will provide materials for low cost and efficient organic electronics that will have great impact on the economy. For example, the organic solar cells will greatly reduce the cost of solar energy which is the most important renewable energy. The research program involves multidisciplinary collaboration in nanoscience and technology and will provide interdisciplinary education and training for graduate, undergraduate and K-12 students. The education and outreaching activities include 1) developing a graduate/undergraduate course entitled "Organic Photovoltaics", 2) offering interdisciplinary research opportunities for graduate, undergraduate and high school students, and 2) developing a nanoscience and technology educational module including a nanomuseum that will provide hands-on experience on nanoscience for college and K-12 students as well as the general audience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0746499</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lei Zhai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lzhai@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078822847</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000345775</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/10/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees]]></Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~87000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~87000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~93000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~87000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~87000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research performed in the program includes three focusing areas.</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp; Dispersing and functionalizating carbon nanotubes (CNTs) using block copolymers containing poly(3-hexylthiophene) and fabricating CNT composites.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have developed a simple and versatile approach to disperse and functionalize CNTs using conjugated block copolymers with well controlled polymer composition and molecular weight using atomic transfer polymerization (ATRP) and reversible addition&ndash;fragmentation chain transfer (RAFT) polymerization. In contrast to traditional CNT functionalization approaches involving invasive chemical treatments that deteriorate the electrical and mechanical properties of CNTs, our approach utilizes non-invasive pi-pi interactions to disperse and functionalize CNTs. Upon a simple sonication, the conjugated block forms a strong pi-pi interaction with CNTs to de-bundle the CNTs, while the non-conjugated block provides the solubility of exfoliated CNTs in a wide range of solvents and polymer matrices. Our study<br />demonstrated that both MWCNTs and SWCNTs can be dispersed effectively in various solvents using conjugated block copolymers (CBCPs). Additionally, the non-conjugated blocks introduce various functional groups on CNT surfaces, facilitating the fabrication of other CNT nanocomposites such as CNT/polymer composites, CNT aerogels and CNT/nanoparticle composites.</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp;Studying the crystallization behaviour of poly(3-hexylthiophene) and thiophene containing conjugated polymers.</p> <p>We have systematically investigated the P3HT crystallization process in solutions by changing molecular weight (Mn), crystallization temperature and polymer concentration. We found that P3HT polymer chains transit from extending to folding in nanowhiskers when the Mn is above a critical value (10K Da), and the folding length can be control by crystallization temperature. Such observation provides the first experimental support of P3HT chain folding when P3HT crystallizes from solutions. Furthermore, 1D nanowhiskers composed of extended P3HT chains can grow into highly ordered two-dimensional (2D) nanoribbons from more concentrated P3HT solutions, generating a new class of large area P3HT crystals. The impact of polymer backbone rigidity of rr-P3HT and other thiophene-containing CPs including poly(3,3-didodecylquaterthiophene) (PQT-12), poly(2,5-bis(3-tetradecylthiophen-2-yl)thieno[3,2-b] thiophene) (PBTTT-14), and poly(2,5-bis(3-tetradecylthiophen-2-yl)thiophen-2-yl)thiophen-2-ylthiazolo[5,4-d]thiazole)(PTzQT-14) on their crystallization behavior in solutions has been investigated in our group through structure characterization, theoretical simulation, and single molecule fluorescence spectroscopy (SMS). Our studies suggest that the inter-ring &sigma; bond rotation energy barrier and backbone conformational transformability of CPs determine the polymer chain flexibility which gives chain-folding tendency of rrP3HT&gt;PBTTT-14&gt;PQT-12&gt;PTzQT-14. It is interesting to notice that PBTTT-14 have higher tendency to fold than PQT-12 despite its rigid fused ring structures, and PTzQT-14 demonstrates very high rigidity due to the combination of fused ring structure and high inter-ring &sigma; bond rotation energy barrier. Such different backbone rigidity leads to chain-folding (for rrP3HT and PBTTT-14) and chain-extending (for PQT-12 and PTzQT-14) structures in CP crystals in solutions.</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;&nbsp;Investigating the formation of poly(3-hexylthiophene) supramolecular structures on carbon nanotubes and graphene derivatives, and fabricating organic field-effect transistor (OFET) devices by directly growing crystalline P3HT nanowires on single-walled carbon nanotube (SWCNT) electrodes.</p> <p>We have discovered that dispersed CNTs and reduced graphene oxide (RGO) could induce the nucleation of P3HT homopolymer and block copolym...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research performed in the program includes three focusing areas.  (1)   Dispersing and functionalizating carbon nanotubes (CNTs) using block copolymers containing poly(3-hexylthiophene) and fabricating CNT composites.   We have developed a simple and versatile approach to disperse and functionalize CNTs using conjugated block copolymers with well controlled polymer composition and molecular weight using atomic transfer polymerization (ATRP) and reversible addition&ndash;fragmentation chain transfer (RAFT) polymerization. In contrast to traditional CNT functionalization approaches involving invasive chemical treatments that deteriorate the electrical and mechanical properties of CNTs, our approach utilizes non-invasive pi-pi interactions to disperse and functionalize CNTs. Upon a simple sonication, the conjugated block forms a strong pi-pi interaction with CNTs to de-bundle the CNTs, while the non-conjugated block provides the solubility of exfoliated CNTs in a wide range of solvents and polymer matrices. Our study demonstrated that both MWCNTs and SWCNTs can be dispersed effectively in various solvents using conjugated block copolymers (CBCPs). Additionally, the non-conjugated blocks introduce various functional groups on CNT surfaces, facilitating the fabrication of other CNT nanocomposites such as CNT/polymer composites, CNT aerogels and CNT/nanoparticle composites.  (2)  Studying the crystallization behaviour of poly(3-hexylthiophene) and thiophene containing conjugated polymers.  We have systematically investigated the P3HT crystallization process in solutions by changing molecular weight (Mn), crystallization temperature and polymer concentration. We found that P3HT polymer chains transit from extending to folding in nanowhiskers when the Mn is above a critical value (10K Da), and the folding length can be control by crystallization temperature. Such observation provides the first experimental support of P3HT chain folding when P3HT crystallizes from solutions. Furthermore, 1D nanowhiskers composed of extended P3HT chains can grow into highly ordered two-dimensional (2D) nanoribbons from more concentrated P3HT solutions, generating a new class of large area P3HT crystals. The impact of polymer backbone rigidity of rr-P3HT and other thiophene-containing CPs including poly(3,3-didodecylquaterthiophene) (PQT-12), poly(2,5-bis(3-tetradecylthiophen-2-yl)thieno[3,2-b] thiophene) (PBTTT-14), and poly(2,5-bis(3-tetradecylthiophen-2-yl)thiophen-2-yl)thiophen-2-ylthiazolo[5,4-d]thiazole)(PTzQT-14) on their crystallization behavior in solutions has been investigated in our group through structure characterization, theoretical simulation, and single molecule fluorescence spectroscopy (SMS). Our studies suggest that the inter-ring &sigma; bond rotation energy barrier and backbone conformational transformability of CPs determine the polymer chain flexibility which gives chain-folding tendency of rrP3HT&gt;PBTTT-14&gt;PQT-12&gt;PTzQT-14. It is interesting to notice that PBTTT-14 have higher tendency to fold than PQT-12 despite its rigid fused ring structures, and PTzQT-14 demonstrates very high rigidity due to the combination of fused ring structure and high inter-ring &sigma; bond rotation energy barrier. Such different backbone rigidity leads to chain-folding (for rrP3HT and PBTTT-14) and chain-extending (for PQT-12 and PTzQT-14) structures in CP crystals in solutions.  (3)  Investigating the formation of poly(3-hexylthiophene) supramolecular structures on carbon nanotubes and graphene derivatives, and fabricating organic field-effect transistor (OFET) devices by directly growing crystalline P3HT nanowires on single-walled carbon nanotube (SWCNT) electrodes.  We have discovered that dispersed CNTs and reduced graphene oxide (RGO) could induce the nucleation of P3HT homopolymer and block copolymers to form supramolecular structures (i.e. nanowires) on their surfaces. Such process is driven by the strong pi-pi interactions between ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
