<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Integrated Scanning and Optical Imaging Techniques to Enable Understanding of Live Cell Dynamics - From Molecular Biology to Physiological Function</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>429783.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>521877</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krastan Blagoev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kblagoev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924666</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this CAREER proposal the PI proposes to develop a uniquely integrated microscopy technology that is broadly applicable across a wide range of molecular dynamic studies in live cells. The technique's capabilities will be demonstrated by studying the dynamic structure-function relationship of the living cell as it adapts to its local mechanical environment. The objectives of the proposed research and educational plan are to: (1) Develop and demonstrate a state-of-the-art integrated microscope system that combines Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM), Fast Spinning-Disk (FSD) Confocal Microscopy and Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence (TIRF) into one instrument; (2) Apply the integrated AFM-optical imaging technology to study protein dynamics in the fundamental process of cellular reorganization in response to mechanical force; (3) Implement an educational plan that will: (a) expose high school students, especially girls and underrepresented minorities, to advancements in the biophysical sciences with the aim of enhancing their interest in pursuing careers in science; (b) develop an innovative graduate course module that uses interactive and visual techniques to help life science and engineering students better understand the physics of advanced imaging; and (c) develop a website on AFM theory and its biological applications to serve as an open-source interactive teaching tool. The education plan will introduce basic science concepts of this interdisciplinary field of research and hands on experience to high school students, focusing on girls and minority students, through a new program: Saturday Morning Biophysics: Image Life! The PI will also mentor one graduate and two undergraduate students in this interdisciplinary, cutting-edge research project.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0747334</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreea</FirstName>
<LastName>Trache</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreea Trache</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trache@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794360826</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491523</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Warren</FirstName>
<LastName>Zimmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Warren E Zimmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wezimmer@medicine.tamhsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798458600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000661659</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/12/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Texas A&amp;M University System  HSC Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>141582986</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY SYSTEM HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Texas A&amp;M University System HSC]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778453572</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7282</Code>
<Text>Midscale Physics Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~83538</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~91288</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~86530</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~88004</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~172517</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The cell is the basic unit of any living organism. Mechanical forces from the surrounding tissue matrix directly impact cellular function and structure. The research supported by this award was designed to study how external mechanical forces affect the dynamic structure-function relationship of the living cell as it adapts to its local mechanical environment. To be able to address this specific question, a novel microscope system that combines live-cell mechanical stimulation with fluorescence imaging into one integrated instrument has been developed. The atomic force microscope can be used to mechanically stimulate live cells or to measure matrix protein binding to specific ligands on the cell surface. Total internal reflection and spinning-disk confocal fluorescence microscopy were used to image the mechanically stimulated live cells expressing green fluorescent proteins. Our results provided new insights into cellular adaptation to mechanical stimuli. We learned that cytoskeletal tension plays a central role in modulating cell adhesion to the matrix. We also learned that contractile state of the cell regulates the ability of the cell to sense and adapt to external forces from the microenvironment.</p> <p>The Outreach Program &lsquo;Saturday Morning Biophysics: Image Life!&rsquo; was implemented as part of the CAREER award. This outreach effort integrated well with our research and provided ample opportunities for active learning. The goal of the program was to introduce biophysical science concepts and hands-on experience to mid- and high-school students, with a focus on increasing the participation of women and minority students in the sciences. This outreach program was attended by 230 girls, grades 6-12, from rural Texas areas.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/16/2015<br>      Modified by: Andreea&nbsp;Trache</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The cell is the basic unit of any living organism. Mechanical forces from the surrounding tissue matrix directly impact cellular function and structure. The research supported by this award was designed to study how external mechanical forces affect the dynamic structure-function relationship of the living cell as it adapts to its local mechanical environment. To be able to address this specific question, a novel microscope system that combines live-cell mechanical stimulation with fluorescence imaging into one integrated instrument has been developed. The atomic force microscope can be used to mechanically stimulate live cells or to measure matrix protein binding to specific ligands on the cell surface. Total internal reflection and spinning-disk confocal fluorescence microscopy were used to image the mechanically stimulated live cells expressing green fluorescent proteins. Our results provided new insights into cellular adaptation to mechanical stimuli. We learned that cytoskeletal tension plays a central role in modulating cell adhesion to the matrix. We also learned that contractile state of the cell regulates the ability of the cell to sense and adapt to external forces from the microenvironment.  The Outreach Program æSaturday Morning Biophysics: Image Life!Æ was implemented as part of the CAREER award. This outreach effort integrated well with our research and provided ample opportunities for active learning. The goal of the program was to introduce biophysical science concepts and hands-on experience to mid- and high-school students, with a focus on increasing the participation of women and minority students in the sciences. This outreach program was attended by 230 girls, grades 6-12, from rural Texas areas.       Last Modified: 07/16/2015       Submitted by: Andreea Trache]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
