<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Solvation and Crowding Effects on Unfolded Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>483827.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>483827</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michele McGuirl</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most protein molecules are able to exist in two dramatically different conformational states, a well-defined folded structure and an unfolded state that is composed of an immense number of rapidly interconverting conformations.  Although biological function is usually associated with the folded state, unfolded polypeptides are now recognized to play important roles in both normal and aberrant cellular function, including protein localization and degradation and the formation of amyloid fibers.  The physical properties of unfolded proteins remain poorly defined and the subject of considerable controversy. Most of the available information about these molecules comes from studies of dilute solutions in denaturants.  This project is directed towards developing an improved understanding of unfolded proteins under more physiological conditions, using a combination of computational and experimental approaches.  The physical properties of several model unfolded proteins will be examined using small-angle x-ray scattering, NMR-based diffusion measurements, and measurements of equilibrium constants for the formation of disulfide bonds between cysteine residues.  These measurements will provide quantitative information about properties such as average dimensions, packing densities and the energetics of intramolecular interactions.  In addition, small-angle neutron scattering will be used to study the unfolded proteins in the presence of high concentrations of other proteins. The experimental results will be directly compared to the predictions of computational simulations recently developed in this laboratory, so as to test the assumptions of the model and allow the experimental data to be interpreted in structural terms.  Together, the computational and experimental results will provide unique information about the effects of solvent interactions and macromolecular crowding on unfolded proteins and will lead to an improved understanding of their behavior in the cellular environment. &lt;br/&gt;This research will have an immediate impact on scientific training through the participation of undergraduate and graduate students, who will be responsible for the majority of the work and will actively contribute to its intellectual progress.  The project also includes an international collaboration, with Dr. Jill Trewhella of the University of Sydney (Australia), and exchange visits between the two laboratories will contribute to the broader education of members of each laboratory. Because the principal investigator is also actively engaged in the teaching of both undergraduate and graduate courses, the methods and ideas developed in this project are very likely to be incorporated into more formal educational activities, as exemplified by his previous development of a biochemistry laboratory course based on materials and methods from his research program.  The computer programs and scripts written for this project will be made available to other investigators and educators, so as to allow further testing and refinement of the models, as well as their use as pedagogical tools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0749464</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David P Goldenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>goldenberg@biology.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015813885</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480375</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75 S 2000 E]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1166</Code>
<Text>MOLECULAR BIOCHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~151264</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~162297</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~170266</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major focus of this study was the characterization of unfolded proteins and the influence of solvent additives (such as urea) and macromolecular crowding on the conformations of these molecules. &nbsp;Proteins can exist in a wide range of conformational states, including compact folded structures with well defined three-dimensional structures and more extended unfolded states that represent broad ensembles of rapidly interconverting conformations. &nbsp;Protein function, including enzymatic catalysis and regulatory activities, are usually associated with folded conformations, but &nbsp;increasing attention has been placed on disordered states in recent years, Disordered proteins include both the precursors of folded structures and a large class of recently-recognized molecules for which the functional state may be disordered, the intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). Both general classes of disordered proteins may be sensitive to changes in solution conditions, and an accurate description of these effects may be crucial to understanding both the normal and pathological functions of proteins. &nbsp;</p> <p>The protein that we have studied most extensively is the bacteriophage&nbsp;&lambda; N protein, which is produced by a virus that infects the bacterium Escherichia coli. The&nbsp;&lambda; N protein plays a critical role in the regulation of gene expression and functions by interacting with other molecules that make up the machinery responsible for transcribing a DNA segment into RNA. &nbsp;Like many proteins that regulate transcription,&nbsp;&lambda; N is intrinsically disordered and thus serves as a model of other regulatory IDPs. &nbsp;We have used small-angle X-ray and neutron scattering (SAXS and SANS) as well as NMR spectroscopy to characterize&nbsp;&lambda; N under a variety of solution conditions.</p> <p>Perhaps the most unique aspect of the work supported by this NSF grant was the use of SANS to study the properties of&nbsp;&lambda; N in the presence of high concentrations of other proteins. &nbsp;Most biochemical and biophysical studies of proteins, both folded and disordered, have been carried out using solutions that are much more dilute than the environments in which most proteins function in vivo. &nbsp;Because they represent broad ensembles of conformations of different dimensions, unfolded proteins are generally expected to be particularly sensitive to macromolecular crowding, but directly measuring these effects is technically difficult, and theoretical treatments have yielded a variety of different predictions. &nbsp;Because neutrons are scattered from atomic nuclei, and are scattered differentially by differerent isotopes of the same element, SANS is particularly well suited for studying one type of molecule in the presence of high concentrations of other molecules. &nbsp;To study the effects of crowding on an IDP, we prepared &nbsp;<sup>2</sup>H-labeled&nbsp;&lambda; N protein and measured SANS in the presence of two unlabeled globular proteins (separately), bovine pancreatic trypsin inhibitor (BPTI) and equine myoglobin (Mb) at concentrations up to 200 mg/mL. &nbsp;The&nbsp;solutions &nbsp;also contained D<sub>2</sub>O at concentrations adjusted to match the scattering from the BPTI and Mb, effectively making them invisible. &nbsp;The SANS measurements were carried out at the Center for Neutron Science at the National Institute of Standards and Technology and at Oak Ridge National Laboratory. Contrary to expectations, these measurements showed almost no effect of crowding on the average dimensions of the disordered protein. &nbsp;These results thus challenge prevailing views on macromolecular crowding and have important implications for the behavior of proteins in vivo.</p> <p>The SANS measurements have been complemented by small-angle X-ray scattering experiments and NMR studies of&nbsp;&lambda; N, which demonstrate that the protein re...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major focus of this study was the characterization of unfolded proteins and the influence of solvent additives (such as urea) and macromolecular crowding on the conformations of these molecules.  Proteins can exist in a wide range of conformational states, including compact folded structures with well defined three-dimensional structures and more extended unfolded states that represent broad ensembles of rapidly interconverting conformations.  Protein function, including enzymatic catalysis and regulatory activities, are usually associated with folded conformations, but  increasing attention has been placed on disordered states in recent years, Disordered proteins include both the precursors of folded structures and a large class of recently-recognized molecules for which the functional state may be disordered, the intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs). Both general classes of disordered proteins may be sensitive to changes in solution conditions, and an accurate description of these effects may be crucial to understanding both the normal and pathological functions of proteins.    The protein that we have studied most extensively is the bacteriophage &lambda; N protein, which is produced by a virus that infects the bacterium Escherichia coli. The &lambda; N protein plays a critical role in the regulation of gene expression and functions by interacting with other molecules that make up the machinery responsible for transcribing a DNA segment into RNA.  Like many proteins that regulate transcription, &lambda; N is intrinsically disordered and thus serves as a model of other regulatory IDPs.  We have used small-angle X-ray and neutron scattering (SAXS and SANS) as well as NMR spectroscopy to characterize &lambda; N under a variety of solution conditions.  Perhaps the most unique aspect of the work supported by this NSF grant was the use of SANS to study the properties of &lambda; N in the presence of high concentrations of other proteins.  Most biochemical and biophysical studies of proteins, both folded and disordered, have been carried out using solutions that are much more dilute than the environments in which most proteins function in vivo.  Because they represent broad ensembles of conformations of different dimensions, unfolded proteins are generally expected to be particularly sensitive to macromolecular crowding, but directly measuring these effects is technically difficult, and theoretical treatments have yielded a variety of different predictions.  Because neutrons are scattered from atomic nuclei, and are scattered differentially by differerent isotopes of the same element, SANS is particularly well suited for studying one type of molecule in the presence of high concentrations of other molecules.  To study the effects of crowding on an IDP, we prepared  2H-labeled &lambda; N protein and measured SANS in the presence of two unlabeled globular proteins (separately), bovine pancreatic trypsin inhibitor (BPTI) and equine myoglobin (Mb) at concentrations up to 200 mg/mL.  The solutions  also contained D2O at concentrations adjusted to match the scattering from the BPTI and Mb, effectively making them invisible.  The SANS measurements were carried out at the Center for Neutron Science at the National Institute of Standards and Technology and at Oak Ridge National Laboratory. Contrary to expectations, these measurements showed almost no effect of crowding on the average dimensions of the disordered protein.  These results thus challenge prevailing views on macromolecular crowding and have important implications for the behavior of proteins in vivo.  The SANS measurements have been complemented by small-angle X-ray scattering experiments and NMR studies of &lambda; N, which demonstrate that the protein remains highly disordered and expanded under a variety of solution conditions but also displays sequence-specific tendencies to form transient &alpha;-helical structures.  We have also used SAXS to characterize the inte...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
