<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IDBR: Field-Based Tomographic Microscopy Instruments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>650305.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>650305</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joyce Fernandes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A grant has been awarded to Drs. Feld and Badizadegan at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology to develop next generation phase microscopy instruments for biological research. The phase contrast microscope and related techniques have been a cornerstone of nearly every biology laboratory for more than half a century. The popularity of these methods lies in their unique ability to visualize live cells and their internal structures without any specific preparation or chemical modification. In spite of their enormous value to biological research, however, current phase microscopy techniques provide only qualitative information about cell structures. In addition, current phase microscopy techniques reduce the three-dimensional structure of the cell to two-dimensional images, thus reducing the value of these techniques in studies in which identifying the precise location of subcellular structures is of value.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research supported by this grant will enable the MIT group to design and fabricate novel instrumentation that will overcome limitations of the current phase microscopy methods, thus significantly broadening the value and scope of phase microscopy in biological research. Most cells and tissue are as transparent as glass, and therefore not clearly visible without chemical alteration such as staining with exogenous dyes. The standard intensity-based phase microscopy methods, which measure the absorption or reflection of light, have therefore difficulty in visualizing live cells in detail. The group will utilize so-called "field-based" approach to analyze variations in the speed of light (or refractive index) which result from variations in the structural components of the cell. This approach enables them to visualize and measure transparent cellular materials with extreme sensitivity. Combined with a novel imaging method that is similar to X-ray computed tomography (CT scan) used by physicians to image the human body, the MIT group will produce 3-dimensional, quantitative images of live cells in real time by quantifying variations in the speed of light at every location inside the cells. In addition, the group proposes to utilize a high-throughput method that will enable extracting quantitative information from a large number of cells in a short period of time. Collectively, these advanced instruments will enable biologists to visualize, measure and monitor the structure of live cells in ways that have not been possible before.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Quantitative characterization of cellular structures in their native state (without chemical or physical alterations) is the ultimate goal in biological microscopy. The instrumentation that will be constructed as a result of this grant award will advance biomedical phase microscopy into the next generation by enabling quantitative, 3-dimensional, real-time, and high-throughput imaging. The biological and biomedical applications of these novel methods are numerous and diverse. In addition, this research is conducted within an interdisciplinary academic environment with scientists, engineers and physicians who are uniquely qualified to guide and oversee successful translation of these novel instruments in biology.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0754339</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramachandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Dasari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramachandra R Dasari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rrdasari@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172535377</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000108443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Feld</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael S Feld</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>msfeld@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172537700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/01/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kamran</FirstName>
<LastName>Badizadegan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kamran Badizadegan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kamran@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172531000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000465113</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/21/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9104</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~251569</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~221792</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~176944</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Optical microscopy has been a major tool for biological and biomedical research for centuries. While other techniques such as electron and X-ray microscopy offer significantly better spatial resolution, light microscopy occupies a central role in biomedical science because of its ease of use and potential for noninvasive and live cell imaging. Extrinsic contrast methods such as fluorescence light microscopy are widely used due to their molecular specificity and high spatial resolution. In contrast, optical methods using intrinsic contrast such as variations in sample absorption or refractive index, offer significant advantages such as live cell imaging without any sample preparation, chemical alteration or exogenous labels.</p> <p>The phase or optical delay of light transmitted through a sample is related to its refractive index distribution, which is the measure of sample&rsquo;s optical density. The use of optical phase in biological imaging of cells has a rich and long history dating back to Zernike&rsquo;s invention of phase-contrast microscopy, for which he won the 1953 Nobel Prize. Differential interference contrast (DIC) microscopy also utilizes the optical phase for cellular imaging with outstanding contrast and high spatial resolution. However,&nbsp;one of the major limitations of these approaches is that they <em>qualitative</em> in nature. Recent developments in phase microscopy have focused on obtaining the <em>quantitative </em>phase information through the use of interferometry and digital imaging devices such as CCD cameras. Over the past several years, our laboratory has developed experimental methods and prototype instruments that enable quantitative imaging of cells and tissues using refractive index as the primary source of contrast.</p> <p>The goal of this proposal has been to design and construct the next-generation instrumentation that will enable real-time, quantitative, tomographic (or three-dimensional) images of live cells and tissues under static or flow conditions. The three-dimensional (3-D) refractive index imaging is an optical analog of X-ray computed tomography, except that the biological sample is not rotated to acquire the data. Instead, biological cells are left to grow in their most native condition, for example, on a glass slide. High-speed two-dimensional optical phase measurements of a cell under observation are acquired for different angles of illumination of the laser beam. Taking the diffraction of light from different cellular organelles into account, high-resolution 3-D images of the cell are produced. Additional signal processing techniques have been developed and implemented to further improve the measurement accuracy and 3-D mapping of refractive index. We have also developed a method to recover the 3-D structural image of a flowing sample. Such an approach will be extremely useful in a scenario where a large number of cells can be made to flow under the microscope field of view for imaging or analysis.</p> <p>The technology we have developed has a broad impact on many areas of biomedical science, and has been successfully used for a number core and collaborative studies. Some of the projects include: non-invasive study of structural and biochemical changes in malaria-infected red blood cells; size and optical density measurement of nanoscale cholesterol ribbons, which may be used as devices for measuring and transducing forces between biological objects; quantification of drug-cell interaction in multiple myeloma cells; and the measurement of dry (non-aqueous) mass during cell growth.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2012<br>      Modified by: Ramachandra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Dasari</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Optical microscopy has been a major tool for biological and biomedical research for centuries. While other techniques such as electron and X-ray microscopy offer significantly better spatial resolution, light microscopy occupies a central role in biomedical science because of its ease of use and potential for noninvasive and live cell imaging. Extrinsic contrast methods such as fluorescence light microscopy are widely used due to their molecular specificity and high spatial resolution. In contrast, optical methods using intrinsic contrast such as variations in sample absorption or refractive index, offer significant advantages such as live cell imaging without any sample preparation, chemical alteration or exogenous labels.  The phase or optical delay of light transmitted through a sample is related to its refractive index distribution, which is the measure of sampleÆs optical density. The use of optical phase in biological imaging of cells has a rich and long history dating back to ZernikeÆs invention of phase-contrast microscopy, for which he won the 1953 Nobel Prize. Differential interference contrast (DIC) microscopy also utilizes the optical phase for cellular imaging with outstanding contrast and high spatial resolution. However, one of the major limitations of these approaches is that they qualitative in nature. Recent developments in phase microscopy have focused on obtaining the quantitative phase information through the use of interferometry and digital imaging devices such as CCD cameras. Over the past several years, our laboratory has developed experimental methods and prototype instruments that enable quantitative imaging of cells and tissues using refractive index as the primary source of contrast.  The goal of this proposal has been to design and construct the next-generation instrumentation that will enable real-time, quantitative, tomographic (or three-dimensional) images of live cells and tissues under static or flow conditions. The three-dimensional (3-D) refractive index imaging is an optical analog of X-ray computed tomography, except that the biological sample is not rotated to acquire the data. Instead, biological cells are left to grow in their most native condition, for example, on a glass slide. High-speed two-dimensional optical phase measurements of a cell under observation are acquired for different angles of illumination of the laser beam. Taking the diffraction of light from different cellular organelles into account, high-resolution 3-D images of the cell are produced. Additional signal processing techniques have been developed and implemented to further improve the measurement accuracy and 3-D mapping of refractive index. We have also developed a method to recover the 3-D structural image of a flowing sample. Such an approach will be extremely useful in a scenario where a large number of cells can be made to flow under the microscope field of view for imaging or analysis.  The technology we have developed has a broad impact on many areas of biomedical science, and has been successfully used for a number core and collaborative studies. Some of the projects include: non-invasive study of structural and biochemical changes in malaria-infected red blood cells; size and optical density measurement of nanoscale cholesterol ribbons, which may be used as devices for measuring and transducing forces between biological objects; quantification of drug-cell interaction in multiple myeloma cells; and the measurement of dry (non-aqueous) mass during cell growth.       Last Modified: 06/29/2012       Submitted by: Ramachandra R Dasari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
