<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interplay between High Energy Astrophysics, Cosmology, and Particle Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI has a broad research program in particle physics, astrophysics, and cosmology. The first set of his goals exploits the Pierre Auger observatory as an ultra-high-energy particle (UHE) physics laboratory. The PI intends to study the development of UHE cosmic ray (CR) cascades in the atmosphere. To distinguish between the effects of the cosmic ray composition and new effects related to novel hadronic physics, the proposed study will investigate the development of the CR cascades in the atmosphere. Another research area is for the PI to determine the flux of cosmogenic UHE neutrinos due to photomeson production (GZK effect). Once the total amount of data on UHE interactions coming from the Auger Observatory increases, the PI hopes to constrain the number of extra dimensions and probe the possibility of TeV-scale gravity (suggested by having extra spatial dimensions) by studying limits on the production rate of black holes in UHE particle interactions. Observations of the showers triggered by UHE neutrinos  will be used to study neutrino interactions and mixing. By studying the development of UHE CR cascades in the atmosphere the PI hopes to identify exotic R-hadrons (standard hadronic states coupled with gluinos), if they exist and are metastable. The detection techniques of HE and VHE gamma rays have recently improved significantly allowing for much better angular resolution and sensitivity of the instruments. A cutting-edge instrument in MeV-sub TeV range GLAST, is scheduled for launch in 2008.  The PI hopes to utilize the GLAST capability to shed light on the origin of gamma-ray emission. The PI also intends to study exotic particle physics at the LHC and Ice Cube: probes of quantum gravity, search for R-hadrons. He also intends to study of the "unparticle" parameter space which is the regime where conformal field theories at short distances can affect the physics seen at the LHC.  The PI writes for several popular magazines and has appeared on BBC radio to publicize the physics potential of the Ice Cube neutrino telecope at the South Pole.  He is also involved with making the Arecibo Radio Observatory in Puerto Rico available for remote observing by high school as well as college students at the University of Milwaukee.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0757598</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>Anchordoqui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luis A Anchordoqui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>luis.anchordoqui@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3475774119</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/10/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee</Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142294853</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O BOX 340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627906399</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O BOX 340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1288</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br />The three year NSF grant ``Interplay between High Energy Astrophysics,Cosmology, and Particle Physics,'' awarded to University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee researcher Luis Anchordoqui, began in 2008. Anchordoqui's research centered on phenomenology of elementary particles with application to cosmic ray astrophysics, cosmology, neutrino astronomy, and collider physics.</p> <p>Cosmic ray astrophysics and accelerator-based particle physics share common roots. In fact many of the key discoveries early in the history of particle physics came from the study of cosmic rays. After a period of divergence between the two fields, both in methodology and in key areas of interest, a confluence is now underway. During this funding period, Anchordoqui combined data from the Pierre Auger (cosmic ray) Observatory, the IceCube neutrino telescope, the NASA Fermi-LAT mission, and the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) with the goal of furthering our understanding of astrophysics and cosmology while simultaneously investigating related areas of fundamental physics.</p> <p><br />Anchordoqui and his collaborators have been leaders in the search for string resonances at the LHC. In particular, they developed many of the tools needed to uncover the first Regge excitation of the string if it is within reach of LHC. &nbsp;Anchordoqui and collaborators have been instrumental in carrying out searches for cosmogenic neutrinos in an energy&nbsp;regime complemented to dedicated neutrino experiments. The group has demonstrated that such an observation would give important information on the chemical composition and may also provide a unique means to hunt for new physics beyond the Standard Model. Anchordoqui&nbsp;published about 20 refereed short author list papers in leading journals over the past three years. &nbsp;Together with members of the Pierre Auger Collaboration, he coauthored an additional 18 papers, and played leading oversight roles&nbsp;for guiding two to completion.</p> <p><br />Anchordoqui has trained two PhD students during the grant period and has conducted a range of outreach and public education activities. He has given public lectures on particle physics, cosmic ray astrophysics, and spin-offs of technology from physics to general society. &nbsp;He has made innovations in education for undergraduates. He is currently participating in UWM's Interdiciplinary Reserach Experience for Teachers (RET) program, an NSF-funded project which includes Geophysics,Chemestry, Physics, and the Arecibo Remote Command Center (ARCC).&nbsp;Anchordoqui plans to participate as a mentor in this 3-year program beginning in 2012.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2011<br>      Modified by: Luis&nbsp;A&nbsp;Anchordoqui</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The three year NSF grant ``Interplay between High Energy Astrophysics,Cosmology, and Particle Physics,'' awarded to University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee researcher Luis Anchordoqui, began in 2008. Anchordoqui's research centered on phenomenology of elementary particles with application to cosmic ray astrophysics, cosmology, neutrino astronomy, and collider physics.  Cosmic ray astrophysics and accelerator-based particle physics share common roots. In fact many of the key discoveries early in the history of particle physics came from the study of cosmic rays. After a period of divergence between the two fields, both in methodology and in key areas of interest, a confluence is now underway. During this funding period, Anchordoqui combined data from the Pierre Auger (cosmic ray) Observatory, the IceCube neutrino telescope, the NASA Fermi-LAT mission, and the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) with the goal of furthering our understanding of astrophysics and cosmology while simultaneously investigating related areas of fundamental physics.   Anchordoqui and his collaborators have been leaders in the search for string resonances at the LHC. In particular, they developed many of the tools needed to uncover the first Regge excitation of the string if it is within reach of LHC.  Anchordoqui and collaborators have been instrumental in carrying out searches for cosmogenic neutrinos in an energy regime complemented to dedicated neutrino experiments. The group has demonstrated that such an observation would give important information on the chemical composition and may also provide a unique means to hunt for new physics beyond the Standard Model. Anchordoqui published about 20 refereed short author list papers in leading journals over the past three years.  Together with members of the Pierre Auger Collaboration, he coauthored an additional 18 papers, and played leading oversight roles for guiding two to completion.   Anchordoqui has trained two PhD students during the grant period and has conducted a range of outreach and public education activities. He has given public lectures on particle physics, cosmic ray astrophysics, and spin-offs of technology from physics to general society.  He has made innovations in education for undergraduates. He is currently participating in UWM's Interdiciplinary Reserach Experience for Teachers (RET) program, an NSF-funded project which includes Geophysics,Chemestry, Physics, and the Arecibo Remote Command Center (ARCC). Anchordoqui plans to participate as a mentor in this 3-year program beginning in 2012.             Last Modified: 12/06/2011       Submitted by: Luis A Anchordoqui]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
