<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research in High Energy Theoretical Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>181525.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>181525</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI is a leading member of the MILC collaboration which performs nonperturbative studes of QCD using the methods of lattice gauge theory. &lt;br/&gt;The goals of his program in general are to calculate strong-interaction effects in the leptonic and semileptonic decays of mesons, determining the equilibrium properties of the quark-gluon plasma produced at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider by determining the behavior of QCD at finite temperature and density, predicting new excited states in QCD that can be studied and observed in experiments, and finally to test and improve the computational methodology used by the MILC collaboration and then compare simulations&lt;br/&gt;using new algorithms with data on the properties on the light hadrons.  An important focus will be to study the Semileptonic and leptonic decays of heavy-light mesons. These quantities are directly measured in current experiments and can therefore immediately be compared to the lattice calculations. He intends to determine the low energy constants of Chiral Perturbation Theory. Once these constants are computed with a sufficient precision, they can in turn be used to compute physical quantities that are itself not directly accessible to lattice calculations.  Another topic that will be investigated will be QCD thermodynamics when strange quarks are added to previous investigations. &lt;br/&gt;This research project will lead to insight into how the theory of Strong Interactions behaves in non-perturbative regions. This is especially important in the interpretation of experiments where this knowledge is crucial such as in understanding the weak decays of strongly interacting particles, and in the quark gluon plasma.  By training students in Lattice QCD the PI has given students excellent training  in Computational Science which has allowed them to excel in other fields which require this training.  The lattice configurations as well as the algorithms developed by the PI are made available to the community at large. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0757333</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carleton</FirstName>
<LastName>DeTar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carleton E DeTar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>detar@physics.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015817537</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000267526</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/06/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75 S 2000 E]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~59225</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~60496</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~61804</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project continues studies of quantum chromodynamics (the theory of the strong interactions of quarks and gluons) through the use of high performance computer simulations.&nbsp; These studies assist in the ongoing search for the most fundamental particles and interactions in nature and in understanding the origins of the universe.&nbsp; The results of our calculations are essential for extracting results from experimental measurements at US accelerator facilities and at the Large Hadron Collider in Europe.</p> <p>The currently accepted theory of the fundamental interactions is called the "Standard Model". The discovery of the mysterious dark matter and dark energy in the cosmos tells us that still more fundamental processes await discovery.&nbsp; It is widely believed that clues about these processes will be revealed through tests of the internal consistency of the Standard Model. Results from our calculations under this grant have helped reveal a tantalizing discrepancy, but further refinements in the calculations are needed to be sure.</p> <p>We are also studying the properties of the "quark gluon plasma", an exotic form of matter that existed in the early universe. It is recreated in a microcosm in experiments at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Laboratory on Long Island.&nbsp; Calculations of the sort we do are our only source of theoretical&nbsp; information about the properties of this plasma.&nbsp; We have calculated the temperature of plasma formation, and we have calculated the pressure and energy density of the plasma as the temperature is increased.</p> <p>Finally, this grant supported the development of community computer codes and community data files used by several other research groups in the US and abroad&nbsp; in their work.&nbsp; It also supported the training of graduate students in high performance computing and statistical analysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/07/2012<br>      Modified by: Carleton&nbsp;E&nbsp;Detar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project continues studies of quantum chromodynamics (the theory of the strong interactions of quarks and gluons) through the use of high performance computer simulations.  These studies assist in the ongoing search for the most fundamental particles and interactions in nature and in understanding the origins of the universe.  The results of our calculations are essential for extracting results from experimental measurements at US accelerator facilities and at the Large Hadron Collider in Europe.  The currently accepted theory of the fundamental interactions is called the "Standard Model". The discovery of the mysterious dark matter and dark energy in the cosmos tells us that still more fundamental processes await discovery.  It is widely believed that clues about these processes will be revealed through tests of the internal consistency of the Standard Model. Results from our calculations under this grant have helped reveal a tantalizing discrepancy, but further refinements in the calculations are needed to be sure.  We are also studying the properties of the "quark gluon plasma", an exotic form of matter that existed in the early universe. It is recreated in a microcosm in experiments at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Laboratory on Long Island.  Calculations of the sort we do are our only source of theoretical  information about the properties of this plasma.  We have calculated the temperature of plasma formation, and we have calculated the pressure and energy density of the plasma as the temperature is increased.  Finally, this grant supported the development of community computer codes and community data files used by several other research groups in the US and abroad  in their work.  It also supported the training of graduate students in high performance computing and statistical analysis.          Last Modified: 10/07/2012       Submitted by: Carleton E Detar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
