<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Probing Fundamental Physics With Cosmology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>New precision Astronomical observations have spurred the development of a ?concordance? cosmological model, based on inflation and having three components to the energy present in the universe: ordinary matter, dark matter, and dark energy.  The model  is constrained by a variety of high-quality, independent measurements such as large-scale structure, the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), gravitational lensing, the primordial abundances of light elements, and Type-IA Supernovae used as standard candles. The objective of the proposed research is to develop and apply theoretical techniques that use cosmological observations to constrain the physics of the early universe, focusing specifically on the successful paradigm of inflation. Inflation?s basic predictions of Gaussian, adiabatic, nearly scale-invariant cosmological perturbations have been beautifully confirmed by recent data, in particular the WMAP 3-year data set. Upcoming observations have the potential to provide data accurate enough to test inflation beyond a simple lowest-order description. This proposal focuses on four possible signals of new physics which might be detected in future data: Features in the density power spectrum, Primordial gravitational waves, primordial non-Gaussianity and Isocurvature fluctuations.The proposed research is designed to make detailed and quantitative connections between observational data and several properties of inflationary models. Based on high-precision cosmological data one hopes to answer fundamental questions such as the origin of the universe, the unification of gravitation with quantum mechanics, and the quantum-mechanical nature of the vacuum. The proposed project will have significant opportunities for participation by graduate and undergraduate students. There is  wide public interest in cosmology. The PI intends to give public lectures on Cosmology at university and community events.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0757693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Kinney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William H Kinney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>whkinney@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166452017</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000319402</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 Lee Entrance]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Probing Fundamental Physics With Cosmology</strong> was a three-year grant funded by the National Science Foundation. The purpose of the grant was to study how astrophysical observations of the universe can be used as a tool to learn about the fundamental laws of nature. The basic idea is simple: if we study the universe very close to the beginning of space and time, we can use the Big Bang itself as a laboratory for studying the fundamental laws of the universe at much higher energies than can be achieved using terrestrial experiments such as Tevatron at Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory in Chicago and the Large Hadron Collider (LHC)&nbsp; in Geneva, Switzerland.</p> <p>A few questions which we hoped to illuminate with the research conducted under this funding were:</p> <p>- How did the Big Bang Happen?</p> <p>- Where did structure in the universe come from?</p> <p>- Can we use observations of the universe to give us a hint as to the nature of the "Theory of Everything" which is sought to unify quantum mechanics with gravity?</p> <p>These are among the foremost unsolved issues facing physics in the twenty-first century, and this ``Physics of the Universe'' has been identified as a top NSF funding priority.</p> <p>The research of the Principal Investigator William H. Kinney and an international group of collaborators focused primarily on the physics of the universe very close to the moment of the Big Bang, when the universe was less than a trillionth of a trillionth of a trillionth of a second old. This is when it is believed that a period of extremely rapid expansion occurred, called <em>inflation</em>. The universe at this early time was so hot and so dense, that to explain it we need to understand particle physics at energies far beyond what we can test in particle accelerators like LHC. This raises the question: how can we learn anything about this time in the universe so close to the Big Bang? Remarkably, we can. During inflation, the universe was expanding so quickly that tiny variations in in space and time created by the Heisenberg Uncertainty principle were stretched to huge sizes in the rapidly expanding universe, and formed the "seeds" which later collapsed under gravity to form galaxies and clusters of galaxies in the universe today. By studing matter in the universe today, we can actually learn something about the earliest moments of the Big Bang itself, and about how gravity and quantum physics might be unified.</p> <p>Particularly useful in this effort is the light left over from the Big Bang itself, called the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), which has been traveling to detectors on the earth since the universe was about three hundred thousand years old. (About 1 percent of static affecting television transmissions is in fact light from the Big Bang!)&nbsp; Imaging this light gives us a picture of the universe in its initial state, and allows us to clearly see the primordial seeds of structure which were created even earler in inflation. New observations of this light by NASA's Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe satellite have measured the CMB with unprecendented accuracy. The results are remarkable: the data are now so good that we can tell the difference between different models for inflation, which are basically different pictures of the physics of the Big Bang itself.&nbsp; In research funded by this grant, we tested models of inflation against  the new data, and performed a detailed analysis of which models fit the  data, and which do not. The end result is that the idea of inflation in the early universe is now not just a theoretical guess, but is strongly supported by high-precision data. The techniques developed will be key to interpreting future data, such as from the European Space Agency's Planck satellite, which is due to be released in 2013.</p> <p>Is inflation the only way to explain the universe we live in? Could there...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Probing Fundamental Physics With Cosmology was a three-year grant funded by the National Science Foundation. The purpose of the grant was to study how astrophysical observations of the universe can be used as a tool to learn about the fundamental laws of nature. The basic idea is simple: if we study the universe very close to the beginning of space and time, we can use the Big Bang itself as a laboratory for studying the fundamental laws of the universe at much higher energies than can be achieved using terrestrial experiments such as Tevatron at Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory in Chicago and the Large Hadron Collider (LHC)  in Geneva, Switzerland.  A few questions which we hoped to illuminate with the research conducted under this funding were:  - How did the Big Bang Happen?  - Where did structure in the universe come from?  - Can we use observations of the universe to give us a hint as to the nature of the "Theory of Everything" which is sought to unify quantum mechanics with gravity?  These are among the foremost unsolved issues facing physics in the twenty-first century, and this ``Physics of the Universe'' has been identified as a top NSF funding priority.  The research of the Principal Investigator William H. Kinney and an international group of collaborators focused primarily on the physics of the universe very close to the moment of the Big Bang, when the universe was less than a trillionth of a trillionth of a trillionth of a second old. This is when it is believed that a period of extremely rapid expansion occurred, called inflation. The universe at this early time was so hot and so dense, that to explain it we need to understand particle physics at energies far beyond what we can test in particle accelerators like LHC. This raises the question: how can we learn anything about this time in the universe so close to the Big Bang? Remarkably, we can. During inflation, the universe was expanding so quickly that tiny variations in in space and time created by the Heisenberg Uncertainty principle were stretched to huge sizes in the rapidly expanding universe, and formed the "seeds" which later collapsed under gravity to form galaxies and clusters of galaxies in the universe today. By studing matter in the universe today, we can actually learn something about the earliest moments of the Big Bang itself, and about how gravity and quantum physics might be unified.  Particularly useful in this effort is the light left over from the Big Bang itself, called the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), which has been traveling to detectors on the earth since the universe was about three hundred thousand years old. (About 1 percent of static affecting television transmissions is in fact light from the Big Bang!)  Imaging this light gives us a picture of the universe in its initial state, and allows us to clearly see the primordial seeds of structure which were created even earler in inflation. New observations of this light by NASA's Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe satellite have measured the CMB with unprecendented accuracy. The results are remarkable: the data are now so good that we can tell the difference between different models for inflation, which are basically different pictures of the physics of the Big Bang itself.  In research funded by this grant, we tested models of inflation against  the new data, and performed a detailed analysis of which models fit the  data, and which do not. The end result is that the idea of inflation in the early universe is now not just a theoretical guess, but is strongly supported by high-precision data. The techniques developed will be key to interpreting future data, such as from the European Space Agency's Planck satellite, which is due to be released in 2013.  Is inflation the only way to explain the universe we live in? Could there be some other way to build a universe like the one we see with our telescopes? Kinney and collaborators investigated a number of imaginative alternati...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
