<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Monte Carlo Calculations for Nucleon Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmihaila@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will develop methods to calculate the properties of&lt;br/&gt;nuclei and nuclear matter by solving the Schroedinger equation for&lt;br/&gt;nucleons interacting via realistic two- and three-body potentials.&lt;br/&gt;Quantum Monte Carlo techniques are used.  The nucleon positions are&lt;br/&gt;sampled using diffusion Monte Carlo while the spin and isospin degrees&lt;br/&gt;of freedom are sampled by the addition of auxiliary fields. Successful&lt;br/&gt;completion of this work will allow us to verify the accuracy of the&lt;br/&gt;nuclear Hamiltonian by reproducing and comparing to experimental results,&lt;br/&gt;and then to predict the properties of nuclei that are currently difficult&lt;br/&gt;or impossible to produce and measure in the laboratory. These data are&lt;br/&gt;needed to understand, for example, astrophysically important systems&lt;br/&gt;and processes such as neutron rich matter and r-process nucleosynthesis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this work include development of quantum many-particle&lt;br/&gt;methods that can be applied to problems in a variety of other fields&lt;br/&gt;such as electronic structure and cold atomic gases.  The project will&lt;br/&gt;train both undergraduate and graduate students, give them exposure at&lt;br/&gt;national and international conferences,  and provide for dissemination&lt;br/&gt;of the results.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0757703</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmidt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin E Schmidt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kevin.schmidt@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809658240</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303049</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/28/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ORSPA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7244</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7752</Code>
<Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was to perform research on methods to calculate the properties of atomic nuclei and the nuclear matter that occurs in stars particularly neutron stars. The constituent protons and neutrons that make up atomic nuclei are small particles that must be described using quantum Mechanics. Since there are many protons and neutrons in nuclei, an efficient way to calculate their properties is to sample their position and spin-isospin states using probability distributions derived from their interactions. Such methods are called quantum Monte Carlo methods, and we have developed&nbsp; such a method which is called the auxiliary field diffusion Monte Carlo method. In this project we have calculated the properties of neutron star matter, over the range of densities that occur in the neutron star. We have predicted the radius of the stars as a function of their mass. These predictions can be verified by observations on binary pulsars. Calculations predict that some of the neutrons in a neutron star will pair and become a superfluid, that is they can flow without viscosity. We have calculated the pairing energy as a function of density to predict this behavior.<br /><br />We have explored the modifications needed to the interactions of the protons and neutrons to account for the observed three-body forces.<br /><br />The project has completed the training of one Ph.D. nuclear theorist, and begun the training of two more, one nearing completion. It has contributed to the education of three other students -- two graduate students and one undergraduate.</p> <p><br />The supefluid calculations done here have broader impact in other areas of physics where superfluidity occurs. This includes atomic, materials physics, and possible applications to quantum computing.<br /><br />These methods allow us to calculate the properties of nuclei and nuclear matter in regimes where laboratory measurements are either costly, difficult, or impossible. In addition, we can perform calculations where measurements can be made to verify the accuracy of our methods.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/06/2013<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Schmidt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was to perform research on methods to calculate the properties of atomic nuclei and the nuclear matter that occurs in stars particularly neutron stars. The constituent protons and neutrons that make up atomic nuclei are small particles that must be described using quantum Mechanics. Since there are many protons and neutrons in nuclei, an efficient way to calculate their properties is to sample their position and spin-isospin states using probability distributions derived from their interactions. Such methods are called quantum Monte Carlo methods, and we have developed  such a method which is called the auxiliary field diffusion Monte Carlo method. In this project we have calculated the properties of neutron star matter, over the range of densities that occur in the neutron star. We have predicted the radius of the stars as a function of their mass. These predictions can be verified by observations on binary pulsars. Calculations predict that some of the neutrons in a neutron star will pair and become a superfluid, that is they can flow without viscosity. We have calculated the pairing energy as a function of density to predict this behavior.  We have explored the modifications needed to the interactions of the protons and neutrons to account for the observed three-body forces.  The project has completed the training of one Ph.D. nuclear theorist, and begun the training of two more, one nearing completion. It has contributed to the education of three other students -- two graduate students and one undergraduate.   The supefluid calculations done here have broader impact in other areas of physics where superfluidity occurs. This includes atomic, materials physics, and possible applications to quantum computing.  These methods allow us to calculate the properties of nuclei and nuclear matter in regimes where laboratory measurements are either costly, difficult, or impossible. In addition, we can perform calculations where measurements can be made to verify the accuracy of our methods.             Last Modified: 05/06/2013       Submitted by: Kevin E Schmidt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
