<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research in Ring Theory and Noncommutative Algebraic Geometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>169502</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tluo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928448</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proposal Title:  Research in Ring Theory and Noncommutative Algebraic&lt;br/&gt;Geometry&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator:  K. R. Goodearl&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Principal Investigator proposes to continue his investigations&lt;br/&gt;into the structure of various classes of noncommutative rings,&lt;br/&gt;particularly quantum coordinate rings (quantized algebras of&lt;br/&gt;functions) and related algebras, with a focus on geometric aspects of&lt;br/&gt;noncommutative rings and ring-theoretic aspects of noncommutative&lt;br/&gt;algebraic geometry. The proposed projects, located within&lt;br/&gt;noncommutative algebra, will build up the infrastructure of and&lt;br/&gt;interconnections among active parts of several related areas -- ring&lt;br/&gt;theory, noncommutative algebraic geometry, and quantum groups. Roughly&lt;br/&gt;speaking, the long-term goals framing many of these projects stem from&lt;br/&gt;noncommutative algebraic geometry, and the basic examples come from&lt;br/&gt;quantum groups, while many lines of approach are recruited from ring&lt;br/&gt;theory. The main focus will be on algebraic and geometric features of&lt;br/&gt;the prime and primitive spectra of quantized coordinate rings. The&lt;br/&gt;goals include classification of prime ideals, finiteness conditions&lt;br/&gt;for prime ideals invariant under tori of automorphisms, verification of&lt;br/&gt;supporting properties such as Auslander-regularity and&lt;br/&gt;Cohen-Macaulayness, and presentations of quantized prime or primitive&lt;br/&gt;spectra as topological quotients of classical spectra or varieties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A pervasive theme in the mathematical study of geometric objects is&lt;br/&gt;that the properties of these objects are completely encoded in the&lt;br/&gt;functions on them, and are often more accessible via these functions&lt;br/&gt;than directly. Within algebraic geometry -- the study of geometric&lt;br/&gt;spaces defined by polynomial equations -- it is the polynomial&lt;br/&gt;functions on a space that determine it. These functions form a ring (a&lt;br/&gt;system endowed with compatible addition and multiplication operations)&lt;br/&gt;which is, moreover, commutative (fg = gf always). In the 1980s,&lt;br/&gt;researchers in the former Soviet Union, in the process of solving&lt;br/&gt;certain problems in theoretical quantum physics, discovered rings&lt;br/&gt;which appear to enjoy all the structure of rings of functions on&lt;br/&gt;geometric spaces, except that the multiplication is noncommutative. In&lt;br/&gt;honor of their origins in quantum theory, these rings are now called&lt;br/&gt;"quantized coordinate rings." It proved very useful to treat them as&lt;br/&gt;if they were rings of functions (except for the noncommutativity), and&lt;br/&gt;the guiding principle in their study became the search for&lt;br/&gt;"noncommutative versions of the geometry." Sufficiently many common&lt;br/&gt;phenomena (both geometric and algebraic) have been discovered in a wide&lt;br/&gt;range of quantized coordinate rings to lead one to conjecture that&lt;br/&gt;general, axiomatizable underpinnings within this class of rings are&lt;br/&gt;responsible for the parallels in their behavior. The main long-term&lt;br/&gt;thrust of the PI's research is to uncover such general structures and&lt;br/&gt;decode their geometric content. In the medium term, the proposal aims&lt;br/&gt;to extend the range of known shared phenomena within this class of&lt;br/&gt;rings, in order to gain better insight into their common base.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0401558</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Goodearl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth R Goodearl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>goodearl@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058933496</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116131</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<CountyName>SANTA BARBARA</CountyName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<CountyName>SANTA BARBARA</CountyName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Research]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~169502</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
