<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NER:     An AFM-based Technique for Nanoscale Flow Mapping</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Wendell Schultz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;PROPOSAL NO.:   CTS-0404167&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR:  THEODORIAN BORCA-TASCIUC&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION:    RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INST.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NER: AN AFM-BASED TECHNIQUE FOR NANOSCALE FLOW MAPPING &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal was received in response to Nanoscale Science and Engineering initiative, NSF 03-043, category NER.  Understanding the dynamics and the structure of flows in and around nanostructures and liquid-solid interfaces is critical for the advancement of future generations of fluidic based biological and chemical sensors.  Currently available flow field characterization methods such as Laser Doppler Velocimetry (LDV) and Particle Image Velocimetry (PIV) rely on optical sensing and are limited in resolution by the wavelength of light.  A novel experimental technique based on Magnetic Force Microscopy (MFM) detection of ferromagnetic or paramagnetic nano-particles seeding the flow will be developed under this grant.  The technique will then be utilized for measurements of the flow field in electroosmotic microchannel flows and in the vicinity of a DNA molecule in the flow. These experiments will set the stage to conduct studies of flows relevant to bio-fluidic and bio-sensing applications such as flows containing DNA molecules. The challenges of this project will be met by a team with expertise in both experimental measurements and theoretical modeling and computation.  The proposed research, if successful, will lead to an understanding of key aspects of fluid flow at the nanoscale, and will pave the way for designing better microfluidic and nanofluidic systems for chemical and biological sensing and nanomanufacturing.  Moreover, by facilitating the study of flows in the vicinity of DNA and other bio-molecules and individual cells this technique will open new horizons for understanding physiological processes in biological systems. This will have a tremendous impact on biotechnology.  The proposed research activity is integrated with a comprehensive educational and outreach program. The results will be made available through a novel haptic device interface and on-line accessible experiments and demonstrations of nanoscale fluid flow phenomena to be developed by undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0404167</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theodorian</FirstName>
<LastName>Borca-Tasciuc</LastName>
<EmailAddress>borcat@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/17/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suvranu</FirstName>
<LastName>De</LastName>
<EmailAddress>des@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/17/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1676</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE:  EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
