<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Efficient Estimation in Semiparametric Models</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>93388.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>93388</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Grace Yang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Principle Investigator proposes to continue his research program &lt;br/&gt;on efficient estimation in semiparametric models with an emphasis &lt;br/&gt;on non- and semiparametric regression models, on bivariate models with &lt;br/&gt;partial knowledge about the marginals, and on time series models.&lt;br/&gt;Special attention will be paid to the possibility of &lt;br/&gt;(efficient) root-n consistent estimation &lt;br/&gt;of curves such as stationary densities and conditional expectations in &lt;br/&gt;time series models with independent innovations.  &lt;br/&gt;Work on regression models will focus on diagnostics and &lt;br/&gt;on imputing when responses are missing at random.&lt;br/&gt;In connection with the latter fully imputed estimators will be studied.&lt;br/&gt;Such estimators impute not only the missing but also the observed responses.&lt;br/&gt;Current work by the Principal Investigator suggests that the &lt;br/&gt;fully imputed estimator is typically better than the partly imputed estimator, &lt;br/&gt;which only imputes the missing responses. &lt;br/&gt;One goal of the research is to prove this conjecture and &lt;br/&gt;to show that fully imputed estimators can even be made to be efficient. &lt;br/&gt;The work on bivariate models will deal with &lt;br/&gt;fine-tuning results for known and equal marginals obtained so far,&lt;br/&gt;and on extending such results to more general models &lt;br/&gt;including those in which the marginal distributions are &lt;br/&gt;linked through a parameter. &lt;br/&gt;Work on two monographs, one on efficient estimation in regression models&lt;br/&gt;and the other on efficient estimation in time series models, is also planned.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will advance the theory of efficient estimation in &lt;br/&gt;semiparametric models and will provide more efficient ways of analyzing &lt;br/&gt;data in many concrete problems.  Since semiparametric models are &lt;br/&gt;widespread in many fields that use statistics, the proposed research will &lt;br/&gt;have an impact on all these fields.  For example, results on time series &lt;br/&gt;and Markov chain models have applications in econometrics and mathematical &lt;br/&gt;finance; results on bivariate models have applications in actuarial sciences &lt;br/&gt;and in medical research; results on imputing are useful in medical studies.&lt;br/&gt;The planned monographs are intended to disseminate some of the research &lt;br/&gt;from the proposed research to a wider audience.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0405791</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anton</FirstName>
<LastName>Schick</LastName>
<EmailAddress>anton@math.binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/14/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
