<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Topics in Set-theoretic Topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>141556</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The principle investigator will explore open problems in several areas of&lt;br/&gt;set-theoretic topology.  Convergence properties have important&lt;br/&gt;implications in a number of fields, yet are not well-understood.  For&lt;br/&gt;example, it is not known if it is consistent that a space which is&lt;br/&gt;Frechet-Urysohn for finite sets must be first-countable.  Settling this&lt;br/&gt;question is likely to lead to a solution of Malychin's well-known problem&lt;br/&gt;whether it is consistent that separable Frechet-Urysohn topological groups&lt;br/&gt;must be metrizable.  Two other themes of this proposal involve function&lt;br/&gt;spaces with the compact-open topology.  Settling one of them would solve a&lt;br/&gt;40 year old problem of J. Ceder, and settling the other would yield a&lt;br/&gt;useful way of determining when these function spaces are Baire spaces.&lt;br/&gt;Another goal of this proposal is to apply Balogh's magnificent technique&lt;br/&gt;for constructing ZFC examples , which he used to settle several&lt;br/&gt;long-standing conjectures, to other problems, and in the process attempt&lt;br/&gt;to simplify and codify the technique to make it easier to use.  Finally,&lt;br/&gt;there have been a number of recent advances on the D-space property, a&lt;br/&gt;property with interesting but not well-understood relationships with&lt;br/&gt;covering properties, which indicate that the time may be ripe for settling&lt;br/&gt;the D-space questions of van Douwen that have stumped researchers for more&lt;br/&gt;than 20 years. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Set theory and general topology are fundamental mathematical disciplines,&lt;br/&gt;with common historical roots, and they serve as essential tools in many&lt;br/&gt;areas of mathematics.  General topology provides a framework for the study&lt;br/&gt;of shapes, from ordinary shapes in real three-dimensional space to much&lt;br/&gt;more abstract shapes and structures.   For example, continuous real-valued&lt;br/&gt;functions are a staple of mathematics, and hence the topological structure&lt;br/&gt;of spaces of continuous functions, which is one of the topics that this&lt;br/&gt;proposal centers on,  has important implications in many fields.    The&lt;br/&gt;same can be said about  the notion of sequential convergence and its&lt;br/&gt;variants, another topic of this proposal.   The principle investigator's&lt;br/&gt;proposed problems lie within the scope of what has been a fruitful&lt;br/&gt;interaction  between general topology and set theory, an interaction&lt;br/&gt;spurred by dramatic advances in set theory and logic in the last forty&lt;br/&gt;years or so and the realization that many long-standing questions in the&lt;br/&gt;general topology of abstract spaces rest on complicated set-theoretic&lt;br/&gt;combinatorics.  Solutions to the proposed problems would deepen our&lt;br/&gt;understanding of the  fundamental topological properties to be explored,&lt;br/&gt;and would likely require new set-theoretical and topological techniques&lt;br/&gt;applicable to a variety of other problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0405216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Gruenhage</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary F Gruenhage</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gruengf@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348446585</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000405913</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Auburn University</Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>368320001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>VPRED, Research &amp; Innovation Ctr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[540 Devall Drive, Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066470972</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AUBURN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066470972</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Auburn University]]></Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>368320001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[VPRED, Research &amp; Innovation]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~141556</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
