<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dirac Operator, Eta Invariant and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>129644</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>DMS-0405890&lt;br/&gt;Title: Dirac operator, eta invariant and applications&lt;br/&gt;PI: Xianzhe Dai (University of California, Santa Barbara)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this proposal the principal investigator studies various questions related &lt;br/&gt;to Dirac operator. This includes the use of Dirac operator in the study of &lt;br/&gt;stability of Riemannian manifolds and positive scalar curvature metrics and &lt;br/&gt;scalar flat metrics on Calabi-Yau manifolds and other special holonomy &lt;br/&gt;manifolds,the study of the significance of eta invariant in conformal geometry &lt;br/&gt;and locally symmetric spaces, the behavior of analytic torsion under conical &lt;br/&gt;degeneration and the use of conical singularity in the study of geometric &lt;br/&gt;quantization in the singular case.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dirac operator and related geometric invariants are playing more and more &lt;br/&gt;fundamental and important role in diverse fields of mathematics and physics.&lt;br/&gt;They reveal much about the structures of the underlying spaces. This proposal &lt;br/&gt;aims for better understanding of conformal structures and special metrics &lt;br/&gt;through the use of Dirac operator and explores the connection with the positive &lt;br/&gt;mass theorems in the general relativity. As is well known, Einstein's general &lt;br/&gt;relativity uses geometry to describe gravity, one of the four fundamental &lt;br/&gt;forces in nature, and the most important one in determining the large scale &lt;br/&gt;structure of our universe. The understanding of mass and momentum is thus of &lt;br/&gt;crucial importance in our ultimate understanding of the universe. Calabi-Yau &lt;br/&gt;spaces and other special holonomy spaces are now playing fundamental role in &lt;br/&gt;the string theory, generally considered the best candidate for the ``theory of &lt;br/&gt;everything''.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0405890</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xianzhe</FirstName>
<LastName>Dai</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dai@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/14/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
