<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Stochastic Automata Networks in Cell Biology -- Modeling, Computation and Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lloyd E. Douglas</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mathias has worked extensively  in numerical linear algebra and matrix analysis.  About a year ago he started  collaborative work with Gregory D. Smith, a theoretical cell biologist,  on modeling intra-cellular calcium ion channels.  The stochastic automaton network (SAN) model that they developled and used was able to recreate the observed excitability of the intra-cellular calcium ion concentration. The use of the SAN approach allowed modelling on a much larger scale than had previously ben done.  Mathias will spend an&lt;br/&gt;immersion year in mathematical biology learning the biological background required for the modeling of ion channels and other problems in mathematical biology.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical biology is a relatively new field.  It brings mathematical modeling methods to bear on a wide range of biological problems from the intra-cellular level, for example modeling the variation of the &lt;br/&gt;concentration of calcium over time within a cell,  to the whole organ level, for example,  modeling the action of the heart.  It is part of a general trend in science to investigate physical phenomena through mathematical models in addition to experiments.  A reliable  mathematical model can provide scientific insights more quickly, and is more effectively than a traditional scientific experiment.  Mathias will immerse himself in mathematical biology for one year, so that in the future he will be able to use his training in mathematics to make research contributions in mathematical biology--with obvious benefits to society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0407946</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Finifter</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dhfini@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/12/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roy</FirstName>
<LastName>Mathias</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mathias@for.mat.bham.ac.uk</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/12/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of William and Mary</Name>
<CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7572213966</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
