<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Axiomatic models of scheduling: fairness and incentive compatibility.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>121857</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel H. Newlon</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;This research project will apply microeconomics, in particular game theory, to the analysis of&lt;br/&gt;queuing and scheduling protocols.  Previous work on this problem has focused on the non&lt;br/&gt;cooperative behavior of participants - in particular the decision to join a queue&lt;br/&gt;or "balk"-, and the incentives to reveal one's waiting cost. It relies on cash&lt;br/&gt;transfers to align incentives with effciency.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is twofold. Firstly it focuses on&lt;br/&gt;fairness and cooperative stability, in particular the ideas of limited liability and&lt;br/&gt;the strategic tranfers of jobs. Secondly it develops a probabilistic model of&lt;br/&gt;scheduling,where cash transfers are ruled out and the server randomly orders&lt;br/&gt;the different jobs according to their processing times and release dates. It is&lt;br/&gt;contrasted with the more familiar quasi-linear model, where cash transfers are&lt;br/&gt;feasible and disutilities are linear in waiting time until job completion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On the fairness side a first concern is to limit a user's liability to wait, i.e.,&lt;br/&gt;to place as tight a cap as possible on his worst case delay, given his own characteristics&lt;br/&gt;and the number of potential other users. The PI will develop a probabilistic model and will analyze different scheduling methods to determine which method best achieves social goals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When the central processor cannot monitor easily the identity of the final consumers of&lt;br/&gt;the jobs it processes, customers can merge their jobs into a single job, use straw men&lt;br/&gt;to split a single job into several small jobs, or transfer parts of their jobs within&lt;br/&gt;a coalition. The scheduling methods for which these cooperative maneuvers&lt;br/&gt;are never profitable will be systematically investigated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Queuing and scheduling are central to&lt;br/&gt;the production of manufactured commodities, to the exploitation of congested&lt;br/&gt;commons such as road networks and the Internet, and much more. The models that will be developed and analyzed encompass all these examples, and other simple scheduling protocols&lt;br/&gt;with universal applicability. In the internet and many other congested&lt;br/&gt;networks, cash transfers are not feasible, and randomization is the only way to&lt;br/&gt;achieve fairness, typically by serving first a short job with a higher probability&lt;br/&gt;than a long job. The simple shortest job first protocol fails to protect short jobs&lt;br/&gt;from being "starved" by longer jobs. This research provides systematic solutions&lt;br/&gt;to this problem, to the related disruption of job transfers accross users,&lt;br/&gt;and to several other normative concerns.&lt;br/&gt;1</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0414543</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Herve</FirstName>
<LastName>Moulin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>moulin@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
