<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Political Budget Cycles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>168426</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy A. Lutz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>POLITICAL BUDGET CYCLES&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This purpose of this project is to study fluctuations in fiscal policy&lt;br/&gt;induced by the election cycle from both a theoretical and empirical&lt;br/&gt;perspective. Conventional wisdom is that incumbents use economic policy,&lt;br/&gt;especially fiscal policy, before elections to influence electoral&lt;br/&gt;outcomes, with electoral considerations often seen as a key factor in&lt;br/&gt;policymaking around elections. Among economists, however, opinion is&lt;br/&gt;divided. One view is that fiscal expansion is indeed used in election&lt;br/&gt;years in many countries to generate desired economic and hence electoral&lt;br/&gt;effects, the other is that fiscal manipulation is punished rather than&lt;br/&gt;rewarded at the polls.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent work of by the PI suggests that the nature of political budget&lt;br/&gt;cycles depends on the experience of the voters with the electoral&lt;br/&gt;system. What accounts for these differences between new and established&lt;br/&gt;democracies? Is deficit spending electorally rewarded in the first group&lt;br/&gt;but punished in the second? What are the characteristics of new&lt;br/&gt;democracies that may explain the strength of the budget cycle. &lt;br/&gt;Especially important here is the information voters have about fiscal&lt;br/&gt;magnitudes. Drazen proposes several ways to measure this, including fiscal&lt;br/&gt;transparency indices. The project will attempt to compare this&lt;br/&gt;explanation with others, such as the fluidity of voting patterns or the&lt;br/&gt;greater amount of rent-seeking that it is argued may characterize new&lt;br/&gt;democracies. The project also studies why experienced voters respond to&lt;br/&gt;election-year economics, focusing on the importance of the amount of&lt;br/&gt;information they have when they enter the voting booth.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0418482</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Drazen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drazen@econ.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1050 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
