<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:     Non-Destructive Hydrogen Embrittlement Detection for High Strength Steels Using Induced Positron Annihilation Technologies</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>94330</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph E. Hennessey</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a field use, nondestructive measurement capability for hydrogen embrittlement (HE) damage in high-strength alloys based on induced positron annihilation. The primary objective of this project will be to demonstrate this innovative technology for the detection, quantification, depth profiling, and assessment of damage progression for hydrogen embrittlement in high-strength alloys associated with critical aerospace components. Numerous aerospace components (e.g., landing gear) have been shown to be subject to early HE failure long before the expected end of life thereby impacting flight safety. Consequently, a physically-based detection tool will be developed that can be used to detect and measure HE in high-strength alloys at any point in the damage progression suitable for manufacturing and field measurement applications in numerous industries. Development of this portable HE detection tool will significantly improve manufacturing process-control/quality control for critical manufacturing processes of concern, while improving safety and radically changing requirements for component maintenance, surveillance and replacement criteria. This revolutionary advancement in HE detection capability will provide a competitive advantage for the aerospace and other industries by providing a fundamentally new approach for the detection of HE.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project will be continued work on Induced Positron Annihilation applications to hydrogen embrittlement damage. This work will provide information not only on current damage, but also on the remaining life of components. This technology will improve process control/quality control and safety, and will positively impact many aspects of the design, manufacturing, and use of components in numerous industries. This technology will result in safer and less expensive operations of potentially hydrogen embrittled machinery; providing long term benefits to manufacturers, maintainers, and operators of machinery subject to this type of damage. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0419214</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jagoda</FirstName>
<LastName>Urban-Klaehn</LastName>
<EmailAddress>klaehn@physics.isu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/10/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Positron Systems, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>BOISE</CityName>
<ZipCode>837027626</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2085144579</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>411 South 5th Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1984</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS SYNTHESIS &amp; PROCESSN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
