<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Ireland Dissertation Enhancement:   Quantum Cascade Laser Based Mid-Infrared Sensor Technology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0420005&lt;br/&gt;Mizaikoff&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this one-year U.S.-Ireland dissertation enhancement project between Georgia Institute of Technology and the National Centre of Sensor Research (NCSR) at Dublin City University, the investigators will collaborate on micro fabrication of integrated sensing devices.  Christy Charlton, a senior graduate student of Boris Mizaikoff, the principal investigator on related  NSF award (0216368), will work with the Director of NCSR, Brian MacCraith, on the development of miniaturized mid-infrared sensing platforms using planar waveguide technology and quantum cascade laser light sources.   This project is part of a strategic research alliance in chemical sensors and biosensors between Georgia Tech and NCSR Dublin that involves an exchange of faculty and students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed approach combines theoretical design aspects with device fabrication and experimental testing.  The project focuses on a new generation of highly sensitive molecule specific sensing devices providing a generic modular sensing platform for development of a wide variety of infrared sensing devices.  The use of spectroscopic sensor technology is at the forefront of current challenges for chemical, biological and biomimetic sensors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project integrates research and education at the international level and involves a unique interdisciplinary education environment for the U.S. student.  The complexity of the proposed problems demands a crosscutting approach in the fields of chemistry, materials sciences, micro fabrication, physics, theory and spectroscopy.  It takes advantage of multi-user facilities in Ireland and extensive Irish expertise in mid-infrared sensor technology based on optical fibers. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0420005</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Boris</FirstName>
<LastName>Mizaikoff</LastName>
<EmailAddress>boris.mizaikoff@chemistry.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/12/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1629</Code>
<Text>BE: NON-ANNOUNCEMENT RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1629</Code>
<Text>BE: Non-Announcement Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5914</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
