<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Development of an In-Situ Neutron-Scattering Facility for Research and Education in the Mechanical Behavior of Materials</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1999996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1999996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070006</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is award from the Major Research Instrumentation [MRI] Program to the University of Tennessee supports the  "Development of an In-Situ Neutron-Scattering Facility for Research and Education in the Mechanical Behavior of Materials". The project is based on partnership between  the University of Tennessee [UT], Oak Ridge National Laboratory [ORNL], and includes collaborators from 16 universities, 13 industries, and 6 national laboratories with diverse disciplines that include [1] Materials Science and Engineering; [2] Physics; [3] Chemistry; [4] Mechanical, Aerospace, and Biomedical Engineering; [5] Civil Engineering; [6] Nuclear Engineering; and [7] Biochemistry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;State-of-the-art in-situ and real-time characterization instrumentation for the VULCAN diffractometer at the impending Spallation Neutron Source [SNS] will be developed. The facility will provide the most intense pulsed-neutron source in the world and will open new scientific frontiers and establish the nation's leadership in the field of the neutron-scattering materials science and technology The instrumentation suite consists of [1] a high-capacity electrohydraulic-mechanical test system, [2] a high-temperature vacuum furnace, [3] a miniature-specimen electromechanical test system, and [4] an electrochemical-environmental cell. The characterization capabilities to be developed will far surpass anything else available in the world.  The simultaneous neutron diffraction and small-angle neutron scattering [SANS] during mechanical testing will have a tremendous impact on the fundamental understanding of the mechanical behavior of materials.  The instrumentation suite will be a major component of the neutron-scattering user facilities and, therefore, will be available to a broad user community.  The instruments can be used across different disciplines, which will foster the integrated research/education interactions among the various disciplines and facilitate the development of new interdisciplinary programs. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This is award from the Major Research Instrumentation [MRI] Program to the University of Tennessee supports the  "Development of an In-Situ Neutron-Scattering Facility for Research and Education in the Mechanical Behavior of Materials". The project is based on partnership between  the University of Tennessee [UT], Oak Ridge National Laboratory [ORNL], and includes collaborators from 16 universities, 13 industries, and 6 national laboratories with diverse disciplines that include [1] Materials Science and Engineering; [2] Physics; [3] Chemistry; [4] Mechanical, Aerospace, and Biomedical Engineering; [5] Civil Engineering; [6] Nuclear Engineering; and [7] Biochemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will develop a suite of instruments for in-situ neutron-diffraction studies of the mechanical behavior of advanced materials at the world's most powerful Spallation Neutron Source [SNS].  The underlying goal of the proposal is to "accomplish the national agenda of advancing neutron science and engineering in the US to the leadership position in the world" by developing and providing the state-of-the-art neutron instrumentation to the user community, which will be broadened by educating a diverse cadre of skilled users.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The instrumentation will be a major component in the national neutron-user facilities, and will be available to the entire research/education community.  Therefore, the development of the sample environment for the SNS facility will add a much needed new capability to the nation's research infrastructures.  These instruments will benefit society through the advances in the fundamental understanding of high-performance materials, leading to the enhanced reliability/performance of engineering components.  A new generation of scientists and engineers will be trained in the use of neutron technologies.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0421219</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
<LastName>Buchanan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rab1@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Liaw</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pliaw@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xun-Li</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wangxl@ornl.gov</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Camden</FirstName>
<LastName>Hubbard</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hubbardcr@ornl.gov</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hahn</FirstName>
<LastName>Choo</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hchoo@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1750</Code>
<Text>MPS DMR INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
