<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Acquisition of Instrumentation for Advanced Materials Characterization</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Perumalsamy N. Balaguru</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The requested MRI equipment will enable the continued growth and development of three SDSM&amp;T research groups; namely, the smart structures group, the composites group and the direct write technology group. Taken together, the SDSM&amp;T research initiatives mentioned above require a complementary suite of instruments capable of highly-accurate dimensioning and profiling of components, and the precise determination of material properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the current focus of SDSM&amp;T research efforts it is envisioned that the Nano-XP system would be utilized in the following research areas: 1) indentation testing of polymer matrix composites (particularly the near fiber region called the interphase), and 2) sensor/ circuitry durability. In addition, other possible areas would include characterization of nano and microstructure of friction stir processed material and characterization of nanofiber composites.&lt;br/&gt;Several evolving technologies offer exciting promise, while at the same time providing significant development challenges. Ultra-low weight design and miniaturization are two notable examples. In both of these cases, and many others, non-contact sensing and measurement are required. Optical methods are among the most powerful non-contact techniques. The proposed ARAMIS 3D high-resolution speckle interferometer featuring natural specular nature of the imaged surface will be used with gossamer structures and direct-write, multifunctional integrated sensors.&lt;br/&gt;Recent advances in materials processing methods, such as direct-write manufacturing, have opened up the possibility of multifunctional structural elements. Direct-write manufacturing enables load-carrying elements of a structure to be designed to serve the additional functions of sensing and actuation. A number of communications, medical, space, and defense applications with tight weight and size constraints are in need of reliable multifunctional structures. The requested dynamic MEMS optical profiler system is ideal at the scales of these applications.&lt;br/&gt;Significant opportunities exist for education and training with this suite of instruments. In this regard, the requested instruments would be utilized in over a dozen courses, totaling more than 400 students/year. In addition, SDSM&amp;T hosts one summer REU site and has a second REU site pending, both of which would utilize this equipment. Finally, Raid City hosts a burgeoning telecommunications industry, which would greatly benefit from the requested equipment through interaction with the laboratory of applied electromagnetics and communications (LAEC) and direct write laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0421058</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Kellar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jon.kellar@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/16/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher H.</FirstName>
<LastName>Jenkins</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cjenkins@me.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/16/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Umesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Korde</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ukorde1@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/16/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Cross</LastName>
<EmailAddress>william.cross@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/16/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6053941218</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 East Saint Joseph Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1039</Code>
<Text>RENEWAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
