<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Increasing Diversity in Computer Science and Mechanical Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this CSEMS project is to increase workforce diversity in computer science and mechanical engineering.  To achieve this goal, the program emphasizes participation by students from underrepresented groups, such as women and minority students, first-generation college students and students from economically challenged areas of Alabama.  The project is 1) recruiting qualified students at the high school level, 2) ensuring a proper support infrastructure exists to enhance success as students and later as working professionals, and 3) providing financial assistance for students who have demonstrated a commitment to their studies in these fields.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computer science and mechanical engineering are both challenging curricula.  A lack of diversity in those fields is attributed to a) fewer female and minority students choosing those majors, b) a lack of a supportive infrastructure, and c) a lack of willingness on the students' part to take the financial risks associated with pursuing these careers in light of the preceding two reasons.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address these issues, the project is using the following approach.  First, over a four-year time period, the project provides scholarships for 21 undergraduates and 3 graduate students.  The distribution of the scholarships is 3 each for sophomore, junior, senior, and first-year graduate students in the Department of Computer Science and 3 each for freshman, sophomore, junior, and senior students in the Department of Mechanical Engineering.  Providing the scholarships helps alleviate some of the financial risks for students in these fields.  The project has a formal structure for assessing and assisting involved students during their academic career, including regular meetings with faculty and student mentors, and involvement of higher-level undergraduate students in research programs for elective course credit.  Finally, the program is introducing the participating undergraduate students to the possibility of academic careers.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;Increasing the diversity of students participating in the fields of computer science and mechanical engineering will only come about through the deliberate efforts of educators in those fields.  This project builds on known research results regarding the recruitment, retention and matriculation of students who are members of underrepresented groups.  Incorporating formal assessment cycles as part of participants' academic careers not only provides for improved retention, but also provides further insight into the difficulties experienced by such students in those fields and allows for the development of new techniques to enhance student success. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;The experiences gained by the students participating in this program should provide a positive influence on their lives.  Beyond those direct beneficiaries, however, a positive impact is also anticipated on both departments involved, on the College of Engineering, and on the institution as a whole.  More than half of the faculty serving on this project are members of underrepresented groups who serve as role models for the students, who in turn serve as role models to students at lower academic levels.  Furthermore, upon graduation, increased diversity in the workforce in computer science and mechanical engineering impacts our society at large.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0422377</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beth</FirstName>
<LastName>Todd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beth A Todd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>btodd.eng@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053481623</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Vrbsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan V Vrbsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vrbsky@cs.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053487352</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304657</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Jones@cs.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053481618</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000345446</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/05/2005</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith A Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kwilliams@eng.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053485152</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000056099</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoyan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoyan Hong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hxy@cs.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053485152</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2>152 Rose Admin. / Box 870104</StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045632635</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>808245794</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama Tuscaloosa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 University Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~330000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
