<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Understanding the Science Connected to Technology (USCT)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>725192.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>725192</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen F. Zuga</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>"Understanding the Science Connected to Technology (USCT)" targets information technology (IT) experiences in a comprehensive training program and professional support system for students and teachers in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM).  Participants have opportunities to assume leadership roles as citizen volunteers within the context of science and technology in an international watershed basin. Training includes collection, analysis, interpretation and dissemination of scientific data. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACTS:  Building on a student volunteer monitoring program called River Watch, the USCT project enables student scientists to conduct surface water quality monitoring activities, analyze data and disseminate results to enhance local decision-making capacity.  The project incorporates state and national education standards and has the potential to reach 173 school jurisdictions and 270,000 students.  USCT will directly impact 81 teachers, 758 students and 18 citizen volunteers. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The USCT project provides direct scientist mentor linkages for each participating school.  This linkage provides a lasting process for life-long learning and an understanding of how IT and STEM subject matter is applied by resource professionals.  Broader impacts include accredited coursework for teachers and students, specialized training congruent with the "No Child Left Behind Act of 2001," and building partnerships with Native American schools. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT:  The USCT project is designed to refocus thinking from static content inside a textbook to a process of learning that includes IT and STEM content. The USCT engages students (the next generation of decision makers) in discovery of science and technology and expands education beyond current paradigms and political jurisdictions. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0423459</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerald</FirstName>
<LastName>VanAmburg</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>08/20/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Fritz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>charles.fritz@nodak.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tri College University, Center for Watershed Education</Name>
<CityName>Fargo</CityName>
<ZipCode>581020000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012319747</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1805 Research Park Drive 2</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
