<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Resources for Network Application Studies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39203</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, developing practical tools for more effective performance evaluation of networked applications and furthering work in adaptive streaming media repair, studies end-user performance perception in network applications through an integrated framework considering user, application, and network layers. The research considers diverse network applications, aiming at bridging the gap in understanding the increased diversity resulting from the rapid rise of these new applications. Often, precise information is lacking regarding how the network improvements benefit the network application. Thus, assessing the benefits of new network treatments becomes difficult, and so does designing the next generation networks that will effectively support QoS of emerging applications. An Application Performance Studies Laboratory will be developed addressing finely control network performance for a range of selected applications. As appropriate, each of the projects will share research resources in the new lab to measure performance for interactive applications, network games, and streaming media repair. Specifically, the infrastructure enables the following projects:&lt;br/&gt; Integrating measures of network performance with user perception,&lt;br/&gt; Quality of service for network games, and&lt;br/&gt; Perceived quality of adaptive streaming media repair.&lt;br/&gt;The methodology employed integrating network performance with end-user application performance allows targeting studies of new applications on emergent networks. The work should culminate in advancing tools measuring the impact of the network and application level treatments on the end-user performance. Novel mechanisms for adaptive streaming media repair are expected.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The research involves strong integration of research and education, enriching education with exciting possibilities in CS research. Undergraduate senior projects will be instrumental in realizing the preparation of network applications for effective studies. Additionally, a new related undergraduate major will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0423362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kinicki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rek@cs.wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wills</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cew@cs.wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Claypool</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>claypool@cs.wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
