<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Syntactic and Composite Foams Conference; Banff, Canada; August 1-5, 2004</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070010</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harsh Deep Chopra</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Division of Materials Research provides partial support to Engineering Conferences International (ECI), which is sponsoring an international conference on "Syntactic and Composite Foams" to be held August 1-5, 2004 in Banff, Canada. The objective of this conference is to provide a unique forum for discourse among scientists and engineers from varied backgrounds on the growing field of composite foams. These foams are typically used in applications that take advantage of their very high specific properties, pore structure, energy absorption characteristics, and flame retardant properties. The sessions are divided into five broad categories: reinforcement characterization, foam characterization, fabrication, modeling, and future directions. The scope of the conference includes the production and characterization of reinforcing and functional materials specifically used for these foams (i.e. hollow spheres, micro/nanoparticles, particles with specific electric, magnetic, dielectric properties, biological, etc.) as well as fabrication, characterization, modeling, and applications of the foams. A main goal of the conference is to obtain a survey of the current work in the field and to promote interaction among participants. Participants will try to reach a consensus with regard to future directions, taking into account the interdisciplinary nature of the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Composite foams have grown out of conventional blown polymer foams to now include the addition of particles, fibers and/or functional elements, resulting in complex microstructures that can be engineered to meet specific applications. Today, by incorporating into composites hollow and solid particles, nanoparticles, fibers, and specialized foaming agents, unique and tailored foam properties can be attained. Because of these innovations, the role of syntactic and composite foams has expanded into the aerospace, automotive, communications, biomedical, electronics, sporting, and transportation industries. The support from the NSF is for graduate students and young scientists to attend the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0426151</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Krishan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chawla</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kchawla@uab.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Polytechnic University of New York</Name>
      <CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
      <ZipCode>112013826</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7182603360</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>15 Metrotech Center</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
