<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER:  Experimental Investigation of Transport Phenomena in Buoyancy Driven Nanofluids</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>23072</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alfonso Ortega</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;A preliminary experimental investigation is proposed to study the transport phenomena in Buoyancy-Driven Nanofluid (BDNF) system. Nanofluids are a new class of heat transfer fluid engineered by suspending nanoparticles in the conventional heat transfer fluid. The presence of the nanoparticles changes the transport properties of the conventional fluid thereby increasing the effective thermal conductivity of nanofluid. Buoyancy-driven nanofluid systems have potential applications in the MEMS and electronics thermal management, as well as in engine cooling systems, superconducting magnets, and other cooling applications.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this study are to develop empirical correlations for predicting the heat transfer in enclosures that contain BDNF and to lay the foundations for a longer term research effort to understand the fundamentals of thermal transport in BDNF. The outcome of this preliminary investigation will serve as groundwork for parametric experimental studies on the influence of parameters such as volume fraction, thermophysical properties of the fluid and nanoparticles, aspect ratio, volumetric expansion coefficient, and velocity of the nanofluids on heat transfer enhancement of buoyancy-driven nanofluids. This information is of practical relevance in determining the thermal performance of buoyancy-driven nanofluids, and designing nanofluid heat transfer systems for cooling of electronics and other engineering systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0427235</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Nnanna</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nnanna_g@utpb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/23/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
