<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ENAM?04 Fourth International Conference on Exotic Nuclei and Atomic Masses</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010600</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ENAM04: Fourth International Conference on Exotic Nuclei&lt;br/&gt;                   and Atomic Masses&lt;br/&gt;                        ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ENAM is a triennial international conference series devoted to the&lt;br/&gt;physics of nuclei far from stability and radioactive ion beams (RIB).&lt;br/&gt;RIB science is extremely broad and diverse.  It spans the gamut from&lt;br/&gt;nuclear structure to astrophysics, tests of fundamental laws of nature,&lt;br/&gt;and myriad applications.  Nevertheless, it is characterized by several&lt;br/&gt;encompassing themes that reflect the major challenges facing modern&lt;br/&gt;science today, and it has deep links to many other fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientifing challenges discussed at ENAM will include the&lt;br/&gt;following compelling questions:&lt;br/&gt;* How are the heavy elements created and how do nuclear properties&lt;br/&gt;  influence the stars?&lt;br/&gt;* What is the structure of atomic nuclei and how do complex systems derive&lt;br/&gt;  their properties from their individual constituents?&lt;br/&gt;* How can complex many-body systems display such astonishing regularities&lt;br/&gt;  and which new symmetries characterize exotic nuclei?&lt;br/&gt;* What are the fundamental symmetries of nature?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Worldwide, the study of exotic nuclei is in rapid advance. With the&lt;br/&gt;large number of radioactive ion beam facilities that are operating,&lt;br/&gt;under construction, and proposed, ENAM is a unique forum to discuss the&lt;br/&gt;exciting developments in the field, including experimental discoveries,&lt;br/&gt;theoretical modeling, technological advances, and applications. The&lt;br/&gt;Fourth Conference will be at Callaway Gardens in Pine Mountain, Georgia&lt;br/&gt;USA.  The timing of the meeting is excellent.  The recent Nuclear&lt;br/&gt;Physics Long Range Plan has identified the Rare Isotope Accelerator as&lt;br/&gt;the highest priority for new construction in nuclear physics for the&lt;br/&gt;United States.  For the RIA community in the USA, and for the RIB&lt;br/&gt;community worldwide, ENAM is the single most important meeting.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0430814</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Witold</FirstName>
<LastName>Nazarewicz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>witek@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1233</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1285</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
