<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Annals of Research on Engineering Education (AREE)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>849421</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sheryl A. Sorby</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Academy of Engineering, in partnership with several engineering journals (including the Journal on Engineering Education, Computer Science Education, and the Journal of Research on Science Teaching) published by professional societies and commercial publishers, is hosting a web portal linking education research papers in engineering (including computer science) and related science (including mathematics) disciplines. This virtual Annals of Research on Engineering Education (AREE) is serving to present, in a unitary fashion: the most rigorous research on engineering education in a manner that builds upon rather than competes with existing outlets within engineering disciplines; a forum for researchers on engineering education to discuss applicable standards for the evaluation of engineering education research; a reference site offering annotated bibliographies of the most recent research on engineering education research; a discussion forum through which engineering faculty and administrators with limited ability (or time) to perform research on engineering education can learn of research findings with immediate implications for improved classroom practice; a gateway to existing archives of relevant engineering education conference; and a gateway to relevant education research in non-engineering disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0434960</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
<LastName>Fortenberry</LastName>
<EmailAddress>N.Fortenberry@asee.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7444</Code>
<Text>NATIONAL SMETE DIGITAL LIBRARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
