<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International: Carnivoran Ecomorphology - Were There Any Creodont "Cats"?</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17490.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17490</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Pearl</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Carnivorous mammals serve an extremely important role as natural regulators of &lt;br/&gt;population growth in other mammals and in enhancing viability within these populations by removing old and unhealthy individuals.  This project will lead to a clearer understanding of the development of the wide variety of adaptive strategies adopted by carnivores to fulfill their roles within ecosystems.  Ecomorphological analysis offers a tool, unencumbered by taxonomic constraint, to look at carnivores (or other groups of animals) as a whole and as such should be of interest not only to those specifically interested in the evolutionary history of carnivores but to modern ecologists and natural resource managers as well.  This international research collaboration combines the strengths of researchers and research facilities in three countries (USA, Germany, Austria) and will enhance international cooperative efforts between the institutions involved as well as the researchers.  Both undergraduate and graduate students from the USA and the two European countries will be involved in all aspects of this research from the initial stages to the development of final reports.  Not only will these students learn how to organize and develop a research project, they will also learn of the benefits of cooperative efforts between researchers from a variety of institutions and backgrounds.  Paleontology, like most other endeavors, is greatly enhanced by a global perspective.  This project will promote such a perspective for all researchers and students involved.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Sedimentary Geology and Paleobiology Program participated in funding this international research project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0436295</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregg</FirstName>
<LastName>Gunnell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gregg.gunnell@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5955</Code>
<Text>AUSTRIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
