<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER: Assessing MNeSV as a Viral Vector for Gene Silencing in Maize</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>228199</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dokamuro@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924508</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Genome sequence data is accumulating rapidly for maize and other cereals, and we need tools that will let us evaluate the functions of maize genes rapidly and inexpensively.  'Gene silencing' (or RNA interference) uses the cell's machinery to destroy specific messenger RNAs before their encoded proteins can be made, effectively turning off a gene's expression without having to make mutations or generate transgenic plants.  Researchers studying broadleaf plants have developed virus-based vectors that take advantage of virus-induced gene silencing (VIGS), in which RNA viruses trigger the plant's gene silencing mechanism to study gene function in Arabidopsis and tobacco.  &lt;br/&gt;Our objective is to develop a virus-based gene silencing vector for maize and other cereals using Maize necrotic streak virus (MNeSV), a newly described tombusvirus that has a relatively easy-to-manipulate, small single-part RNA genome.  We think MNeSV is a good candidate, because successful gene silencing vectors were developed for a related virus (Tomato bushy stunt virus) that infects broadleaf plants.  MNeSV-based vectors will be easy and cost efficient to use, and lack insect transmissibility.  However, the project is risky, because we do not currently have the information on the function of MNeSV genes that is required to develop a stable vector for gene silencing, nor do we know the virus' complete host range.  Therefore, our specific objectives for this project include:  identifying MNeSV genes necessary for vector function using mutation analysis; determining whether we can infect wheat, barley, oats, sorghum, and rice with MNeSV using vascular puncture inoculation-a method we developed to inoculate germinating seeds with viruses and viral nucleic acids; and, to design and construct some preliminary virus vectors.  In addition, we will determine whether we can express MNeSV from plasmid cDNA by cloning the virus behind a plant promoter.  Although this is also high-risk, it would save researchers the time and expense of making the MNeSV RNA in the lab.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We are highly optimistic that this project will result in production of a basic VIGS vector, development of an infectious cDNA version of the MNeSV vector, and identification of additional cereals hosts of MNeSV.  If successful, MNeSV-based vectors could be used by researchers to investigate maize and cereal gene function using the large pool of genomic and EST sequences already available.  Thus, while high-risk, the proposed project has far-reaching impacts for the Plant Genome Program if it is successful.  Vector constructs will be available without restriction from OkSU and USDA to scientists for research purposes.  Information on the vectors will be made available via journal article(s) and through a link from a website [http://plantpath.osu.edu/faculty/redinbaugh.php].  &lt;br/&gt;We will employ undergraduates to assist with this research project, giving them hands-on research experience in molecular biology and plant virology.  We will work to recruit these students from under-represented groups including African Americans, Native Americans and women.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0440916</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kay</FirstName>
<LastName>Scheets</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kay M Scheets</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kay.scheets@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4057445559</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000362065</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Redinbaugh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret G Redinbaugh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>redinbaugh.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3302633965</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242361</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 WHITEHURST HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~28200</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
