<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Active Learning for Programming in Information Technology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The emerging field of Information Technology is one of several fields that require students to learn computer programming. However, traditional instructional techniques -- primarily lecture-based -- have not been effective for these and other students. This project provides, tests, and shares alternative instructional techniques that support students in these fields and enables them to continue past an instructional roadblock. Active learning materials are under development for classroom testing and a subsequent series of presentations and workshops for faculty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. The use of traditional teaching techniques in technical fields has not succeeded with many under-represented groups, such as females, returning adults, and less-abstract minded students. Although active learning techniques are based on sound pedagogical principles, they have been slow to diffuse into the culture of computer programming instruction. The materials that underlie this project have been pilot tested for two years, and have shown evidence of success in increasing student comprehension and satisfaction, which leads to higher course completion rates. Developing and testing these materials in a more rigorous way will create a validated, easy-to-use resource that can be distributed to faculty in other academic institutions, and will provide the empirical evidence that is necessary for others to adopt.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact. Science and technology loses many able and capable students because its culture is not always supportive of a variety of learning styles amongst its students. Computer programming is one of the most valuable skills in an information age, yet the traditional programming culture has been reluctant to shift its mindset. By developing and validating these materials, and providing associated workshops, presentations, and published materials this project is helping to change the culture of computer programming, and consequently increases the potential to attract and retain beginning students in this critical field of science and technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0442987</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Whittington</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kjw@it.rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/23/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7427</Code>
<Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
