<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Purchase of an X-Ray Diffractometer</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>205546.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>205546</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090002</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation and Facilities: Departmental Multi-User Instrumentation (CRIF:MU) Program, the Department of Chemistry at Colorado State University will acquire an X-ray diffractometer with CCD detector and low-temperature system. The research to be supported by this X-ray instrumentation covers a broad range of organic, inorganic, organometallic, and materials chemistry. The new X-ray diffraction system will serve the structural needs of six major users and eight other users at Colorado State University and at least eight other academic researchers in the Colorado/Wyoming region. The instrumentation will impact the research of well over 100 undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows; support the hands-on instruction and training in diffraction-based structural chemistry provided by existing courses at Colorado State and regional institutions; and support the ability to provide demonstrations of X-ray diffraction methods to visitors, high school chemistry groups, and K-12 teachers (through Colorado State's Center for Science, Mathematics, and Technology Education).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The X-ray diffractometer allows accurate and precise measurements of the full three dimensional structure of a molecule, including bond distances and angles, and it provides accurate information about the spatial arrangement of the molecule relative to the neighboring molecules. Such structural studies have a large impact in a number of areas, especially in the synthesis of important organic and inorganic chemicals and in understanding chemical interactions with biomolecules.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0443577</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Dorhout</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dorhout@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/21/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oren</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>opa@lamar.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/21/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Rappe</LastName>
<EmailAddress>anthony.rappe@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/21/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
