<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2005 Liquid Crystals Gordon Conference, Colby-Sawyer College, New London, New Hampshire, June 19-24, 2005</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Nelson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Interest in liquid crystal research and education in recent years is strong internationally due to a broadly based recognition of the technological importance and scientific challenges involved in the discovery and study of new materials. There is a steady influx of scientists from other disciplines who see the opportunities for performing exciting research in this area. The2005 Liquid Crystals Gordon Conference will provide the venue for a major international meeting to be held June 19-24, 2005 at Colby-Sawyer College, New London, New Hampshire. The goal of the conference is to facilitate international collaborations and information exchange across a broad spectrum of researchers with interests in liquid crystal materials and applications. Areas to be discussed include new concepts for design and synthesis of novel functional liquid crystal materials, fundamental studies in structure, theory and modeling, and related areas of applications to displays, sensors and other devices. The NSF funds will be used primarily to support the participation of students, post-doctoral scholars, and early career faculty, as well as senior U.S. session chairs and invited speakers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The liquid crystal community has a significant impact on technological advances of high significance to society through the development of new materials for electronics and photonics, including the design and construction of novel display devices and sensor materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0443733</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lavrentovich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>olavrent@kent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
