<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Molecular Level Effects for Simple Electrode Reactions at Well Defined Polarizable Electrodes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>438400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090006</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Professor W. Ronald Fawcett of the University of California-Davis is performing experimental work to elucidate molecular effects in interfacial electrochemistry.  His project is developing new methods for the growth and isolation of micron-scale single crystal surfaces that are enabling the study of double layer effects on very fast electron transfer reactions whose kinetics may not be measured at electrodes of macroscale dimensions.  High frequency voltammetry techniques are being applied to investigate limitations to electron transfer related to interfacial structure and charge and reorganization of solvent.  Reactions involving complex ions in solution and underpotential deposition processes are emphasized.  In addition, quantum chemical calculations are being performed to evaluate the charge distribution within polyatomic reactants for improved assessment of the magnitude of double layer corrections.  Other areas under study include double layer structure in the presence of divalent ions and diffuse layer properties at self assembled monolayer modified electrodes.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advances being made by the Fawcett group are contributing new techniques to support investigations of heterogeneous electron transfer.  These reactions impact a broad range of processes, including corrosion, metal deposition, energy conversion and the operation of chemical sensors.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0451103</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>W. Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Fawcett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wrfawcett@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/18/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1972</Code>
<Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1972</Code>
<Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
