<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigating the Needs of Elementary School Teachers of Mathematics at Different Points During Sustained Professional Development</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2497257.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2595127</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This five-year Teacher Professional Continuum Research project seeks to map a trajectory for the evolution of elementary school mathematics teachers engaged in sustained professional development.  Bringing together expertise from the School of Education and the Department of Mathematics and Statistics, the project is housed at the Center for Research in Mathematics and Science Education (CRMSE) at San Diego State University.  The goal of the project is to identify and understand the evolution of elementary school mathematics teachers' changing perspectives and needs as they participate in professional development.  Drawing from a pool of more than 500 elementary school teachers, the sample includes 120 elementary school mathematics teachers engaged in sustained professional development for different lengths of time.  Four teacher cohorts of 30 teachers each are represented in the study as initial participants, advancing participants, teacher leaders and preservice.  Initial participants are in the beginning stage of sustained professional development.  Advancing participants have completed at least two years, and teacher leaders at least four years of sustained professional development.  The preservice cohort provides a critical anchor for the beginning teachers' evolutionary trajectory and insights into groups at later trajectory points.  Three diverse school districts in San Diego County participate in the study. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study investigates the central research question of what are the similarities and differences among elementary school teachers at three points during sustained professional development in terms of their knowledge, beliefs and practices.  Project participants have been involved in Cognitively Guided Instruction (CGI), an NSF-funded research and professional development effort focused on addressing children's mathematics thinking.   The study employs a cross-sectional design to investigate teacher change and growth on distinct points along the trajectory.  Mixed methods and triangulation of data will be utilized to analysis multiple measures of teacher growth (beliefs, knowledge and practices).  The research instrumentation will involve belief surveys, content assessments, observation protocols for professional development and classroom instruction and noticing instruments to assess teacher interpretation of classroom interactions.  Eight case studies provide in-depth analyses of teachers' knowledge, beliefs and practices at four distinct points of the teacher professional continuum within the context of sustained professional development:  prospective teachers, initial participants, advancing participants and teacher leaders.  Additionally, a longitudinal analysis of eight cases provides important information about the changing needs of teachers as they evolve from initial participants to advancing participants.  &lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;Secondary to the central research question is a formative assessment on the relevance and application of the research findings to the field, specifically the community of professional development providers.  The formative assessment will examine the usefulness of  research findings to disparate models of professional development for both prospective and practicing teachers.  Professional development facilitators and providers will participate as co-researchers in the formative assessment component and will participate in dissemination of the research findings.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0455785</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randolph</FirstName>
<LastName>Philipp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Randolph A Philipp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rphilipp@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6195944453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444595</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/14/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victoria</FirstName>
<LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victoria Jacobs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vrjacobs@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3363344667</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000272934</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/14/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073371346</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921151338</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5300 Campanile Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7271</Code>
<Text>TEACHER PROFESSIONAL CONTINUUM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>DISCOVERY RESEARCH K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0405</Code>
<Name>NSF, EDUCATION &amp; HUMAN RESOURC</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0407</Code>
<Name>NSF,Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~999186</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~498304</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~499930</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~499837</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~97870</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>A Study of Teachers Engaged in Sustained Professional Development<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></strong></p> <div><br />  <hr size="1" /> </div> <p>Providing mathematics instruction that supports children's development of complex reasoning is challenging; most teachers have not had access to the support needed to provide this ambitious instruction.&nbsp; Consequently, we face a major educational challenge in the United States because our educational system lacks built-in means for teachers to gain this expertise.&nbsp; In particular, teachers seldom have access to professional development that is sustained over many years and focused in meaningful ways on their practice.&nbsp; The motivation for this study was to investigate what teachers might gain by having access to sustained, focused, professional development, and thereby, help us understand the cost to our educational system by <em>not</em> making such sustained professional development accessible to teachers.&nbsp; In our study of 129 teachers, &ldquo;Studying Teachers&rsquo; Evolving Perspectives&rdquo; (STEP), we studied what K&ndash;3 teachers learned as a result of engaging in sustained professional development focused on children&rsquo;s mathematical thinking&mdash;a focus with a long history of success.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Three groups of experienced K&ndash;3 teachers with 0&ndash;4 or more years of sustained professional development and a group of preservice teachers participated. In the professional development, children&rsquo;s ways of thinking about rich mathematical content was the starting point for discussing issues related to teaching and learning mathematics.&nbsp; We studied the teachers&rsquo; (a) mathematical content knowledge; (b) beliefs about mathematics, teaching, and learning; (c) professional noticing of children&rsquo;s mathematical thinking; and (d) responsiveness to individual children&rsquo;s thinking.&nbsp; Expertise in these four areas is necessary for achieving the vision of ambitious teaching; we selected them to capture differences among participant groups and to inform researchers and professional developers in assessing and supporting teachers&rsquo; development.</p> <p><strong>Content </strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Teachers hold specialized knowledge not possessed by the general public. We assessed teachers&rsquo; specialized mathematical content knowledge through eight open-ended items that address foundational mathematical ideas for primary-grades students in contexts that arise naturally in the work of teachers.&nbsp; A major finding in our study is that focusing on children&rsquo;s mathematical thinking is a productive context for learning mathematical content knowledge.</p> <p><strong>Beliefs</strong></p> <p><strong> </strong>&nbsp;Evidence is substantial that the beliefs teachers hold about mathematics, teaching, and learning affect their teaching. However, measuring beliefs is complicated because beliefs must be inferred. We drew inferences about beliefs from teachers&rsquo; interpretations of rich contexts.&nbsp; Increasing experience with children&rsquo;s thinking across participant groups was related to increasing sophistication of beliefs about mathematics, learning, and teaching linked to ambitious teaching.&nbsp; More growth in beliefs occurred within 2 years of professional development than beyond 2 years.</p> <p><strong>Professional Noticing of Children&rsquo;s Mathematical Thinking</strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em></strong>Teachers cannot respond to every classroom event and must make choices. Before responding they must <em>notice </em>the event.&nbsp; We focused on <em>professional noticing of children&rsquo;s mathematical thinking,</em> a set of three...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A Study of Teachers Engaged in Sustained Professional Development[1]       Providing mathematics instruction that supports children's development of complex reasoning is challenging; most teachers have not had access to the support needed to provide this ambitious instruction.  Consequently, we face a major educational challenge in the United States because our educational system lacks built-in means for teachers to gain this expertise.  In particular, teachers seldom have access to professional development that is sustained over many years and focused in meaningful ways on their practice.  The motivation for this study was to investigate what teachers might gain by having access to sustained, focused, professional development, and thereby, help us understand the cost to our educational system by not making such sustained professional development accessible to teachers.  In our study of 129 teachers, "Studying TeachersÆ Evolving Perspectives" (STEP), we studied what K&ndash;3 teachers learned as a result of engaging in sustained professional development focused on childrenÆs mathematical thinking&mdash;a focus with a long history of success.              Three groups of experienced K&ndash;3 teachers with 0&ndash;4 or more years of sustained professional development and a group of preservice teachers participated. In the professional development, childrenÆs ways of thinking about rich mathematical content was the starting point for discussing issues related to teaching and learning mathematics.  We studied the teachersÆ (a) mathematical content knowledge; (b) beliefs about mathematics, teaching, and learning; (c) professional noticing of childrenÆs mathematical thinking; and (d) responsiveness to individual childrenÆs thinking.  Expertise in these four areas is necessary for achieving the vision of ambitious teaching; we selected them to capture differences among participant groups and to inform researchers and professional developers in assessing and supporting teachersÆ development.  Content                  Teachers hold specialized knowledge not possessed by the general public. We assessed teachersÆ specialized mathematical content knowledge through eight open-ended items that address foundational mathematical ideas for primary-grades students in contexts that arise naturally in the work of teachers.  A major finding in our study is that focusing on childrenÆs mathematical thinking is a productive context for learning mathematical content knowledge.  Beliefs    Evidence is substantial that the beliefs teachers hold about mathematics, teaching, and learning affect their teaching. However, measuring beliefs is complicated because beliefs must be inferred. We drew inferences about beliefs from teachersÆ interpretations of rich contexts.  Increasing experience with childrenÆs thinking across participant groups was related to increasing sophistication of beliefs about mathematics, learning, and teaching linked to ambitious teaching.  More growth in beliefs occurred within 2 years of professional development than beyond 2 years.  Professional Noticing of ChildrenÆs Mathematical Thinking              Teachers cannot respond to every classroom event and must make choices. Before responding they must notice the event.  We focused on professional noticing of childrenÆs mathematical thinking, a set of three interrelated skills: (a) attending to childrenÆs strategies, (b) interpreting childrenÆs understandings, and (c) deciding how to respond on the basis of childrenÆs understandings.  Participants responded in writing to video or student work from K&ndash;3 classrooms.  We found that not everyone possesses expertise in professional noticing of childrenÆs mathematical thinking, but it can be learned.  Specifically, increasing experience with childrenÆs thinking across participant groups was related to increasing expertise on the professional-noticing tasks. The first 2 years of professional development seemed to provide support for d...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
