<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Prospects in Theoretical Physics at the Institute for Advanced Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"Funding request to help fund the PiTP Summer School ?Introduction to LHC Physics? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Prospects in Theoretical Physics (PiTP) is an intensive two-week summer program designed for graduate students considering a career in theoretical physics. First held by the School of Natural Sciences at the Institute for Advanced Study in the summer of 2002, the PiTP program is designed to provide lecture courses and informal sessions on the latest advances and open questions in various areas of theoretical physics. One of the goals of the program is to help the physics community train the next generation of scholars in theoretical physics. A special effort is made to reach out to women and minorities, as well as to graduate students in small universities who typically do not have the same opportunities and access to leaders in the field as graduate students in large research institutions. PiTP 2005 will be an introduction to LHC physics, intended for graduate students. The course is specifically designed to introduce Collider phenomenology to theorists - including string theorists - who are not specialists in this subject. The goal is to help young physicists prepare for the physics that will emerge from the LHC.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0457415</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seiberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>seiberg@physics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chiara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nappi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cnappi@Princeton.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Institute For Advanced Study</Name>
      <CityName>PRINCETON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085404907</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6097348000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>EINSTEIN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
