<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation Award: The Characterization of IL-6 on Cystic Fibrosis Airway Epithelial Cells Membrane Integrity and Bacterial Clearance</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299926.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299926</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Emanuel WAddell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ewaddell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924644</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Research Initiation Awards provide support for junior and mid-career faculty at Historically Black Colleges and Universities who are building new research programs or redirecting and rebuilding existing research programs. It is expected that the award helps to further the faculty member's research capability and effectiveness, improve research and teaching at the home institution, and involves undergraduate students in research experiences. The award to Bowie State University has potential to broaden impacts in several areas. The proposed work will allow the researchers who understand epithelial cell function and better comprehend bacterial viability and membrane cohesion. undergraduate students will receive training in cell biology, biochemistry, immunology and microbiology. This undergraduate research opportunity will allow students to develop marketable skills which will diversify the global scientific workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this study is to identify the role of IL-6 in Cystic Fibrosis (CF) airway epithelial cells’ ability to maintain membrane integrity and effective bacterial clearance following B. cenocepacia infection. The specific aims of this project are to:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(1) characterize the role of IL-6 on membrane integrity of B. cenocepacia infected CF airway epithelial cells; and &lt;br/&gt;(2) investigate the role of IL-6 on bacterial viability and growth of B. cenocepacia within CF airway epithelial cells. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Methodologies proposed include utilization of bacterial infection models on polarized epithelial cells, transepithelial electronic resistance techniques, epithelial transmigration assays, fluorescence microscopy, and IL-6R pharmacological inhibitors. Outcomes of this study will shed light onto the first line of defense within IL-6 rich environments, especially regarding epithelial cell biology. The effect of IL-6 on maintaining uncompromised barriers is a key finding that will transform our breadth of knowledge within cell biology, immunology, and microbiology, making it interdisciplinary in its contributions to science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000160</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Devyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Gillette</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Devyn D Gillette</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dgillette@bowiestate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3018604542</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000779753</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bowie State University</Name>
<CityName>BOWIE</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>207159465</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3018604399</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>14000 Jericho Park Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>616163721</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOWIE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bowie State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bowie</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207159465</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140000 Jerico Park Blvd, CNMNS 3]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9264</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH INITIATION AWARD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299926</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
