<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Seismic Investigation of the Puerto Rico Subduction Zone: Structure, Seismic Hazard, and Hydration of Slow-spreading Lithosphere</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350493.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>241226</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ktjohnso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927442</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Seismic investigation of the Puerto Rico subduction zone&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Puerto Rico Trench (PRT) poses major earthquake and tsunami hazards. Tsunamis generated at this subduction zone may also impact the U.S. East Coast. This project supports land and sea seismic experiments across the PRT and Puerto Rico. The experiments will define the detailed seismic structure of the PRT, advance our understanding of the PRT, and improve hazard assessment. The project consists of: (1) Three wide-angle seismic reflection/refraction profiles using ocean bottom seismometers (OBS); (2) Four multichannel seismic (MCS) reflection profiles, two parallel to and inland from the trench, and two parallel to the central OBS profile. (3) An array of more than 100 short-period land seismometers deployed across the Puerto Rico island, together with a dozen broad-band seismometers to record earthquakes for 18 months. The project will provide support for training several graduate students and an early career scientist, as well as research opportunities for faculty and students at a minority serving institution. The project will also support training of science journalists and public lectures to reach Puerto Rico residents.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports an active-source seismic experiment across the Puerto Rico Trench (PRT), its outer rise, and across the island arc, together with a land passive-source experiment. The PRT is a highly oblique subduction zone, where old Atlantic plate subducts under the Caribbean plate at a slow rate. The PRT is associated with anomalous and unexplained characteristics, such as the widest trench (below 6,000 m), the lowest gravity anomaly on Earth, and anomalous subsidence of the north coast of Puerto Rico. This project will acquire, analyze, and interpret multiple types of data: Three wide-angle seismic reflection/refraction profiles across the PRT with OBSs and an additional line south of the Puerto Rico island; four MCS reflection profiles, two each parallel and perpendicular to the PRT axis; an array of active- and passive-source land seismic stations on the Puerto Rico island; and multibeam bathymetry, 3.5 kHz sub-bottom profiler, gravity, and magnetics. The experiments are designed to address three key questions: (1) What is the shallow geometry of the subducting slab and its lateral continuity along the 500-km section of the trench? (2) What are the degree and spatial extent of hydration of the Atlantic lithosphere entering the Puerto Rico Trench? (3) Does oceanic bivergent thrust system represent double-sided subduction or a crustal retro-wedge of one-sided subduction? Results of the integrated seismic experiments are expected to significantly advance our understanding of the above scientific questions and assessment of the PRT seismic and tsunami hazard.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001776</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shuoshuo</FirstName>
<LastName>Han</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shuoshuo Han</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>han@ig.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124716156</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000728660</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas Institute for Geophysics]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787584445</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10100 Burnet Rd., ROC/Bldg. 196]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~116400</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~124826</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
