<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2020 IEEE International Symposium on Hardware Oriented Security and Trust (HOST): San Jose, CA - May 2020</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeremy Epstein</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jepstein@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928338</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Trusted hardware is the foundation of cybersecurity. The International Symposium on Hardware-Oriented Security and Trust (HOST) is a leading forum for hardware security researchers. This travel grant enables student researchers to attend the symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this proposed activity includes professional development for undergraduate and graduate students as well as continued growth of the symposium. HOST 2020 will be held in San Jose, CA on May 4-7, 2020. This project provides opportunities for 60 students to receive travel support to attend HOST 2020. Their attendance enables them to learn about the latest tools, design methods, architectures, circuits, and novel applications of secure hardware. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical contributions from previous symposia have covered topics such as: (1) counterfeit detection and avoidance, (2) side channel analysis and fault analysis, (3) hardware architectures for cryptography, and (4) physically unclonable functions (PUFs). The travel grants encourage more students to consider a technical submission, participation in growing hardware demonstration space to a large diverse audience, or even to attend as a means to prepare for a technical submission in future years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002804</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Domenic</FirstName>
<LastName>Forte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Domenic Forte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dforte@ece.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523921525</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000663973</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Designated as the "root-of-trust", hardware (i.e., integrated circuit chips, printed circuit boards, and firmware) is the most critical layer to cybersecurity. Unfortunately, countless recent stories highlight that security weaknesses in hardware are pervasive, can now be exploited remotely (through software), and are challenging to mitigate. To address these issues, security must be recognized as a fundamental element to be incorporated into the design, manufacturing, validation, maintenance, and upgrade of hardware for all types of systems. New processes that integrate security and trust into design flows and add hardware features to enable trusted execution are complex and require a concerted, multidisciplinary effort. To this end, the mission of the IEEE Symposium on Hardware Oriented Security and Trust (HOST) is (1) to be a leading and globally recognized forum that unites researchers, practitioners, and users from the computer security, microelectronics, and EDA communities; (2) to disseminate cutting-edge ideas, technologies, and results in areas of overlap between hardware and security; (3) to provide a platform for leaders in industry, government, and academia to share their unique perspectives and to help shape the direction and priorities of the community; and (4) to address shortages in the security workforce by recruiting and training students from a diverse group for productive careers with prospective employers.</p> <p>The primary goal of this project was to engage as many students as possible who would attend HOST for the first time and would not normally attend HOST (high school, undergrads, MS students, PhD student who do not have papers, etc.). A secondary goal was to provide opportunities to as many students from underrepresented groups as possible, such as women, minorities, and persons with disabilities. The hope is that this will get such students interested in pursuing a PhD in hardware security. A third goal was to put students in touch with as many industry employers as possible. Being one of the premier events in hardware security technology and research, these students who attend HOST will have a chance to talk with senior researchers from government, industry, and academia and to get exposed to the latest research in hardware security. Further, HOST offers many other activities to aid in student professional development, such as (1) Technical Talks, (2) Student Demos and Competition; (3) Student Posters and Competition; and (4) Tutorial Day. HOST provides best paper, demo, and poster awards to motivate and reward the top student researchers. In addition, HOST 2020 included two new activities to increase interaction between students and potential employers in industry: Exhibition and Industry Mentoring.</p> <p>The HOST organizing committee created an application system for students to provide their background information and express interest in attending HOST 2020. The call for applications was posted on the HOST website and social media. Further, the committee asked the call for applications to be e-mailed by leaders of national groups representing women and minorities to increase their participation. Over two deadlines (one in Spring 2020 and the other in Fall 2020), HOST received over 100 applications. The demographical information of the students who submitted applications and were offered travel support was as follows: Asian: 55.1%, Black or African American: 10.2%, Hispanic: 12.2%, White: 22.4%, Female: 21.4%, Male: 77.6%, and Non-binary (1%). Some students who were offered the grant unfortunately could not attend &ndash; this was primarily due to the pandemic that caused HOST 2020 to be postponed from May 2020 to December 2020 and to become a virtual event. Hence, some students had graduated, and others could not attend due to finals and other institutional obligations. Nevertheless, registration of over 70 students were supported by NSF to attend the tutorials, industry mentoring session, and main conference while 9 additional students were supported by industry.</p> <p>HOST was able to meet many of the goals that it had set forth. Aside from the above success in key demographics, other important outcomes were as follows. 79.6% of the student travel grant recipients were first time attendees of HOST. 62.2% of them did not have a paper or demo at HOST, and thus would not have attended without support. 86% of students shared CVs with industry sponsors and over 30 signed up for the industry-student mentorship event on the first day. 17 recipients competed in the poster competition on the last day. HOST 2020 was also the largest event in its history with 454 registrations and with the largest percentage of attendees from industry (50%) to engage with students. Using industry support, HOST also implemented a successful participation tracking system and offered over $5k in prizes to incentivize attendees to participate in the entire virtual event and reward those that attended Q&amp;A sessions, volunteered to judge student competitions, completed tutorial surveys, and attended exhibition.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Domenic&nbsp;Forte</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Designated as the "root-of-trust", hardware (i.e., integrated circuit chips, printed circuit boards, and firmware) is the most critical layer to cybersecurity. Unfortunately, countless recent stories highlight that security weaknesses in hardware are pervasive, can now be exploited remotely (through software), and are challenging to mitigate. To address these issues, security must be recognized as a fundamental element to be incorporated into the design, manufacturing, validation, maintenance, and upgrade of hardware for all types of systems. New processes that integrate security and trust into design flows and add hardware features to enable trusted execution are complex and require a concerted, multidisciplinary effort. To this end, the mission of the IEEE Symposium on Hardware Oriented Security and Trust (HOST) is (1) to be a leading and globally recognized forum that unites researchers, practitioners, and users from the computer security, microelectronics, and EDA communities; (2) to disseminate cutting-edge ideas, technologies, and results in areas of overlap between hardware and security; (3) to provide a platform for leaders in industry, government, and academia to share their unique perspectives and to help shape the direction and priorities of the community; and (4) to address shortages in the security workforce by recruiting and training students from a diverse group for productive careers with prospective employers.  The primary goal of this project was to engage as many students as possible who would attend HOST for the first time and would not normally attend HOST (high school, undergrads, MS students, PhD student who do not have papers, etc.). A secondary goal was to provide opportunities to as many students from underrepresented groups as possible, such as women, minorities, and persons with disabilities. The hope is that this will get such students interested in pursuing a PhD in hardware security. A third goal was to put students in touch with as many industry employers as possible. Being one of the premier events in hardware security technology and research, these students who attend HOST will have a chance to talk with senior researchers from government, industry, and academia and to get exposed to the latest research in hardware security. Further, HOST offers many other activities to aid in student professional development, such as (1) Technical Talks, (2) Student Demos and Competition; (3) Student Posters and Competition; and (4) Tutorial Day. HOST provides best paper, demo, and poster awards to motivate and reward the top student researchers. In addition, HOST 2020 included two new activities to increase interaction between students and potential employers in industry: Exhibition and Industry Mentoring.  The HOST organizing committee created an application system for students to provide their background information and express interest in attending HOST 2020. The call for applications was posted on the HOST website and social media. Further, the committee asked the call for applications to be e-mailed by leaders of national groups representing women and minorities to increase their participation. Over two deadlines (one in Spring 2020 and the other in Fall 2020), HOST received over 100 applications. The demographical information of the students who submitted applications and were offered travel support was as follows: Asian: 55.1%, Black or African American: 10.2%, Hispanic: 12.2%, White: 22.4%, Female: 21.4%, Male: 77.6%, and Non-binary (1%). Some students who were offered the grant unfortunately could not attend &ndash; this was primarily due to the pandemic that caused HOST 2020 to be postponed from May 2020 to December 2020 and to become a virtual event. Hence, some students had graduated, and others could not attend due to finals and other institutional obligations. Nevertheless, registration of over 70 students were supported by NSF to attend the tutorials, industry mentoring session, and main conference while 9 additional students were supported by industry.  HOST was able to meet many of the goals that it had set forth. Aside from the above success in key demographics, other important outcomes were as follows. 79.6% of the student travel grant recipients were first time attendees of HOST. 62.2% of them did not have a paper or demo at HOST, and thus would not have attended without support. 86% of students shared CVs with industry sponsors and over 30 signed up for the industry-student mentorship event on the first day. 17 recipients competed in the poster competition on the last day. HOST 2020 was also the largest event in its history with 454 registrations and with the largest percentage of attendees from industry (50%) to engage with students. Using industry support, HOST also implemented a successful participation tracking system and offered over $5k in prizes to incentivize attendees to participate in the entire virtual event and reward those that attended Q&amp;A sessions, volunteered to judge student competitions, completed tutorial surveys, and attended exhibition.       Last Modified: 04/01/2021       Submitted by: Domenic Forte]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
