<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020: Friend or foe: Neural regulation of dynamic social environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Marenda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmarenda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922157</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of life in innovative ways. Social behavior is complex, individuals must use external information from a continually changing environment in order to display appropriate behavioral responses. The external social information is then applied within the current social context. Behavioral responses are thus dependent on the situation. This response dependency must also be reflected by predictable patterns within the brain. This research aims to uncover how neural (nervous system) activity orchestrates behavior in a socially and environmentally sensitive way. This work will broaden our understanding of how fundamental social behaviors are coordinated within the brain, while also providing opportunities in research training for undergraduates and high school students of underrepresented minorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research utilizes the convict cichlid (Amatitlania nigrofasciata) as a study system to establish the rule of life that social behavior is facilitated by predictable interactions of brain areas within the Social Decision-Making Network, specifically those sensitive to social information and those encoding reward. The convict cichlid is ideally suited to address this hypothesis, as this species displays pair bonding and parental care, two behavioral suites which contain both aggressive and affiliative elements. Parents both provision and guard eggs, and mated pairs reinforce their bond through affiliative displays, while also guarding mates against conspecifics. How are both distinct and shared behavioral displays, occurring within and across behavioral suites, regulated within the brain? This research implements compartment analysis of temporal activity by fluorescent in situ hybridization (catFISH) to compare the neuronal response of temporally isolated social stimulus events across four comparisons, within and across behavioral suites: (1a.) parental care (brood provision vs. brood guarding) and 1b.) pair bonding (mate affiliation vs. mate guarding), and second, compares similar behavioral displays, which occur in distinct behavioral suites (similar behavioral displays). 1c.) Brood provisioning vs. mate affiliation (affiliative behavior), and (1d.) brood guarding vs. mate guarding (aggressive behavior). Finally, brain regions will be dissected out and behaviorally active neurons will be tagged and selectively retrieved using ribosomal capture (PhosphoTRAP), in order to uncover the genomic signatures of neurons active in response to each independent stimulus. Hence, through integrating neural circuitry and genomics, this work will further our understating of brain-behavior relationships. The impact of the project will be broadened by involving high school and undergraduate students from underrepresented groups in the research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010906</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ross</FirstName>
<LastName>DeAngelis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ross S DeAngelis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5129171311</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000761659</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>DeAngelis               Ross           S</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618203176</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121188</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8049</Code>
<Text>Biology Postdoctoral Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Goals of the project</strong></p> <p>My project aims to understand how distinct behavioral displays, which have shared motivation in their fitness outcomes are regulated in the brain. Conversely, how are behaviors similar in display, but with distinct motivational states regulated within the brain. For example, the defense of offspring and defense of a mate are both stereotypical forms of aggressive displays, yet one former has the fitness outcome of offspring survival, while the latter protects mating opportunities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Major Activities</strong></p> <p>Through careful observation and then meticulous quantification of 12 different behaviors in three different categories (aggressive, affiliative, and parental) I was able to show that each of these four conditions engenders distinct behavioral profiles after examining all behavioral displays (Image 1).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Major Activities Aim 1</strong></p> <p>After careful consideration of the best approach to aim 1, my sponsor and I have determined that immunofluorescent staining would be most appropriate in uncovering the spatial patterns of neural activity, reward signaling pathways, and signaling pathways of neurohormones important for social behavior. we have decided to label the brain for dopamine, oxytocin, vasopressin, while also co-labeling with the neural activity mark pS6. I had to validate these immunolabeling assays ensuring that each antibody used was made in a different animal to ensure no cross reactivity and that each antibody was specific to our intended antigen target. With the help of a talented undergraduate we were able to do this with all intended targets (see Image 2).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Major Activities Aim 2</strong></p> <p>To uncover the genomic response of behaviorally active neurons, in Aim 2 we have decided to conduct single-nuclei RNA (snRNA-seq) sequencing. To date, I am halfway through my goal of 6 individuals per each of the 4 behavioral paradigms. While I have not yet sequenced these tissues, I have been working closely on another project using snRNA-seq to gain experience and become proficient in the nuclei isolation as well as the analysis pipeline. We have been able to identify behaviorally relevant cellular clusters, expression of neural activity genes in the clusters, and are working to resolve the cellular identity of those cluster (Image 3).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>In my NSF PRFB I proposed to work with the Hyde Bronx Charter school in NYC to improve the scientific curriculum. Due the incredible impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and through conversation with school representative we have decided to delay that endeavor until further notice as we wait for normalcy to return. I therefore decided to become a part of the Inclusive Student Training in Collections and field-based Topics initiative (InSTInCT) to provide opportunities to undergraduates eager to participate in research. I consider myself extremely fortunate to be a part of this program, Marisa Ballard (an African American woman) has been the most capable and productive undergraduate I have worked with during my 10 years in scientific research. Marisa and I decided that the immunofluorescent labeling part of this project would be most suitable for her. Marisa took to the methodology quickly, and is now leading the effort in our immunolabeling techniques. She has also decided to continue working on the project through the next academic year and I expect great work from her both in the next year and in her future scientific development. So while my goal assisting the science department and providing opportunities to high school students at the Hyde Bronx school has been delayed, I have still made an impact by incorporating Marisa into a prominent role of this proposal.</p> <p><br /><strong>Training Goals</strong></p> <p>I have taken several steps to promote my leadership capabilities including taking on 3 distinguished undergraduates (one of an underrepresented minority) and worked closely with them each with their own part in the project. I have transferred my knowledge of fish care taking, BORIS behavioral scoring, and immunofluorescent labeling (one undergraduate on each topic). This has tested my ability to teach new skills to others while also incorporating their feedback in my leadership tactics and skills. We now conduct weekly project meetings to address current issues and figure out solutions to potential problems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Career Development</strong></p> <p>In my career development I have received invaluable training under the guidance of my sponsor, Dr. Hans Hofmann, as well as senior members of the lab and others. Thus far the abstract for this project has already been invited for two contributed talks, one which I presented to the neuroscience department retreat here at the University of Texas, and one as a selected abstract for the Society of Behavioral Endocrinology. As an integral part of the Hofmann lab I interact daily with talented, motivated, and intelligent people who challenge my leadership skills, my experimental approaches, and greatly contribute to my overall growth as I continue towards my goal of becoming and independent investigator.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Ross&nbsp;S&nbsp;Deangelis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069633593_IF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069633593_IF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Immunofluorescent labeling of IT and PS6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069633593_IF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Immunofluorescent labeling of IT and PS6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Validation of immunofluorescent labeling of nuclear marker DAPI (blue), isotocin (green), ribosomal protein S6 (red) and combined</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ross DeAngelis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ross&nbsp;S&nbsp;Deangelis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Immunofluorescent labeling of IT and PS6</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069502889_PCA--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069502889_PCA--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Different conditions generate distinct behavioral profiels"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069502889_PCA--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Different conditions generate distinct behavioral profiels"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">principal component analysis of preliminary behavioral trials show that each paradigm generates distinct behavioral profiles when examine the first two principle components</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ross DeAngelis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ross&nbsp;S&nbsp;Deangelis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Different conditions generate distinct behavioral profiels</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069711077_heatmap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069711077_heatmap--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Clustering of cell types"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2010906/2010906_10673817_1627069711077_heatmap--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Clustering of cell types"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Heatmap of cellular clustering based on the the top 10% most variable marker genes of known cell types</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ross DeAngelis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ross&nbsp;S&nbsp;Deangelis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Clustering of cell types</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Goals of the project  My project aims to understand how distinct behavioral displays, which have shared motivation in their fitness outcomes are regulated in the brain. Conversely, how are behaviors similar in display, but with distinct motivational states regulated within the brain. For example, the defense of offspring and defense of a mate are both stereotypical forms of aggressive displays, yet one former has the fitness outcome of offspring survival, while the latter protects mating opportunities.     Major Activities  Through careful observation and then meticulous quantification of 12 different behaviors in three different categories (aggressive, affiliative, and parental) I was able to show that each of these four conditions engenders distinct behavioral profiles after examining all behavioral displays (Image 1).     Major Activities Aim 1  After careful consideration of the best approach to aim 1, my sponsor and I have determined that immunofluorescent staining would be most appropriate in uncovering the spatial patterns of neural activity, reward signaling pathways, and signaling pathways of neurohormones important for social behavior. we have decided to label the brain for dopamine, oxytocin, vasopressin, while also co-labeling with the neural activity mark pS6. I had to validate these immunolabeling assays ensuring that each antibody used was made in a different animal to ensure no cross reactivity and that each antibody was specific to our intended antigen target. With the help of a talented undergraduate we were able to do this with all intended targets (see Image 2).     Major Activities Aim 2  To uncover the genomic response of behaviorally active neurons, in Aim 2 we have decided to conduct single-nuclei RNA (snRNA-seq) sequencing. To date, I am halfway through my goal of 6 individuals per each of the 4 behavioral paradigms. While I have not yet sequenced these tissues, I have been working closely on another project using snRNA-seq to gain experience and become proficient in the nuclei isolation as well as the analysis pipeline. We have been able to identify behaviorally relevant cellular clusters, expression of neural activity genes in the clusters, and are working to resolve the cellular identity of those cluster (Image 3).        Broader Impacts  In my NSF PRFB I proposed to work with the Hyde Bronx Charter school in NYC to improve the scientific curriculum. Due the incredible impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and through conversation with school representative we have decided to delay that endeavor until further notice as we wait for normalcy to return. I therefore decided to become a part of the Inclusive Student Training in Collections and field-based Topics initiative (InSTInCT) to provide opportunities to undergraduates eager to participate in research. I consider myself extremely fortunate to be a part of this program, Marisa Ballard (an African American woman) has been the most capable and productive undergraduate I have worked with during my 10 years in scientific research. Marisa and I decided that the immunofluorescent labeling part of this project would be most suitable for her. Marisa took to the methodology quickly, and is now leading the effort in our immunolabeling techniques. She has also decided to continue working on the project through the next academic year and I expect great work from her both in the next year and in her future scientific development. So while my goal assisting the science department and providing opportunities to high school students at the Hyde Bronx school has been delayed, I have still made an impact by incorporating Marisa into a prominent role of this proposal.   Training Goals  I have taken several steps to promote my leadership capabilities including taking on 3 distinguished undergraduates (one of an underrepresented minority) and worked closely with them each with their own part in the project. I have transferred my knowledge of fish care taking, BORIS behavioral scoring, and immunofluorescent labeling (one undergraduate on each topic). This has tested my ability to teach new skills to others while also incorporating their feedback in my leadership tactics and skills. We now conduct weekly project meetings to address current issues and figure out solutions to potential problems.     Career Development  In my career development I have received invaluable training under the guidance of my sponsor, Dr. Hans Hofmann, as well as senior members of the lab and others. Thus far the abstract for this project has already been invited for two contributed talks, one which I presented to the neuroscience department retreat here at the University of Texas, and one as a selected abstract for the Society of Behavioral Endocrinology. As an integral part of the Hofmann lab I interact daily with talented, motivated, and intelligent people who challenge my leadership skills, my experimental approaches, and greatly contribute to my overall growth as I continue towards my goal of becoming and independent investigator.             Last Modified: 07/23/2021       Submitted by: Ross S Deangelis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
