<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  ReefGen</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to regenerate coral reefs on the brink of extinction. Approximately one-quarter of the world’s coral reefs have disappeared and almost two-thirds are at risk today. The innovation introduces a scalable method to plant heat-resistant corals to rejuvenate dying reefs. The technology is a multi-arm dexterous robot crawler. Planting one nursery coral every 10 seconds, with a cluster of three robots, the technology is capable of planting 100x faster than any method currently in use. This intervention will have a direct and beneficial impact on environmental restoration, marine ecosystems, and the tourism industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will design a coral planting robot that traverses the ocean floor and performs complex tasks. Challenges include creating an autonomous wet chain and producing a wet chain sled, as well as addressing recharging difficulties.  Planting must take place where the coral is bound sufficiently so that it is not dislodged by waves or currents. Other technical challenges include identifying exposed hard surfaces as well as healthy coral to leave it undisturbed.  This project will enable reintroduction of key species with different environmental tolerance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014581</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Pompa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Pompa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jon@daringengineering.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8146826432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000838072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Josh</FirstName>
<LastName>Burgess</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Josh Burgess</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>josh@goodmachine.studio</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8317477350</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000818888</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/23/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>REEFGEN INC.</Name>
<CityName>SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<ZipCode>941101320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8317477350</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2180 FOLSOM ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>117334872</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REEFGEN INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Good Machine LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941101320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2180 Folsom street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-dc690968-7fff-f7d9-a3a1-1a2a0d25441f" style="line-height: 1.2; text-align: justify; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">ReefGen is planning to scale up coral restoration capacity worldwide to keep pace with the rate of coral mortality. This task is ambitious given that current estimates of coral loss rate and coral restoration rate differ by 6 orders of magnitude. The path chosen to achieve this needed correction is through increasing the rate of outplanting of nursery-raised corals using robotics and automation. The overarching phase 1 goal of the ReefGen project is to develop a proof of concept robotic system that can rapidly plant corals and be replicated at low cost. Such a system is needed to overcome the limits of manpower available to perform reef outplanting work.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; text-align: justify; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">This robot's end purpose will be to attach live corals onto damaged reefs. This allows rapid re-colonization and a possibility for the restored population of corals to reach self-sustaining reproduction faster than other methods. The reason for using this method is that corals matured in a nursery will have high survival rates and can be located in places where coral spawn is not naturally available due to a lack of reproductive adults in the area.</span></p> <h3 style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 14pt; margin-bottom: 10pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 13.999999999999998pt; font-family: Cambria,serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Overview of activities in phase 1</span></h3> <p style="line-height: 1.2; text-align: justify; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">ReefGen's Phase 1 work has allowed us to prove that our approach to planting corals is feasible and has great promise. We have built a robotic system that is capable of preparing a hard substrate for a coral planting and permanently attaching a coral. We have completed preliminary field trials with a simple system, proving the viability of each functional step of the planting system. Furthermore, our method has been positively received by the coral restoration community.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; text-align: justify; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The Phase 1 work of the project was successful in advancing the state of the art of coral planting technology and in developing relationships for commercialization and partnerships with other groups in the production chain of the industry.&nbsp;</span></p> <h2 id="docs-internal-guid-c031516a-7fff-ba48-ba4c-bb0dd872d316" style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 18pt; margin-bottom: 3pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 18pt; font-family: Cambria,serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Phase I Conclusions</span></h2> <p style="line-height: 1.2; text-align: justify; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Under Phase 1 funding, Reefgen rapidly </span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">developed key components of a robotic system to plant corals</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> from a nursery in a hard substrate under water. We also </span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">built a functional coral planting robot</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">. In six months, we were able to assemble COTS components and in-house fabricated parts into a system that actually can plant a coral in the ocean. We also</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> developed a method, process, and devices to attach the corals to reefs instantaneously</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">, which was not previously possible. With a solid dedication to field testing every innovation as we made it, we were able to test all of our hardware regularly. Through our field program, we </span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">demonstrated coral disk planting, both in the lab and in the ocean</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">. Multiple times we were able to complete the cycle of preparing a hard surface and attaching a coral.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">We applied for and received an extension period for Phase 1 work on Reefgen. We had already achieved much of the intended progress for Phase 1 by demonstrating a system that can rapidly attach a nursery coral to a simulated reef in our initial 6 month window. However, the demonstrations of technical feasibility were performed with hardware that was built specifically to perform a task in a limited set of circumstances and with significant manual control. Continuing work in our extended Phase 1 period allowed us to circle back and build a more forward looking robotic planting system as well as work on organizational growth. We switched to a more capable electronics and software suite, built an expandable / reconfigurable ROV, raised more money, hired more staff, and built many relationships during our extension time.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The development path mapped out for the next few years includes further development of all of the components begun in Phase 1. Because this system involves many interdependent software, hardware, and sensor systems, the development map includes simultaneous work on all aspects of the vehicle and coral planting process.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/03/2021<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Pompa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747284928_dl2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747284928_dl2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reefgen ROV 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747284928_dl2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reefgen ROV 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Blue ROV modified to prepare a substrate and plant corals from a nursery</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jon Pompa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;Pompa</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reefgen ROV 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747461561_dl3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747461561_dl3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reefgen planting ROV2 swimming"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747461561_dl3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reefgen planting ROV2 swimming"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Reefgen has developed a reconfigurable vehicle for planting corals on damaged reefs</div> <div class="imageCredit">Manyu Belani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;Pompa</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reefgen planting ROV2 swimming</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747598170_dl1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747598170_dl1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ROV preparing a test substrate for coral planting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2014581/2014581_10671063_1622747598170_dl1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ROV preparing a test substrate for coral planting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Reefgen ROV prepares an underwater substrate to receive a nursery coral using a rotary tool.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Manyu Belani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;Pompa</div> <div class="imageTitle">ROV preparing a test substrate for coral planting</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ReefGen is planning to scale up coral restoration capacity worldwide to keep pace with the rate of coral mortality. This task is ambitious given that current estimates of coral loss rate and coral restoration rate differ by 6 orders of magnitude. The path chosen to achieve this needed correction is through increasing the rate of outplanting of nursery-raised corals using robotics and automation. The overarching phase 1 goal of the ReefGen project is to develop a proof of concept robotic system that can rapidly plant corals and be replicated at low cost. Such a system is needed to overcome the limits of manpower available to perform reef outplanting work. This robot's end purpose will be to attach live corals onto damaged reefs. This allows rapid re-colonization and a possibility for the restored population of corals to reach self-sustaining reproduction faster than other methods. The reason for using this method is that corals matured in a nursery will have high survival rates and can be located in places where coral spawn is not naturally available due to a lack of reproductive adults in the area. Overview of activities in phase 1 ReefGen's Phase 1 work has allowed us to prove that our approach to planting corals is feasible and has great promise. We have built a robotic system that is capable of preparing a hard substrate for a coral planting and permanently attaching a coral. We have completed preliminary field trials with a simple system, proving the viability of each functional step of the planting system. Furthermore, our method has been positively received by the coral restoration community.  The Phase 1 work of the project was successful in advancing the state of the art of coral planting technology and in developing relationships for commercialization and partnerships with other groups in the production chain of the industry.  Phase I Conclusions Under Phase 1 funding, Reefgen rapidly developed key components of a robotic system to plant corals from a nursery in a hard substrate under water. We also built a functional coral planting robot. In six months, we were able to assemble COTS components and in-house fabricated parts into a system that actually can plant a coral in the ocean. We also developed a method, process, and devices to attach the corals to reefs instantaneously, which was not previously possible. With a solid dedication to field testing every innovation as we made it, we were able to test all of our hardware regularly. Through our field program, we demonstrated coral disk planting, both in the lab and in the ocean. Multiple times we were able to complete the cycle of preparing a hard surface and attaching a coral.   We applied for and received an extension period for Phase 1 work on Reefgen. We had already achieved much of the intended progress for Phase 1 by demonstrating a system that can rapidly attach a nursery coral to a simulated reef in our initial 6 month window. However, the demonstrations of technical feasibility were performed with hardware that was built specifically to perform a task in a limited set of circumstances and with significant manual control. Continuing work in our extended Phase 1 period allowed us to circle back and build a more forward looking robotic planting system as well as work on organizational growth. We switched to a more capable electronics and software suite, built an expandable / reconfigurable ROV, raised more money, hired more staff, and built many relationships during our extension time.   The development path mapped out for the next few years includes further development of all of the components begun in Phase 1. Because this system involves many interdependent software, hardware, and sensor systems, the development map includes simultaneous work on all aspects of the vehicle and coral planting process.        Last Modified: 06/03/2021       Submitted by: Jonathan Pompa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
