<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Attendee Support for the 2020 AAAI Doctorial Consortium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17100.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Donlon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jdonlon@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928074</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant supports to student travel for select students participating in 25th AAAI/SIGAI Doctoral Consortium (DC), which will be held on February 7-8, 2020,  in  New  York,  New  York.  This activity will bring together a broad community of researchers in the field of AI, and support junior researchers at this critical early-career stage.  The DC creates the opportunity to bring in participants who might not have attended an AI conference due to lack of resources. This is especially true for those at smaller institutions and those which have less developed AI programs. Engaging such participants has the potential to draw more talent into AI research, improve research ideas in their formative stage, and engender collaborations across the breadth of disciplines.  This event provides students with invaluable exposure to outside perspectives on their work at a critical time in their research and also enables them to explore their career objectives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015041</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin Ning Hui</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin Ning Hui Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>justinnhli@oxy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3233414116</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000715179</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Occidental College</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900413314</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3232591414</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Campus Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046436051</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OCCIDENTAL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046436051</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Occidental College]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900413314</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 Campus Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~17100</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence Doctoral Consortium (AAAI-DC) is an associated meeting at one of the largest artificial intelligence (AI) international conferences in the world. The Doctoral Consortium provides an opportunity for PhD students to share their work, to receive mentorship from leading AI researchers, and to network with peers and industry professionals. This grant allowed six computer science doctoral students from around the country to attend AAA-DC, and funded their travel, lodgings and sustenance. As part of the consortium, the students heard from Ayanna Howard, a leading roboticist, on the challenges of being a researcher, and also from a panel of academics and industry researchers on career opportunities.<br /><br />Although the development of each doctoral student is necessarily personal, AAAI-DC offered multiple opportunities for both technical and professional development of the participants. On the technical side, the participants get to hear about ongoing research in other areas, and potentially find new collaborators. On the professional side, the speaker on imposter syndrome, and the panel on career paths, were both designed to improve the effectiveness and future potential of the attendees. The mentors typically got in contact with their attendees beforehand, gave feedback on work and/or presentations, and many keep in touch afterwards as well. In both cases, this grant better prepared the participants in completing their research and leading a career in computer science and artificial intelligence.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Justin Ning Hui&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence Doctoral Consortium (AAAI-DC) is an associated meeting at one of the largest artificial intelligence (AI) international conferences in the world. The Doctoral Consortium provides an opportunity for PhD students to share their work, to receive mentorship from leading AI researchers, and to network with peers and industry professionals. This grant allowed six computer science doctoral students from around the country to attend AAA-DC, and funded their travel, lodgings and sustenance. As part of the consortium, the students heard from Ayanna Howard, a leading roboticist, on the challenges of being a researcher, and also from a panel of academics and industry researchers on career opportunities.  Although the development of each doctoral student is necessarily personal, AAAI-DC offered multiple opportunities for both technical and professional development of the participants. On the technical side, the participants get to hear about ongoing research in other areas, and potentially find new collaborators. On the professional side, the speaker on imposter syndrome, and the panel on career paths, were both designed to improve the effectiveness and future potential of the attendees. The mentors typically got in contact with their attendees beforehand, gave feedback on work and/or presentations, and many keep in touch afterwards as well. In both cases, this grant better prepared the participants in completing their research and leading a career in computer science and artificial intelligence.       Last Modified: 10/04/2020       Submitted by: Justin Ning Hui Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
