<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Sensitive Nanoscintillators for Multiplexed Detection of Radioisotopes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of core-shell nanomaterials for sensitive detection of low-energy radioisotopes commonly used as molecular labels and tracers in quantitative biological, chemical and environmental studies. These nanomaterials can be used in place of traditional methods for measuring low-energy radioisotopes and offer greater sensitivity and better sample compatibility, while also resulting in less hazardous waste. The technology platform is expected to demonstrate several advantages over other methods in particularly challenging, information-rich areas of research, including detection of molecules within living cells. The nanomaterials platform, with further development, will also allow for the simultaneous detection of multiple compounds, an important factor in the study of complex biological samples. These advances will provide critical new tools for bioscience research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will improve the sensitivity of a novel core-shell nanomaterial platform and develop a basic template for multi-color, multiplexed assays as well as an accompanying first-generation instrument capable of translating these advances to commercial application.  Radioisotope labels remain the gold standard in a wide range of quantitative biological, chemical and environmental studies and have played a critical role in the investigation of biological systems for almost a century. However, the low energy and short penetration depth of the most commonly used radioisotopes necessitate the use of liquid scintillation counting, solid scintillation counting or scintillation proximity assays for detection.  These assays are often incompatible with living systems, are not readily multiplexed and/or provide limited time-resolved measurement capabilities. The goals of this project are: 1) advance nanomaterial preparation to yield higher reproducibility and sensitivity signals; 2)  yield multicolor materials for simultaneous multiplexed assays; and, 3) generate a dual color scintillation counter than enables and demonstrates the utility of the platform for multiplexed assays. These goals will be accomplished by exploring a variety of scintillant fluorophores and polymer linkages in parallel with instrument design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015125</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Janczak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colleen Janczak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>colleenjanczak@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4152907622</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000817963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SCINTILLATION NANOTECHNOLOGIES LLC</Name>
<CityName>VAIL</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>856412047</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4152907622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>13889 E PLACITA PROPIA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>116902843</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SCINTILLATION NANOTECHNOLOGIES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210041</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1306 E. University Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224700</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
