<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research NSF INCLUDES: Early STEM Engagement for Minority Males through a Network of Minority Serving Institutions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/20/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6417.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6417</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monya Ruffin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mruffin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924635</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Morgan State University INCLUDES project will build on an existing regional partnership of four Historically Black Colleges and Universities that are working together to improve STEM outcomes for middle school minority male students that are local to Morgan State in Baltimore, North Carolina A&amp;T in Greensboro, Jackson State in Mississippi, and Kentucky State in Frankfort. Additional partners include SRI International, the National CARES Mentoring Network, and the Verizon Foundation. Using the collective impact-style approaches such as planning and implementing a Network Improvement Community (NIC), developing a shared agenda and implementing mutually reinforcing activities, these partners will address two common goals: (1) Broaden the participation of underrepresented minority males in science and engineering through educational experiences that prepare them for careers in STEM fields; and (2) Create a Network Improvement Community focused on STEM achievement in minority males.  Program elements include high-quality instruction in STEM content, mentoring, and professional development. The project will expand to include eight additional partners (six HBCUs and two Hispanic-Serving Institutions) and schools and districts in communities local to their campuses. The INCLUDES pilot will help scale innovations that target impacting minorities in STEM. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop STEM learning pathways for middle school minority males by harnessing the collective impact of 12 university partners, local K-12 schools and districts with which they partner, and surrounding community organizations and businesses with a vested interest in achieving common goals. Products will include a roadmap for addressing the problem through a Network Improvement Community, a website that will contribute to the knowledge base regarding effective strategies for enhancing STEM educational opportunities for minority males, and common metrics, assessments, and shared measurement systems that will be used to measure the collective impact of the Network Improvement Community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016442</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cindy</FirstName>
<LastName>Ziker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cindy S Ziker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cindyziker@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4806946753</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000679606</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ZIKER ENTERPRISES LLC</Name>
<CityName>SAN JOSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>951256341</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4806946753</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2769 SUNBONNET CT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>807425975</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ZIKER ENTERPRISES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ZIKER ENTERPRISES LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN JOSE</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>951256341</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029Z</Code>
<Text>Launch Pilots INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031Z</Code>
<Text>Alliances INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0419</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~6417</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Minority males are underrepresented in the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) workforce as compared to their representation in the US population. Roadblocks that continue to challenge minority males include: disparity in access to high quality STEM educational resources, a lack of role models, and a shortage of highly trained, minority STEM educators. The NSF INCLUDES Collaborative Research: Early STEM Engagement for Minority Males through a Network of Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) Design and Development Launch Pilot Project, led by Morgan State University, grew out of an existing regional partnership of four Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) that worked together to improve STEM outcomes for middle school minority male students local to Morgan State University, North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University, Jackson State University, and Kentucky State University, with SRI International and Ziker Research serving as mini-backbone organizations. The American Association for the Advancement of Science served as the project evaluator. Additional partners included the National CARES Mentoring Network and the Verizon Foundation. Using collective impact-style approaches, such as implementing a Network Improvement Community (NIC), developing a shared agenda, and implementing mutually reinforcing activities, these partners addressed two common goals: Goal 1: Broaden the participation of underrepresented minority males in science and engineering through educational experiences that prepare them for careers in STEM fields; and Goal 2: Create a Network Improvement Community focused on STEM achievement in minority males. A supplement was awarded to the project in September of 2019. During the supplemental period of performance, two additional goals were addressed: Goal S1: Participate in INCLUDES Coordination Hub Activities; and Goal S2: The eSEM team will provide data to and participate in the INCLUDES National Network.</span></p> <p><span>Intellectual Merit: This project developed STEM learning pathways for middle school minority males by harnessing the collective impact of 12 university partners, local K-12 schools and districts with which they partner, and surrounding community organizations and businesses with a vested interest in achieving common goals. Products include a roadmap for addressing the problem of improving STEM outcomes for minority males, a website that contributes to the knowledge base regarding effective strategies for enhancing STEM educational opportunities for minority males (<a href="https://esem-includes.org/"><span>https://esem-includes.org/</span></a>&nbsp;), and a video that was included in the 2017 STEM for All Showcase (<a href="https://stemforall2017.videohall.com/presentations/1046"><span>https://stemforall2017.videohall.com/presentations/1046</span></a>). The PI partnered with a STEM education researcher from Bowie State University to secure additional NSF funding to conduct research at four eSEM HBCUs (Award #1743335 - Black Males in Middle School (HBCU-DCL EAGER): Investigating How STEM Mentoring Programs and Experiences Influences Their Academic and Career Interest in Engineering). A presentation highlighting this initiative was delivered during a roundtable at the American Educational Research Association's 2019 Annual Conference in Toronto, Canada. Publications are pending.</span></p> <p><span>Broader Impact: The project developed and implemented a networked improvement community (NIC) consisting of HBCUs, MSIs, researchers, practitioners, business and industry partners, community members, and mentoring organizations that created a model for broadening the participation of minority males in STEM learning. This effort has impacted over 2,000 students and 150 teachers in twelve communities spread throughout 11 states. The first steps in building the NIC involved the development of a collaborative infrastructure and the implementation of a face-to-face convening in May of 2017, that provided an opportunity for campuses offering male initiatives, community organizations, leading experts, and researchers to obtain insight into research outcomes and the national discourse around male STEM achievement. This meeting, hosted at Morgan State University, included a two-day workshop entitled&nbsp;<em><span>Building a Networked Improvement Community Around Engaging Minority Males in STEM.&nbsp;</span></em>The workshop, which engaged over 50 participants from academia, private industry, and K-12 education, provided presentations from researchers on black male achievement, impact of informal STEM learning environments, and mathematics education. Break-out sessions focused on the development of a preliminary driver diagram and defining next steps for the NIC.</span></p> <p><span>Leveraging the collective impact of a diverse group of stakeholders working together, the successful implementation of this project has resulted in the development of the eSEM Roadmap, strategies for improving STEM education, and resources for increasing the number of minority males who are prepared to start on the path to a STEM career.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>During the project, the eSEM team actively engaged with the National INCLUDES Network through events offered by the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub (<a href="https://www.includesnetwork.org/home">https://www.includesnetwork.org/home</a>).&nbsp;Data generated about growing the NIC was disseminated at the 2017 and 2018 NSF INCLUDES Principal Investigators Meetings, through the eSEM project website, and during a presentation by the Principal Investigator at the 2018 American Society for Engineering Education (citation below).</span></p> <p><span>Ladeji-Osias, J. O., &amp; Ziker, C. S., &amp; Gloster, C., &amp; Ali, K. S., &amp; Gilmore, D. C. (2018, June), Board 79: Building a Networked Improvement Community (NIC) around Engaging Minority Males in STEM Paper presented at 2018 ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition, Salt Lake City, Utah.&nbsp;<a href="https://peer.asee.org/30109"><span>https://peer.asee.org/30109</span></a></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Cindy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Ziker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598543194181_9-27-2017_eSEMposter--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598543194181_9-27-2017_eSEMposter--rgov-800width.jpg" title="eSEM Project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598543194181_9-27-2017_eSEMposter--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="eSEM Project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Early STEM Engagement for Minority Males through a Network of Minority Serving Institutions (eSEM)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Morgan State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cindy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Ziker</div> <div class="imageTitle">eSEM Project</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598542078450_eSEMWorkshopAttendees--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598542078450_eSEMWorkshopAttendees--rgov-800width.jpg" title="eSEM Workshop Attendees"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598542078450_eSEMWorkshopAttendees--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="eSEM Workshop Attendees"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2017 eSEM Workshop: Building a Networked Improvement CommunityAround Engaging Minority Males in STEM</div> <div class="imageCredit">Morgan State University</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cindy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Ziker</div> <div class="imageTitle">eSEM Workshop Attendees</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598542779192_eSEMProjectPartners--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598542779192_eSEMProjectPartners--rgov-800width.jpg" title="eSEM Project Collaboration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/2016442/2016442_10460769_1598542779192_eSEMProjectPartners--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="eSEM Project Collaboration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">eSEM Projectt Partners</div> <div class="imageCredit">Morgan State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cindy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Ziker</div> <div class="imageTitle">eSEM Project Collaboration</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Minority males are underrepresented in the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) workforce as compared to their representation in the US population. Roadblocks that continue to challenge minority males include: disparity in access to high quality STEM educational resources, a lack of role models, and a shortage of highly trained, minority STEM educators. The NSF INCLUDES Collaborative Research: Early STEM Engagement for Minority Males through a Network of Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) Design and Development Launch Pilot Project, led by Morgan State University, grew out of an existing regional partnership of four Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) that worked together to improve STEM outcomes for middle school minority male students local to Morgan State University, North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University, Jackson State University, and Kentucky State University, with SRI International and Ziker Research serving as mini-backbone organizations. The American Association for the Advancement of Science served as the project evaluator. Additional partners included the National CARES Mentoring Network and the Verizon Foundation. Using collective impact-style approaches, such as implementing a Network Improvement Community (NIC), developing a shared agenda, and implementing mutually reinforcing activities, these partners addressed two common goals: Goal 1: Broaden the participation of underrepresented minority males in science and engineering through educational experiences that prepare them for careers in STEM fields; and Goal 2: Create a Network Improvement Community focused on STEM achievement in minority males. A supplement was awarded to the project in September of 2019. During the supplemental period of performance, two additional goals were addressed: Goal S1: Participate in INCLUDES Coordination Hub Activities; and Goal S2: The eSEM team will provide data to and participate in the INCLUDES National Network.  Intellectual Merit: This project developed STEM learning pathways for middle school minority males by harnessing the collective impact of 12 university partners, local K-12 schools and districts with which they partner, and surrounding community organizations and businesses with a vested interest in achieving common goals. Products include a roadmap for addressing the problem of improving STEM outcomes for minority males, a website that contributes to the knowledge base regarding effective strategies for enhancing STEM educational opportunities for minority males (https://esem-includes.org/ ), and a video that was included in the 2017 STEM for All Showcase (https://stemforall2017.videohall.com/presentations/1046). The PI partnered with a STEM education researcher from Bowie State University to secure additional NSF funding to conduct research at four eSEM HBCUs (Award #1743335 - Black Males in Middle School (HBCU-DCL EAGER): Investigating How STEM Mentoring Programs and Experiences Influences Their Academic and Career Interest in Engineering). A presentation highlighting this initiative was delivered during a roundtable at the American Educational Research Association's 2019 Annual Conference in Toronto, Canada. Publications are pending.  Broader Impact: The project developed and implemented a networked improvement community (NIC) consisting of HBCUs, MSIs, researchers, practitioners, business and industry partners, community members, and mentoring organizations that created a model for broadening the participation of minority males in STEM learning. This effort has impacted over 2,000 students and 150 teachers in twelve communities spread throughout 11 states. The first steps in building the NIC involved the development of a collaborative infrastructure and the implementation of a face-to-face convening in May of 2017, that provided an opportunity for campuses offering male initiatives, community organizations, leading experts, and researchers to obtain insight into research outcomes and the national discourse around male STEM achievement. This meeting, hosted at Morgan State University, included a two-day workshop entitled Building a Networked Improvement Community Around Engaging Minority Males in STEM. The workshop, which engaged over 50 participants from academia, private industry, and K-12 education, provided presentations from researchers on black male achievement, impact of informal STEM learning environments, and mathematics education. Break-out sessions focused on the development of a preliminary driver diagram and defining next steps for the NIC.  Leveraging the collective impact of a diverse group of stakeholders working together, the successful implementation of this project has resulted in the development of the eSEM Roadmap, strategies for improving STEM education, and resources for increasing the number of minority males who are prepared to start on the path to a STEM career.   During the project, the eSEM team actively engaged with the National INCLUDES Network through events offered by the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub (https://www.includesnetwork.org/home). Data generated about growing the NIC was disseminated at the 2017 and 2018 NSF INCLUDES Principal Investigators Meetings, through the eSEM project website, and during a presentation by the Principal Investigator at the 2018 American Society for Engineering Education (citation below).  Ladeji-Osias, J. O., &amp; Ziker, C. S., &amp; Gloster, C., &amp; Ali, K. S., &amp; Gilmore, D. C. (2018, June), Board 79: Building a Networked Improvement Community (NIC) around Engaging Minority Males in STEM Paper presented at 2018 ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition, Salt Lake City, Utah. https://peer.asee.org/30109             Last Modified: 08/27/2020       Submitted by: Cindy S Ziker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
