<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Dynamic Nuclear Polarization (DNP) Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>999999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>999999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical Description:&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award is to acquire a klystron microwave source and a magnet for dynamic nuclear polarization nuclear magnetic resonance (DNP NMR) spectroscopy together with an existing 400 MHz NMR console. DNP uses microwaves to increase detection sensitivity by up to two orders of magnitude, making materials characterization that was previously intractable via a traditional NMR (spectral acquisition of months) now accessible with a collection time of hours. A broad user base with diverse, interdisciplinary research activities on energy storage, heterogeneous catalysis, biomaterials, and NMR methods development benefits from the instrument acquisition and is bolstered by partnerships with industry in the greater New York/New Jersey area. Practical training in DNP NMR in both undergraduate and graduate coursework at Columbia as well as bridge programs between Columbia and Barnard (an all women liberal arts Columbia affiliate) are integrated with research to increase the participation of underrepresented groups in the training infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;DNP NMR spectroscopy has revolutionized the characterization of low sensitivity elements and surface species, allowing structural assignment at the molecular level for systems of fundamental or commercial interest. The 263 GHz klystron/400 MHz sweepable magnet offers i) an appropriate mid-field strength to study materials with large anisotropies (e.g. nanoparticles and clusters), ii) multinuclear NMR capabilities that enable the study of challenging low gamma/quadrupolar NMR nuclei in technologically relevant materials (e.g. batteries and catalysts), and iii) the development of new designer radicals for DNP. The klystron microwave source fits within the space constraints and minimizes instrument maintenance. The instrument acquisition enables and accelerates the characterization of a wide range of inorganic and biomaterials, with an emphasis on sustainability, as well as educational activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation award is jointly funded by the Division of Materials Research (DMR) and Division of Chemistry (CHE).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018756</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>McDermott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ann E McDermott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aem5@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128548393</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000237066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Marbella</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lauren E Marbella</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lem2221@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128542213</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000796092</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 West 120th Street, Mudd Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~999999</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
