<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Self-similar Solutions of Geometric Flows</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>36512.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>36512</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A geometric flow is the gradient flow associated to a functional on a manifold with a geometric interpretation. Not only is the theory of geometric flows a fundamental subject in mathematics, but it also has potential applications to other scientific fields including computer sciences, material sciences and physics. One of the most important problems in the study of geometric flows is to understand all possible singularities of the flows, which are in turn modeled by self-similar solutions of the flows. The proposed research on the moduli space of such self-similar solutions is expected to broaden and advance the knowledge and techniques both within and outside of mathematics, such as the topology of manifolds, image processing, crystal growths and the large-scale structure of the universe. In the meanwhile, new ideas and tools will be developed in various mathematical disciplines ranging from differential geometry to analysis. In addition, the PI will continue mentoring and organizing seminars and workshops for undergraduates, graduate students and young researchers. The PI will also actively participate in the promotion of women in mathematics to enhance diversity and gender equity in the society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main objective of this proposed project is to establish various geometric and analytic properties of the space of self-similar solutions of geometric flows. First, the PI, in the continuing collaboration with Brett Kotschwar at the Arizona State University, will apply the Carleman type technique to attack the rigidity problem for noncompact gradient Ricci solitons. Second, appealing to the tools inspired in part by the theory of minimal surfaces, the PI aims to describe a much detailed picture of two-dimensional smooth noncompact self-shrinkers of finite genus of mean curvature flow. To achieve this, the PI will begin with investigating the asymptotic structures at infinity of such self-shrinkers which are conjectured to be regular cones or cylinders. Then the PI intends to address the Cylinder Rigidity Conjecture of Ilmanen concerning the uniqueness of self-shrinking cylinders. At the end, the PI, with Joel Spruck at the Johns Hopkins University, plans to seek the sufficient and necessary conditions of the existence of the asymptotic Dirichlet problem for the self-shrinker equation. Third, in higher dimensions, the PI, joint with Neshan Wickramasekera at the University of Cambridge, will extend the regularity theory of stable minimal submanifolds to derive estimates on the size of singular sets of entropy stable weak self-shrinkers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lu</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lu Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lu.wang@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082133252</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628760</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd Mail Code]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~36512</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In collaboration with J. Bernstein, the PI studied geometric and analytic properties of hypersurfaces with low entropy. In particular, Bernstein and the PI proved conjectures of Colding-Ilmanen-Minicozzi-White on the sharp lower bound on entropy of closed hypersurfaces of dimension less than seven and of nonflat self-shrinkers, i.e., self-shrinking solutions to mean curvature flow. They also studied global properties of self-expanders, i.e., self-expanding solutions to mean curvature flow, and applied them to verify the Schoenflies conjecture for closed hypersurfaces of low entropy. In collaboration with B. Kotschwar, the PI studied the asymptotic rigidity of shrinking Ricci solitons. In particular, Kotschwar and the PI proved that, under assumptions on the decay rate, any asymptotically cylindrical shrinking Ricci soliton is isometric to the standard cylinder metric. They also showed that for any asymptotically conical shrinking Ricci soliton, the isometry group of the asymptotic cone is embedded into the isometry group of the Ricci soliton. The PI verified an assertion of Ilmanen that every end of any 2-dimensionsl self-shrinker is asymptotic either to a cone with isolated singularity at the vertex or to a round cylinder.&nbsp;</p> <p>The PI supervised two Ph.D. students, one of whom received Ph.D. degree in Spring 2018 from the University of Wisconsin-Madison. The other at Caltech (transferred from University of Wisconsin-Madison) has passed the candidacy exam, a milestone towards the Ph.D. degree, and has made much progress on research projects on mean curvature flow. The PI also supervised one master student, who received the master degree in Spring 2018 from the University of Wisconsin-Madison. The PI also served on thesis committee for several graduate students at University of Wisconsin-Madison. Besides, the PI mentored three sophomores from Imperial College London on a project about properties of harmonic functions. This resulted a presentation to a group of sophomores and faculties in the department.</p> <p>The PI helped recruite female graduate students and other underrepresented groups by participating in the departmental graduate admission committee. In addition to organizing the geometry and topology seminar, the PI co-organized the Women in Mathematics at Wisconsin (WIMAW) lecture series, help invite speakers and host social events, such as lunch for female graduate students and postdocs with speakers, to discuss career developments and related issues. The PI also co-organized a session on geometric analysis in the 2018 Joint Mathematics Meetings in San Diego, CA. The majority of the speakers that were invited consists of graduate students and postdocs. As to attract students to the field, the PI taught min-courses on mean curvature flow at several occastions: Mini-School on Mean Curvature Flow and Ricci Flow at Fields Institute in 2017, Summer School in Minimal Surfaces, Flows, and Relativity at University of Connecticut in 2018, Preview for the Women in Mathematics program at the Institute for Advanced Study in 2019, Winter School for the Southern California Geometric Analysis Seminar at University of California-Irvine in 2020.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Lu&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In collaboration with J. Bernstein, the PI studied geometric and analytic properties of hypersurfaces with low entropy. In particular, Bernstein and the PI proved conjectures of Colding-Ilmanen-Minicozzi-White on the sharp lower bound on entropy of closed hypersurfaces of dimension less than seven and of nonflat self-shrinkers, i.e., self-shrinking solutions to mean curvature flow. They also studied global properties of self-expanders, i.e., self-expanding solutions to mean curvature flow, and applied them to verify the Schoenflies conjecture for closed hypersurfaces of low entropy. In collaboration with B. Kotschwar, the PI studied the asymptotic rigidity of shrinking Ricci solitons. In particular, Kotschwar and the PI proved that, under assumptions on the decay rate, any asymptotically cylindrical shrinking Ricci soliton is isometric to the standard cylinder metric. They also showed that for any asymptotically conical shrinking Ricci soliton, the isometry group of the asymptotic cone is embedded into the isometry group of the Ricci soliton. The PI verified an assertion of Ilmanen that every end of any 2-dimensionsl self-shrinker is asymptotic either to a cone with isolated singularity at the vertex or to a round cylinder.   The PI supervised two Ph.D. students, one of whom received Ph.D. degree in Spring 2018 from the University of Wisconsin-Madison. The other at Caltech (transferred from University of Wisconsin-Madison) has passed the candidacy exam, a milestone towards the Ph.D. degree, and has made much progress on research projects on mean curvature flow. The PI also supervised one master student, who received the master degree in Spring 2018 from the University of Wisconsin-Madison. The PI also served on thesis committee for several graduate students at University of Wisconsin-Madison. Besides, the PI mentored three sophomores from Imperial College London on a project about properties of harmonic functions. This resulted a presentation to a group of sophomores and faculties in the department.  The PI helped recruite female graduate students and other underrepresented groups by participating in the departmental graduate admission committee. In addition to organizing the geometry and topology seminar, the PI co-organized the Women in Mathematics at Wisconsin (WIMAW) lecture series, help invite speakers and host social events, such as lunch for female graduate students and postdocs with speakers, to discuss career developments and related issues. The PI also co-organized a session on geometric analysis in the 2018 Joint Mathematics Meetings in San Diego, CA. The majority of the speakers that were invited consists of graduate students and postdocs. As to attract students to the field, the PI taught min-courses on mean curvature flow at several occastions: Mini-School on Mean Curvature Flow and Ricci Flow at Fields Institute in 2017, Summer School in Minimal Surfaces, Flows, and Relativity at University of Connecticut in 2018, Preview for the Women in Mathematics program at the Institute for Advanced Study in 2019, Winter School for the Southern California Geometric Analysis Seminar at University of California-Irvine in 2020.       Last Modified: 11/03/2020       Submitted by: Lu Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
