<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID - Assessing the response of the Seychelles-Chagos Thermocline Ridge ecosystem to an Indian Ocean Dipole event</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>191842.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>191842</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joaquin Martinez Martinez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmartine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Phytoplankton constitute the base of the marine food web. Their diversity, productivity and abundance have a huge influence on fisheries. For example, seasonal increases in phytoplankton biomass caused by the surge of deep ocean nutrient rich waters into the upper sunlit layers in the Equatorial Indian Ocean lead to an increase in tuna stocks. However, non-periodic increases of sea surface temperatures in the Seychelles-Chagos Thermocline Ridge region in the eastern Equatorial Indian Ocean, a phenomenon known as the Indian Ocean Dipole, weakens deep ocean water surge, which seems to alter phytoplankton community structure and to reduce phytoplankton’s productivity to the detriment of tuna stocks. Yet, the impact from such unpredictable events is not fully understood. This project investigates the impacts of an ongoing Indian Ocean Dipole, one of the most severe on record, on phytoplankton. The broader impacts of the project relate to its value to inform fisheries management plans in that area. Data derived from this study is valuable to understand and predict wider changes in the food web in a region that is coming under increasing pressures of global warming. All the data is made publicly available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team is working with South Korean collaborators to understand how changes in phytoplankton biomass and in deep chlorophyll maxima may be linked to changes in phytoplankton productivity and growth rates due nutrient and/or iron limitation as a result of the weakening of deep-water upwelling. The team is also investigating the impact of the dipole event on cell size of dominating phytoplankton populations. Finally, they are testing if the phytoplankton community rely primarily on recycled as opposed to new nitrogenous nutrients for photosynthesis and growth during dipole events. The hypotheses are tested through extensive biological, hydro-chemical and biogeochemical measurements that include: 1) microscopic, Flow Cytometry, FlowCAM and HPLC pigment based analysis of phytoplankton biomass, community composition and size structure and Fast Repetition Rate based measurements of phytoplankton photosynthetic competency along a cruise  track and different depths in the water column, and 2) on-deck incubation based photosynthesis and nutrient uptake experiments. In situ measurements and sample collection is carried out as part of the Korea-US inDian Ocean Scientific (KUDOS) Research Program cruise (April-May 2020) on board the Korea Institute of Ocean Sciences and Technology Ship R/V Isabu, one of the only multi-disciplinary oceanographic cruises planned for the Seychelles-Chagos Thermocline Ridge region during the dipole event.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019983</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>JOAQUIM</FirstName>
<LastName>GOES</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>JOAQUIM I GOES</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jig@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658467</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000088542</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Helga</FirstName>
<LastName>Gomes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Helga Gomes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>helga@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546851</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000581620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109640170</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W,]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>006Z</Code>
<Text>Multiple Environmental Stressors</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1389</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8242</Code>
<Text>Marine Nitrogen Cycle</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~191842</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This study was planned for the Seychelles-Chagos Thermocline Ridge (SCTR), a large and persistent open ocean upwelling feature in the southwestern Equatorial Indian Ocean Region (5-15<sup>o</sup>S, 54-70<sup>o</sup>E). This region characterized by elevated phytoplankton biomass, is a large foraging ground for tuna fisheries in the Indian Ocean. However, not much is known about the structure of SCTR&rsquo;s phytoplankton communities, on account of the lack of dedicated biological oceanographic cruises to the region. Most measurements in the region recent past focused on ocean circulation responses and air-sea interactions, because of their importance for water mass circulation, moisture transport across the Equatorial Indian Ocean, and regional rainfall patterns over SE Asia.</p> <p>In May of 2019, the SCTR began showing signs of unusual warming, and by the beginning of July 2019, it became evident that the Equatorial Indian Ocean was experiencing an IOD event. By Sept of 2019, the IOD began to intensify at a rapid pace, we requested for funding for a &ldquo;natural event&rdquo; based RAPID grant to study the implications of the IOD on native phytoplankton phytoplankton of the SCTR. Our study planned from the 1<sup>st</sup> of April to the 8<sup>th</sup> of May 2020, on board the South Korean research ship, <em>R/V Isabu</em>, included measurements and deck based incubation experiments, aimed at filling this significant knowledge gap; more specifically to understand the impact of the IOD event on phytoplankton photo-physiology, productivity and biomass accumulation as it relates to these 4 hypotheses:</p> <p><strong>H<sub>1</sub></strong>- During an IOD event the SCTR experiences a sharp decline in phytoplankton biomass including significant weakening of its deep chlorophyll maxima.</p> <p><strong>H<sub>2</sub></strong> - The reduction in phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR during an IOD is due to acute nutrient and/or iron limitation of phytoplankton productivity and growth rates.</p> <p><strong>H<sub>3</sub></strong> - The reduction in phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR is accompanied by a significant alteration in phytoplankton community structure towards populations dominated by smaller phytoplankton.</p> <p><strong>H<sub>4</sub></strong> - During an IOD event, phytoplankton communities in the SCTR rely primarily on recycled versus new nitrogenous nutrients for photosynthesis and growth.</p> <p>In Feb. 2020, when preparing for shipment of equipment to Busan, South Korea, the home port of <em>R/V Isabu</em>, we were informed of potential delays in the departure date of the cruise because of Covid-19 in South Korea.&nbsp; By early March 2020 when the virus had reached pandemic proportions, we were informed that the cruise would be postponed indefinitely. We have been assured us that the cruise will take place despite the delay.</p> <p>On account of this setback, we turned to satellite data as our only resource to monitor the evolution of the IOD, while simultaneously monitoring changes in phytoplankton biomass. and changes in the SCTR using. This report presented here is based primarily on information garnered from satellite datasets. It was supplemented with data collected from our voluntary participation in the GO-SHIP IO7 of May-June 2018 cruise in the Indian Ocean led by NOAA PMEL These combined datasets allowed us to address <strong>H<sub>1</sub></strong>, the results revealing that the IOD event 2019 (Fig. 1A-D) had a significant impact on phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR. Additionally, we report that although the IOD of 2019 was strong, biological response both in the SCTR and off the coast of Sumatra, Indonesia was muted as compared to the equally intense IOD event of 1997/1998. These findings are being written up into two research manuscripts. During this study, we participated in the publication of 2 research manuscripts, one fully supported by this study and 2 others supported partially by this study.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Challenges and pathway forward:</strong></p> <p><strong> </strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The delay of the cruise planned for the months of May-June of 2020 has been a significant setback for our planned studies. Our colleagues from KIOST have assured us that they do not plan to cancel the <em>R/V Isabu</em> cruise to the western Indian Ocean, especially because they have instruments on moorings in the water, which have to be retrieved and replaced with a fresh set of instruments.&nbsp; The biggest uncertainty for us now is the continuation of the pandemic, which has precluded us from obtaining a firm date for the cruise. If an opportunity arises, we would like to participate in this cruise and will seek an extension of our RAPID grant to fulfill our objectives. A request for an extension will be submitted as per NSF guidelines.</p> <p><strong>Manuscript Published:</strong></p> <p>Rixen T., Cowie G., Gaye B., Goes J., Gomes H. do R., Hood R. R, Lachkar Z. Schmidt H., Segschneider J., Singh A. (2020). Reviews and syntheses: Present, past, and future of the oxygen minimum zone in the northern Indian Ocean. Biogeosciences,17(23):6051-6080.</p> <p>Goes, J. I.., H. do R. Gomes, S. de Rada, D. Kiefer, K. Al-Hashmi (in press) Physical and biogeochemical characteristics of the Indian Ocean Marginal Seas - Sea of Oman; In Oceanography of the Indian Ocean</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Joaquim&nbsp;I&nbsp;Goes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616244817238_Fig.1A-D--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616244817238_Fig.1A-D--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1A-D"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616244817238_Fig.1A-D--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1A-D"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 1 A) Progression of the IOD as seen in the time series of the Dipole Mode Index (DMI). A positive DMI reflects the strength of the IOD. B) Time series of SST and Chl a in the SCTR, C) Chl a anomalies showing decline in phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR, and D) decline in SST and increase in Chl</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joaquim I. Goes</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joaquim&nbsp;I&nbsp;Goes</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1A-D</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616245287764_Fig.2A-B--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616245287764_Fig.2A-B--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FIg. 2A-B"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616245287764_Fig.2A-B--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FIg. 2A-B"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 2 A) Snapshot of A) sea surface temperature (MODIS-Aqua) and B) wind speed (Aquarius) anomaly fields in the Indian Ocean during the peak of the IOD in Nov. 2019. These fields show cooling along the coast of Sumatra due to greatly enhanced easterly Equatorial winds</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joaquim I Goes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joaquim&nbsp;I&nbsp;Goes</div> <div class="imageTitle">FIg. 2A-B</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616246334122_Fig.3A-B--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616246334122_Fig.3A-B--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 3A-B"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616246334122_Fig.3A-B--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 3A-B"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 3A) Chl a anomalies and B) SST anomalies in the Equatorial Indian Ocean region observed during the peak of the IOD in Nov. 2019. These anomalies show a decline in SST off the coast of Sumatra associated with easterly Equatorial wind.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joaquim I. Goes</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joaquim&nbsp;I&nbsp;Goes</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 3A-B</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616247151717_Fig.4A-B--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616247151717_Fig.4A-B--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 4A-B"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616247151717_Fig.4A-B--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 4A-B"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 4A) Chl a anomalies and B) SST anomalies in the Equatorial Indian Ocean region observed during the peak of the IOD in Nov. 1998. These anomalies show that the biological response in the Equatorial Indian Ocean was much stronger during the 1998/1998 IOD event than in 2019</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joaquim I. Goes</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joaquim&nbsp;I&nbsp;Goes</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 4A-B</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616247738559_Fig.5A-D--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616247738559_Fig.5A-D--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 5A-D"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2019983/2019983_10653228_1616247738559_Fig.5A-D--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 5A-D"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 5. Distribution of in-situ A) seawater temperature, B) nitrate, C) Chl a and D) Fv/Fm  along the south-north Go-SHIP IO7 section. These data were collected on borad NOAA ship R/V Ron Brown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joaquim I. Goes, Victoria Coles</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joaquim&nbsp;I&nbsp;Goes</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 5A-D</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This study was planned for the Seychelles-Chagos Thermocline Ridge (SCTR), a large and persistent open ocean upwelling feature in the southwestern Equatorial Indian Ocean Region (5-15oS, 54-70oE). This region characterized by elevated phytoplankton biomass, is a large foraging ground for tuna fisheries in the Indian Ocean. However, not much is known about the structure of SCTR’s phytoplankton communities, on account of the lack of dedicated biological oceanographic cruises to the region. Most measurements in the region recent past focused on ocean circulation responses and air-sea interactions, because of their importance for water mass circulation, moisture transport across the Equatorial Indian Ocean, and regional rainfall patterns over SE Asia.  In May of 2019, the SCTR began showing signs of unusual warming, and by the beginning of July 2019, it became evident that the Equatorial Indian Ocean was experiencing an IOD event. By Sept of 2019, the IOD began to intensify at a rapid pace, we requested for funding for a "natural event" based RAPID grant to study the implications of the IOD on native phytoplankton phytoplankton of the SCTR. Our study planned from the 1st of April to the 8th of May 2020, on board the South Korean research ship, R/V Isabu, included measurements and deck based incubation experiments, aimed at filling this significant knowledge gap; more specifically to understand the impact of the IOD event on phytoplankton photo-physiology, productivity and biomass accumulation as it relates to these 4 hypotheses:  H1- During an IOD event the SCTR experiences a sharp decline in phytoplankton biomass including significant weakening of its deep chlorophyll maxima.  H2 - The reduction in phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR during an IOD is due to acute nutrient and/or iron limitation of phytoplankton productivity and growth rates.  H3 - The reduction in phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR is accompanied by a significant alteration in phytoplankton community structure towards populations dominated by smaller phytoplankton.  H4 - During an IOD event, phytoplankton communities in the SCTR rely primarily on recycled versus new nitrogenous nutrients for photosynthesis and growth.  In Feb. 2020, when preparing for shipment of equipment to Busan, South Korea, the home port of R/V Isabu, we were informed of potential delays in the departure date of the cruise because of Covid-19 in South Korea.  By early March 2020 when the virus had reached pandemic proportions, we were informed that the cruise would be postponed indefinitely. We have been assured us that the cruise will take place despite the delay.  On account of this setback, we turned to satellite data as our only resource to monitor the evolution of the IOD, while simultaneously monitoring changes in phytoplankton biomass. and changes in the SCTR using. This report presented here is based primarily on information garnered from satellite datasets. It was supplemented with data collected from our voluntary participation in the GO-SHIP IO7 of May-June 2018 cruise in the Indian Ocean led by NOAA PMEL These combined datasets allowed us to address H1, the results revealing that the IOD event 2019 (Fig. 1A-D) had a significant impact on phytoplankton biomass in the SCTR. Additionally, we report that although the IOD of 2019 was strong, biological response both in the SCTR and off the coast of Sumatra, Indonesia was muted as compared to the equally intense IOD event of 1997/1998. These findings are being written up into two research manuscripts. During this study, we participated in the publication of 2 research manuscripts, one fully supported by this study and 2 others supported partially by this study.     Challenges and pathway forward:               The delay of the cruise planned for the months of May-June of 2020 has been a significant setback for our planned studies. Our colleagues from KIOST have assured us that they do not plan to cancel the R/V Isabu cruise to the western Indian Ocean, especially because they have instruments on moorings in the water, which have to be retrieved and replaced with a fresh set of instruments.  The biggest uncertainty for us now is the continuation of the pandemic, which has precluded us from obtaining a firm date for the cruise. If an opportunity arises, we would like to participate in this cruise and will seek an extension of our RAPID grant to fulfill our objectives. A request for an extension will be submitted as per NSF guidelines.  Manuscript Published:  Rixen T., Cowie G., Gaye B., Goes J., Gomes H. do R., Hood R. R, Lachkar Z. Schmidt H., Segschneider J., Singh A. (2020). Reviews and syntheses: Present, past, and future of the oxygen minimum zone in the northern Indian Ocean. Biogeosciences,17(23):6051-6080.  Goes, J. I.., H. do R. Gomes, S. de Rada, D. Kiefer, K. Al-Hashmi (in press) Physical and biogeochemical characteristics of the Indian Ocean Marginal Seas - Sea of Oman; In Oceanography of the Indian Ocean       Last Modified: 04/01/2021       Submitted by: Joaquim I Goes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
