<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development of a Sterilization-based Reusable Catheterization System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to improve the process of intermittent urinary catheterization while decreasing the risk of associated infection For individuals who cannot empty their bladder due to anatomic or physiologic causes, single-use intermittent catheterization is the safest method for bladder emptying. Despite this, typical catheterization methods produce an annual 40-60% risk of complicated urinary tract infection, leading to over $4 billion of avoidable healthcare costs and patient morbidity. Some catheterization tools are safer than standard disposable catheters (e.g. no-touch catheters), but these are more costly and rarely used. To address this cost, some individuals attempt to sterilize their single-use catheters and reuse them in an off-label manner, increasing the risk of urinary tract infection to 70-80% per year. This project aims to develop a safe reusable catheter with the benefits of a no-touch catheter, allowing for an at-home sterilization device; this innovation will allow for a decrease in urinary tract infection risk, improvement in catheter usability, decreased catheter spending, and a 99% reduction of catheter-associated waste.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will focus on the technical sterilization abilities of this novel purpose-built catheter sterilization device, especially when dealing with anticipated formation of bacterial biofilms. This research will involve exposing catheter samples to pathogen-inoculated urine, performing the anticipated cleaning and sterilization methodologies, and utilizing previously-validated fluorescence imaging techniques to document the presence and location of surviving bacteria and biofilm formation. It is expected that the intended sterilization techniques inherent in this novel device will provide adequate sterilization assurance for safe catheter reuse. This project will also focus on the feasibility of the laboratory-validated cleaning and sterilization protocol for anticipated users to perform without medical supervision. This research will examine cleaning and sterilization protocols by individual catheter users to determine points of potential risk to inform design of the device and the protocol.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021595</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Souvik</FirstName>
<LastName>Paul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Souvik Paul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>souvik@cathbuddy.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5162708097</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000781801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CATHBUDDY, INC.</Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<ZipCode>132100000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5162708097</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>841 E Fayette Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>081246363</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CATHBUDDY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CathBuddy, Inc. at Central New York Biotech Accelerator]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132101521</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[841 E FAYETTE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF Phase I SBIR project was intended to establish proof of concept of a resuable no-touch intermittent urinary catheter system. In the first specific aim, catheter prototypes were developed in production equivalent materials; these prototypes were inoculated with robust uropathogens that cause complicated urinary tract infections in the second specific aim and subsequently cleaned and disinfected with a prototype catheter reprocessor. The prototype catheters were then deconstructed and analyzed in order to assess how complete the cleaning and disinfection processes were.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>In fulfilling the goals of this research proposal, the CathBuddy, Inc. team worked with the University of Notre Dame to utilize their novel antibody immunofluorescence imaging technique to assess the extent to which biofilms remained on the surfaces of previously inoculated urinary catheter prototypes.</p> <p>Additionally, the viability of an alternate to the single-use medical supply paradigm that is dominant in the durable medical supply industry was established through the conducted work. The reusable approach is translatable to other durable medical equipment categories where cost proves to be a real barrier to the adoption of clinically significant innovations.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Successful commercialization of the proof of concept established in this Phase I project will ultimately benefit individuals living with disabilities - most notably individuals living with urinary retention who rely on single-use intermittent catheters to urinate. The impact of increasing access to quality catheters that have been shown in academic literature to reduce complicated urinary tract infection incidence by upwards of 30% is measured in the hundreds of millions of dollars of avoided healthcare expenses every year. There are significant positive impacts to quality of life as well - catheter users are projected to be able to experience more spontaneity, flexibility, and independence in their daily lives, and to be able to more fully engage in their communities as a result. Finally, single-use catheterization generates upwards of 85 million pounds of plastic waste every year. The successful commercialization of this innovation will help to dramatically reduce that impact by 80% or more.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><br /></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Souvik&nbsp;Paul</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF Phase I SBIR project was intended to establish proof of concept of a resuable no-touch intermittent urinary catheter system. In the first specific aim, catheter prototypes were developed in production equivalent materials; these prototypes were inoculated with robust uropathogens that cause complicated urinary tract infections in the second specific aim and subsequently cleaned and disinfected with a prototype catheter reprocessor. The prototype catheters were then deconstructed and analyzed in order to assess how complete the cleaning and disinfection processes were.  Intellectual Merit  In fulfilling the goals of this research proposal, the CathBuddy, Inc. team worked with the University of Notre Dame to utilize their novel antibody immunofluorescence imaging technique to assess the extent to which biofilms remained on the surfaces of previously inoculated urinary catheter prototypes.  Additionally, the viability of an alternate to the single-use medical supply paradigm that is dominant in the durable medical supply industry was established through the conducted work. The reusable approach is translatable to other durable medical equipment categories where cost proves to be a real barrier to the adoption of clinically significant innovations.   Broader Impacts  Successful commercialization of the proof of concept established in this Phase I project will ultimately benefit individuals living with disabilities - most notably individuals living with urinary retention who rely on single-use intermittent catheters to urinate. The impact of increasing access to quality catheters that have been shown in academic literature to reduce complicated urinary tract infection incidence by upwards of 30% is measured in the hundreds of millions of dollars of avoided healthcare expenses every year. There are significant positive impacts to quality of life as well - catheter users are projected to be able to experience more spontaneity, flexibility, and independence in their daily lives, and to be able to more fully engage in their communities as a result. Finally, single-use catheterization generates upwards of 85 million pounds of plastic waste every year. The successful commercialization of this innovation will help to dramatically reduce that impact by 80% or more.           Last Modified: 08/12/2021       Submitted by: Souvik Paul]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
