<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2020 IEEE SGComm Conference. To be Held  November, 11-13, 2020 at Arizona State University.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald Wunsch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dwunsch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927102</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposal requests support for students to participate in the 2020 IEEE SmartGridCommunications Conference (SGComm 2020), which was originally to take place in Tempe, AZ, October 6--9, 2020, but because of the COVID-19 pandemic will now be a virtual conference taking place from Nov. 11-13, 2020. The SGComm 2020, in its eleventh year, is a well established annual conference of the IEEE Communications Society focused on emerging data and information processing challenges in the electric power grid and energy systems. The conference offers opportunities to its participants for sharing of scientific discoveries related to various computing, communications, sensing, and information processing aspects of energy systems.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;SGComm 2020, a key conference of the IEEE Communications Society, has a theme this year entitled “Trustworthy Sensing, Communications, Processing and Analytics for a Sustainable Grid”.  The conference will feature a comprehensive high-quality technical program including 4 symposia on Communications and Networking,Cyber Security and Privacy, Control and Operations, Grid Analytics and Computation as well as tutorials and workshops focused on emerging challenges and topics. The event will gather researchers and practitioners studying various aspects of the electric power grid including sensing, data processing, computing, communications, data analytics, and information sciences that are key today to ensure reliable and resilient grid operations. Finally, the conference also includes two keynote talks by leading researchers and a panel discussion, involving industry and academic leaders, on the ways to leverage technology and data science to address the key challenges for the new decade: grid resilience and sustainable energy use in the face of climate change.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests participation of about 25 students enrolled in US institutions (as well as US citizens attending international institutions) by providing registration fees to the conference. Such participation will have a positive impact on both grid-centric research in US institutions and workforce development. It will contribute to the preparation of the next cadre of engineering professionals who can advance and ensure integration of computing, data, security, and analytics technology in the electric grid while keeping the focus on sustainability, reliability, and resilience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024805</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oliver</FirstName>
<LastName>Kosut</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oliver Kosut</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>okosut@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lalitha</FirstName>
<LastName>Sankar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lalitha Sankar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lalithasankar@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809654953</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000547715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~8750</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
