<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID - The LSST Documentary Project</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nigel Sharp</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nsharp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Vera C. Rubin Observatory Documentary Project (working title) will follow the people building the NSF- and DOE-funded Rubin Observatory during construction and into its ten-year primary scientific mission.  This is a critical period in the building of the observatory (formerly the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope, LSST).  This award bridges an unfortunate gap, allowing the filmmaker to start essential filming while working to raise full production financing, including possible future seed funding from NSF.  It reinforces support from within the Rubin team, from the American Institute of Physics, Cambridge and Oxford universities (UK), and from the private sector.  The time-critical events include visits to the project by the NSF Director and the DOE Under-Secretary for Science, a visit by French contributors, and major meetings for the Data Management Leadership team, for the Operations Team, and to discuss commissioning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This long-term documentary project will capture the human drama of creating a one-of-a-kind system for scientific exploration, and will further NSF’s mission to broaden participation in STEM fields, foster a better understanding of science and the scientific process, and ensure everyone an opportunity to participate in and contribute to the research enterprise.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027217</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Kahn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Kahn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skahn@lsst.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206210194</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000670889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[452 Lomita Mall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>054F</Code>
<Text>LSST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1798</Code>
<Text>Special Projects (AST)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~14960</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The Vera C. Rubin Observatory Project is building ?a well-understood system that will produce an unprecedented astronomical data set for studies of the deep and dynamic universe, make the data widely accessible to a diverse community of scientists, and engage the public to explore the Universe with us.?</p> <p class="Default">This project advanced public engagement by supporting development of an initiative, tentatively known as ?The Vera C. Rubin Observatory Documentary Project?, which will follow the people building the Vera C. Rubin Observatory and preparing for Rubin?s primary 10-year scientific mission, the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST).&nbsp; This initial grant covered travel and equipment expenses for two weeks of filming at the Department of Energy national laboratory, SLAC, from October 27 to November 1, 2019, and again December 9-13, 2019, by filmmaker Alison Rose, OOnt, DGC.&nbsp; Rose filmed the visits of NSF Director France Cordova and Department of Energy Under Secretary for Science Paul Dabbar to the camera clean room.&nbsp; Rose also documented the completion of the focal plane, a milestone in the construction of the one-of-a-kind, state-of-the-art, LSST camera, by a diverse team of scientists and engineers.&nbsp; She was able to film the Rubin Observatory Project Director, Steve Kahn, at work, and meet with potential US film crew, including graduates of Stanford?s MFA documentary program.&nbsp; Other coincident events were recorded, particularly the quarterly meeting of the Data Management Leadership Team, the arrival of the French team from CNRS-IN2P3 in France to begin installing the filter carousel and exchange system, and the SLAC-IR2 winter All Hands meeting and annual Christmas Party.</p> <p class="Default">Rose is an independent documentary filmmaker specializing in documentaries about astronomy (see Star Men ?www.starmen.space and Galileo?s Sons), and she had been self-financing development of a documentary project about Rubin since the successful completion of an AURA contract in 2017.&nbsp; The goal of the documentary project is to enhance the broader impacts of Rubin Observatory communications, education, and public outreach by allowing the general public to follow the diversity of people and expertise engaged in the exciting work of constructing Rubin Observatory and preparing it for operation, to encourage audiences of all ages to join Rubin?s mission to explore our Universe.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/13/2021<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;Kahn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The Vera C. Rubin Observatory Project is building ?a well-understood system that will produce an unprecedented astronomical data set for studies of the deep and dynamic universe, make the data widely accessible to a diverse community of scientists, and engage the public to explore the Universe with us.? This project advanced public engagement by supporting development of an initiative, tentatively known as ?The Vera C. Rubin Observatory Documentary Project?, which will follow the people building the Vera C. Rubin Observatory and preparing for Rubin?s primary 10-year scientific mission, the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST).  This initial grant covered travel and equipment expenses for two weeks of filming at the Department of Energy national laboratory, SLAC, from October 27 to November 1, 2019, and again December 9-13, 2019, by filmmaker Alison Rose, OOnt, DGC.  Rose filmed the visits of NSF Director France Cordova and Department of Energy Under Secretary for Science Paul Dabbar to the camera clean room.  Rose also documented the completion of the focal plane, a milestone in the construction of the one-of-a-kind, state-of-the-art, LSST camera, by a diverse team of scientists and engineers.  She was able to film the Rubin Observatory Project Director, Steve Kahn, at work, and meet with potential US film crew, including graduates of Stanford?s MFA documentary program.  Other coincident events were recorded, particularly the quarterly meeting of the Data Management Leadership Team, the arrival of the French team from CNRS-IN2P3 in France to begin installing the filter carousel and exchange system, and the SLAC-IR2 winter All Hands meeting and annual Christmas Party. Rose is an independent documentary filmmaker specializing in documentaries about astronomy (see Star Men ?www.starmen.space and Galileo?s Sons), and she had been self-financing development of a documentary project about Rubin since the successful completion of an AURA contract in 2017.  The goal of the documentary project is to enhance the broader impacts of Rubin Observatory communications, education, and public outreach by allowing the general public to follow the diversity of people and expertise engaged in the exciting work of constructing Rubin Observatory and preparing it for operation, to encourage audiences of all ages to join Rubin?s mission to explore our Universe.       Last Modified: 08/13/2021       Submitted by: Steven Kahn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
