<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Rapid: Collaborative Research: Agile and effective responses to emerging pathogen threats through open data and open analytics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The same types of questions arise during every emergent viral outbreak regarding its origin, its evolution, the manner of spread, and how to detect and mitigate it. Many, if not all, of these questions depend on rapid and reliable genomic analysis of diverse viral sample sequences by multiple laboratories. Early viral investigation is often impaired lack of reproducibility, rigor, and data/analytic sharing; the current investigation of COVID-19 is no different. Essential questions such as the extent of intra-host genomic variability (indicative of adaptation or multiple infection), viral evolution (selection, recombination), transmission (phylogentic and phylogeographic) cannot be answered reliably if researchers cannot trust/replicate the source data and analytical approaches. The goal of this award is to develop, deploy, and continuously update viral genomic analysis workflows to enable the analysis and monitoring of viral evolution and dynamics for SARS-CoV-2, and to use the lessons learned to prepare capacity for future outbreaks.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Bioinformatics workflows for critical tasks in investigating COVID-19 and future viral outbreaks will be developed and COVID-19 deep sequencing data will be analyzed and shared openly via Galaxy and Datamonkey to facilitate and accelerate evolutionary discovery and enable the study of and response to inevitable future infectious disease outbreaks. In an age of digital connectivity, open and accessible shared data and analysis platforms have the potential to transform the way biomedical research is done, opening the way to ‘global research markets’, where competition arises from deriving understanding rather than access to samples and data. By enabling any researcher with an Internet connection to perform the same analyses as are done by top-flight research groups in resource-rich countries, this award will deliver critical components to resource limited settings, which are often those that are first and disproportionately affected by viral outbreaks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027196</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergei</FirstName>
<LastName>Pond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergei K Pond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>spond@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000397072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226018</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1925 N. 12th St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>085Y</Code>
<Text>ICB: Infrastructure Capacity f</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 pandemic is the first "real-time genomics" pandemic; millions of viral genomes collected worldwide make it possible to study how the virus evolves during various phases of the pandemic. This award supported software engineering and methodology development needed to analyze large volumes of viral genomic data (covid19.galaxyproject.org, www.hyphy.org).&nbsp;This award supported, in part, multi-disciplinary analyses of SARS-CoV-2 evolution and resulted in two published papers and two preprints (both accepted as papers)<br /><br /></p> <ul> <li>A PLoS Biology paper (https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001115) which examined selective forces that acted upon the virus during its emergence in the human population (from the likely bat source). We found that SARS-CoV-2 emerged as an already capable human pathogen and did not experience significant selective pressures until October 2020.</li> <li>A Molecular Biology and Evolution paper (https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/38/8/3046/6257226#281505587), where we developed an innovative technique to estimate the progenitor genome for all SARS-CoV-2 strain (placing it in China in the Fall of 2019, and three mutations different from the reference genome), and developed an intutitive "mutation"-based approach to classify SARS-CoV-2 strains, and track their spread.</li> <li>A BioRXiv preprint (https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.05.24.445313v1), accepted in Molecular Biology and Evolution, in which we looked for similarities in evolutionary patterns among human endemic beta-coronaviruses (SARS-1, SARS-2, HKU1 and OC43) to attempt to predict genomic locations where SARS-CoV-2 may be changing as it spreads through the human population. We found seven such sites, which may represent evolutionary pathways that betacoronaviruses may undergo during adaptation to the human host</li> <li>A MedRxiv preprint(https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.02.23.21252268v3), accepted in Cell. By examining patterns of mutations that arose in SARS-CoV-2 genomes during the pandemic we find evidence of a major change in the selective forces acting on various SARS-CoV-2 genes and gene segments, that likely coincided with the emergence of the 501Y (alpha, beta, gamma) lineages. We find evidence that a significant portion of the ongoing adaptive evolution of the 501Y lineages also involves further convergence between the lineages. This highlights the importance of monitoring how members of these known 501Y lineages, and others still undiscovered, are convergently evolving similar strategies to ensure their persistence in the face of mounting infection and vaccine induced host immune recognition.</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Sergei&nbsp;K&nbsp;Pond</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 pandemic is the first "real-time genomics" pandemic; millions of viral genomes collected worldwide make it possible to study how the virus evolves during various phases of the pandemic. This award supported software engineering and methodology development needed to analyze large volumes of viral genomic data (covid19.galaxyproject.org, www.hyphy.org). This award supported, in part, multi-disciplinary analyses of SARS-CoV-2 evolution and resulted in two published papers and two preprints (both accepted as papers)    A PLoS Biology paper (https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001115) which examined selective forces that acted upon the virus during its emergence in the human population (from the likely bat source). We found that SARS-CoV-2 emerged as an already capable human pathogen and did not experience significant selective pressures until October 2020. A Molecular Biology and Evolution paper (https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/38/8/3046/6257226#281505587), where we developed an innovative technique to estimate the progenitor genome for all SARS-CoV-2 strain (placing it in China in the Fall of 2019, and three mutations different from the reference genome), and developed an intutitive "mutation"-based approach to classify SARS-CoV-2 strains, and track their spread. A BioRXiv preprint (https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.05.24.445313v1), accepted in Molecular Biology and Evolution, in which we looked for similarities in evolutionary patterns among human endemic beta-coronaviruses (SARS-1, SARS-2, HKU1 and OC43) to attempt to predict genomic locations where SARS-CoV-2 may be changing as it spreads through the human population. We found seven such sites, which may represent evolutionary pathways that betacoronaviruses may undergo during adaptation to the human host A MedRxiv preprint(https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.02.23.21252268v3), accepted in Cell. By examining patterns of mutations that arose in SARS-CoV-2 genomes during the pandemic we find evidence of a major change in the selective forces acting on various SARS-CoV-2 genes and gene segments, that likely coincided with the emergence of the 501Y (alpha, beta, gamma) lineages. We find evidence that a significant portion of the ongoing adaptive evolution of the 501Y lineages also involves further convergence between the lineages. This highlights the importance of monitoring how members of these known 501Y lineages, and others still undiscovered, are convergently evolving similar strategies to ensure their persistence in the face of mounting infection and vaccine induced host immune recognition.        Last Modified: 08/16/2021       Submitted by: Sergei K Pond]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
