<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Enabling Rapid Scale-up of COVID-19 Treatment using Next-Generation Light Driven Chemistry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) project is to develop a photocatalytic process to facilitate enhanced speed and efficiency for production of key intermediate chemicals for production of Remdesivir, a potential life-saving drug in the fight against COVID-19. Remdesivir has been identified as one of the most promising treatments for COVID-19; recently receiving fast-track approval for Phase III trials and compassionate use against this rapidly spreading and deadly disease. However, today Remdesivir is not an approved drug and is therefore not manufactured at scale. This project offers potential for accelerated production of Remdesivir by removing manufacturing bottlenecks of intermediates that threaten rapid scale-up and efficient manufacturing. Upon approval, process bottlenecks could inhibit mass-production, delay global availability and jeopardize millions of lives. An optimized production method for key intermediates is urgently needed to meet worldwide demand that will be critical in the race to control the pandemic. Potential problems with the current processes include costly and hazardous raw materials, low yields, expensive and specialized equipment required for harsh operating conditions and air- and water-free environments, and arduous purification and facility clean-up procedures. In addition, this project also provides a simplified, modular and faster approach for building libraries of derivative molecules to screen against COVID-19 and future viral threats.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project proposes to develop an optimized manufacturing process for Remdesivir, one of the most promising COVID-19 therapeutic candidates identified to date, using photocatalysis, a powerful new chemical technology driven by light. Research objectives include using photocatalysis to develop a vastly superior synthesis route requiring fewer process steps, less toxic reagents and milder and safer reaction conditions. The new route will eliminate the need for specialized production equipment and procedures to maintain cryogenic temperatures and air- and water-free environments, will result in faster production times and overall higher yields, and will alleviate arduous purification and facility clean-up. The improved process will also facilitate installation of new molecular architectures and development of derivative molecules vital for efficacy screening against this and future viral threats. A second objective is to optimize the process for manufacturing at scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027590</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chern-Hooi</FirstName>
<LastName>Lim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chern-Hooi Lim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chern@newiridium.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4846394247</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000749088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Iridium</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031961</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4846394247</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2870 E College Ave, Unit 106</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>084642387</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW IRIDIUM INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Iridium/ Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805231872</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1301 Center Ave, Room B110]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Remdesivir recently received FDA approval to treat Covid-19 but global supply is currently limited by challenging chemistry involving two critical process bottlenecks. The key outcome of this project was establishing proof of concept that our next generation light-driven &ldquo;photocatalytic&rdquo; platform powered by patent pending organic photocatalysts (PCs) can resolve the two bottlenecks thus accelerating the production of remdesivir to make this treatment for Covid-19 globally accessible, especially in low and middle income countries (LMICs).</p> <p>Our platform successfully synthesized several combinations of model compounds that closely resemble the actual chemical components of remdesivir involved in the two bottleneck steps thus demonstrating efficacy in creating the required chemical bonds to form the actual remdesivir molecule within a similar model system. Success with model systems not only demonstrates proof of concept for the challenging synthesis of remdesivir but is also equally relevant to the more general problems of a) creating new anti-viral drugs based on similar chemical structures to combat existing and new viral diseases, e.g. building drug analog platforms, and b) streamlining production of those same existing and new anti-viral drugs thus reducing treatment costs, including for HIV.</p> <p>Our investigations with light-driven methods also uncovered two situations of novel reactivity resulting in bond formations under certain conditions that were previously unknown in the field. When developed, these new capabilities have the potential to lead to several promising applications and merit further exploration in follow on research.&nbsp;</p> <p>Secondary outcomes of this project include establishing freedom to operate which led to the filing of a provisional patent application for the use of our methods in remdesivir synthesis. Another secondary outcome is the development of an analytical framework to support a technoeconomic analysis and feasibility study of our new process to facilitate industrial adoption. The framework will help determine how the developed technology can be rapidly incorporated into the supply-chain to deliver measurable impact in global remdesivir production.</p> <p>This project also uncovered potential future collaboration opportunities with other organizations working on process improvement projects to increase the supply of remdesivir. Integrating our work with advances from these projects, each focusing on different parts of the remdesivir supply chain, could yield significant synergistic outcomes. Furthermore, a more wholistic solution resulting from a collaborative effort would lead to greater opportunities to establish initial distribution of the final product.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2020<br>      Modified by: Chern-Hooi&nbsp;Lim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Remdesivir recently received FDA approval to treat Covid-19 but global supply is currently limited by challenging chemistry involving two critical process bottlenecks. The key outcome of this project was establishing proof of concept that our next generation light-driven "photocatalytic" platform powered by patent pending organic photocatalysts (PCs) can resolve the two bottlenecks thus accelerating the production of remdesivir to make this treatment for Covid-19 globally accessible, especially in low and middle income countries (LMICs).  Our platform successfully synthesized several combinations of model compounds that closely resemble the actual chemical components of remdesivir involved in the two bottleneck steps thus demonstrating efficacy in creating the required chemical bonds to form the actual remdesivir molecule within a similar model system. Success with model systems not only demonstrates proof of concept for the challenging synthesis of remdesivir but is also equally relevant to the more general problems of a) creating new anti-viral drugs based on similar chemical structures to combat existing and new viral diseases, e.g. building drug analog platforms, and b) streamlining production of those same existing and new anti-viral drugs thus reducing treatment costs, including for HIV.  Our investigations with light-driven methods also uncovered two situations of novel reactivity resulting in bond formations under certain conditions that were previously unknown in the field. When developed, these new capabilities have the potential to lead to several promising applications and merit further exploration in follow on research.   Secondary outcomes of this project include establishing freedom to operate which led to the filing of a provisional patent application for the use of our methods in remdesivir synthesis. Another secondary outcome is the development of an analytical framework to support a technoeconomic analysis and feasibility study of our new process to facilitate industrial adoption. The framework will help determine how the developed technology can be rapidly incorporated into the supply-chain to deliver measurable impact in global remdesivir production.  This project also uncovered potential future collaboration opportunities with other organizations working on process improvement projects to increase the supply of remdesivir. Integrating our work with advances from these projects, each focusing on different parts of the remdesivir supply chain, could yield significant synergistic outcomes. Furthermore, a more wholistic solution resulting from a collaborative effort would lead to greater opportunities to establish initial distribution of the final product.          Last Modified: 12/16/2020       Submitted by: Chern-Hooi Lim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
