<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Group Support Grant for IEEE/CVF CVPR 2020 Doctoral Consortium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924768</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the participation of students from US-based institutions in the Doctoral Consortium at the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2020, which will be held virtually due to COVID-19. CVPR is the premier annual conference in computer vision with over 9000 participants from all over the world. The award helps the career development of some of the brightest junior researchers in computer vision to increase the number of active researchers and educators in STEM and ensures that the computer vision community, through its recent graduates, makes fast advances in solving problems that will benefit society as a whole. The Doctoral Consortium aims to have representation from a diverse group of participants in terms of gender, ethnic background, academic institution, and geographic location.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF support covers some of the costs for 40 selected US-based graduate students to participate in the Doctoral Consortium and CVPR conference. The Doctoral Consortium highlights the work of senior PhD students who are within six months of receiving their degrees (including recent graduates) and gives these students an opportunity to discuss their research and career options with faculty and researchers who have relevant expertise and experience. The opportunity to receive advice on their research work and career plans from experts from different institutions is particularly important due to the uncertainty of job prospects and disruption of traditional networking and recruiting events caused by COVID-19. Participants and recipients of support are selected by the 2020 CVPR Doctoral Consortium Chair. The support covers admissible conference-related costs such as registration. This year's Doctoral Consortium features a poster session, one-on-one mentoring, and panel discussion, all held virtually. These components were introduced in past doctoral consortiums and were well received.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032772</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Souvenir</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Souvenir</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>souvenir@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2157077379</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000730388</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~22500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was intended to support the participation of students from US-based institutions in the Doctoral Consortium at the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2020. CVPR is the premier annual conference in computer vision with over 9000 participants from all over the world. The award helps the career development of some of the brightest junior researchers in computer vision to increase the number of active researchers and educators in STEM and ensures that the computer vision community, through its recent graduates, makes fast advances in solving problems that will benefit society as a whole. The Doctoral Consortium aims to have representation from a diverse group of participants in terms of gender, ethnic background, academic institution, and geographic location.</p> <p>Due to COVID-19, the June 2020 conference was quickly shifted to a virtual platform and the format of the Doctoral Consortium was modified to account for the differences in time zones between the junior researchers and senior mentors. Junior researchers presented recorded video presentations of their research work for the mentors to comment asynchronously. Additionally, one-on-one mentoring meetings were held via video conferencing. The award supported the conference registration fees of 12 researchers from institutions across the United States.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2021<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Souvenir</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was intended to support the participation of students from US-based institutions in the Doctoral Consortium at the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2020. CVPR is the premier annual conference in computer vision with over 9000 participants from all over the world. The award helps the career development of some of the brightest junior researchers in computer vision to increase the number of active researchers and educators in STEM and ensures that the computer vision community, through its recent graduates, makes fast advances in solving problems that will benefit society as a whole. The Doctoral Consortium aims to have representation from a diverse group of participants in terms of gender, ethnic background, academic institution, and geographic location.  Due to COVID-19, the June 2020 conference was quickly shifted to a virtual platform and the format of the Doctoral Consortium was modified to account for the differences in time zones between the junior researchers and senior mentors. Junior researchers presented recorded video presentations of their research work for the mentors to comment asynchronously. Additionally, one-on-one mentoring meetings were held via video conferencing. The award supported the conference registration fees of 12 researchers from institutions across the United States.          Last Modified: 08/10/2021       Submitted by: Richard Souvenir]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
