<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Immunological adaptations in bats to moderate the effect of coronavirus infection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>105116.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>105116</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Shisler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshisler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925368</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>All aspects of society have been upended by COVID-19. While most research has understandably focused on clinical applications, how the ancestors of SARS-CoV2 survive and circulate in nature is vital to both prevent future epidemics and help health professionals develop therapeutic treatments. Because some bat species are natural carriers of many coronaviruses, including the closest known relatives of SARS-CoV-2, the team supported by this award will identify consistent differences between bats and other mammals likely involved in moderating infection by regulating virus entry and mounting an effective immune response. This project will address how bats escape illness despite carrying a wide range of viruses. As part of this work, the research team will develop educational displays related to the bat immunology for public display at the Museum of Texas Tech. Results for the study will also be published in peer-reviewed journals, presented at scientific meetings, and posted to shared data repositories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Researchers supported by this award hypothesize there are consistent differences in the genes involved in the immune response pathways of bats compared to other mammals, such that: a) bats show disproportionate numbers of unique genomic adaptations; b) there is higher expression of immune system genes in bats than in comparable mouse and human tissues, and c) expression of genes involved in coronavirus cell entry in bats differs in RNA profile, limiting the extent pathogenesis when compared to humans and mice. To test these hypotheses, the team will analyze genome structure across diverse bats species, and differential expression analysis of different tissues, in the context of viral tropism and immune response. Resulting data will inform researchers and clinicians as they anticipate and treat these respiratory syndromes. This RAPID award is made by the Physiological and Structural Systems Cluster in the BIO Division of Integrative Organismal Systems, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032006</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Ray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.4.ray@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8068341677</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box 41035, 349 Admin Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~105116</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
