<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MsRI-EW: Precision Nanoscale Patterning and Characterization – From Cybernetic Proteins to Nanoengineered Quantum Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41932.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41932</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aranya Chakrabortty</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>achakrab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An enormous challenge lies in developing nanoscale patterning methods to combine nanoelectronics with biological systems. Conventional patterning techniques have severe limitations when combining hard and soft materials. For example, electron beam lithography (EBL) can create patterns only a few nanometers in size, but requires sacrificial resists. These resists can be incompatible with biological materials and have environmental and safety concerns. Ice lithography is a novel technique that uses solid condensed gas instead of resist. This technique offers a path to atomically precise manufacturing to create nanophotonic and nanolectronic structures. There is, however, no such infrastructure in the United States. This conference will lay the foundations for a world-unique high precision facility that combines ice lithography with in-situ electron and scanning probe microscopy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of this multidisciplinary workshop is to bring together scientists and researchers from engineering, physics, chemistry, and biology in order to exchange ideas in recent innovations and trends in high resolution (below 5 nm) nanofabrication and characterization techniques. The workshop will highlight the science and technology at the cross-roads of quantum phenomena and bio-inspired materials. The natural self-assembly process, inherent to several classes of bio-inspired materials, has resulted in some of the most intriguing nanostructures. Tailoring the functionality of these structures remains a challenge that requires new processes for nanopatterning and nanofabrication. The workshop will provide a unique platform for researchers in academia and industry for envisioning a path forward towards advancing 3D nanofabrication, additive manufacturing, and nano-electronic devices using ice lithography. Additionally, the workshop will serve as a forum for integrating ideas on the synthesis and nanoscale characterization of functional nanomaterials and devices that seamlessly bridge condensed matter and biology. The workshop will lay the foundation for the establishment of future research infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034637</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gavin</FirstName>
<LastName>King</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gavin King</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kinggm@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5738827560</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000562187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suchismita</FirstName>
<LastName>Guha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suchismita Guha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>guhas@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5738843687</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485997</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mizzou North, Room 501]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153890272</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006326904</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Missouri-Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[422 Physics Bldg.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8615</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Devices and Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~41932</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The major goal of the NSF-ECCS 2064337 award on MsRI-EW: Precision Nanoscale Patterning and Characterization - From Cybernetic Proteins to Nanoengineered Quantum Devices was to establish a platform for exchanging ideas in recent innovations and trends in sub-5 nm nanofabrication and characterization techniques by bringing together scientists and researchers from multidisciplinary areas of Engineering, Physics, Chemistry, and Biology. The workshop was organized over two and a half days (August 5-7, 2020) at the University of Missouri, Columbia (MU). Given the situation due to COVID-19, the workshop was 100% virtual.</p> <p>This workshop included invited presentations by leading scientists from universities, national laboratories and government organizations in the United States and Europe, and aimed to stimulate intellectual and technological exchanges, discussions of ideas and emerging trends, and identification of short- and long-term research issues related to the development of high-resolution nanofabrication and characterization techniques. Additionally, workshop attendees explored the scientific issues and technological challenges in bridging nanoengineered devices and biological systems.&nbsp;</p> <p>Key outcomes of the workshop include the identification of ice lithography as a promising pathway to achieve high resolution patterning on diverse substrate surfaces as well as a lack of infrastructure in the United States designed for and devoted to ice lithography. Ice lithography, which uses amorphous solid phase condensed gases (amorphous ices) as sacrificial resist layers, offers the potential of a robust and generalizable path to atomically precise manufacturing for manipulating matter with sub-5 nm spatial resolution. The workshop provided a forum to discuss the development of US-based ice lithography infrastructure for integrating biological materials research with conventional semiconductor technology. Whereas investments in this arena have recently been made in Europe and in Asia, we are not aware of similar investment in the US. Such an infrastructure could revolutionize functional materials and devices that seamlessly bridge condensed matter and biology.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong>:</p> <p>Over 90 individuals registered for the event, representing nine distinct academic institutions, six national laboratories and government organizations, two research institutes, and two companies. There were 24 invited speakers at the workshop, roughly one third of whom were affiliated with MU and two thirds from institutions across the US and Europe. Many disciplines were represented, including Biology, Biochemistry, Chemical and Biomedical Engineering, Chemistry, Materials Science, Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, and Physics. In addition to geographic and scientific discipline diversity, the group of speakers included five early career scientists as well as eight individuals from underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines.</p> <p>The workshop brought together several postdoctoral scholars, graduate, and undergraduate students from diverse academic backgrounds. Though the workshop was virtual, it was still able to provide opportunities for these individuals to interact with leading researchers from the US and Europe. To lower the barrier for conversation, informal discussions were held in break out rooms throughout the workshop and there was a stand-alone two-hour poster session on the second day of the workshop. This allowed graduate students to showcase their research to an attentive audience. Hence, the workshop provided multiple opportunities for students and early career scientists to interact with international experts in the field on a personal one-to-one basis.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2021<br>      Modified by: Suchismita&nbsp;Guha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2034637/2034637_10680244_1626734282072_MidscaleResearchFlyer--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2034637/2034637_10680244_1626734282072_MidscaleResearchFlyer--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Midscale Research Infrastructure Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2034637/2034637_10680244_1626734282072_MidscaleResearchFlyer--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Midscale Research Infrastructure Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Workshop Poster</div> <div class="imageCredit">Suchi Guha/Gavin King</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Suchismita&nbsp;Guha</div> <div class="imageTitle">Midscale Research Infrastructure Workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  The major goal of the NSF-ECCS 2064337 award on MsRI-EW: Precision Nanoscale Patterning and Characterization - From Cybernetic Proteins to Nanoengineered Quantum Devices was to establish a platform for exchanging ideas in recent innovations and trends in sub-5 nm nanofabrication and characterization techniques by bringing together scientists and researchers from multidisciplinary areas of Engineering, Physics, Chemistry, and Biology. The workshop was organized over two and a half days (August 5-7, 2020) at the University of Missouri, Columbia (MU). Given the situation due to COVID-19, the workshop was 100% virtual.  This workshop included invited presentations by leading scientists from universities, national laboratories and government organizations in the United States and Europe, and aimed to stimulate intellectual and technological exchanges, discussions of ideas and emerging trends, and identification of short- and long-term research issues related to the development of high-resolution nanofabrication and characterization techniques. Additionally, workshop attendees explored the scientific issues and technological challenges in bridging nanoengineered devices and biological systems.   Key outcomes of the workshop include the identification of ice lithography as a promising pathway to achieve high resolution patterning on diverse substrate surfaces as well as a lack of infrastructure in the United States designed for and devoted to ice lithography. Ice lithography, which uses amorphous solid phase condensed gases (amorphous ices) as sacrificial resist layers, offers the potential of a robust and generalizable path to atomically precise manufacturing for manipulating matter with sub-5 nm spatial resolution. The workshop provided a forum to discuss the development of US-based ice lithography infrastructure for integrating biological materials research with conventional semiconductor technology. Whereas investments in this arena have recently been made in Europe and in Asia, we are not aware of similar investment in the US. Such an infrastructure could revolutionize functional materials and devices that seamlessly bridge condensed matter and biology.  Broader Impact:  Over 90 individuals registered for the event, representing nine distinct academic institutions, six national laboratories and government organizations, two research institutes, and two companies. There were 24 invited speakers at the workshop, roughly one third of whom were affiliated with MU and two thirds from institutions across the US and Europe. Many disciplines were represented, including Biology, Biochemistry, Chemical and Biomedical Engineering, Chemistry, Materials Science, Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, and Physics. In addition to geographic and scientific discipline diversity, the group of speakers included five early career scientists as well as eight individuals from underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines.  The workshop brought together several postdoctoral scholars, graduate, and undergraduate students from diverse academic backgrounds. Though the workshop was virtual, it was still able to provide opportunities for these individuals to interact with leading researchers from the US and Europe. To lower the barrier for conversation, informal discussions were held in break out rooms throughout the workshop and there was a stand-alone two-hour poster session on the second day of the workshop. This allowed graduate students to showcase their research to an attentive audience. Hence, the workshop provided multiple opportunities for students and early career scientists to interact with international experts in the field on a personal one-to-one basis.       Last Modified: 07/19/2021       Submitted by: Suchismita Guha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
