<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Supporting Student Development Activities at the International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB2020)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17498.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17498</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924768</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Opportunities to present, discuss and receive feedback on scholarship within a broader community are critical components of student professional development. A doctoral consortium and undergraduate student mentoring program are ways to foster meaningful interchanges between scholars at varying levels and nurture career pathways. With a transition to virtual programming for the 2020 International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB 2020) due to the COVID-19 pandemic, this award supports the incorporation of a doctoral consortium and undergraduate student mentoring program as part of the conference. IJCB combines two major biometrics research conferences, the Biometrics Theory, Applications, and Systems (BTAS) conference and the International Conference on Biometrics (ICB). The combined conference brings together leading computer vision experts presenting on advances in fundamental biometrics techniques, new biometrics algorithms and technologies, analyses of the social impact of biometrics technology, and identity in behavior analysis. The goals of the doctoral consortium are to highlight the work of advanced Ph.D. students and facilitate feedback by senior members of the professional biometrics community. The goal of the undergraduate student mentoring program is to match undergraduate students majoring in STEM areas with faculty and industry professionals for advisement and networking in biometrics. These activities will broaden participation for undergraduate and doctoral students in the conference and the biometrics professional community at large.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IJCB2020 will be held virtually in fall 2020. The doctoral consortium consists of three main components: virtual poster presentations by doctoral participants, individualized feedback by senior members of the community, and breakout sessions on career and professional development topics. The undergraduate student mentoring program supports monthly mentoring sessions in September-December 2020. Student participants and mentors will be recruited through several means, including the conference website, the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) Biometrics Council, and related organization mailing lists and selected through an application process, with participation encouraged by individuals from traditionally underrepresented groups. Mentor matching will be facilitated through the completion of a survey of geographic locations, mentoring preferences, biometrics areas of interest/experience, and interpersonal preferences. Up to ten students will be supported to participate in the doctoral consortium, and up to thirty undergraduate students will be supported to participate in the undergraduate student mentoring program. The project is complemented by a comprehensive evaluation plan to include surveys from mentors and mentees on the strengths, weaknesses, and impacts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2038085</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioannis</FirstName>
<LastName>Kakadiaris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ioannis A Kakadiaris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ioannisk@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137431255</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000095195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susie</FirstName>
<LastName>Gronseth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susie L Gronseth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slgronse@central.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137435036</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000736485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University Of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4800 Calhoun Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~17498</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Two mentoring programs in biometrics, one targeting doctoral students and the second for undergraduate students, were developed and implemented to foster meaningful interchanges between scholars at varying levels and nurture career pathways. A doctoral consortium experience was conducted. The works of advanced doctoral students were highlighted at the 2020 International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB 2020) on September 28, 2020, and feedback by senior researchers and experts in the field was provided. Three months of mentoring followed in October through December 2020 using a two-tiered design in which doctoral students continued mentoring sessions with their senior researcher/expert mentor, and undergraduate students interested in biometrics and related STEM fields were mentored by the doctoral students as well as senior researchers/experts. In total, 11 doctoral students, 17 senior researchers (10 in the Doctoral Consortium program and seven in the Undergraduate program), and 50 undergraduate students participated in the programs. The project activities aimed to broaden participation for undergraduate and doctoral students in the conference and the biometrics professional community at large. Targeted recruitment efforts were conducted to engage participants from underrepresented areas. A third of mentees were female, and there was a wide variation in geographic locations among the participants, with 14 countries represented, including Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Chile, France, Germany, India, Italy, Portugal, Singapore, Slovenia, Spain, and the US.</p> <p>During the project timeframe, over 1,800 interactions were captured between mentors and mentees in the MentorLoop platform across the two programs (&gt;600 in the Doctoral Consortium and &gt;1,200 in the Undergraduate program). About 85% of undergraduate mentees reported having a sense of belonging to a community of learners through their involvement in the mentoring program, and 90% reported that participating in the mentorship program helped broaden their view of biometrics. About 85% of doctoral student participants were affirmative about their assigned mentors guiding their educational and career goals during the program's mentoring sessions. They were similarly positive (85% agreed to strongly agree) that the interactions they had with mentors and other mentees through the program were valuable and helped to broaden their views of biometrics. About 85% of mentors indicated satisfaction with the mentoring relationship that they had with their mentees and similarly reported that the mentorship programs facilitated a sense of belonging to a community of learners.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Ioannis&nbsp;A&nbsp;Kakadiaris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Two mentoring programs in biometrics, one targeting doctoral students and the second for undergraduate students, were developed and implemented to foster meaningful interchanges between scholars at varying levels and nurture career pathways. A doctoral consortium experience was conducted. The works of advanced doctoral students were highlighted at the 2020 International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB 2020) on September 28, 2020, and feedback by senior researchers and experts in the field was provided. Three months of mentoring followed in October through December 2020 using a two-tiered design in which doctoral students continued mentoring sessions with their senior researcher/expert mentor, and undergraduate students interested in biometrics and related STEM fields were mentored by the doctoral students as well as senior researchers/experts. In total, 11 doctoral students, 17 senior researchers (10 in the Doctoral Consortium program and seven in the Undergraduate program), and 50 undergraduate students participated in the programs. The project activities aimed to broaden participation for undergraduate and doctoral students in the conference and the biometrics professional community at large. Targeted recruitment efforts were conducted to engage participants from underrepresented areas. A third of mentees were female, and there was a wide variation in geographic locations among the participants, with 14 countries represented, including Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Chile, France, Germany, India, Italy, Portugal, Singapore, Slovenia, Spain, and the US.  During the project timeframe, over 1,800 interactions were captured between mentors and mentees in the MentorLoop platform across the two programs (&gt;600 in the Doctoral Consortium and &gt;1,200 in the Undergraduate program). About 85% of undergraduate mentees reported having a sense of belonging to a community of learners through their involvement in the mentoring program, and 90% reported that participating in the mentorship program helped broaden their view of biometrics. About 85% of doctoral student participants were affirmative about their assigned mentors guiding their educational and career goals during the program's mentoring sessions. They were similarly positive (85% agreed to strongly agree) that the interactions they had with mentors and other mentees through the program were valuable and helped to broaden their views of biometrics. About 85% of mentors indicated satisfaction with the mentoring relationship that they had with their mentees and similarly reported that the mentorship programs facilitated a sense of belonging to a community of learners.          Last Modified: 03/29/2021       Submitted by: Ioannis A Kakadiaris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
