<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Improving the Post-Flood Financial Resiliency of Low- and Moderate-Income Households</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49658.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49658</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project addresses resiliency to natural disasters from a perspective that is frequently not researched but one that has major human impact - financial resilience.  Prior research has found that low income households suffer disproportionately from disasters and recover less quickly than other residents. Financial resilience—the ability to recover from an economic shock—underpins other aspects of recovery and is a necessary condition for broader urban disaster resilience. Despite this, it is an under-investigated aspect of climate adaptation. While the problem has been identified, actionable research into solutions is scarce. The proposed project is designed to fill this gap. This project's specific objective is to demonstrate that increasing the financial resilience of low and moderate income (LMI) households (both homeowners and renters) in New York City presents an essential element of resilience strategies especially in response to increasing urban flooding risk.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project, across both phases, will be comprised of three inter-related research components: (1) designing a pilot policy intervention; (2) improving disaster financial literacy among households and capacity among city staff; and (3) developing a metric of financial resilience to disasters, especially for LMI households. The work will be a joint effort between the Wharton Risk Center at the University of Pennsylvania, the New York City Mayor’s Office of Resiliency, and the Center for NYC Neighborhoods, as well as other partner researchers. The work will be informed by an advisory board with deep expertise on this challenge. The pilot program will be a public-private partnership to demonstrate the importance of financial resiliency as a complement to other more typically researched approaches - since LMI households tend to have insufficient savings, can be locked out of credit, cannot afford standard insurance, and suffer disproportionately more longer term damage.  Phase 1 of this project will be a period of stakeholder engagement, involving scoring policies against chosen criteria, to identify the most promising solution for piloting in Phase II:  (1) parametric microinsurance, (2) premium reductions for low-cost flood mitigation, (3) a local flood insurance affordability program, (4) community assistance plus a high-deductible NFIP policy, (5) right-sizing insurance coverage, and (6) community-based insurance. The second project component will be developing disaster financial literacy tools and building expertise on this topic among civic partner organizations through specific products and engagement strategies. Prior work has found that increasing financial literacy makes individuals better able to withstand shocks. The third component will develop a metric of financial resilience to disasters for LMI households. This metric will be designed to inform the broader academic literature, which lacks an established approach to measurement of this specific concept, as well as be practically useful to city programs. Constructing the metric will draw on city data, as well as a survey of LMI households. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is in response to Track B - CIVIC Innovation Challenge - Resilience to Natural Disasters a collaboration with NSF and the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Kousky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carolyn M Kousky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ckousky@wharton.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2155730515</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539760</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wharton Risk Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191043236</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3819 Chsetnut Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49658</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Flooding is the costliest natural disaster in the United States and climate changes are now escalating flood risk is many communities?including New York City. Prior research has found that low income households suffer disproportionately from disasters and recover less quickly than more privileged residents. Yet, there are significant gaps in our current financial recovery programs and policies when it comes to the specific needs of low and moderate income (LMI) households.&nbsp;</p> <p>This was a Stage 1 Civic Innovations project. Our broad objective is to increase the financial resilience of LMI households in New York City to escalating flood risk.&nbsp; Stage 1 was a collaboration between the Wharton Risk Center at the University of Pennsylvania, the New York City Mayor?s Office of Climate Resiliency (MOCR), and the Center for New York City Neighborhoods (CNYCN). It also involved a representative from the NYC Office of Management and Budget and an advisory board of subject matter experts.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The team used Stage 1 as an idea accelerator to examine half a dozen innovative, inclusive insurance interventions and to identify which would be most impactful, implementable, and sustainable.&nbsp; One publication was released during the planning grant period; an issue brief summarizing these policy options for harnessing risk transfer to help low- and moderate-income households with disaster recovery.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> This publication is available as a resource to help other local governments and community service organizations beyond NYC harness these tools. Through an intensive process involving more than 30 semi-structured expert interviews, exploratory analyses, stakeholder engagement, and consultation with our advisory board, the team evaluated the policy proposals, along with several hybrid options and other suggestions raised during the stakeholder process. Each proposal was assessed using the following criteria: effectiveness, feasibility, cost, sustainability over time, administrative burden, partner willingness, and interaction with existing city policies.</p> <p>From this process, the team chose two pilots for Stage 2.&nbsp; The key pilot would be the purchase, by CNYCN, of a parametric flood insurance policy designed to rapidly provide emergency cash grants to LMI households in the event of a flood. In addition, research and development would be undertaken on parametric flood policies that community development finance institutions could provide to protect LMI borrowers.&nbsp;</p> <p>The team?s Stage 1 expert engagement and exploratory analyses also clarified existing gaps in the academic literature, enabling the team to refine their research goals for Stage 2.&nbsp; It became clear that the serious challenges that delays in receiving funds pose for the recovery of LMI households need to be documented systematically by researchers in a manner that can guide policy interventions. Secondly, in order to motivate and sustain more public sector financial support for insurance-based approaches, there needs to be more documentation of the community-level benefits insurance can provide.&nbsp; Both of these gaps would be filled by the project?s proposed Stage 2 research activities.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the Stage 1 stakeholder engagements, the team identified specific capacity-building and literacy tools that would support the proposed innovative insurance pilots. Instead of trying to reach households directly, the team would have a greater impact with a ?train the trainers? approach, leading to capacity building for housing advisors in Stage 2 in order to build on existing outreach networks to households. Additionally, Stage 1 validated the need for Stage 2 to build a risk transfer community of practice that would enable members to engage across sectors in forming new solutions and collaborations.&nbsp; Additionally, a full replicability study as part of Stage 2 would provide important insights for other communities across the country.</p> <p>Finally, the Stage 1 project provided the opportunity for one graduate student to contribute to the project, helping to train the next generation of policy-focused researchers.&nbsp;</p> <p>The final output of Stage 1 was the Stage 2 proposal.&nbsp; This proposal has four interrelated objectives, all developed, as discussed in Stage 1: (1) developing and deploying innovative, inclusive insurance pilots, (2) creating a community of practice that harnesses risk transfer for social recovery goals, (3) increasing the literacy and capacity of all partners, and (4) linking research to actionable change.&nbsp;</p> <div><br />  <hr size="1" /> <div> <p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> Kousky, C. and Wiley, H. (2021). Improving the Post-Flood Financial Resilience of Lower-Income Households through Insurance. Wharton Risk Center Issue Brief: January.</p> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2021<br>      Modified by: Carolyn&nbsp;M&nbsp;Kousky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Flooding is the costliest natural disaster in the United States and climate changes are now escalating flood risk is many communities?including New York City. Prior research has found that low income households suffer disproportionately from disasters and recover less quickly than more privileged residents. Yet, there are significant gaps in our current financial recovery programs and policies when it comes to the specific needs of low and moderate income (LMI) households.   This was a Stage 1 Civic Innovations project. Our broad objective is to increase the financial resilience of LMI households in New York City to escalating flood risk.  Stage 1 was a collaboration between the Wharton Risk Center at the University of Pennsylvania, the New York City Mayor?s Office of Climate Resiliency (MOCR), and the Center for New York City Neighborhoods (CNYCN). It also involved a representative from the NYC Office of Management and Budget and an advisory board of subject matter experts.    The team used Stage 1 as an idea accelerator to examine half a dozen innovative, inclusive insurance interventions and to identify which would be most impactful, implementable, and sustainable.  One publication was released during the planning grant period; an issue brief summarizing these policy options for harnessing risk transfer to help low- and moderate-income households with disaster recovery.[1] This publication is available as a resource to help other local governments and community service organizations beyond NYC harness these tools. Through an intensive process involving more than 30 semi-structured expert interviews, exploratory analyses, stakeholder engagement, and consultation with our advisory board, the team evaluated the policy proposals, along with several hybrid options and other suggestions raised during the stakeholder process. Each proposal was assessed using the following criteria: effectiveness, feasibility, cost, sustainability over time, administrative burden, partner willingness, and interaction with existing city policies.  From this process, the team chose two pilots for Stage 2.  The key pilot would be the purchase, by CNYCN, of a parametric flood insurance policy designed to rapidly provide emergency cash grants to LMI households in the event of a flood. In addition, research and development would be undertaken on parametric flood policies that community development finance institutions could provide to protect LMI borrowers.   The team?s Stage 1 expert engagement and exploratory analyses also clarified existing gaps in the academic literature, enabling the team to refine their research goals for Stage 2.  It became clear that the serious challenges that delays in receiving funds pose for the recovery of LMI households need to be documented systematically by researchers in a manner that can guide policy interventions. Secondly, in order to motivate and sustain more public sector financial support for insurance-based approaches, there needs to be more documentation of the community-level benefits insurance can provide.  Both of these gaps would be filled by the project?s proposed Stage 2 research activities.   During the Stage 1 stakeholder engagements, the team identified specific capacity-building and literacy tools that would support the proposed innovative insurance pilots. Instead of trying to reach households directly, the team would have a greater impact with a ?train the trainers? approach, leading to capacity building for housing advisors in Stage 2 in order to build on existing outreach networks to households. Additionally, Stage 1 validated the need for Stage 2 to build a risk transfer community of practice that would enable members to engage across sectors in forming new solutions and collaborations.  Additionally, a full replicability study as part of Stage 2 would provide important insights for other communities across the country.  Finally, the Stage 1 project provided the opportunity for one graduate student to contribute to the project, helping to train the next generation of policy-focused researchers.   The final output of Stage 1 was the Stage 2 proposal.  This proposal has four interrelated objectives, all developed, as discussed in Stage 1: (1) developing and deploying innovative, inclusive insurance pilots, (2) creating a community of practice that harnesses risk transfer for social recovery goals, (3) increasing the literacy and capacity of all partners, and (4) linking research to actionable change.        [1] Kousky, C. and Wiley, H. (2021). Improving the Post-Flood Financial Resilience of Lower-Income Households through Insurance. Wharton Risk Center Issue Brief: January.         Last Modified: 08/03/2021       Submitted by: Carolyn M Kousky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
