<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Analyzing the Impact of Collaborative Processes on the Performance of Large-Scale Polycentric Environmental Governance Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>426812.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>209806</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The performance of complex environmental governance can improve through enhanced collaboration. The research team analyzes the system-wide impacts of collaborative water governance efforts that have been implemented over the past 2 decades in an increasingly-threatened watershed: the Colorado River Basin (CRB). Located in the western United States and northern Mexico, the CRB faces sustainability challenges due to both historical water over-allocation and continued aridification from climate change. Demands for water now regularly exceed available supplies, creating negative impacts for the people, economies, and environments that depend on the Colorado River. Although policy making in the CRB has become more participatory in recent decades, addressing the roots of this evolving sustainability crisis requires a deeper transformation in the way the basin’s diverse stakeholders work together to govern the Colorado River. Through an assessment and comparison of past and on-going collaborative water governance processes, this research provides timely lessons for improving governance of the CRB that are also transferrable to other complex socio-environmental systems facing resource scarcity challenges. Additionally, this project engages a diverse team of students in interdisciplinary policy research and supports outreach and education activities for decision makers, water management professionals, and the broader community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through the development of a synergistic research and education program, this CAREER project addresses a knowledge gap at the nexus of two core concepts in environmental governance: polycentricity and collaboration. Polycentric arrangements, characterized by multiple semi-autonomous centers of decision-making authority, are assumed to be well-suited to govern complex socio-environmental systems, in part because they support diverse, adaptable institutions that can be matched to local conditions. A polycentric system’s ability to perform, or achieve desired goals at the system level, however, is often challenged by insufficient coordination among the numerous actors and entities involved at different scales of governance. Collaborative governance processes, which have become nearly ubiquitous in the environmental policy domain over the last 30 years, may help to solve some of these coordination problems by engaging diverse policy actors in consensus-oriented deliberation and decision making around shared problems. Though intuitive, there is a paucity of empirical evidence about the broader impacts of collaborative governance processes on the performance of polycentric systems. Guided by the Ecology of Games Theory, this project integrates longitudinal content analysis of policy documents, elite interviews, and large-n surveys of policy actors to model and assess how various collaborative processes have impacted the structure (i.e. connections among actors and forums) and function (i.e. cooperation, learning, and resource distribution) of the Colorado River Basin’s polycentric water governance system from 2000 to the present. Addressing the evolving sustainability challenges in this basin requires enhanced collaboration among the fragmented entities that govern its water through an intricate set of interlocking federal, state, local, and tribal institutions. Comparing the impacts of different collaborative processes on basin-scale governance over time and in relation to changing social and environmental conditions provides new practical and theoretical insight into approaches for solving complex environmental governance challenges across the globe.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Decision, Risk and Management Sciences Program and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2048133</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Koebele</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Koebele</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ekoebele@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7756827668</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000767471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects / MS 325]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>146515460</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~209806</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
