<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Temporally Uniform Grid Convergence of Discrete Approximations and Numerical Simulations in the Problems of Wave Propagation over Unbounded Domains</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>94989.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>94989</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Two major well-recognized difficulties in numerical simulation of waves&lt;br/&gt;propagating over unbounded domains are the accumulation of error during &lt;br/&gt;long time intervals and necessity to truncate the domain and subsequently &lt;br/&gt;set the artificial boundary conditions (ABCs) at the external artificial&lt;br/&gt;boundary. These two issues turn out to be closely related. In the previous&lt;br/&gt;work of the PI with collaborators that has been done in the framework of&lt;br/&gt;the scalar wave equation, we have used the inherently three-dimensional &lt;br/&gt;phenomenon of lacunae and developed a methodology that modifies any &lt;br/&gt;appropriate discrete scheme so that the long-term error buildup is fully &lt;br/&gt;eliminated while all of the original properties of the scheme (e.g., order &lt;br/&gt;of accuracy) are preserved. Moreover, the procedure allows one to replace &lt;br/&gt;the original infinite domain by a finite computational domain, which leads &lt;br/&gt;to obtaining highly accurate non-local unsteady ABCs. These ABCs are built &lt;br/&gt;directly for the discrete formulation of the problem, their temporal non-&lt;br/&gt;locality is fixed and limited, and they possess full geometric universality. &lt;br/&gt;The key objective of the proposed project is to extend the aforementioned &lt;br/&gt;methodology to wave-type models of practical interest, in particular, the &lt;br/&gt;Maxwell's equations (electromagnetic waves) and the linearized Euler's and &lt;br/&gt;full-potential equations (acoustic waves). The attainability of this goal &lt;br/&gt;is accounted for by the fact that the solutions to these equations have &lt;br/&gt;sharp aft fronts of the waves (manifestation of lacunae), which is the &lt;br/&gt;exact same behavior as displayed by the solutions to the wave equation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Numerical simulation of waves on unbounded domains has numerous applications &lt;br/&gt;that range from scattering of electromagnetic waves from aircraft and ground &lt;br/&gt;vehicles (radar technology) to antenna design to calculation of the acoustic&lt;br/&gt;fields produced by the airframe and airplane's jet engines for the purpose of &lt;br/&gt;reducing the noise levels around airports, as well as inside the passenger &lt;br/&gt;compartments. The results that we expect to obtain are going to benefit the &lt;br/&gt;foregoing applied areas. Indeed, we anticipate the creation of a universal &lt;br/&gt;framework that would allow one to modify a wide class of already existing and &lt;br/&gt;proven methods so that to enable two additional crucial capabilities -- long-&lt;br/&gt;term integration and accurate computation of infinite-domain wave fields on &lt;br/&gt;truncated domains. Besides, as the proposed research unfolds, it will &lt;br/&gt;necessarily include communication and collaboration with physicists and &lt;br/&gt;engineers, as well as preparation of course materials and training young &lt;br/&gt;researchers.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0107146</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Semyon</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsynkov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Semyon V Tsynkov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tsynkov@math.ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195151877</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243099</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2>Admin. III, STE 240</StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0101</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2001~94989</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
