<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Center on Materials and Devices for Information Technology Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18350001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>36331318</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070004</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Science and Technology Center on Materials and Devices for Information Technology Research, University of Washington, Seattle is a multi-disciplinary and multi-institutional activity designed to support a goal-directed, sustained effort to broadly advance the science and technology of materials, devices and systems for advancing information technology. Center activities involve six universities, University of Washington (UW: lead institution), plus the U. of Arizona (UA), California Institute of Technology (Caltech), U. of Southern California (USC), U. of California at Santa Barbara (UCSB) and Berkeley (UCB). The STC emphasizes vertical integration of knowledge and applications that span the intellectual range in fundamental optoelectronic materials and engineering research from molecules to integrated devices and systems for improved signal generation and detection and for improved information transport, processing, and storage. Research is divided among four strategic thrust areas: 1) Electro-Optic and All-Optical Materials and Devices; 2) Infrared Organic Light-Emitting Diodes, Amplifiers, and Lasers; 3) Advanced Assembly and Patterning Approaches to Integrated Optics; 4) Theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational activity is planned around three primary elements: 1) Under-represented groups and institutions in the STC including Minority and HBCU partnerships, emphasis on undergraduate participation in research, and an aggressive outreach effort; 2) A vertically integrated program on education in optical science, materials, and devices; 3) Integration of science, engineering, and business education. The Center includes assessment strategies for evaluation of the effectiveness of new approaches in their educational activities which have a strong web based component. The Center aims to create a vertically integrated, web-based, modular resource emphasizing optical science, materials and devices, offering 1) resources for developing courses and for students' independent studies, 2) web-based courses, and 3) an STC-"IT" news-page (with links to industrial websites) describing new technical advances, job opportunities, conferences, professional courses, and academic curricula. The Center has a strong, collaborative program for fostering outreach to and participation by non-center researchers in research activities. Interaction with industry and Federal Laboratories will be implemented at several levels. Projects with early societal impact will be integrated with longer-term projects. For example, development of 3D integrated circuitry, the exploitation of photonic bandgap device structures, and the exploitation of controlled coupling to microresonators will be a theme of both short-term (e.g., electro-optic information processing) and longer-range (e.g., all-optical information processing) impact projects to advance knowledge, understanding, and technology performance in information technology. This center is projected to become a focal point in the U.S. for education of the workforce in the fields of telecommunication and information processing; photonics; and opto-electronics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0120967</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
<LastName>Dalton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Larry R Dalton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dalton@chem.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066165745</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000326503</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2002</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/23/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Reid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip J Reid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>preid@chem.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065436147</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000428228</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1297</Code>
<Text>STC Integrative Partnrshps Adm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7213</Code>
<Text>STC CLASS OF 2002</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9163</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0102</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0103</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2002~3789999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2003~3639999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~3653500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~3640000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~3604000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~4000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~3347820</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~2656000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="STCARBody">This summary highlights the accomplishments of the Center on Materials and Devices for Information Technology Research (CMDITR) from its 2002 inception to sunset in 2013.&nbsp; CMDITR was created to meet the emerging need for new materials and devices in the broad area of information technology.&nbsp; The overall goal of the Center was to create organic-based photonic materials and devices that in comparison to existing materials would result in faster information transfer, lower power consumption, better chip-scale integration, improved manufacturing flexibility, at a reduced cost. The decision to focus on organic and hybrid materials was predicated on the conviction that through a combination of theory, synthesis, and material characterization one could produce fundamentally new materials that would outperform existing technologies. In addition to advances in information technology, the Center was charged with the development of new educational tools and recruitment strategies designed to prepare a broad and talented workforce to place the United States at the front of the emerging area of information technology. During the Center&rsquo;s existence roughly 50 investigators, 300 graduate students, and 120 postdoctoral scholars spread over nine institutions participated in CMDITR. With regards to knowledge transfer, 1450 peer-reviewed publications were produced, and seven startup companies were created based on the intellectual property created by the Center.&nbsp; This intellectual property includes over 300 invention disclosures and 350 national and international patents and patent applications.&nbsp;</p> <p class="STCARBody">&nbsp;</p> <p class="STCARBody">In addition to the research and technology accomplishments, CMDITR played a central role in the development and implementation of a variety of educational and diversity programs at participating institutions.&nbsp; For example, the Center played a seminal role in the creation of Entrepreneur Certificate programs in the School of Business at University of Washington.&nbsp; Thousands of K-12 and college students participated in outreach and educational opportunities created by CMDITR, with some of these activities becoming national models by which to encouraging students to pursue careers in science and technology. In the areas of education and diversity enhancement, CMDITR partnered with Norfolk State University (NSU) to assist in the creation of their Materials Science and Engineering Ph.D. program, and with the National GEM consortium to increase the number of underrepresented minority science and engineering students that participate in STCs and advanced degree programs. CMDITR has also played an important role in promoting faculty and graduate student diversity.&nbsp; The Center&rsquo;s knowledge transfer program was remarkably successful, spinning off new companies (such as LumoFlex LLC, Soluxra, and TIPD) and developing strong ties with established electronics (e.g. Intel) and chemical companies (e.g. Solvay).&nbsp; These partnerships provided effective venues by which to transition CMDITR-developed technology into the commercial sector.&nbsp; CMDITR educational programs evolved to place greater emphasis on undergraduate and graduate education in order to focus our efforts on training students in science and engineering, but also providing these students with extensive exposure to ethics, diversity, and business development. &nbsp;CMDITR also instituted new professional development programs to prepare students for the transition from academia to the workplace. The legacy of CMDITR is found in the variety of new research centers created at partner institutions, many of which are housed in new buildings created to support the research, educational, and diversity efforts pioneered by the Center.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2013<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This summary highlights the accomplishments of the Center on Materials and Devices for Information Technology Research (CMDITR) from its 2002 inception to sunset in 2013.  CMDITR was created to meet the emerging need for new materials and devices in the broad area of information technology.  The overall goal of the Center was to create organic-based photonic materials and devices that in comparison to existing materials would result in faster information transfer, lower power consumption, better chip-scale integration, improved manufacturing flexibility, at a reduced cost. The decision to focus on organic and hybrid materials was predicated on the conviction that through a combination of theory, synthesis, and material characterization one could produce fundamentally new materials that would outperform existing technologies. In addition to advances in information technology, the Center was charged with the development of new educational tools and recruitment strategies designed to prepare a broad and talented workforce to place the United States at the front of the emerging area of information technology. During the CenterÆs existence roughly 50 investigators, 300 graduate students, and 120 postdoctoral scholars spread over nine institutions participated in CMDITR. With regards to knowledge transfer, 1450 peer-reviewed publications were produced, and seven startup companies were created based on the intellectual property created by the Center.  This intellectual property includes over 300 invention disclosures and 350 national and international patents and patent applications.    In addition to the research and technology accomplishments, CMDITR played a central role in the development and implementation of a variety of educational and diversity programs at participating institutions.  For example, the Center played a seminal role in the creation of Entrepreneur Certificate programs in the School of Business at University of Washington.  Thousands of K-12 and college students participated in outreach and educational opportunities created by CMDITR, with some of these activities becoming national models by which to encouraging students to pursue careers in science and technology. In the areas of education and diversity enhancement, CMDITR partnered with Norfolk State University (NSU) to assist in the creation of their Materials Science and Engineering Ph.D. program, and with the National GEM consortium to increase the number of underrepresented minority science and engineering students that participate in STCs and advanced degree programs. CMDITR has also played an important role in promoting faculty and graduate student diversity.  The CenterÆs knowledge transfer program was remarkably successful, spinning off new companies (such as LumoFlex LLC, Soluxra, and TIPD) and developing strong ties with established electronics (e.g. Intel) and chemical companies (e.g. Solvay).  These partnerships provided effective venues by which to transition CMDITR-developed technology into the commercial sector.  CMDITR educational programs evolved to place greater emphasis on undergraduate and graduate education in order to focus our efforts on training students in science and engineering, but also providing these students with extensive exposure to ethics, diversity, and business development.  CMDITR also instituted new professional development programs to prepare students for the transition from academia to the workplace. The legacy of CMDITR is found in the variety of new research centers created at partner institutions, many of which are housed in new buildings created to support the research, educational, and diversity efforts pioneered by the Center.          Last Modified: 09/13/2013       Submitted by: Philip J Reid]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
