<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>K-Trivial Varieties - Degenerations, Automorphisms, and Periods</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>319996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>319996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Algebraic geometry is concerned with the study of algebraic varieties, that is geometric objects defined by polynomial equations. Such objects are ubiquitous in mathematics, and are relevant to a variety of real world applications ranging from cryptography, to computational biology, to models of the universe in physics. Indeed, the Calabi-Yau threefolds, a special class of algebraic varieties, are abstract representations of the shape of the universe in string theory. A very consequential, wide-open question regarding the Calabi-Yau threefolds is the existence of finitely many types of such objects. This proposal is concerned with the study of Calabi-Yau threefolds and of a related, wider class of algebraic varieties, the so-called K-trivial varieties. A number of questions ranging from the above-mentioned finiteness question to more tangible questions will be investigated. This study will involve a number of the PI’s graduate students and postdocs. Some additional research and outreach activities related to the subject are also planned. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study of K-trivial varieties, that is algebraic varieties with trivial canonical class, is a central subject in algebraic geometry. The proposed projects will focus on two main classes of K-trivial varieties:  hyper-Kaehler manifolds and  Calabi-Yau threefolds. The motivational goals driving this study are the finiteness of deformation types for such objects, and the complementary question of constructing new deformation classes (especially in the hyper-Kaehler case).  Intermediate steps towards these challenging objectives include questions regarding the automorphism groups, that is the symmetries of such objects; the deformations and degenerations, that is breaking up the K-trivial varieties into simpler, more manageable pieces; and the fibrations of K-trivial varieties (especially Lagrangian fibrations for hyper-Kaehler manifolds), that is constructing such varieties from lower dimensional objects.  A main tool in this investigation is Hodge theory, and the associated period maps.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2101640</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Radu</FirstName>
<LastName>Laza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Radu Laza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>radu.laza@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316324506</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179153</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117943651</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~319996</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
