<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Mineral-associated organic matter: an overlooked source and mediator of bioavailable nitrogen</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>374590.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404592</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kendra McLauchlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmclauch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922217</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Plants need nitrogen (N) to survive, but it remains a mystery exactly where, when, and how plants acquire enough N from the soil. This N dilemma limits productivity and leads to challenges in predicting and managing N cycling in natural and managed systems. This project examines a new, more holistic perspective on the terrestrial N cycle that encompasses multiple sources of N from the soil. The research focuses on the previously overlooked role of mineral-associated organic matter (MAOM) as a potential major driver of N supply to plants. Long-standing theories consider MAOM to be largely inaccessible to plants and microbes, but emerging evidence highlights the need to re-examine this wholesale classification. This work examines the potential N-supplying capacity of MAOM in the zone of soil surrounding roots, a critical nutrient hotspot. Ultimately, the results provide new insights into the role of MAOM as a mediator of bioavailable N, which will challenge our fundamental understanding of the processes that regulate soil N cycling in terrestrial ecosystems. The work involves participation in a program at Oklahoma State University, which aims to increase the participation of under-represented populations in STEM disciplines. The project also supports a collaboration with the Oklahoma Conservation Commission to develop a student-led workshop and video series on soil biogeochemistry with specific relevance to soil organic matter and MAOM management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching objective is to quantify and characterize the intrinsic and plant-mediated capacity of MAOM to supply bioavailable N. The guiding hypothesis emphasizes the dependence of MAOM-N supply on the intrinsic physical-chemical properties of MAOM, the bioavailability of MAOM relative to other forms of soil organic matter, and plant-microbial mechanisms that can facilitate the mobilization of N from MAOM. The project pursues the following objectives: 1) Examine edaphic factors regulating plant and microbial access to MAOM-N; 2) Identify mechanisms driving MAOM-N mobilization; 3) Assess feedbacks between plant investment in belowground carbon and MAOM-N mobilization. The study assesses soils varying in geochemical properties using laboratory and greenhouse experiments. Experimental manipulations combined with stable isotope tracing allow for the tracing of MAOM-derived N into bioavailable pools, as well as uptake by microbes and plants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2103187</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Jilling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Jilling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrea.jilling@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4057442679</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000818152</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049987720</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>740786019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[368 Ag Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7381</Code>
<Text>Ecosystem Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CL10</Code>
<Text>CLB-Career Life Balance</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~374590</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~30002</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
