<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: The Integrity of Mail Voting</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120283.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120283</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Given the increase use of vote by mail (VBM) due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the investigators focus on mail-in voters' experience with how they seek, obtain, complete, return and have their mail ballots counted. They examine citizens' perceptions about the integrity of elections using VBM by assessing concerns about variation in the institutional structures of VBM, the secrecy of VBM the process, and the coercion that VBM voters may face from their peer group. The investigators use a state-centric survey design that includes an oversample in 10 states that have a mixture of VBM systems. The oversample is important and gives additional statistical power and leverage about state election administration and laws. The sample consist of only registered voters who report voting by mail in the 2020 election. Surveys are solicited online using Qualtrics software. E-mail addresses for registered voters by state will be purchased from L2. The investigators completed 200 online surveys with mail voters in 40 states, and 1,000 with mail voters in 10 states, along with 100 in-person voters in each these states, for a total sample of 23,000. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research provides a baseline for concerns about voter integrity related to mail balloting. Furthermore, it establishes whether alternative mail voting systems differ in terms of when, where, and with whom mail ballots are completed and returned. This project should inform scholars and policy makers in several areas of VBM policy administration. Findings from the study are also valuable in increasing public confidence in VBM election procedures. The research involves undergraduate researchers at all three campuses of the collaborative study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2105671</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Stein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert M Stein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stein@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133482795</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148052</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>120Y</Code>
<Text>AIB-Acctble Institutions&amp;Behav</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~120283</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Mail Voting in the 2020 Election</span></p> <p>The 2020 Presidential election produced the highest voter turnout in over 100 years.&nbsp; This occurred despite the first worldwide pandemic in a hundred years and an unprecedented attack on the institution of mail assisted voting by an incumbent President and his party.</p> <p>In the face of the COVID-19 pandemic, states and local jurisdictions sought out ways to protect voters and poll workers from contracting and spreading the virus during the 2020 election.&nbsp; In addition to encouraging social distancing and the wearing of facemasks, many states and voters took up mail voting as means of avoiding in-person contact and exposure to the virus.&nbsp;</p> <p>In 2020, 11 states expanded voter opportunities to cast a mail ballot (NCSL 2020).&nbsp; An estimated 46% of voters cast a mail ballot in 2020, up from 21% in 2016 (CPS 2020; 2016).&nbsp; The increase in mail voting occurred despite President Trump&rsquo;s persistent claims that &ldquo;mail-in ballots will lead to massive electoral fraud and a rigged 2020 election.&rdquo;&nbsp; How did fear from COVID-19, Republican partisan resistance to mail voting and states&rsquo; efforts to protect voters and poll workers shape mail voting in the 2020?</p> <p>We address four questions about mail voting in the 2020 election.&nbsp; Who voted by mail in 2020 and why? Who switched to mail voting from another mode of voting in 2020 and why?&nbsp; What were the experiences of mail voters in the 2020 election, and who is likely to continue voting by mail in the future and why?&nbsp;</p> <p>Drawing on a national post-election survey of 2020 voters, we identify first time mail voters and continuing mail voters in states with different and new opportunities for mail voting.&nbsp; Our sample of all 2020 voters is sufficiently granular (N=~10K mail voters) to distinguish between the experiences of mail-in voters in states with different types of postal voting, threats from COVID-19 and partisan preferences.</p> <p>Differences among partisans voting by mail skewed in the 2020 election, with a significantly greater proportion of Democrats (68%) reporting they voted by mail than Republicans (35%). &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Among Biden supporters, 78% cited fear of contracting COVID-19 as a reason for voting for mail.&nbsp; Only 16% of Trump supporters cited COVID-19 as a reason for voting by mail.&nbsp; States that adopted no-excuse mail voting for the 2020 election experienced nearly the same rate of voting by mail (33%) as those states that continued to require an excuse to vote by mail (35%).&nbsp;&nbsp; .</p> <p>Sixty-four percent of first-time mail voters cited fear from contracting COVID-19 as a reason for voting by mail in 2020.&nbsp; Among all mail voters in 2020, 45% reported choosing to vote by mail because of the fear of contracting or spreading the virus.&nbsp; Among persons who previously voted by mail only 35% reported COVID-19 as reason for voting by mail in 2020. &nbsp;</p> <p>The highest rated mode of voting in 2020 was mail voting. Sixty-nine percent of mail voters rated their voting experience as excellent, compared to 57% of early in-person voters and 54% of Election Day votes.&nbsp; Nearly two-thirds of both first-time mail voters (62%) and continuing mail voters (63%) rated their voting experience in 2020 as excellent.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Partisanship is strongly related to voter confidence by mode of voting.&nbsp; Among Trump voters who voted by mail only 39% were very confident their ballot was counted as they intended.&nbsp; Among Biden supporters, 91% of mail voters were very confident their ballot counted as they intended.&nbsp;</p> <p>Partisanship is a strong correlate of 2020 mail voters&rsquo; intentions to vote by mail in future elections.&nbsp; Among Trump supporters who voted by mail in 2020 only 21% of first-time mail voters and 62% of previous mail voters reported they would be very likely to vote by mail in future elections.&nbsp; Among Biden supporters 60% of first-time mail voters and 90% of previous mail voters reported they would be very likely to vote by mail in future elections.&nbsp;</p> <p>The future of mail in voting is likely to be determined by a constellation of factors that are in tension with each other.&nbsp; Voters&rsquo; fear from public health threats e.g., COVID-19, partisan concerns with the integrity of mail voting and state laws regulating mail voting have opposing and variable effects on voters&rsquo; intention and ability to cast a mail ballot.&nbsp; All three conditions are subject to change on the near term.&nbsp; Moreover, how these factors interact to influence mail voting is unclear and the subject of future investigations.&nbsp; Fear from public health threats would seem less likely to shape future mail voting, while partisan challenges to voting by mail and state laws regulating voting by mail remains salient influences on the incidence of mail voting.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;M&nbsp;Stein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Mail Voting in the 2020 Election  The 2020 Presidential election produced the highest voter turnout in over 100 years.  This occurred despite the first worldwide pandemic in a hundred years and an unprecedented attack on the institution of mail assisted voting by an incumbent President and his party.  In the face of the COVID-19 pandemic, states and local jurisdictions sought out ways to protect voters and poll workers from contracting and spreading the virus during the 2020 election.  In addition to encouraging social distancing and the wearing of facemasks, many states and voters took up mail voting as means of avoiding in-person contact and exposure to the virus.   In 2020, 11 states expanded voter opportunities to cast a mail ballot (NCSL 2020).  An estimated 46% of voters cast a mail ballot in 2020, up from 21% in 2016 (CPS 2020; 2016).  The increase in mail voting occurred despite President Trump’s persistent claims that "mail-in ballots will lead to massive electoral fraud and a rigged 2020 election."  How did fear from COVID-19, Republican partisan resistance to mail voting and states’ efforts to protect voters and poll workers shape mail voting in the 2020?  We address four questions about mail voting in the 2020 election.  Who voted by mail in 2020 and why? Who switched to mail voting from another mode of voting in 2020 and why?  What were the experiences of mail voters in the 2020 election, and who is likely to continue voting by mail in the future and why?   Drawing on a national post-election survey of 2020 voters, we identify first time mail voters and continuing mail voters in states with different and new opportunities for mail voting.  Our sample of all 2020 voters is sufficiently granular (N=~10K mail voters) to distinguish between the experiences of mail-in voters in states with different types of postal voting, threats from COVID-19 and partisan preferences.  Differences among partisans voting by mail skewed in the 2020 election, with a significantly greater proportion of Democrats (68%) reporting they voted by mail than Republicans (35%).     Among Biden supporters, 78% cited fear of contracting COVID-19 as a reason for voting for mail.  Only 16% of Trump supporters cited COVID-19 as a reason for voting by mail.  States that adopted no-excuse mail voting for the 2020 election experienced nearly the same rate of voting by mail (33%) as those states that continued to require an excuse to vote by mail (35%).   .  Sixty-four percent of first-time mail voters cited fear from contracting COVID-19 as a reason for voting by mail in 2020.  Among all mail voters in 2020, 45% reported choosing to vote by mail because of the fear of contracting or spreading the virus.  Among persons who previously voted by mail only 35% reported COVID-19 as reason for voting by mail in 2020.    The highest rated mode of voting in 2020 was mail voting. Sixty-nine percent of mail voters rated their voting experience as excellent, compared to 57% of early in-person voters and 54% of Election Day votes.  Nearly two-thirds of both first-time mail voters (62%) and continuing mail voters (63%) rated their voting experience in 2020 as excellent.     Partisanship is strongly related to voter confidence by mode of voting.  Among Trump voters who voted by mail only 39% were very confident their ballot was counted as they intended.  Among Biden supporters, 91% of mail voters were very confident their ballot counted as they intended.   Partisanship is a strong correlate of 2020 mail voters’ intentions to vote by mail in future elections.  Among Trump supporters who voted by mail in 2020 only 21% of first-time mail voters and 62% of previous mail voters reported they would be very likely to vote by mail in future elections.  Among Biden supporters 60% of first-time mail voters and 90% of previous mail voters reported they would be very likely to vote by mail in future elections.   The future of mail in voting is likely to be determined by a constellation of factors that are in tension with each other.  Voters’ fear from public health threats e.g., COVID-19, partisan concerns with the integrity of mail voting and state laws regulating mail voting have opposing and variable effects on voters’ intention and ability to cast a mail ballot.  All three conditions are subject to change on the near term.  Moreover, how these factors interact to influence mail voting is unclear and the subject of future investigations.  Fear from public health threats would seem less likely to shape future mail voting, while partisan challenges to voting by mail and state laws regulating voting by mail remains salient influences on the incidence of mail voting.       Last Modified: 12/01/2021       Submitted by: Robert M Stein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
