<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Quantum Engineering Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>81204.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>81204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nadia El-Masry</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nelmasry@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924975</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;In order to address the next needed steps in creating a quantum information science, mathematics, engineering, and technology (QISMET) workforce in the engineering disciplines, this workshop will be held, to be attended by representatives of industry, national labs, and the full US university ecosystem from flagship schools to four-year colleges. The workshop will describe the community challenges, explore opportunities to address those challenges, and map out a path forward for near-term progress. The workshop will identify realistic deliverables: &lt;br/&gt;(a) recommendations for creating a quantum engineering minor; and &lt;br/&gt;(b) recommendations for creating a quantum engineering major and/or specialized track within engineering majors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop recommendations will be realizable over the next 2-5 years in most US universities.&lt;br/&gt;Quantum engineering education is required to create future quantum engineers in quantum computing, communications, and sensing. These areas of fundamental science will not become robust technologies without quantum engineering expertise. The workshop will develop a clear vision for quantum engineering education at the undergraduate level and beyond for the U.S. workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The recommendations provided by this workshop on best ways to create a quantum engineering discipline at the undergraduate level will help guide educational development and investment in US universities and government agencies such as NSF. Students reading the web site and/or roadmap paper where these recommendations are presented will have a quick and clear understanding of the scope of quantum engineering and the educational innovation needed to support its development. At the present time, digital quantum computers are often in the press while the quantum workforce education to support their development is mostly not in place. This workshop will help expand the understanding of quantum engineering education and quantum information science more generally to students and professionals from many engineering subfields, to STEM professionals, and to the wider public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2110432</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lincoln</FirstName>
<LastName>Carr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lincoln D Carr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lcarr@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3032733759</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000452928</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE COLORADO SCHOOL OF MINES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado School of Mines]]></Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804011843</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 Illinois St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~81204</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
