<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IUCRC Phase III: Worcester Polytechnic Institute: Center for Resource Recovery and Recycling (CR3)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Crystal Leach</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>crleach@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922667</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Center for Resource Recovery and Recycling, CR3, is a multi-institution IUCRC that focuses on sustainable stewardship of the earth’s material resources. As it enters Phase III, CR3 will build on its Phase I and Phase II accomplishments to advance sustainable technologies that recover, remanufacture, and reuse all types of materials throughout the manufacturing process. These advancements will help reduce energy costs and increase profitability for a variety of industrial sectors, while protecting natural resources and the environment. Materials use in 2020 is approximately 90 Gt globally, and is likely to reach 170 Gt in the next forty years. The manufacturing industry that converts these materials into commodities needs technologies that enable this conversion more efficiently while generating less production waste and consuming less energy. The recycling industry that processes the production and post-consumer wastes needs methods that are cleaner and profitable. Research supporting materials recovery and recyclability is multidisciplinary and must respond to the needs of a multiplicity of commercial stakeholders across the supply chain. CR3 brings two leading universities with expertise in materials science and engineering (Worcester Polytechnic Institute and Colorado School of Mines) together with key constituents in the resource recovery and recycling area to develop comprehensive technology transfer pathways to industry. CR3 research efforts address product manufacturing waste, post-consumer waste, instrumentation, sensors and controls, design for disassembly and conversion of trash to treasure.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary focus of CR3 is on key sectors of iron and steel, non-ferrous structural metals, light metals, rare-earths, energy materials and photovoltaic metals, high value refractory metals and electronic materials. Key unmet industrial needs in these sectors are driving the following research thrusts for the Center: (a) polymeric material remanufacturing and use, (b) environmentally sustainable materials recovery, (c) reduction of the carbon and water footprint, (d) low-cost alternatives to current materials, and (e) natural resource depletion. CR3's research projects utilize core and supporting technical competencies across both academic sites. Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI) brings competencies to the Center that include thermodynamic and kinetic modeling, hydrometallurgy and electrometallurgy, physical metallurgy and inorganic chemistry.  Competencies also include physical, chemical, and mechanical property testing, and additive manufacturing, as well as sensor and measurement device application development. WPI  brings competencies in life-cycle assessment (LCA) and environmental impact assessments, commercial feasibility assessments, robotics, sorting technology, and industry 4.0 concepts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2113498</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brajendra</FirstName>
<LastName>Mishra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brajendra Mishra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmishra@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5088315711</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384059</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Powell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>IV</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam C Powell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>acpowell@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5088316898</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yan</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yan Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yanwang@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5088315453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000588058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041508581</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WORCESTER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041508581</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WORCESTER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE]]></Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016092280</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 INSTITUTE ROAD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
