<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AccelNet-Implementation: FLUXNET Coordination to Understand Ecosystem Function through Continuous Observations of Ecosystem-Atmosphere Interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1983930.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1983930</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claire Hemingway</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chemingw@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927135</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Global ecosystems provide services that sustain society, including providing food, fiber and timber, and water cycle regulation.  An important service is the sequestering of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere, which greatly slows the rate of climate change.  Understanding ecosystem-atmosphere interactions, and the response of these to environmental change, is an urgent challenge.  This AccelNet Implementation Track award will link over ten existing national and international networks focused on continuous observations of ecosystem-atmosphere interactions at over 1000 locations around the world.  The FLUXNET Coordination Project will fill fundamental knowledge gaps in science, engineering, and societal issues associated with ongoing changes in ecosystem function and the related cycling of carbon and water.  FLUXNET is a global network of regional networks, consisting of scientists measuring the exchange of carbon dioxide, water, energy, and other greenhouse gas fluxes between ecosystems and the atmosphere.  This project will develop the next generation of the FLUXNET network of networks to be a self-sustaining global collaboration focused on supporting early career scientists, expanding the diversity of scientists, biomes, and climate regions involved, and empowering international collaboration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the diversity of life on Earth, a full understanding of the role of ecosystems in the Earth system can only be achieved through a network-of-networks approach.  The central goals of the FLUXNET Coordination Project are to provide novel training and exchange opportunities, develop strong international collaborations, and build tools and protocols that ensure continued capacity of FLUXNET to provide continuous observations of ecosystem-atmosphere interactions across the globe.  Such measurements have proven essential for understanding ecosystem function, calibrating space-borne observations, and developing models used to project future climate.  The project will develop data-focused processing protocols and pipelines, as well as people-focused education and exchange opportunities.  Network activities include annual in-person meetings at national and international venues, monthly webinars, workshops and synthesis publications, and student and early-career researcher personnel exchanges.  The project will use creative and transformative approaches to international collaboration and networked science to achieve its goal of building the next generation of FLUXNET to be a self-sustaining flagship of networked global scientific cooperation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Accelerating Research through International Network-to-Network Collaborations (AccelNet) program is designed to accelerate the process of scientific discovery and prepare the next generation of U.S. researchers for multiteam international collaborations. The AccelNet program supports strategic linkages among U.S. research networks and complementary networks abroad that will leverage research and educational resources to tackle grand scientific challenges that require significant coordinated international efforts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Co-funding for this award is provided by the Macrosystems Biology and NEON-Enabled Science Program and the NEON Program in the Directorate for Biological Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2113978</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>davidjpmoore@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206266000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000611902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Trevor</FirstName>
<LastName>Keenan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Trevor Keenan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trevorkeenan@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104865686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000786492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Novick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly A Novick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>knovick@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128550516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000657060</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947203114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[117 Hilgard Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>069Y</Code>
<Text>AccelNet - Accelerating Resear</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5912</Code>
<Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5913</Code>
<Text>BRAZIL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5920</Code>
<Text>ITALY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7561</Code>
<Text>CANADA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1983930</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
