<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IUCRC Phase III: Marquette University: Center for Water Equipment and Policy (WEP)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>87366</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Crystal Leach</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>crleach@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922667</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Clean drinking water and sanitation are economic and policy issues that need to be addressed for sustainable growth of the US economy. A collaboration between University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee and Marquette University, the IUCRC for Water Equipment and Policy (WEP) provides innovative water technologies and processes to promote advancement of the water industry and conducts research to inform water policy makers. During Phase I and II, WEP has completed nearly 100 pre-competitive research projects in four thrust areas: water sensors, novel materials, innovative treatment systems, and water policy research. Through research, the WEP Center has provided innovative products and solutions to address industrial partners’ unmet/underserved needs in point-of-use technologies, emerging contaminants, sustainability, and energy conservation. In Phase III, the WEP Center aims to capitalize on past success, grow center research through new customer discovery, expand the research team through site additions, continuously refine the technology roadmap, explore new frontiers of water science for break-through technologies, and train a talented workforce to meet the nation’s needs in drinking water quality and wastewater management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Marquette University site of WEP is comprised of researchers and facilities to develop the next generation of technologies to treat and protect drinking water and natural waters. On the shores of Lake Michigan in Milwaukee, WI, Marquette University water researchers work with regulators and industry representatives in equipment manufacturing, municipal utility, and chemical production to advance water technology and protect Great Lakes water. Researchers in civil and environmental engineering, electrical engineering, biological sciences, and law/policy collaborate to address contemporary challenges identified by Center members.  WEP also seeks to train the next generation of water technology professionals. Member-driven research to address policy information needs is conducted by the Marquette University Law School's Water Law and Policy Initiative in collaboration with engineers and scientists. Unique resources and capabilities for collaborative research include the Marquette University Water Quality Center, the V. Clayton Lafferty Laboratory for Advanced Microsystems Research, and the Nanoscale Devices Laboratory where work is performed to develop novel processes and sensors for the water industry as well as to train students and postdoctoral researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2113851</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Zitomer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel H Zitomer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.zitomer@mu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142885733</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000209374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brooke Mayer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Brooke.Mayer@marquette.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142882161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000556476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marquette University</Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1881</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046929621</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARQUETTE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006439962</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marquette University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091Z</Code>
<Text>Data Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~42366</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
