<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI-TT: Storing energy in the electric vehicle’s automotive body</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samir M. Iqbal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smiqbal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927529</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Partnerships for Innovation - Technology Translation (PFI-TT) project is the development of a body shell for electric vehicles (EVs) that addresses the range anxiety, i.e., drivers concern about the miles per charge. The proposed project seeks to increase the miles per charge by developing a dual-function carbon fiber composite for the automotive body. The carbon fiber composite will store electrical energy in addition to providing the mechanical strength necessary to function as a structural component. The stored energy achieves enhanced miles per charge, attracting better acceptance for EVs. The increased EV usage imparts a positive impact on the environment. Beyond EVs, the energy-storing carbon composite has potential application as the structural component of space vehicles. The energy-storing capability may also be used in wearable electronic devices. Finally, the project develops entrepreneurial and leadership skills for participating undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project increases the miles per charge of electric vehicles (EVs) by storing energy in their automotive body shell in addition to the existing batteries. Currently, there is a significant effort to manufacture more EVs to reduce global warming and make the US less dependent on foreign fuel. A major limitation to achieving the widespread use of EVs is the low miles per charge. The objective of the research is to make a 0.5 m2 dual-function carbon composite. The highly enhanced energy storage ability of the carbon composite is obtained by judiciously engineering carbon fibers.  This project provides the ability to make an energy-storing composite with aqueous semisolid gel electrolytes. The structural composites will be safe from fire hazards in case of an accident, unlike organic electrolyte-based lithium-ion batteries. As carbon composites are already being employed in vehicles as lightweight structural components, vehicle manufacturers may be able to easily adopt a dual-function carbon composite as the body shell.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2122779</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Svetlana</FirstName>
<LastName>Shtrom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Svetlana S Shtrom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>svetlana.shtrom@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078235150</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000833913</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayan</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jayan Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Jayan.Thomas@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078821120</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Florida Board of Trustees]]></Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12424 Research Pkwy, Suite 400]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>POWER, CONTROLS &amp; ADAPTIVE NET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~250000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
