<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Response to the 2021 Earthquake Swarm and Volcanic Eruption in Reykjanes, Iceland</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>78471.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>78471</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dennis Geist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dgeist@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924361</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is exceptionally difficult to capture the early phases of an eruption, especially in a remote area. The Fagradaldsfjall eruption in Iceland is unusual in that it was preceded by an earthquake swarm that lasted for nearly a month. This provided the opportunity to investigate the potential eruption site, collect high resolution (centimeter-scale) preliminary DEMs of the most probable eruption sites, generate associated DEMs and orthomosaics using UAS, as well as obtain the necessary permissions to access the area in the event of the eruption. Consequently, when the eruption began, its opening phase and development since have been monitored. Pre-eruption surveys of valleys that are most likely to become lava flow paths are being mapped. Maps are also being constructed of the surface expression of specific seismic events to determine links between surface fracture patterns and earthquake source mechanisms. Active lava emplacement processes are being measured to establish better constraints on effusion rates, lava emplacement dynamics, lava thermo-rheology, and lava cooling. In addition to providing information that will be useful for lava-flow hazards, the project is funding the research of a graduate student.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2021 earthquake swarm on the Reykjanes peninsula has generated &gt;50,000 earthquakes since 21 February and on 3 March tremor was identified, signaling magma movement. In the following days, the magma came within 1 km of the surface and an eruption began at 8:45 pm GMT on March 19 in the hilly Krísuvík region, which is located &lt;50 km southwest of Reykjavík. The proposed effort constitutes an immediate response to the earthquake swarm and eruption to collect data for the scientific community. A Ground-Control Point (GCP) network will be established, including 60 aerial targets located using Differential Global Positioning System (DPGS) measurements and the installation of three meterological stations for continuous environmental measurement. These are needed to establish geodetic control for UAS and traditional aerial surveys as well s constrain environmental conditions, which is vital for thermal remote sensing. Once the GCP is established, Unoccupied Aircraft System (UAS) observations shall be obtained and used to generate 8–16 cm/post digital elevation models (DEMs) and 2–4 cm/pixel orthoimages, depending on local ground elevation. Data are being archived to ensure that GCP information and UAS observations are made freely available to the public via the University of Arizona’s ReDATA system, which is a Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR) archive that enables rapid release of data, with digital object identifiers (DOIs). The research of a graduate student is being funded, and the information will be useful to local authorities for hazard assessment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2131889</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher W Hamilton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hamilton@lpl.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3013053818</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000797816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[888 N Euclid Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~78471</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
