<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Lipid Mass Tags Designed Via Selective Dissociation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>625000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kelsey Cook</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kcook@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927490</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging program in the Division of Chemistry, Xin Yan and her group at Texas A&amp;M University are working to develop novel approaches to characterizing unsaturated lipids (fatty acids/esters) using mass spectrometry. Changes in the concentrations of lipid species in biological systems occur after perturbation by physiological processes, hence knowing the structures and concentrations of lipids is essential to elucidate their roles in physiological and pathological processes. Dr. Yan and her group are developing approaches to allow accurate quantification of multiple unsaturated lipids (including difficult-to-detect non-polar lipids) in a single experiment. The integrated educational plan seeks to amplify the scientific impact by broadening access to chemical education and chemical measurement research including live demos of fun experiments, engagement of students in chemistry open houses, and providing research opportunities for undergraduates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Accurate quantification of a lipid mixture with isomeric resolution has been a long-standing challenge. To address this challenge, a set of isobaric lipid mass tags (LMTs) is being designed to react selectively with lipid double bonds. By designing and tuning the LMT chemistry, diagnostic ions for determining double bond isomers are selectively produced in low energy collision-induced dissociation. Charged mass reporters corresponding to lipids from different samples are released upon higher energy dissociation, thereby enabling accurate quantitation of lipids from multiplexed samples in a single run. The combination of information from the two tandem MS experiments in a single run enables the quantification and identification of unsaturated lipid isomers. Development of LMTs will facilitate future investigations into lipid structure/function relationships. Broader impacts of the educational plan include promoting interest in and broadening access to chemical education and chemical measurement research for all levels of students. Disseminating science through live demos seeks to motivate middle/high school students to appreciate science at an early stage. Providing active engagement in experiments is seen as a good, hands-on approach to encouraging students to consider pursuing careers in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics)-related fields. The innovation X program and research training are expected to provide undergraduate and graduate students with opportunities to work with advanced analytical technologies and develop new strategies for unsolved chemical measurement problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/07/2022</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2145487</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xin Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xyan@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798622142</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000813964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/07/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433255</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3255 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~250000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
