<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CyberCorps Scholarship for Service: Cyber Defense of Intelligent Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3198315.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1043203</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Li Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>liyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922677</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The complexity and capabilities of autonomous systems and automation, ranging from e-voting to unmanned flight, are increasing. In addition, artificial intelligence (AI) plays a significant and growing role in the operation of such critical systems. Protecting these intelligent systems and using AI for cybersecurity and cyber-defense systems requires a workforce with multidisciplinary training and experience. The national demand for such cybersecurity professionals far exceeds the supply; and the demand is particularly critical in government. Moreover, pathways to government positions are less clear to new professionals than more visible opportunities in the commercial sector. This project will provide scholarships to undergraduate and graduate students studying cybersecurity at Oakland University (OU). Recruitment of women and minority students, who are currently underrepresented in the cybersecurity workforce, will be prioritized. OU has a concentration of faculty with expertise in autonomous systems and AI as part of its mission in serving employers in southeastern Michigan, most of whom have a national, if not global, reach. This project will provide students with a visible, competitive pathway to exciting, rewarding careers in serving the United States government in cybersecurity and cyber-defense.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;OU’s cybersecurity program offers undergraduate and graduate students the opportunity to engage in a curriculum with hands-on activities and multidisciplinary courses in information technology, computer science, engineering, management, and ethics. Courses are aligned with the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education (NICE) Workforce Framework. OU’s Center for Cybersecurity brings together seventeen faculty from six departments covering computer science, engineering, mathematics, political science, sociology, social work, and criminal justice. The Center provides an immersive cyber-defense ecosystem for students, including research experiences, projects, clubs, organizations, camps, and a long history of outreach to K-12 students and teachers. Students will complete a project with a faculty and government mentor with activities including security policies, system vulnerabilities and countermeasures, legal and social issues, artificial intelligence in mobile security and wireless security, protecting machine learning algorithms, and security in big data. The program will also include a multi-level advising and mentorship program specifically for cybersecurity in government. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by the CyberCorps® Scholarship for Service (SFS) program, which funds proposals establishing or continuing scholarship programs in cybersecurity and aligns with the U.S. National Cyber Strategy to develop a superior cybersecurity workforce. Following graduation, scholarship recipients are required to work in cybersecurity for a Federal, state, local, or tribal Government organization for the same duration as their scholarship support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2022</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2146280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darrin</FirstName>
<LastName>Hanna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darrin M Hanna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmhanna@oakland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2483702170</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000329144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lunjin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lunjin Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>l2lu@oakland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2483702231</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huirong</FirstName>
<LastName>Fu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huirong Fu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fu@oakland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2483704456</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492046</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amartya</FirstName>
<LastName>Sen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amartya Sen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sen@oakland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3178351932</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000786083</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oakland University</Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<ZipCode>483094401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2483704116</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>530 Wilson Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041808262</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OAKLAND UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041808262</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oakland University]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>483094401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[530 Wilson Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1668</Code>
<Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7254</Code>
<Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~1043203</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
