<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Set Theory and Its Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420395.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420395</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A century ago, there was a movement to put mathematics on a rigorous, unified foundation. Because the notion of a set is among the most primitive in mathematics, it was used as the basic fabric with which to build the more complicated objects of mathematics. Since that time, it has been realized that the properties of infinite sets are themselves quite subtle and defy a complete axiomatization. Moreover, these set-theoretic complexities sometimes manifest themselves in more complex mathematical structures, such as those studied in algebra, analysis, and geometry. The aim of this project is to further develop both our understanding of set-theoretic methods and also how they can be applied to problems arising in fields of mathematics such as algebra, analysis, and topology. While the project involves several lines of investigation, a central theme will be to develop a deeper understanding of the structure of the algebra of all piece-wise linear functions from the unit interval to itself using the lens of transfinite ordinal numbers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first part of the research project involves attempting to prove the following conjecture of Matthew Brin and Mark Sapir: if G is a group of piece-wise linear homeomorphims of the unit interval, then either G is elementary amenable or else G contains an isomorphic copy of Richard Thompson's group F. It is the PI's thesis that not only is this conjecture true, but that it will be a consequence of a much finer analysis of subgroup structure of PLoI, the group of piece-wise linear homeomophisms of the unit interval. This analysis is expected to have a number of other consequences: that the finitely generated subgroups of F are well quasi-ordered by embeddability; that any finitely presented subgroup of PLoI is either abelian or contains a copy of F; that Peano Arithmetic does not prove that F is amenable. Central to the analysis will be the countable transfinite ordinals. The second part of the research project concerns further developing techniques in pure set theory: methods for studying the combinatorics of the second uncountable cardinal via forcing axioms; the role that Jensen's diamond principle plays in the theory of the sets of hereditary cardinality at most aleph1. The project also supports graduate students working in other fields of logic, including computability theory and model theory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1600635</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin T Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>justin@math.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072554185</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148534201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[212 Garden Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~123527</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~164550</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~132318</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The following are the most significant results which were produced during the grant period:<br /><br />A new family of examples of finitely generated elementary subgroups of the group of piecewise linear order preserving permutations of the unit interval.&nbsp; All of these groups embed into Richard Thompson's group F.&nbsp; These groups can easily be described both using visual diagrams and via operations analogous to the arithmetic operations on the ordinals.&nbsp; This family of groups is well ordered by the embeddability relation in ordertype &epsilon;<sub>0</sub>, the first ordinal closed under exponentiation base &omega;.&nbsp; The least upper bound of their elementary amenability classes is &epsilon;<sub>0</sub>.&nbsp; It is conjectured by the PI that any subgroup of F either contains a copy of F or else is embeddable into a group from this family.&nbsp; This would settle a longstanding conjecture of Brin and Sapir.<br /><br />It is consistent with the ZFC axioms of set theory that there is a minimal non-&sigma;-scattered linear order which is not separable and is not Aronszajn.&nbsp; Here a linear order is &sigma;-scattered if it can be covered by countably many subsets which do not contain a copy of the rational line.&nbsp; A non-&sigma;-scattered linear order is minimal if it embeds into all of its non-&sigma;-scattered suborders.&nbsp; Previously it was known that there were additional axioms of set theory (PFA<sup>+</sup>) which allowed for the classification of minimal non-&sigma;-scattered linear orders.&nbsp; These additional axioms, however, implied that all minimal non-&sigma;-scattered linear orders were either separable or Aronszajn.</p> <p>A combinatorial characterization of when a filter of projections on Hilbert space is generic over the inner model L(R).&nbsp; This is the noncommutative analog of a result of Di Prisco and Todorcevic asserting that if there is a supercompact cardinal, then the selective ultrafilters are precisely those filters on the natural numbers which are generic over L(R).</p> <p>The Cech cohomological dimension of the ordinal &omega;<sub>n</sub> is n.&nbsp; The methods of the proof give a generalization of Todorcevic's method of minimal walks which is expected to be fruitful in the study of the ordinals &omega;<sub>n</sub>.</p> <p>There do not exist idempotent means on free binary systems.&nbsp; This refutes a conjecture previously made by the PI which, if verified, would have shown that Thompson's group F is amenable.&nbsp; The proof suggests a revised conjecture which would also imply that F is amenable.<br /><br />The project supported 10 graduate students and 1 postdoctoral fellow<br />working in set theory at Cornell University.&nbsp; It facilitated travel to conferences to present the research from the grant.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/19/2019<br>      Modified by: Justin&nbsp;T&nbsp;Moore</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The following are the most significant results which were produced during the grant period:  A new family of examples of finitely generated elementary subgroups of the group of piecewise linear order preserving permutations of the unit interval.  All of these groups embed into Richard Thompson's group F.  These groups can easily be described both using visual diagrams and via operations analogous to the arithmetic operations on the ordinals.  This family of groups is well ordered by the embeddability relation in ordertype &epsilon;0, the first ordinal closed under exponentiation base &omega;.  The least upper bound of their elementary amenability classes is &epsilon;0.  It is conjectured by the PI that any subgroup of F either contains a copy of F or else is embeddable into a group from this family.  This would settle a longstanding conjecture of Brin and Sapir.  It is consistent with the ZFC axioms of set theory that there is a minimal non-&sigma;-scattered linear order which is not separable and is not Aronszajn.  Here a linear order is &sigma;-scattered if it can be covered by countably many subsets which do not contain a copy of the rational line.  A non-&sigma;-scattered linear order is minimal if it embeds into all of its non-&sigma;-scattered suborders.  Previously it was known that there were additional axioms of set theory (PFA+) which allowed for the classification of minimal non-&sigma;-scattered linear orders.  These additional axioms, however, implied that all minimal non-&sigma;-scattered linear orders were either separable or Aronszajn.  A combinatorial characterization of when a filter of projections on Hilbert space is generic over the inner model L(R).  This is the noncommutative analog of a result of Di Prisco and Todorcevic asserting that if there is a supercompact cardinal, then the selective ultrafilters are precisely those filters on the natural numbers which are generic over L(R).  The Cech cohomological dimension of the ordinal &omega;n is n.  The methods of the proof give a generalization of Todorcevic's method of minimal walks which is expected to be fruitful in the study of the ordinals &omega;n.  There do not exist idempotent means on free binary systems.  This refutes a conjecture previously made by the PI which, if verified, would have shown that Thompson's group F is amenable.  The proof suggests a revised conjecture which would also imply that F is amenable.  The project supported 10 graduate students and 1 postdoctoral fellow working in set theory at Cornell University.  It facilitated travel to conferences to present the research from the grant.       Last Modified: 06/19/2019       Submitted by: Justin T Moore]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
