<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Index Herbariorum Upgrade: A Project to Improve Access to Information about the World's Plant and Fungal Collections Assets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>77284.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>77284</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Scientists document the earth's plant and fungal diversity through dried reference specimens maintained in collections known as herbaria.  There are approximately 2,800 herbaria in the world today, associated with them are approximately 10,000 biodiversity specialists. Index Herbariorum, established in 1935, is a guide to the world's herbaria and their staff. Accurate, comprehensive information about the holdings of the world's herbaria make it easier for scientists to answer questions about the documentation of the world's plant and fungal diversity, namely: How many species are represented in herbaria, and which areas of the earth are the best documented?  Who are the experts in plant identification, and how can these be contacted? Facilitating access to and communication among herbaria will help to maintain the vitality and relevance of these institutions and ensure that they can continue to serve humankind.  Index Herbariorum also serves as a model for how other natural history collections can create an inventory of their members and set up an effective collaborative network.  An enhanced Index Herbariorum will empower countries such as the U.S. to better manage their collection repositories by providing insight into how collection resources and scientific expertise have developed over time, how they may change in the future.  The project also offers a model for communication, coordination, and collaboration between museum institutions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No other type of natural history collection has a resource that approaches Index Herbariorum in its longevity and comprehensiveness. The New York Botanical Garden has maintained this unique resource for the past 41 years. Originally published in book form, the index first became available as an on-line searchable database in 1997.  Since then the database has been available as a read-only, online reference.  Through this project, The New York Botanical Garden will make this already vital resource updateable by the user community, and more easily linked to other online databases. These changes will expand the accuracy, accessibility and sustainability of this resource and make it easier to maintain in the future. The activities that will be carried out to accomplish these goals include: (1) Adjusting the data structure of IH to bring it into compliance with the emerging Natural Collections Description standard and to increase the effectiveness of searching key data, and indicate the status of collection digitization efforts; (2) creating a new user interface that will allow users to input updates to the index that will be vetted then incorporated into the index; (3) seting up APIs (Application Programming Interfaces) to the database so the data can be fed to other applications without human mediation; and (4) informing the user community about the new updating procedures, and mounting a campaign to update 80% of those entries that have not been updated since 2000.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1600051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Thiers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara M Thiers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bthiers@nybg.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7188178622</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Tulig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melissa Tulig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>melissa.tulig@bishopmuseum.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3478216147</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York Botanical Garden</Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<ZipCode>104585126</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7188178840</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2900 Southern Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073250946</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073250946</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York Botanical Garden]]></Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>104585126</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2900 Southern Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~77284</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Scientists document the earth&rsquo;s plant and fungal diversity through dried reference specimens maintained in collections known as herbaria.&nbsp; There are approximately 3000 herbaria in the world today, associated with approximately 13,000 biodiversity specialists. <em>Index Herbariorum</em>, established in 1935, is a guide to the world&rsquo;s herbaria and their staff.&nbsp; No other type of natural history collection has a resource that approaches <em>Index Herbariorum</em> in its longevity and comprehensiveness.&nbsp; The New York Botanical Garden has maintained this unique resource for the past 41 years. Originally published in book form, the index first became available as an on-line searchable database in 1997.&nbsp; Since then the database has been available as a read-only reference.&nbsp; Through this project,&nbsp; The New York Botanical Garden was able to&nbsp; make this already vital resource updateable by user community, and more easily linked to other online databases. We were also able to reach out to all herbaria included in the Index to verify information held in there.&nbsp; All of these changes have&nbsp; expanded the accuracy, accessibility and sustainability of this resource and have made it much easier to maintain in the future.</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em>The activities required to accomplish these goals included: (1) Adjusting the data structure of IH to bring it into compliance with the emerging Natural Collections Description standard, and to increase the effectiveness of searching key data such as the names of important collectors, name of plants and fungi, and geographical place names; (2) Creating a new user interface that will allow users to input updates to the index that will be vetted then incorporated into the index; (3) creating APIs to the database so the data can be fed to other applications without human mediation; (4) Informing the user community about the new updating procedures, and summarizing the status of the world's herbarium in an annual report, available for download from the Index Herbariorum website..</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;<em>Intellectual Merit</em></strong></p> <p>The natural history museum community has a salient need for a model system for keeping track of the members of that community and for facilitating communication within the community and with all users of natural history data. <em>Index Herbariorum</em> has long been a model in its comprehensiveness, accuracy and widespread acceptance as a community standard.&nbsp; With the expansion and enhancements described in this proposal, <em>Index Herbariorum</em> has become a 21st century resource that, if replicated for other types of collections, can be the foundation for unprecedented access to the world&rsquo;s collections holdings.<em>Other herbaria</em> use IH as a source of contact information for herbarium commerce, for forming partnerships, and as a source of expertise for improving their own collections. <em>Scientists</em> use IH to as a source of data and institutional information for their research and for developing partnerships for multi-institutional collaborative projects. IH is used as a standard for identifying herbaria in publications, on permits, and in determining the suitability of an herbarium as a permanent specimen repository.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong><em>&nbsp;B</em></strong><strong><em>roader Impact</em></strong></p> <p>Accurate, comprehensive information about the holdings of the world&rsquo;s herbaria&nbsp; make it easier for scientists to answer questions about the documentation of the world&rsquo;s plant and fungal diversity, namely: How many species are represented in herbaria, and which areas of the earth are the best documented?&nbsp; Who are the experts in plant identification, and how can these be contacted? Facilitating access to and communication among herbaria will help to maintain the vitality and relevance of these institutions and ensure that they can continue to serve humankind.&nbsp; <em>Index Herbariorum</em>&nbsp;serves as a model for how other natural history collections can create an inventory of their members and set up an effective collaborative network.&nbsp; An enhanced <em>Index Herbariorum</em>empowers countries such as the U.S. to better manage their collection repositories by providing insight into how collection resources and scientific expertise have developed over time, how they may change in the future.&nbsp; Two recently graduated&nbsp; college undergraduate interns&nbsp; participated in this project, and through it gained an appreciation of herbaria as a resource for biodiversity and cultural studies, and gained experience in communicating with&nbsp; international members of the scientific community.&nbsp; Both interns used this experience to leverage new opportunities in graduate student and employment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2018<br>      Modified by: Barbara&nbsp;M&nbsp;Thiers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Scientists document the earth?s plant and fungal diversity through dried reference specimens maintained in collections known as herbaria.  There are approximately 3000 herbaria in the world today, associated with approximately 13,000 biodiversity specialists. Index Herbariorum, established in 1935, is a guide to the world?s herbaria and their staff.  No other type of natural history collection has a resource that approaches Index Herbariorum in its longevity and comprehensiveness.  The New York Botanical Garden has maintained this unique resource for the past 41 years. Originally published in book form, the index first became available as an on-line searchable database in 1997.  Since then the database has been available as a read-only reference.  Through this project,  The New York Botanical Garden was able to  make this already vital resource updateable by user community, and more easily linked to other online databases. We were also able to reach out to all herbaria included in the Index to verify information held in there.  All of these changes have  expanded the accuracy, accessibility and sustainability of this resource and have made it much easier to maintain in the future.   The activities required to accomplish these goals included: (1) Adjusting the data structure of IH to bring it into compliance with the emerging Natural Collections Description standard, and to increase the effectiveness of searching key data such as the names of important collectors, name of plants and fungi, and geographical place names; (2) Creating a new user interface that will allow users to input updates to the index that will be vetted then incorporated into the index; (3) creating APIs to the database so the data can be fed to other applications without human mediation; (4) Informing the user community about the new updating procedures, and summarizing the status of the world's herbarium in an annual report, available for download from the Index Herbariorum website..      Intellectual Merit  The natural history museum community has a salient need for a model system for keeping track of the members of that community and for facilitating communication within the community and with all users of natural history data. Index Herbariorum has long been a model in its comprehensiveness, accuracy and widespread acceptance as a community standard.  With the expansion and enhancements described in this proposal, Index Herbariorum has become a 21st century resource that, if replicated for other types of collections, can be the foundation for unprecedented access to the world?s collections holdings.Other herbaria use IH as a source of contact information for herbarium commerce, for forming partnerships, and as a source of expertise for improving their own collections. Scientists use IH to as a source of data and institutional information for their research and for developing partnerships for multi-institutional collaborative projects. IH is used as a standard for identifying herbaria in publications, on permits, and in determining the suitability of an herbarium as a permanent specimen repository.     Broader Impact  Accurate, comprehensive information about the holdings of the world?s herbaria  make it easier for scientists to answer questions about the documentation of the world?s plant and fungal diversity, namely: How many species are represented in herbaria, and which areas of the earth are the best documented?  Who are the experts in plant identification, and how can these be contacted? Facilitating access to and communication among herbaria will help to maintain the vitality and relevance of these institutions and ensure that they can continue to serve humankind.  Index Herbariorum serves as a model for how other natural history collections can create an inventory of their members and set up an effective collaborative network.  An enhanced Index Herbariorumempowers countries such as the U.S. to better manage their collection repositories by providing insight into how collection resources and scientific expertise have developed over time, how they may change in the future.  Two recently graduated  college undergraduate interns  participated in this project, and through it gained an appreciation of herbaria as a resource for biodiversity and cultural studies, and gained experience in communicating with  international members of the scientific community.  Both interns used this experience to leverage new opportunities in graduate student and employment.          Last Modified: 10/23/2018       Submitted by: Barbara M Thiers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
