<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NDSO2015: National Data Science Organizers Workshop 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>32073.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>32073</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Interest in Data Science has been increasing at a breathtaking pace, as a result of the vast amounts of data that are being generated and collected across all sectors of society and economy. Many Data Science Meetup groups have been created across the country, each with an active local membership and a vibrant set of community-driven activities. The objective of this workshop is to connect the rapidly growing number of participants in these Data Science Meetup groups, in order to take the best advantage of this wealth of data science talent across the nation in addressing some of the national priority goals, including the goal of creating a well-educated Data Science workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will result in data science meetup groups collaborating with local governments and non-profits to advance their impact and create data science solutions to national priority issues, including socioeconomic issues. The workshop will allow participants to network with their peers, including meetup organizers, nonprofits, government agencies, in order to create a national data science network. The meeting organizers have an established track record and extensive experience working with governments and non-profits on the use of data science techniques to address social issues, and have created several open source systems to address education, health, energy, and economic development problems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1600085</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rayid</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rayid Ghani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rayid@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8472758457</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000663876</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicag</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5735 S. Ellis]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~32073</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 5.0px Helvetica} --> <p class="p1">The National Data Science Organizers project was launched as an effort to explore whether the individuals that are participating in a growing number of data science related meetups and grassroots organizations can help the United States make the most of the opportunities created by Big Data. In 2014, we spent almost a year gathering support from large Meetups and nonprofits. In 2015, the University of Chicago's Center for Data Science and Public Policy worked with the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy, the National Science Foundation, and Meetup.com to bring together with Meetup organizers, nonprofits, and the Big Data Regional Hub network to run an initial kickoff workshop in DC.</p> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 5.0px Helvetica} --> <p class="p1">The in-person kickoff meeting focused partially on shared learnings across the network of meetups with attendees giving presentations and workshops on data science project scoping, running hackathons, and ensuring projects have continuity. The project also lead to the creation of a new data science curriculum focused on disconnected youth that is still available and in use across the US on the learning platform LRNG. Additionally, through the launch of the National Data Science Challenge, we have given the opportunity for local engagement, learning, and mentorship through a shared challenge across an active community.</p> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 5.0px Helvetica} p.p2 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 5.5px Helvetica} --> <p class="p1">The kickoff meeting furthered mutual understanding of the data science process, how NSF-funded big data hubs can better act as catalysts for the volunteer data science community, and have visibly lead to two large national challenges that have engaged the big data hubs, the volunteer data science community, and local and national government agencies and actors.</p> <p class="p2">Because of the natural collaborations with governments and nonprofits that NDSO has focused on through the kickoff meeting, the national challenges, and online curriculum, there has been local capacity building within those collaborating institutions in their own understanding of their data, their capacity to use data to deliver better outcomes, and make data available for stakeholders to understand what is working.</p> <p class="p1">The primary impact has been, through the LRNG data science curriculum, to expose underrepresented youth in the data science field to the opportunities and challenges in data science. In its second year, this curriculum has already been used by dozens of cities across the country to engage disconnected youth in STEM education.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Rayid&nbsp;Ghani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The National Data Science Organizers project was launched as an effort to explore whether the individuals that are participating in a growing number of data science related meetups and grassroots organizations can help the United States make the most of the opportunities created by Big Data. In 2014, we spent almost a year gathering support from large Meetups and nonprofits. In 2015, the University of Chicago's Center for Data Science and Public Policy worked with the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy, the National Science Foundation, and Meetup.com to bring together with Meetup organizers, nonprofits, and the Big Data Regional Hub network to run an initial kickoff workshop in DC.  The in-person kickoff meeting focused partially on shared learnings across the network of meetups with attendees giving presentations and workshops on data science project scoping, running hackathons, and ensuring projects have continuity. The project also lead to the creation of a new data science curriculum focused on disconnected youth that is still available and in use across the US on the learning platform LRNG. Additionally, through the launch of the National Data Science Challenge, we have given the opportunity for local engagement, learning, and mentorship through a shared challenge across an active community.  The kickoff meeting furthered mutual understanding of the data science process, how NSF-funded big data hubs can better act as catalysts for the volunteer data science community, and have visibly lead to two large national challenges that have engaged the big data hubs, the volunteer data science community, and local and national government agencies and actors. Because of the natural collaborations with governments and nonprofits that NDSO has focused on through the kickoff meeting, the national challenges, and online curriculum, there has been local capacity building within those collaborating institutions in their own understanding of their data, their capacity to use data to deliver better outcomes, and make data available for stakeholders to understand what is working. The primary impact has been, through the LRNG data science curriculum, to expose underrepresented youth in the data science field to the opportunities and challenges in data science. In its second year, this curriculum has already been used by dozens of cities across the country to engage disconnected youth in STEM education.          Last Modified: 07/13/2018       Submitted by: Rayid Ghani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
