<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH:   The evolution of major life-history transitions: a transcriptomic analysis of developmental shifts in echinoids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20258.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20258</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the genetic basis of alternate types of larval development. Many ocean-dwelling animal species have a free-living larval stage, which is generally one of two major types. They are either long-lived, feeding larvae that develop over the course of months to years, or short-lived, non-feeding larvae that develop in a matter of hours to days. Larval type (feeding or non-feeding) has many important ecological and evolutionary ramifications, as it influences the size of species' ranges, connections between populations, and the potential for speciation and extinction. Although evolutionary transitions from feeding to non-feeding larvae occur frequently, we know little about the genetic changes that underlie these transitions. This project will test the hypothesis that larval development type depends upon certain maternal effects: messenger RNA (mRNA) in the eggs. The researchers will collect mRNA sequencing data from eggs of sand dollar and sea biscuit species to determine if differing developmental types are associated with different maternal mRNA. In addition, the project will support the training of minority undergraduate researchers and the creation of a public exhibit at a nature center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Preliminary research on two closely related species of echinoderm sea biscuits, which exhibit different larval developmental modes, demonstrated that larval developmental patterns are strongly driven by maternal factors. Although such maternal effects also drive the developmental patterns of larvae in several other systems, the underlying cause of this maternal effect remains unclear. This project will test the novel hypothesis that the strong maternal effect on development is due to differences in maternally deposited mRNA. The researchers will sequence the maternally deposited mRNA from unfertilized eggs of several closely related species pairs of sand dollars and sea biscuits that have alternate larval types. These data will also be used to create a time-calibrated phylogeny to correct for phylogenetic signal. Using these data, the project will determine how maternally deposited mRNA differs in eggs of feeding and non-feeding echinoderm larvae, and how those differences influence the evolution of alternate developmental pathways.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1600965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Grosberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard K Grosberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkgrosberg@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307521114</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000461078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Armstrong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne F Armstrong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frarmstrong@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307547700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678239</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20258</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Frances Armstrong has completed her doctoral dissertation "The evolution of major life-history transitions: a transcriptomic analysis of developmental shifts in echinoids" which was supported by an NSF Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant. During her dissertation, she was fascinated by the strong role of maternal effects on the developmental patterns of offspring. &nbsp;While mothers have many ways of influencing their offspring, such as providing care and energy, Armstrong was interested in investigating the genetic aspects of maternal effects. &nbsp;Mothers deposit RNA--the genetic precursors to proteins--in the eggs they lay to regulate early development. &nbsp;This project allowed Armstrong to identify and quantify the RNA that mothers from different species put into their eggs to analyze how maternally deposited RNA differs between offspring with differing developmental patterns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To conduct this project, Armstrong collected eggs from 11 species of echinoderms (sea urchins, sand dollars, and sea biscuits).&nbsp;&nbsp;This group presents a great opportunity for understanding the evolution of development due to the remarkable variability we see in their larval types even between closely related species. &nbsp;Armstrong traveled to both Japan and Panama to collect eggs from 5 of the species, while collaborators mailed samples for the other 6 species from Florida, Maine, and Australia. &nbsp;Armstrong was able to obtain RNA from all of the species and&nbsp;used next generation sequencing technology along with bioinformatic tools to identify which specific RNA molecules were present in the eggs of each species.&nbsp;&nbsp;The vast majority of the RNA present in the eggs were shared across species, as they are crucial to regulating vital developmental processes such as cell division and cycles.&nbsp;&nbsp;However, a handful of genes differed between species with alternate life cycles. These genes are candidate genes that may be integral to both the evolution and regulation of developmental patterns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As part of this grant, Armstrong additionally focused on educational outreach.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;She used funds from the grant to purchase two microscopes for the Punta Culebra Nature Center in Panama City, Panama.&nbsp;&nbsp;These microscopes are part of a lesson plan she helped create to educate local elementary school children about the diversity of larvae in the tropical waters around them. A great deal of Armstrong&rsquo;s dissertation was conducted in Panama with the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute.&nbsp;&nbsp;By donating microscopes to this organization, she was able to share some of her research with the people who interact with these wonderful organisms most.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;F&nbsp;Armstrong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1600965/1600965_10418050_1536513052647_Clypeasteroids--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1600965/1600965_10418050_1536513052647_Clypeasteroids--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sand Dollars and Sea Biscuits"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1600965/1600965_10418050_1536513052647_Clypeasteroids--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sand Dollars and Sea Biscuits"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sand dollars and sea biscuits are an incredibly diverse group of organisms.  While most people see the white shells after they have died and washed up on the beach, the living organisms are actually quite colorful.  This image shows five Caribbean species which were studied as part of this grant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anne Frances Armstrong</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anne&nbsp;F&nbsp;Armstrong</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sand Dollars and Sea Biscuits</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1600965/1600965_10418050_1537286107147_Feria2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1600965/1600965_10418050_1537286107147_Feria2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STRI Feria Del Mar"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1600965/1600965_10418050_1537286107147_Feria2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STRI Feria Del Mar"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">As part of this grant, Co-PI Armstrong used funds to donate microscopes to the Punta Culebra Nature Center in Panama. She is pictured here showing students sand dollar larvae under a microscope at the annual Ocean Fair in Bocas Del Toro, Panama.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anne Frances Armstrong</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anne&nbsp;F&nbsp;Armstrong</div> <div class="imageTitle">STRI Feria Del Mar</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Frances Armstrong has completed her doctoral dissertation "The evolution of major life-history transitions: a transcriptomic analysis of developmental shifts in echinoids" which was supported by an NSF Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant. During her dissertation, she was fascinated by the strong role of maternal effects on the developmental patterns of offspring.  While mothers have many ways of influencing their offspring, such as providing care and energy, Armstrong was interested in investigating the genetic aspects of maternal effects.  Mothers deposit RNA--the genetic precursors to proteins--in the eggs they lay to regulate early development.  This project allowed Armstrong to identify and quantify the RNA that mothers from different species put into their eggs to analyze how maternally deposited RNA differs between offspring with differing developmental patterns.     To conduct this project, Armstrong collected eggs from 11 species of echinoderms (sea urchins, sand dollars, and sea biscuits).  This group presents a great opportunity for understanding the evolution of development due to the remarkable variability we see in their larval types even between closely related species.  Armstrong traveled to both Japan and Panama to collect eggs from 5 of the species, while collaborators mailed samples for the other 6 species from Florida, Maine, and Australia.  Armstrong was able to obtain RNA from all of the species and used next generation sequencing technology along with bioinformatic tools to identify which specific RNA molecules were present in the eggs of each species.  The vast majority of the RNA present in the eggs were shared across species, as they are crucial to regulating vital developmental processes such as cell division and cycles.  However, a handful of genes differed between species with alternate life cycles. These genes are candidate genes that may be integral to both the evolution and regulation of developmental patterns.     As part of this grant, Armstrong additionally focused on educational outreach.   She used funds from the grant to purchase two microscopes for the Punta Culebra Nature Center in Panama City, Panama.  These microscopes are part of a lesson plan she helped create to educate local elementary school children about the diversity of larvae in the tropical waters around them. A great deal of Armstrong?s dissertation was conducted in Panama with the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute.  By donating microscopes to this organization, she was able to share some of her research with the people who interact with these wonderful organisms most.            Last Modified: 09/21/2018       Submitted by: Anne F Armstrong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
