<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH:   Gene Regulation Evolution and Speciation in House Mice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20357.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20357</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will make use of controlled laboratory experiments utilizing the model system of house mice (Mus musculus) to understand the role of gene regulation in speciation. A primary goal of speciation research is to uncover the genetic differences between species that underlie reproductive isolation. While much of the work in this field has focused on identifying specific genes that contribute to reproductive isolation between species, gene regulation may play a large role in this process. Despite this, there are been few systematic attempts to link regulatory evolution to reproductive isolation. Characterizing regulatory evolution between house mouse subspecies will provide novel insight into how regulatory networks evolve and diverge which has broad implications for our understanding of the evolution of complex phenotypes as well as the speciation process. In addition, the investigators will engage in research with undergraduates from underrepresented groups and provide public and K12 outreach on this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Taking advantage of a cross between house mouse subspecies, where hybrid dysfunction is largely unidirectional, the proposed work will use a variety of genomic methods (i.e., ChiP-sequencing, mRNA-sequencing, and ribosome profiling) to characterize changes in gene regulation on the transcriptional and translational level that are associated with hybrid sterility. This dissertation work will address the following questions: 1) What is the role of different levels of gene regulation to species divergence? and 2) What is the role of regulatory divergence in reproductive isolation between species? The work outlined here will be the first to: 1) characterize divergence in translational efficiency between mammalian species, and 2) examine the relationship between hybrid sterility and gene regulation on the transcriptional and translational level.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1601699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Nachman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael W Nachman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mnachman@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106421792</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444375</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katya</FirstName>
<LastName>Mack</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katya Mack</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>katyamack@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8473454393</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000704173</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947205800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[VLSB, Harmon Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20357</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Gene expression is a molecular phenotype that is essential to organismal form and fitness. Understanding the role of gene expression in variation within and divergence between species is important for understanding phenotypic evolution and the process of speciation. Towards this goal, we sought to address two primary questions regarding the role of gene regulation in the evolutionary process: 1) what is the role of regulatory variation in phenotypic variation within and between populations, and 2) how does regulatory variation and divergence contribute to speciation? As the premier biomedical model, house mice (<em>Mus musculus</em>) provide an excellent model system for studying gene expression evolution and divergence.&nbsp;</p> <p>Towards the first goal of understanding regulatory variation within species, we used 50 wild caught individuals&nbsp;<em>Mus musculus domesticus</em>to identify and characterize regulatory variation segregating within this the species. We identified a large number of&nbsp;<em>cis</em>- regulatory changes segregating within and between populations, and through correlations between gene expression, genetic variants, and phenotypic variation, were able to identify putative regulatory variation associated with divergence between populations and adaptive phenotypic variation. Results from this work have been published in&nbsp;<em>Genome Research&nbsp;</em>(Mack et al. 2018) and a second manuscript is in preparation to be submitted this year.&nbsp;</p> <p>Towards our second goal, we collected tissue samples (liver, testis) from&nbsp;<em>Mus musculus domesticus and Mus musculus musculus&nbsp;</em>individuals as well as sterile and fertile hybrids produced from this cross to generate ribosome profiling and ATAC-seq libraries. Motivated by our finding that compensatory evolution at regulatory variants is associated with hybrid male sterility in crosses between subspecies of house mice (Mack et al. 2016&nbsp;<em>Genome Res</em>), we are using these data to (1) characterize the evolution of regulatory regions (ATAC-seq), transcript abundance (RNAsq), and translation rate between closely related species (ribosome profiling), and (2) associate these characteristics with hybrid male sterility in house mice. Work on this project is ongoing and will be prepared as a manuscript for submission to a peer-reviewed journal once completed.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The results of this research have been shared at academic conferences and in seminars (at the University of Montana, Duke University, and UC Berkeley), incorporated into guest lectures for undergraduate and graduate classes (at Monmouth University, UC Berkeley, and the Watson School of Biology, Cold Spring Harbor) and used for outreach activities in Berkeley elementary schools through the Community Resource for Science "Be a Scientist" program. Finally, bioinformatics methods learned from this work have been used to create multiple workshops on data analysis for the Computational Genomics Resource Lab (CGRL) Berkeley.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2019<br>      Modified by: Katya&nbsp;Mack</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Gene expression is a molecular phenotype that is essential to organismal form and fitness. Understanding the role of gene expression in variation within and divergence between species is important for understanding phenotypic evolution and the process of speciation. Towards this goal, we sought to address two primary questions regarding the role of gene regulation in the evolutionary process: 1) what is the role of regulatory variation in phenotypic variation within and between populations, and 2) how does regulatory variation and divergence contribute to speciation? As the premier biomedical model, house mice (Mus musculus) provide an excellent model system for studying gene expression evolution and divergence.   Towards the first goal of understanding regulatory variation within species, we used 50 wild caught individuals Mus musculus domesticusto identify and characterize regulatory variation segregating within this the species. We identified a large number of cis- regulatory changes segregating within and between populations, and through correlations between gene expression, genetic variants, and phenotypic variation, were able to identify putative regulatory variation associated with divergence between populations and adaptive phenotypic variation. Results from this work have been published in Genome Research (Mack et al. 2018) and a second manuscript is in preparation to be submitted this year.   Towards our second goal, we collected tissue samples (liver, testis) from Mus musculus domesticus and Mus musculus musculus individuals as well as sterile and fertile hybrids produced from this cross to generate ribosome profiling and ATAC-seq libraries. Motivated by our finding that compensatory evolution at regulatory variants is associated with hybrid male sterility in crosses between subspecies of house mice (Mack et al. 2016 Genome Res), we are using these data to (1) characterize the evolution of regulatory regions (ATAC-seq), transcript abundance (RNAsq), and translation rate between closely related species (ribosome profiling), and (2) associate these characteristics with hybrid male sterility in house mice. Work on this project is ongoing and will be prepared as a manuscript for submission to a peer-reviewed journal once completed.   The results of this research have been shared at academic conferences and in seminars (at the University of Montana, Duke University, and UC Berkeley), incorporated into guest lectures for undergraduate and graduate classes (at Monmouth University, UC Berkeley, and the Watson School of Biology, Cold Spring Harbor) and used for outreach activities in Berkeley elementary schools through the Community Resource for Science "Be a Scientist" program. Finally, bioinformatics methods learned from this work have been used to create multiple workshops on data analysis for the Computational Genomics Resource Lab (CGRL) Berkeley.           Last Modified: 10/27/2019       Submitted by: Katya Mack]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
