<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Interactions among nitrogen and phosphorus through plant-microbial mutualisms in tropical rain forests</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18850.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18850</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Schade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The tropics contain some of the largest, fastest growing and carbon-rich forests on Earth. As they grow, tropical trees store large amounts of atmospheric carbon dioxide in their biomass, slowing the increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide and hence the pace of climate change. Yet, all trees require large amounts of soil nutrients, especially nitrogen and phosphorus, to grow, and it remains unclear whether the supply of soil nutrients will be sufficient to meet the demands of predicted tree growth in the future. For example, soil phosphorus concentrations are relatively low in tropical forest soils, and some research suggests that low phosphorus supply may limit increases in tree growth and carbon storage. However, previous work suggests that some tropical trees may be better than others at obtaining scarce nutrients because of their relationships with soil microorganisms that enhance the ability to scavenge nutrients. This research will explore how different tropical trees access soil nutrients and whether these microbial partnerships offer some trees an advantage over their competitors. Overall, this research will improve the understanding of how tropical forests may respond to global environmental change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Trees capable of symbiotic nitrogen (N) fixation, a plant-microbial mutualism that converts atmospheric N into biological forms, are abundant in tropical forests. Previous work suggests that N fixing trees have an advantage over non-N fixing trees in acquiring soil phosphorus (P) via the production of N-rich phosphatase enzymes that mineralize organic P and by hosting arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi that scavenge for inorganic P. This advantage could lead to competition for soil P in which N fixing trees outperform non-N fixing trees. This project will explore the interactions between N fixing and non-N fixing trees via an experimental seedling study on the Osa Peninsula, Costa Rica in which multiple species from each plant group will be grown alone or in competition under five P treatments that vary by the P compound being delivered. In addition, previous work suggests that this N and P interaction may not be constrained to trees that fix N, but may be evident in trees that have high foliar N regardless of fixation. Thus, foliar N may be an indirect control of P acquisition on an individual plant basis, as well as on a landscape scale if plants with similar foliar N concentrations are aggregated. Therefore, this research will also explore the relationships between foliar N, P acquisition, and the biogeochemical consequences across a set of individual emergent canopy trees and forest plots characterized by high and low foliar N. The results from both projects have the potential to elucidate complex plant-microbially mediated N and P interactions that operate above- and belowground, and on multiple spatial scales.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1601408</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cory</FirstName>
<LastName>Cleveland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cory C Cleveland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cory.cleveland@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4062436018</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419065</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Megan</FirstName>
<LastName>Nasto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Megan Nasto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>megan.nasto@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000706432</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Montana</Name>
<CityName>Missoula</CityName>
<ZipCode>598120001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>32 CAMPUS DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UH 116]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010379790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MONTANA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079602596</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Montana]]></Name>
<CityName>Missoula</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598120001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[32 CAMPUS DRIVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~18850</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Tropical forests are critical drivers of Earth's climate due to their vast exchanges of energy, water, and nutrients with the global atmosphere. Yet, despite the well-recognized importance of this biome to the global climate, fundamental uncertainties remain in our understanding of the nutrient cycles that underlie the productivity and dynamics of these forests worldwide. One of the more interesting problems lies in the resolution of the nitrogen cycle. Though it is often assumed that lowland tropical rain forests are rich in nitrogen relative to phosphorus, they contain far more symbiotic nitrogen fixing trees - trees that host bacteria in root nodules that acquire nitrogen from the atmosphere in exchange for carbon - than ecological theory would suggest. Our NSF DDIG funded research explored how soil phosphorus may be playing a role in driving the abundance and activity of nitrogen fixing trees in tropical rain forests.&nbsp;</p> <p>We used obervational and experimental techniques from ecosystem ecology, biogeochemistry, and plant physiology to assess how tropical nitrogen and non-nitrogen fixing trees acquire soil phosphorus. We then assessed how differences in their phosphorus acquisition strategies may enable them to coexist or compete for soil phosphorus, as well as respond to environmental change.</p> <p>Our work showed that nitrogen and non-nitrogen fixing trees predominantly rely on different phosphorus acquisition strategies that enable them to acquire different forms of soil phosphorus. While this has the potential to lead to their coexistence, when grown in competition, nitrogen fixing trees enhanced their acquisition of phosphorus to a greater degree than non-nitrogen fixing trees, increasing their competitive ability. Our work also showed that when grown in nutrient poor soil and under elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations, nitrogen fixing trees enahnced their acquisition of both nitrogen and phosphorus to a greater degree than non-nitrogen fixing trees, enabling them to grow quicker.&nbsp;</p> <p>Together, our work indicates that nitrogen fixing trees have a greater capacity than non-nitogen fixing trees to acquire the critical nutrients needed for growth. These key findings are a critical next step towards understanding the abundance and activity of nitrogen fixing trees in the tropics. Even more, our work improved our ability to predict how one of Earth's most critical biomes may change in response to future environmental change, thus aiding a variety of management and conservation goals.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Cory&nbsp;C&nbsp;Cleveland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Tropical forests are critical drivers of Earth's climate due to their vast exchanges of energy, water, and nutrients with the global atmosphere. Yet, despite the well-recognized importance of this biome to the global climate, fundamental uncertainties remain in our understanding of the nutrient cycles that underlie the productivity and dynamics of these forests worldwide. One of the more interesting problems lies in the resolution of the nitrogen cycle. Though it is often assumed that lowland tropical rain forests are rich in nitrogen relative to phosphorus, they contain far more symbiotic nitrogen fixing trees - trees that host bacteria in root nodules that acquire nitrogen from the atmosphere in exchange for carbon - than ecological theory would suggest. Our NSF DDIG funded research explored how soil phosphorus may be playing a role in driving the abundance and activity of nitrogen fixing trees in tropical rain forests.   We used obervational and experimental techniques from ecosystem ecology, biogeochemistry, and plant physiology to assess how tropical nitrogen and non-nitrogen fixing trees acquire soil phosphorus. We then assessed how differences in their phosphorus acquisition strategies may enable them to coexist or compete for soil phosphorus, as well as respond to environmental change.  Our work showed that nitrogen and non-nitrogen fixing trees predominantly rely on different phosphorus acquisition strategies that enable them to acquire different forms of soil phosphorus. While this has the potential to lead to their coexistence, when grown in competition, nitrogen fixing trees enhanced their acquisition of phosphorus to a greater degree than non-nitrogen fixing trees, increasing their competitive ability. Our work also showed that when grown in nutrient poor soil and under elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations, nitrogen fixing trees enahnced their acquisition of both nitrogen and phosphorus to a greater degree than non-nitrogen fixing trees, enabling them to grow quicker.   Together, our work indicates that nitrogen fixing trees have a greater capacity than non-nitogen fixing trees to acquire the critical nutrients needed for growth. These key findings are a critical next step towards understanding the abundance and activity of nitrogen fixing trees in the tropics. Even more, our work improved our ability to predict how one of Earth's most critical biomes may change in response to future environmental change, thus aiding a variety of management and conservation goals.        Last Modified: 07/05/2018       Submitted by: Cory C Cleveland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
