<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR: - TT:  Forming Metals Like Plastics: Thermoplastic Blowmolding of Metallic Glasses</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>206000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating the ability to thermoplastically form metallic glasses like plastics to fill the need of net-shaping metals. Net-shaping, a process that shapes a material in one processing step into its final shape, is well established for thermoplastics, but thermoplastics are too weak for most structural applications. In structural applications that are critical, such as aerospace, automotive, and hard-tissue replacements, metals are typically used. Forming of metals, however, has been limited. This project will combine metal-like properties and plastic-like processing. Particularly, thermoplastic based blow-molding and stretch blow-molding, will be translated during this project from a scientific discovery into a technological process, which can meet the need for a metal net-shape process.  These blow-molding processes have potentially vast commercial ramification as they could replace many of the currently used metal processing methods, and hence replace many of the applications currently occupied by metals and plastics. In order to reach such a translation, this project will determine processing parameters that are required for a commercial fabrication process. In addition, a commercial viability study will be carried out considering capital investment, processing time, and materials costs. As a product, a commercial apparatus and processing procedure will be determined in consultation with equipment manufacturers. Specifically, cycle time will be minimized, and processing conditions optimized for speed, energy efficiency, and robustness. Considering the redundancy of machining, joining, and other finishing procedures, and taking into account the processing speed and accuracy, blow-molding of metallic glasses is envisioned to replace currently used materials and processes used for electronic casings.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application. The effect of high strain rate on the deformation behavior is not well understood. Particularly, if the metallic glass forming liquid remains to behave like a Newtonian liquid as strain rates exceeding 0.1/sec. Accurate understanding of the deformation behavior, the metallic glasses' response to temperature and pressure is crucial for future modeling of mold filling during blow-molding and stretch blow-molding.  How the high strain rates effects the mechanical properties of the metallic glass also will be investigated. Bending experiments will be conducted and the strain to failure will be used as a quantitative measure for bending ductility. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Involved personnel include graduate students, post-docs, undergraduate students, and visiting undergraduate students. They will be exposed to the whole range of technological development; from fundamental science of determining the deformation behavior, to engineering aspects of developing appropriate processes and machinery, to commercial and business aspects of viability and comparison studies. Students will be exposed to the state of the art metallurgy processes and characterization methods and will also develop a deeper understanding of the connection between science, innovation, and entrepreneurial skills.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1601867</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Schroers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan Schroers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jan.schroers@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034324346</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491081</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Jensen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Jensen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kyle.jensen@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2037854689</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000702924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065116816</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[15 Prospect St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project focuses on translating the ability to thermoplastically form metallic glasses like plastics to fill the need of net-shaping metals. Net-shaping, a process that shapes a material in one processing step into its final shape, is well established for thermoplastics, but thermoplastics are too weak for most structural applications. In structural applications that are critical, such as aerospace, automotive, and hard-tissue replacements, metals are typically used. Forming of metals, however, has been limited. This project combined metal-like properties and plastic-like processing. This was achieved through exploring stretch-blowmolding. Blowmolding have been previously demonstrated for metallic glasses as an effective forming method. However, the highly non-uniform thickness distribution limits the shapes that can be blowmolded to below ~100% strain. To lift this limitation, we propose to first stretch the feedstock mechanically into the mold cavity, and subsequently blow mold to replicate even complex, and high-strain requiring, shapes. Within this project a stretch-blowmolding machine was designed and built. With this machine, we carried out research on the wall thickness variation. We found that stretching alone is insufficient to result in low wall thickness variation. However, when different temperatures are applied in the center and edges of the feedstock, relatively uniform wall thickness can be achieved.</p> <p>To demonstrate this capability, we formed a complex shape from a flat, sheet-like feedstock, into a complex shape, requiring more than 1000% strain.</p> <p>The ability to net-shape even most complex shapes through this highly energy and cost-efficient process suggest a wide commercial adaptation of this process. However, as today&rsquo;s most practical metallic glasses, that are suited for thermoplastic forming, are relatively expensive, early adapters of this technology will be in applications that can tolerate higher costs for better performance.&nbsp; A wide spread use of this technology will need, in addition of the outcome of this project, require the development of inexpensive metallic glasses. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Jan&nbsp;Schroers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601867/1601867_10418758_1530371618677_stretchblowmoldingsummary--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601867/1601867_10418758_1530371618677_stretchblowmoldingsummary--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Stretch-blowmolding with metallic glasses."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601867/1601867_10418758_1530371618677_stretchblowmoldingsummary--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Stretch-blowmolding with metallic glasses."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stretch-blowmolding apparatus that was designed and built under this project was used to reveal strategies for high thickness uniformity. This has enabled to form complex articles from sheet-like feedstock.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jan Schroers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jan&nbsp;Schroers</div> <div class="imageTitle">Stretch-blowmolding with metallic glasses.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project focuses on translating the ability to thermoplastically form metallic glasses like plastics to fill the need of net-shaping metals. Net-shaping, a process that shapes a material in one processing step into its final shape, is well established for thermoplastics, but thermoplastics are too weak for most structural applications. In structural applications that are critical, such as aerospace, automotive, and hard-tissue replacements, metals are typically used. Forming of metals, however, has been limited. This project combined metal-like properties and plastic-like processing. This was achieved through exploring stretch-blowmolding. Blowmolding have been previously demonstrated for metallic glasses as an effective forming method. However, the highly non-uniform thickness distribution limits the shapes that can be blowmolded to below ~100% strain. To lift this limitation, we propose to first stretch the feedstock mechanically into the mold cavity, and subsequently blow mold to replicate even complex, and high-strain requiring, shapes. Within this project a stretch-blowmolding machine was designed and built. With this machine, we carried out research on the wall thickness variation. We found that stretching alone is insufficient to result in low wall thickness variation. However, when different temperatures are applied in the center and edges of the feedstock, relatively uniform wall thickness can be achieved.  To demonstrate this capability, we formed a complex shape from a flat, sheet-like feedstock, into a complex shape, requiring more than 1000% strain.  The ability to net-shape even most complex shapes through this highly energy and cost-efficient process suggest a wide commercial adaptation of this process. However, as today?s most practical metallic glasses, that are suited for thermoplastic forming, are relatively expensive, early adapters of this technology will be in applications that can tolerate higher costs for better performance.  A wide spread use of this technology will need, in addition of the outcome of this project, require the development of inexpensive metallic glasses.                  Last Modified: 06/30/2018       Submitted by: Jan Schroers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
