<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometry of Langlands Duality</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>164999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>164999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project aims to relate and unify recent developments in mathematics and theoretical particle physics. The mathematical origin of these developments is the so-called Langlands program, which is the modern view on the classical mathematical discipline of number theory. The Langlands program functions today as a bridge between central disciplines of mathematics, such as representation theory, algebraic geometry, and number theory, and central disciplines in physics, such as gauge theory and string theory. This project will use this connection in both directions by applying ideas from physics to mathematics, through a new use of locality, and applying mathematical constructions to physics, by constructing the "theory X," the conjectural six-dimensional conformal field theory that should unify all important quantum field theories in lower dimensions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central theme of this project is to extend the geometric Langlands program from objects of dimension one (in algebraic geometry) to arbitrary dimensions. The goal of the project is to develop conceptual breakthroughs into a full mathematical machinery. These breakthroughs include an extension of the basic case of the geometric Langlands program (the so called geometric Class Field Theory) to arbitrary dimension. This development is expected to be influential in mathematics, in particular through the introduction of the relative motivic cohomology. The general geometric Langlands program will also be investigated, based on recent results in constructing and generalizing the loop Grassmannian from the point of view of statistical mechanics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1601735</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Mirkovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan Mirkovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mirkovic@math.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135456023</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000425139</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[710 North Pleasant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~164999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A. Outcomes.<br />This project is a part of an ongoing effort to understand the <br />``duality'' phenomenon in mathematics and physics, which can be described as an observation that that contrary to our expectations<br />reality has more than one description. A huge&nbsp; amount evidence for such <br />dualities has been found and this constitutes&nbsp; one of the&nbsp; strongest <br />informations we have about fundamental physics <br />(such as structure of space and elementary particles)<br />as well as key areas of mathematics (Number Theory, Representation Theory, Algebraic Geometry etc). The study of these dualities is therefore a central effort which even at the low level of our understanding yields<br />fundamental insights and acts as a bridge between the previously <br />unrelated fields. <br /><br />My background is in the ``geometric Langlands program'' which <br />brought us the mathematical observation of the duality phenomena,<br />the ``Langlands duality''. Though this is one of key <br />successes of mathematics of 20th century it still accounts only for spaces that have only one dimension (some very abstract version of curves).<br />The project was devoted towards rebuilding the foundations of this subject<br />so that it can apply to objects in&nbsp; arbitrary dimension (versions of surfaces, solids and much more).<br />&nbsp;I take the view that <br />going&nbsp; beyond&nbsp; dimension one will force us to&nbsp; avoid the traditional reliance on calculations in special cases and make more drastic steps in fundamentally understanding the&nbsp; Langlands duality.<br /><br /><br />The basis of my approach is <br />a construction of a specific ``cohomology theory'', i.e., a mechanism of <br />distilling information from geometry. <br />This should take place in ``Algebraic Geometry''<br />which is arguably the highest developed part of geometry. The new <br />feature is that <br />my cohomology theory should be <br />``inner'' for algebraic geometry.<br />This means that&nbsp; the information that it distills from an object in algebraic geometry will be a simpler object but it will still be an object of algebraic geometry -- this really means that it will have subtle structure which will allow it to pack a huge amount of information.<br />I expect that in this setting the Langlands duality&nbsp; will become <br />understandable -- that it will take the form of a&nbsp; well understood <br />phenomenon of ``Poincare Duality'' from the field of ``Topology''.<br /><br />The outcomes of the project include&nbsp; construction of such inner cohomology<br />in the traditional geometry of dimension one. (Some advances have been made in higher dimension but these are still very preliminary). <br />This construction is the basis of the<br />envisioned continuation of the project under&nbsp; the current grant.<br />The Langlands program can be divided into two parts the more basic ``commutative'' case and the deeper<br />``non-commutative'' case. <br />In the commutative case&nbsp; the understanding is fairly complete. <br />The main advancement in the non-commutative case<br />is a new construction of known cohomology objects.<br />I expect that this approach will&nbsp; work in higher dimension where the<br />traditional approach to non-commutative cohomology does not work<br />neither in mathematics nor in physics.<br />Though I describe it here in mathematical terms, <br />this work is motivated in large part by experience and needs of physics. <br /><br /><br />B. Intellectual merits. <br /><br />The project attempts to improve the infrastructure of mathematics.<br />It should forge a new relation between <br />fields of mathematics: geometric Class Field Theory<br />(in Number Theory and the geometric Langlands program)<br />motivic cohomology<br />(in Algebraic Geometry) and&nbsp; derived geometry (Homotopy Theory).<br />It should advance these mathematical fields and hopefully also<br />the Quantum Field Theory in physics.<br /><br /><br /><br />C. Broader impacts.<br /><br />The nature of the project is interdisciplinary,<br />for instance the geometric Class Field Theory<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp; (a high point of Number Theory)<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp; is combined with an adaptation of motivic<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp; cohomology (Algebraic Geometry)<br />in order to give it an interpretation as<br />Poincare duality (Topology). <br />The project should have impact in QFT <br />though this part is at present<br />not developed. <br /><br />I have worked for 2 years with an undergraduate Bowen Yang <br />(now a Caltech PhD student).<br />My PhD students <br />Bradley Willocks <br />and Zhijie Dong Maureen <br />have graduated recently. <br />My current student Andreas Hayash is working on a central part of <br />the project.<br />I spent the Spring semester of 2019 <br />at Mathematical Sciences Research Center at Berkeley.<br />There I have&nbsp; <br />intensely worked with Raeez Lorgat a graduate student in physics. <br />This work with graduate students&nbsp; part had a <br />significant diversity component as <br />half of my students were from under-represented&nbsp; minorities. <br />In recent years&nbsp; I have&nbsp; volunteered to<br />conduct a seminar at UMass <br />that prepares undergraduate students for the Putnam Exam.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Ivan&nbsp;Mirkovic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A. Outcomes. This project is a part of an ongoing effort to understand the  ``duality'' phenomenon in mathematics and physics, which can be described as an observation that that contrary to our expectations reality has more than one description. A huge  amount evidence for such  dualities has been found and this constitutes  one of the  strongest  informations we have about fundamental physics  (such as structure of space and elementary particles) as well as key areas of mathematics (Number Theory, Representation Theory, Algebraic Geometry etc). The study of these dualities is therefore a central effort which even at the low level of our understanding yields fundamental insights and acts as a bridge between the previously  unrelated fields.   My background is in the ``geometric Langlands program'' which  brought us the mathematical observation of the duality phenomena, the ``Langlands duality''. Though this is one of key  successes of mathematics of 20th century it still accounts only for spaces that have only one dimension (some very abstract version of curves). The project was devoted towards rebuilding the foundations of this subject so that it can apply to objects in  arbitrary dimension (versions of surfaces, solids and much more).  I take the view that  going  beyond  dimension one will force us to  avoid the traditional reliance on calculations in special cases and make more drastic steps in fundamentally understanding the  Langlands duality.   The basis of my approach is  a construction of a specific ``cohomology theory'', i.e., a mechanism of  distilling information from geometry.  This should take place in ``Algebraic Geometry'' which is arguably the highest developed part of geometry. The new  feature is that  my cohomology theory should be  ``inner'' for algebraic geometry. This means that  the information that it distills from an object in algebraic geometry will be a simpler object but it will still be an object of algebraic geometry -- this really means that it will have subtle structure which will allow it to pack a huge amount of information. I expect that in this setting the Langlands duality  will become  understandable -- that it will take the form of a  well understood  phenomenon of ``Poincare Duality'' from the field of ``Topology''.  The outcomes of the project include  construction of such inner cohomology in the traditional geometry of dimension one. (Some advances have been made in higher dimension but these are still very preliminary).  This construction is the basis of the envisioned continuation of the project under  the current grant. The Langlands program can be divided into two parts the more basic ``commutative'' case and the deeper ``non-commutative'' case.  In the commutative case  the understanding is fairly complete.  The main advancement in the non-commutative case is a new construction of known cohomology objects. I expect that this approach will  work in higher dimension where the traditional approach to non-commutative cohomology does not work neither in mathematics nor in physics. Though I describe it here in mathematical terms,  this work is motivated in large part by experience and needs of physics.    B. Intellectual merits.   The project attempts to improve the infrastructure of mathematics. It should forge a new relation between  fields of mathematics: geometric Class Field Theory (in Number Theory and the geometric Langlands program) motivic cohomology (in Algebraic Geometry) and  derived geometry (Homotopy Theory). It should advance these mathematical fields and hopefully also the Quantum Field Theory in physics.    C. Broader impacts.  The nature of the project is interdisciplinary, for instance the geometric Class Field Theory        (a high point of Number Theory)        is combined with an adaptation of motivic        cohomology (Algebraic Geometry) in order to give it an interpretation as Poincare duality (Topology).  The project should have impact in QFT  though this part is at present not developed.   I have worked for 2 years with an undergraduate Bowen Yang  (now a Caltech PhD student). My PhD students  Bradley Willocks  and Zhijie Dong Maureen  have graduated recently.  My current student Andreas Hayash is working on a central part of  the project. I spent the Spring semester of 2019  at Mathematical Sciences Research Center at Berkeley. There I have   intensely worked with Raeez Lorgat a graduate student in physics.  This work with graduate students  part had a  significant diversity component as  half of my students were from under-represented  minorities.  In recent years  I have  volunteered to conduct a seminar at UMass  that prepares undergraduate students for the Putnam Exam.       Last Modified: 10/23/2019       Submitted by: Ivan Mirkovic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
