<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH:   Mechanisms of reproductive isolation along the speciation continuum: from micro- to macro-evolutionary scales</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19157.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19157</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will examine the forces maintaining diversity in populations, species, and more distantly related lineages to build a more comprehensive picture of the speciation process in California Jewelflowers. Understanding how new species originate from existing ones is a major goal in biology. After new species are formed, both ecological and genetic forces may act to preserve species boundaries, prevent hybridization, and maintain biodiversity.  It is unclear if these forces act similarly at population, species, and higher taxonomic levels. A comprehensive understanding of how biodiversity is generated and maintained in a single group of plants will inform basic models of the maintenance of Earth's biodiversity. It will also guide important conservation and management decisions for small, isolated, or fragmented populations.  This research will provide training of a graduate student and several undergraduate research assistants. It will also provide citizens with a richer context for understanding plant biodiversity through public outreach efforts on California's plant biodiversity.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous research at the middle and late stages of speciation in the plant clade Streptanthus suggests that both genetic incompatibilities and divergent ecology contribute to the maintenance of species-level diversity.  Experimental hybridizations show that genetic incompatibility increases with species divergence times. Some recently diverged species pairs can, however, still produce viable hybrid offspring in the greenhouse.  Field research shows that ecological differences in such species, including microhabitat affinity, pollinator preferences and constancy, and phenology may play a role in maintaining potential interbreeders as distinct species in nature.  It is unclear whether the same ecological and evolutionary forces act at different stages of the speciation continuum, or if distinct genetic and ecological forces are characteristic of each stage of speciation.  This research delves deeper into the early stages of speciation in Streptanthus, by focusing on population divergence and early reproductive isolation at the population level.  Experimental hybridizations and Restriction site Associated DNA sequencing will be used to examine patterns of genetic relatedness among multiple geographically and environmentally divergent populations of S. breweri. The same techniques will also be used to analyze the influence of genetic, geographic, and environmental distance, on reproductive isolation at the population level.  This research complements previous work in Streptanthus, providing new data on population-level processes, which will illuminate patterns of reproductive isolation observed at the species level, and provide a comprehensive view of the speciation process within a single study system.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1601186</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Strauss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon Y Strauss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>systrauss@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307528415</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000156400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Christie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Christie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kchristie@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9286998410</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000702164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~19157</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding how new species originate from existing ones, and thus how biodiversity is generated, is a major goal in biology.&nbsp; A species can be defined as an evolutionary lineage that is generally unable to interbreed with other lineages.&nbsp; After new species form, both ecological and genetic forces may act to preserve species boundaries and prevent hybridization.&nbsp; It is often unclear whether the same ecological and evolutionary forces act similarly in populations, species, and at higher taxonomic levels.&nbsp; This research aimed to build a complete view of the speciation process in California Jewelflowers (wildflower relatives to culinary mustards), spanning populations, species, and more distantly related lineages.&nbsp; An unusually high proportion of California Jewelflowers are geographically restricted and occur nowhere else in the world, and thus are an important component of California&rsquo;s plant biodiversity.&nbsp; California itself is a worldwide biodiversity hotspot, so understanding the ecological and evolutionary process that contribute to biodiversity locally will have major implications for our general understanding as well.</p> <p>Here we measured nine potential mating barriers in 39 California Jewelflower species pairs, and explored how each barrier evolved across five million years of evolutionary divergence. &nbsp;Our results suggest that ecological differences shape divergence at the population and species levels, while genetic differences act to enforce species boundaries later on.&nbsp; We found that close relatives occurred in close geographic proximity as opposed to further apart, suggesting that spatial isolation even at the local scale can be important to the generation of biodiversity.&nbsp; These findings help explain the high degree of plant diversity in California, and more generally suggest how speciation can proceed in plants.&nbsp; We have published these findings in the journal <em>Evolution</em>, and have made our data publically available through the Dryad Digital Repository.</p> <p>Next we looked at single species pair, Brewer&rsquo;s Jewelflower and Green Jewelflower, in an area where both species live together.&nbsp; Despite the fact that both species occupy similar specialized habitats, we found that mixed populations were rare.&nbsp; We found that subtle differences in habitat, flowering time, and pollinator communities, as well as nuances of pollinator and reproductive interactions all contribute to the maintenance of species boundaries when close relatives co-occur. &nbsp;Overall, these results suggest that many of the same mating barriers that seemed to be important across multiple California Jewelflowers also play an important role when species occur together in space and time.&nbsp; We discovered that close relatives occupying extremely similar habitats can be isolated by multiple reproductive barriers, and thus can maintain their integrity even when they co-occur with potential hybridizers.</p> <p>Lastly we explored ecological, genetic, and reproductive differences within multiple populations of Brewer&rsquo;s Jewelflowers.&nbsp; Here we found that adaptation to different climates influenced flowering time, and thus individuals may be less able to interbreed with indigenous plants following migration to different areas of the species range.&nbsp; Additionally we found that populations isolated at the scale of tens of kilometers showed genetic incompatibilities and failed to produce hybrid offspring.&nbsp; While patchy or fragmented environments can often reduce genetic diversity and population sizes, in some cases these same insular environments can generate biodiversity as well.&nbsp; In sum, we achieved our scientific goal to build a comprehensive view of the speciation process, spanning early population divergence all the way to complete genetic incompatibility, all within a single study system. &nbsp;While our work focused on the California Jewelflowers, other recent studies suggest that it may represent processes common across the biodiversity hotspot of the California Floristic Province and beyond. &nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to its scientific contribution, this project provided additional broader impacts to the community. &nbsp;Throughout the project we trained six undergraduate students as part of independent research internships in evolution and ecology.&nbsp; These outstanding individuals came from a variety of backgrounds including first-generation college students, English-language learners, immigrants to the United States, and individuals with learning disabilities.&nbsp; We engaged students from UC Davis&rsquo; ESA SEEDS chapter, which is committed to increasing diversity in the field of ecology, as well as a student from the National Science Foundation&rsquo;s Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program.&nbsp; One of our mentees presented his research at a campus-wide research symposium for undergraduates.&nbsp; Several of these undergraduates have gone on to graduate school to pursue the study of ecology.&nbsp; Lastly, we presented our research findings to the community at several botanical society meetings, which hopefully provided the public with a richer context for understanding plant biodiversity, and thus promoted a deeper conservation ethic for preserving it.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Kyle&nbsp;Christie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930394306_Shesperidis2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930394306_Shesperidis2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Green Jewelflower"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930394306_Shesperidis2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Green Jewelflower"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Green Jewelflower grows on harsh serpentine soil.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Christie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kyle&nbsp;Christie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Green Jewelflower</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930478908_Sbreweri--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930478908_Sbreweri--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Brewer's Jewelflower"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930478908_Sbreweri--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Brewer's Jewelflower"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Brewer's Jewelflower occurs nowhere else in the world besides in California; it is restricted to harsh  serpentine soils.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Christie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kyle&nbsp;Christie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Brewer's Jewelflower</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930601785_pollination--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930601785_pollination--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bumblebee pollinates Green Jewelflower"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930601785_pollination--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bumblebee pollinates Green Jewelflower"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Pollinator differences and pollinator behavior contribute to reduced matings between co-occurring relatives.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Christie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kyle&nbsp;Christie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bumblebee pollinates Green Jewelflower</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930695019_Kyle_fieldwork_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930695019_Kyle_fieldwork_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fieldwork"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930695019_Kyle_fieldwork_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fieldwork"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A graduate student collects seeds for greenhouse experiments.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Christie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kyle&nbsp;Christie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fieldwork</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930778009_undergrad_presentation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930778009_undergrad_presentation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Undergraduate research presentation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930778009_undergrad_presentation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Undergraduate research presentation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An undergraduate student presents his research findings at a campus-wide research symposium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Christie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kyle&nbsp;Christie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Undergraduate research presentation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930951297_undergrad_research--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930951297_undergrad_research--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Undergraduate research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1601186/1601186_10420092_1528930951297_undergrad_research--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Undergraduate research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Undergraduates conduct hands-on research in the greenhouse.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Christie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kyle&nbsp;Christie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Undergraduate research</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding how new species originate from existing ones, and thus how biodiversity is generated, is a major goal in biology.  A species can be defined as an evolutionary lineage that is generally unable to interbreed with other lineages.  After new species form, both ecological and genetic forces may act to preserve species boundaries and prevent hybridization.  It is often unclear whether the same ecological and evolutionary forces act similarly in populations, species, and at higher taxonomic levels.  This research aimed to build a complete view of the speciation process in California Jewelflowers (wildflower relatives to culinary mustards), spanning populations, species, and more distantly related lineages.  An unusually high proportion of California Jewelflowers are geographically restricted and occur nowhere else in the world, and thus are an important component of California?s plant biodiversity.  California itself is a worldwide biodiversity hotspot, so understanding the ecological and evolutionary process that contribute to biodiversity locally will have major implications for our general understanding as well.  Here we measured nine potential mating barriers in 39 California Jewelflower species pairs, and explored how each barrier evolved across five million years of evolutionary divergence.  Our results suggest that ecological differences shape divergence at the population and species levels, while genetic differences act to enforce species boundaries later on.  We found that close relatives occurred in close geographic proximity as opposed to further apart, suggesting that spatial isolation even at the local scale can be important to the generation of biodiversity.  These findings help explain the high degree of plant diversity in California, and more generally suggest how speciation can proceed in plants.  We have published these findings in the journal Evolution, and have made our data publically available through the Dryad Digital Repository.  Next we looked at single species pair, Brewer?s Jewelflower and Green Jewelflower, in an area where both species live together.  Despite the fact that both species occupy similar specialized habitats, we found that mixed populations were rare.  We found that subtle differences in habitat, flowering time, and pollinator communities, as well as nuances of pollinator and reproductive interactions all contribute to the maintenance of species boundaries when close relatives co-occur.  Overall, these results suggest that many of the same mating barriers that seemed to be important across multiple California Jewelflowers also play an important role when species occur together in space and time.  We discovered that close relatives occupying extremely similar habitats can be isolated by multiple reproductive barriers, and thus can maintain their integrity even when they co-occur with potential hybridizers.  Lastly we explored ecological, genetic, and reproductive differences within multiple populations of Brewer?s Jewelflowers.  Here we found that adaptation to different climates influenced flowering time, and thus individuals may be less able to interbreed with indigenous plants following migration to different areas of the species range.  Additionally we found that populations isolated at the scale of tens of kilometers showed genetic incompatibilities and failed to produce hybrid offspring.  While patchy or fragmented environments can often reduce genetic diversity and population sizes, in some cases these same insular environments can generate biodiversity as well.  In sum, we achieved our scientific goal to build a comprehensive view of the speciation process, spanning early population divergence all the way to complete genetic incompatibility, all within a single study system.  While our work focused on the California Jewelflowers, other recent studies suggest that it may represent processes common across the biodiversity hotspot of the California Floristic Province and beyond.    In addition to its scientific contribution, this project provided additional broader impacts to the community.  Throughout the project we trained six undergraduate students as part of independent research internships in evolution and ecology.  These outstanding individuals came from a variety of backgrounds including first-generation college students, English-language learners, immigrants to the United States, and individuals with learning disabilities.  We engaged students from UC Davis? ESA SEEDS chapter, which is committed to increasing diversity in the field of ecology, as well as a student from the National Science Foundation?s Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program.  One of our mentees presented his research at a campus-wide research symposium for undergraduates.  Several of these undergraduates have gone on to graduate school to pursue the study of ecology.  Lastly, we presented our research findings to the community at several botanical society meetings, which hopefully provided the public with a richer context for understanding plant biodiversity, and thus promoted a deeper conservation ethic for preserving it.             Last Modified: 06/13/2018       Submitted by: Kyle Christie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
