<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>3He in Confinement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>462500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>462500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>giannacc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;At very low temperatures all matter enters a regime described only by quantum mechanics where the states of matter are called quantum states.  Some of these states allow electron currents to flow that are completely frictionless and in helium liquids the atoms can flow without generating any heat, and are called superfluids.  In this project new classes of the superfluid of the light isotope of helium, helium-three, are engineered in anisotropic confinement using extremely small-scale porous glass prepared in the project laboratory. The topology of these states allows storage of quantum information which is an essential component of the quantum calculations that promise a revolution in computer technology. Both the low temperatures and the topology of the quantum states are essential. Graduate students and undergraduates, as well as some high school students, learn the specialized techniques that are required to make the porous glass materials and characterize them using scanning electron microscopy, cryogenics, and optical methods to achieve the project goals: creating and identifying new topological quantum states of liquid helium.  High quality samples are also provided for collaborations with other laboratories in the USA, France, Japan, and the United Kingdom for a range of research applications on quantum fluids.  Furthermore, an active software based tool on our website is developed and maintained by graduate students, to make accessible the physical properties of the superfluids we study.  The PI continues advocacy for public awareness of helium as a precious natural resource serving on the recently convened APS, ACS, and MRS sponsored Helium Economics Committee, and appearances before congress, on national television, for science magazines, and at invited talks at international conferences and workshops. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This project for graduate student research includes the search for new quantum states with engineered symmetry among the manifold of possible fermionic p-wave 3He superfluids. Nano-structured environments from dense arrays of small pores in alumina membranes are used to define specific anisotropic environments and cooled to ultra-low temperatures for investigation using ultra-sound and high resolution NMR.  A second part of the project is to use high porosity silica aerogel that is fabricated with controlled anisotropy.  With this approach the recent predictions for such new states of matter are tested, particularly the interplay of states with chiral and non-chiral symmetry.  The topology of such superfluids support Majorana excitations that have been proposed as a key component of quantum information processing and has a direct connection to topological superconductors.  A central aspect of the theory is that anisotropic environments can stabilize anisotropic superfluid states.  There is already an indication of this in superfluid 3He that parallels the behavior of the topological superconductor UPt3.  In the project's research control of the surface conditions are performed using single atom layers of the bosonic superfluid 4He.  Additionally, acoustic resonant cavities are produced using nanofabrication facilities. The project supports continuing funding for graduate education and undergraduate research in experimental physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1602542</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Halperin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William P Halperin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>w-halperin@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000185369</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080834</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~462500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Intellectual merit:</em></p> <p>We have discovered how to stabilize new types of <sup>3</sup>He superfluid phases exhibiting different spontaneous broken symmetries by engineering anisotropy through confinement of the superfluid in highly porous, anisotropic,&nbsp; silica aerogels. &nbsp;Quantum manipulation and control is at the heart of the new era of quantum information processing. We have demonstarted&nbsp;control of the angular momentum orientation In the quantum coherent superfluid B-phase&nbsp;using aerogel anisotropy and characterized by NMR spectra with very high resolution spectroscopy recently implemented with NSF support.</p> <p>We have discovered a new critical magnetic field in&nbsp;<sup>3</sup>He superfluid phases in anisotropic silica aerogel. &nbsp;In this grant we have fully characterized the nature of this critical field and have traced its origin to the time-reversal symmetry breaking A-phase.</p> <p>We have shown that the collective modes of pure&nbsp;<sup>3</sup>He superfluid phases, where these modes are the intrinsic vibrations that are the fingerprint of the quantum order, &nbsp;have frequencies that reveal the magnitude of the interactions that cause the superfluid to form with corrections for angular momentum channels that have not been observed previously. &nbsp;These so-called massive modes are directly analogous to the Higgs modes of elementary particle physics responsible for their fundamental masses.</p> <p>These accomplishments have a direct connection to unconventional superconducting materials, serving as an essential point of reference and a paradigm for their behavior, as well as impact on the physics of elementary particles.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts:</em></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This program has highlighted research training of two graduate students and includes the current participation of a local high school student through internship in the PI's laboratory performing advanced C++ numerical simulations of the gelation process of aerogelwhich have direct impact on superfluid science in our laboratory and others throughout the world.</p> <p>&nbsp;Our outreach to other science education programs have involved significant participation from elementary school students.&nbsp; In the past three years, acoustic research on aerogels was performed by three local high school students.&nbsp; Another success story involves three young girls, 7<sup>th</sup> grade students, who learned how to grow silica alcogels as part of their science projects. They entered a science competition that won state and regional championships a great trimph for dedicated elementary school students and mentoring from the graduate student team supported by this grant. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Research in quantum fluids and solids has broad impact on the condensed matter physics community.&nbsp; The importance of low temperature research and technology is manifest in the need for new instrumentation pushing limits in electron temperatures ever lower, the need for trained postdocs, new faculty appointments in experimental condensed matter physics, and recruitment of young theorists with background in many body physics, complex symmetry breaking and quantum phase transitions. We have shown that the paradigm of superfluid <sup>3</sup>He provides guidance to really challenging scientific problems ranging from quantum information science to materials physics.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/19/2019<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;P&nbsp;Halperin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit:  We have discovered how to stabilize new types of 3He superfluid phases exhibiting different spontaneous broken symmetries by engineering anisotropy through confinement of the superfluid in highly porous, anisotropic,  silica aerogels.  Quantum manipulation and control is at the heart of the new era of quantum information processing. We have demonstarted control of the angular momentum orientation In the quantum coherent superfluid B-phase using aerogel anisotropy and characterized by NMR spectra with very high resolution spectroscopy recently implemented with NSF support.  We have discovered a new critical magnetic field in 3He superfluid phases in anisotropic silica aerogel.  In this grant we have fully characterized the nature of this critical field and have traced its origin to the time-reversal symmetry breaking A-phase.  We have shown that the collective modes of pure 3He superfluid phases, where these modes are the intrinsic vibrations that are the fingerprint of the quantum order,  have frequencies that reveal the magnitude of the interactions that cause the superfluid to form with corrections for angular momentum channels that have not been observed previously.  These so-called massive modes are directly analogous to the Higgs modes of elementary particle physics responsible for their fundamental masses.  These accomplishments have a direct connection to unconventional superconducting materials, serving as an essential point of reference and a paradigm for their behavior, as well as impact on the physics of elementary particles.  Broader Impacts:        This program has highlighted research training of two graduate students and includes the current participation of a local high school student through internship in the PI's laboratory performing advanced C++ numerical simulations of the gelation process of aerogelwhich have direct impact on superfluid science in our laboratory and others throughout the world.   Our outreach to other science education programs have involved significant participation from elementary school students.  In the past three years, acoustic research on aerogels was performed by three local high school students.  Another success story involves three young girls, 7th grade students, who learned how to grow silica alcogels as part of their science projects. They entered a science competition that won state and regional championships a great trimph for dedicated elementary school students and mentoring from the graduate student team supported by this grant.          Research in quantum fluids and solids has broad impact on the condensed matter physics community.  The importance of low temperature research and technology is manifest in the need for new instrumentation pushing limits in electron temperatures ever lower, the need for trained postdocs, new faculty appointments in experimental condensed matter physics, and recruitment of young theorists with background in many body physics, complex symmetry breaking and quantum phase transitions. We have shown that the paradigm of superfluid 3He provides guidance to really challenging scientific problems ranging from quantum information science to materials physics.              Last Modified: 08/19/2019       Submitted by: William P Halperin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
