<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Three-dimensional nanoelectrodes for non-invasive intracellular electrophysiology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The drug development pipeline requires that potential drugs pass through a gamut of tests which demonstrate the drugs' efficacy and safety. The drug safety test starts from cellular studies before moving into animals and finally humans. As a drug moves from cellular measurements to animal measurements, the time and money involved increase dramatically. Therefore, it is essential to detect potential drug toxicity early on, preferably at the cellular level. The drug toxicity manifests mostly as non-specific binding to ion channels and therefore affecting cardiac action potentials. The current golden standard technique to detect action potential changes is patch clamps. However, the patch clamp has very low throughput and is challenging to implement, which limit the number of drug trials or drug candidates that can be screened. The proposed nanoelectrode device allows these companies to expedite testing and reduce the cost of cellular tests. In particular, nanoelectrodes can measure electrophysiology in high throughput and low toxicity and therefore allowing testers to measure more drugs with greater ease.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Current drug toxicology screens inevitably involve patch clamp electrophysiology to test off-target cardiac activity. Patch clamp is technically challenging to use and has limited multiplexing capability. Over the last six years, this group has worked to develop a new nanotechnology tool for electrophysiology. The proposed tool measures intracellular recordings of mammalian cells with high throughput and low requirements on technical capability in the experimenter. Signals recorded by these nanoelectrodes are carried out from the culture under test on metal leads and amplified at an external multi-electrode array (MEA) amplifier. This team expects to have customers in both pharmaceutical toxicology and academic laboratories who are interested in pursuing electrophysiological questions.  This team also believes that anyone interested in the initial screening of new drugs for their toxicological side effects would be interested in the proposed technology that could be integrated into automated cell culture systems and offers simple handling and experimentation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1602438</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bianxiao</FirstName>
<LastName>Cui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bianxiao Cui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bcui@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507259573</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Staford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943054401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[333 Campus Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Through the course of I-Corps, our team came to understand the impact that our vertical nanoelectrode technology could have on society. The following is a summary of what we learned from the variety of pharmaceutical employees, consultants, and regulators whom we interviewed, concluding with the steps we have taken towards commercialization with this in mind.</p> <p>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The early 1980&rsquo;s and 90&rsquo;s saw a rash of drugs withdrawn from the market for cardiotoxic side-effects which harmed scores of patients. Terfenadine is an oft-cited example which was marketed as a non-sedating antihistamine but induced many cases of long-QT syndrome in the global population.<sup>1,2</sup> As a result, the Food and Drug Administration and International Conference on Harmonization published outlining a battery of required tests which screen compounds at ascending levels of biological complexity and relevance to better characterize the safety of a compound before it reaches clinical trials.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In recent years, the hERG assay in particular has come under scrutiny for its potential to yield a high rate of false positives. The hERG channels are both promiscuous small molecule binders and cooperative components of a complex system of ion flux regulatory machinery in the cell membrane. This second fact has given way to the inadequacy of the hERG assay as the first cardiac safety screen in the course of a drug&rsquo;s development: there are multiple known examples of compounds which bind the hERG channels with high affinity (which would lead to a failing grade in the hERG assay) but show no cardiotoxic effects at the animal level due to the offsetting effects of other channels&rsquo; binding to the compound.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Such analysis has given rise to the Comprehensive <em>in vitro</em> Pro-arrhythmia Assay (CiPA) initiative. The first edition of the initiative in 2013 would enable pharmaceutical companies to revisit compounds they had eliminated from their pipelines solely due to the hERG assay.<sup>3</sup> The experimental onus of this new CiPA assay would be significantly greater than that of the current guidance. A hypothetical screening protocol would involve automated patch clamp on multiple heterologously expressing cell lines, computational simulation, and multielectrode array (MEA) and impedance measurement of high-purity stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>While the use of this variety of instruments is necessary given current technology, the nanopillar electrode array platform recently developed by our group and others<sup>4&ndash;6</sup> offers the opportunity to give multiplexed intracellular action potential measurements of single cardiomyocytes in a beating, confluent monolayer. This measurement would significantly reduce the workload brought by the CiPA initiative.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Using our grant from the I-Corps program, we completed a study comparing our technology to the precedent gold standard using pharmaceutically relevant cell types.<sup>7</sup> We were able to appropriately contextualize the work with the knowledge gained through I-Corps. The resultant paper acts as a sort of statement of merit for the technology which is vital in the pre-clinical medical device field. We additionally forged ahead to reduce the complexity of the nanofabrication process of the electrodes: a critical step in driving down cost and ensuring commercial viability.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Roy, M.-L. <em>et al.</em> <em>Circ. </em>&nbsp;<strong>94,</strong> 817&ndash;823 (1996).</p> <p>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Carter, C. A. <em>et al.</em> <em>Drug Intell. Clin. Pharm.</em> <strong>19,</strong> 812&ndash;817 (1985).</p> <p>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Sager, P. T. <em>et al.</em> <em>Am. Heart J.</em> <strong>167,</strong> 292&ndash;300 (2014).</p> <p>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Xie, C. <em>et al.</em> <em>Nat. Nanotechnol.</em> <strong>7,</strong> 185&ndash;90 (2012).</p> <p>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Lin, Z. C. <em>et al.</em> <em>Nat. Commun.</em> <strong>5,</strong> 1&ndash;10 (2014).</p> <p>6.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Hai, A. <em>et al.</em> <em>Lab Chip</em> <strong>12,</strong> 2865&ndash;73 (2012).</p> <p>7.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Lin, Z. C. <em>et al.</em> <em>Microsystems Nanoeng.</em> <strong>In press,</strong> (2017).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/16/2017<br>      Modified by: Bianxiao&nbsp;Cui</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Through the course of I-Corps, our team came to understand the impact that our vertical nanoelectrode technology could have on society. The following is a summary of what we learned from the variety of pharmaceutical employees, consultants, and regulators whom we interviewed, concluding with the steps we have taken towards commercialization with this in mind.    The early 1980?s and 90?s saw a rash of drugs withdrawn from the market for cardiotoxic side-effects which harmed scores of patients. Terfenadine is an oft-cited example which was marketed as a non-sedating antihistamine but induced many cases of long-QT syndrome in the global population.1,2 As a result, the Food and Drug Administration and International Conference on Harmonization published outlining a battery of required tests which screen compounds at ascending levels of biological complexity and relevance to better characterize the safety of a compound before it reaches clinical trials.              In recent years, the hERG assay in particular has come under scrutiny for its potential to yield a high rate of false positives. The hERG channels are both promiscuous small molecule binders and cooperative components of a complex system of ion flux regulatory machinery in the cell membrane. This second fact has given way to the inadequacy of the hERG assay as the first cardiac safety screen in the course of a drug?s development: there are multiple known examples of compounds which bind the hERG channels with high affinity (which would lead to a failing grade in the hERG assay) but show no cardiotoxic effects at the animal level due to the offsetting effects of other channels? binding to the compound.              Such analysis has given rise to the Comprehensive in vitro Pro-arrhythmia Assay (CiPA) initiative. The first edition of the initiative in 2013 would enable pharmaceutical companies to revisit compounds they had eliminated from their pipelines solely due to the hERG assay.3 The experimental onus of this new CiPA assay would be significantly greater than that of the current guidance. A hypothetical screening protocol would involve automated patch clamp on multiple heterologously expressing cell lines, computational simulation, and multielectrode array (MEA) and impedance measurement of high-purity stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes.   While the use of this variety of instruments is necessary given current technology, the nanopillar electrode array platform recently developed by our group and others4&ndash;6 offers the opportunity to give multiplexed intracellular action potential measurements of single cardiomyocytes in a beating, confluent monolayer. This measurement would significantly reduce the workload brought by the CiPA initiative.   Using our grant from the I-Corps program, we completed a study comparing our technology to the precedent gold standard using pharmaceutically relevant cell types.7 We were able to appropriately contextualize the work with the knowledge gained through I-Corps. The resultant paper acts as a sort of statement of merit for the technology which is vital in the pre-clinical medical device field. We additionally forged ahead to reduce the complexity of the nanofabrication process of the electrodes: a critical step in driving down cost and ensuring commercial viability.     1.        Roy, M.-L. et al. Circ.  94, 817&ndash;823 (1996).  2.        Carter, C. A. et al. Drug Intell. Clin. Pharm. 19, 812&ndash;817 (1985).  3.        Sager, P. T. et al. Am. Heart J. 167, 292&ndash;300 (2014).  4.        Xie, C. et al. Nat. Nanotechnol. 7, 185&ndash;90 (2012).  5.        Lin, Z. C. et al. Nat. Commun. 5, 1&ndash;10 (2014).  6.        Hai, A. et al. Lab Chip 12, 2865&ndash;73 (2012).  7.        Lin, Z. C. et al. Microsystems Nanoeng. In press, (2017).          Last Modified: 01/16/2017       Submitted by: Bianxiao Cui]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
