<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Proof-of-concept fiber-based miniature multiphoton microscope using adaptable optics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>222000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on combining miniature adaptable optics with multiphoton laser scanning microscopy to fill the need for a versatile, implantable, three-dimensional imaging system for studying brain activity in awake behaving animals. The fiber-coupled miniature multiphoton microscope is important because it allows neuroscientists an unprecedented ability to study dynamics of complex neuronal circuits while animals are undergoing different behavior tasks.  The project will result in a proof-of-concept demonstration of our product operating in freely moving animals.  The fiber-coupled miniature multiphoton microscope will allow full three-dimensional scanning through active focusing with no mechanically moving parts in a compact, light weight design.  The product can be readily connected to a commercial-laser scanning microscope. These features allow for reduced cost, flexibility in configuration of the wavelength or imaging modality to be performed, and can provide imaging over larger brain volumes when compared to the leading head-mounted microscope systems in this market space.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gaps as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application.  Although light microscopy has rapidly advanced for studies of biological systems, one major gap is the ability to use these advanced imaging tools for dynamic studies in the brain in freely moving animals.  We propose to combine the advantages of two-photon excitation with depth scanning using adaptive optics in a compact fiber-coupled design.  Current commercially available miniature microscopes only allow for single imaging planes, do not enable active focusing during imaging and do not allow both targeted imaging and optogenetic stimulation. The miniature multiphoton fiber-coupled microscope will use a fiber-bundle to translate the laser-scanned signal to the distal microscope head and miniature adaptable optical elements to provide fast active focusing. This will accomplish high versatility for applications such as fast region-of-interest imaging, optogenetic stimulation, and depth imaging with multiphoton techniques. Personnel involved in this project including undergraduate and graduate students, will receive experience in technology translation through meetings with business partners, attending technology conferences, and participating in outreach events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project engages 3i (Intelligent Imaging Innovations), an international company that specializes in delivering advanced optical microscope systems. This collaboration will allow implementation of this fiber-coupled microscope into commercial systems and speed delivery to a global commercial market.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1602128</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diego</FirstName>
<LastName>Restrepo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diego Restrepo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Diego.Restrepo@ucdenver.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037243405</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000182582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Bright</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor M Bright</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brightv@spot.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037351734</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417752</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Gibson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily Gibson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Emily.Gibson@ucdenver.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037243678</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000524694</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juliet</FirstName>
<LastName>Gopinath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juliet T Gopinath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>juliet.gopinath@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034925568</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545775</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Denver-Downtown Campus</Name>
<CityName>Aurora</CityName>
<ZipCode>800452571</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3037240090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>F428, AMC Bldg 500</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[13001 E 17th Place, Rm W1126]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>015634884</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Denver-Downtown Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Aurora</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>800452571</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12700 E. 19th Ave., Research 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8808</Code>
<Text>Veterans Research Supplements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~22000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The brain&rsquo;s complex neural networks perform critical functions that govern our behavior, cognition, and intuition and have not been understood or reproduced by artificial networks. To date, the complexity of the network&rsquo;s interactions has inhibited the formation of a theoretical framework. Further advances in neuroscience will rely on technologies enabling studies, in diverse species, of long-range interactions of neurons, spanning individual-individual interactions to emergent or large group level network analysis. Importantly, these advances require development of affordable cutting-edge technology to record and modulate neuronal activity in multiple brain areas.</p> <p>The goal of this project was to optimize and disseminate a technology developed through an NSF IDBR (Instrument Development for Biological Research) Grant, DBI-1353757, for a miniature fiber coupled multiphoton microscope using an adaptive electrowetting lens.&nbsp; The technology can achieve optical recording and optogenetic neuromodulation for use in studies in freely moving animals and opens up new opportunities to study brain networks during behavior.</p> <p>The major outcomes are:</p> <p>1.&nbsp; The project led to the development of a compact miniature two-photon fiber-coupled microscope (2P-FCM) to be easily integrated on any commercial multiphoton microscope system.&nbsp; This allows the technology to be distributed as an inexpensive add-on to current microscope systems to allow freely moving animal imaging.&nbsp;</p> <p>2.&nbsp; The project led to the first successful demonstration of the 2P-FCM with a tunable focus electrowetting lens for three-dimensional in vivo two-photon imaging of neural activity.</p> <p>3.&nbsp; Software was developed for image correction and removing pixelation through the fiber.&nbsp; The software is described in an open access publication (Ozbay et al., Scientific Reports 2018) and is freely available.</p> <p>4.&nbsp; The project connected university researchers with a local small business to take an idea from its conception into a real commercial product for wide dissemination.&nbsp; The technology optimized under this grant will continue towards commercialization through a Small Business Innovation Research grant that was recently awarded to the commercial partners, with potential for local job creation.</p> <p>5.&nbsp; The students involved in the project gained experience in technology transfer and the commercialization process that can assist them in future career opportunities.&nbsp; In fact, one of the students graduated and has taken an industry position with our small business partner.</p> <p>6.&nbsp; The project promoted science and engineering to the general public through laboratory tours for 50 high school girls for the annual Girl&rsquo;s Career Day (sponsored by University of Colorado Center for Women's Health Research) and through lab tours for high school students run by the University of Colorado Science Discovery Program.&nbsp;</p> <p>7.&nbsp; The project provided research and training opportunities for two graduate students and four undergraduate students including one veteran and two from underrepresented groups in science and engineering.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Gibson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The brain?s complex neural networks perform critical functions that govern our behavior, cognition, and intuition and have not been understood or reproduced by artificial networks. To date, the complexity of the network?s interactions has inhibited the formation of a theoretical framework. Further advances in neuroscience will rely on technologies enabling studies, in diverse species, of long-range interactions of neurons, spanning individual-individual interactions to emergent or large group level network analysis. Importantly, these advances require development of affordable cutting-edge technology to record and modulate neuronal activity in multiple brain areas.  The goal of this project was to optimize and disseminate a technology developed through an NSF IDBR (Instrument Development for Biological Research) Grant, DBI-1353757, for a miniature fiber coupled multiphoton microscope using an adaptive electrowetting lens.  The technology can achieve optical recording and optogenetic neuromodulation for use in studies in freely moving animals and opens up new opportunities to study brain networks during behavior.  The major outcomes are:  1.  The project led to the development of a compact miniature two-photon fiber-coupled microscope (2P-FCM) to be easily integrated on any commercial multiphoton microscope system.  This allows the technology to be distributed as an inexpensive add-on to current microscope systems to allow freely moving animal imaging.   2.  The project led to the first successful demonstration of the 2P-FCM with a tunable focus electrowetting lens for three-dimensional in vivo two-photon imaging of neural activity.  3.  Software was developed for image correction and removing pixelation through the fiber.  The software is described in an open access publication (Ozbay et al., Scientific Reports 2018) and is freely available.  4.  The project connected university researchers with a local small business to take an idea from its conception into a real commercial product for wide dissemination.  The technology optimized under this grant will continue towards commercialization through a Small Business Innovation Research grant that was recently awarded to the commercial partners, with potential for local job creation.  5.  The students involved in the project gained experience in technology transfer and the commercialization process that can assist them in future career opportunities.  In fact, one of the students graduated and has taken an industry position with our small business partner.  6.  The project promoted science and engineering to the general public through laboratory tours for 50 high school girls for the annual Girl?s Career Day (sponsored by University of Colorado Center for Women's Health Research) and through lab tours for high school students run by the University of Colorado Science Discovery Program.   7.  The project provided research and training opportunities for two graduate students and four undergraduate students including one veteran and two from underrepresented groups in science and engineering.       Last Modified: 04/01/2019       Submitted by: Emily Gibson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
