<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Virtual 3D reconstruction of hollow organs from white light endoscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>White light endoscope (WLE) is a medical device that allows physicians to conduct real-time video explorations of the interior of organs to detect disease or guide surgery. Unfortunately, the WLE video data are too cumbersome in their native form to review post-treatment; hence, the information is often reduced to handwritten notes or a few still-image frames for inclusion in medical records. The loss of this visually rich information limits the ability of WLE to inform clinical decisions about treatment and surgery. In particular, diseases like bladder cancer, which holds the unfortunate distinction as the 4th most common cancer in men and the highest treatment cost per patient-lifetime of all cancers, would benefit from novel ways to review WLE video data to facilitate early detection of tumors and to better track changes in the bladder wall of patients likely to experience recurrence (&gt; 50%). The goal of this project is to develop new technology to produce 3D visualizations of the interior of hollow organs such as the bladder from WLE videos. The availability of such technology will provide physicians with new tools to make better informed decisions about treatment and surgery, as well as provide researchers with new technology to enable novel studies on disease progression, ultimately leading to better health outcomes and lower treatment costs for diseases like cancer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed novel algorithm applies state-of-the-art techniques in computer vision to the problem of 3D reconstruction of the shape and surface appearance of hollow organs. A key innovation in the proposed approach is that the algorithm is suitable to reconstruct a full, 3D model of an organ from endoscopic video captured with standard clinical hardware and requires only minor modifications to the standard clinical workflow. The ability to create these reconstructions from standard equipment and workflows arises from careful design decisions regarding (1) the protocol for endoscopic video collection, (2) necessary image pre-processing steps and (3) the particular combination of state-of-the-art techniques developed in the computer vision community into an end-to-end pipeline unique for our application. In brief, the overall algorithm involves the following steps: down-sample raw image data, process selected frames, determine camera poses, extrapolate the organ surface as a mesh and apply image-based texture to the finalized mesh. The team's initial application is for reconstructing urinary bladder using standard rigid cystoscopy data; to date the team has validated the ability to perform 3D reconstructions using standard clinical cystoscopy videos of &gt; 30 human patients. As the proposed method can powerfully augment the visual medical record of internal organ appearance, it is broadly applicable to endoscopy and represents a significant advance in monitoring the appearance of a patient's organ over time, as may be well suited for applications such as cancer surveillance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1602118</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Audrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Audrey Bowden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>a.bowden@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153434339</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589217</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943054088</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Ginzton Lab,348 Via Pueblo Mall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The intellectual merit of this project was to develop new algorithms to enable 3D reconstructions of the bladder from cystoscopy videos. As part of the i-Corps program, during the project period our team of three (PI, student and business mentor) examined the degree to which these reconstructions could be easily integrated into the workflow of the standard of care for bladder cancer management. After conducting more than 100 interviews with doctors, residents, hospital administrators and industry representatives at endoscopy companies, we learned a great deal abotu the process for incorporating new technology into a hospital, including the chain of approval and barriers to adoption. Through our discussions, we also identified other clinical challenges that may be in more of a need for a current solution than what we proposed. Toward the end of the &nbsp;process, the team was asked to make a go-no go decision regarding whether to form a company based on this work. We decided that the current status of the work was in mor eneed of refinement and that a no-go decision was most appropriate. A portion of the project time was also dedicated to improvign the tehnology - which we learned is important to best showcase it to prospective users - and the end result was suitable for scientific publication and is currently in review at a relevant scientific journal.</p> <p>The broader impact of this work stems from the generalizable nature of the technology. Indeed, through discussion with potential users we learned that there is an aspect of it that is gneralizable; however, for the purpose of developing a viable business model we learned that it was most appropriate to focus on a specific use case. This fact limited the scope of the market that would be served by the technology and the potential broader impact in its current state.</p> <p>Summary of Outcomes:</p> <p>104 interviews with clinical staff, administrators, corporate reps</p> <p>New learning about hospital administrative procedures for adopting technology</p> <p>New learning about busines model canvas, hypothesis forming and testing</p> <p>Improved 3D reconstruction technology</p> <p>New learning about clinical pain points and prospective technology opportunities</p> <p>New learning about endoscopy company processes for adopting new technology</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Audrey&nbsp;Ellerbee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1602118/1602118_10403328_1473876260056_593_EndoSlam_12152015Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1602118/1602118_10403328_1473876260056_593_EndoSlam_12152015Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Team Intro Slide"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1602118/1602118_10403328_1473876260056_593_EndoSlam_12152015Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Team Intro Slide"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Endoslam Team and a brief graphic showing the nature of the technology and the overall final metrics for interviews.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristen Lurie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Audrey&nbsp;Ellerbee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Team Intro Slide</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1602118/1602118_10403328_1473876341580_593_EndoSlam_12092015Workflow--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1602118/1602118_10403328_1473876341580_593_EndoSlam_12092015Workflow--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hospital Tech Intro Workflow"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1602118/1602118_10403328_1473876341580_593_EndoSlam_12092015Workflow--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hospital Tech Intro Workflow"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Shows the completed workflow diagram we teased out as part of the program that underscores the players involved in introducing new technology into a hospital system.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristen Lurie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Audrey&nbsp;Ellerbee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hospital Tech Intro Workflow</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit of this project was to develop new algorithms to enable 3D reconstructions of the bladder from cystoscopy videos. As part of the i-Corps program, during the project period our team of three (PI, student and business mentor) examined the degree to which these reconstructions could be easily integrated into the workflow of the standard of care for bladder cancer management. After conducting more than 100 interviews with doctors, residents, hospital administrators and industry representatives at endoscopy companies, we learned a great deal abotu the process for incorporating new technology into a hospital, including the chain of approval and barriers to adoption. Through our discussions, we also identified other clinical challenges that may be in more of a need for a current solution than what we proposed. Toward the end of the  process, the team was asked to make a go-no go decision regarding whether to form a company based on this work. We decided that the current status of the work was in mor eneed of refinement and that a no-go decision was most appropriate. A portion of the project time was also dedicated to improvign the tehnology - which we learned is important to best showcase it to prospective users - and the end result was suitable for scientific publication and is currently in review at a relevant scientific journal.  The broader impact of this work stems from the generalizable nature of the technology. Indeed, through discussion with potential users we learned that there is an aspect of it that is gneralizable; however, for the purpose of developing a viable business model we learned that it was most appropriate to focus on a specific use case. This fact limited the scope of the market that would be served by the technology and the potential broader impact in its current state.  Summary of Outcomes:  104 interviews with clinical staff, administrators, corporate reps  New learning about hospital administrative procedures for adopting technology  New learning about busines model canvas, hypothesis forming and testing  Improved 3D reconstruction technology  New learning about clinical pain points and prospective technology opportunities  New learning about endoscopy company processes for adopting new technology       Last Modified: 09/14/2016       Submitted by: Audrey Ellerbee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
