<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Physics of Interacting Quantum Systems with Phase Transitions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>285000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>285000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research and education on quantum systems that have many interacting particles. The main goal is to identify the conditions for the onset of transitions between different states of organization of the constituent particles, and to put forward a set of proposals to detect such transitions experimentally. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In classical physics, a thermal phase transition occurs when the temperature of a material reaches a critical point and the material undergoes a change in state, such as the transition from water to ice. At very low temperatures, classical laws break down and quantum physics takes over. At that level, different quantum phases can emerge from the competition between different interactions in the system. Distinct phases are associated with different macroscopic properties that can be experimentally detected, such as good or bad conductivity. This topic of research is tightly connected with the development of new materials. New phases of matter are critical components of emerging technologies, which may revolutionize how we use and produce energy, may lead to new types of electronic devices, and may facilitate the scaling up of quantum computers. The potential economical and social impact of the discovery of novel phases of matter is immense. Yet, one needs to know where to look to have a higher chance to find them.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will also foster the participation of women in physics and improve the educational infrastructure at the Stern College for Women of Yeshiva University by offering new research opportunities and training in core areas of physics and in computational methods. Female undergraduate students will continue to coauthor papers with the PI and disseminate their results at conferences. Students from local high schools will also have the opportunity to experience research at Stern College for Women. This effort is facilitated by the PI's collaboration with three of her former students, who are now physics teachers in high schools for girls. Furthermore, the plan to expand a webpage designed for posting computer programs from courses and research findings will contribute to the integration of teaching and research at other undergraduate institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research and education on computational and analytical methods to advance our understanding of low-dimensional quantum systems with short- and long-range interactions. The focus will be on two main topics that carry potential to open new research avenues. They are:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Identifying the conditions for the onset of quantum phase transitions at excited states and putting forward a set of proposals to detect such transitions experimentally.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Studies of ground state quantum phase transitions are of crucial importance to fields as diverse as nuclear physics, condensed matter physics, and cosmology. Progress in this field may carry the key to unsolved problems in condensed matter physics and may lead to novel phases of matter. Recently, a new element has been brought to the picture: the existence of excited-state quantum phase transitions. They have mainly been examined in models from quantum optics, molecular and nuclear physics. This project will expand the analysis to also include condensed matter models. This will bring new perspectives, tools, and approaches to the understanding of many-body condensed matter systems as well as to the existing studies of excited-state quantum phase transitions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Exploring the counterintuitive scenario of achieving localization by increasing the range of the interactions, instead of increasing on-site disorder or the amplitude of the interactions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite innumerable studies about the metal-insulator transition, the subject is still partially understood. These transitions are usually divided in two categories: disorder-driven Anderson transitions and interaction-driven Mott transitions. The main current interest, however, is on the richer and more complicated case where both interaction and disorder are taken into account simultaneously. The usual expectation is that in the presence of long-range interactions, localization should become more difficult. Yet, long-range interactions can also lead to subspaces inside of which the states are highly localized. This project will explore new scenarios, such as the latter, which will bring a new viewpoint to the subject of localization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will also foster the participation of women in physics and improve the educational infrastructure at the Stern College for Women of Yeshiva University by offering new research opportunities and training in core areas of physics and in computational methods. Female undergraduate students will continue to coauthor papers with the PI and disseminate their results at conferences. Students from local high schools will also have the opportunity to experience research at Stern College for Women. This effort is facilitated by the PI's collaboration with three of her former students, who are now physics teachers in high schools for girls. Furthermore, the plan to expand a webpage designed for posting computer programs from courses and research findings will contribute to the integration of teaching and research at other undergraduate institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1603418</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lea</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferreira dos Santos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lea Ferreira dos Santos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lsantos2@yu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123407705</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000326361</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yeshiva University</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100333201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129605217</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 West 185th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071036636</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YESHIVA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071036636</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yeshiva University - Stern College for Women]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100164605</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[245 Lexington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~190000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This NSF grant funded research and educational activities in the area of quantum systems that have many interacting particles. Progress in this area may lead to new scientific and technological applications, such as the discovery of new phases of matter that may eventually lead to the production of new materials, and the development of efficient methods to store and transfer quantum information, which are needed for quantum simulators and quantum computers.<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; RESEARCH:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The group employed computational and analytical methods to advance our understanding of these many-body quantum systems. The activities resulted in 25 papers, 2 book chapters, 2 proceeding articles, and 56 talks, which attest for the success and impact of the project. Among the main outcomes, we mention:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; *) The derivation of an expression that describes the entire evolution of a quantity widely studied in many-body quantum dynamics, the so-called survival probability. With this expression, the group was able to identify the origin of different behaviors at different time scales and also to determine the time for the system to finally reach equilibrium. While previous studies based on analytical approximations or numerical simulations were contradictory, some indicating that the equilibration time should increase with system size and others that it should decrease, our expression demonstrates that the time increases exponentially with system size. The group was also able to provide a physical explanation for this fact.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; *) The conclusion that a quantity known as out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC), which has been studied in fields as diverse as condensed matter physics and high energy physics, is a detector of instability, rather than chaos. Classical chaos refers to the extreme sensitivity to initial conditions, which makes the prediction of the behavior of some systems very difficult, such as the weather, spread of diseases, and population growth. There has been great interest in extending this notion to the quantum domain, especially to many-body quantum physics. It was recently proposed that the exponential growth of the OTOC should be a quantum signature of classical chaos. During the period of the grant, the PI studied this quantity theoretically and experimentally with various collaborators. An important conclusion was that the OTOC shows exponential behavior not only for chaotic systems, but also for non-chaotic systems at a point that separates them in two different quantum phases. This is a point of instability of the system, not necessarily of chaotic behavior.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Various new questions have also emerged from these studies and resulted in a new proposal involving a collaboration with Israel. The recently accepted NSF-BSF grant will guarantee the continuation of the PI's research and educational activities.<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; TRAINING and EDUCATION:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; *) The grant was used to train a postdoctoral fellow, who was assisted in all the steps of his interviews for employment. He is now an editor for the Physical Review X, a prestigious journal of the American Physical Society. <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; *) The grant made it possible for the PI to extend her continuous efforts to foster the participation of women in STEM fields by engaging female undergraduate students in her research projects. She worked with 5 female undergraduate students (Miriam Baitner, Eliana Feifel, Shira Segal, Aviva Shooman, and Chemda Wiener) and 2 male undergraduate students (Bar Alluf and Jechiel Van Dijk). Three of them have graduated and are now studying for a Master in Computer Science, a Master in Biomedical Engineering, and a PhD in Physics. Two of the female students prepared talks for the March Meeting. <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; *) To modernize the curriculum at Stern College for Women, the PI created a course called &ldquo;Computational Methods in Scientific Research&rdquo;, which is entirely in Python and attended by science and computer science majors. <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; *) Together with a Math junior professor, the PI helped students from Stern College for Women to organize a Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) Chapter. This will allow them to have visitors from other universities, to learn about topics of their interest in math and computer science, and to network with students from other SIAM chapters.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2020<br>      Modified by: Lea&nbsp;Ferreira Dos Santos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     This NSF grant funded research and educational activities in the area of quantum systems that have many interacting particles. Progress in this area may lead to new scientific and technological applications, such as the discovery of new phases of matter that may eventually lead to the production of new materials, and the development of efficient methods to store and transfer quantum information, which are needed for quantum simulators and quantum computers.      RESEARCH:     The group employed computational and analytical methods to advance our understanding of these many-body quantum systems. The activities resulted in 25 papers, 2 book chapters, 2 proceeding articles, and 56 talks, which attest for the success and impact of the project. Among the main outcomes, we mention:     *) The derivation of an expression that describes the entire evolution of a quantity widely studied in many-body quantum dynamics, the so-called survival probability. With this expression, the group was able to identify the origin of different behaviors at different time scales and also to determine the time for the system to finally reach equilibrium. While previous studies based on analytical approximations or numerical simulations were contradictory, some indicating that the equilibration time should increase with system size and others that it should decrease, our expression demonstrates that the time increases exponentially with system size. The group was also able to provide a physical explanation for this fact.     *) The conclusion that a quantity known as out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC), which has been studied in fields as diverse as condensed matter physics and high energy physics, is a detector of instability, rather than chaos. Classical chaos refers to the extreme sensitivity to initial conditions, which makes the prediction of the behavior of some systems very difficult, such as the weather, spread of diseases, and population growth. There has been great interest in extending this notion to the quantum domain, especially to many-body quantum physics. It was recently proposed that the exponential growth of the OTOC should be a quantum signature of classical chaos. During the period of the grant, the PI studied this quantity theoretically and experimentally with various collaborators. An important conclusion was that the OTOC shows exponential behavior not only for chaotic systems, but also for non-chaotic systems at a point that separates them in two different quantum phases. This is a point of instability of the system, not necessarily of chaotic behavior.     Various new questions have also emerged from these studies and resulted in a new proposal involving a collaboration with Israel. The recently accepted NSF-BSF grant will guarantee the continuation of the PI's research and educational activities.      TRAINING and EDUCATION:     *) The grant was used to train a postdoctoral fellow, who was assisted in all the steps of his interviews for employment. He is now an editor for the Physical Review X, a prestigious journal of the American Physical Society.      *) The grant made it possible for the PI to extend her continuous efforts to foster the participation of women in STEM fields by engaging female undergraduate students in her research projects. She worked with 5 female undergraduate students (Miriam Baitner, Eliana Feifel, Shira Segal, Aviva Shooman, and Chemda Wiener) and 2 male undergraduate students (Bar Alluf and Jechiel Van Dijk). Three of them have graduated and are now studying for a Master in Computer Science, a Master in Biomedical Engineering, and a PhD in Physics. Two of the female students prepared talks for the March Meeting.      *) To modernize the curriculum at Stern College for Women, the PI created a course called "Computational Methods in Scientific Research", which is entirely in Python and attended by science and computer science majors.      *) Together with a Math junior professor, the PI helped students from Stern College for Women to organize a Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) Chapter. This will allow them to have visitors from other universities, to learn about topics of their interest in math and computer science, and to network with students from other SIAM chapters.       Last Modified: 06/07/2020       Submitted by: Lea Ferreira Dos Santos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
