<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Computational and Experimental Investigation of High-Flux Heating of Supercritical Fluids in Microscale Geometries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>153277.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>153277</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ying Sun</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yisun@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computational and Experimental Investigation of High-Flux Heating of Supercritical Fluids in Microscale Geometries&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At a sufficiently high temperature and pressure, fluids become supercritical. When a supercritical fluid is heated, it does not undergo a change in phase from a liquid to vapor like in familiar boiling processes. Rather the fluid undergoes a continuous transition from "liquid like" to "gas like" properties without the formation of bubbles. During this "pseudo-critical" transition, the fluid can absorb a great quantity of heat per degree of temperature increase, which potentially enables new high-intensity heat transfer technologies without the instabilities, critical heat flux, and maldistribution issues that cause challenges in two-phase boiling solutions. By harnessing the unique properties of supercritical fluids, it may be possible to further develop higher power, compact computer chips and more efficient high temperature solar thermal systems. To explore these possibilities, the research team will study a new thermal management framework employing supercritical carbon dioxide (sCO2) in the pseudo-critical region (7.5 ? 8.5 MPa, 30 ? 40°C) in microscale flow geometries. Under these conditions sCO2 has extremely high volumetric heat capacity and thermal conductivity, enabling management of high heat fluxes (~500 W cm-2). New engineering resources and models formulated in this study will enable rapid adoption of supercritical cooling in real-world technologies. Additionally, improved understanding of microscale supercritical fluid transport can yield advances in diverse technologies including enhanced oil extraction, near-zero global warming potential (GWP) supercritical refrigeration and power cycles, and solvent/impregnation processes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team will conduct an integrated experimental and computational investigation to elucidate the complex governing phenomena during heating of sCO2 and general supercritical fluids at pseudocritical conditions in microscale geometries. Local fast-response temperature measurements and infrared thermal imaging will resolve the existence of, and quantify the effects of key supercritical phenomena at this scale, including pseudo-boiling, intrinsic flow pulsations, heat-transfer enhancement and/or deterioration due to sharp property variations, pin-fin wake interactions, and conjugate heat transfer effects. Experiments will be conducted with supercritical CO2 at high pressure (75 &lt; P &lt; 200 bar) and heat fluxes, and microfabrication techniques will be leveraged to explore advanced geometries of interest for electronics cooling and solar thermal applications. Extensive detached eddy simulation (DES) computations will be performed to provide detailed local flow data to complement experiments, and enable generalization beyond specific working fluids and operating conditions. DES represents a new approach to study supercritical convective transport that captures key unsteady turbulent phenomena in the channel bulk, unlike Reynolds averaged formulations employed in previous studies, but without the extreme computational costs of LES/DNS that also fully resolve near-wall regions. Once experimentally validated, simulations will be employed to extend results to supercritical flows with diverse configurations and geometries. In these studies individual fluid property trends will be modulated independently to isolate and quantify critical effects that have previously only been characterized through lumped parameter descriptions. This approach will enable generalization of results to the broader family of supercritical flows, rather than just specific fluids employed in experiments. Integration of detailed experimental and computational data will yield consolidated analytical transport models, facilitating rapid translation of fundamental research to practical thermal management technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1604538</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Rattner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander S Rattner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ASR20@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148634387</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000703137</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~153277</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Motivation and Overview:<br />The overall goal of this research project was to develop and apply computational methods to understand heat transfer processes of supercritical fluid flows in microscale geometries for emerging thermal energy technologies. Above a specific pressure and temperature (the "critical point"), fluids become "supercritical" and no longer undergo sharp liquid-to-gas phase change during heating. At near critical conditions, supercritical fluids have extreme capacity for heat absorption and low resistance to flow. This leads to the motivating hypothesis of this project, which is that supercritical fluids have potential to effectively cool emerging high power electronic devices more effectively than existing solutions. Supercritical fluid technologies are also being explored for renewable power generation and high performance propulsion systems. However, there was minimal data available for the behavior of supercritical fluids in microscale high-intensity flow geometries that would be used in such applications. To address this need, the project team performed high-resolution simulations of supercritical CO2 transport to understand unique transport physics and develop practical resources for thermal engineering. This work was conducted collaboratively with an experimental team at Oregon State University, who provided key validation data for simulations.<br /><br />Technical Outcomes:<br />First, the project team implemented a large-eddy simulation (LES) approach to study turbulent supercritical fluid flow in microchannels with high heat fluxes, accounting for coupled heat transfer in solid domains. The approach was validated with experimental data from colleagues at Oregon State. An open source software library for supercritical properties with demonstration cases was published to enable other researchers to apply this methodology. Computations were then performed to determine the independent effects of flow rate, pressure, heat flux, and gravity on supercritical heat transfer in microchannels. "Maps" were formed to help engineers predict the presence of flow phenomena that can affect heat transfer performance. Guidelines were proposed to identify the most appropriate analytic heat transfer design models for different operating conditions. Additionally, first-of-kind studies were performed of supercritical transport in enhanced configurations with pin-fin arrays and jet impingement. Findings from these studies can help push the boundaries of high-intensity heat transfer equipment. Results were disseminated to the research community through multiple conference presentations and papers, an archival journal publication (additional papers anticipated), and in a MS thesis and PhD dissertation.<br /><br />Broader Impacts:<br />Motivated by the fundamental findings from this investigation, private funding has been awarded to the team to develop prototype supercritical-fluid-based cooling systems for high power electronics. This may lead to a fielded commercial solution for extreme thermal management systems. This project supported the PhD training of a student who is now applying their expertise to thermal management of emerging 5G wireless communication systems. This project also supported the training of a MS student who seeks to pursue a PhD in thermal sciences. An undergraduate student was supported for a summer research assistantship that provided valuable practical training for their career in Mechanical Engineering. Finally, this project supported the development of an interactive schlieren imaging exhibit for the Discovery Space of Central Pennsylvania. This exhibit allows intuitive exploration and visualization of normally invisible heat transfer and fluid flow processes. The Discovery Space has over 600 member families and a large visitor base. We hope that the exhibit will excite museum visitors about science and motivate young people to pursue further education and careers in STEM.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;S&nbsp;Rattner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613312580194_Fig-1-LESRendering--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613312580194_Fig-1-LESRendering--rgov-800width.jpg" title="LES Microchannel Rendering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613312580194_Fig-1-LESRendering--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="LES Microchannel Rendering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Representative rendering of velocity contours in turbulent supercritical CO2 microchannel flow.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Nabil, A.S. Rattner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;S&nbsp;Rattner</div> <div class="imageTitle">LES Microchannel Rendering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613312815950_Fig-2-Pin-FinRendering--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613312815950_Fig-2-Pin-FinRendering--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pin Fin Rendering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613312815950_Fig-2-Pin-FinRendering--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pin Fin Rendering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Representative rendering of heat flux, temperature, and velocity contours for supercritical CO2 flow and heat transfer through a pin-fin enhanced microscale passage.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Nabil, A.S. Rattner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;S&nbsp;Rattner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pin Fin Rendering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613313180207_Fig-3-JetImpingementRendering--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613313180207_Fig-3-JetImpingementRendering--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Jet Impingement Rendering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613313180207_Fig-3-JetImpingementRendering--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Jet Impingement Rendering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Representative rendering of velocity contours for supercritical CO2 jet impingement heat transfer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. AlKandari, A.S. Rattner</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;S&nbsp;Rattner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Jet Impingement Rendering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613313915829_Fig-4-SchlierenImagingExhibit--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613313915829_Fig-4-SchlierenImagingExhibit--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Schlieren Imaging Exhibit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1604538/1604538_10450963_1613313915829_Fig-4-SchlierenImagingExhibit--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Schlieren Imaging Exhibit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schlieren imaging exhibit installed at the Discovery Space of Central PA children's science museum. This exhibit allows interactive exploration of fluid flows due to heat transfer and natural convection. Representative images of convection from a lit match and hair dryer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A.S Rattner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;S&nbsp;Rattner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Schlieren Imaging Exhibit</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Motivation and Overview: The overall goal of this research project was to develop and apply computational methods to understand heat transfer processes of supercritical fluid flows in microscale geometries for emerging thermal energy technologies. Above a specific pressure and temperature (the "critical point"), fluids become "supercritical" and no longer undergo sharp liquid-to-gas phase change during heating. At near critical conditions, supercritical fluids have extreme capacity for heat absorption and low resistance to flow. This leads to the motivating hypothesis of this project, which is that supercritical fluids have potential to effectively cool emerging high power electronic devices more effectively than existing solutions. Supercritical fluid technologies are also being explored for renewable power generation and high performance propulsion systems. However, there was minimal data available for the behavior of supercritical fluids in microscale high-intensity flow geometries that would be used in such applications. To address this need, the project team performed high-resolution simulations of supercritical CO2 transport to understand unique transport physics and develop practical resources for thermal engineering. This work was conducted collaboratively with an experimental team at Oregon State University, who provided key validation data for simulations.  Technical Outcomes: First, the project team implemented a large-eddy simulation (LES) approach to study turbulent supercritical fluid flow in microchannels with high heat fluxes, accounting for coupled heat transfer in solid domains. The approach was validated with experimental data from colleagues at Oregon State. An open source software library for supercritical properties with demonstration cases was published to enable other researchers to apply this methodology. Computations were then performed to determine the independent effects of flow rate, pressure, heat flux, and gravity on supercritical heat transfer in microchannels. "Maps" were formed to help engineers predict the presence of flow phenomena that can affect heat transfer performance. Guidelines were proposed to identify the most appropriate analytic heat transfer design models for different operating conditions. Additionally, first-of-kind studies were performed of supercritical transport in enhanced configurations with pin-fin arrays and jet impingement. Findings from these studies can help push the boundaries of high-intensity heat transfer equipment. Results were disseminated to the research community through multiple conference presentations and papers, an archival journal publication (additional papers anticipated), and in a MS thesis and PhD dissertation.  Broader Impacts: Motivated by the fundamental findings from this investigation, private funding has been awarded to the team to develop prototype supercritical-fluid-based cooling systems for high power electronics. This may lead to a fielded commercial solution for extreme thermal management systems. This project supported the PhD training of a student who is now applying their expertise to thermal management of emerging 5G wireless communication systems. This project also supported the training of a MS student who seeks to pursue a PhD in thermal sciences. An undergraduate student was supported for a summer research assistantship that provided valuable practical training for their career in Mechanical Engineering. Finally, this project supported the development of an interactive schlieren imaging exhibit for the Discovery Space of Central Pennsylvania. This exhibit allows intuitive exploration and visualization of normally invisible heat transfer and fluid flow processes. The Discovery Space has over 600 member families and a large visitor base. We hope that the exhibit will excite museum visitors about science and motivate young people to pursue further education and careers in STEM.       Last Modified: 02/14/2021       Submitted by: Alexander S Rattner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
