<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Langevin Subgrid Scale Closure and Discontinuous Galerkin Exascale Large Eddy Simulation of Complex Turbulent Flows</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>35365.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>35365</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harsha Chelliah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1603131/1603589/1604142  &lt;br/&gt;Givi/Mavriplis/Girimaji&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Turbulent combustion is encountered in nearly all energy conversion devices, such as internal combustion engines, gas turbines, boilers, and gas burners. Turbulent combustion involves many complex physical and chemical phenomena. The ability to predict accurately the turbulent combustion process is critical to the design and optimization of combustion devices for achieving low emissions and high efficiency. This research will develop accurate computer models and numerical algorithms that can reveal the fundamental turbulent combustion processes and allow industry to design clean combustion devices, thus benefiting the environment. Extensive code development and computer simulations will be conducted. Additionally, this project will also include numerous education and outreach activities, including the development of an Interdisciplinary Computational Science Minor to provide additional courses on high-performance computing, student training in the multidisciplinary field of Computational Modeling and Simulation, K-12 outreach through the INVESTING NOW and CAMP-SOAR programs, and recruitment of students from minority and under-represented groups through the EXCEL program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In an effort to increase the accuracy of turbulent combustion simulation, this award provides funding to develop a new Langevin subgrid scale (SGS) closure and to implement it with a new discontinuous Galerkin numerical scheme for large eddy simulation  (LES) of turbulent flows. The former provides accurate modeling of the SGS transport for a wide range of turbulent flows, including compressible and chemically reactive. The combined methodology will be put together in a package in which the available computational cores are utilized in a dynamic, adaptive manner. This is an important concept in high performance computing necessary for massively parallel simulations up to petascale, and towards (future) exascale. The new LES tool will be employed for predictions of several turbulent flows. The computational requirements for the proposed LES, in its most sophisticated form and utilizing the highest intended resolution, will be several orders of magnitude less than that required for direct numerical simulations. When successfully completed, this research will have a significant impact on turbulent combustion research.  It will be extremely valuable for both industry and government agencies. The outcome of this work can also positively impact other disciplines, such as climate and atmospheric modeling or bioengineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1604142</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharath</FirstName>
<LastName>Girimaji</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharath S Girimaji</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>girimaji@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798451674</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000124893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3141 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~35365</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI served as a consultant in this research project. The outcomes include: (1) Adaptation of a closure model for rapid pressure-strain correlation in compressible flows to Langevin equation; (2) Identification of different pathways of interaction between kinetic and internal energy - including pressure-dilatation; and (i3) Characterization of scalar mixing efficiencies of different compressible local topologies.&nbsp;</p> <p>The rapid pressure-strain correlation model incorporates different physics in different Mach number regimes. At low Mach numbers, the model reduces to well-known incompressible model. In the limit of high Mach number, the pressure effects vanish as the inertial effects (production) is significantly larger. At intermediate Reynolds numbers (Ma ~ 1), the wave-like character of pressure nullifies some of the production. This leads to reduced kinetic energy growth rate. Attempts were made to incorporate these effects into a Langevin model.</p> <p>A framework for the analysis of different pathways of interaction between internal and kinetic energy was developed. A new turbulent internal energy variable was developed. The key feature of this formulation is that the sum of internal and kinetic energy is conserved. This framework aslo enables clear identification of different pathways of interaction between internal and kinetic modes of energy in a compressible, reacting flow field.</p> <p>An analytical approach was developed to characterize and quantify the capability of different compressible flow topologies to enhance scalar mixing at the small scales (molecular mixing).&nbsp; The mixing capabilities of different solenoidal and dilatational topologies were established.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2020<br>      Modified by: Sharath&nbsp;S&nbsp;Girimaji</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI served as a consultant in this research project. The outcomes include: (1) Adaptation of a closure model for rapid pressure-strain correlation in compressible flows to Langevin equation; (2) Identification of different pathways of interaction between kinetic and internal energy - including pressure-dilatation; and (i3) Characterization of scalar mixing efficiencies of different compressible local topologies.   The rapid pressure-strain correlation model incorporates different physics in different Mach number regimes. At low Mach numbers, the model reduces to well-known incompressible model. In the limit of high Mach number, the pressure effects vanish as the inertial effects (production) is significantly larger. At intermediate Reynolds numbers (Ma ~ 1), the wave-like character of pressure nullifies some of the production. This leads to reduced kinetic energy growth rate. Attempts were made to incorporate these effects into a Langevin model.  A framework for the analysis of different pathways of interaction between internal and kinetic energy was developed. A new turbulent internal energy variable was developed. The key feature of this formulation is that the sum of internal and kinetic energy is conserved. This framework aslo enables clear identification of different pathways of interaction between internal and kinetic modes of energy in a compressible, reacting flow field.  An analytical approach was developed to characterize and quantify the capability of different compressible flow topologies to enhance scalar mixing at the small scales (molecular mixing).  The mixing capabilities of different solenoidal and dilatational topologies were established.       Last Modified: 04/07/2020       Submitted by: Sharath S Girimaji]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
