<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Integrated Microfluidic System for Cell Separation and Enrichment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating an integrated microfluidic device capable of processing milliliters of whole blood by rapidly isolating and enriching rare cells (such as circulating tumor cells, CTCs), resulting in faster sample preparation for high fidelity diagnostic and prognostic measurements that are critically needed in many therapeutic applications.  This integrated microfluidic platform is important due to the direct impact on cancer patients and supporting infrastructure resulting from bringing this game-changing microfluidic device to market. Patient diagnosis and monitoring would become simpler, cheaper, faster, and more convenient. Moreover, the usage of this microfluidic platform is not limited to cancer diagnosis, but extends to any disease or condition measured via changes in cellular physical properties in a sample of biological fluid. The project will result in an optimized, integrated cell separator and enrichment prototype microfluidic device. The team will demonstrate its utility with clinically relevant levels of CTCs in whole blood to determine its feasibility for improved cancer diagnosis and monitoring. This integrated microfluidic device has the following unique features: (a) label-free cell separation, enrichment, and release, (b) clinical scale sample volumes and single pass through device to achieve complete cell isolation and enrichment (100% target capture) in approximately 20 minutes, and (c) device is amenable to mass production. When compared to the leading competing methods for CTC isolation and purification from whole blood in this market space, these features provide the following advantages: (a) simpler operation, (b) quicker, more reliable test results, and (c) lower cost per test and small form factor towards a potentially portable system for use in various point-of-care applications or resource limited settings.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main technology gaps to be addressed during the project are associated with optimizing the microfluidic device to achieve the rigorous performance levels required for CTC analysis (isolate and enrich 5 CTCs/7.5mL whole blood for downstream detection). These gaps will be bridged by having multiple integrated microfluidic devices working simultaneously in parallel and improving the sensitivity of the device to sufficiently separate and capture cells of similar size. In addition, personnel involved in this project, especially undergraduate students, graduate students, and post-docs, will gain innovation and technology translation experiences. They will become well versed in microfluidic cell sorting, enrichment, chip design, manufacturing, and the needs of primary end-users in multiple business spaces around the world. They will also gain firsthand experience in working in a multidisciplinary academic-industrial environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1604014</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abraham</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abraham P Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aplee@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498248155</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219062</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>Papautsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ian Papautsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>papauts@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3124133800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000090207</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Natural Sciences II, UCI-402]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit: To demonstrate separation of beads from diluted blood, 15 &micro;m polystyrene beads, which emulate the size of Circulating Tumor Cells (CTCs), were spiked into diluted blood. Three blood dilutions &ndash; 3&times;, 5&times;, 10&times; were used for the demonstrations of beads separation and to investigate the yield of polystyrene beads from low dilutions of blood. Typically, in inertial microfluidics blood dilutions of 20-200&times; are used, for high separation efficiency and purity, as shown in our previous work [1]. We spiked beads at three different concentrations of, 1,000, 10,000 and 25,000 cell/mL.&nbsp;High separation efficiency of beads is achieved using the iMF chip at the flow conditions mentioned earlier (Fig. 1). No beads are lost in Outlet 1 or Outlet 3 of the parallel array chip. Our results show that at CTC separation is not affected at lower dilution of 3&times; or 5&times;.&nbsp; With lower blood dilution RBC removal efficiency gets reduced. This is due to particle-particle interaction at higher concentration of RBC, which flow into the &ldquo;CTC&rdquo; outlet.&nbsp; As a result, Enrichment ratio of the collected sample from Outlet 2 also reduces at lower concentrations of beads/mL (Fig. 2).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact:&nbsp;Under this project, Graduate Student Researcher Neha Garg received IRB approval for the usage and handling of bloodsamples from healthy blood donors. This approval allows us to use whole blood samples in our experiments to realisticallytest the device. In addition, all the researchers were required to complete the blood safety training under EH&amp;S at UCI. All&nbsp;researchers Neha Garg, and Prithviraj Mukherjee gave presentations to the industrial partner Frank Narz at Qiagen, gaining experience in monthly teleconferences. Finally, Neha Garg gained experience in presenting research and networking at The 21st International Conference on Miniaturized Systems for Chemistry and Life Sciences (&mu;TAS 2017, Savannah, Georgia),while all three graduate researchers also gained this experience at the CADMIM semiannual IAB meetings.&nbsp;Monthly update reports for this project were presented to industrial collaborator Qiagen. In addition, graduate student researchers Dylan Boyle, Neha Garg, and Prithviraj Mukherjee have also presented project related posters at the semiannual IndustrialReview Board meetings for CADMIM (2016-2018).&nbsp;One of the broader impacts of this project will be to bridge the gap between academia and industry. Through direct, regular interaction with UCI, UIC, and Qiagen researchers, all students will gain firsthand knowledge of the business aspects and technical challenges in commercial CTC screening. The CADMIM NSF I/UCRC will also provide opportunities to interact with other companies that have interest in diagnostic applications, possibly leading to new ideas and complimentary innovations.Through the UCI-UIC-Qiagen partnership students will become well versed in designing and manufacturing state-of-the-art microfluidic cell sorting and enrichment.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2018<br>      Modified by: Abraham&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1604014/1604014_10419630_1535957705304_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1604014/1604014_10419630_1535957705304_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1604014/1604014_10419630_1535957705304_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Bead separation in Five parallel channel array</div> <div class="imageCredit">Abraham P. Lee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Abraham&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1604014/1604014_10419630_1535958035236_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1604014/1604014_10419630_1535958035236_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1604014/1604014_10419630_1535958035236_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Concentration of cells/beads at inlet and outlet with a 15 µm suspension of 1000 beads/mL.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Abraham P. Lee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Abraham&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: To demonstrate separation of beads from diluted blood, 15 &micro;m polystyrene beads, which emulate the size of Circulating Tumor Cells (CTCs), were spiked into diluted blood. Three blood dilutions &ndash; 3&times;, 5&times;, 10&times; were used for the demonstrations of beads separation and to investigate the yield of polystyrene beads from low dilutions of blood. Typically, in inertial microfluidics blood dilutions of 20-200&times; are used, for high separation efficiency and purity, as shown in our previous work [1]. We spiked beads at three different concentrations of, 1,000, 10,000 and 25,000 cell/mL. High separation efficiency of beads is achieved using the iMF chip at the flow conditions mentioned earlier (Fig. 1). No beads are lost in Outlet 1 or Outlet 3 of the parallel array chip. Our results show that at CTC separation is not affected at lower dilution of 3&times; or 5&times;.  With lower blood dilution RBC removal efficiency gets reduced. This is due to particle-particle interaction at higher concentration of RBC, which flow into the "CTC" outlet.  As a result, Enrichment ratio of the collected sample from Outlet 2 also reduces at lower concentrations of beads/mL (Fig. 2).      Broader Impact: Under this project, Graduate Student Researcher Neha Garg received IRB approval for the usage and handling of bloodsamples from healthy blood donors. This approval allows us to use whole blood samples in our experiments to realisticallytest the device. In addition, all the researchers were required to complete the blood safety training under EH&amp;S at UCI. All researchers Neha Garg, and Prithviraj Mukherjee gave presentations to the industrial partner Frank Narz at Qiagen, gaining experience in monthly teleconferences. Finally, Neha Garg gained experience in presenting research and networking at The 21st International Conference on Miniaturized Systems for Chemistry and Life Sciences (&mu;TAS 2017, Savannah, Georgia),while all three graduate researchers also gained this experience at the CADMIM semiannual IAB meetings. Monthly update reports for this project were presented to industrial collaborator Qiagen. In addition, graduate student researchers Dylan Boyle, Neha Garg, and Prithviraj Mukherjee have also presented project related posters at the semiannual IndustrialReview Board meetings for CADMIM (2016-2018). One of the broader impacts of this project will be to bridge the gap between academia and industry. Through direct, regular interaction with UCI, UIC, and Qiagen researchers, all students will gain firsthand knowledge of the business aspects and technical challenges in commercial CTC screening. The CADMIM NSF I/UCRC will also provide opportunities to interact with other companies that have interest in diagnostic applications, possibly leading to new ideas and complimentary innovations.Through the UCI-UIC-Qiagen partnership students will become well versed in designing and manufacturing state-of-the-art microfluidic cell sorting and enrichment.       Last Modified: 09/03/2018       Submitted by: Abraham P Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
