<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Coordinated Experiments and Simulations of Near-Surface Turbulent Flow over Barchan Dunes: Informing Models of Dune Migration and Interaction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29063.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29063</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI:  Christensen, Kenneth / Best, James / Anderson, William&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1603211 / 1604155 / 1603254&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The focus of the proposed research is to explore the migration of sand dunes in large scale, desert environments or ocean floor environments. The proposed collaborative approach involves experiments, theory and simulations to understand the process of dune migration under turbulent flow. The findings of this work can be important for Aeolian dune migration, a problem that can be critical to predicting and mitigating desertification as it occurs in the Western US and in other places in the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding and predicting the morphodynamics of subaqueous barchan dunes is critical for management of waterways and quantifying transport of nutrients and pollutants. Similarly, understanding these processes for aeolian barchan dunes is important for characterizing desertification processes and for informing numerical weather prediction. At large dune spacings, barchan kinematics can be accurately predicted using sediment transport models predicated on mean bed shear stress. However, barchans typically occur in fields. Since dune migration rate is size dependent, a heterogeneous dune field will result in variable bedform spacing, with smaller (faster) dunes approaching larger (slower) dunes. Thus, when two dunes are in close proximity, the upstream one will produce an unsteady, turbulent wake that will sculpt the morphology of the downstream one, introducing significant morphological complexity owing to spatially-heterogeneous turbulence. Such effects are not captured by current state-of-the-art models. (These approaches simulate the bedform evolution but do not resolve the overlying flow; they instead use a spatially homogeneous representation of turbulence as the flow input). Informed by preliminary research, and compelled by deficiencies in existing dune modeling approaches, it is hypothesized that the "missing link" to elucidating the morphodynamics of interacting barchan dunes is the unsteady nature of the turbulence generated within the inter-dune space. It is proposed to pursue a collaborative research effort that leverages an innovative measurement protocol and scientific computing, complemented by observations in nature. The results will transform the understanding of dune-dune flow field interactions for fixed-bed dunes as a function of proximity and volumetric ratio and will form the basis for advancing morphodynamic models. Planar and volumetric PIV measurements will be conducted in a refractive-index-matched environment (allowing unprecedented optical access to the flow) for targeted dune configurations. These experiments will validate large-eddy simulations that will enable larger spatial volumes and a much broader suite of dune field parameters to be explored, with the latter informed by field observations. The culminating task will involve incorporating the turbulence heterogeneity identified into existing morphodynamic models to test the hypothesis.  The proposed work will have an impact not only in fluid dynamics through its impact on engineering turbulent flows, but also to other disciplines including boundary-layer meteorology, geomorphology and sedimentology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1604155</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Best</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James L Best</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jimbest@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172441839</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 S. First Street, Suite A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~29063</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Barchan dunes are three-dimensional, crescent-shaped bedforms that form in a wide range of environments, including eolian deserts, fluvial channels, continental shelves, and other planetary surfaces. Barchan dunes have been described from the deserts of Earth and the craters of Mars.</p> <p>The primary aim of this research was to investigate the structure of turbulent flow associated with interacting barchan dunes, and how turbulence affects the nature of such barchan-barchan interactions. Barchan dunes are typically formed under unidirectional flows, but in environments where there is a limited sand supply &ndash; such that sediment moving across an underlying, often more resistant, surface accumulates sediment into these crescent-shaped dunes. As barchan dunes migrate in the direction of the prevailing wind or water flow, neighboring barchans start to interact with each other prior to coming into direct contact. As the speed of barchan dune movement is inversely proportional to barchan sediment volume, a common scenario involves smaller, faster migrating barchans overtaking and colliding with larger, slower moving barchans. Such dune collisions result in complex changes to the shape of the dunes and modified sediment transport patterns, both of which are linked inextricably to the associated turbulent flow structure overlying the dunes. Past work has indicated the complexity of such barchan interactions, but has not detailed the fluid dynamics of these interactions. This research sought to address this gap in our knowledge.</p> <p>In order to investigate these complex flow processes, measurements were made using the technique of particle image velocimetry (PIV) over representative acrylic models of barchan dunes in a novel laboratory flume channel. PIV involves tracking the motion of neutrally-buoyant particles within the flow using high-intensity laser light sheets and high-speed, high-resolution cameras, such that their instantaneous velocity, and thus whole-flow field patterns, can be measured. The bedform configurations used in these experiments mimicked the early stages of the barchan collision process, wherein a smaller upstream barchan approaches a larger downstream barchan. In addition, an isolated symmetric barchan case was also investigated a baseline situation. In order to obtain full optical access around the barchan dunes, particularly in the near-surface region, experiments were conducted in the large-scale refractive index matching (RIM) laboratory flumes at the University of Notre Dame, flumes based on original facilities developed at the University of Illinois. These unique facilities match the refractive index of the fluid with that of the acrylic dune model under investigation, so that the model appears &lsquo;invisible&rsquo; within the flow. This then permits uninhibited optical access to the flow field, thus facilitating high-fidelity measurements that would be otherwise infeasible in a wind tunnel or water flume, especially near the surface of the barchan or in areas of complex topography between the interacting dunes.</p> <p>The baseline isolated barchan was examined first, and data was obtained from numerous measurements in three measurement planes. The results reveal the complexity and three-dimensionality of the &lsquo;wake&rsquo; flow generated downstream of the isolated barchan. Our results then show how this flow field is modified by the presence of an upstream barchan in various collision scenarios. The separated shear layer in the wake of the upstream barchan, which is a region of high turbulence intensity, is populated by large-scale 3D coherent flow structures that, after being generated by the upstream barchan, convect and eventually impinge onto the surface of the downstream barchan, thereby enhancing near-bed turbulent stresses. Such flow structures, shown in this study to take the form of both hairpin-shaped vortices shed in the wake and horseshoe-shaped vortices formed over the upstream slope of the dunes, possess significant turbulent kinetic energy and thus have the potential to mobilize sediment. As the two barchans near each other, the characteristics of flow separation and the spatial structure of the coherent flow motions become modified, with the offset between the dunes inducing additional flow asymmetries in the structure of flow.</p> <p>Our study has yielded new conceptual models of the structure of flow in the wake of an isolated barchan and in the interdune region between interacting barchans. These results provide an important framework for interpreting observed morphodynamics of natural interacting barchan dunes and build a foundation for further study of important field-scale dynamics, in a range of environments and flow types. The research has also provided the methodological and conceptual foundation for a new collaborative international research project, with colleagues at the University of Notre Dame and three institutions in the United Kingdom (Southampton, Oxford and Loughborough), in a linked field-laboratory project investigating the origin, and growth, of eolian dunes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/08/2019<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;L&nbsp;Best</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1604155/1604155_10436781_1570487952081_Barchanduneflowmodels--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1604155/1604155_10436781_1570487952081_Barchanduneflowmodels--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The flow field around barchan dunes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1604155/1604155_10436781_1570487952081_Barchanduneflowmodels--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The flow field around barchan dunes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conceptual models of hairpin and horseshoe vortices formed around: (a) the isolated barchan,  and (b-c) the interdune region for two progressive stages of barchan interactions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nathaniel Bristow, University of Notre Dame</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;L&nbsp;Best</div> <div class="imageTitle">The flow field around barchan dunes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Barchan dunes are three-dimensional, crescent-shaped bedforms that form in a wide range of environments, including eolian deserts, fluvial channels, continental shelves, and other planetary surfaces. Barchan dunes have been described from the deserts of Earth and the craters of Mars.  The primary aim of this research was to investigate the structure of turbulent flow associated with interacting barchan dunes, and how turbulence affects the nature of such barchan-barchan interactions. Barchan dunes are typically formed under unidirectional flows, but in environments where there is a limited sand supply &ndash; such that sediment moving across an underlying, often more resistant, surface accumulates sediment into these crescent-shaped dunes. As barchan dunes migrate in the direction of the prevailing wind or water flow, neighboring barchans start to interact with each other prior to coming into direct contact. As the speed of barchan dune movement is inversely proportional to barchan sediment volume, a common scenario involves smaller, faster migrating barchans overtaking and colliding with larger, slower moving barchans. Such dune collisions result in complex changes to the shape of the dunes and modified sediment transport patterns, both of which are linked inextricably to the associated turbulent flow structure overlying the dunes. Past work has indicated the complexity of such barchan interactions, but has not detailed the fluid dynamics of these interactions. This research sought to address this gap in our knowledge.  In order to investigate these complex flow processes, measurements were made using the technique of particle image velocimetry (PIV) over representative acrylic models of barchan dunes in a novel laboratory flume channel. PIV involves tracking the motion of neutrally-buoyant particles within the flow using high-intensity laser light sheets and high-speed, high-resolution cameras, such that their instantaneous velocity, and thus whole-flow field patterns, can be measured. The bedform configurations used in these experiments mimicked the early stages of the barchan collision process, wherein a smaller upstream barchan approaches a larger downstream barchan. In addition, an isolated symmetric barchan case was also investigated a baseline situation. In order to obtain full optical access around the barchan dunes, particularly in the near-surface region, experiments were conducted in the large-scale refractive index matching (RIM) laboratory flumes at the University of Notre Dame, flumes based on original facilities developed at the University of Illinois. These unique facilities match the refractive index of the fluid with that of the acrylic dune model under investigation, so that the model appears ?invisible? within the flow. This then permits uninhibited optical access to the flow field, thus facilitating high-fidelity measurements that would be otherwise infeasible in a wind tunnel or water flume, especially near the surface of the barchan or in areas of complex topography between the interacting dunes.  The baseline isolated barchan was examined first, and data was obtained from numerous measurements in three measurement planes. The results reveal the complexity and three-dimensionality of the ?wake? flow generated downstream of the isolated barchan. Our results then show how this flow field is modified by the presence of an upstream barchan in various collision scenarios. The separated shear layer in the wake of the upstream barchan, which is a region of high turbulence intensity, is populated by large-scale 3D coherent flow structures that, after being generated by the upstream barchan, convect and eventually impinge onto the surface of the downstream barchan, thereby enhancing near-bed turbulent stresses. Such flow structures, shown in this study to take the form of both hairpin-shaped vortices shed in the wake and horseshoe-shaped vortices formed over the upstream slope of the dunes, possess significant turbulent kinetic energy and thus have the potential to mobilize sediment. As the two barchans near each other, the characteristics of flow separation and the spatial structure of the coherent flow motions become modified, with the offset between the dunes inducing additional flow asymmetries in the structure of flow.  Our study has yielded new conceptual models of the structure of flow in the wake of an isolated barchan and in the interdune region between interacting barchans. These results provide an important framework for interpreting observed morphodynamics of natural interacting barchan dunes and build a foundation for further study of important field-scale dynamics, in a range of environments and flow types. The research has also provided the methodological and conceptual foundation for a new collaborative international research project, with colleagues at the University of Notre Dame and three institutions in the United Kingdom (Southampton, Oxford and Loughborough), in a linked field-laboratory project investigating the origin, and growth, of eolian dunes.          Last Modified: 10/08/2019       Submitted by: James L Best]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
