<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Homogeneous Plasmonic Assays for Instantaneous Microbial Detection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>301147.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>301147</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stamchan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928684</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Abbas, Abdennour &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1605191&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A new approach for a rapid identification and quantification of microbial content and type in food and environmental samples will be investigated. If successful, the results could address current need in food safety and food spoilage detection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A new approach for rapid identification and quantification of the microbial content and type in food and environmental samples,  will be investigated. Rapid screening (less than 2 hours) for the presence or absence of yeasts, molds, gram-negative bacteria, gram-positive bacteria and other phylogenetic microbial classes regardless of the strain or species will be developed. Current rapid methods rely on incubation followed by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for identification. The proposed homogeneous phylogenetic-plasmonic assays are based on the combination of plasmonic and colorimetry mechanisms (generation of color by the aggregation of metal nanoparticles), and the identification and targeting of specific phylogenetic entities on the microbial surface, which are specific to a certain class of microorganisms, and can be activated to interact with plasmonic nanoparticles. Such an interaction results in a rapid formation of a nanoparticle monolayer surrounding the microorganism, leading to rapid color change of the sample from red to dark-blue, visible to the naked eye. As a result, the proposed assay technology is expected to reduce cost and time needed for analysis and decision making would become feasible in less than two hours. Beyond the applied aspects of the project, the proposed research will explore microbial surface entities, particularly disulfide bridge-containing proteins, and shed light on their importance, distribution and role in molecular recognition reactions and stability of microbial cells. The main direct impact of this research is to enhance the capabilities of food and environmental diagnostic laboratories by enabling rapid microbial screening in food plants and environmental sites, allowing timely implementation of a preventive or curative response. The project proposes to build collaboration with industrial partners, which will help fill the gap between academic research and the development of commercial products that benefit society. The proposed research program will introduce graduate, undergraduate students, and post-docs to transdisciplinary research and educate them on how to solve problems by applying different fields of science and engineering, such as nanotechnology, chemistry, biotechnology and food engineering. The results of this research will be broadly disseminated through conferences, peer-reviewed publications, potential patents and news articles to inform the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1605191</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abdennour</FirstName>
<LastName>Abbas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abdennour Abbas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aabbas@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126244292</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551086130</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2004 Folwell ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~301147</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div><strong>Intelectual Merit:</strong></div> <div>The project&nbsp;<em>Homogeneous Plasmonic&nbsp;</em><em>Assays for Instantaneous Microbial Detection </em>is focused on the development of rapid microbial detection technologies for food safety by using nanotechnology. The method uses a bioinspired concept for the screening of microorganisms without using antibodies or receptors. The PI?s team has now confirmed that disulfide-bridge proteins on the surface of bacteria and chitin on the surface of fungi can be used for rapid screening of microorganisms. The PI?s group has also discovered new properties of Au nanoparticles that could be used for sensitive chemiluminescent and plasmonic microbial screening, such as the new catalytic properties of gold nanoplates. The project led to a better inderstanding of the interaction between metal nanoparticles and microorganisms and helped design faster and cheaper microbial detection methods.<strong><br /></strong></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Research products:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Durimng this project, the the PI?s team received one issued US Patent and 3 US patents pending, published 4 manuscripts in Scientific Reports (Top 30 papers in Chemistry in 2017), Advanced Healthcare&nbsp;&nbsp;Materials (Frontispiece article), Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemis<a class="buttonBg" href="por?awardId=1605191&amp;reportNumber=10423399">Save</a>try (Forefront paper), and&nbsp;Chemical Communications.</p> <p><strong>Broader impact</strong></p> <p><em>Training and Workforce development:</em> The project allowed the PI to train 4 postdoctoral research associates (Dr. Renu Singh, Dr. Phuong Bui, Dr. Olga Saipiana, Aiqin Fang). All postdocs were trained on Nanodiagnostics and all found positions in academia or industry during Fall 2017. Also, the project helped train a PhD student (Ms. Snober Ahmed) and a Masters student (Ms. Ke Xu), who respectively joined McMaster University as a Research Associate and McGill University with a graduate fellowship.</p> <p><em>New Teaching Course:</em> Since the project is based on bioinspired detection technologies, the PI has prepared and submitted a new transdisciplinary Grand Challenge Course ?Bioinspired approaches to sustainability: greening technologies and lives?<em> (</em>GCC 3015<em>). </em>The course started in Spring 2017.</p> <p><em>Diversity and Outreach: </em>The PI?s lab mentored for over a year two K12 students from underrepresented groups: Curtis Love and<em> </em>Alondra Fuentes Avila from Murray Middle School. Also, the PI mentored Joseph Ching and Caroline Sassan from the Wayzata High School in the framework of the Honors Mentor Program for Gifted Students.</p> <p><em>Technology Transfer: </em>One US patent was issued in 2018, and 3 Provisional patents were filled in 2017. Also, the project strengthened the collaboration with industrial partners including General Mills and the Schwan Food Company which offered a 5-year graduate fellowship to the PI?s laboratory starting Spring 2019 to advance rapid microbial diagnostics for food safety.</p> <p><strong><strong><span>Dissemination</span></strong> and Media Highlights</strong></p> <p>The PI and his team presented the outcomes of this project in 6 different conferences and seminars, including the NanoEngineering for Medicine and Biology Conference, Aug. 2018; (2)&nbsp;Annual ASABE International Meeting, July 2018;&nbsp;(3) World Congress in Biosensors, June 2018; (4) Atlantic Basin Conference on Chemistry, Jan. 2018; (5) Food Defense Conference, May 2017; (6) Material Research Society Fall Meeting, Nov. 2016.</p> <p>The research was also highlighted in TV and online new media, including:</p> <p>- Press release: ?Researchers use green gold to rapidly detect and identify harmful bacteria?, <em>Phys.Org</em>, July 31, 2018.&nbsp;</p> <p>- TV news broadcast: Jeff Edmondson, ?New tech may speed up Oak wilt detection?, <em>KARE11</em>, November 14, 2017.&nbsp;</p> <p>- Portable luminometer to rapidly detect, identify harmful bacteria, Feedstuffs, Aug 15, 208</p> <p>-&nbsp;Researchers Developed Method for Identification of Harmful Bacteria, Oak Tribune, November 30, 2018</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2019<br>      Modified by: Abdennour&nbsp;Abbas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Intelectual Merit: The project Homogeneous Plasmonic Assays for Instantaneous Microbial Detection is focused on the development of rapid microbial detection technologies for food safety by using nanotechnology. The method uses a bioinspired concept for the screening of microorganisms without using antibodies or receptors. The PI?s team has now confirmed that disulfide-bridge proteins on the surface of bacteria and chitin on the surface of fungi can be used for rapid screening of microorganisms. The PI?s group has also discovered new properties of Au nanoparticles that could be used for sensitive chemiluminescent and plasmonic microbial screening, such as the new catalytic properties of gold nanoplates. The project led to a better inderstanding of the interaction between metal nanoparticles and microorganisms and helped design faster and cheaper microbial detection methods.      Research products:   Durimng this project, the the PI?s team received one issued US Patent and 3 US patents pending, published 4 manuscripts in Scientific Reports (Top 30 papers in Chemistry in 2017), Advanced Healthcare  Materials (Frontispiece article), Analytical and Bioanalytical ChemisSavetry (Forefront paper), and Chemical Communications.  Broader impact  Training and Workforce development: The project allowed the PI to train 4 postdoctoral research associates (Dr. Renu Singh, Dr. Phuong Bui, Dr. Olga Saipiana, Aiqin Fang). All postdocs were trained on Nanodiagnostics and all found positions in academia or industry during Fall 2017. Also, the project helped train a PhD student (Ms. Snober Ahmed) and a Masters student (Ms. Ke Xu), who respectively joined McMaster University as a Research Associate and McGill University with a graduate fellowship.  New Teaching Course: Since the project is based on bioinspired detection technologies, the PI has prepared and submitted a new transdisciplinary Grand Challenge Course ?Bioinspired approaches to sustainability: greening technologies and lives? (GCC 3015). The course started in Spring 2017.  Diversity and Outreach: The PI?s lab mentored for over a year two K12 students from underrepresented groups: Curtis Love and Alondra Fuentes Avila from Murray Middle School. Also, the PI mentored Joseph Ching and Caroline Sassan from the Wayzata High School in the framework of the Honors Mentor Program for Gifted Students.  Technology Transfer: One US patent was issued in 2018, and 3 Provisional patents were filled in 2017. Also, the project strengthened the collaboration with industrial partners including General Mills and the Schwan Food Company which offered a 5-year graduate fellowship to the PI?s laboratory starting Spring 2019 to advance rapid microbial diagnostics for food safety.  Dissemination and Media Highlights  The PI and his team presented the outcomes of this project in 6 different conferences and seminars, including the NanoEngineering for Medicine and Biology Conference, Aug. 2018; (2) Annual ASABE International Meeting, July 2018; (3) World Congress in Biosensors, June 2018; (4) Atlantic Basin Conference on Chemistry, Jan. 2018; (5) Food Defense Conference, May 2017; (6) Material Research Society Fall Meeting, Nov. 2016.  The research was also highlighted in TV and online new media, including:  - Press release: ?Researchers use green gold to rapidly detect and identify harmful bacteria?, Phys.Org, July 31, 2018.   - TV news broadcast: Jeff Edmondson, ?New tech may speed up Oak wilt detection?, KARE11, November 14, 2017.   - Portable luminometer to rapidly detect, identify harmful bacteria, Feedstuffs, Aug 15, 208  - Researchers Developed Method for Identification of Harmful Bacteria, Oak Tribune, November 30, 2018       Last Modified: 08/06/2019       Submitted by: Abdennour Abbas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
