<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Microbial Fuel Cell Optimization through Digital Microfluidic Electrochemistry in Single-Bacterial Drops</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>152000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>152000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Municipal wastewater treatment processes consume significant amounts of energy.   However, the organic materials fed into the waste treatment process offer the potential for energy-positive waste water treatment if this waste organic material can be converted into energy.  Many bacteria that grow in waste water can be harnessed to consume these organic contaminants to clean up the water and at the same time generate electrical current from their metabolism.  These bacteria are bound within an electrode of a device called a microbial fuel cell to harvest this current as electrical power.  To achieve maximum power output from microbial fuel cells, it must be determined how many species of bacteria, when organized into complex colonies known as biofilms, collaborate to convert organic matter into electricity.  This project will study this collaborative metabolism within a novel miniaturized culture system capable of high-through analysis to accelerate the screening process.  This miniature culture system will be capable of measuring metabolism of a single bacterial species, as well as in small mixed colonies of many bacteria, from a single drop of culture.  This information will be used to determine how the electrical current produced and the organic matter consumed depends on bacterium type, as well as the potential synergy between many types of bacteria.  The educational activities inspired by this project feature a hands-on teaching module for high school girls, who will build a simple microbial fuel cell to power a light-emitted diode (LED) or a digital watch.  It is hoped this activity will illustrate to high school girls the potential of renewable green energy and biotechnology as exciting future career choices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The microbial fuel cell system components, which include electrodes, membranes, and bacteria, must be carefully engineered to achieve optimal power generation. This project will focus on genetic optimization of the bacteria within the electrode.  This optimization is challenging given the interconnected manner in which wastewater bacteria grow. Towards this end, the proposed research has two primary objectives. The first objective is to develop a high-throughput digital microfluidic (DMF) platform for studying microbial fuel cell metabolism and electrical current evolution from single species of bacteria or small colonies of mixed bacteria. The second goal is to optimize the bacterial communities for high power density through high-throughput analysis of single bacterium electron transfer limitations. The DMF chip will be fabricated with droplet actuation electrodes, nanostructured electrochemical electrodes, and isolated on-chip microwell cell culture chambers.  The droplet actuation electrode deposits a culture droplet into the microwell, and nanostructured electrodes within the culture microwell will enable the detection of single bacterium output current as well as measurement of specific cell culture contents using cyclic voltammetry.  Bacteria known to consume organic matter in waste water and convert it into electrical current through microbioelectrochemical metabolic processes, including P. aeruginosa, Geobacter  (G. sulfurreducens) and Shewanella (S. oneidensis) will first be studied as the model exoelectrogens in single species culture.  By selectively increasing complexity and heterogeneity in the culture systems, beginning with isolated single species and moving to mixed bacterial colonies, a better understanding of the synergism among bacteria can be systematically determined.  Through this study, it also is hoped that the DMF chip will become established as a new tool for studying electron transfer processes in bioelectrochemically-active bacteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1605482</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hassett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Hassett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.hassett@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135581154</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000128905</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[51 Goodman Dr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041064767</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041064767</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Cincinnati]]></Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>452670524</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[231 Albert Sabin Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~152000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of our proposed work was to develop an optimization and analysis platform for microbial fuel cells (MFCs) based on&nbsp;<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">d</span></strong>igital&nbsp;<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">m</span></strong>icro<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">f</span></strong>luidic (DMF) on-chip droplet cell cultures and micro electrochemistry sensing techniques. This platform integrated two key technologies: 1) a DMF chip fabricated with highly efficient droplet actuation electrodes and nanostructured electrochemical electrodes, and 2) isolated on-chip micro cell cultures for single-bacterium electron transfer detection and bacteria power generation characterization. MFCs have multiple components that affect the overall power generation efficiency of MFCs. This important work focused on optimizing the bacterial communities in MFCs for high power density and also develop an on-chip high throughput platform for analyzing single bacterium electron transfer limitations in MFCs. The Daniel lab at Cornell University provided expertise on platform development, while the Hassett lab at the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine provided expertise in MFC bacterial physiology and genetic engineering of optimized electrogens and electrogenic bacterial consortia. Both labs have interacted well and collaborate extensively to achieve the proposed goals in a timely fashion.&nbsp;<em>P. aeruginosa</em>,&nbsp;<em>Geobacter&nbsp;</em>(<em>G. sulfurreducens</em>) and&nbsp;<em>Shewanella&nbsp;</em>(<em>S. oneidensis</em>) were used<em>&nbsp;</em>as the<em>&nbsp;</em>MFC exoelectrogens because they are commonly found in soils (a very competitive environment) and wastewaters and are widely considered the most important exoelectrogenic bacteria for future commercial MFCs. Recent DMF advances in on-chip cell culture and electrochemical measurements offer a new degree of freedom for isolated single-cell analysis and on-chip electrochemical measurements. On-chip microwell cell cultures are dispensed from an on-chip reservoir to minimize manual operation. By integrating multiple microcell cultures on chip, high resolution batch processing is possible in a limited space. Although some technical glitches were encountered, we still fulfilled our goals of generating a powerful new system for potential downstream use as an alternative energy platform. It is anticipated that the DMF chip will become a new standard for single bacterium analysis and the foremost tool for probing bacterial electron transfer for MFC cell culture optimization. Two highly regarded publications resulted from this work that were in referred journals (see below).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?sort=date&amp;term=Shreeram+DD&amp;cauthor_id=29288437">Devesh D Shreeram</a><sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29288437/#affiliation-1">1</a></sup>,&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?sort=date&amp;term=Panmanee+W&amp;cauthor_id=29288437">Warunya Panmanee</a><sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29288437/#affiliation-2">2</a></sup>,&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?sort=date&amp;term=McDaniel+CT&amp;cauthor_id=29288437">Cameron T McDaniel</a><sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29288437/#affiliation-2">2</a></sup>,&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?sort=date&amp;term=Daniel+S&amp;cauthor_id=29288437">Susan Daniel</a><sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29288437/#affiliation-3">3</a></sup>,&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?sort=date&amp;term=Schaefer+DW&amp;cauthor_id=29288437">Dale W Schaefer</a><sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29288437/#affiliation-1">1</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29288437/#affiliation-4">4</a></sup>,&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?sort=date&amp;term=Hassett+DJ&amp;cauthor_id=29288437">Daniel J Hassett</a><sup>&nbsp;</sup>2018.&nbsp;<strong>Effect of impaired twitching motility and biofilm dispersion on performance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa-powered microbial fuel cells.&nbsp;</strong>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol. 45: 103-109.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Tahernia M, Mohammadifar M, Gao Y, Panmanee W,<strong>&nbsp;Hassett DJ</strong>, Choi S.&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32452395/">A 96-well high-throughput, rapid-screening platform of extracellular electron transfer in microbial&nbsp;<strong>fuel</strong>&nbsp;cells.</a>Biosens Bioelectron. 2020 Aug 15;162:112259. doi: 10.1016/j.bios.2020.112259. Epub 2020&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2020<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hassett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of our proposed work was to develop an optimization and analysis platform for microbial fuel cells (MFCs) based on digital microfluidic (DMF) on-chip droplet cell cultures and micro electrochemistry sensing techniques. This platform integrated two key technologies: 1) a DMF chip fabricated with highly efficient droplet actuation electrodes and nanostructured electrochemical electrodes, and 2) isolated on-chip micro cell cultures for single-bacterium electron transfer detection and bacteria power generation characterization. MFCs have multiple components that affect the overall power generation efficiency of MFCs. This important work focused on optimizing the bacterial communities in MFCs for high power density and also develop an on-chip high throughput platform for analyzing single bacterium electron transfer limitations in MFCs. The Daniel lab at Cornell University provided expertise on platform development, while the Hassett lab at the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine provided expertise in MFC bacterial physiology and genetic engineering of optimized electrogens and electrogenic bacterial consortia. Both labs have interacted well and collaborate extensively to achieve the proposed goals in a timely fashion. P. aeruginosa, Geobacter (G. sulfurreducens) and Shewanella (S. oneidensis) were used as the MFC exoelectrogens because they are commonly found in soils (a very competitive environment) and wastewaters and are widely considered the most important exoelectrogenic bacteria for future commercial MFCs. Recent DMF advances in on-chip cell culture and electrochemical measurements offer a new degree of freedom for isolated single-cell analysis and on-chip electrochemical measurements. On-chip microwell cell cultures are dispensed from an on-chip reservoir to minimize manual operation. By integrating multiple microcell cultures on chip, high resolution batch processing is possible in a limited space. Although some technical glitches were encountered, we still fulfilled our goals of generating a powerful new system for potential downstream use as an alternative energy platform. It is anticipated that the DMF chip will become a new standard for single bacterium analysis and the foremost tool for probing bacterial electron transfer for MFC cell culture optimization. Two highly regarded publications resulted from this work that were in referred journals (see below).     Devesh D Shreeram 1, Warunya Panmanee 2, Cameron T McDaniel 2, Susan Daniel 3, Dale W Schaefer 1 4, Daniel J Hassett 2018. Effect of impaired twitching motility and biofilm dispersion on performance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa-powered microbial fuel cells. J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol. 45: 103-109.     Tahernia M, Mohammadifar M, Gao Y, Panmanee W, Hassett DJ, Choi S. A 96-well high-throughput, rapid-screening platform of extracellular electron transfer in microbial fuel cells.Biosens Bioelectron. 2020 Aug 15;162:112259. doi: 10.1016/j.bios.2020.112259. Epub 2020           Last Modified: 08/25/2020       Submitted by: Daniel J Hassett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
