<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is made as part of the FY 2016 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The title of the project for this fellowship to James E. Pascoe is "Operator Theory and Several Complex Variables." The host institution for the fellowship is Washington University, and the sponsoring scientist is John McCarthy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1606260</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Pascoe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James E Pascoe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6197179634</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678360</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pascoe                  James          E</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930112</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University in St. Louis]]></Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Noncommutative function theory, the study of the free functional calculus, is used in the study of <strong>scalable</strong> or <strong>dimensionless</strong> problems in systems engineering. Additionally, important qualitative properties, such as positivity, of functions are often accessible in the free case. A qualitative understanding of the free functional calculus is important for applications; it gives a way to work around the fact that matrix calculations are <strong>computationally expensive</strong> when analyzing matrix inequalities.</p> <p>Via the connection to moment problems, matrix monotonicity, and many other areas, the functional calculus has deep and well-studied consequences for science and engineering. For example,classically, John von Neumann and Eugene Wigner applied Lo&#776;wner&rsquo;s theorem on matrix monotonicity to the theory of quantum collisions. Other applications of Lo&#776;wner&rsquo;s theorem have includedinclude quantum data processing, wireless communications and engineering. The principal investigator&rsquo;s investigation of the functional calculus in several variables potentially admits applicationsto a broader class of problems.</p> <p>Several complex variables has long stood as one of the cornerstones of modern mathematics. In the early 90s, Jim Agler developed new methods in several complex variables using techniques from functional analysis and systems engineering. More recently, some of the same techniques havebeen used to understand the functional calculus (an important tool in functional analysis and its applications) in several variables, the free functional calculus. Much of the work along these lines has been to extend theorems from one variable to several variables. Essentially, we study natural enough functions depending on several matrices</p> <p>We investigated the free functional calculus, several complex variables, and related topics. Works accomplished under this grant included but is not limited to:</p> <p>(1) Classification of matrix monotone functions in several variables via a generalization of Lo&#776;wner&rsquo;s theorem, an important tool in manipulating matrix inequalities. Namely, any matrix monotone function in several variables analytically continues to a noncommutative analogue of the upper half plane.</p> <p>(2) Analytic continuation theorems in several complex variables and their applications, including so-called wedge-of-the-edge theorems.</p> <p>(3) Understanding the geometry of stable polynomials</p> <p>(4) An investigation of invariant theory for free rational functions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2020<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;E&nbsp;Pascoe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Noncommutative function theory, the study of the free functional calculus, is used in the study of scalable or dimensionless problems in systems engineering. Additionally, important qualitative properties, such as positivity, of functions are often accessible in the free case. A qualitative understanding of the free functional calculus is important for applications; it gives a way to work around the fact that matrix calculations are computationally expensive when analyzing matrix inequalities.  Via the connection to moment problems, matrix monotonicity, and many other areas, the functional calculus has deep and well-studied consequences for science and engineering. For example,classically, John von Neumann and Eugene Wigner applied Lo&#776;wner’s theorem on matrix monotonicity to the theory of quantum collisions. Other applications of Lo&#776;wner’s theorem have includedinclude quantum data processing, wireless communications and engineering. The principal investigator’s investigation of the functional calculus in several variables potentially admits applicationsto a broader class of problems.  Several complex variables has long stood as one of the cornerstones of modern mathematics. In the early 90s, Jim Agler developed new methods in several complex variables using techniques from functional analysis and systems engineering. More recently, some of the same techniques havebeen used to understand the functional calculus (an important tool in functional analysis and its applications) in several variables, the free functional calculus. Much of the work along these lines has been to extend theorems from one variable to several variables. Essentially, we study natural enough functions depending on several matrices  We investigated the free functional calculus, several complex variables, and related topics. Works accomplished under this grant included but is not limited to:  (1) Classification of matrix monotone functions in several variables via a generalization of Lo&#776;wner’s theorem, an important tool in manipulating matrix inequalities. Namely, any matrix monotone function in several variables analytically continues to a noncommutative analogue of the upper half plane.  (2) Analytic continuation theorems in several complex variables and their applications, including so-called wedge-of-the-edge theorems.  (3) Understanding the geometry of stable polynomials  (4) An investigation of invariant theory for free rational functions.       Last Modified: 12/16/2020       Submitted by: James E Pascoe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
