<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pressure Tuning of Competing Quantum States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Transitions between different states - solid to liquid to gas, conductor to insulator - are common occurrences. At the absolute zero of temperature, different physics enters. Quantum mechanics plays a central role, altering the universal response that has been mapped out for classical transitions. This can lead to new possibilities in the optical response of materials, the electronic character of devices, or the magnetic capacity of storage materials. This project probes the quantum characteristics of model systems in three related arenas: parsing the cooperation and competition between magnetism and superconductivity, delineating the new states of matter accessed when sheets of electrons are placed in very high magnetic fields, and deciphering the way in which an insulator can be transformed into a metal. In each case, the research takes advantage of the ability of diamond anvil cell technology to access pressures outside of everyday techniques and to transmit high energy x-rays. The wide array of techniques, from x-ray scattering at a synchrotron to electrical measurements in the laboratory, and the necessity to apply physics, chemistry and materials science to these studies, trains students well for careers in industry, the national laboratories, or academia. Bringing research perspectives to education is another emphasis, including connections with STEM teachers and the general public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;The effects of a quantum phase transition can be felt up to surprisingly high temperatures. Many materials of technological import demonstrate unusual electronic, optical, and magnetic properties that have been ascribed to the close proximity of quantum critical points. However, complex materials properties, conflated with competing ground states, have made it difficult to discern the essential physics. Moreover, without temperature as a variable, studies of quantum critical points are hard pressed to approach the exactitude that has become the hallmark of experiments on classical critical phenomena. This project combines high-resolution studies of pure materials tuned to accessible quantum critical points using pressure to reveal fundamental aspects of magnetism, disorder, correlated materials, and quantum phase transitions. These include the competition between modulated spin order and superconductivity, the fundamental quantum magnetism of spin singlets arranged on a square lattice, and the transition from insulator to metal in a correlated material. The wide array of techniques, from x-ray scattering to magnetotransport, trains students well for careers in industry, the national laboratories, or academia. Advances in diamond anvil cell technology are important for condensed matter physicists and geophysicists alike. Supporting STEM teachers and helping them develop curricula is a priority.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1606858</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosenbaum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas F Rosenbaum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tfr@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956301</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000121938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E.California Blvd 204-31]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>053Z</Code>
<Text>Quantum Leap Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Physics near the absolute zero of temperature is different than what we experience in our ordinary world. Of particular interest is the study of materials undergoing changes of state: from insulator to metal, from ordinary conductor to superconductor, from superconductor to magnet.&nbsp;&nbsp;These phase transitions at the absolute zero of temperature involve fundamentally different physics than their finite temperature analogues. In this low temperature limit, the Heisenberg uncertainty principle inextricably intertwines the static and dynamical response of the material changing state, introducing a special quantum character to both the transition and the nature of the new state that emerges.&nbsp;</p> <p>The effects of a so-called quantum phase transition can be felt up to surprisingly high temperatures. Many materials of technological import demonstrate unusual electronic, optical, and magnetic properties that have been ascribed to the close proximity of a quantum phase transition.&nbsp;&nbsp;These include materials that change properties enormously with the application of a small magnetic field or can conduct electricity without resistance, making them suitable for such applications as magnetic storage, high frequency electronics, and sensing. However, without temperature as a variable, studies of quantum phase transitions are hard pressed to approach the exactitude that has become the hallmark of experiments on classical transitions.</p> <p>We have probed the singular mixture of statics and dynamics stirred up by quantum fluctuations in a number of model experimental systems.&nbsp;The major goal of this project is to attempt to isolate the key physical parameters and mechanisms at quantum phase transitions by tuning the materials using high pressures and measuring their changing properties with high resolution employing x-rays and various electronic, magnetic and optical probes. The wide array of techniques should train students well for careers in industry, the national laboratories, or academia. Advances in high pressure work should influence physicists and geologists alike. Helping coalesce efforts in scientific engagement with K-12 education and in developing hands-on research experiences for middle and high school students, through programs like the Science Olympiad, is both a laboratory and personal priority.</p> <p>The power of gaining microscopic information about quantum materials can be illustrated in the following examples:</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;<em>Telling Magnetic Up from Down</em>. A material?s ability to conduct electricity can change with the application of a magnetic field. The common lore is that the electrons that carry the current, and hence the electrical properties of the material as a whole, do not care whether the magnetic field points up or down, whether it is directed left or right. We have discovered an exception to this rule in a family of powerful, commercially-important magnets. In this case, the fixed magnetic order inside the material breaks the symmetry between up and down, left and right, so an externally applied magnetic field directed up can increase the electrical conductivity while a field directed down can decrease the conductivity. The response is linear in field which is also unusual. These insights reveal the fundamental magnetic structure of highly coercive materials and may be important in the design of heterostructures grown by layering different magnetic materials with different electrical properties on top of one another.&nbsp;</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;<em>Disrupting&nbsp;</em><em>Charge and Spin Order by Changing Symmetry</em>. Symmetry plays a deterministic role in the laws of Nature. Of particular recent interest are systems where reflecting all the atoms about their center leaves the material looking different, so-called broken inversion symmetry. In such cases new quantum states can emerge, and when they absorb energy, they can have interesting and sometimes useful properties. We have found that high pressures applied to a material with strong interactions between the charges and unusual spin order can break inversion symmetry, while keeping the overall structural symmetry intact. We explore how the different phases transform into each other, each phase with its own special qualities.&nbsp;</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;<em>Measuring Charge and Spin under High Pressures</em>.&nbsp;&nbsp;X-rays are very sensitive to an electron?s charge. They are much less sensitive to an electron?s spin, the quantum-mechanical parameter that lies at the heart of a material?s magnetic response. Placing a quantum material between two diamonds and squeezing, a good way to change its physical state, makes the magnetic x-ray measurements extremely difficult. Then cool it down near absolute zero to amplify the material?s quantum character. This describes the new techniques we have developed to tell magnetic order from disorder and metal from insulator in diamond anvil pressure cells.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;F&nbsp;Rosenbaum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Physics near the absolute zero of temperature is different than what we experience in our ordinary world. Of particular interest is the study of materials undergoing changes of state: from insulator to metal, from ordinary conductor to superconductor, from superconductor to magnet.  These phase transitions at the absolute zero of temperature involve fundamentally different physics than their finite temperature analogues. In this low temperature limit, the Heisenberg uncertainty principle inextricably intertwines the static and dynamical response of the material changing state, introducing a special quantum character to both the transition and the nature of the new state that emerges.   The effects of a so-called quantum phase transition can be felt up to surprisingly high temperatures. Many materials of technological import demonstrate unusual electronic, optical, and magnetic properties that have been ascribed to the close proximity of a quantum phase transition.  These include materials that change properties enormously with the application of a small magnetic field or can conduct electricity without resistance, making them suitable for such applications as magnetic storage, high frequency electronics, and sensing. However, without temperature as a variable, studies of quantum phase transitions are hard pressed to approach the exactitude that has become the hallmark of experiments on classical transitions.  We have probed the singular mixture of statics and dynamics stirred up by quantum fluctuations in a number of model experimental systems. The major goal of this project is to attempt to isolate the key physical parameters and mechanisms at quantum phase transitions by tuning the materials using high pressures and measuring their changing properties with high resolution employing x-rays and various electronic, magnetic and optical probes. The wide array of techniques should train students well for careers in industry, the national laboratories, or academia. Advances in high pressure work should influence physicists and geologists alike. Helping coalesce efforts in scientific engagement with K-12 education and in developing hands-on research experiences for middle and high school students, through programs like the Science Olympiad, is both a laboratory and personal priority.  The power of gaining microscopic information about quantum materials can be illustrated in the following examples:  (1) Telling Magnetic Up from Down. A material?s ability to conduct electricity can change with the application of a magnetic field. The common lore is that the electrons that carry the current, and hence the electrical properties of the material as a whole, do not care whether the magnetic field points up or down, whether it is directed left or right. We have discovered an exception to this rule in a family of powerful, commercially-important magnets. In this case, the fixed magnetic order inside the material breaks the symmetry between up and down, left and right, so an externally applied magnetic field directed up can increase the electrical conductivity while a field directed down can decrease the conductivity. The response is linear in field which is also unusual. These insights reveal the fundamental magnetic structure of highly coercive materials and may be important in the design of heterostructures grown by layering different magnetic materials with different electrical properties on top of one another.   (2) Disrupting Charge and Spin Order by Changing Symmetry. Symmetry plays a deterministic role in the laws of Nature. Of particular recent interest are systems where reflecting all the atoms about their center leaves the material looking different, so-called broken inversion symmetry. In such cases new quantum states can emerge, and when they absorb energy, they can have interesting and sometimes useful properties. We have found that high pressures applied to a material with strong interactions between the charges and unusual spin order can break inversion symmetry, while keeping the overall structural symmetry intact. We explore how the different phases transform into each other, each phase with its own special qualities.   (3) Measuring Charge and Spin under High Pressures.  X-rays are very sensitive to an electron?s charge. They are much less sensitive to an electron?s spin, the quantum-mechanical parameter that lies at the heart of a material?s magnetic response. Placing a quantum material between two diamonds and squeezing, a good way to change its physical state, makes the magnetic x-ray measurements extremely difficult. Then cool it down near absolute zero to amplify the material?s quantum character. This describes the new techniques we have developed to tell magnetic order from disorder and metal from insulator in diamond anvil pressure cells.              Last Modified: 09/05/2020       Submitted by: Thomas F Rosenbaum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
