<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dualizing modules in algebra and geometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>92561.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>92561</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI proposes to investigate the existence of homotopical dualizing modules in number theory and algebraic geometry and the implications thereof. Specifically, there will be two valuable instances of such dualizing modules. One will be studied in joint work with Tomer Schlank; it will give a homotopical extension of the arithmetic duality theorems of Tate-Poitou, which state that the cohomology of certain absolute Galois groups has a twisted form of self-duality. The PI and Tomer Schlank will also investigate applications of such duality results to problems of existence of rational points on algebraic varieties. A different example is related to the spectra of topological modular forms with or without level structures. Previous work of the PI suggests that the spectrally derived moduli stack of generalized elliptic curves has a simply describable dualizing sheaf of commutative ring spectra; an objective of the proposed project is to prove that result. Topological modular forms are crucial for understanding v2 periodic homotopy in the sphere spectrum; though somewhat removed from the theme of duality, the PI will collaborate with Mark Behrens, Kyle Ormsby, and Nathaniel Stapleton to compute the cooperations in the homology based on connective topological modular forms. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Duality is a pervasive concept in mathematics; the proposed project will study different types of duality in a unified framework, thereby arriving at novel and otherwise inaccessible information. In particular, the project is motivated by the idea that introducing a homotopical viewpoint can shed new light on our understanding of geometry and arithmetic. One of the objects with such curious self-duality properties, namely topological modular forms, lends itself to vast applications, some already explored and others not, as it mirrors itself in homotopy, algebraic geometry, number theory, and even quantum field theory as the receptacle of the Witten genus.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1606479</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vesna</FirstName>
<LastName>Stojanoska</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vesna Stojanoska</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vesna@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172650883</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000631405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 SOUTH FIRST ST.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~92561</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching goal of this project was to study duality and related concepts in homotopy theory. Homotopical data appears whenever we study objects whose continuous deformations are allowed, and one of the goals of homotopy theory is to develop tools for working with such data. In pure mathematics, geometric shapes are a classical source of deformable data, but less obviously so, number theory produces similar structures amenable to homotopical methods.</p> <p><br />Duality is the presence of particular unexpected symmetries, and most often these are parametrized by invertible objects. My work with Mathew established a new method for classifying invertible objects. It has already been utilized in several applications beyond the original one, where we detected exotic line bundles on a homotopical enhancement of a classical object in number theory, the moduli stack of elliptic curves.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Systematically organizing homotopical patterns leads to chromatic homotopy, where again connections to number theory are revealed. In work with Beaudry, Barthel, Greenlees, Heard, Mathew, I have explored duality and invertibility from this point of view. We found that for K-theory and its higher chromatic analogues, only the expected line bundles appear, and duality introduces interesting shifts often predictable using classical representation theory.</p> <p><br />Throughout the duration of this award, I have been active as a mentor and participant in the Women in Topology and Women in Number Theory workshops. So far, this effort has resulted in 5 publications on 3 different topics, joint with a total of 10 other women at various career stages.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Vesna&nbsp;Stojanoska</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching goal of this project was to study duality and related concepts in homotopy theory. Homotopical data appears whenever we study objects whose continuous deformations are allowed, and one of the goals of homotopy theory is to develop tools for working with such data. In pure mathematics, geometric shapes are a classical source of deformable data, but less obviously so, number theory produces similar structures amenable to homotopical methods.   Duality is the presence of particular unexpected symmetries, and most often these are parametrized by invertible objects. My work with Mathew established a new method for classifying invertible objects. It has already been utilized in several applications beyond the original one, where we detected exotic line bundles on a homotopical enhancement of a classical object in number theory, the moduli stack of elliptic curves.    Systematically organizing homotopical patterns leads to chromatic homotopy, where again connections to number theory are revealed. In work with Beaudry, Barthel, Greenlees, Heard, Mathew, I have explored duality and invertibility from this point of view. We found that for K-theory and its higher chromatic analogues, only the expected line bundles appear, and duality introduces interesting shifts often predictable using classical representation theory.   Throughout the duration of this award, I have been active as a mentor and participant in the Women in Topology and Women in Number Theory workshops. So far, this effort has resulted in 5 publications on 3 different topics, joint with a total of 10 other women at various career stages.                Last Modified: 09/07/2018       Submitted by: Vesna Stojanoska]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
