<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Haptic-Based Learning Experiences as Cognitive Mediators for Conceptual Understanding and Representational Fluency in Engineering Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>325081.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>325081</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dana L. Denick</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddenick@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928866</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Haptic-Based Learning Experiences as Cognitive Mediators for Conceptual Understanding and Representational Fluency in Engineering Education&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Statics is a backbone course for several engineering disciplines, a direct pre-requisite for dynamics and mechanics of materials, and a pivotal player in engineering structural design. Researchers have identified Statics as a major impediment for students to succeed in follow-on core courses (therefore affecting retention in engineering) as well as on practical design capstone courses. It is known that students enter Statics with misconceptions that are not corrected through traditional instruction. This project investigates the use of feedback devices, known as haptics, in which students can manipulate a computer-generated structure and feel the forces that are generated. It is hypothesized that the use of the haptic device will provide students specific feedback to help them develop a better conceptual understanding of Statics. This project targets a foundational topic in engineering education known to significantly affect both future performance and retention. The results of this research are broadly relevant to institutions and their students, as essentially all students in mechanical, civil, aerospace, and biomedical disciplines take Statics. Similarly, the products of this research inform learning interventions in related concepts in science and engineering (e.g., buoyancy, electricity and magnetism, and dynamics, among others).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research advances understanding of haptic-mediated learning by exploring specific affordances and constraints of visuo-haptic simulations in a laboratory experiment emphasizing statics misconceptions. Visuo-haptic simulation using force-feedback devices for education is timely, yet understudied. This research significantly extends the community's understanding of the affordances and constraints of using haptic devices for teaching difficult concepts. Following a design-based research approach, this project develops new knowledge about how haptic-based learning experiences can mediate conceptual understanding and representational competence of difficult concepts in statics. It investigates how we can best use touch technologies to help students connect system behaviors in terms of governing forces and their different representational forms. This proposal focuses on the following specific research questions (RQs): &lt;br/&gt;1. To what extent do haptic-based learning experiences improve student conceptual understanding and representational fluency? Working hypothesis: the force feedback of haptic devices reinforces representations (mathematical, visual) of mechanics systems and improves conceptual understanding. &lt;br/&gt;2. How do the short-term, long-term, and transfer learning gains between visual-only-enhanced, physical manipulative-enhanced, and haptic-enhanced learning activities compare? Working hypothesis: students experience greater learning gains when instruction includes haptic devices. &lt;br/&gt;3. What are the differences in students' explanations and representations of experienced phenomena before and after using the haptic-based learning experiences? Working hypothesis: haptic devices and learning experiences provide a new platform on which students can build understanding, and provide a new vocabulary for articulating device structure, function, and performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The newly derived knowledge will inform our understanding about how students "learn by touch" as well as our understanding of the interplay between conceptual understanding and representational competence. Our long-term goal is to identify the extent to which interacting with haptic-based learning experiences (HABLE) mediates students' conceptual understanding and representational fluency of difficult concepts in statics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1606396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Berger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward J Berger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bergere@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654960193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/08/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bedrich</FirstName>
<LastName>Benes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bedrich Benes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbenes@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654944600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000291472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alejandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Magana-de-Leon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alejandra J Magana-de-Leon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>admagana@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654943994</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000541666</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ida</FirstName>
<LastName>Ngambeki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ida Ngambeki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ingambek@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941055</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[401 N Grant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~325081</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Body">The main contribution of this project identified of how to best use touch technologies to help students connect system behaviors in terms of governing forces in the Statics domain.</p> <p class="Body">Intellectual merit:&nbsp; We followed a learner-centered approach for designing visuohaptic simulations and curricular materials.&nbsp; We implemented three steps: (1) requirements analysis and specification, (2) multimedia application design, and (3) inspection and evaluation of prototypes.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Body">We developed three visuohaptic simulations, three visual-only simulations, and three physical manipulatives. The first simulation (<a href="https://youtu.be/71vQRRU-IU0">https://youtu.be/71vQRRU-IU0</a>) probes students&rsquo; understanding of static friction force and the effects of variables such as: (1) density vs. weight, (2) object&rsquo; area of contact vs. weight, (3) friction force vs. surface area. The second simulation (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-bFc6zN6CZo) presents a system of trusses where students explore ideas such as: (1) tension and compression, and (2) zero force members (3) resultant of force systems in equilibrium. The third simulation (<a href="https://youtu.be/j5h2xjcK4ds">https://youtu.be/j5h2xjcK4ds</a>) presents a system of pulleys to explore the effects of different configurations including: (1) numbers of pulleys, (2) length of the string, (3) direction of the pull, and (4) different radius of the pulleys.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Body">Design principles for developing visuohaptic simulations were identified: Visual cues to provide force measurements, color-coding to easy and quickly identify the force magnitude, constraining rotational movement of the objects, ability to feel the weight of the objects, visual cues with spatial location to scaffold navigation in a 3D space, inclusion of a ruler to measure displacement, and inclusion of a visualization of the free body diagram.&nbsp; We also prepared scaffolding and guidance in the form of worksheets that were developed based on a prediction-observation-explanation strategy.</p> <p class="Body">This study extends the understanding of haptic devices' affordances and constraints for teaching force-related science concepts. When pre-assessed, undergraduate students demonstrated fragmented ideas of the concept of friction after a formal lecture. In the post-assessment, after either using a physical manipulative or a visuohaptic simulation, we identified that the physical manipulative tool did not provide a learning advantage. In contrast, the visuohaptic simulation resulted in a positive impact on learning.</p> <p class="Body">We also analyzed explanations provided by the learners for answering conceptual questions related to friction concepts. The thematic analysis of students' answers to the conceptual questions (i.e., role of the objects' weight in friction and the objects' size in friction) suggested six main codes organized into two categories; haptically-oriented and visually-oriented categories. The haptically-oriented category is related to the learners' actions performed to move the cubes (e.g., how hard they have to push a cube on a surface). The visually-oriented category, is related to the cubes' actions after the learner initiated the movement (e.g., how fast the cubes moved). During and after the interaction with the visuohaptic simulation, learners tended to provide haptically-oriented explanations, suggesting that the haptic feedback promoted the inference of the forces acting on the cubes while sliding. &nbsp;The sequencing and order of presenting the visual and tactile feedback was also relevant. Our results suggest\that the sequenced approach of haptic and minimal visual feedback to haptic and enhanced visual feedback (H -&gt; H+V) was a productive configuration. In the first interaction, students inferred the forces acting on the cubes, and in the second interaction, students read the information from the computer screen to confirm or change their observations.</p> <p class="Body">Broader impacts: The curricular materials, simulations, and findings of the research associated with this project have had a direct impact on mechanical, materials and civil engineering disciplines, human computer interaction and design, as well as engineering technology disciplines.&nbsp;The outcomes of this research also include a set of principles for the design and integration of visuohaptic simulations for conceptual understanding of difficult concepts in science and engineering.</p> <p class="Body">Active dissemination occurred via integration of haptic-enabled laboratory experiences into other courses where the PIs have existing and active collaborations, such as in physics. Specifically, over 1000 undergraduate students from majors in engineering technology, physics education, and psychology have been exposed to the learning materials. The learning materials including the visuohaptic simulations and the guiding materials were shared with faculty at other institutions who have implemented the learning materials with a group of 50 engineering students.&nbsp; In addition, eight graduate students, six of them female students, and three of them from underrepresented groups, participated in this project.&nbsp;They all received training in educational research, human-computer interaction, and engineering education.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Body">We have also disseminated our learning materials and findings to educators and researchers from learning sciences community, engineering education community and human-computer interaction community through research seminars, and conference presentations for engineering and science educators, both nationally and internationally. In addition to the eight journal manuscripts and five conference proceedings published or accepted throughout the duration of the project, three master thesis and two doctoral dissertations were completed, with one more doctoral dissertation in progress. We also delivered a presentation summarizing the project&rsquo;s findings at National Science Foundation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/08/2021<br>      Modified by: Alejandra&nbsp;J&nbsp;Magana-De-Leon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The main contribution of this project identified of how to best use touch technologies to help students connect system behaviors in terms of governing forces in the Statics domain. Intellectual merit:  We followed a learner-centered approach for designing visuohaptic simulations and curricular materials.  We implemented three steps: (1) requirements analysis and specification, (2) multimedia application design, and (3) inspection and evaluation of prototypes.  We developed three visuohaptic simulations, three visual-only simulations, and three physical manipulatives. The first simulation (https://youtu.be/71vQRRU-IU0) probes students’ understanding of static friction force and the effects of variables such as: (1) density vs. weight, (2) object’ area of contact vs. weight, (3) friction force vs. surface area. The second simulation (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-bFc6zN6CZo) presents a system of trusses where students explore ideas such as: (1) tension and compression, and (2) zero force members (3) resultant of force systems in equilibrium. The third simulation (https://youtu.be/j5h2xjcK4ds) presents a system of pulleys to explore the effects of different configurations including: (1) numbers of pulleys, (2) length of the string, (3) direction of the pull, and (4) different radius of the pulleys.  Design principles for developing visuohaptic simulations were identified: Visual cues to provide force measurements, color-coding to easy and quickly identify the force magnitude, constraining rotational movement of the objects, ability to feel the weight of the objects, visual cues with spatial location to scaffold navigation in a 3D space, inclusion of a ruler to measure displacement, and inclusion of a visualization of the free body diagram.  We also prepared scaffolding and guidance in the form of worksheets that were developed based on a prediction-observation-explanation strategy. This study extends the understanding of haptic devices' affordances and constraints for teaching force-related science concepts. When pre-assessed, undergraduate students demonstrated fragmented ideas of the concept of friction after a formal lecture. In the post-assessment, after either using a physical manipulative or a visuohaptic simulation, we identified that the physical manipulative tool did not provide a learning advantage. In contrast, the visuohaptic simulation resulted in a positive impact on learning. We also analyzed explanations provided by the learners for answering conceptual questions related to friction concepts. The thematic analysis of students' answers to the conceptual questions (i.e., role of the objects' weight in friction and the objects' size in friction) suggested six main codes organized into two categories; haptically-oriented and visually-oriented categories. The haptically-oriented category is related to the learners' actions performed to move the cubes (e.g., how hard they have to push a cube on a surface). The visually-oriented category, is related to the cubes' actions after the learner initiated the movement (e.g., how fast the cubes moved). During and after the interaction with the visuohaptic simulation, learners tended to provide haptically-oriented explanations, suggesting that the haptic feedback promoted the inference of the forces acting on the cubes while sliding.  The sequencing and order of presenting the visual and tactile feedback was also relevant. Our results suggest\that the sequenced approach of haptic and minimal visual feedback to haptic and enhanced visual feedback (H -&gt; H+V) was a productive configuration. In the first interaction, students inferred the forces acting on the cubes, and in the second interaction, students read the information from the computer screen to confirm or change their observations. Broader impacts: The curricular materials, simulations, and findings of the research associated with this project have had a direct impact on mechanical, materials and civil engineering disciplines, human computer interaction and design, as well as engineering technology disciplines. The outcomes of this research also include a set of principles for the design and integration of visuohaptic simulations for conceptual understanding of difficult concepts in science and engineering. Active dissemination occurred via integration of haptic-enabled laboratory experiences into other courses where the PIs have existing and active collaborations, such as in physics. Specifically, over 1000 undergraduate students from majors in engineering technology, physics education, and psychology have been exposed to the learning materials. The learning materials including the visuohaptic simulations and the guiding materials were shared with faculty at other institutions who have implemented the learning materials with a group of 50 engineering students.  In addition, eight graduate students, six of them female students, and three of them from underrepresented groups, participated in this project. They all received training in educational research, human-computer interaction, and engineering education.  We have also disseminated our learning materials and findings to educators and researchers from learning sciences community, engineering education community and human-computer interaction community through research seminars, and conference presentations for engineering and science educators, both nationally and internationally. In addition to the eight journal manuscripts and five conference proceedings published or accepted throughout the duration of the project, three master thesis and two doctoral dissertations were completed, with one more doctoral dissertation in progress. We also delivered a presentation summarizing the project’s findings at National Science Foundation.          Last Modified: 03/08/2021       Submitted by: Alejandra J Magana-De-Leon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
