<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Some Questions in Commutative Algebra</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/31/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>104355.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>104355</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Janet Striuli</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed projects are in the area of commutative algebra, which is a study of systems of algebraic (polynomial) equations with solutions in commutative rings. A commutative ring may be viewed as an abstract analogue of the integers, in which one can add, subtract and multiply. In the past few decades, commutative algebra has not only found remarkable interactions with other research areas in mathematics, but proven a valuable tool to other disciplines, such as engineering and computer science.  The PI will involve graduate students in his research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will work on several projects arising in commutative algebra. He will investigate properties of local cohomology modules (e.g. vanishing and finiteness) and their connections with topology of algebraic varieties and study singularities in characteristic p and their invariants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1606414</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenliang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenliang Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wlzhang@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000513544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S. Marshfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MB 502, M/C 551]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098987217</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~104355</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the award period, the pI conducted research activities on topics including:</p> <p>1. structure of local cohomology modules</p> <p>2. singularities in prime charactersitic</p> <p>3. de Rham cohomology&nbsp;</p> <p>4. algebraic D-modules</p> <p>These activities have resulted in 16 published (or accepted) research articles and 1 submitted.</p> <p>The outcomes have resolved several open questions, produced the first computationally feasible algorithm to compute the support of local cohomology modules in prime characteristic p, furthered our understanding of behaviors of singularities in families in characteristic p, discovered new class of D-modules that admit finite-dimensional de Rham cohomology and a new duality phenomenon for de Rham cohomology.</p> <p>During this award period, the PI has supervised 2 PhD students and 1 NSF postdoc. One of the PHD students has graduated and holds a postdoc position at University of Michigan. The PI has 4 joint projects with the NSF postdoc which resulted in 2 publications and one submitted research article.</p> <p>During this award period, the PI organized an international conferene on 'D-modules in commutative algebra' in CIMAT, Mexico, an AMS MRC workshop in Snowbird, Utah, and a workshop on 'Local Cohomology' at UIC.</p> <p>The PI has spoken in seminars, Colloquium, and conferences on the results produced from research activities supported by this award..&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Wenliang&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the award period, the pI conducted research activities on topics including:  1. structure of local cohomology modules  2. singularities in prime charactersitic  3. de Rham cohomology   4. algebraic D-modules  These activities have resulted in 16 published (or accepted) research articles and 1 submitted.  The outcomes have resolved several open questions, produced the first computationally feasible algorithm to compute the support of local cohomology modules in prime characteristic p, furthered our understanding of behaviors of singularities in families in characteristic p, discovered new class of D-modules that admit finite-dimensional de Rham cohomology and a new duality phenomenon for de Rham cohomology.  During this award period, the PI has supervised 2 PhD students and 1 NSF postdoc. One of the PHD students has graduated and holds a postdoc position at University of Michigan. The PI has 4 joint projects with the NSF postdoc which resulted in 2 publications and one submitted research article.  During this award period, the PI organized an international conferene on 'D-modules in commutative algebra' in CIMAT, Mexico, an AMS MRC workshop in Snowbird, Utah, and a workshop on 'Local Cohomology' at UIC.  The PI has spoken in seminars, Colloquium, and conferences on the results produced from research activities supported by this award..         Last Modified: 09/27/2018       Submitted by: Wenliang Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
