<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ECCS-CDS&amp;E: Predictive modeling of atomically thin multifunctional semiconductors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>342333.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>342333</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mohammod Ali</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>moali@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924632</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Atomically thin two-dimensional materials are promising for novel electronic and optoelectronic device applications. Most work on two-dimensional materials focuses on graphene and transition metal dichalcogenides. This work focuses on materials that contain elements with lone-pair electrons such as tin selenide, which crystallize in layered structures and simultaneously display many interesting functional properties.  The project will use state-of-the-art predictive materials simulation algorithms to uncover the fundamental materials physics and functional properties of these novel two-dimensional materials and identify promising candidates for electronic and optoelectronic device applications. The proposed work also involves the development and application of innovative simulation algorithms and high-performance computing tools for the high-fidelity predictive modeling of novel materials and devices in order to advance the current frontiers in electronics. This project will also advance the education, training, and mentoring of graduate and undergraduate students in materials physics, electronic and optoelectronic devices, computational techniques, and high-performance computing. The proposed work also will produce open-source computer codes that will be shared with the educational and research communities. The research findings will be incorporated in the undergraduate curriculum and communicated to the general public through outreach presentations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed research is to understand and predict the structural and functional properties (structure, thermodynamics, band structure, vibrational properties, electronic and thermal transport, optical response, strain effects, band alignments) of freestanding and substrate-deposited atomically thin layered semiconducting materials with predictive calculations based on density functional theory and related methods. Materials to explore include SnSe and GeSe, which contain cations with lone-pair electrons. These materials crystallize in layered structures and display an array of unique functional properties, such as anisotropic spin transport and unusually strong optical absorbance in the visible range. A genetic algorithm will be applied to identify promising new materials that simultaneously exhibit multiple functionalities for novel electronic, spintronic, and optoelectronic device applications. The findings of the research project are expected to advance the development and manufacturing of novel electronic and optoelectronic devices with functionalities that are limited by current materials availability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1607796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emmanouil</FirstName>
<LastName>Kioupakis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emmanouil Kioupakis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kioup@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347643321</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000603889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9236</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~342333</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this award was to understand the properties such as the synthesis properties, atomic structure, electronic properties, and optical properties, of new semiconducting materials that are only a few atoms thin. Semiconducting materials such as AlN, GaN, and InN are important commercial semiconductors that are used for electronics that operate at high power and for solid-state light emitters that emit visible light in LED light bulbs or ultraviolet light for disinfection and sterilization. Recently, GaN was synthesized as an atomically thin film. Such two-dimensional materials are important because the extreme quantum confinement of electrons at the atomic scale drastically modifies their properties and enables additional control of its light-emitting properties. In this project, we performed predictive atomistic calculations to understand the electronic and optical properties of atomically thin nitride materials. A unique feature of these materials is that the asymmetry of their crystal structure, consisting of alternating positively and negatively charged atomic planes, results in a strong electric field perpendicular to the two-dimensional plane that separates the excited electrons from their unoccupied states (holes) and further modifies the optical properties. We found that light emission from monolayer 2D GaN occurs in the deep ultraviolet range, which is promising for sterilization and water-purification applications. We also found that by controlling the stacking orientation in bilayer stacks of these materials we can further control the light emission wavelength from the visible to the ultraviolet, as well as control the rate of light emission. Our results could have transformative applications in visible and ultraviolet light-emitting devices for lighting, displays, and sterilization. The project also supported the education and training of a graduate student in materials theory and high-performance computing. The educational goals are the incorporation the result of this research in the undergraduate educational curriculum and the training of graduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Emmanouil&nbsp;Kioupakis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this award was to understand the properties such as the synthesis properties, atomic structure, electronic properties, and optical properties, of new semiconducting materials that are only a few atoms thin. Semiconducting materials such as AlN, GaN, and InN are important commercial semiconductors that are used for electronics that operate at high power and for solid-state light emitters that emit visible light in LED light bulbs or ultraviolet light for disinfection and sterilization. Recently, GaN was synthesized as an atomically thin film. Such two-dimensional materials are important because the extreme quantum confinement of electrons at the atomic scale drastically modifies their properties and enables additional control of its light-emitting properties. In this project, we performed predictive atomistic calculations to understand the electronic and optical properties of atomically thin nitride materials. A unique feature of these materials is that the asymmetry of their crystal structure, consisting of alternating positively and negatively charged atomic planes, results in a strong electric field perpendicular to the two-dimensional plane that separates the excited electrons from their unoccupied states (holes) and further modifies the optical properties. We found that light emission from monolayer 2D GaN occurs in the deep ultraviolet range, which is promising for sterilization and water-purification applications. We also found that by controlling the stacking orientation in bilayer stacks of these materials we can further control the light emission wavelength from the visible to the ultraviolet, as well as control the rate of light emission. Our results could have transformative applications in visible and ultraviolet light-emitting devices for lighting, displays, and sterilization. The project also supported the education and training of a graduate student in materials theory and high-performance computing. The educational goals are the incorporation the result of this research in the undergraduate educational curriculum and the training of graduate students.       Last Modified: 04/28/2021       Submitted by: Emmanouil Kioupakis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
