<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Compact Binary Mergers in the Advanced LIGO Era</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>180000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A new window on the universe opened recently with the detection of gravitational waves by the LIGO gravitational wave observatory. Other telescopes observe electromagnetic waves (that includes visible light), and this new window will give us quite different and complementary information. The work described here seeks to understand better how to get the most information from these gravitational wave observations. In particular, we study the very violent merger of neutron stars and black holes to determine how the properties of these systems are encoded in both gravitational and electromagnetic waves.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals supported by this award are to study the dynamics of compact objects and the radiation they emit to capture the most science possible from aLIGO and similar detectors. We will do so through computational studies of binary systems incorporating magnetized matter with resistive effects, realistic equations of state, electromagnetic and neutrino emission, and r-process nucleosynthesis. Our efforts will include the following: (i) We will determine gravitational waveforms from these binaries, with a focus on observable imprints from the neutron star equation of state, mass, and radius.  (ii) We will investigate the construction of analytic and phenomenological gravitational wave templates. (iii) We will study outflows from merging binaries as an indicator of events with characteristic electromagnetic and neutrino signals. (iv) We will study the global behavior of magnetic fields  and the electromagnetic emissions, such as jets, that originate in the magnetosphere of coalescing binaries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1607291</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Liebling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven L Liebling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steve.liebling@liu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5162993439</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000421110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Long Island University</Name>
<CityName>BROOKVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>115481327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7184881413</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>700 NORTHERN BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Projects]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065933103</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LONG ISLAND UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065933103</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Long Island University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>115481300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1244</Code>
<Text>Gravity Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project studied various astrophysical scenarios expected to be observed by LIGO, a new gravitational wave observatory.&nbsp; Such an observatory is sensitive to ripples in spacetime which are most efficiently generated by the acceleration of very compact, massive objects such as neutron stars and black holes.&nbsp; Indeed, LIGO has observed the mergers of binary black hole systems and also binary neutron stars.&nbsp;<br />Because such observations are extremely difficult and LIGO's results represent the first direct detections of gravitational waves, one essentially has to have predications of what the various signals will look like in order to extract the science from these observations.&nbsp; One of the most important methods for predicting what such systems will look like is to carry-out fully nonlinear, numerical modeling.<br />Much of the numerical work involves Einstein's theory of gravity, and indeed observations are perfectly consistent with Einstein's theory.&nbsp; However, as observations get more precise and possible surprises are observed, one hopes to either test Einstein's theory or discover that nature follows some alternative.&nbsp; This project therefore studied various modifications, including: binary black hole mergers in Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton gravity, black hole collisions with a near horizon modification as might be expected from a quantum theory of gravity, and also binary neutron star mergers within a theory of gravity augmented with a scalar field.<br />This project also involves improving our codes and techniques for such modeling. Likewise, this research helps train students and postdoctoral scholars in numerical modeling.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/20/2020<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;L&nbsp;Liebling</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project studied various astrophysical scenarios expected to be observed by LIGO, a new gravitational wave observatory.  Such an observatory is sensitive to ripples in spacetime which are most efficiently generated by the acceleration of very compact, massive objects such as neutron stars and black holes.  Indeed, LIGO has observed the mergers of binary black hole systems and also binary neutron stars.  Because such observations are extremely difficult and LIGO's results represent the first direct detections of gravitational waves, one essentially has to have predications of what the various signals will look like in order to extract the science from these observations.  One of the most important methods for predicting what such systems will look like is to carry-out fully nonlinear, numerical modeling. Much of the numerical work involves Einstein's theory of gravity, and indeed observations are perfectly consistent with Einstein's theory.  However, as observations get more precise and possible surprises are observed, one hopes to either test Einstein's theory or discover that nature follows some alternative.  This project therefore studied various modifications, including: binary black hole mergers in Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton gravity, black hole collisions with a near horizon modification as might be expected from a quantum theory of gravity, and also binary neutron star mergers within a theory of gravity augmented with a scalar field. This project also involves improving our codes and techniques for such modeling. Likewise, this research helps train students and postdoctoral scholars in numerical modeling.             Last Modified: 09/20/2020       Submitted by: Steven L Liebling]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
