<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Physics and Applications of Cooperative Effects in Nonlinear and Quantum Optics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Forrey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rforrey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925199</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A dense collection of atoms can display collective phenomena which are fundamentally different from those in dilute samples. An example is super-radiance, where an ensemble of atoms collectively interacts with a specific light field. While recognized long ago, this topic has gained importance over the last few years. Many areas of fundamental research, such as quantum information science, and of applications, such as the construction of accurate atomic clocks, now utilize collective properties of dense ensembles. Density effects can be detrimental. Increasing the interaction strength between atoms can destroy the coherent response of the atoms to external stimuli, which is necessary for quantum computers or precise clocks. The goal of this project is to (i) find and understand density-dependent collective effects and their consequences, (ii) to investigate methods to either mitigate or isolate the effects in a way to improve experimental control of the ensembles, and (iii) to research the various ways in which such effects can enable new technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Basic questions will be studied regarding collective effects in cooperative media, such as: Do super-radiant effects depend on density or optical depth? What exactly is the role of the exchange interaction? What makes driven cooperative systems special? Is super-radiance fully described by pairwise correlations, and for which systems are other approximations needed? In order to achieve these goals, new analytical and numerical methods will be developed. In addition, the particular effects that will be investigated in this project include induced and spontaneous collective line shifts, spin and light field "squeezing" and entanglement. In addition, statistics and nonlinearities of the dynamic Casimir effect will be compared to the collective effects of super-radiant systems. Most of these projects will include collaboration with experimental efforts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1607637</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Yelin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susanne F Yelin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>syelin@g.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174951383</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492004</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[438 Whitney Road Ext.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>"More is different" is a common quote to indicate the central questions of many-body physics. It means, in the present context, that the interaction of light with an ensemble of radiators, such as atoms, can qualitatively be different from just the sum over the interaction of light with a single such radiator.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the presence of many radiators that can all interact with the same light field nonlinear correlations build up which lead to speed-up ("superradiance") or slow-down ("subradiance") of the usual spontaneous decay process. In addition, the frequency of the emitted light can shift. These effects are highly non-linear and can sensitively depend on various parameters. This makes a general description and understanding of such effects difficult. In this project, we developed a theory which increases understanding and showed special examples and comparison with experiments to prove this.</p> <p>The reason why these findings are important are not just of fundamental value. Nowadays, many experiments in quantum optics including, for example, quantum information science and metrology, are reaching regimes where those cooperative effects automatically play an important role. One of the reasons is that in both cases, scaling up the number of atoms or "qubits" in the system is necessary for their usefulness. Thus, the goal of this work was to, on one hand, allow better interpretation and preparation for such experiments, and on the other hand, to develop tools that add new and potentially helpful aspects to them.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Susanne&nbsp;F&nbsp;Yelin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ "More is different" is a common quote to indicate the central questions of many-body physics. It means, in the present context, that the interaction of light with an ensemble of radiators, such as atoms, can qualitatively be different from just the sum over the interaction of light with a single such radiator.   In the presence of many radiators that can all interact with the same light field nonlinear correlations build up which lead to speed-up ("superradiance") or slow-down ("subradiance") of the usual spontaneous decay process. In addition, the frequency of the emitted light can shift. These effects are highly non-linear and can sensitively depend on various parameters. This makes a general description and understanding of such effects difficult. In this project, we developed a theory which increases understanding and showed special examples and comparison with experiments to prove this.  The reason why these findings are important are not just of fundamental value. Nowadays, many experiments in quantum optics including, for example, quantum information science and metrology, are reaching regimes where those cooperative effects automatically play an important role. One of the reasons is that in both cases, scaling up the number of atoms or "qubits" in the system is necessary for their usefulness. Thus, the goal of this work was to, on one hand, allow better interpretation and preparation for such experiments, and on the other hand, to develop tools that add new and potentially helpful aspects to them.        Last Modified: 02/29/2020       Submitted by: Susanne F Yelin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
