<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Neutrino Interactions in the NuMI Off-Axis Electron Neutrino Appearance (NOvA) Near Detector</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>246000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Shank</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshank@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Neutrinos are among the most abundant particles in the universe, emanating from stars, nuclear reactors, the core of the earth and even interactions from the early universe. Despite their abundance, there is limited knowledge about many of the fundamental properties of neutrinos such as their mass. A broad international research program is progressing to study the properties of these particles. One aspect of this program is to investigate neutrino oscillations: one type of neutrino changing into another type. Measuring these oscillations could lead to new models of particle interaction. In order for measurements to continue to improve, understanding how the neutrino interacts with other types of matter becomes critical. This project will carry out a focused research effort with the objective to characterize neutrino interactions with matter to enhance the domestic neutrino research program. This work will also have broad impact by enhancing the "big data" initiative at WSU, which is a multidisciplinary effort that seeks to engage the campus, its student base, and local industry in cutting-edge data analytic techniques which are applicable in a wide range of both industrial and academic fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will be accomplished by analyzing neutrino interaction data from the NuMI Off-axis electron-neutrino Appearance experiment (NOvA) near detector. The NOvA near detector is sited in the main injector neutrino source at Fermilab, just outside Chicago, Illinois. This setup provides a very intense, near mono-energetic source of neutrinos, and a detector ideal for measuring a broad range of interaction types.  One of the limitations of neutrino oscillation measurement is the uncertainty in neutrino - nucleon interactions. This work will provide new and critical neutrino-nucleon measurements to help more fully understand the nature of neutrino interactions with matter while providing several young scientists opportunities to engage in world leading high energy particle physics research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1607410</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mathew</FirstName>
<LastName>Muether</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mathew Muether</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mathew.muether@wichita.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3169783285</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681935</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wichita State University</Name>
<CityName>Wichita</CityName>
<ZipCode>672600007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3169783285</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1845 Fairmount</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Box 007]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053078127</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WICHITA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053078127</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wichita State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Wichita</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>672600007</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1845 Fairmount Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~246000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Professor Muether worked as the NOvA cross-section physics analysis coordinator and advised multiple graduate students on neutrino interaction analyses. This work has resulted in NOvA's recently publicly presented results from its first two cross-section measurements focused on neutral pion production using its near detector data.&nbsp;</p> <p>One of the presented measurements focused on neutrinos that interacted coherently via the weak neutral-current with atomic nuclei creating neutrino interactions with no vertex activity and a single forward neutral pion&nbsp;particle.&nbsp;This measurement represents one of the most precise measurements of this process performed to date. Results have been published in Physical Review D.</p> <p>The NOvA Cross Section group also measured the differential semi-inclusive cross section for charged-current interactions producing at least one neutral pion by identifying events with a muon and at&nbsp;least one photon (likely from pion decay) in the final state. Results are currently being prepared for publication.</p> <p>Development work for future pion production analyses was also completed. Graduate assistant Alan Cedeno and undergraduate researcher Reed Bowles from WSU both successfully developed event selection for a future neutral current neutral pion semi-inclusive measurement. Alan utilized NOvA's machine learning tools to identify a sample of Neutral Current Neutral pions with a purity of better than 70% and uncertainties in the 12% range. Alan successfully defended his graduate thesis on this project and has since joined the Illinois Institute of Technology. Reed successfully developed a 3-prong selector of the same channel using deep learning tools. Additionally, graduate student Zak Elkarghli has begun the development of a deep-learning-based vertex finder, with an aim to improve vertexing in NOvA and ultimately pion energy reconstruction.&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, one of the primary efforts of the neutrino interaction group lead by Prof. Muether currently underway is to characterize the muon-neutrino and electron-neutrino charged current interactions on the detector's nuclear material.&nbsp;Preliminary results from both channels have been presented at the Fermilab Joint Theory-Experiment Seminar and a paper on each measurement is nearly complete. &nbsp;</p> <p>Work has also been complete on topics with Broader impacts. Professor Muether is leading a campus-wide effort at Wichita State on data analytics education and research. He has organized seminars for campus faculty to present their work using data analytics tools. Professor Muether has been working to develop an interdisciplinary data science program at the university which enables training of students to meet industry needs for analysts. Professor Muether served as part of the leadership committee which drafted a successful proposal for a "cluster-hire" in the area of "Data-Driven Decision Making". This will be a multi-faculty hire split between the colleges of Engineering and Liberal Arts and Science that will work to develop and enable multi-disciplinary academic and research efforts on campus focused on the development of data analytic tools and their deployment into domain-specific areas of science and industry. WSU is developing an "Innovation Campus" which hosts industry partners like Airbus, and GoCreate. This effort will help to further build the relationship between these two sides of campus giving local students unique exposure to industry and technical experience. &nbsp;</p> <p>Prof. Muether has worked to develop a 12 credit-hour certificate program on the topic of Data Analysis. The certificate will be joint between Physics, Statistics, and Mathematics, offering students a succinct program to quickly come up to speed on modern data analysis techniques and to produce a capstone project to apply their new knowledge. This will serve as a useful way to introduce talented students to the data issues of High Energy Particle Physics while preparing them with skills desired by industry. The program requires a Capstone Course which can include a physics-based project focused on analytics.</p> <p>Prof. Muether has worked with WSU?s Office of Research to engage local and national industry including Nvidia, AirBus, Accuweather, and&nbsp;ZE Powergroup seeking to understand their technical needs and how the university can most successfully train students to enter this growing workforce. This effort allows Prof. Muether to broadly apply his technical skills while learning new techniques that could be brought to bear on High Energy Particle Physics Problems.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Professor Muether is also involved in outreach through social media. He is chair of the NOvA social media team which produces content for the project's Twitter, Facebook, and Instagram accounts. The group regularly reaches groups of more than 20,000 viewers with content like control room tours, updates on the project work, and stories about collaborators and their work in the community.&nbsp;</p> <p>Prof. Muether is also supporting underrepresented populations in science as the WSU representative for the APS Bridge Program which seeks to engage students from underrepresented minorities and place them in graduate programs which will help them bridge background deficiencies and blossom into strong researchers.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Mathew&nbsp;Muether</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602172279385_Pi0FOM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602172279385_Pi0FOM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Neutral Pion Selector Figure of Merit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602172279385_Pi0FOM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Neutral Pion Selector Figure of Merit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NOvA neutral current neutral pion production fractional cross section uncertainty as a function of selector ID.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alan Cedeno</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mathew&nbsp;Muether</div> <div class="imageTitle">Neutral Pion Selector Figure of Merit</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602172563863_CCpi0--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602172563863_CCpi0--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Charged-current neutral pion results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602172563863_CCpi0--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Charged-current neutral pion results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Kinematic cross section distributions for CC neutral pion production in NOvA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">NOvA Collaboration</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mathew&nbsp;Muether</div> <div class="imageTitle">Charged-current neutral pion results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299201548_NCPi0--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299201548_NCPi0--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Neutral Current Coherent Neutral Pion Results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299201548_NCPi0--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Neutral Current Coherent Neutral Pion Results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The left plot compares this measurement to previous measurements. The right plot compares this measurement with the genie predicted flux-averaged cross section from the Rein-Sehgal model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Phys. Rev. D 102, 012004</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mathew&nbsp;Muether</div> <div class="imageTitle">Neutral Current Coherent Neutral Pion Results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299418477_nueCC--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299418477_nueCC--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Electron Neutrio Results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299418477_nueCC--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Electron Neutrio Results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Electron Neutrino cross-section with respect to lepton energy in slices of lepton angle.</div> <div class="imageCredit">NOvA Collaboratoin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mathew&nbsp;Muether</div> <div class="imageTitle">Electron Neutrio Results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299520115_numuCC--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299520115_numuCC--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Muon neutrino interaction results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1607410/1607410_10435801_1602299520115_numuCC--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Muon neutrino interaction results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Muon-neutrino cross section with respect to lepton energy in slices of lepton angle.</div> <div class="imageCredit">NOvA Collaboratoin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mathew&nbsp;Muether</div> <div class="imageTitle">Muon neutrino interaction results</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Professor Muether worked as the NOvA cross-section physics analysis coordinator and advised multiple graduate students on neutrino interaction analyses. This work has resulted in NOvA's recently publicly presented results from its first two cross-section measurements focused on neutral pion production using its near detector data.   One of the presented measurements focused on neutrinos that interacted coherently via the weak neutral-current with atomic nuclei creating neutrino interactions with no vertex activity and a single forward neutral pion particle. This measurement represents one of the most precise measurements of this process performed to date. Results have been published in Physical Review D.  The NOvA Cross Section group also measured the differential semi-inclusive cross section for charged-current interactions producing at least one neutral pion by identifying events with a muon and at least one photon (likely from pion decay) in the final state. Results are currently being prepared for publication.  Development work for future pion production analyses was also completed. Graduate assistant Alan Cedeno and undergraduate researcher Reed Bowles from WSU both successfully developed event selection for a future neutral current neutral pion semi-inclusive measurement. Alan utilized NOvA's machine learning tools to identify a sample of Neutral Current Neutral pions with a purity of better than 70% and uncertainties in the 12% range. Alan successfully defended his graduate thesis on this project and has since joined the Illinois Institute of Technology. Reed successfully developed a 3-prong selector of the same channel using deep learning tools. Additionally, graduate student Zak Elkarghli has begun the development of a deep-learning-based vertex finder, with an aim to improve vertexing in NOvA and ultimately pion energy reconstruction.   Additionally, one of the primary efforts of the neutrino interaction group lead by Prof. Muether currently underway is to characterize the muon-neutrino and electron-neutrino charged current interactions on the detector's nuclear material. Preliminary results from both channels have been presented at the Fermilab Joint Theory-Experiment Seminar and a paper on each measurement is nearly complete.    Work has also been complete on topics with Broader impacts. Professor Muether is leading a campus-wide effort at Wichita State on data analytics education and research. He has organized seminars for campus faculty to present their work using data analytics tools. Professor Muether has been working to develop an interdisciplinary data science program at the university which enables training of students to meet industry needs for analysts. Professor Muether served as part of the leadership committee which drafted a successful proposal for a "cluster-hire" in the area of "Data-Driven Decision Making". This will be a multi-faculty hire split between the colleges of Engineering and Liberal Arts and Science that will work to develop and enable multi-disciplinary academic and research efforts on campus focused on the development of data analytic tools and their deployment into domain-specific areas of science and industry. WSU is developing an "Innovation Campus" which hosts industry partners like Airbus, and GoCreate. This effort will help to further build the relationship between these two sides of campus giving local students unique exposure to industry and technical experience.    Prof. Muether has worked to develop a 12 credit-hour certificate program on the topic of Data Analysis. The certificate will be joint between Physics, Statistics, and Mathematics, offering students a succinct program to quickly come up to speed on modern data analysis techniques and to produce a capstone project to apply their new knowledge. This will serve as a useful way to introduce talented students to the data issues of High Energy Particle Physics while preparing them with skills desired by industry. The program requires a Capstone Course which can include a physics-based project focused on analytics.  Prof. Muether has worked with WSU?s Office of Research to engage local and national industry including Nvidia, AirBus, Accuweather, and ZE Powergroup seeking to understand their technical needs and how the university can most successfully train students to enter this growing workforce. This effort allows Prof. Muether to broadly apply his technical skills while learning new techniques that could be brought to bear on High Energy Particle Physics Problems.    Professor Muether is also involved in outreach through social media. He is chair of the NOvA social media team which produces content for the project's Twitter, Facebook, and Instagram accounts. The group regularly reaches groups of more than 20,000 viewers with content like control room tours, updates on the project work, and stories about collaborators and their work in the community.   Prof. Muether is also supporting underrepresented populations in science as the WSU representative for the APS Bridge Program which seeks to engage students from underrepresented minorities and place them in graduate programs which will help them bridge background deficiencies and blossom into strong researchers.           Last Modified: 10/09/2020       Submitted by: Mathew Muether]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
