<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Degree-One Maps, Surgery, and Heegaard Genus of 3-Manifolds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>237615.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>237615</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Three-manifolds are objects modeled on the three-dimensional space that we are living in.  A doughnut and the spatial universe are both examples of three-manifolds. These objects arise naturally in many contexts in physical and other natural sciences and model many interesting phenomena. A geometric way of studying them is to cut a complicated three-manifold into simpler three-dimensional pieces along two-dimensional surfaces. For example, a so-called Heegaard splitting is such a decomposition. One can also use a technique known as surgery on a three-manifold that replaces a geometric piece with a different one. In this project, the PI plans to study various questions on three-manifolds using Heegaard splitting and surgery. The research targets several central questions in low-dimensional topology and knot theory, which has potential impact on other areas of scientific investigations, such as the topological structures of DNA.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, the PI plans to study topology of three-manifolds. The first part of the research is to study a long-standing conjecture concerning Heegaard genus and degree-one map. The conjecture can be translated into a study of how Heegaard genus changes under a special type of surgeries and the PI plans to study such surgeries. The PI also plans to study several related questions on Heegaard genus of certain amalgamated three-manifolds. The second part of the project is to explore a new approach to proving the Berge Conjecture. This approach is inspired by the PI's observation that if there is a certain intersection pattern, then one can perform a stabilization and then an unstabilization, changing a Heegaard splitting of a knot exterior (in a lens space) into a meridionally primitive splitting. The PI plans to develop new tools and use techniques from his previous work to achieve these goals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1607830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tao</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tao Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>taoli@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523767</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~77986</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~78820</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~80809</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW77517494 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW77517494 BCX0">The main goal of this NSF funded project is to study low-dimensional topology. &nbsp;Topology is a branch of mathematics studying the qualitative shape and intrinsic properties of geometric objects. Topological ideas are present in almost all areas of today's mathematics. Manifolds are geometric objects that locally modeled on the Euclidean spaces. &nbsp;For instance, a 2-dimensional manifold is just a surface. &nbsp;The main focus of this project is 3-dimensional manifolds, often referred to as 3-manifolds. &nbsp;Three-manifold research has attracted significant attention in that 3-manifolds have beautiful geometric and combinatorial structures and many important questions remain unsolved. &nbsp;A better understanding of these structures is of central interest in geometry and topology and may have a profound impact on physical and other natural sciences. <br /><br />A geometric way of studying 3-manifolds is to cut a complicated 3-manifold into simpler 3-dimensional pieces along 2-dimensional surfaces. For example, a Heegaard splitting is such a decomposition. One can also perform surgery on a 3-manifold by replacing a geometric piece with a different one.&nbsp; In this project, the PI carried out an in-depth study on various questions on 3-manifolds using Heegaard splitting and surgery. &nbsp;The first question is the so-called Berge Conjecture, which says that, if a knot in the 3-dimensional sphere admits a lens-space surgery, then the knot must be one of a known list of knots tabulated by John Berge. The Berge Conjecture is one of the most fundamental questions in low-dimensional topology. The PI and his collaborators made a breakthrough by proving that the Berge Conjecture holds for all knots that can be unknotted by a single tunnel. Since all the Berge knots can be unknotted using a single tunnel, this result can be viewed as one-half of the Berge Conjecture. <br /><br />The PI also studied an important relation between 3-manifolds called degree-one map. &nbsp;A long-standing conjecture in 3-manifold topology asserts that the minimal genus of Heegaard splittings of a 3-manifold does not decrease under a degree-one map. The PI transforms this conjecture into a question about a type of surgery that replaces a certain submanifold with a simple 3-manifold called handlebody. In this project, the PI proved the genus-one case of this conjecture. An immediate corollary of this result is that the tunnel number of a satellite knot is at least as large as the tunnel number of its pattern knot.<br /><br />The PI's Ph.D. student Mustafa Cengiz, partially supported by the NSF grant, has obtained some interesting results on the relation between Heegaard splitting, open-book decomposition of 3-manifolds, and the translation distance of fibration. Cengiz proved that the translation distance of any fibered knot in the 3-dimensional sphere is at most three. This partially confirmed a conjecture of Schleimer.<br /><br />The PI has also used this project to train junior graduate students in summer reading and research programs at Boston College. &nbsp;The PI has taught a graduate topic course and he has incorporated materials from this project into this course. &nbsp;The PI has also given lectures in conferences and seminars on his research in this NSF project.&nbsp;</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/15/2020<br>      Modified by: Tao&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goal of this NSF funded project is to study low-dimensional topology.  Topology is a branch of mathematics studying the qualitative shape and intrinsic properties of geometric objects. Topological ideas are present in almost all areas of today's mathematics. Manifolds are geometric objects that locally modeled on the Euclidean spaces.  For instance, a 2-dimensional manifold is just a surface.  The main focus of this project is 3-dimensional manifolds, often referred to as 3-manifolds.  Three-manifold research has attracted significant attention in that 3-manifolds have beautiful geometric and combinatorial structures and many important questions remain unsolved.  A better understanding of these structures is of central interest in geometry and topology and may have a profound impact on physical and other natural sciences.   A geometric way of studying 3-manifolds is to cut a complicated 3-manifold into simpler 3-dimensional pieces along 2-dimensional surfaces. For example, a Heegaard splitting is such a decomposition. One can also perform surgery on a 3-manifold by replacing a geometric piece with a different one.  In this project, the PI carried out an in-depth study on various questions on 3-manifolds using Heegaard splitting and surgery.  The first question is the so-called Berge Conjecture, which says that, if a knot in the 3-dimensional sphere admits a lens-space surgery, then the knot must be one of a known list of knots tabulated by John Berge. The Berge Conjecture is one of the most fundamental questions in low-dimensional topology. The PI and his collaborators made a breakthrough by proving that the Berge Conjecture holds for all knots that can be unknotted by a single tunnel. Since all the Berge knots can be unknotted using a single tunnel, this result can be viewed as one-half of the Berge Conjecture.   The PI also studied an important relation between 3-manifolds called degree-one map.  A long-standing conjecture in 3-manifold topology asserts that the minimal genus of Heegaard splittings of a 3-manifold does not decrease under a degree-one map. The PI transforms this conjecture into a question about a type of surgery that replaces a certain submanifold with a simple 3-manifold called handlebody. In this project, the PI proved the genus-one case of this conjecture. An immediate corollary of this result is that the tunnel number of a satellite knot is at least as large as the tunnel number of its pattern knot.  The PI's Ph.D. student Mustafa Cengiz, partially supported by the NSF grant, has obtained some interesting results on the relation between Heegaard splitting, open-book decomposition of 3-manifolds, and the translation distance of fibration. Cengiz proved that the translation distance of any fibered knot in the 3-dimensional sphere is at most three. This partially confirmed a conjecture of Schleimer.  The PI has also used this project to train junior graduate students in summer reading and research programs at Boston College.  The PI has taught a graduate topic course and he has incorporated materials from this project into this course.  The PI has also given lectures in conferences and seminars on his research in this NSF project.         Last Modified: 10/15/2020       Submitted by: Tao Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
