<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ACM SIGMOD Conference 2016: Student Activities and Travel Support</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to provide a unique opportunity for about 16 database students to present their research results, learn cutting edge research, and interact with internationally recognized researchers from both academia and industry at the Association for Computing Machinery's Special Interest Group on Management of Data (ACM SIGMOD) 2016 Conference (http://sigmod2016.org/) that will be held June 26 - July 1, 2016 in San Francisco, California. As one of the most prestigious conferences in data management research, ACM SIGMOD and the associated Symposium on Principles of Database Systems (PODS) have contributed significantly to the advance of all aspects of data management technologies and applications since 1975. Besides meeting with researchers from academia and industry during regular program sessions, in SIGMOD/PODS 2016 students will be able to participate in the following interactive activities as partially supported by this project: a new researcher symposium, an undergraduate research poster competition, face-to-face meetings with leading researchers, and a student mentoring workshop. These opportunities will have a long lasting impact on the future career of the participants. This award will provide partial support for students from U.S. institutions, especially female and minority students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ACM SIGMOD/PODS is a dynamic and comprehensive program for publication, education, and interaction; and it is a leading international forum for database researchers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore cutting-edge ideas and results and to exchange techniques, tools, and experiences.  ACM SIGMOD/PODS plays a significant role in training the future generation of leaders and workforce in the critical field of data management.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1607205</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eugene Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ew2493@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104995876</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000690634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100277922</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The annual ACM SIGMOD conference is a leading international forum for database researchers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore cutting-edge ideas and results, and to exchange techniques, tools, and experiences.&nbsp; ACM SIGMOD is today a dynamic and comprehensive program for publication, education, and interaction, including research papers, tutorials, panels, industrial papers, technical demonstrations, undergraduate research papers. The program also includes workshops that demand dedicated coverage due to their relevance to the current data management research and development, industrial exhibits, a &ldquo;New Researcher&rdquo; symposium, and keynote talks by leaders in academia and industry.</p> <p>The 2016 conference was held in San Francisco, CA USA during 6/26 - 7/1.&nbsp; Students, particularly from lesser known schools, are often unable to attend due to the costs of registration, travel, and hotel stay.&nbsp; To this end, this award served to enable 17 to attend the SIGMOD conference that woud otherwise have had financial difficulty in attended. Each student was allocated up to $1,250 for travel reimbursement. In addition, ACM SIGMOD provided free registration for these students. This allows these students to meet with leading database researchers, see the breadth of industry opportunities, and student-specific activites at the conference, including the New Researcher Symposium, the Undergraduate Research Poster Competition, and the student programming contest.&nbsp; These students included&nbsp;six female students and one latinx student.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2018<br>      Modified by: Eugene&nbsp;Wu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The annual ACM SIGMOD conference is a leading international forum for database researchers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore cutting-edge ideas and results, and to exchange techniques, tools, and experiences.  ACM SIGMOD is today a dynamic and comprehensive program for publication, education, and interaction, including research papers, tutorials, panels, industrial papers, technical demonstrations, undergraduate research papers. The program also includes workshops that demand dedicated coverage due to their relevance to the current data management research and development, industrial exhibits, a "New Researcher" symposium, and keynote talks by leaders in academia and industry.  The 2016 conference was held in San Francisco, CA USA during 6/26 - 7/1.  Students, particularly from lesser known schools, are often unable to attend due to the costs of registration, travel, and hotel stay.  To this end, this award served to enable 17 to attend the SIGMOD conference that woud otherwise have had financial difficulty in attended. Each student was allocated up to $1,250 for travel reimbursement. In addition, ACM SIGMOD provided free registration for these students. This allows these students to meet with leading database researchers, see the breadth of industry opportunities, and student-specific activites at the conference, including the New Researcher Symposium, the Undergraduate Research Poster Competition, and the student programming contest.  These students included six female students and one latinx student.       Last Modified: 10/02/2018       Submitted by: Eugene Wu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
