<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Arctic Horizons: Social Science and the High North</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>61487.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>61487</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna M. Kerttula</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the past 15 years, the Arctic has experienced substantial social and environmental transformations. Some of these changes are on pace with predictions of the late 1990s, but others have occurred much more rapidly than expected. Many of the documented and anticipated shifts in the Arctic are linked to environmental change: changing sea ice and snow cover, coastal erosion leading to displacement of modern villages and destruction of preserved archaeological sites, questions of subsistence food security, increased shipping and oil exploration, with their associated economic impacts (positive and negative) and risk of oil spills, to name just a few. Many other changes in the Arctic are largely independent of changing climate: continued loss of Native languages, high rates of unemployment, domestic violence and substance abuse, and the increased influence of social media among and between isolated communities of the high north. Yet, while the North has always seemed remote and marginal to global or US national interests, Arctic people and environments are increasingly connected socially, economically, and environmentally to those living to the south.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The potential for an increasingly ice-free Arctic Ocean, for example, opens up possibilities for new shipping routes shifting economic costs and benefits for global markets, for expanded exploitation of the circumpolar basin?s fossil fuel and mineral resources,  and for attendant new focus on the north as an economic and security zone of strategic and tactical importance. All of these potential transformations have impacts not only on the United States' northernmost communities, but also on the global and national economic, social, and cultural systems best studied by social scientists in interdisciplinary collaborations capable of providing information and strategies of need for policy development and community development.   The National Science Foundation?s Arctic Social Sciences Program (ASSP) is the leading source of funding for U.S.-based social sciences research in the Arctic. Just as the Arctic has changed, Arctic social sciences have experienced substantial growth and development, transitioning from an emerging field of research to a well-established multidisciplinary research area; yet the research priorities for NSF?s Arctic Social Sciences program were last updated in 1999.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Arctic Horizons project will bring together members of the Arctic social science research and indigenous communities to reassess the goals, potentials, and needs of these diverse communities and ASSP within the context of a rapidly changing circumpolar North. A series of five topical and regional workshops held across the country will bring together approximately 150 western and indigenous scholars to discuss the future of Arctic social science research. Additional participation by the broader Arctic social sciences, indigenous science, and stakeholder communities will be solicited through an interactive web platform that will also share workshop and&lt;br/&gt; project outcomes, supported by special sessions at national and regional conferences.  The results of the workshops and on-line input will be compiled at a final synthesis workshop with a report produced to describes the community's vision for the future of Arctic social science research. This re-envisioning process will help shape future Arctic social science research and inform Arctic economic, environmental, and political policy development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Arctic Horizons project provides a framework and process that will bring together the Arctic social science research and Arctic indigenous communities to reassess goals, potentials, and needs in the diverse disciplinary and transdisciplinary currents of social science research of the circumpolar North.  A series of five regional workshops and one synthesis workshop will engage approximately 150 western and indigenous scholars in the re-visioning process.  Additional participation by the broader Arctic social sciences, indigenous science, and stakeholder communities will be solicited through an interactive web platform that will also be used to share  workshop and project outcomes (e.g. videos of speakers, workshop notes, copy of the report), as well as through special sessions at regional conferences (e.g. Alaska Anthropological Association Annual Meeting, Arctic Science Summit Week, Association of American Geographers). Whenever possible, keynote addresses will be video live cast through the platform and preserved for convenient review. Dynamic embeddable data visualizations will present the running results of project analytics, including text analysis of associations in the transcripts of workshop discussions, participant survey results, citation surveys, and an analysis of all 737 NSF grants issued since 1981. The resulting community-based vision will inform research investments for Arctic social science research over the next decade. Arctic social sciences have experienced substantial growth and development over the past 15 years, transitioning from an emerging field of research to a well-established multidisciplinary research area since the last Arctic social sciences visioning workshop held in 1999.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is the collaboration of five institutions, all of which have a strong history of supporting Arctic social science research (UAF and Brown) or are developing new programs that support Arctic social science research (UNI and PSU).   The process will be overseen by a senior advisory panel that includes social scientists and indigenous community members.  The project will leverage the broad research networks of the PIs to recruit participation from a diverse and wide-ranging group&lt;br/&gt; of early, mid and senior career scholars, ensuring gender and disciplinary equity and the participation of underrepresented groups.  This will be achieved through targeted invitation to workshops, a promotional campaign for web input through electronic media, and through participant recruitment at conferences and meetings. The capstone event is a synthesis workshop where the information generated at each of the regional/topical workshops and the on-line input will be combined in a report on the research priorities collectively identified by the Arctic social sciences community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1608912</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Butler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia L Butler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>virginia@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5037253303</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261366</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Etnier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael A Etnier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mike.etnier@wwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3607388292</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shelby</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shelby Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shelby.anderson@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5037253318</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Portland State University</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Attn: Sponsored Projects Admin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052226800</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052226800</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Portland State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~61487</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Arctic Horizons is a multi-institution collaboration that hosted a series of workshops and town halls in 2016 in an effort to bring together the Arctic social science research community.&nbsp; Our goal was to reassess Arctic social science research priorities for the next decade.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Since the last ASSP visioning workshop in 1999, social science research in the Arctic has experienced substantial growth and transitioned from an emerging program at the National Science Foundation (NSF) to a well-established multidisciplinary research area. Changes in the Arctic over the last 20 years create opportunities for some and challenges for others, revealing vulnerability, innovation and resilience at community, state and national levels. The impacts of the International Polar Year in 2007-2008 and NSF investment in the Arctic Social Sciences Program (ASSP) were transformational for defining social sciences in the Arctic and ensuring that the United States secured a leading role in Northern social science research. The ASSP funded research that provides foundational, interdisciplinary knowledge critical to understanding Arctic peoples and to the development of local, national, and international policies. Arctic Social Science research sheds light on the dynamic contexts of contemporary Arctic environmental, economic, political, social, and strategic opportunities and challenges. It contributes towards safeguarding the cultural heritage of the North&rsquo;s Indigenous peoples. ASSP projects integrate natural science data, social science approaches, Indigenous Knowledge, and Community-Based Monitoring to understand the rapidly changing Arctic and public policy choices before us in this new age. Every indication suggests that the volume and diversity of human activities in the Arctic will increase, and thus, so will demand for social scientific study.</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Workshop Findings</strong></p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Arctic social science makes major, pioneering contributions to: community-based research methodologies, Indigenous scholarship, sociology of disaster, language vitality studies, social and environmental impact assessment, co-management studies, socio-ecological systems research and modeling, and resilience theory.</li> </ul> <ul> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Arctic social science research is increasingly collaborative and community-driven.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Political tensions among Arctic countries can stymie collaborative research and reduce access to new knowledge. </li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Research on the effects of a wide range of interactive changes will be crucial to future Arctic social science research.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Climate change and other socio-environmental processes, coupled with development, result in the rapid loss of heritage resources, including Indigenous languages, marine and land resources, and archaeological sites.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>The loss of Indigenous languages continues in various parts of the Arctic, although in some regions language vitality remains high.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Major technological and methodological changes in remote sensing instrumentation, sampling techniques, and data sharing enable less invasive and collaborative investigations in the lab and in the field.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Interdisciplinary social/natural science partnerships are extensive and expanding.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Research Priorities </strong></p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Convergent research on socio-ecological systems.</li> <li>Past and present drivers of change in the North, including climate change.</li> <li>Demographics of past and present migration</li> <li>Community health and healing, social aspects of health.</li> <li>Food, water, and energy security.</li> <li>Youth and gender studies.</li> <li>Sustainability and sustainable development.</li> <li>Globalization and new colonialism.</li> <li>Innovations in data curation, management, sharing, discoverability, and access.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4"><strong>Recommendations for the Support of Social Science Research in the Arctic</strong></p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Promote and support Indigenous scholarship, including improved support for Indigenous community collaboration with social scientists.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Make ethics concerning research and information sovereignty of Arctic Indigenous communities a standard element of regional research design.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Pursue international, interdisciplinary, and comparative research and funding.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Expand efforts to mentor the next generation of northern scholars and to promote equity in northern research.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Address rapid loss of cultural heritage, including loss of Indigenous languages and archaeological sites through climate change.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Invest in language revitalization programs.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Improve and support research communication with the public and Indigenous communities.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Invest in data management, maintenance, and services for sharing, discoverability, and access; balance issues of confidentiality and information sovereignty with the open data movement.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Encourage researchers to share methodological innovations, findings, and data developed in Arctic studies with scientists focusing on other regions.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Provide a venue to foster participatory discussion on the state of the discipline.</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Expand the number of agencies, foundations, and organizations that include funding for Arctic Social Science Research in their mandates.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>The Arctic social science community is uniquely positioned to:</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Make crucial contributions to understand change in the North through study of shifting intersections between people, communities, environments, heritage, policy infrastructure, and development.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Contribute to policy production around issues of sustainability, climate change response, globalization, militarization, and development.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Inform engineering, natural sciences, and other interdisciplinary collaborations through our research on past and present human experience and knowledge of the built and natural environments of the Arctic.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Empower Indigenous communities in the North through collaborative research and the elevation of Indigenous knowledge and experience in policy discourse.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Contribute to the present and future needs of peoples in the North with our work on issues of sustainability, heritage, climate change impacts and response, urban and rural socioeconomic systems and development, community resilience, health and well-being, food security, gender and youth studies.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Shelby&nbsp;Anderson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Arctic Horizons is a multi-institution collaboration that hosted a series of workshops and town halls in 2016 in an effort to bring together the Arctic social science research community.  Our goal was to reassess Arctic social science research priorities for the next decade.  Since the last ASSP visioning workshop in 1999, social science research in the Arctic has experienced substantial growth and transitioned from an emerging program at the National Science Foundation (NSF) to a well-established multidisciplinary research area. Changes in the Arctic over the last 20 years create opportunities for some and challenges for others, revealing vulnerability, innovation and resilience at community, state and national levels. The impacts of the International Polar Year in 2007-2008 and NSF investment in the Arctic Social Sciences Program (ASSP) were transformational for defining social sciences in the Arctic and ensuring that the United States secured a leading role in Northern social science research. The ASSP funded research that provides foundational, interdisciplinary knowledge critical to understanding Arctic peoples and to the development of local, national, and international policies. Arctic Social Science research sheds light on the dynamic contexts of contemporary Arctic environmental, economic, political, social, and strategic opportunities and challenges. It contributes towards safeguarding the cultural heritage of the North?s Indigenous peoples. ASSP projects integrate natural science data, social science approaches, Indigenous Knowledge, and Community-Based Monitoring to understand the rapidly changing Arctic and public policy choices before us in this new age. Every indication suggests that the volume and diversity of human activities in the Arctic will increase, and thus, so will demand for social scientific study. Workshop Findings    Arctic social science makes major, pioneering contributions to: community-based research methodologies, Indigenous scholarship, sociology of disaster, language vitality studies, social and environmental impact assessment, co-management studies, socio-ecological systems research and modeling, and resilience theory.       Arctic social science research is increasingly collaborative and community-driven.     Political tensions among Arctic countries can stymie collaborative research and reduce access to new knowledge.      Research on the effects of a wide range of interactive changes will be crucial to future Arctic social science research.     Climate change and other socio-environmental processes, coupled with development, result in the rapid loss of heritage resources, including Indigenous languages, marine and land resources, and archaeological sites.     The loss of Indigenous languages continues in various parts of the Arctic, although in some regions language vitality remains high.     Major technological and methodological changes in remote sensing instrumentation, sampling techniques, and data sharing enable less invasive and collaborative investigations in the lab and in the field.     Interdisciplinary social/natural science partnerships are extensive and expanding.    Research Priorities     Convergent research on socio-ecological systems. Past and present drivers of change in the North, including climate change. Demographics of past and present migration Community health and healing, social aspects of health. Food, water, and energy security. Youth and gender studies. Sustainability and sustainable development. Globalization and new colonialism. Innovations in data curation, management, sharing, discoverability, and access.    Recommendations for the Support of Social Science Research in the Arctic    Promote and support Indigenous scholarship, including improved support for Indigenous community collaboration with social scientists.     Make ethics concerning research and information sovereignty of Arctic Indigenous communities a standard element of regional research design.     Pursue international, interdisciplinary, and comparative research and funding.     Expand efforts to mentor the next generation of northern scholars and to promote equity in northern research.     Address rapid loss of cultural heritage, including loss of Indigenous languages and archaeological sites through climate change.     Invest in language revitalization programs.     Improve and support research communication with the public and Indigenous communities.     Invest in data management, maintenance, and services for sharing, discoverability, and access; balance issues of confidentiality and information sovereignty with the open data movement.     Encourage researchers to share methodological innovations, findings, and data developed in Arctic studies with scientists focusing on other regions.     Provide a venue to foster participatory discussion on the state of the discipline.     Expand the number of agencies, foundations, and organizations that include funding for Arctic Social Science Research in their mandates.      The Arctic social science community is uniquely positioned to:     Make crucial contributions to understand change in the North through study of shifting intersections between people, communities, environments, heritage, policy infrastructure, and development.      Contribute to policy production around issues of sustainability, climate change response, globalization, militarization, and development.      Inform engineering, natural sciences, and other interdisciplinary collaborations through our research on past and present human experience and knowledge of the built and natural environments of the Arctic.      Empower Indigenous communities in the North through collaborative research and the elevation of Indigenous knowledge and experience in policy discourse.      Contribute to the present and future needs of peoples in the North with our work on issues of sustainability, heritage, climate change impacts and response, urban and rural socioeconomic systems and development, community resilience, health and well-being, food security, gender and youth studies.           Last Modified: 03/06/2018       Submitted by: Shelby Anderson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
