<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Innovations in Social Science Learning: The Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>248882.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>248882</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Nixon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Model creates an immersive methodological experience for undergraduates in the social sciences. It provides students with specific data collection and analytical skills applicable to a variety of professional STEM careers. Undergraduates will experience firsthand the challenges of data collection and management. This field workshop is a type of course-based research for undergraduates. The design seeks to draw on the possible synergy between classroom learning and independent research, broadly considered by educators to be a transformative approach within STEM education. It does this by creating direct conceptual linkages between materials presented by instructors and hands-on student experiences. In this approach, undergraduates work in small groups to analyze the data they collected using a conceptual design they created, providing personal ownership of both data as well as the results. This is a process that is believed to enhance the overall learning experience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific goal of this project is to create a more methodologically rigorous social science course and assess its 1) effectiveness among enrolled students, 2) impact on student STEM-related learning, 3) scalability for inclusion of similar immersive courses within other university colleges and departments, and 4) transferability to other institutions. This type of methodological coursework is best suited for local field sites that offer local opportunities to begin integrating semester-long research experiences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1608007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sally</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sally J Stevens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sstevens@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206269558</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527800</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Mayer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brianmayer@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206213531</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000438667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~248882</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Innovations in Social Science Learning: The Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop investigated the potential for improving a variety of student learning outcomes through a faculty-led community research experience for undergraduate students. Specifically, we asked whether STEM-related learning outcomes such as the acquisition of research skills, improved self-efficacy, and motivation to pursue a scientific career could be improved by providing a semester-long applied learning experience cummulating in scientific presentations to a general audience. Overall, we found that these student learning outcomes, along with measures of civic engagement, were improved at a greater rate than in other similar courses utilizing more traditional lecture-based approaches.&nbsp;</p> <p>However, we also found that undergraduate students selecting to participate in these experiential learning courses were also much more likely to begin with higher levels of skills compared to their traditinal course counterparts. We found that some of the most significant experiences linked to student outcomes were the public presentations, where students could actively witness the significance of their hard work throughout the semester to an audience outside of the university. This moment of mattering beyond the classroom resulted in significant increases in a desire to pursue a scientific career as well as measures of civic engagement.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also observed significant patterns of students' initial motivation to learn through experiential learning being tied to stronger student learning outcomes. This is significant for STEM educators, as simply learning the behaviors in the course linked to positive outcomes was insufficient when compared to the influence of students being motivated to learn. For future efforts to improve STEM education, whether in the college classroom or elsewhere, our findings suggest that specific attention to motivating students to learn - in our case, through an applied communtiy-based research setting with clear social justice outcomes - will lead to greater improvements in skills and careers.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;Mayer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867685283_PovertyForum_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867685283_PovertyForum_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poster Presentation in Poverty Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867685283_PovertyForum_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poster Presentation in Poverty Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students in the Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop prepare posters reporting on their analyses of causes and consequences of poverty.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lora Harwood, University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Brian&nbsp;Mayer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poster Presentation in Poverty Workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867775756_PovertyForum_7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867775756_PovertyForum_7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Students"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867775756_PovertyForum_7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Students"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students participating in the Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lora Harwood, University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Brian&nbsp;Mayer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Students</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867835712_Poverty_Forum_8--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867835712_Poverty_Forum_8--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Crowd at Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Forum"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1608007/1608007_10454695_1569867835712_Poverty_Forum_8--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Crowd at Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Forum"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Crowd at Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Forum</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lora Harwood, University of Arizona</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Brian&nbsp;Mayer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Crowd at Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop Forum</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Innovations in Social Science Learning: The Poverty in Tucson Field Workshop investigated the potential for improving a variety of student learning outcomes through a faculty-led community research experience for undergraduate students. Specifically, we asked whether STEM-related learning outcomes such as the acquisition of research skills, improved self-efficacy, and motivation to pursue a scientific career could be improved by providing a semester-long applied learning experience cummulating in scientific presentations to a general audience. Overall, we found that these student learning outcomes, along with measures of civic engagement, were improved at a greater rate than in other similar courses utilizing more traditional lecture-based approaches.   However, we also found that undergraduate students selecting to participate in these experiential learning courses were also much more likely to begin with higher levels of skills compared to their traditinal course counterparts. We found that some of the most significant experiences linked to student outcomes were the public presentations, where students could actively witness the significance of their hard work throughout the semester to an audience outside of the university. This moment of mattering beyond the classroom resulted in significant increases in a desire to pursue a scientific career as well as measures of civic engagement.   We also observed significant patterns of students' initial motivation to learn through experiential learning being tied to stronger student learning outcomes. This is significant for STEM educators, as simply learning the behaviors in the course linked to positive outcomes was insufficient when compared to the influence of students being motivated to learn. For future efforts to improve STEM education, whether in the college classroom or elsewhere, our findings suggest that specific attention to motivating students to learn - in our case, through an applied communtiy-based research setting with clear social justice outcomes - will lead to greater improvements in skills and careers.        Last Modified: 09/30/2019       Submitted by: Brian Mayer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
