<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Novel phases of electronic insulators and quantum Hall systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>214000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>214000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexios Klironomos</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aklirono@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924920</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research and education on the physics of new kinds of quantum phenomena in materials. The electronic properties of most solids are understood within a quantum mechanical description of a large number of interacting electrons that are moving in the background of charged atom cores that form the bulk of the solid. An important modern realization is that due to quantum mechanics, the properties of spatially distant electrons in the solid can be inextricably tied together, a phenomenon called entanglement. Quantum mechanical entanglement plays a role in determining macroscopic properties of the solid. A striking and paradigmatic example occurs when the motion of electrons is restricted to two dimensions and is subjected to a strong perpendicular magnetic field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will develop new concepts and methods to deal with such electronic states and their identification in experiments. He will also develop a deeper understanding of the interplay between symmetry and entanglement, which are two of the central pillars of modern quantum physics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Historically, such fundamental research on electronic materials has generated many of the concepts that underlie modern electronic technology. The proposed research will contribute to the continuum of scientific and technological knowledge enabling future technology that harvests quantum entanglement in fundamental ways.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to research, the award supports the training of graduate students in modern concepts and methods in condensed-matter physics. Undergraduates will be involved in the research when possible. The PI will develop lectures to expose graduate students to the phenomenology of correlated materials and the associated experimental probes. He will also develop lectures to convey the excitement of condensed matter physics to other scientists.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research and education on the physics of novel quantum states of electronic insulators and quantum Hall systems. Specific phases of interest are liquids of composite fermions in quantum Hall systems, quantum spin liquids in insulating magnets, and strongly correlated relatives of topological insulators. There has been a remarkable convergence of these three seemingly different topics in the last two years. The project will develop these connections further and exploit them to further our understanding of each topic. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific questions that will be pursued are: i) a microscopic lowest-Landau-level theory of the metallic particle-hole-symmetric half-filled Landau level, ii) a theoretical description of current experiments on quantum spin liquid states, iii) theory and realization of strong correlation effects in topological insulators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project (i) is fundamental to the theory of the quantum Hall effect and seeks to provide a microscopic foundation to recent developments on a long-wavelength effective theory for the metallic state in the half-filled Landau level. Project (ii) will seek to develop the theory of quantum spin liquids in contact with many ongoing experiments on Mott insulators that find evidence for various kinds of quantum spin-liquid phases. Project (iii) will study the interplay of strong correlation effects and topological insulator phenomena, two cornerstones of modern work on quantum materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to research, the award supports the training of graduate students in modern concepts and methods in condensed-matter physics. Undergraduates will be involved in the research when possible. The PI will develop lectures to expose graduate students to the phenomenology of correlated materials and the associated experimental probes. He will also develop lectures to convey the excitement of condensed matter physics to other scientists.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1608505</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Senthil</FirstName>
<LastName>Todadri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Senthil Todadri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>senthil@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172536831</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000115048</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~214000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual impact: The PI and his research group made significant progress in a few different areas of research in this funding period.</p> <p>One topic is the study of novel phases of magnetic materials where magnetic long range order is prevented by the combination of quantum zero point motion and &nbsp;geometruic frustration. &nbsp;Prompted by some recent experimental developments, the PI's group studied the effects of impurities in a class of such phases of matter. They demonstrated that even weak impurities can completely alter the basic properties of such states, and explored the resulting physics. In other work the PI's group studied a particularly novel class of such phases in which the excitations incliude an emergent ``photon". Their work provided a classification of such emergent photon phases in the presence of various physically relevant symmetries of the microscopic spin system.&nbsp;</p> <p>A second topic that the PI extensively studied is the interplay of band topology and correlations in moire graphene systems. The PI's group first identified a number of moire graphene systems with nearly flat Chern bands. They proposed that such systems may be ideal platforms to find ferromagnetism and quantum anomalous Hall effects, and developed models of specific moire materials where such effects are seen. This proposal has been confirmed in some beautiful recent experiments.&nbsp;</p> <p>A third topic is on novel phase transitions in quantum many body systems, and their description through quantum field theories. The PI and his collaborator described a number of surprising quantum `critical phenomena' for which there were no prior examples. One such phenomenon is that of the emergence, in three space dimensions of novel (``deconfined") degrees of freedom just at the quantum critical point even though these are absent (``confined") in either phase. A second novel example is that of what they dubbed ``unnecessary quantum critical points"; these are quantum critical points that live inside a single phase of matter unlike the usual ones which separate two distinct phases. Based on these insights this work also conjectured &nbsp;the possibility of a novel ``duality" of a strongly coupled gauge theory in three space dimensions to a much simpler theory.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The PI &nbsp;has also collaborated with experimental groups both at his home insititution and elsewhere, and provided theory support.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impact: The broader impact &nbsp;comes primarily from the training of graduate students. One student has succesfully defended his thesis. Another stiudent is currently being trained and is on track to defend her thesis in 1.5 years. &nbsp;The PI has co-written two reviews (one on novel phases of magnetism and the other on the phenomenon of duality and its use in studying quantum phase transitions) which should help introduce some modern developments &nbsp;in condensed matter physics to a broader audience.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/13/2020<br>      Modified by: Senthil&nbsp;Todadri</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual impact: The PI and his research group made significant progress in a few different areas of research in this funding period.  One topic is the study of novel phases of magnetic materials where magnetic long range order is prevented by the combination of quantum zero point motion and  geometruic frustration.  Prompted by some recent experimental developments, the PI's group studied the effects of impurities in a class of such phases of matter. They demonstrated that even weak impurities can completely alter the basic properties of such states, and explored the resulting physics. In other work the PI's group studied a particularly novel class of such phases in which the excitations incliude an emergent ``photon". Their work provided a classification of such emergent photon phases in the presence of various physically relevant symmetries of the microscopic spin system.   A second topic that the PI extensively studied is the interplay of band topology and correlations in moire graphene systems. The PI's group first identified a number of moire graphene systems with nearly flat Chern bands. They proposed that such systems may be ideal platforms to find ferromagnetism and quantum anomalous Hall effects, and developed models of specific moire materials where such effects are seen. This proposal has been confirmed in some beautiful recent experiments.   A third topic is on novel phase transitions in quantum many body systems, and their description through quantum field theories. The PI and his collaborator described a number of surprising quantum `critical phenomena' for which there were no prior examples. One such phenomenon is that of the emergence, in three space dimensions of novel (``deconfined") degrees of freedom just at the quantum critical point even though these are absent (``confined") in either phase. A second novel example is that of what they dubbed ``unnecessary quantum critical points"; these are quantum critical points that live inside a single phase of matter unlike the usual ones which separate two distinct phases. Based on these insights this work also conjectured  the possibility of a novel ``duality" of a strongly coupled gauge theory in three space dimensions to a much simpler theory.      The PI  has also collaborated with experimental groups both at his home insititution and elsewhere, and provided theory support.         Broader impact: The broader impact  comes primarily from the training of graduate students. One student has succesfully defended his thesis. Another stiudent is currently being trained and is on track to defend her thesis in 1.5 years.  The PI has co-written two reviews (one on novel phases of magnetism and the other on the phenomenon of duality and its use in studying quantum phase transitions) which should help introduce some modern developments  in condensed matter physics to a broader audience.        Last Modified: 02/13/2020       Submitted by: Senthil Todadri]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
