<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF NPGI Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2016</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>216000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>216000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dokamuro@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924508</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF National Plant Genome Initiative Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2015. The fellowship supports a research and training plan in a host laboratory for the Fellow who also presents a plan to broaden participation in biology. The title of the research and training plan for this fellowship to Danelle Seymour is "Exploring the causes and consequences of rapid transposon evolution in grass genomes" The host institution for the fellowship is the University of California, Irvine and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Brandon Gaut.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The most economically important crop species, including rice, maize, wheat, and barley are members of the grass family. The genomes of these species are extremely variable in size, and this is largely the result of rapid proliferation of mobile genetic elements, or transposons. While the genomic distribution of transposons in each species has been reported, the evolutionary forces that shape rapid, global changes in their distributions are unknown. This project aims to characterize the evolutionary forces that drive large changes in genome structure in eight grass species and whether such changes also have functional consequences. This project will provide the fellow with an evolutionary perspective important for connecting basic genomics research to plant phenotype, as well as the opportunity to provide long-term mentoring to undergraduates interested in genomics research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Transposons are insertional mutagens and host genomes have evolved mechanisms to mitigate their spread. Transposon silencing can reduce transcription of flanking endogenous genes, but the duration of these changes is unclear due to the rapid evolution of inserted sequences. Exploring the interplay between these two forces, transposon proliferation and host silencing of transposition, is central to understanding how plant genomes evolve. This research aims to characterize the extent that transposon proliferation impacts the evolution of host genomes and ultimately the host phenotype using a comparative phylogenetic approach focusing on eight grass species. First, a unified framework for transposon identification and annotation in all eight species will be developed which will serve as an important community resource. Next, this resource will be used to characterize the role of transposons in the evolution of gene expression. Using a phylogenetic approach, it is possible to characterize the duration of transposon-induced phenotypic changes, in this case gene expression, and the extent that such changes shape the evolution of gene expression networks in this important plant family.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1609024</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Seymour</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danelle K Seymour</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>9512338303</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000704501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Seymour                 Danelle        K</Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<ZipCode>925061219</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926972525</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8105</Code>
<Text>NPGI PostDoc Rsrch Fellowship</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7174</Code>
<Text>POSTDOC FELLOW IN SCI, MATH EN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~216000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p>The most economically important crop species, including rice, maize, wheat, and barley are members of the grass family. As a result of their economic and agronomic importance, high quality genome sequences have been generated for a number of member species. The genomes of these species are extremely variable for genome size, largely the result of rapid transposable element (TE) proliferation in each lineage. TEs are insertional mutagens and host genomes have evolved mechanisms, such as epigenetic silencing, to mitigate their spread. Exploring the interplay between these two forces, TE proliferation and host silencing of transposition, is central to understanding how plant genomes evolve. We aim to characterize the extent that genome size (i.e. TE proliferation) impacts the evolution of host genomes and ultimately the host phenotype using a comparative phylogenetic approach that focuses on eight species in the grass family. In particular, we focus on the impact of TE proliferation on a specific host phenotype - the level of DNA methylation in gene sequences, also known as gene-body methylation. To start, genome-wide estimates of DNA methylation and gene expression were collected and compared both at a genome-wide level and also across nearly 3,000 single copy orthologous genes in the eight focal grass species. We found that genome size is correlated with genome-wide levels of DNA methylation, but that there is no correlation between genome size (a proxy for TE abundance) and gene-body methylation as measured by the level of DNA methylation in exons. Using a phylogenetic approach, we then showed that gene-body methylation is evolving under evolutionary constraint and that shifts in gene-body methylation are associated with small, but significant shifts in gene expression. Together, this suggests that gene-body methylation is a trait that is visible to natural selection and that perturbations to gene-body methylation status are likely deleterious.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Throughout the lifetime of this award, the fellow gained expertise in evolutionary biology, statistics, and bioinformatics with a focus on economically important grass species. The host laboratory provided the necessary environment to achieve the stated training goals, namely the development of informatic and statistical skills necessary for phylogenetic analyses, and career development goals, including the development of scientific writing and communication skills as well as network building. In addition to training and career development goals, the fellow mentored undergraduates from underrepresented groups interested in genomics research. To improve communication at outreach events, the fellow attended a science communication course. Communication strategies from this course were implemented at various outreach events including a public lecture to California citrus growers on leveraging genetics and genomics in citrus breeding as well as multiple tours of a citrus germplasm collection for undergraduate students and other members of the public.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2019<br>      Modified by: Danelle&nbsp;K&nbsp;Seymour</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit  The most economically important crop species, including rice, maize, wheat, and barley are members of the grass family. As a result of their economic and agronomic importance, high quality genome sequences have been generated for a number of member species. The genomes of these species are extremely variable for genome size, largely the result of rapid transposable element (TE) proliferation in each lineage. TEs are insertional mutagens and host genomes have evolved mechanisms, such as epigenetic silencing, to mitigate their spread. Exploring the interplay between these two forces, TE proliferation and host silencing of transposition, is central to understanding how plant genomes evolve. We aim to characterize the extent that genome size (i.e. TE proliferation) impacts the evolution of host genomes and ultimately the host phenotype using a comparative phylogenetic approach that focuses on eight species in the grass family. In particular, we focus on the impact of TE proliferation on a specific host phenotype - the level of DNA methylation in gene sequences, also known as gene-body methylation. To start, genome-wide estimates of DNA methylation and gene expression were collected and compared both at a genome-wide level and also across nearly 3,000 single copy orthologous genes in the eight focal grass species. We found that genome size is correlated with genome-wide levels of DNA methylation, but that there is no correlation between genome size (a proxy for TE abundance) and gene-body methylation as measured by the level of DNA methylation in exons. Using a phylogenetic approach, we then showed that gene-body methylation is evolving under evolutionary constraint and that shifts in gene-body methylation are associated with small, but significant shifts in gene expression. Together, this suggests that gene-body methylation is a trait that is visible to natural selection and that perturbations to gene-body methylation status are likely deleterious.     Broader impacts   Throughout the lifetime of this award, the fellow gained expertise in evolutionary biology, statistics, and bioinformatics with a focus on economically important grass species. The host laboratory provided the necessary environment to achieve the stated training goals, namely the development of informatic and statistical skills necessary for phylogenetic analyses, and career development goals, including the development of scientific writing and communication skills as well as network building. In addition to training and career development goals, the fellow mentored undergraduates from underrepresented groups interested in genomics research. To improve communication at outreach events, the fellow attended a science communication course. Communication strategies from this course were implemented at various outreach events including a public lecture to California citrus growers on leveraging genetics and genomics in citrus breeding as well as multiple tours of a citrus germplasm collection for undergraduate students and other members of the public.       Last Modified: 08/27/2019       Submitted by: Danelle K Seymour]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
