<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Collaborative Research: Novel Nanostructured Metal Oxides for Efficient Solar Energy Conversion - Theory, Synthesis, and Interfacial Carrier Dynamics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>180775.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180775</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James H. Edgar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jedgar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Description: Metal oxide materials could offer earth-abundant, non-toxic alternatives to existing light-absorber materials in thin-film solar cells. However, efficiency of solar cells based on existing metal oxides is typically low due to poor material properties. In this project, researchers at the Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI) and the University of Texas at Arlington (UTA) are working on increasing the efficiency of metal oxides by theoretically predicting and experimentally synthesizing metal oxide materials with new compositions and enhanced properties. In addition, efficiency is enhanced by structuring these materials on the nanoscale level. These efforts are guided by terahertz spectroscopy measurements, which are used to understand relationships between the material composition, nanoscale structure and efficiency. The expected outcome of this SusChEM project is essential new knowledge for the development of sustainable thin-film solar cells composed of metal oxides capable of solar energy conversion with practical efficiencies. The project involves training and participation of graduate and undergraduate researchers. In addition, the WPI researchers are developing and delivering workshops and teaching modules on photovoltaics and nanotechnology for middle school girls and high school teachers from local districts serving large populations of low-income, minority and underrepresented students. The UTA researchers are serving African-American and Hispanic high-school students through interactive computer labs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: The objective of this SusChEM research is to significantly improve solar energy conversion efficiencies in multi-metal oxides, which could offer earth-abundant, non-toxic alternatives to existing thin-film materials such as CIGS and CdTe. Metal oxides typically suffer from large band gaps or poor charge mobilities, or both, which has thus far restricted their solar-electricity efficiency. This project tackles these issues via three synergistic approaches: i) theoretically predicting and synthesizing new alloys of multi-metal oxides with improved band gaps and higher charge mobilities for solar energy conversion, ii) coating thin layers of these new oxides onto nanowire-array current-collectors to enhance their efficiency and iii) using terahertz spectroscopy to study the bulk carrier dynamics and interfacial charge transfer in these nanostructured oxides and further improve efficiency. This multi-pronged approach is the first to i) investigate new multi-metal oxide alloys that hold much promise for band engineering via alloying while still achieving relatively high mobility, ii) simultaneously apply 'extremely-thin-absorber' nanostructuring and interfacial engineering strategies to improve the charge collection efficiency of multi-metal oxide absorbers and iii) study the ultrafast carrier dynamics in thin metal oxide absorbers on a nanostructured current-collector, focusing on both bulk carrier dynamics and charge extraction at the absorber/current-collector interface.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1609811</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Muhammad</FirstName>
<LastName>Huda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Muhammad Huda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huda@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172721097</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000552392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8249</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~180775</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p>Finding the right materials is critical for the efficient and cost-effective proliferation of any renewable and sustainable energy technology to meet future energy demands. For solar energy-based technologies, such as photovoltaics, the essential component is the solar absorber semiconductors that capture sunlight and convert it to electricity. Metal-oxides are known to be strong, sturdy materials and can be excellent solar absorber materials. These can potentially be produced at a lower cost than other conventional semiconductor materials. However, metal-oxides come with their limitations, such as poor electrical conductivity. Metal oxides that can accommodate two or more metal elements have the flexibility to overcome these limitations. These metal-oxides can be obtained either by mixing an existing metal oxide with two or more types of metals or discovering new metal oxides with targeted properties?the present project aimed to address both these two approaches by first-principles theory computations. In the computational simulation part of the project, we predict not only new materials but also predict chemical parameters to guide experimental synthesis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merits</strong></p> <p>The materials landscape of metal-oxide is enormous, as the number of possible metal-oxides that have two or three types of metals is numerous. The first hurdle is then to select a class of suitable metal-oxides that are efficient solar energy absorbers, that is, having an appropriate range of band gaps, with less resistance for electron transport within the materials. This overall project is a theory-experiment collaborative quest to understand and overcome challenges posed by a class of metal-oxide materials with no tightly bound conduction electrons and absorb solar energy optimally at the visible range. One such oxide is a bismuth-vanadium oxide (BiVO<sub>4</sub>). It has moderately good light absorption property, however, with sluggish electron mobility. First, we have shown that the electron mobility can be improved by alloying it with another metal, Niobium, which helps to loosen the electron in the conduction channel. Secondly, each Bi atom in BiVO<sub>4</sub> has two electrons in its s-orbital, known as lone pair electrons, that affect the band gap and charge carriers? mobility. These lone pair electrons can affect the structural and electronic properties of crystals. A mixed lone pair system, bismuth antimony tungstate (BiSbWO4), was considered to further understand and tune the lone pair electrons? behavior, where lone pair electrons in antimony (Sb) are more active than Bi. The Sb lone-pair antibonding band was found to reduce the overall band gap of BiSbWO<sub>4</sub> and help the valence electrons move relatively easily as compared to the Bi-oxides. Then we turned our attention to a new metal-oxide. Previously we have predicted a new quaternary metal oxide, copper-bismuth-tungsten oxide (CuBiW<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub>), via entirely theoretical modeling. During this project, the experimental collaborator synthesized this material for the first time. We performed further computations to facilitate the experimental synthesis and characterizations. The synthesis was done via one of the theoretically predicted synthesis routes. The features of optical absorptions and p-type conductions were explained by Cu-vacancies in the calculated band structures. Furthermore, several low-index, stoichiometric surfaces of CuBiW<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub> were identified for further computational investigations. Calculated surface energies were then used to predict the equilibrium crystal shape. The (01) and (101) surfaces were equally the most stable, each constituting about 30% of the crystal shape.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The materials investigated and discovered in this project can lead to new photovoltaics (solar cells), which can generate electricity from sunlight, thereby decreasing the generation of energy from the burning of fossil fuels, which creates pollution and causes global warming through the emission of carbon dioxide. The materials can also be used as photocatalysts, which can harness solar energy to produce useful chemical reactions. Such technologies can one day become commercially available to society. Graduate students who were involved in this project are now accepting postdoctoral research positions in similar fields, thereby contributing to the workforce in the science and technology of solar energy. This project has trained three doctoral students (one student completed his Ph.D. under this project, the other two students were involved at different times) and several undergraduate students. About 20 talks were given in several international conferences by the PI and the students. The total number of peer-reviewed publications under this funding period is 18, and one book chapter was published.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2021<br>      Modified by: Muhammad&nbsp;Huda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  Finding the right materials is critical for the efficient and cost-effective proliferation of any renewable and sustainable energy technology to meet future energy demands. For solar energy-based technologies, such as photovoltaics, the essential component is the solar absorber semiconductors that capture sunlight and convert it to electricity. Metal-oxides are known to be strong, sturdy materials and can be excellent solar absorber materials. These can potentially be produced at a lower cost than other conventional semiconductor materials. However, metal-oxides come with their limitations, such as poor electrical conductivity. Metal oxides that can accommodate two or more metal elements have the flexibility to overcome these limitations. These metal-oxides can be obtained either by mixing an existing metal oxide with two or more types of metals or discovering new metal oxides with targeted properties?the present project aimed to address both these two approaches by first-principles theory computations. In the computational simulation part of the project, we predict not only new materials but also predict chemical parameters to guide experimental synthesis.     Intellectual Merits  The materials landscape of metal-oxide is enormous, as the number of possible metal-oxides that have two or three types of metals is numerous. The first hurdle is then to select a class of suitable metal-oxides that are efficient solar energy absorbers, that is, having an appropriate range of band gaps, with less resistance for electron transport within the materials. This overall project is a theory-experiment collaborative quest to understand and overcome challenges posed by a class of metal-oxide materials with no tightly bound conduction electrons and absorb solar energy optimally at the visible range. One such oxide is a bismuth-vanadium oxide (BiVO4). It has moderately good light absorption property, however, with sluggish electron mobility. First, we have shown that the electron mobility can be improved by alloying it with another metal, Niobium, which helps to loosen the electron in the conduction channel. Secondly, each Bi atom in BiVO4 has two electrons in its s-orbital, known as lone pair electrons, that affect the band gap and charge carriers? mobility. These lone pair electrons can affect the structural and electronic properties of crystals. A mixed lone pair system, bismuth antimony tungstate (BiSbWO4), was considered to further understand and tune the lone pair electrons? behavior, where lone pair electrons in antimony (Sb) are more active than Bi. The Sb lone-pair antibonding band was found to reduce the overall band gap of BiSbWO4 and help the valence electrons move relatively easily as compared to the Bi-oxides. Then we turned our attention to a new metal-oxide. Previously we have predicted a new quaternary metal oxide, copper-bismuth-tungsten oxide (CuBiW2O8), via entirely theoretical modeling. During this project, the experimental collaborator synthesized this material for the first time. We performed further computations to facilitate the experimental synthesis and characterizations. The synthesis was done via one of the theoretically predicted synthesis routes. The features of optical absorptions and p-type conductions were explained by Cu-vacancies in the calculated band structures. Furthermore, several low-index, stoichiometric surfaces of CuBiW2O8 were identified for further computational investigations. Calculated surface energies were then used to predict the equilibrium crystal shape. The (01) and (101) surfaces were equally the most stable, each constituting about 30% of the crystal shape.  Broader Impacts  The materials investigated and discovered in this project can lead to new photovoltaics (solar cells), which can generate electricity from sunlight, thereby decreasing the generation of energy from the burning of fossil fuels, which creates pollution and causes global warming through the emission of carbon dioxide. The materials can also be used as photocatalysts, which can harness solar energy to produce useful chemical reactions. Such technologies can one day become commercially available to society. Graduate students who were involved in this project are now accepting postdoctoral research positions in similar fields, thereby contributing to the workforce in the science and technology of solar energy. This project has trained three doctoral students (one student completed his Ph.D. under this project, the other two students were involved at different times) and several undergraduate students. About 20 talks were given in several international conferences by the PI and the students. The total number of peer-reviewed publications under this funding period is 18, and one book chapter was published.          Last Modified: 03/03/2021       Submitted by: Muhammad Huda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
