<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Photophysics and Stability of Multichromophoric Polyelectrolytes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>284956.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>284956</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James H. Edgar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jedgar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical description: The research team studies a class of water-soluble polymers that are capable of light emission. The materials are being studied in collaboration with chemists who are developing them for biomedical imaging of tumors, and for applications to detection of proteins and DNA sequences of medical interest. These polymers organize into geometries that are determined by factors such as salt and acid concentrations in the water. Those geometries strongly influence both the color and brightness of the light emitted from the polymers. The project employs microscopy of single polymer strands to investigate how the polymer conformation and solution conditions affect the intensity and stability of the emitted light. Participation in the research provides training for graduate students in optics and polymer science, as well as interactions with international collaborators working on problems with medical significance. Since the materials under study are non-toxic, the research team is using them to develop hands-on activities as part of a summer course at the University of Rochester for gifted students, and for exhibitions for the general public at the Rochester Museum and Science Center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description: The research team is testing models of how energy transfer in multi-chromophore ensembles comprising fluorescent conjugated polyelectrolytes controls their degradation, fluorescence intensity, and spectrum. In particular, the group is investigating the circumstances under which chromophore aggregation leads to fluorescence quenching and fluctuations in the emission intensity and spectrum. The hypothesis that intense fluorescence arises from bleaching of nearly non-emissive chromophores is being tested using superresolution imaging combined with simultaneous spectroscopy. A complementary approach to measure the absorption of single chains using photothermal detection is being developed to test the "dark matter" hypothesis for fluorescence quenching in these materials. The researchers are studying the spectroscopy and fluorescence dynamics for these conjugated polyelectrolyte chains in different salt and pH environments, as well as when adsorbed on hydrophilic and hydrophobic surfaces. The team is developing computational models of energy transfer for guiding the design of polymer morphology, to improve fluorescence efficiency and stability for imaging applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1609451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lewis</FirstName>
<LastName>Rothberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lewis J Rothberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rothberg@chem.rochester.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5852734725</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000182317</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rochester</Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041294109</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041294109</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[518 Hylan Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~284956</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Context:</p> <p>The main goals of the project concern ways to improve the efficiency of luminescent polymers that could be used to make organic light emitting diodes (OLEDs) for display applications. The incentive to use polymers is that they can be solution processed so that they could be manufactured using printing techniques that are much less expensive.</p> <p>Intellectual merit:</p> <p>One outcome of the research is a better understanding of the relationship between the way that the polymer films are deposited and the resulting light emission spectrum and efficiency. A model describing the polymer by only two different types of chromophores was tested and found to be lacking. A more complex model was developed that enabled us to predict and demonstrate that it would be possible to improve polymer film brightness by pre-illumination with specific colors at the reddest part of the polymer absorption. The conditions under which the improvement can be significant were documented.</p> <p>A second finding pertains to a phenomenon whereby luminescence from polymer films can be observed at very long times after initial photoexcitation. This "delayed luminescence" derives from the same charge recombination mechanism that produces luminescence in OLEDs. The research opens a new approach to testing how many of the charge recombination events result in producing the desired luminescent state and how this depends on the polymer composition. It also provides a way to test hypotheses which assert that there is a 25% maximum efficiency for OLEDs that exploit fluorescence rather than phosphorescence which is a key design constraint that the industry would like to find a way to circumvent. This work was a breakthrough that will motivate follow up experiments to measure the fraction of charge recombination events resulting in luminescence and to screen for effective polymeric OLED materials for the next several years.</p> <p>Broader impact:</p> <p>A collaboration with a small company named Molecular Glasses supported their work to design host materials for OLEDs that would suppress one of the major causes of low efficiency. In particular, when the emitting molecules are organized so that they are too close together, their luminescence efficiency drops precipitously. Experimental work in the lab measuring excited state lifetimes and correlating these with calorimetric data on their materials helped them to show that their host materials do in fact block aggregation of the dye molecules, resulting in an increase in light emission as well as much greater long term stability.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/19/2020<br>      Modified by: Lewis&nbsp;J&nbsp;Rothberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Context:  The main goals of the project concern ways to improve the efficiency of luminescent polymers that could be used to make organic light emitting diodes (OLEDs) for display applications. The incentive to use polymers is that they can be solution processed so that they could be manufactured using printing techniques that are much less expensive.  Intellectual merit:  One outcome of the research is a better understanding of the relationship between the way that the polymer films are deposited and the resulting light emission spectrum and efficiency. A model describing the polymer by only two different types of chromophores was tested and found to be lacking. A more complex model was developed that enabled us to predict and demonstrate that it would be possible to improve polymer film brightness by pre-illumination with specific colors at the reddest part of the polymer absorption. The conditions under which the improvement can be significant were documented.  A second finding pertains to a phenomenon whereby luminescence from polymer films can be observed at very long times after initial photoexcitation. This "delayed luminescence" derives from the same charge recombination mechanism that produces luminescence in OLEDs. The research opens a new approach to testing how many of the charge recombination events result in producing the desired luminescent state and how this depends on the polymer composition. It also provides a way to test hypotheses which assert that there is a 25% maximum efficiency for OLEDs that exploit fluorescence rather than phosphorescence which is a key design constraint that the industry would like to find a way to circumvent. This work was a breakthrough that will motivate follow up experiments to measure the fraction of charge recombination events resulting in luminescence and to screen for effective polymeric OLED materials for the next several years.  Broader impact:  A collaboration with a small company named Molecular Glasses supported their work to design host materials for OLEDs that would suppress one of the major causes of low efficiency. In particular, when the emitting molecules are organized so that they are too close together, their luminescence efficiency drops precipitously. Experimental work in the lab measuring excited state lifetimes and correlating these with calorimetric data on their materials helped them to show that their host materials do in fact block aggregation of the dye molecules, resulting in an increase in light emission as well as much greater long term stability.          Last Modified: 10/19/2020       Submitted by: Lewis J Rothberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
