<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Development of Optoelectronic Devices for the Far-Infrared</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>183500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>183500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: Development of Optoelectronic Devices for the Far-Infrared&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;General Abstract: The objective of this research effort is to develop optical materials and devices that control and emit far-infrared (far-IR) light with wavelengths between 20-60ìm.  There are a number of important applications for light in this wavelength range, ranging from imaging for astronomy and cosmology efforts and sensing of aromatic hydrocarbons, asphaltenes, and biological materials. However, the far-IR is an extremely challenging wavelength range to work in, with little to no optical infrastructure for either conducting fundamental research or developing optical devices and systems, making the far-IR arguably one of the few remaining frontiers of the electromagnetic spectrum.  The challenges of the far-IR largely stem from the lattice vibrations (phonons) of most of the semiconductors used for optoelectronic devices across the electromagnetic spectrum.  In the far-IR, phonons strongly absorb light and conventional device designs are no longer appropriate.  In this program we will look to harness these lattice vibrations and utilize them to generate electromagnetic radiation, or light.  In doing so, we will develop an architecture for engineering designer far-IR materials and emitters that incorporate unique light-matter interactions in an oft-neglected portion of the optical spectrum, resulting in an optical toolkit for the far-IR and a new generation of optical devices.  At the same time, we will undertake both educational and outreach efforts, as well as a coherent effort to grow the visibility and impact of far-IR optoelectronics research, which has no agreed-upon dissemination systems (journals, conferences, workshops), commercial vendors, or even nomenclature.  &lt;br/&gt;    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract: Technological developments over the past several decades have significantly increased our ability to generate, control, and detect electromagnetic (EM) radiation across an ever-increasing range of wavelengths. Much of this progress has been spurred by the rapid growth of semiconductor optoelectronic technologies. Yet the far-infrared (far-IR, 20-60 ìm) wavelength range has not shared in this explosive growth.  Ironically, a primary reason for the lack of progress in the far-IR lies in the semiconductor crystal lattice itself: characteristic vibrations of the lattice, known as phonons, interact strongly with far-IR light and result in strong optical absorption.  This program aims to explore and develop a set of technologies, materials, and phenomena which will serve as the technical foundation of an optical infrastructure for the largely undeveloped far-IR wavelength range.    In particular, we propose to develop optical materials and opto-phononic-electronic (OPE) devices that control and emit far-IR light by engineering electronic transport, surface waves, and the interaction of these surface waves with bulk optical phonons.  In doing so, we will develop an architecture for engineering designer far-IR materials and OPE emitters that incorporate unique light-matter interactions in an oft-neglected portion of the optical spectrum, resulting in an optical toolkit for the far-IR and a new generation of optical devices.  Concurrent with the technical thrusts of the proposed effort, we will: i) bring STEM-based activities into K12 classrooms and after-school programs and ii) work to cultivate an intellectual community with a shared interest in the far-IR by means of virtual communities and special issues in peer-reviewed publications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1609362</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony Hoffman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ajhoffman@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746317432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633139</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[275 Fitzpatrick Hall of Engineer]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~183500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This program aimed to develop optical materials and opto-phononic-electronic (OPE) devices that control and emit far-infrared (far-IR) light by engineering surface waves and the interaction of these surface waves with bulk and/or engineered optical phonons.&nbsp;&nbsp;In doing so, we looked to develop an architecture for engineering designer far-IR materials and OPE emitters that incorporate unique light-matter interactions in an oft-neglected portion of the optical spectrum, resulting in an optical toolkit for the far-IR and a new generation of optical devices.</p> <p>The significant project outcomes of the effort included</p> <p>The design, growth, fabrication, and characterization of complex layered semiconductor (quantum cascade-like) devices designed to emit into hybrid optical modes consisting of propagating electromagnetic waves (light) coupled to vibrational waves in the semiconductor lattice (phonons).&nbsp;&nbsp;These hybrid waves, known as polaritons, were designed to be excited by far-infrared electronic transitions engineered in the layered semiconductor material.</p> <p>The development of materials leveraging resonant response of lattice vibrations in polar materials (phononic resonances) for enhanced absorption/emission of far-IR light.</p> <p>Demonstration of coupled systems (antennas and phononic materials) for engineering light-matter interactions at long wavelengths.&nbsp;&nbsp;We demonstrated that by patterning antennas on phononic material we were able to effectively condense the antenna resonances (spectrally) so that multiple harmonics of the antenna response could be excited in a narrow wavelength range.&nbsp;&nbsp;Such systems provided the demonstration of quasi-monochromatic multimode antennas.</p> <p>Demonstrating the ability to engineer the far field thermal emission from phononic materials with outcoupling antennas.&nbsp;&nbsp;Thermal emission from such systems were simulated, and experimentally measured, demonstrating the ability to control not only the spectral, but spatial, thermal emission from heated surfaces.</p> <p>Engineering the temporal response of thermal emitters leveraging phononic resonances. In this thrust we designed and numerically simulated ultra-fast thermal emitters, so-called ?thermal flashes?, capable of directed thermal emission on nanosecond time scales.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project advances the disciplines of optics, optical materials, and optoelectronics by expanding the wavelength range covered by both passive and active, electrically-injected semiconductor devices and leveraging new light-matter interactions to create fundamentally new devices.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition to the technical output of the program, the PIs made significant efforts to expand the visibility of far-IR research in the larger optics and photonics community.&nbsp;&nbsp;PI Hoffman led a successful special feature issue of Optics Express focused largely on long wavelength photonics, entitled ?Mid-Infrared, Long-Wave Infrared, and Terahertz Photonics?.&nbsp;&nbsp;The Feature Issue included 40 papers, making it the largest Feature Issue published by Optics Express to date. PI Wasserman published two lengthy peer-reviewed publications providing overviews of the field of phonon-polaritonics.&nbsp;&nbsp;The first, co-authored with the Caldwell group at Vanderbilt, was an invited tutorial in the Journal of Applied Physics, focused on measurement techniques for long wavelength and far-infrared phonon-polariton based structures and devices.&nbsp;&nbsp;The second, co-authored with Stavroula Foteinoupolou, Ganapathi Subramania, and Sanjay Krishna (from the University of New Mexico, Sandia National Labs, and The Ohio State University respectively), was a comprehensive review article on phonon polaritonics published in the journal Nanophotonics. Prof. Wasserman also served as the co-chair of the 2019 Infrared Terahertz and Quantum Workshop (ITQW) which is the premier international conference for far-IR optoelectronics.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, this project trained four graduate students, one undergraduate student, and three research experience for undergraduates (REU) students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;Hoffman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1609362/1609362_10445284_1614626243525_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1609362/1609362_10445284_1614626243525_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Monochromatic Multimode Optical Antennas"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1609362/1609362_10445284_1614626243525_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Monochromatic Multimode Optical Antennas"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of monochromatic multimode optical antennas all being excited by the same wavelength of incident light.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anthony Hoffman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;Hoffman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Monochromatic Multimode Optical Antennas</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This program aimed to develop optical materials and opto-phononic-electronic (OPE) devices that control and emit far-infrared (far-IR) light by engineering surface waves and the interaction of these surface waves with bulk and/or engineered optical phonons.  In doing so, we looked to develop an architecture for engineering designer far-IR materials and OPE emitters that incorporate unique light-matter interactions in an oft-neglected portion of the optical spectrum, resulting in an optical toolkit for the far-IR and a new generation of optical devices.  The significant project outcomes of the effort included  The design, growth, fabrication, and characterization of complex layered semiconductor (quantum cascade-like) devices designed to emit into hybrid optical modes consisting of propagating electromagnetic waves (light) coupled to vibrational waves in the semiconductor lattice (phonons).  These hybrid waves, known as polaritons, were designed to be excited by far-infrared electronic transitions engineered in the layered semiconductor material.  The development of materials leveraging resonant response of lattice vibrations in polar materials (phononic resonances) for enhanced absorption/emission of far-IR light.  Demonstration of coupled systems (antennas and phononic materials) for engineering light-matter interactions at long wavelengths.  We demonstrated that by patterning antennas on phononic material we were able to effectively condense the antenna resonances (spectrally) so that multiple harmonics of the antenna response could be excited in a narrow wavelength range.  Such systems provided the demonstration of quasi-monochromatic multimode antennas.  Demonstrating the ability to engineer the far field thermal emission from phononic materials with outcoupling antennas.  Thermal emission from such systems were simulated, and experimentally measured, demonstrating the ability to control not only the spectral, but spatial, thermal emission from heated surfaces.  Engineering the temporal response of thermal emitters leveraging phononic resonances. In this thrust we designed and numerically simulated ultra-fast thermal emitters, so-called ?thermal flashes?, capable of directed thermal emission on nanosecond time scales.   This project advances the disciplines of optics, optical materials, and optoelectronics by expanding the wavelength range covered by both passive and active, electrically-injected semiconductor devices and leveraging new light-matter interactions to create fundamentally new devices.  In addition to the technical output of the program, the PIs made significant efforts to expand the visibility of far-IR research in the larger optics and photonics community.  PI Hoffman led a successful special feature issue of Optics Express focused largely on long wavelength photonics, entitled ?Mid-Infrared, Long-Wave Infrared, and Terahertz Photonics?.  The Feature Issue included 40 papers, making it the largest Feature Issue published by Optics Express to date. PI Wasserman published two lengthy peer-reviewed publications providing overviews of the field of phonon-polaritonics.  The first, co-authored with the Caldwell group at Vanderbilt, was an invited tutorial in the Journal of Applied Physics, focused on measurement techniques for long wavelength and far-infrared phonon-polariton based structures and devices.  The second, co-authored with Stavroula Foteinoupolou, Ganapathi Subramania, and Sanjay Krishna (from the University of New Mexico, Sandia National Labs, and The Ohio State University respectively), was a comprehensive review article on phonon polaritonics published in the journal Nanophotonics. Prof. Wasserman also served as the co-chair of the 2019 Infrared Terahertz and Quantum Workshop (ITQW) which is the premier international conference for far-IR optoelectronics.    Finally, this project trained four graduate students, one undergraduate student, and three research experience for undergraduates (REU) students.          Last Modified: 03/01/2021       Submitted by: Anthony Hoffman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
