<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigation and design of dendritic peptide bolaamphiphile vectors for siRNA delivery</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Randy Duran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rduran@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925326</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical:&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the basic physiochemical properties of a new bolaamphiphile (bola) vector system for siRNA delivery and to design new pH-responsive bolas for improved siRNA delivery efficiency. Despite the tremendous potential of RNAi for therapeutics, the lack of safe and effective delivery vehicles hampers the clinical promise of siRNA. Recently the PI's lab has demonstrated a new design of bolaamphiphiles as promising synthetic vectors for siRNA delivery. The bolas show high efficiency and low cytotoxicity for intracellular siRNA delivery, and fluorocarbon bolas also show excellent serum stability. Despite the excellent performances for bolas, many fundamental questions remain unanswered. This project details PI's plans to address several key questions for this new delivery system. The first major aim of the study is to combine both experimental and computational studies to understand the fundamental properties of bola/siRNA complexes, such as the structure and morphology of the complexes, binding affinity and stability of the complexes, as well as how do they interact with serum and membranes. The fundamental insight gained in the first aim will enable to design more effective bola vectors for siRNA delivery. In the second aim PI proposes a specific design of acid-labile bolas for improving the efficiency for siRNA transfection. The proposed multi-disciplinary research activity will provide students excellent training in many areas including organic/polymer synthesis, biomaterials, nanomaterials, and biology. This will provide great opportunities to train graduate and undergraduate students, especially for minority and women students currently working on this project. The PI is also strongly committed to various K-12 outreach programs that are aimed to excite the younger generation with science and to enhance general public understanding and appreciation of chemical sciences and technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical:&lt;br/&gt;RNA interference (RNAi) technology has demonstrated tremendous utility both for fundamental biological research and for disease treatments. The high potency and specificity of gene silencing induced by small interfering RNA (siRNA) makes this technology particularly promising for treatment of various diseases including cancer, viral infections, obesity and diabetes. One major roadblock preventing it from realization of clinical applications for siRNA technology is the lack of efficient methods to deliver siRNA into cells. This study explores a novel molecular delivery system for safe and efficienct siRNA delivery. The goal of this project is to understand the basic chemi-physical properties of a new molecular delivery system for siRNA delivery and to design new stimuli-responsive delivery molecules for improved siRNA delivery efficiency. Ultimately, the knowledge gained from this study will facilitate the development of safe and efficient siRNA delivery vectors that can have tremendous impact on biotechnological and pharmaceutical industries. In addition, the proposed multi-disciplinary research activity will provide excellent training for graduate and undergraduate students, especially for minority and women students currently working on this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1609946</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhibin</FirstName>
<LastName>Guan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhibin Guan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zguan@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498245172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000251274</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926972025</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1123 Reines Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of this project is to design and investigate a special type of surfactant-like compounds called dendritic bolaamphiphiles as carriers for intracellular delivery of small interference RNA (siRNA) and other RNAs. As a new modality for treatments, RNA-based therapies have received much attention and are revolutionizing modern medicine. One of the most compelling example is the vaccine development for COVID-19. Currently, the two front running COVID-19 vaccines developed by the&nbsp;&#8203;&#8203;&#8203;&#8203;Pfizer-BioNTech and Moderna, respectively, are both based on mRNA technology. Nevertheless, one major challenge of RNA-based medicine is the lack of efficient methods for intracellular delivery of RNAs.&nbsp;Working with a group of talented graduate and undergraduate students, we successfully developed a series of organic and polymeric compounds that show high efficiency in delivery of various kinds of RNAs including short siRNA, intermediate sgRNA, and long mRNA. A key design strategy for our carriers is the use of dendritic peptides to present multifunctional amino acid side groups to faciliate binding to RNAs, uptake by cells, and efficient escape from intracellular compartments such as endosome and lysosome. Through structure-function studies, we reveal key features of our molecular carriers that contribute to high efficiency for RNA delivery. In addition to fundamental studies of carrier design, we also collaborate with medical researchers on applications relevant to clinical uses. For example, in one collaborative study we&nbsp;<span>demosntrated that our carriers can efficiently deliver siRNA into fat tissue cells (adipocytes), which is relevant for obesity treatment. In another collaborative study, we discovered that our dendritic polypeptide carriers show inflammasome activity, which is promising to be used as adjuvants for boosting vaccination efficiency.</span></p> <p><span>For broad impact, t</span>he multi-disciplinary research activities involved in this study encompass many areas including organic and polymer synthesis, polymer property studies, and biological assays of the designed biomaterials, which provided great opportunities to train graduate and undergraduate students. The design, synthesis and characterization of the dendritic peptide amphiphiles and polymers as well as the fundamental structure-property studies provide a rich and diverse set of problems on which undergraduate and graduate students can strengthen their foundations in the fundamentals of biomaterials and polymer chemistry and broaden their knowledge and experimental skills to include other disciplines. Young scientists involved in this project are receiving unique training in biomaterials research at the interface of materials chemistry, organic/polymer synthesis, and biomaterials science. The graduate and undergraduate students will be well positioned to become future leaders in biomaterials field. The PI's direct involvement in both classroom teaching and laboratory research provided an integrated education and training experience to students at various levels. Furthermore, the&nbsp;<span>PI and researchers on this project have participated in various outreach activities to local communities.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Zhibin&nbsp;Guan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this project is to design and investigate a special type of surfactant-like compounds called dendritic bolaamphiphiles as carriers for intracellular delivery of small interference RNA (siRNA) and other RNAs. As a new modality for treatments, RNA-based therapies have received much attention and are revolutionizing modern medicine. One of the most compelling example is the vaccine development for COVID-19. Currently, the two front running COVID-19 vaccines developed by the &#8203;&#8203;&#8203;&#8203;Pfizer-BioNTech and Moderna, respectively, are both based on mRNA technology. Nevertheless, one major challenge of RNA-based medicine is the lack of efficient methods for intracellular delivery of RNAs. Working with a group of talented graduate and undergraduate students, we successfully developed a series of organic and polymeric compounds that show high efficiency in delivery of various kinds of RNAs including short siRNA, intermediate sgRNA, and long mRNA. A key design strategy for our carriers is the use of dendritic peptides to present multifunctional amino acid side groups to faciliate binding to RNAs, uptake by cells, and efficient escape from intracellular compartments such as endosome and lysosome. Through structure-function studies, we reveal key features of our molecular carriers that contribute to high efficiency for RNA delivery. In addition to fundamental studies of carrier design, we also collaborate with medical researchers on applications relevant to clinical uses. For example, in one collaborative study we demosntrated that our carriers can efficiently deliver siRNA into fat tissue cells (adipocytes), which is relevant for obesity treatment. In another collaborative study, we discovered that our dendritic polypeptide carriers show inflammasome activity, which is promising to be used as adjuvants for boosting vaccination efficiency.  For broad impact, the multi-disciplinary research activities involved in this study encompass many areas including organic and polymer synthesis, polymer property studies, and biological assays of the designed biomaterials, which provided great opportunities to train graduate and undergraduate students. The design, synthesis and characterization of the dendritic peptide amphiphiles and polymers as well as the fundamental structure-property studies provide a rich and diverse set of problems on which undergraduate and graduate students can strengthen their foundations in the fundamentals of biomaterials and polymer chemistry and broaden their knowledge and experimental skills to include other disciplines. Young scientists involved in this project are receiving unique training in biomaterials research at the interface of materials chemistry, organic/polymer synthesis, and biomaterials science. The graduate and undergraduate students will be well positioned to become future leaders in biomaterials field. The PI's direct involvement in both classroom teaching and laboratory research provided an integrated education and training experience to students at various levels. Furthermore, the PI and researchers on this project have participated in various outreach activities to local communities.       Last Modified: 01/21/2021       Submitted by: Zhibin Guan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
