<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Plasmonically Enhanced Stimulated Coherent Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>550000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924956</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program in the Division of Chemistry and the NanoBiosensing Program in the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems, Professors Ziegler and Reinhard at Boston University merge two very active research areas that have independently already impacted many aspects of our lives; nanomaterials and laser technology.  The goal of the project is to exploit the special capabilities afforded by the combination of these two disciplines to advance a technical solution to some important societal needs.  More specifically, these researchers explore how ultrafast pulsed laser light interacting with metal nano-materials can be used to enhance and control chemistry on metal surfaces for applications such as chemical catalysis, pollution mitigation, energy conversion, chemical imaging and sensing applications. The on-going experiments develop a detailed description of how molecules interact with nanostructured metal surfaces. Well-established methodologies are already in place that allow the design of nanoscale surfaces with exquisite control.  The results of these experiments reveal molecular level details of how these materials interact with molecules and thus provide information on optimizing nanostructures design strategies for the applications cited above. The collaborative nature of this research effort provides participating students with unique experience at the interface of materials and ultrafast science, and thus promote cross-disciplinary activities in science and technology at Boston University.  In synergy with the research, this grant supports a substantial education and outreach program to include participation of local Community College students and faculty, inner city and greater Boston area High School students, and High School teachers in conjunction with a newly awarded NSF research experience for undergraduates (REU) site program, as well as other BU based outreach programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The merger of ultrafast spectroscopy and nanotechnology is being used to study the dynamics and interactions of molecules on plasmonically active surfaces via three ultrafast laser techniques.  Plasmonically enhanced (PE) optical heterodyne detected Raman spectroscopy (PE-OHD-RIKES) offers sensitivity advantages for viewing Raman responses on plasmonic surfaces, especially for low frequency modes resulting from molecular-surface physi-adsorption, and a phase sensitive methodology for understanding vibrational and plasmon contributions to nonlinear responses.  Analysis of PE three-pulse photon echo peak shift measurements (PE 3PEPS) yields a dynamical description of optical dephasing, or equivalently solvation, of molecules on plasmonic surfaces (inhomogeneous energy distributions, spectral diffusion and fluctuation timescales). Finally, the successful implementation of PE femtosecond stimulated Raman spectroscopy (PE-FSRS), could have enormous impact as a new probe of surface chemistry allowing vibrationally-specific labels to follow the evolution of short-lived intermediates and rapid conformation changes of excited molecules on plasmonic surfaces. Determined dynamical and structural properties of analytes on plasmonic substrates is being contrasted with those of liquid solutions and correlated with observed plasmonic based phenomenon such as SERS enhancement factors. Substrates are being fabricated by a template-guided self-assembly procedure which results in electromagnetically strongly coupled nanoparticle cluster arrays where optical fields are enhanced by both near field coupling between nanoparticles, and diffractive coupling between clusters.  Detailed molecular level information about how molecules interact with engineered plasmonic surfaces is providing rational design strategies for maximizing plasmon enhancement of optical responses and chemical outcomes. The implementation of this methodology is impactful upon optical imaging capabilities in terms of improved sensitivity and faster acquisition times, real time monitoring of photoinduced surface chemical reactivity, enhanced chemical and biological sensing capabilities, and improved strategies for subsequent spontaneous SERS and other plasmonic based techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1609952</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Ziegler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence D Ziegler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lziegler@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173538663</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000184670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bjoern</FirstName>
<LastName>Reinhard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bjoern Reinhard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmr@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173538669</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~550000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Shinning light that has a wavelength that matches the surface plasmon resonances of nanostructured metals, such as gold and silver, results in a large enhancement of this incident optical radiation field.&nbsp;&nbsp;Technologies can be developed for imaging and sensing for example that provide greater sensitivities by exploiting this combination of metal nanoparticles and selective excitation colors. &nbsp;This is called plasmonic enhancement (PE).&nbsp;&nbsp;When laser light is used to excite and detect PE vibrational resonant molecular signatures, oddly shaped spectral features were obtained in such PE stimulated experiments. However, sensitivities at the single molecule level are achieved in the stimulated Raman experiments that have been carried out as evidence of the sensitivity achievable with this PE approach. &nbsp;Two explanations for these unusual lineshapes have been discoverd and both may be operative.&nbsp;&nbsp;One is based on interference effects from the emission of the nanoparticles themselves and the other is due to the complex character (i.e. real and imaginary part) &nbsp;of the enhancement factor that only comes into play for stimulated, i.e. two laser, Raman experiments. Predicted lineshapes due to plasmon emission interference are shown in an accompanying figure for different enhancement strengths (g) and matches what has been observed.&nbsp;&nbsp;Understanding the lineshape of these strongly enhanced vibrational features is important for the use of this approach for imaging capabilities so the identity of molecules&nbsp;&nbsp;of interest can be established.&nbsp;&nbsp;In another component of this project&nbsp;it was discovered&nbsp;that controlled&nbsp;deposition of silver on&nbsp;gold nanostructures (nanobipyramids) allowed tuning of the localized plasmon resonance to both higher or lower energies permitting better resonance with a selected molecular state of interest.</p> <p>Sum frequency generation (SFG), another vibrationally resonant nonlinear laser technique, was used to probe how self assembled monolayers align on metal surfaces.&nbsp;&nbsp;Plasmonic resonance effects are surface roughness dependent and contribute to the dispersive lineshapes found in these SFG spectra on Au and Ag as well.&nbsp;&nbsp;Self-assembling monolayers of n-alkylthiols show remarkable odd-even (n) chain length effects that are dependent on the orientational structural details of the molecules with these metal surface as evident in the accompanying figure.&nbsp;&nbsp;Such molecular level details are&nbsp;&nbsp;important to understanding the macroscopic properties of these materials which have applications in sensing and chromatography.</p> <p>Dense gases and supercritical fluids are high temperature and pressure environments for important chemical activity spanning applications from internal combustion engine reactions to coffee decaffeination.&nbsp;&nbsp;An ultrafast, laser multidimensional IR technique (2DIR) was used to study dense gases and supercritical fluids (SCF) to understand how chemistry might be different in these solvents than in &ldquo;normal&rdquo; liquid solvents, and to develop a better detailed description of these dense phase regions that are common to all materials. Although we are taught in general chemistry that SCFs are a homogenous region with properties in between those of the gas and liquid, our ultrafast laser experiments find that high dense and supercritical solutions are better described as a mix of co-existing freely rotating molecules, that is a gas population, and hindered molecules trapped in liquid population regions below finite sized barriers (see picture). The supercritical region corresponds to the panels in between the gas and liquid depictions in this figure.</p> <p>Furthermore, excited rotational and vibrational energy relaxation appears to be governed by independent binary collisions in the supercritical regions studies thus far, a gas-like response in a dense fluid.&nbsp;&nbsp;Near the critical point dynamics at the molecular scale is found to slow as long length scale spatial correlations increase at the state point.&nbsp;&nbsp;Thus the molecular environment &ldquo;knows&rdquo; that longer scale, macroscopic critical effects are occurring and has an influence on the local molecualr environment. This technique will be used to divide the supercritical region into liquid and gas like regions and confirm theoretical predictions about the existence of such boundaries in the supercritical regime.</p> <p>Students working on these projects are trained in understanding matter-radiation interaction, nonlinear laser physics, the design and characterization of plasmonic nanostructures, their fabrication, near- and far-field&nbsp;&nbsp;analysis through electromagnetic simulations, data collection and processing protocols and lab safety best practices, all skills transferable to both commercial as well as subsequent academic laboratories.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Lawrence&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ziegler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570155535920_FSRS_LineshapeNSF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570155535920_FSRS_LineshapeNSF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Calculated dispersive stimulated Raman line shape"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570155535920_FSRS_LineshapeNSF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Calculated dispersive stimulated Raman line shape"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PE-FSRS spectra as a function of the plasmonic enhancement factor,  g. The spectra looks increasingly dispersive with increase in the enhancement factor.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Phys. Chem. C, 120, pp 20998?21006 (2016)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ziegler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Calculated dispersive stimulated Raman line shape</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570156149922_Odd_Even_NSF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570156149922_Odd_Even_NSF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Odd/even SFG intensities of alkylthiols"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570156149922_Odd_Even_NSF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Odd/even SFG intensities of alkylthiols"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SFG intensities of terminal methyl group on alkylthiols of chain length n.</div> <div class="imageCredit">In preparation publication.</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ziegler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Odd/even SFG intensities of alkylthiols</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570156554137_Barriers_scf_NSF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570156554137_Barriers_scf_NSF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rotational barriers as a function of density"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1609952/1609952_10440527_1570156554137_Barriers_scf_NSF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rotational barriers as a function of density"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Illustrative representation of the rotational potential barrier due to rotor-bath interactions as a function of solvent/bath density.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics, 21, 21249 (2019)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ziegler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rotational barriers as a function of density</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Shinning light that has a wavelength that matches the surface plasmon resonances of nanostructured metals, such as gold and silver, results in a large enhancement of this incident optical radiation field.  Technologies can be developed for imaging and sensing for example that provide greater sensitivities by exploiting this combination of metal nanoparticles and selective excitation colors.  This is called plasmonic enhancement (PE).  When laser light is used to excite and detect PE vibrational resonant molecular signatures, oddly shaped spectral features were obtained in such PE stimulated experiments. However, sensitivities at the single molecule level are achieved in the stimulated Raman experiments that have been carried out as evidence of the sensitivity achievable with this PE approach.  Two explanations for these unusual lineshapes have been discoverd and both may be operative.  One is based on interference effects from the emission of the nanoparticles themselves and the other is due to the complex character (i.e. real and imaginary part)  of the enhancement factor that only comes into play for stimulated, i.e. two laser, Raman experiments. Predicted lineshapes due to plasmon emission interference are shown in an accompanying figure for different enhancement strengths (g) and matches what has been observed.  Understanding the lineshape of these strongly enhanced vibrational features is important for the use of this approach for imaging capabilities so the identity of molecules  of interest can be established.  In another component of this project it was discovered that controlled deposition of silver on gold nanostructures (nanobipyramids) allowed tuning of the localized plasmon resonance to both higher or lower energies permitting better resonance with a selected molecular state of interest.  Sum frequency generation (SFG), another vibrationally resonant nonlinear laser technique, was used to probe how self assembled monolayers align on metal surfaces.  Plasmonic resonance effects are surface roughness dependent and contribute to the dispersive lineshapes found in these SFG spectra on Au and Ag as well.  Self-assembling monolayers of n-alkylthiols show remarkable odd-even (n) chain length effects that are dependent on the orientational structural details of the molecules with these metal surface as evident in the accompanying figure.  Such molecular level details are  important to understanding the macroscopic properties of these materials which have applications in sensing and chromatography.  Dense gases and supercritical fluids are high temperature and pressure environments for important chemical activity spanning applications from internal combustion engine reactions to coffee decaffeination.  An ultrafast, laser multidimensional IR technique (2DIR) was used to study dense gases and supercritical fluids (SCF) to understand how chemistry might be different in these solvents than in "normal" liquid solvents, and to develop a better detailed description of these dense phase regions that are common to all materials. Although we are taught in general chemistry that SCFs are a homogenous region with properties in between those of the gas and liquid, our ultrafast laser experiments find that high dense and supercritical solutions are better described as a mix of co-existing freely rotating molecules, that is a gas population, and hindered molecules trapped in liquid population regions below finite sized barriers (see picture). The supercritical region corresponds to the panels in between the gas and liquid depictions in this figure.  Furthermore, excited rotational and vibrational energy relaxation appears to be governed by independent binary collisions in the supercritical regions studies thus far, a gas-like response in a dense fluid.  Near the critical point dynamics at the molecular scale is found to slow as long length scale spatial correlations increase at the state point.  Thus the molecular environment "knows" that longer scale, macroscopic critical effects are occurring and has an influence on the local molecualr environment. This technique will be used to divide the supercritical region into liquid and gas like regions and confirm theoretical predictions about the existence of such boundaries in the supercritical regime.  Students working on these projects are trained in understanding matter-radiation interaction, nonlinear laser physics, the design and characterization of plasmonic nanostructures, their fabrication, near- and far-field  analysis through electromagnetic simulations, data collection and processing protocols and lab safety best practices, all skills transferable to both commercial as well as subsequent academic laboratories.           Last Modified: 10/03/2019       Submitted by: Lawrence D Ziegler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
