<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nonlinear Growth of Polyelectrolyte Multilayers: Chain Dynamics and Film Structure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>423707.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>423707</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PART I: NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on controlling the structure of functional polymer coatings. Such coatings could be used, e.g., for biomedical or optical applications.  Examples might be coatings that can deliver drugs locally in a multi-stage, time-resolved protocol,  or structured polymer films that can serve as precursors for better anti-reflective optical coatings. To support these advanced applications, (a) the coatings should be able to be easily deposited on a variety of surfaces via an environmentally friendly process, and (b) their structure should be easily controlled by the deposition procedure and conditions. The layer-by-layer (LbL) technique is a unique method which, through a deposition process entirely in water can create conformal coatings of controlled thickness on virtually any surface. The challenge, however, is to control the mixing of polymer molecules within the coated film to preserve film layering.  This project will explore the effect of various molecular and deposition parameters on film layering, with the goal of achieving structured films which can be deposited through fewer steps. Advanced instrumental techniques will be used to take snapshots of how multilayered structures, water content, and film mechanical properties can be manipulated. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Importantly, this project will create a fertile training ground for the participating graduate, undergraduate and high-school students. The PI is currently the academic advisor of the "Women in Materials Science" (WIMS) organization, which is strongly involved in many outreach activities, ranging from on-campus tours and demonstrations for Girl Scouts and high-school students to visits to local schools with the goal of encouraging and engaging female and minority 5-7th graders to pursue careers in science and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PART II: TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ability to control dynamics and the structure of layer-by-layer (LbL) polyelectrolyte films lies at the heart of advanced biomedical and optical applications of polyelectrolyte multilayer (PEM) films. Of specific interest are films with defined and controlled internal stratification. Yet nonlinearly growing LbL films (NL-LbLs) which deposit at larger thicknesses and therefore are highly desirable for many applications, suffer from molecular intermixing. This proposal aims to (a) uncover the mechanism of polymer chain diffusion within NL-PEMs during film growth, (b) establish correlations between molecular interactions, dynamics, and order for a broad range of NL-PEM films and (c) use this knowledge to control structure of NL-PEMs and develop strategies for constructing stratified and gradient LbL films. This project will involve synthesizing well-defined polybase-polyacid (PB-PA) pairs associated through ionic pairing or hydrogen-bonding. Interchain dynamics will be studied during PEM assembly, as well as at a post-assembly step. Neutron reflectometry (NR) will be used to track diffusion of polymer chains across the film thickness, in situ ellipsometry to determine film water content, and nanoindentation to explore film mechanical properties during film construction. At the post-assembly step, NR will be applied to resolve internal stratification, and fluorescence recovery after pattern photobleaching (FRAP) to study lateral mobility of assembled chains. This knowledge will then be used to rationally construct films with programmable density, water content, charge balance, and permeability. It will also enable rationally designed diffusional barriers and gradients of water content within NL-PEM films, in order to achieve films useful as matrices for conformal antireflective coatings or for sequential drug delivery via improved control of permeability of functional molecules.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1610725</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Svetlana</FirstName>
<LastName>Sukhishvili</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Svetlana A Sukhishvili</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>svetlana@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794589840</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~423707</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has been focused on controlling the structure of functional polymer coatings for biomedical and optical applications. When deposited at the surface of sutures or prosthetic implants, such coatings can deliver drugs locally. This is important as current coatings do not support the need for multistage, time-resolved delivery of various drugs, such as anesthetics or antibiotics. For optical applications, structured polymer coatings can serve as precursors for better anti-reflective coatings. This project has explored an environmentally friendly process of layer-by-layer (LbL) deposition of conformal coatings from aqueous solutions.</p> <p>Preserving film structure is paramount to achieving maximum utility of coatings. Therefore, we sought to find coating deposition parameters, such as time or polymer type, to enable control over film layering. Advanced instrumental techniques have been used to take snapshots of how multilayered structures and water content could be manipulated.</p> <p><span>Our main findings are focused on establishing direct correlation between the rate of polymer chain mixing and film layering. First, we have found that with LbL films constructed using weakly associating polymer pairs tend to have significant chain mixing, yet layering can be preserved by using short polymer deposition times (Fig. 1). Second, we have directly measured how the degree of polymer chain mixing increases with an increase in the deposition time during film construction. &nbsp;Finally, we have provided the first demonstration of how a competitive solvent can be used to tune film growth and chain mixing in LbL films.</span></p> <p>We further applied the knowledge generated during the fundamental studies of chain dynamics and film structure to rationally design drug delivery coatings, which were able to retain or release drug molecules in response to temperature variations. When deposited on fibrous mats, such coatings can provide dual benefits of accelerated wound healing and infection control.</p> <p>The results of this project resulted in nine publications in peer-revised journals, fourteen invited presentations by the Principal Investigator, and thirteen presentations by the participating graduate students at the national and international conferences.</p> <p>Importantly, this project created a fertile training ground for the participating graduate, undergraduate and high-school students. The Principal Investigator is the academic advisor of the "Women in Materials Science" (WIMS) organization, which is strongly involved in many outreach activities, reaching well beyond the gender issues. WIMS targets a broad group of elementary, middle, high school, undergraduate students and teachers, and sets its goal to promote materials science and engineering, and specifically polymer science, to young minds. NSF-funded students prepared hands-on experiments which involved polymers and used them during many outreach activities which ranged from on-campus tours and demonstrations for Girl Scouts, high-school students and general public to visits to local schools with the goal of encouraging and engaging female and minority 5-7th graders to pursue careers in science and engineering.</p> <p>The project directly involved several undergraduate students recruited through the Aggie Leadership program, and also greatly enhanced the exposure of graduate students to modern aspects of polymer science. Graduate students involved in the project significantly enriched their knowledge through systematic interactions with researchers at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL). Students supported by NSF traveled to Oak Ridge twice a year to perform neutron reflectivity experiments, and participated in weekly conference calls with ORNL. Through NSF-funded students, the developed collaborations have enriched the greater university community involved in studies of soft materials.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2019<br>      Modified by: Svetlana&nbsp;A&nbsp;Sukhishvili</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1610725/1610725_10412837_1567714310173_Outcomespicture--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1610725/1610725_10412837_1567714310173_Outcomespicture--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Controlling mixing of polymer chains within layered polymer films via polymer deposition time."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1610725/1610725_10412837_1567714310173_Outcomespicture--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Controlling mixing of polymer chains within layered polymer films via polymer deposition time."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig.1. Deposition time controls mixing of polymer chains within layered polymer films.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Victor Selin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Svetlana&nbsp;A&nbsp;Sukhishvili</div> <div class="imageTitle">Controlling mixing of polymer chains within layered polymer films via polymer deposition time.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has been focused on controlling the structure of functional polymer coatings for biomedical and optical applications. When deposited at the surface of sutures or prosthetic implants, such coatings can deliver drugs locally. This is important as current coatings do not support the need for multistage, time-resolved delivery of various drugs, such as anesthetics or antibiotics. For optical applications, structured polymer coatings can serve as precursors for better anti-reflective coatings. This project has explored an environmentally friendly process of layer-by-layer (LbL) deposition of conformal coatings from aqueous solutions.  Preserving film structure is paramount to achieving maximum utility of coatings. Therefore, we sought to find coating deposition parameters, such as time or polymer type, to enable control over film layering. Advanced instrumental techniques have been used to take snapshots of how multilayered structures and water content could be manipulated.  Our main findings are focused on establishing direct correlation between the rate of polymer chain mixing and film layering. First, we have found that with LbL films constructed using weakly associating polymer pairs tend to have significant chain mixing, yet layering can be preserved by using short polymer deposition times (Fig. 1). Second, we have directly measured how the degree of polymer chain mixing increases with an increase in the deposition time during film construction.  Finally, we have provided the first demonstration of how a competitive solvent can be used to tune film growth and chain mixing in LbL films.  We further applied the knowledge generated during the fundamental studies of chain dynamics and film structure to rationally design drug delivery coatings, which were able to retain or release drug molecules in response to temperature variations. When deposited on fibrous mats, such coatings can provide dual benefits of accelerated wound healing and infection control.  The results of this project resulted in nine publications in peer-revised journals, fourteen invited presentations by the Principal Investigator, and thirteen presentations by the participating graduate students at the national and international conferences.  Importantly, this project created a fertile training ground for the participating graduate, undergraduate and high-school students. The Principal Investigator is the academic advisor of the "Women in Materials Science" (WIMS) organization, which is strongly involved in many outreach activities, reaching well beyond the gender issues. WIMS targets a broad group of elementary, middle, high school, undergraduate students and teachers, and sets its goal to promote materials science and engineering, and specifically polymer science, to young minds. NSF-funded students prepared hands-on experiments which involved polymers and used them during many outreach activities which ranged from on-campus tours and demonstrations for Girl Scouts, high-school students and general public to visits to local schools with the goal of encouraging and engaging female and minority 5-7th graders to pursue careers in science and engineering.  The project directly involved several undergraduate students recruited through the Aggie Leadership program, and also greatly enhanced the exposure of graduate students to modern aspects of polymer science. Graduate students involved in the project significantly enriched their knowledge through systematic interactions with researchers at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL). Students supported by NSF traveled to Oak Ridge twice a year to perform neutron reflectivity experiments, and participated in weekly conference calls with ORNL. Through NSF-funded students, the developed collaborations have enriched the greater university community involved in studies of soft materials.       Last Modified: 09/05/2019       Submitted by: Svetlana A Sukhishvili]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
