<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Teaching Critical Thinking Skills in Science with sInvestigator</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chovis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924625</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A team of experts from computer science, artificial intelligence, science teaching and pedagogy, systems architecture, software engineering, knowledge engineering and human computer interaction at George Mason University (GMU) is developing a cognitive assistance tool, "sInvestigator," to help students acquire critical thinking skills in addressing scientific problems. The sInvestigator cognitive assistant is a significant technological innovation, based upon a computational theory of reasoning in science. It incorporates a substantial amount of general knowledge about scientific reasoning with evidence guiding and helping the student with the scientific inquiry process. The tool is novel and operates on multiple computer platforms. It is designed for students to use at home and in the lab and supports their acquisition of the core competency of evidence-based reasoning. The resulting theory is extendable to all STEM disciplines both undergraduate and K-12. Broadening participation is achieved through workshops having the capacity of 50-70 participants. Recruiting targets community colleges and minority serving institutions to attract women and underrepresented groups to the workshops organized in collaboration with the GMU Center for Teaching and Faculty Excellence. Evidence based reasoning is at the core of problem solving and decision making not only in STEM disciplines but also law, intelligence analysis, forensics, medicine, history, archeology and other domains. The developed educational materials together with sInvestigator exercises are widely distributed. Information on how teachers and researchers can freely obtain the sInvestigator are posted on GMU's Learning Agents Center website.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The three-year project is first piloted in two Honors courses enrolling 30-40 students. Working in teams, students are guided to approach a scientific problem as ceaseless discovery of evidence, hypothesis and arguments. New knowledge is added by answering research questions that explore improvements in student perception of science process skills and gains in student content knowledge, as measured by course assessments. Students experience numerous opportunities to exercise imagination and creativity and acquire critical scientific practices, particularly: (1) Asking questions; (2) Constructing explanations; (3) Engaging in argument from evidence; and (4) Obtaining, evaluating and communicating explanations (NRC, 2012 p.3). The use of sInvestigator is explored in a sequence of courses to learn what works and what does not work and incrementally evolve the theory and the approach while developing and testing case studies. The mixed-methods evaluation is mostly formative with a focus on understanding students' collaborative experiences with sInvestigator through surveys and interviews. Modification of assessment tools is made based upon evaluation which allows for analysis of student intrinsic motivation, career motivation, self-determination, self-efficacy and grade motivation. In the final year a quasi-experimental research design will be used to evaluate the impact of sInvestigator in a general science course with 250-300 students in two course sections. The design allows for a comparison group on student achievement scores using course assessments, a Science Motivation Questionnaire and a Science Process skills inventory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1611742</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gheorghe</FirstName>
<LastName>Tecuci</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gheorghe Tecuci</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tecuci@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039931722</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239149</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Trefil</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James S Trefil</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7039932183</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000285855</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mihai</FirstName>
<LastName>Boicu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mihai Boicu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mboicu@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039931591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000504671</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dorin</FirstName>
<LastName>Marcu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dorin Marcu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmarcu@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039931535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000612841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Holincheck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy Holincheck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nholinch@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039938136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000709678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Mason University</Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077817450</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE MASON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077817450</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Mason University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairfax</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main outcomes of this project are:</p> <ul> <li>An inquiry-based approach to helping students learn critical thinking skills for solving scientific problems.</li> <li>A computational theory of evidence-based reasoning in science that forms the basis of this approach.</li> <li>An intelligent computer system, called sInvestigator (science Investigator), that implements the computational theory, greatly facilitates the development of inquiry-based exercises by instructors, and provides a hands-on learning experience to students.</li> <li>Sample exercises for students from middle school through university.</li> </ul> <ol> </ol> <p class="Text">The developed inquiry-based approach engages the students in understanding, extending, creating, critiquing, and debating evidence-based scientific argumentations in real-life scientific investigations. It involves using science cross-cutting concepts and disciplinary core ideas, giving the students numerous opportunities to exercise imagination and creativity, and develop critical scientific practices, particularly: (1) Asking questions; (2) Constructing explanations; (3) Engaging in argument from evidence; and (4) Obtaining, evaluating, and communicating explanations.</p> <p class="Text">Figure 1 presents the developed model of scientific inquiry as discovery of evidence, hypotheses, and arguments which is implemented in sInvestigator. For simplicity, Figure 1 shows only two hypothesized answers but the actual number depends on the specific scientific inquiry considered.</p> <p class="Text">A classical textbook example of using inquiry in a science class is presented in "Inquiry and the National Science Education Standards: A Guide for Teaching and Learning," pp.5-11, National Research Council, 2000, Washington, DC: The National Academies Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.17226/9596">https://doi.org/10.17226/9596</a>. Figure 2 illustrates an adaptation of this example to show how sInvestigator can naturally support inquiry-based teaching and learning.</p> <p class="Text">The process started with the instructor formulating the scientific inquiry (Why are these three trees different? They used to be the same.), and challenging the students to imagine possible answers, leading to the following hypotheses:</p> <ul> <li>It must be too much water that causes a tree to die.</li> <li>Insects are eating two of the trees.</li> <li>The trees have different ages.</li> </ul> <p class="Text">The students were then invited to pick a hypothesis which led to three groups, a water group, an illness group, and an age group. Each group carried out its investigation, discovering a variety of sources with information about characteristics of trees, their life cycles, and their environments. The water group that investigated the first hypothesis decomposed it into two simpler sub-hypotheses that showed more clearly what evidence may be used to test them:</p> <ul> <li>There is too much water at the root of the dying tree.</li> <li>Too much water at the root causes the tree to die.</li> </ul> <p class="Text">To discover evidence for the first sub-hypothesis, the group decided to look at the ground around the trees every hour that they could, taking turns on making individual observations, until they had sufficient data indicating that there is too much water at the root of the dying tree. An evidence item for the second hypothesis was found on the Internet.</p> <p class="Text">The team then assessed and justified the credibility and relevance of the discovered evidence. They also conducted a deeper credibility analyses of the Internet article by assessing author's competence (affiliation and history), objectivity (relationship to current knowledge and conflict of interest), and publication's reputation. Then sInvestigator computed the probabilities of all the hypotheses and generated a draft report. The team finalized the report and debated it in class.</p> <p class="Text">sInvestigator was experimentally used in the following undergraduate honors science courses for non-science majors at George Mason University: HNRS 353 Modern Scientific Revolutions, HNRS 353 Science of Cities, and HNRS 240 History of Science. Case studies for middle school and high school science classes have also been developed.</p> <p>The sInvestigator website (<a href="http://lac.gmu.edu/sInvestigator/index.html">http://lac.gmu.edu/sInvestigator/index.html</a>) is maintained as the most complete and up to date repository of information on our research on teaching critical thinking in science, including instructions to download the most recent version of the system for both PC and Mac. It contains a wide variety of exercises for representative inquiry-based experiences, such as: Analysis of competing scientific theories; Predicting, observing and explaining the result of an experiment; Explaining a physical phenomenon; Classifying an entity (e.g., organism or a rock); Arguing about a socio-scientific issue; Exploring a mystery. The report titled Inquiry-based Teaching of Critical Thinking Skills in Science with sInvestigator (<a href="http://lac.gmu.edu/publications/2021/sInvestigator-Report.pdf">http://lac.gmu.edu/publications/2021/sInvestigator-Report.pdf</a>) presents several of these exercises.</p> <p class="Text">The developed inquiry-based approach to learning critical thinking skills for solving scientific problems helps improve the quality of reasoning of the students in any activity involving evidence-based reasoning, which is at the core of many problem-solving and decision-making tasks in a wide variety of domains, such as cybersecurity, law, intelligence analysis, forensics, medicine, history, archaeology, and many others. A tool like sInvestigator can help educators prepare students to identify and interpret Internet sources in a shared pursuit of information literacy which they will need as scholars and as engaged citizens. This is a core competency which is important for any person, in any area of activity.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2021<br>      Modified by: Gheorghe&nbsp;Tecuci</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1611742/1611742_10463008_1611703338227_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1611742/1611742_10463008_1611703338227_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1611742/1611742_10463008_1611703338227_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Scientific inquiry as discovery of evidence, hypotheses, and arguments.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gheorghe&nbsp;Tecuci</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1611742/1611742_10463008_1611703653982_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1611742/1611742_10463008_1611703653982_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1611742/1611742_10463008_1611703653982_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Inquiry representation in the interface of sInvestigator.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gheorghe&nbsp;Tecuci</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main outcomes of this project are:  An inquiry-based approach to helping students learn critical thinking skills for solving scientific problems. A computational theory of evidence-based reasoning in science that forms the basis of this approach. An intelligent computer system, called sInvestigator (science Investigator), that implements the computational theory, greatly facilitates the development of inquiry-based exercises by instructors, and provides a hands-on learning experience to students. Sample exercises for students from middle school through university.    The developed inquiry-based approach engages the students in understanding, extending, creating, critiquing, and debating evidence-based scientific argumentations in real-life scientific investigations. It involves using science cross-cutting concepts and disciplinary core ideas, giving the students numerous opportunities to exercise imagination and creativity, and develop critical scientific practices, particularly: (1) Asking questions; (2) Constructing explanations; (3) Engaging in argument from evidence; and (4) Obtaining, evaluating, and communicating explanations. Figure 1 presents the developed model of scientific inquiry as discovery of evidence, hypotheses, and arguments which is implemented in sInvestigator. For simplicity, Figure 1 shows only two hypothesized answers but the actual number depends on the specific scientific inquiry considered. A classical textbook example of using inquiry in a science class is presented in "Inquiry and the National Science Education Standards: A Guide for Teaching and Learning," pp.5-11, National Research Council, 2000, Washington, DC: The National Academies Press. https://doi.org/10.17226/9596. Figure 2 illustrates an adaptation of this example to show how sInvestigator can naturally support inquiry-based teaching and learning. The process started with the instructor formulating the scientific inquiry (Why are these three trees different? They used to be the same.), and challenging the students to imagine possible answers, leading to the following hypotheses:  It must be too much water that causes a tree to die. Insects are eating two of the trees. The trees have different ages.  The students were then invited to pick a hypothesis which led to three groups, a water group, an illness group, and an age group. Each group carried out its investigation, discovering a variety of sources with information about characteristics of trees, their life cycles, and their environments. The water group that investigated the first hypothesis decomposed it into two simpler sub-hypotheses that showed more clearly what evidence may be used to test them:  There is too much water at the root of the dying tree. Too much water at the root causes the tree to die.  To discover evidence for the first sub-hypothesis, the group decided to look at the ground around the trees every hour that they could, taking turns on making individual observations, until they had sufficient data indicating that there is too much water at the root of the dying tree. An evidence item for the second hypothesis was found on the Internet. The team then assessed and justified the credibility and relevance of the discovered evidence. They also conducted a deeper credibility analyses of the Internet article by assessing author's competence (affiliation and history), objectivity (relationship to current knowledge and conflict of interest), and publication's reputation. Then sInvestigator computed the probabilities of all the hypotheses and generated a draft report. The team finalized the report and debated it in class. sInvestigator was experimentally used in the following undergraduate honors science courses for non-science majors at George Mason University: HNRS 353 Modern Scientific Revolutions, HNRS 353 Science of Cities, and HNRS 240 History of Science. Case studies for middle school and high school science classes have also been developed.  The sInvestigator website (http://lac.gmu.edu/sInvestigator/index.html) is maintained as the most complete and up to date repository of information on our research on teaching critical thinking in science, including instructions to download the most recent version of the system for both PC and Mac. It contains a wide variety of exercises for representative inquiry-based experiences, such as: Analysis of competing scientific theories; Predicting, observing and explaining the result of an experiment; Explaining a physical phenomenon; Classifying an entity (e.g., organism or a rock); Arguing about a socio-scientific issue; Exploring a mystery. The report titled Inquiry-based Teaching of Critical Thinking Skills in Science with sInvestigator (http://lac.gmu.edu/publications/2021/sInvestigator-Report.pdf) presents several of these exercises. The developed inquiry-based approach to learning critical thinking skills for solving scientific problems helps improve the quality of reasoning of the students in any activity involving evidence-based reasoning, which is at the core of many problem-solving and decision-making tasks in a wide variety of domains, such as cybersecurity, law, intelligence analysis, forensics, medicine, history, archaeology, and many others. A tool like sInvestigator can help educators prepare students to identify and interpret Internet sources in a shared pursuit of information literacy which they will need as scholars and as engaged citizens. This is a core competency which is important for any person, in any area of activity.       Last Modified: 01/26/2021       Submitted by: Gheorghe Tecuci]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
