<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigating the Competition Between Exciton Delocalization and Radiative Recombination in 1D Semiconductor Quantum Wires</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>416798.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>416798</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James H. Edgar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jedgar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical Description: One-dimensional semiconductor wires with lengths longer than micrometers can efficiently absorb light that in turn generates mobile charge carriers within the semiconductor. When the diameters of these materials become small, on the order of nanometers to tens of nanometers, both the colors of the light that are preferentially absorbed and the energies of the charge carriers within the semiconductor material can be manipulated. These one-dimensional materials are called semiconductor nanowires, and they represent the smallest structures that can efficiently generate and transport charges along specific directions. The main goal of this interdisciplinary research project is to characterize the efficiency of semiconductor nanowires in terms of charge-carrier generation and transport. An emphasis is placed on optimizing the chemical and physical properties of semiconductor nanowires so their viability in application designs can be evaluated. The research uses both traditional optical spectroscopy and advanced laser techniques to probe the energies of the charge carriers within the nanowires and to characterize the fate of these charge carriers as a function of time and position along single nanowire. Particular attention is given to measuring how well the charge carriers are transported along the length of the nanowires. Another focus of this project is on training the next generation of scientists, especially those from underrepresented backgrounds with diverse expertise in materials science, chemistry, and physics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: This research is focused on optimizing the properties of semiconductor quantum wires synthesized by using the solution-liquid-solid strategy with a particular focus on cadmium telluride and cadmium selenide quantum wires. The research team is performing absorbance and photoluminescence spectroscopy experiments to characterize the energies of charge carriers photo-generated within them as well as the photoluminescence quantum yields of the these nanostructures. The dynamics of the electrons, holes, and excitons within the quantum wires are characterized by performing photoluminescence lifetime and transient absorption spectroscopy experiments. Specific goals include: 1) characterization of the exciton lifetime dependences on photoluminescence quantum yield, surface passivation and structural quality of the quantum wires; 2) measurement of exciton diffusion length along single quantum wires and its dependence on photoluminescence quantum yield, surface passivation and quantum wire structural quality; and 3) investigation of the apparent competition between efficient exciton diffusion and the probability for radiative recombination within the quantum wires.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1611149</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Loomis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard A Loomis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>loomis@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149358534</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000216824</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive, CB 1054]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~135681</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~138895</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~142222</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the period of this NSF DMR award, our group focused on characterizing charge carrier (electron and hole) dynamics in one-dimensional (1D) semiconductor nanomaterials. Semiconductor quantum wires (QWs) are promising for use in photovoltaic and nanoelectronics devices because they offer a) the tunability of band-gap energies by adjusting the diameters of the QWs, and b) the dimensionality for efficient directional transport of charges over microscopic distances. Our interdisciplinary efforts combined synthetic methods development with several types of optical spectroscopy measurements. We improved the properties of CdTe and CdSe QWs so that we could begin to probe their potential. Optical spectroscopy experiments revealed the lifetimes of electron-hole pairs bound as 1D excitons in CdTe QWs far exceed the natural radiative lifetime of excitons in bulk and other CdTe nanoparticles (NPs), ~25 ns. We also probed the relaxation of excited carriers to the band edge in real time.</p> <p>On the synthetic front, we improved the synthesis of CdTe and CdSe QWs, paying particular attention to the physical morphology and crystallinity of the QWs. We developed ligand-replacement and surface-passivation schemes for both CdTe and CdSe NPs. A good measure of the quality of the surface of a semiconductor NP is the photoluminescence (PL) quantum yield (QY), or the efficiency of radiative recombination. We improved the PL QY of CdTe QWs from ~0.1%, which was previously a good value for QWs, to above 25%. These PL QY values are approaching those of spherical quantum dots (QDs), which are utilized in many commercial devices.</p> <p>We synthesized core/shell NPs with the goal of tuning the dynamics of the charge carriers. We synthesized CdSe/PbS QDs and quantum platelets, and we showed that the band gap of these NPs can be shifted by growing shells with different thicknesses, 1-8 PbS monolayers. The CdSe/PbS heterostructures have inverse-type I band alignment based on bulk band-gap energies; the electrons and holes would be generated in the CdSe core of the NPs, and relax in the PbS shell region. By making CdSe/PbS core/shell structures with very thin shells, the band alignment could be tuned to type II; the electrons would remain in the CdSe core region, and the holes would separate to and relax in the shell region. The optical spectra of these core/shell NPs indicate that while the energetics do shift with shell growth, the electrons and holes remain highly overlapped within the NPs, and type II band alignment was not achieved. Different schemes must be developed to grow even thicker shells, where the type II alignment may be achieved.</p> <p>The relaxation of excited carriers to the band edge was tracked in time using transient absorption spectroscopy (TAS) and implementing a new model to unravel overlapping signals that complicate the data. TAS experiments performed on semiconductor NPs contain overlapping induced-absorption and bleach signals, associated with new absorption transitions and decreases in absorption probability caused by the presence of the photogenerated electrons and holes. The energies and strengths of these signals in the TAS data evolve with time, thereby making the characterization of the carrier dynamics difficult. We developed a model, quantum-state renormalization (QSR), that accounts for the energetic shifting of the quantum-confinement states of the electrons and holes induced by optical excitation. We showed the population of the carriers after initial excitation in CdTe QWs could be probed in real time as they relax to the band edge and ultimately recombine. The hole relaxation rate is very fast, &gt;2&nbsp;? 10<sup>12</sup> eV / sec, but the rate of the electron relaxation is slower, and occupation of the electrons through the different quantum-confinement states was observed. A schematic representing the electron relaxation through the different states is included in <strong>Figure 1</strong>. The measured rates for de-occupation of the different states do not match those for occupation of the next-lower quantum-confinement states, indicated by solid bold arrows. This indicates there are intermediate states involved in the electron relaxation that are not detected in the TAS experiments, thin arrows in the figure. We propose the electrons relax via coupling with phonons, or through the generation of heat, in the QWs and not via Auger, or charge-charge coupling, that occurs in spherical semiconductor QDs.</p> <p>The research conducted as part of this award is highly interdisciplinary, and the training of talented scientists with broad skill sets was a priority. Loomis actively strived to enhance diversity in STEM through several programs. He initiated and secured funding for the program <em>Recruitment of Chemists with Diverse Backgrounds into Academia at WU: A Visiting Research Fellow Program</em>. Two faculty members and six minority undergraduate students have participated in this program. Loomis also co-initiated <em>Partnerships to Advance STEM Readiness</em> in St. Louis region high schools. Here, University faculty meet with teachers from local schools to discuss teaching concepts, styles and issues with presenting course materials in different ways.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2019<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;A&nbsp;Loomis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1611149/1611149_10430922_1571264180943_FinalOutcomesFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1611149/1611149_10430922_1571264180943_FinalOutcomesFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. The dynamics of electrons relaxing through the quantum-confinement states in the conduction band of CdTe quantum wires."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1611149/1611149_10430922_1571264180943_FinalOutcomesFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1. The dynamics of electrons relaxing through the quantum-confinement states in the conduction band of CdTe quantum wires."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Growth and decay profiles measured in transient absorption spectroscopy experiments indicate complicated relaxation dynamics. Some electrons relax to the lowest-energy state within 0.5 ps, while others take nearly 2 ps. The relaxation likely involves coupling with phonons and intermediate states.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Electron occupancy in CdTe QWs</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;A&nbsp;Loomis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1. The dynamics of electrons relaxing through the quantum-confinement states in the conduction band of CdTe quantum wires.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the period of this NSF DMR award, our group focused on characterizing charge carrier (electron and hole) dynamics in one-dimensional (1D) semiconductor nanomaterials. Semiconductor quantum wires (QWs) are promising for use in photovoltaic and nanoelectronics devices because they offer a) the tunability of band-gap energies by adjusting the diameters of the QWs, and b) the dimensionality for efficient directional transport of charges over microscopic distances. Our interdisciplinary efforts combined synthetic methods development with several types of optical spectroscopy measurements. We improved the properties of CdTe and CdSe QWs so that we could begin to probe their potential. Optical spectroscopy experiments revealed the lifetimes of electron-hole pairs bound as 1D excitons in CdTe QWs far exceed the natural radiative lifetime of excitons in bulk and other CdTe nanoparticles (NPs), ~25 ns. We also probed the relaxation of excited carriers to the band edge in real time.  On the synthetic front, we improved the synthesis of CdTe and CdSe QWs, paying particular attention to the physical morphology and crystallinity of the QWs. We developed ligand-replacement and surface-passivation schemes for both CdTe and CdSe NPs. A good measure of the quality of the surface of a semiconductor NP is the photoluminescence (PL) quantum yield (QY), or the efficiency of radiative recombination. We improved the PL QY of CdTe QWs from ~0.1%, which was previously a good value for QWs, to above 25%. These PL QY values are approaching those of spherical quantum dots (QDs), which are utilized in many commercial devices.  We synthesized core/shell NPs with the goal of tuning the dynamics of the charge carriers. We synthesized CdSe/PbS QDs and quantum platelets, and we showed that the band gap of these NPs can be shifted by growing shells with different thicknesses, 1-8 PbS monolayers. The CdSe/PbS heterostructures have inverse-type I band alignment based on bulk band-gap energies; the electrons and holes would be generated in the CdSe core of the NPs, and relax in the PbS shell region. By making CdSe/PbS core/shell structures with very thin shells, the band alignment could be tuned to type II; the electrons would remain in the CdSe core region, and the holes would separate to and relax in the shell region. The optical spectra of these core/shell NPs indicate that while the energetics do shift with shell growth, the electrons and holes remain highly overlapped within the NPs, and type II band alignment was not achieved. Different schemes must be developed to grow even thicker shells, where the type II alignment may be achieved.  The relaxation of excited carriers to the band edge was tracked in time using transient absorption spectroscopy (TAS) and implementing a new model to unravel overlapping signals that complicate the data. TAS experiments performed on semiconductor NPs contain overlapping induced-absorption and bleach signals, associated with new absorption transitions and decreases in absorption probability caused by the presence of the photogenerated electrons and holes. The energies and strengths of these signals in the TAS data evolve with time, thereby making the characterization of the carrier dynamics difficult. We developed a model, quantum-state renormalization (QSR), that accounts for the energetic shifting of the quantum-confinement states of the electrons and holes induced by optical excitation. We showed the population of the carriers after initial excitation in CdTe QWs could be probed in real time as they relax to the band edge and ultimately recombine. The hole relaxation rate is very fast, &gt;2 ? 1012 eV / sec, but the rate of the electron relaxation is slower, and occupation of the electrons through the different quantum-confinement states was observed. A schematic representing the electron relaxation through the different states is included in Figure 1. The measured rates for de-occupation of the different states do not match those for occupation of the next-lower quantum-confinement states, indicated by solid bold arrows. This indicates there are intermediate states involved in the electron relaxation that are not detected in the TAS experiments, thin arrows in the figure. We propose the electrons relax via coupling with phonons, or through the generation of heat, in the QWs and not via Auger, or charge-charge coupling, that occurs in spherical semiconductor QDs.  The research conducted as part of this award is highly interdisciplinary, and the training of talented scientists with broad skill sets was a priority. Loomis actively strived to enhance diversity in STEM through several programs. He initiated and secured funding for the program Recruitment of Chemists with Diverse Backgrounds into Academia at WU: A Visiting Research Fellow Program. Two faculty members and six minority undergraduate students have participated in this program. Loomis also co-initiated Partnerships to Advance STEM Readiness in St. Louis region high schools. Here, University faculty meet with teachers from local schools to discuss teaching concepts, styles and issues with presenting course materials in different ways.       Last Modified: 10/16/2019       Submitted by: Richard A Loomis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
