<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative proposal: Variable Selection in the high dimensional, low sample size setting -- Beyond the Linear Regression and Normal Errors Model</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Revolutionary new technologies are producing high-throughput biological data at a resolution that was unthinkable only a decade ago. These new forms of data pose enormous challenges and opportunities for statisticians and computer scientists. This project develops new sophisticated statistical methods and computational algorithms for analyzing and integrating complex high-dimensional data. The work is motivated by collaborations with leading biological scientists at Cornell-Ithaca and Weill Cornell Medical College working in diverse research areas including plant biology, nutrition, neurology, cancer epigenomics, and veterinary medicine. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to develop new statistical models and computational algorithms for high-dimensional, low sample size, high-throughput biological data, including new methods for the analysis of microarrays, the identification of quantitative trait loci, association mapping, label-free shotgun proteomics and metabolomics. The proposed methods involve innovative extensions of modern statistical building blocks, including the use of random effects for regularization, shrinkage estimation, Bayesian statistics, and mixtures for posterior classification and prediction. Novel modifications of the expectation-maximization algorithm are proposed for scalable and efficient model fitting and inference.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1611893</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wells</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin T Wells</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mtw1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558801</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000438891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Booth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James G Booth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jb383@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072546505</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000344058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148532601</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Comstock Hall-Academic II]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A new model-based variable selection method was developed for situations in which the number of predictors, P, is greater than the number of observations, N. The challenge was to develop a computationally efficient, and scalable method that can be used in different settings. Among the most widely used frameworks in statistics is the Generalized Linear Model (GLM), which includes the normal distribution for continuous outcomes, the binomial distribution for counts, and Poisson responses. The latter can be used to perform survival analysis; that is when the response is a (possibly censored) survival time. In the first stage of the project, we developed the theory, algorithms and the software to deal with GLMs. In the second stage we extended the approach to model selection in the context of graphical models and quantile regression, all in the P greater than N setting.</p> <p>One example is the analysis of the logarithm of riboflavin (vitamin B12) for N=71 subjects and their expression levels for P=4,088 genes. Our algorithm discovered a model involving six genes with an R-squared value (a measure of how well the model fits the data on a scale of 0 to 1) of 0.85. However, settling on one model is likely inappropriate because some predictors may be part of a network on highly correlated variables. In fact, using a correlation threshold of 0.75 between genes expression values our algorithm reported a total of 62 relevant predictors. Another example concerns the age at onset of lung cancer among N=379 current or former smokers and the expression of P=13,492 genes. In this case we were interested in whether the 15th percentile (early onset) and the median of the response were related to the expression of any genes. Our algorithm did not find any genes predicting the median age of onset. However, the SCO1 gene was found to be a good predictor of early onset which is interesting because SCO1 is known to play a critical role in copper incorporation in the cytochrome c oxidase and lung cancer.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2021<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;G&nbsp;Booth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A new model-based variable selection method was developed for situations in which the number of predictors, P, is greater than the number of observations, N. The challenge was to develop a computationally efficient, and scalable method that can be used in different settings. Among the most widely used frameworks in statistics is the Generalized Linear Model (GLM), which includes the normal distribution for continuous outcomes, the binomial distribution for counts, and Poisson responses. The latter can be used to perform survival analysis; that is when the response is a (possibly censored) survival time. In the first stage of the project, we developed the theory, algorithms and the software to deal with GLMs. In the second stage we extended the approach to model selection in the context of graphical models and quantile regression, all in the P greater than N setting.  One example is the analysis of the logarithm of riboflavin (vitamin B12) for N=71 subjects and their expression levels for P=4,088 genes. Our algorithm discovered a model involving six genes with an R-squared value (a measure of how well the model fits the data on a scale of 0 to 1) of 0.85. However, settling on one model is likely inappropriate because some predictors may be part of a network on highly correlated variables. In fact, using a correlation threshold of 0.75 between genes expression values our algorithm reported a total of 62 relevant predictors. Another example concerns the age at onset of lung cancer among N=379 current or former smokers and the expression of P=13,492 genes. In this case we were interested in whether the 15th percentile (early onset) and the median of the response were related to the expression of any genes. Our algorithm did not find any genes predicting the median age of onset. However, the SCO1 gene was found to be a good predictor of early onset which is interesting because SCO1 is known to play a critical role in copper incorporation in the cytochrome c oxidase and lung cancer.           Last Modified: 01/10/2021       Submitted by: James G Booth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
