<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Plasmonic Nanoantenna Electrode Arrays (NEAs) for Massively Multiplexed Identification of Stem-Cell Derived Cardiac Cells in Regenerative Therapies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>287465.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>287465</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Zhang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jzhang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collaborative Research: Plasmonic Nanoantenna Electrode Arrays (NEAs) for Massively Multiplexed Identification of Stem-Cell Derived Cardiac Cells in Regenerative Therapies&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nontechnical Abstract: Heart diseases are one of the leading causes of death in the US. Stem cellbased regenerative therapies are among the most promising treatment techniques. However, cells derived from stem cells are not uniform; only some percentage of the initial cell culture develops into the cell type of interest. Undifferentiated cells that remain within the cell population could lead to tumor.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, immature cells or cells with over-sensitivity would hinder the synchronous beating of the heart muscle cells, which can cause heart failure. Current methods to examine the purity of stem-cell based heart cells depend on cell surface markers, which is not a precise way to determine cellular functionality. This proposal offers a high-throughput screening technique to directly measure the&lt;br/&gt;functionality of differentiated heart muscle cells through their specific membrane potential changes during contraction. The proposed molecular-nanoplasmonic label-free voltage sensors will allow screening of single cell membrane potentials within confluent cell cultures and provide an accurate method for selecting and purifying functional cells from a mixed group. Development of such a precise technique would present a remarkable technological leap in stem cell-based research and strategies for cardiac regeneration. In addition to scientific and technological advancements, this research program will provide educational opportunities to underrepresented groups and minorities, and enhance involvement of undergraduate and graduate students in nanoscience and technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract: The objective of this research proposal is to introduce ultrasensitive molecularplasmonic voltage probes for non-invasive, real-time and subcellular precision mapping of cardiac cell membrane potentials. These electrophysiological nanoprobes could have significant impact in differentiation of stem cell derived cardiac cells through massively parallel and precise mapping of single&lt;br/&gt;cell membrane potentials. Given the lack of experimental electrophysiological techniques with high spatial and temporal precision capabilities, this research program could significantly contribute to cardiac cell studies and regenerative therapies. The specific objectives of this research program are:&lt;br/&gt;(1) to develop molecular-plasmonic voltage sensors by using electromagnetic simulations, high throughput fabrication and chemical synthesis techniques, and optical/electrical characterization.&lt;br/&gt;(2) to realize real time and label free detection of tiny potential variations at diffraction limited spot sizes with microsecond temporal resolutions and high signal-to-noise ratios.&lt;br/&gt;(3) to achieve non-destructive imaging of single cells in large cell populations and distinguish individual cell characteristics in -cultured/multiple cell state.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research program involves theoretical understanding and numerical design of molecularplasmonic devices. Devices merging nano/micro-meter components will be fabricated using state of lithography and synthesis techniques. Fabricated devices will be tested using excitable cell populations with varying densities and cell compositions. Furthermore, changes in the membrane potentials of&lt;br/&gt;cardiomyocytes that are being differentiated from hiPSC will be measured in real-time.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1611083</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pinar</FirstName>
<LastName>Zorlutuna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pinar Zorlutuna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Pinar.Zorlutuna.1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746317432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>104E</Code>
<Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~287465</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>State-of-art methods for measuring cell membrane potential utilize patch- clamps or microelectrodes. However, both techniques face significant limitations. Patch clamp technique is a powerful&#8232;method to study single cell potentials. Nonetheless, it is intrusive and harmful to the cells,&#8232;preventing reliable and long-term single cell studies. Patch-clamp technique also requires high level of user skills and interference limiting simultaneous measurements to a few cells,&#8232;a fundamental limitation while working on cellular networks. On the other hand, microelectrodes can be arrayed to take measurements from multiple sites, but, they are prone to signals coming from neighboring cells and it is very hard to make single cell measurements. Microelectrode measurements also require alignment of the cellular pattern with that of the fabricated electrode layout. However, growth of cellular network is determined by the biology unlike electrode&#8232;layout controlled by design. Furthermore, none of the existing techniques could be used to measure subcellular membrane potential changes of a 3D cellular network concurrently at several distinct locations. Given the lack of experimental techniques with high spatial and temporal precision capabilities, we believe that our research program can significantly contribute&#8232;the advancements in these fields. Development of such nano-photonic sensors will transform&#8232;the field of cellular electrophysiology and will open an avenue for a new generation of sensors&#8232;for membrane potential studies in both 2-D and 3-D live tissues.</p> <p>The newly developed sensor that enables intensity-based measurements while using&nbsp;all-photonic and label-free detection approachcan be used as a better way of measuring membrane potential of single cells within confluent cell cultures, which can be used as a high accuracy method for selecting and purifying functional cells from a mixed group of cells. For example, upon differentiation, cells derived from stem cells are not uniform; only a percentage of the initial cell culture differentiates to the cell type of interest (i.e. neuron or cardiomyocyte). Although the stem cell- derived cells are very promising cell sources for clinical applications, major limiting factor in their usage is tumor formation due to undifferentiated cells that remain within the cell population. For cardiac therapies, an additional drawback of remaining undifferentiated, immature cells or cells with over-sensitivity would hinder the synchronous beating of the cardiomyocytes which can cause arrhythmia or ventricular fibrillation, and eventually heart failure. The current method to examine the purity of the culture depends on cell surface markers while the functionality of a cardiomyocyte cell is defined by its specific membrane potential changes during action potential. Therefore, the method developed in this project will enable screening individual cells of a group of differentiated cardiomyocytes, which can provide a better means of measuring the phenotype of these cells, as well as for selection and purification purposes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2020<br>      Modified by: Pinar&nbsp;Zorlutuna</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1611083/1611083_10442748_1605717198971_RCMonAuchip_008--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1611083/1611083_10442748_1605717198971_RCMonAuchip_008--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CMs on nanohole arrays"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1611083/1611083_10442748_1605717198971_RCMonAuchip_008--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CMs on nanohole arrays"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM image of a cardiomyocyte on the nanohole array plasmonic sensors</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zorlutuna and Yanik</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pinar&nbsp;Zorlutuna</div> <div class="imageTitle">CMs on nanohole arrays</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ State-of-art methods for measuring cell membrane potential utilize patch- clamps or microelectrodes. However, both techniques face significant limitations. Patch clamp technique is a powerful&#8232;method to study single cell potentials. Nonetheless, it is intrusive and harmful to the cells,&#8232;preventing reliable and long-term single cell studies. Patch-clamp technique also requires high level of user skills and interference limiting simultaneous measurements to a few cells,&#8232;a fundamental limitation while working on cellular networks. On the other hand, microelectrodes can be arrayed to take measurements from multiple sites, but, they are prone to signals coming from neighboring cells and it is very hard to make single cell measurements. Microelectrode measurements also require alignment of the cellular pattern with that of the fabricated electrode layout. However, growth of cellular network is determined by the biology unlike electrode&#8232;layout controlled by design. Furthermore, none of the existing techniques could be used to measure subcellular membrane potential changes of a 3D cellular network concurrently at several distinct locations. Given the lack of experimental techniques with high spatial and temporal precision capabilities, we believe that our research program can significantly contribute&#8232;the advancements in these fields. Development of such nano-photonic sensors will transform&#8232;the field of cellular electrophysiology and will open an avenue for a new generation of sensors&#8232;for membrane potential studies in both 2-D and 3-D live tissues.  The newly developed sensor that enables intensity-based measurements while using all-photonic and label-free detection approachcan be used as a better way of measuring membrane potential of single cells within confluent cell cultures, which can be used as a high accuracy method for selecting and purifying functional cells from a mixed group of cells. For example, upon differentiation, cells derived from stem cells are not uniform; only a percentage of the initial cell culture differentiates to the cell type of interest (i.e. neuron or cardiomyocyte). Although the stem cell- derived cells are very promising cell sources for clinical applications, major limiting factor in their usage is tumor formation due to undifferentiated cells that remain within the cell population. For cardiac therapies, an additional drawback of remaining undifferentiated, immature cells or cells with over-sensitivity would hinder the synchronous beating of the cardiomyocytes which can cause arrhythmia or ventricular fibrillation, and eventually heart failure. The current method to examine the purity of the culture depends on cell surface markers while the functionality of a cardiomyocyte cell is defined by its specific membrane potential changes during action potential. Therefore, the method developed in this project will enable screening individual cells of a group of differentiated cardiomyocytes, which can provide a better means of measuring the phenotype of these cells, as well as for selection and purification purposes.             Last Modified: 11/18/2020       Submitted by: Pinar Zorlutuna]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
