<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Developing Undergraduate Scientists through Inquiry-Based Chemistry Laboratories</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>296189.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>296189</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dawn Rickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drickey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924674</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Department of Chemistry at State University of New York at Old Westbury (SUNY-OW) will explore how undergraduate students can be motivated to work independently and gain skills with inquiry-based laboratory experiences. This project will bridge the gap between desired student learning outcomes and current instructional practices. Compared to traditional cookbook-style laboratory experiences, which leave many students unacquainted with scientific methodology and argumentation, inquiry-based experiences provide a richer and more meaningful learning experience. The project will also explore the impact of team teaching on student engagement and learning progress. SUNY-OW accepts a larger number of transfer students and will actively disseminate their findings to their feeder community colleges and other institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will study creative approaches for improving STEM learning and learning environments, with a focus on a research-rich and a skills-rich chemistry laboratory curriculum. The goal is to improve undergraduates' understanding of scientific methodology and argumentation via inquiry-based laboratory teaching and argumentative writing. By integrating students' self-designed projects into teaching laboratories, the project will provide opportunities for students to work independently and to think critically as scientists. Through guided argumentative writing, students' deep thinking will be persistently focused on projects while their knowledge-based understanding develops. The impact of instructor-guided and student-generated inquiries on learning will be examined. This project will generate new evidence regarding effective instruction in the chemistry laboratory, thus leading to a better instructional design in undergraduate chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1611887</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Weinstein-Lloyd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith B Weinstein-Lloyd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lloydj@oldwestbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5168762728</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000138142</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Duncan</FirstName>
<LastName>Quarless</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Duncan A Quarless</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>quarlessd@oldwestbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5168762734</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000188277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruomei</FirstName>
<LastName>Gao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruomei Gao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gaor@oldwestbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5168764224</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000568883</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bright</FirstName>
<LastName>Emenike</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>U</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bright U Emenike</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emenikeb@oldwestbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000702661</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College at Old Westbury</Name>
<CityName>Old Westbury</CityName>
<ZipCode>115680210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5168763167</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 210</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>152606729</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY College at Old Westbury]]></Name>
<CityName>Old Westbury</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>115681717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Store Hill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~296189</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="OutlineElement Ltr BCX8 SCXW98559501"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW98559501 BCX8">This project (Level 1 &ndash; Engaged Student Learning) provided opportunities for undergraduates to design their own experiments and engage in argumentative writing in chemistry laboratories. Scientific practices were promoted through knowledge construction, experimental design and implementation, and experimental error analysis. Two teaching sequences were applied to develop students&rsquo; argumentative abilities: (1) an argumentative writing workshop divided into four modules for conceptual learning and (2) weekly laboratory report writing for knowledge application. The four writing workshop modules guided students through the processes of identifying key components of an argument (evidence, justifications, and claims), selecting appropriate and inappropriate justifications, constructing strong justifications and conclusions, and analyzing experimental errors. Learning was further enhanced through weekly laboratory report writing using students&rsquo; own data and/or observations. To better understand the roles of conceptual learning and inquiry-based practices, we assessed students&rsquo; transformation of knowledge about precision and accuracy in the laboratory components of Introductory Chemistry, Analytical Chemistry, Instrumental Analysis and Physical Chemistry. Student performance in written laboratory reports reveals that repetition of concepts and specific feedback from instructors are essential in knowledge construction. Those instructional models may be adopted in other science laboratory courses or for online teaching without changing the structure of curricula.</p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr BCX8 SCXW98559501"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW98559501 BCX8">The Student Assessment of Their Learning Gains (SALG) demonstrated a growth in understanding course materials and gaining skills. Instructors&rsquo; evaluations reveal that students were challenged but also improved on writing assignments that required scientific arguments. In addition, SUNY College at Old Westbury is a minority-serving institution and has Bachelor and Master programs with salient features of K-12 teacher training. This project not only impacts the learning of students enrolled in chemistry laboratories but also benefits K-12 education in the Long Island area eventually.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Ruomei&nbsp;Gao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project (Level 1 &ndash; Engaged Student Learning) provided opportunities for undergraduates to design their own experiments and engage in argumentative writing in chemistry laboratories. Scientific practices were promoted through knowledge construction, experimental design and implementation, and experimental error analysis. Two teaching sequences were applied to develop students’ argumentative abilities: (1) an argumentative writing workshop divided into four modules for conceptual learning and (2) weekly laboratory report writing for knowledge application. The four writing workshop modules guided students through the processes of identifying key components of an argument (evidence, justifications, and claims), selecting appropriate and inappropriate justifications, constructing strong justifications and conclusions, and analyzing experimental errors. Learning was further enhanced through weekly laboratory report writing using students’ own data and/or observations. To better understand the roles of conceptual learning and inquiry-based practices, we assessed students’ transformation of knowledge about precision and accuracy in the laboratory components of Introductory Chemistry, Analytical Chemistry, Instrumental Analysis and Physical Chemistry. Student performance in written laboratory reports reveals that repetition of concepts and specific feedback from instructors are essential in knowledge construction. Those instructional models may be adopted in other science laboratory courses or for online teaching without changing the structure of curricula.   The Student Assessment of Their Learning Gains (SALG) demonstrated a growth in understanding course materials and gaining skills. Instructors’ evaluations reveal that students were challenged but also improved on writing assignments that required scientific arguments. In addition, SUNY College at Old Westbury is a minority-serving institution and has Bachelor and Master programs with salient features of K-12 teacher training. This project not only impacts the learning of students enrolled in chemistry laboratories but also benefits K-12 education in the Long Island area eventually.           Last Modified: 11/30/2020       Submitted by: Ruomei Gao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
