<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2016</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Postdoctoral Fellow: Jeana Drake&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number 1611943&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2016, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports a research and teaching plan for the Fellow to take transformative approaches to grand challenges in biology that employ biological collections in highly innovative ways. The title of the research plan for this fellowship to Jeana Drake is 'Coral skeleton protein evolution: Using ancient and modern skeletal protein data to elucidate coral evolutionary patterns'. The host institution for this fellowship is the University of California, Los Angeles, and the sponsoring scientist is David Jacobs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research is to develop and test evolutionary models of proteins in corals, and how evolution of these proteins relates to climate change over the past 250 million years. The Fellow is using fossil coral collections from the Triassic, Jurassic, Cretaceous and Tertiary periods, from the American Museum of Natural History and the Smithsonian Institution, and gene sequence data from modern corals housed in university and private aquaria, to study the evolution of coral biomineralization proteins. After employing standard geochemical analyses to confirm the pristine nature of fossil coral specimens, the Fellow is using mass spectrometry to sequence fossil proteins from corals that lived just before or after dramatic climate shifts in the last 250 million years. She is also developing constant evolutionary rate models based on gene sequences from modern corals within the same families as the fossil coral specimens. Finally, the Fellow is testing the validity of these evolutionary rate models using the fossil protein sequences. The Fellow's research examines the evolutionary patterns of corals across climate change events, and will clarify the robustness versus plasticity of individual coral biomineralization proteins.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Fellow is furthering her skills in geochemistry, molecular biology, and bioinformatics, and managing a research project within a multidisciplinary setting. The Fellow is training undergraduate and graduate students in laboratory methods as well as preparation of manuscripts, posters and presentations. She is doing outreach at a local high school to share research concepts and outcomes with students and to include highly motivated students in laboratory work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1611943</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeana</FirstName>
<LastName>Drake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeana Drake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>4157284724</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000709829</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drake                   Jeana</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>914062404</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900957246</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>001Y</Code>
<Text>Collections Postdocs</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The present research achieved several goals stated in the proposal: (1) Fossil stony coral skeletons from several publicly and privately held collections were analyzed to determine preservation of both mineral and endogenous proteins.&nbsp; (2) Four proteins were sequenced from fossil coral skeletons aged 130,000 years.&nbsp; Two of these proteins are known from previously published modern coral skeletal proteomes as well as from four additional modern coral skeletal proteomes generated as part of this research. A manuscript describing this outcome is in the final stages of preparation. &nbsp;&nbsp;Further, and also as part of this project, these two proteins were shown to be good targets for quantitative analysis of differential abundance due to environmental variation.&nbsp; A summary of the quantitative analysis of modern coral skeletal proteins has been shared with colleagues for incorporation into a second manuscript. (3) A methodological framework was established to optimize the choice of fossil specimens from which proteins are extracted for sequencing.&nbsp; This is particularly important as over gram of starting skeletal material is required for the full suite of analyses from x-ray diffraction through protein extraction and sequencing, where the bulk of the starting material requirement is for protein sequencing and nearly all analyses are destructive.&nbsp; A third manuscript describing this outcome is in the final stages of preparation.&nbsp; In total, the present research has been presented at eight conferences, symposia, and guest lectures, with an additional abstract submitted for inclusion in an upcoming coral reefs conference.&nbsp; (4)&nbsp; Nine undergraduate and graduate students at the fellow&rsquo;s host institution, UCLA, plus two undergraduate and one graduate student at other institutions were mentored over the course of this research.&nbsp; (5)&nbsp; Eighteen students at a local public high school have been trained in proteomics and bioinformatics software as part of an afterschool proteomics training course designed specifically for the present research project. 80% of students at this high school identify as black, latinx, or as two or more races, and 90% qualify for free or reduced lunches.&nbsp; Therefore, this project has helped to increase the access to STEM research by students in minority groups.</p> <p>Based on outcomes 1-3 detailed above, additional collaborations have been established to sequence fossil and modern proteomes ranging from more species of stony corals to hydrocorals and soft corals to fish otoliths.&nbsp; These additional projects will continue to serve as vehicles to train undergraduate and graduate college students as well as high school students in basic science research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2019<br>      Modified by: Jeana&nbsp;Drake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The present research achieved several goals stated in the proposal: (1) Fossil stony coral skeletons from several publicly and privately held collections were analyzed to determine preservation of both mineral and endogenous proteins.  (2) Four proteins were sequenced from fossil coral skeletons aged 130,000 years.  Two of these proteins are known from previously published modern coral skeletal proteomes as well as from four additional modern coral skeletal proteomes generated as part of this research. A manuscript describing this outcome is in the final stages of preparation.   Further, and also as part of this project, these two proteins were shown to be good targets for quantitative analysis of differential abundance due to environmental variation.  A summary of the quantitative analysis of modern coral skeletal proteins has been shared with colleagues for incorporation into a second manuscript. (3) A methodological framework was established to optimize the choice of fossil specimens from which proteins are extracted for sequencing.  This is particularly important as over gram of starting skeletal material is required for the full suite of analyses from x-ray diffraction through protein extraction and sequencing, where the bulk of the starting material requirement is for protein sequencing and nearly all analyses are destructive.  A third manuscript describing this outcome is in the final stages of preparation.  In total, the present research has been presented at eight conferences, symposia, and guest lectures, with an additional abstract submitted for inclusion in an upcoming coral reefs conference.  (4)  Nine undergraduate and graduate students at the fellow?s host institution, UCLA, plus two undergraduate and one graduate student at other institutions were mentored over the course of this research.  (5)  Eighteen students at a local public high school have been trained in proteomics and bioinformatics software as part of an afterschool proteomics training course designed specifically for the present research project. 80% of students at this high school identify as black, latinx, or as two or more races, and 90% qualify for free or reduced lunches.  Therefore, this project has helped to increase the access to STEM research by students in minority groups.  Based on outcomes 1-3 detailed above, additional collaborations have been established to sequence fossil and modern proteomes ranging from more species of stony corals to hydrocorals and soft corals to fish otoliths.  These additional projects will continue to serve as vehicles to train undergraduate and graduate college students as well as high school students in basic science research.       Last Modified: 10/10/2019       Submitted by: Jeana Drake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
