<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Construction of DNA Programmed Minimal Cells with Membrane Mechanosensitive Functions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>438990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>438990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drockcli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With advances in synthetic biology, it is now possible to try to build a synthetic cell with the minimum number of components (a minimal cell) in order to understand  what are the essential elements needed to sustain life.  Over the past decade, several approaches to assembling cell analogs using the molecules of life have been proposed. So far, however, no minimal cells capable of basic cell functions have been constructed from scratch, and this objective is still in a distant future. In particular, the construction of a cell-sized genetically programmed lipid vesicle with an active sensory membrane has not been achieved yet. The goal of this project is to construct a minimal cell, consisting of a cell-free expression system encapsulated into a phospholipids vesicle, capable of sensing the environment through its lipid bilayer by expressing mechanosensitive channels. This step, central for synthetic cell engineering, will provide fundamental insights necessary to understand how basic biological functions are created that characterize the link between genotype and phenotype. This highly multidisciplinary work will also provide insights on how to engineer truly functional minimal cell systems that could be useful in other research areas such as biotechnologies and medicine.  Students at all levels will be trained in an interdisciplinary environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The bottom-up construction of complex biochemical systems in vitro is a rapidly growing research area. The proposed work will offer a path towards bottom-up construction of DNA programmed minimal cells with membrane mechanosensitive functions. The research effort is divided into three parts. Genetic programming will be developed to control the activation of in vitro transcription-translation gene circuits from a membrane non-permeable inducer. Mechanosensitive channels such as MscL from E. coli will be incorporated into the phospholipids bilayer of liposomes and the mechanosensitivity will be tested by the activation of a reporter protein. Finally, mechanical activation through the membrane will be coupled to the physical growth of the bilayer by synthesizing lipids from chemical precursors. This work addresses fundamental questions about the integration of molecular parts at the scale of a cell to build biological functions. If successful, the work will address a critical step in the synthesis of cell-sized compartments with active membranes coupled to gene regulation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1612917</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allen Po-Chih</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allen Po-Chih Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>allenliu@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347647719</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619649</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~438990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Period supported:</span>&nbsp;9/1/2016-8/31/2020&nbsp;</p> <p>Research on synthetic cells has grown immensely within the field of bottom-up synthetic biology. Synthetic cells hold the promise of serving as a highly advanced targeted therapeutic platform while also enabling researchers to study cell-like processes&nbsp;<em>in vitro.</em>&nbsp;Many defining characteristics of synthetic cells have been proposed over the years to mimic different cellular processes. While creating a true cell-like entity remains extremely challenging, significant efforts are being made in reconstituting essential cell functions in such systems. One desirable feature of synthetic cells is their ability to interact with and possibly adapt to subsequent changes in their surroundings. Previous studies have demonstrated the ability of engineered systems to respond to changes in their chemical environment. But cells not only detect variations in chemical gradients but also sense different types of mechanical forces. In this project, we worked towards the creation of synthetic cells which can respond to mechanical and chemical stimuli. Using biochemical tools and microfluidic platforms, we developed modular synthetic cells which can be programmed with DNA to impart mechanosensitivity and chemical signaling. We used hypo-osmotic shock to induce an increase in membrane tension to mediate small molecule detection inside synthetic cells thus establishing a 'smart' biosensor which can be activated by external stimulus. By coupling such mechanosensitivity to DNA-based gene circuits, we further developed a synthetic cell which underwent induced gene expression resulting in a changed morphology. We also studied passive transport of graphene quantum dots across the membranes of cell-like lipid vesicles with different lipid compositions which was accurately predicted using computational models developed by the Violi Lab (University of Michigan). This collaborative work led to the development of a predictive model which could be beneficial in designing more effective drug molecules. Additional work in this project led to the investigation of shear force induced changes in shape of synthetic cells and their ability to sense such perturbations which could serve as models for force-sensitive targeted therapeutics through infusion in blood.</p> <p>The project has enabled the training of a PhD student and several undergraduate (6) researchers and a visiting Master's student from University of Strathclyde (Scotland). The PhD student collaborated with another student from Noireaux lab (University of Minnesota) to get trained in the use of&nbsp;<em>E. coli&nbsp;</em>cell-free expression system made in their lab. The PI underwent a sabbatical at the Schwille lab in Max Planck Institute of Biochemistry (Germany) during which the PhD student was invited to learn a different technique for making lipid bilayer vesicles which was later adapted in our lab. The work resulting from this project was presented by the student and PI in several international conferences. The project led to the completion of a PhD degree for this student. One undergraduate student gained significant expertise with several microfluidic and biochemical techniques and aspires to pursue a career in academia. Altogether, three publications, one perspective and one review article resulted directly from this award and another manuscript is under preparation. The PI has given &gt;35 invited seminars and presentations in the US, Europe, and Asia over the duration of this award. The PIs have organized Special Issue on bottom-up synthetic biology, published articles in magazines and organized relevant workshops.</p> <p>In summary, research afforded by this award has major broader impact. It provided training opportunities to graduate and undergraduate researchers that inspired them to pursue careers in science and technology. The dissemination of our work in peer-reviewed publications and through the PI's presentations help promote this research area. Our work has revealed strategies to build synthetic cells whose functions can be controlled by manipulating DNA and can be used as experimental models for studying different cellular phenomena. We anticipate these advances to play a major role in future design of more complex synthetic cells and their use in therapeutic applications with modularity in design and targeted functionalities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Allen Po-Chih&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Period supported: 9/1/2016-8/31/2020   Research on synthetic cells has grown immensely within the field of bottom-up synthetic biology. Synthetic cells hold the promise of serving as a highly advanced targeted therapeutic platform while also enabling researchers to study cell-like processes in vitro. Many defining characteristics of synthetic cells have been proposed over the years to mimic different cellular processes. While creating a true cell-like entity remains extremely challenging, significant efforts are being made in reconstituting essential cell functions in such systems. One desirable feature of synthetic cells is their ability to interact with and possibly adapt to subsequent changes in their surroundings. Previous studies have demonstrated the ability of engineered systems to respond to changes in their chemical environment. But cells not only detect variations in chemical gradients but also sense different types of mechanical forces. In this project, we worked towards the creation of synthetic cells which can respond to mechanical and chemical stimuli. Using biochemical tools and microfluidic platforms, we developed modular synthetic cells which can be programmed with DNA to impart mechanosensitivity and chemical signaling. We used hypo-osmotic shock to induce an increase in membrane tension to mediate small molecule detection inside synthetic cells thus establishing a 'smart' biosensor which can be activated by external stimulus. By coupling such mechanosensitivity to DNA-based gene circuits, we further developed a synthetic cell which underwent induced gene expression resulting in a changed morphology. We also studied passive transport of graphene quantum dots across the membranes of cell-like lipid vesicles with different lipid compositions which was accurately predicted using computational models developed by the Violi Lab (University of Michigan). This collaborative work led to the development of a predictive model which could be beneficial in designing more effective drug molecules. Additional work in this project led to the investigation of shear force induced changes in shape of synthetic cells and their ability to sense such perturbations which could serve as models for force-sensitive targeted therapeutics through infusion in blood.  The project has enabled the training of a PhD student and several undergraduate (6) researchers and a visiting Master's student from University of Strathclyde (Scotland). The PhD student collaborated with another student from Noireaux lab (University of Minnesota) to get trained in the use of E. coli cell-free expression system made in their lab. The PI underwent a sabbatical at the Schwille lab in Max Planck Institute of Biochemistry (Germany) during which the PhD student was invited to learn a different technique for making lipid bilayer vesicles which was later adapted in our lab. The work resulting from this project was presented by the student and PI in several international conferences. The project led to the completion of a PhD degree for this student. One undergraduate student gained significant expertise with several microfluidic and biochemical techniques and aspires to pursue a career in academia. Altogether, three publications, one perspective and one review article resulted directly from this award and another manuscript is under preparation. The PI has given &gt;35 invited seminars and presentations in the US, Europe, and Asia over the duration of this award. The PIs have organized Special Issue on bottom-up synthetic biology, published articles in magazines and organized relevant workshops.  In summary, research afforded by this award has major broader impact. It provided training opportunities to graduate and undergraduate researchers that inspired them to pursue careers in science and technology. The dissemination of our work in peer-reviewed publications and through the PI's presentations help promote this research area. Our work has revealed strategies to build synthetic cells whose functions can be controlled by manipulating DNA and can be used as experimental models for studying different cellular phenomena. We anticipate these advances to play a major role in future design of more complex synthetic cells and their use in therapeutic applications with modularity in design and targeted functionalities.          Last Modified: 09/01/2020       Submitted by: Allen Po-Chih Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
