<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: SpecMax: Spectrum Trading and Harvesting Designs for Multi-Hop Communications in Cognitive Radio Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/23/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>430002.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>430002</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cognitive radio (CR) is a revolutionary paradigm that releases spectrum and enables secondary users (SUs) to opportunistically access under-utilized spectrum. Due to the great economic value of spectrum, CR technology has also promoted many spectrum-trading designs in cognitive radio networks (CRNs). Unfortunately, most existing designs rely on the premise that the SUs hand-held devices have powerful CR capability, which may not be easily embedded into lightweight small-sized radios of SUs' devices. Besides, existing designs mainly focus on per-user based spectrum trading for single-hop communications, and lack deep understanding of multi-hop end-to-end service provision. Moreover, the prevalent idea of choosing the best band makes secondary services vulnerable to interruption due to the returns of primary users. Finally, to facilitate spectrum trading, more accurate information of spectrum availability should be provided. Motivated by these facts, this project aims to construct a framework to investigate the spectrum trading in multi-hop CRNs, which includes the study of (1) designing a novel CRN architecture to facilitate the accessing of SUs without CR capability, (2) extending spectrum trading for multi-hop CR communications, (3) harvesting spectrum under spectrum uncertainty, and (4) constructing a fine-grained mobile spectrum map. The results of this project can advance the state of the art in spectrum trading designs and enrich the scientific knowledge of network designs and network economics. The project is thus crucial to the success of CRNs, which can provide great opportunities for job creation, greater productivity, and economic growth. This project also involves research publications/talks, curriculum development, minority student recruitment, training and mentoring, and outreach to K-12 students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1613661</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miao</FirstName>
<LastName>Pan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miao Pan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mpan2@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137430557</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4800 Calhoun]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~82859</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~84709</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~86617</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~88585</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~87232</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cognitive radio (CR) technology releases the spectrum from shackles of authorized licenses, and enables secondary users (SUs) to opportunistically access to the under-utilized licensed spectrum. Due to the great economic value of spectrum, CR technology has also initiated the spectrum market and promoted many interesting spectrum trading designs in cognitive radio networks (CRNs). Most existing designs rely on the premise that the SUs&rsquo; hand-held devices have powerful CR capability. Unfortunately, CR capability may not be easily embedded into light-weight small-sized radios of SUs&rsquo; devices. Besides, existing spectrum trading approaches lack deep understanding of multi-hop end-to-end service provision. Moreover, considering the uncertain of spectrum supply, the prevalent idea of choosing the best band makes secondary services vulnerable to interruption due to the returns of primary users (PUs). An effective spectrum trading design which can address the challenges above is therefore in dire need.</p> <p><br />In this project, the spectrum trading network architecture and multiple novel spectrum trading designs have been developed to facilitate SUs without CR devices to participate in spectrum trading, and enable economic-robust, multi-hop and privacy preserving spectrum trading under uncertain spectrum supply, in order to effectively improve spectrum utilization and benefit both PUs and SUs in CRNs. The research outcomes have the potential to boost such spectrum trading solutions. Besides, the transformative and interdisciplinary nature of this project's research outcomes will advance the knowledge of wireless communications engineering, and can potentially be used by industry for network development and impact future industrial standardization. Correspondingly, the research outcomes have impact on people's daily lives and further provide greater opportunities for job creation and economic growth.</p> <p><br />Together with a few NSF sponsored projects, this project has partially supported multiple graduate students including four female PhD students. In particular, two female students working on this project have graduated as PhD, and become assistant professors in electrical engineering and/or computer science departments in universities after their graduation, continuing to train the next generation national work force. Multiple MS students and the undergraduate student sponsored by this project continue their PhD study in wireless communications and networking after their graduation. The results of this project have also been disseminated through publications in technical journals, keynote speeches and presentations at conferences, and invited talks at both national and international institutions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Miao&nbsp;Pan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cognitive radio (CR) technology releases the spectrum from shackles of authorized licenses, and enables secondary users (SUs) to opportunistically access to the under-utilized licensed spectrum. Due to the great economic value of spectrum, CR technology has also initiated the spectrum market and promoted many interesting spectrum trading designs in cognitive radio networks (CRNs). Most existing designs rely on the premise that the SUs’ hand-held devices have powerful CR capability. Unfortunately, CR capability may not be easily embedded into light-weight small-sized radios of SUs’ devices. Besides, existing spectrum trading approaches lack deep understanding of multi-hop end-to-end service provision. Moreover, considering the uncertain of spectrum supply, the prevalent idea of choosing the best band makes secondary services vulnerable to interruption due to the returns of primary users (PUs). An effective spectrum trading design which can address the challenges above is therefore in dire need.   In this project, the spectrum trading network architecture and multiple novel spectrum trading designs have been developed to facilitate SUs without CR devices to participate in spectrum trading, and enable economic-robust, multi-hop and privacy preserving spectrum trading under uncertain spectrum supply, in order to effectively improve spectrum utilization and benefit both PUs and SUs in CRNs. The research outcomes have the potential to boost such spectrum trading solutions. Besides, the transformative and interdisciplinary nature of this project's research outcomes will advance the knowledge of wireless communications engineering, and can potentially be used by industry for network development and impact future industrial standardization. Correspondingly, the research outcomes have impact on people's daily lives and further provide greater opportunities for job creation and economic growth.   Together with a few NSF sponsored projects, this project has partially supported multiple graduate students including four female PhD students. In particular, two female students working on this project have graduated as PhD, and become assistant professors in electrical engineering and/or computer science departments in universities after their graduation, continuing to train the next generation national work force. Multiple MS students and the undergraduate student sponsored by this project continue their PhD study in wireless communications and networking after their graduation. The results of this project have also been disseminated through publications in technical journals, keynote speeches and presentations at conferences, and invited talks at both national and international institutions.       Last Modified: 12/05/2020       Submitted by: Miao Pan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
