<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Construction of DNA Programmed Minimal Cells with Membrane Mechanosensitive Functions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>454597.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>454597</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drockcli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With advances in synthetic biology, it is now possible to try to build a synthetic cell with the minimum number of components (a minimal cell) in order to understand  what are the essential elements needed to sustain life.  Over the past decade, several approaches to assembling cell analogs using the molecules of life have been proposed. So far, however, no minimal cells capable of basic cell functions have been constructed from scratch, and this objective is still in a distant future. In particular, the construction of a cell-sized genetically programmed lipid vesicle with an active sensory membrane has not been achieved yet. The goal of this project is to construct a minimal cell, consisting of a cell-free expression system encapsulated into a phospholipids vesicle, capable of sensing the environment through its lipid bilayer by expressing mechanosensitive channels. This step, central for synthetic cell engineering, will provide fundamental insights necessary to understand how basic biological functions are created that characterize the link between genotype and phenotype. This highly multidisciplinary work will also provide insights on how to engineer truly functional minimal cell systems that could be useful in other research areas such as biotechnologies and medicine.  Students at all levels will be trained in an interdisciplinary environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The bottom-up construction of complex biochemical systems in vitro is a rapidly growing research area. The proposed work will offer a path towards bottom-up construction of DNA programmed minimal cells with membrane mechanosensitive functions. The research effort is divided into three parts. Genetic programming will be developed to control the activation of in vitro transcription-translation gene circuits from a membrane non-permeable inducer. Mechanosensitive channels such as MscL from E. coli will be incorporated into the phospholipids bilayer of liposomes and the mechanosensitivity will be tested by the activation of a reporter protein. Finally, mechanical activation through the membrane will be coupled to the physical growth of the bilayer by synthesizing lipids from chemical precursors. This work addresses fundamental questions about the integration of molecular parts at the scale of a cell to build biological functions. If successful, the work will address a critical step in the synthesis of cell-sized compartments with active membranes coupled to gene regulation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1613677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
<LastName>Noireaux</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vincent Noireaux</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>noireaux@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126246589</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000155968</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[115 Union Street SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~454597</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Overview:</span></strong></p> <p>The bottom-up construction of synthetic biological cells has become a major goal of multidisciplinary research. Over the past decade, several approaches to assembling cell analogs using the molecules of life have been proposed. So far, however, minimal cells capable of basic cell functions have been difficult to build from scratch, and this objective is still in a distant future. In particular, the construction of a cell-sized genetically programmed liposome with an active sensory membrane capable of responding to mechanical stresses has not been achieved yet. The goal of this project was to construct a minimal cell, consisting of a cell-free expression system encapsulated into cell-sized phospholipids vesicle, capable of sensing the environment through its lipid bilayer by expressing and dynamically synthesizing the mechanosensitive channel MscL from the bacterium <em>E. coli</em>. Achieving such step, central for synthetic cell engineering, provides fundamental insights necessary to understand how basic biological functions are created that characterize the link between genotype and phenotype. This highly multidisciplinary work also provides insights on how to engineer truly functional minimal cell systems that could be useful in other research areas such as biotechnologies and medicine. Indeed, engineering mechanically robust cell-sized compartments capable of sensing the physical and chemical environment is an essential step towards making synthetic cells capable of carrying functions that address societal issues such as those related to bioremediation or human health. Prior to this award, only a few synthetic cell systems loaded with executable genetic information and harboring membrane sensors were reported because developing active functions at the membrane of synthetic cells is still very challenging for several reasons: (i) characterizing the function of membrane proteins in synthetic cells is difficult as it requires developing specific assays, (ii) expressing membrane proteins into synthetic cells depends on many factors that have not been characterized yet, such as the relationship between the lipid composition of the membrane and the function of the protein.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Achievements and outcomes:</span></strong></p> <p>In our first work during this award, we constructed a synthetic cell system capable of responding to changes in the osmotic pressure of the outer solution, a capability essential to create mechanically robust synthetic cells. This system consisted of expressing the <em>E. coli</em> mechanosensitive membrane protein MscL using a cell-free transcription-translation system (TXTL) encapsulated into synthetic liposomes of diameters 1-20 &micro;m comparable to real living cells. TXTL enables the dynamical synthesis of proteins from DNA templates as in real living cells. Upon osmotic stress, the dynamically synthesized MscL transmembrane channels open up due to the tension in the lipid membrane so as to decrease the tension in the lipid bilayer. Direct visualization of this mechanism was possible using fluorescence microscopy by monitoring the fluorescence of a calcium biosensor and the leak of polymers of various sizes. We demonstrated two different gene circuit architectures that exhibit different reaction kinetics that are preserved across length scale from bulk reactions to micron-sized encapsulated droplets or vesicles.</p> <p>The second part of the research consisted of building an adaptive synthetic cell based on mechanosensing, biosensing, and inducible gene circuits. We built a synthetic cell system capable of responding to environmental stimuli via the MscL mechanosensitive channel and subsequently synthesizing proteins responsible for cell mechanical robustness, specifically the production of the <em>E. coli </em>cytoskeleton protein MreB. The synthesis of GFP (used as a fluorescent marker of cell-free expression) and MreB was controlled by the lac repressor and a Lac01/&sigma;28 amplifier, creating an AND gate consisting of the chemical inducer IPTG and the hypo-osmotic conditions. We showed that when MreB is expressed, it readily associates with the inner membrane of the liposomes, forming a cortex-like structure. The synthetic cell developed in this work can be further expanded by leveraging orthogonal TXTL reactions to mediate simultaneous or sequential induction with different membrane-impermeable molecules, thus providing modularity in the number of different systems that can be reconstituted within the same compartment. To our knowledge, this is the first work that couples an external stimulus to inducible gene expression by way of mechanosensitivity. Our experiments provide information, including positive and negative results, on how to integrate multiple biological mechanisms into a synthetic cell system involving membrane properties and inducible gene expression. The experimental approach presented in this work could be used to learn the dynamics of multi-protein interactions or step-by-step assembly in order to better understand the complexities of real cells.</p> <p>During the award, two graduate students were trained on this highly multidisciplinary project, which was the core of their PhDs. This research was also showcased at the Cold Spring Harbor laboratory summer course Synthetic Biology, for which Vincent Noireaux was an instructor. The results obtained during this project were presented at more than 20 conferences, in either talks or posters.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Vincent&nbsp;Noireaux</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview:  The bottom-up construction of synthetic biological cells has become a major goal of multidisciplinary research. Over the past decade, several approaches to assembling cell analogs using the molecules of life have been proposed. So far, however, minimal cells capable of basic cell functions have been difficult to build from scratch, and this objective is still in a distant future. In particular, the construction of a cell-sized genetically programmed liposome with an active sensory membrane capable of responding to mechanical stresses has not been achieved yet. The goal of this project was to construct a minimal cell, consisting of a cell-free expression system encapsulated into cell-sized phospholipids vesicle, capable of sensing the environment through its lipid bilayer by expressing and dynamically synthesizing the mechanosensitive channel MscL from the bacterium E. coli. Achieving such step, central for synthetic cell engineering, provides fundamental insights necessary to understand how basic biological functions are created that characterize the link between genotype and phenotype. This highly multidisciplinary work also provides insights on how to engineer truly functional minimal cell systems that could be useful in other research areas such as biotechnologies and medicine. Indeed, engineering mechanically robust cell-sized compartments capable of sensing the physical and chemical environment is an essential step towards making synthetic cells capable of carrying functions that address societal issues such as those related to bioremediation or human health. Prior to this award, only a few synthetic cell systems loaded with executable genetic information and harboring membrane sensors were reported because developing active functions at the membrane of synthetic cells is still very challenging for several reasons: (i) characterizing the function of membrane proteins in synthetic cells is difficult as it requires developing specific assays, (ii) expressing membrane proteins into synthetic cells depends on many factors that have not been characterized yet, such as the relationship between the lipid composition of the membrane and the function of the protein.     Achievements and outcomes:  In our first work during this award, we constructed a synthetic cell system capable of responding to changes in the osmotic pressure of the outer solution, a capability essential to create mechanically robust synthetic cells. This system consisted of expressing the E. coli mechanosensitive membrane protein MscL using a cell-free transcription-translation system (TXTL) encapsulated into synthetic liposomes of diameters 1-20 &micro;m comparable to real living cells. TXTL enables the dynamical synthesis of proteins from DNA templates as in real living cells. Upon osmotic stress, the dynamically synthesized MscL transmembrane channels open up due to the tension in the lipid membrane so as to decrease the tension in the lipid bilayer. Direct visualization of this mechanism was possible using fluorescence microscopy by monitoring the fluorescence of a calcium biosensor and the leak of polymers of various sizes. We demonstrated two different gene circuit architectures that exhibit different reaction kinetics that are preserved across length scale from bulk reactions to micron-sized encapsulated droplets or vesicles.  The second part of the research consisted of building an adaptive synthetic cell based on mechanosensing, biosensing, and inducible gene circuits. We built a synthetic cell system capable of responding to environmental stimuli via the MscL mechanosensitive channel and subsequently synthesizing proteins responsible for cell mechanical robustness, specifically the production of the E. coli cytoskeleton protein MreB. The synthesis of GFP (used as a fluorescent marker of cell-free expression) and MreB was controlled by the lac repressor and a Lac01/&sigma;28 amplifier, creating an AND gate consisting of the chemical inducer IPTG and the hypo-osmotic conditions. We showed that when MreB is expressed, it readily associates with the inner membrane of the liposomes, forming a cortex-like structure. The synthetic cell developed in this work can be further expanded by leveraging orthogonal TXTL reactions to mediate simultaneous or sequential induction with different membrane-impermeable molecules, thus providing modularity in the number of different systems that can be reconstituted within the same compartment. To our knowledge, this is the first work that couples an external stimulus to inducible gene expression by way of mechanosensitivity. Our experiments provide information, including positive and negative results, on how to integrate multiple biological mechanisms into a synthetic cell system involving membrane properties and inducible gene expression. The experimental approach presented in this work could be used to learn the dynamics of multi-protein interactions or step-by-step assembly in order to better understand the complexities of real cells.  During the award, two graduate students were trained on this highly multidisciplinary project, which was the core of their PhDs. This research was also showcased at the Cold Spring Harbor laboratory summer course Synthetic Biology, for which Vincent Noireaux was an instructor. The results obtained during this project were presented at more than 20 conferences, in either talks or posters.       Last Modified: 09/01/2020       Submitted by: Vincent Noireaux]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
