<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Prague Topology Symposium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Topology is a branch of mathematics which investigates qualitative aspects of geometry and analysis through an abstractions of notions such as limits, continuity, connectedness, and convergence.  This subject is central to modern mathematics and has a rich history stretching back more than a century. TOPOSYM is a series of international topology conferences held in Prague, Czech Republic, in a five- year cycle since 1961. The conference has long served as a geographic and intellectual meeting point. On one hand it has a large attendance both from North America (and the US in particular) and from Europe (and Eastern Europe in particular). On the other, a large cross section of the more analytical side of topology is represented at the meeting. The Twelfth Symposium on General Topology (TOPOSYM 2016) will be held July 25-29, 2016 in Prague, Czech Republic, under the auspices of the Institute of Mathematics of the Czech Academy of Sciences and the Faculty of Mathematics and Physics of the Charles University. This grant will support the US based participants who attend the symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference covers a broad range of topics on the more analytical side of topology:  general and set-theoretic topology, descriptive set theory, continuum theory, topological dynamics, topology in functional analysis and algebra, and categorical topology. The conference will contain invited lectures by many leaders in the field of general and set-theoretic topology: A. Arhangel'skii, L. Aurichi, D. Dikranjan, A. Dow, M. Hrusak, O. Kalenda, A. Kechris, P. Koszmider, M. Krupski, W. Kubis, A. Kwiatkowska, J. Lopez-Abad, V. Martinez de la Vega, J. Melleray, J. van Mill, A. Miller, J. Moore, C. Mouron, L. Nguyen Van The, L. Oversteegen, C. Rosendal, M. Sabok, S. Solecki, L. Soukup, M. Tkachenko, S. Todorcevic, T. Usuba, B. Weiss. The primary goal of the conference is to aid in the dissemination of the knowledge of these speakers. In addition to this, collecting such a group of experts at a meeting will inevitably lead to new collaborations and the furthering of basic research in the field of topology.&lt;br/&gt;The conference website is at http://www.toposym.cz/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1613386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin T Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>justin@math.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072554185</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosendal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christian Rosendal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rosendal@math.uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129963041</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489292</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supported US based participants travel to attend the 2016 Prague Topology Symposium (TOPOSYM).&nbsp; TOPOSYM is a long running conference series in  Prague specializing in topology and its interactions with set theory,  combinatorics, dynamics, and functional analysis.&nbsp; The conference takes place every five years in Prague, Czech Republic and has traditionally served as a meeting point between the East and the West.&nbsp; The 2016 meeting was very broadly attended: there were 217 participants from 40 countries on 6 continents.&nbsp; The conference featured 130 talks out of which 28 were longer invited lectures.</p> <p>The topics represented in these invited lectures ranged from set theoretical and combinatorial aspects of general topology, abstract general topology to pure descriptive set theory and the topological dynamics of Polish group actions, including its applications to the study of planar continua. Thus, the conference provided a very broad overview of the current research in the field along with connections to very classical problems within general topology.</p> <p>Of the participants, 34 were from the US.&nbsp; The grant supported 22 participants based at US institutions:&nbsp; Jeffrey Bergfalk, Nathan Carlson, Xiao Chang, Andrew Cooper, Tadek Dobrowolski, Alan Dow, Paul Gartside, Patrick Hartley, Chuan Liu, John Mayer, Paul McKenney, Arnold Miller, Justin Moore, Chris Mouron, Lex Oversteegen, Krzystof Plotka, Radmila Sazdanovic, Iian Smythe, Slawomir Solecki, Jerry Vaughan, Jindrich Zapletal, and Joseph Zielinski<span>.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Christian&nbsp;Rosendal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supported US based participants travel to attend the 2016 Prague Topology Symposium (TOPOSYM).  TOPOSYM is a long running conference series in  Prague specializing in topology and its interactions with set theory,  combinatorics, dynamics, and functional analysis.  The conference takes place every five years in Prague, Czech Republic and has traditionally served as a meeting point between the East and the West.  The 2016 meeting was very broadly attended: there were 217 participants from 40 countries on 6 continents.  The conference featured 130 talks out of which 28 were longer invited lectures.  The topics represented in these invited lectures ranged from set theoretical and combinatorial aspects of general topology, abstract general topology to pure descriptive set theory and the topological dynamics of Polish group actions, including its applications to the study of planar continua. Thus, the conference provided a very broad overview of the current research in the field along with connections to very classical problems within general topology.  Of the participants, 34 were from the US.  The grant supported 22 participants based at US institutions:  Jeffrey Bergfalk, Nathan Carlson, Xiao Chang, Andrew Cooper, Tadek Dobrowolski, Alan Dow, Paul Gartside, Patrick Hartley, Chuan Liu, John Mayer, Paul McKenney, Arnold Miller, Justin Moore, Chris Mouron, Lex Oversteegen, Krzystof Plotka, Radmila Sazdanovic, Iian Smythe, Slawomir Solecki, Jerry Vaughan, Jindrich Zapletal, and Joseph Zielinski.       Last Modified: 04/24/2017       Submitted by: Christian Rosendal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
