<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Singular limits with geometric effects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>280000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>280000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Embid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pembid@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924859</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the ongoing research program of the Principal Investigator on the mathematical analysis of some problems arising in engineering and applied science, in particular involving fluids in thin domains and thin elastic structures.  The Principal Investigator will combine techniques from several areas of mathematics to study certain engineering design problems.  These problems are linked by their "singular limits" context and the fact that their solutions are tuned to a variable geometry setting or to a-posteriori obtained geometrical constraints.  The topics that will be tackled fall into four categories: (1) dimension reduction in fluid dynamics (e.g., determining effective two-dimensional models for the behavior of a fluid in a thin domain), (2) modeling and analysis of the shape of a growing body (as in various contexts in biology), (3) rigidity and flexibility of elastic prestrained materials (as caused, for example, by inhomogeneous growth or swelling or shrinkage), (4) energy scaling regimes in elasto-plastic materials (for which deformations are irreversible beyond a certain point).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The following analytical techniques will be investigated: (1) dimension reduction and homogenization of compressible Navier-Stokes equations using relative entropy and scaling of the Korn and the conformal Korn inequalities in thin domains, (2) a novel "controlled growth" model, due to A. Bressan, that couples the partial differential equation for the transport of morphogen-producing cells (in cellular biology) with two constrained minimization problems for the morphogen concentration and the growth velocity, (3) variational models in prestrained elasticity in the presence of the Monge-Ampere constraint without any a-priori assumption on the structure of its minimizers (such as convexity, higher regularity, or boundary conditions) studied using convex integration, (4) dimension reduction via Gamma-convergence in the context of elasto-plasticity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1613153</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marta</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewicka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marta Lewicka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lewicka@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248375</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297521</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~280000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The most important outcomes of this project are summarized as the following mathematical findings, whose details were presented in the indicated papers:</p> <p>In paper <strong>"Quantitative immersability of Riemann metrics and the infinite hierarchy of prestrained shell models" (Lewicka)</strong>, we related the following two important contexts: (i) Given a Riemann metric on a thin 3d film, we posed the question of what is the infimum of the averaged pointwise deficit of an immersion from being an orientation preserving isometric immersion of the metric, over all weakly regular immersions. This deficit is measured by the non-Euclidean energies which can be seen as modifications of the classical nonlinear three-dimensional elasticity. (ii) We completed the scaling analysis of the non-Euclidean energies in the context of dimension reduction as the film's thickness goes to 0, and the derivation of their Gamma-limits in all energy regimes beyond bending. We showed the energy quantisation and identified conditions for the validity of each scaling, in terms of the vanishing of Riemann curvatures up to appropriate orders, and in terms of the matched isometry expansions. We also establish the asymptotic behaviour of the minimizing immersions in the limit of vanishing thickness.&nbsp;</p> <p>In paper <strong>"Random Tug of War games for the p-Laplacian" (Lewicka)</strong>, we proposed a new finite difference approximation to the Dirichlet problem for the homogeneous p-Laplace equation posed on an N-dimensional domain, in connection with the Tug of War games with noise. Our game and the related mean-value expansion, superposes the &ldquo;deterministic averages&rdquo; taken overballs, with the &ldquo;stochastic averages&rdquo; taken over N-dimensional ellipsoids whose aspect ratio depends on N, p and whose orientations span all directions while determining inf / sup on the deterministic averages. We showed that the unique solutions of the related dynamic programming principle coincide with the well-defined game values. Our game has thus the min/max property: the order of supremizing the outcomes over strategies of one player and infimizing over strategies of their opponent, is immaterial. We further showed that domains satisfying appropriate boundary regularity condition are game regular in this context, i.e. the family of the aforementioned solutions converges uniformly to the unique viscosity solution of the Dirichlet problem.</p> <p>In paper "<strong>A model of controlled growth" (Bressan-Lewicka)</strong>, we considered a free boundary problem for a system of PDEs, modeling the growth of a biological tissue. A morphogen, controlling volume growth, is produced by specific cells and then diffused and absorbed throughout the domain. The geometric shape of the growing tissue is determined by the instantaneous minimization of an elastic deformation energy, subject to a constraint on the volumetric growth. For an initial domain with regular boundary, our main result established the local existence and uniqueness of a classical solution, up to a rigid motion.</p> <p>In paper <strong>"Convex integration for the Monge-Ampere equation in two dimensions" (Lewicka- Pakzad)</strong>, we focused on the questions of flexibility and rigidity of solutions to the Monge-Ampere equation which arise as a natural geometrical constraint in prestrained nonlinear elasticity. In particular, we proved existence of degenerate i.e. &ldquo;flexible&rdquo; weak solutions constructed through methods of convex integration "a la Nash &amp; Kuiper" and establish the related h-principle for the Monge-Ampere equation in two dimensions. These solutions appear at low Holder regularity exponents. We also showed rigidity at sufficiently large Holder exponents.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/08/2021<br>      Modified by: Marta&nbsp;Lewicka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The most important outcomes of this project are summarized as the following mathematical findings, whose details were presented in the indicated papers:  In paper "Quantitative immersability of Riemann metrics and the infinite hierarchy of prestrained shell models" (Lewicka), we related the following two important contexts: (i) Given a Riemann metric on a thin 3d film, we posed the question of what is the infimum of the averaged pointwise deficit of an immersion from being an orientation preserving isometric immersion of the metric, over all weakly regular immersions. This deficit is measured by the non-Euclidean energies which can be seen as modifications of the classical nonlinear three-dimensional elasticity. (ii) We completed the scaling analysis of the non-Euclidean energies in the context of dimension reduction as the film's thickness goes to 0, and the derivation of their Gamma-limits in all energy regimes beyond bending. We showed the energy quantisation and identified conditions for the validity of each scaling, in terms of the vanishing of Riemann curvatures up to appropriate orders, and in terms of the matched isometry expansions. We also establish the asymptotic behaviour of the minimizing immersions in the limit of vanishing thickness.   In paper "Random Tug of War games for the p-Laplacian" (Lewicka), we proposed a new finite difference approximation to the Dirichlet problem for the homogeneous p-Laplace equation posed on an N-dimensional domain, in connection with the Tug of War games with noise. Our game and the related mean-value expansion, superposes the "deterministic averages" taken overballs, with the "stochastic averages" taken over N-dimensional ellipsoids whose aspect ratio depends on N, p and whose orientations span all directions while determining inf / sup on the deterministic averages. We showed that the unique solutions of the related dynamic programming principle coincide with the well-defined game values. Our game has thus the min/max property: the order of supremizing the outcomes over strategies of one player and infimizing over strategies of their opponent, is immaterial. We further showed that domains satisfying appropriate boundary regularity condition are game regular in this context, i.e. the family of the aforementioned solutions converges uniformly to the unique viscosity solution of the Dirichlet problem.  In paper "A model of controlled growth" (Bressan-Lewicka), we considered a free boundary problem for a system of PDEs, modeling the growth of a biological tissue. A morphogen, controlling volume growth, is produced by specific cells and then diffused and absorbed throughout the domain. The geometric shape of the growing tissue is determined by the instantaneous minimization of an elastic deformation energy, subject to a constraint on the volumetric growth. For an initial domain with regular boundary, our main result established the local existence and uniqueness of a classical solution, up to a rigid motion.  In paper "Convex integration for the Monge-Ampere equation in two dimensions" (Lewicka- Pakzad), we focused on the questions of flexibility and rigidity of solutions to the Monge-Ampere equation which arise as a natural geometrical constraint in prestrained nonlinear elasticity. In particular, we proved existence of degenerate i.e. "flexible" weak solutions constructed through methods of convex integration "a la Nash &amp; Kuiper" and establish the related h-principle for the Monge-Ampere equation in two dimensions. These solutions appear at low Holder regularity exponents. We also showed rigidity at sufficiently large Holder exponents.       Last Modified: 04/08/2021       Submitted by: Marta Lewicka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
