<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:Improving Understanding of Magma Storage and Transport Prior to the Minoan eruption at Santorini Volcano</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding the timescales of magma storage and transport beneath volcanoes is vital to hazard evaluation and risk mitigation. Several recent studies have used diffusion chronometry at Santorini volcano (Greece) to identify the timescales associated with final magma chamber assembly prior to the catastrophic ~1628 BC ?Minoan? eruption. An intriguing aspect of these studies is that the timescale estimates appear to vary depending on the mineral that is used. Orthopyroxene (Opx) crystals suggest very short timescales ranging from days up to ~30 yrs, whereas clinopyroxene (Cpx) crystals give much longer timescales of up to several thousands of years. This project will test a hypothesis that the Cpx have a deeper origin (thus a longer history) in the Santorini magmatic system than the Opx. If this is the case, the Cpx timescales are recording a more complete story of the magmatic processes related to the Minoan magma than the Opx, which only retrieve the final assembly of the pre-eruptive magma chamber. This research will be conducted at the Earth Observatory of Singapore (EOS) with the guidance and technical expertise of Dr. Fidel Costa, a leading researcher in the study of magmatic timescales and techniques used in this project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The pyroxenes will be analyzed for a range of trace element abundances via laser ablation inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (LA-ICP-MS) with a 193 nm Photon Machines laser and a Thermo quadrupole mass spectrometer located at the EOS. Using existing data on trace element partitioning between pyroxenes, the Minoan Cpx and Opx will be tested to examine: (1) whether they grew in equilibrium with each other, (2) whether they grew in equilibrium with the glass matrix (suggesting crystallization in a shallow reservoir) and (3) the equilibrium conditions (notably the pressure) of crystallization for each pyroxene. It is expected that Cpx will be in disequilibrium with respect to Opx and the glass, and will have a higher equilibrium pressure than that of Opx. The outcomes of this project will have implications for the model of magmatic storage at Santorini, the study of timescales of large explosive volcanic eruptions in general and for the technique of Fe-Mg diffusion chronometry in pyroxenes as a tool for understanding the timescales of magma chamber development and the behavior of active volcanic systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the National Research Foundation of Singapore.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1613887</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Taya</FirstName>
<LastName>Flaherty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Taya T Flaherty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>4125924673</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Flaherty                Taya           T</Name>
<CityName>Glenshaw</CityName>
<ZipCode>151163033</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Flaherty                Taya           T]]></Name>
<CityName>Glenshaw</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>151163033</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5927</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This study focused on constraining the timescales of final magma chamber assembly before the ~1628 BC caldera-forming &lsquo;Minoan&rsquo; eruption of Santorini by further investigating the previous application of a geochemical technique called &ldquo;diffusion chronometry&rdquo;, a method in which high-temperature magmatic residence timescales are calculated by modelling the extent of diffusive exchange across chemical zones in erupted crystals. The P.I. used this technique during her Master&rsquo;s research, focusing on Fe-Mg interdiffusion modelling in orthopyroxene (opx) and clinopyroxene (cpx) minerals from the Minoan eruption; however, a large discrepancy in timescales of up to three orders of magnitude difference was found, depending on the mineral used. The resolution of such a timescale difference is important implications for risk management, particularly for interpreting signs of future unrest at Santorini volcano. We argued that the timescale inconsistency was either due to errors in the diffusion modelling approaches or to a different crystallization and transport history for the orthopyroxene and clinopyroxene crystals within the Santorini magmatic system. Correct interpretation of diffusion chronometry timescale results relies on an assumption that minerals have a relatively short and uncomplicated history in the magmatic system; therefore, it was necessary that we investigate the origins of the opx and cpx crystals to test the latter hypothesis.</p> <p>To better understand the conditions of crystallization for each mineral, a detailed trace element study of the pyroxenes was undertaken by the P.I. at the host institution under the supervision of experts in this type of study. The P.I. was trained by experienced personnel on state-of-the-art laser ablation inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (LA-ICP-MS) instruments, as well as in using other techniques and relevant software for understanding the conditions of mineral crystallization. High-quality trace element data was obtained from opx and cpx crystals and, using published data on the known partitioning of trace elements between pyroxenes during their growth, the nature of their origins was explored.</p> <p>The trace element data was very insightful and gave many interesting clues about the crystallization history of the pyroxenes. Additionally, during the time spent at the host location, a journal article containing a new experimentally-determined rate of diffusion for opx was accepted for publication. When incorporating this new diffusion rate into our calculations, timescales yielded by diffusion chronometry in opx increased such that the timescale discrepancy from the two minerals significantly decreased. Combined with further study of the chemical zoning of the crystals and refinement of the diffusion modelling techniques used, we successfully constrained the timescales of pre-eruptive magma chamber construction prior to the Minoan eruption to starting ~500 years prior to eruption, and rapidly accelerating within the final ~50-100 years.</p> <p>These geologically very short timescales have important implications for our understanding of the Santorini volcanic system and similar systems also capable of large, explosive eruptions. Our timescale results have been recently submitted for review in a high-impact, international journal; meanwhile, the pyroxene trace element data will continue to be of use to the P.I. in her Ph.D. research project on recent eruptions of Santorini and will be published at a later date as part of this larger study.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Taya&nbsp;T&nbsp;Flaherty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This study focused on constraining the timescales of final magma chamber assembly before the ~1628 BC caldera-forming ?Minoan? eruption of Santorini by further investigating the previous application of a geochemical technique called "diffusion chronometry", a method in which high-temperature magmatic residence timescales are calculated by modelling the extent of diffusive exchange across chemical zones in erupted crystals. The P.I. used this technique during her Master?s research, focusing on Fe-Mg interdiffusion modelling in orthopyroxene (opx) and clinopyroxene (cpx) minerals from the Minoan eruption; however, a large discrepancy in timescales of up to three orders of magnitude difference was found, depending on the mineral used. The resolution of such a timescale difference is important implications for risk management, particularly for interpreting signs of future unrest at Santorini volcano. We argued that the timescale inconsistency was either due to errors in the diffusion modelling approaches or to a different crystallization and transport history for the orthopyroxene and clinopyroxene crystals within the Santorini magmatic system. Correct interpretation of diffusion chronometry timescale results relies on an assumption that minerals have a relatively short and uncomplicated history in the magmatic system; therefore, it was necessary that we investigate the origins of the opx and cpx crystals to test the latter hypothesis.  To better understand the conditions of crystallization for each mineral, a detailed trace element study of the pyroxenes was undertaken by the P.I. at the host institution under the supervision of experts in this type of study. The P.I. was trained by experienced personnel on state-of-the-art laser ablation inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (LA-ICP-MS) instruments, as well as in using other techniques and relevant software for understanding the conditions of mineral crystallization. High-quality trace element data was obtained from opx and cpx crystals and, using published data on the known partitioning of trace elements between pyroxenes during their growth, the nature of their origins was explored.  The trace element data was very insightful and gave many interesting clues about the crystallization history of the pyroxenes. Additionally, during the time spent at the host location, a journal article containing a new experimentally-determined rate of diffusion for opx was accepted for publication. When incorporating this new diffusion rate into our calculations, timescales yielded by diffusion chronometry in opx increased such that the timescale discrepancy from the two minerals significantly decreased. Combined with further study of the chemical zoning of the crystals and refinement of the diffusion modelling techniques used, we successfully constrained the timescales of pre-eruptive magma chamber construction prior to the Minoan eruption to starting ~500 years prior to eruption, and rapidly accelerating within the final ~50-100 years.  These geologically very short timescales have important implications for our understanding of the Santorini volcanic system and similar systems also capable of large, explosive eruptions. Our timescale results have been recently submitted for review in a high-impact, international journal; meanwhile, the pyroxene trace element data will continue to be of use to the P.I. in her Ph.D. research project on recent eruptions of Santorini and will be published at a later date as part of this larger study.           Last Modified: 07/06/2017       Submitted by: Taya T Flaherty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
