<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Sedimentary Record of Typhoon Ketsana from Vietnam: Implications for Long-Term Tropical Cyclon</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A better understanding of tropical cyclone processes is imperative in order to predict and mitigate the effects of similar future storms on the environment and expanding coastal communities. Southeast Asia, in particular, is susceptible to frequent typhoons and severe damage, and rapidly expanding populations tend to settle on the coasts where there is concentrated economic activity, exacerbating the negative consequences of coastal hazards. The objective of this research is to analyze sediment deposits left by the storm surge associated with Typhoon Ketsana on the Vietnam coast near Da Nang in 2009. Microfossil data will be combined with physical sedimentological data to characterize the impacts of the tropical cyclone on Vietnam. This project will improve understanding of tropical cyclone inundation characteristics and impacts and contribute to more accurate risk assessment and coastal hazard planning for dense populations in coastal communities. Research will be conducted at the Earth Observatory of Singapore, Nanyang Technological University and will be supervised by Assistant Professor Adam Switzer, who is an internationally recognized expert in tsunami and storm deposits. The Earth Observatory of Singapore is in an ideal location to study tropical cyclone events with state of the art facilities necessary to complete this research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Coastal sediments archive geologic evidence of tropical cyclones and these sedimentary deposits improve our understanding of landfalling storm processes. The documentation of the geological evidence of this catastrophic marine inundation will contribute to a better understanding of tropical cyclones and their associated processes. Microfossil (foraminifera) composition of the deposits and physical sedimentological data will be compared with samples collected from the beach face and offshore. A combination of foraminiferal taxonomy and taphonomy data for the samples collected will assist in the analysis of the marine inundation event of Typhoon Ketsana. The coastal stratigraphic record in Vietnam can be compared with other depositional records from tropical cyclones to help calibrate the characteristics of past storm events in sediment records. Characterization of tropical cyclone events is immensely important for advancing knowledge and understanding within geologic, oceanographic, and environmental fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the National Research Foundation of Singapore.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1613879</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Walker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer S Walker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6109559634</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710757</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Walker                  Jennifer       S</Name>
<CityName>New Brunswick</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018521</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Walker                  Jennifer       S]]></Name>
<CityName>New Brunswick</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>089018521</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5927</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coastal sediments archive geologic evidence of tropical cyclones and these sedimentary deposits improve our understanding of landfalling storm processes. The objective of this project was to analyze sediment deposits left by the storm surge associated with Typhoon Ketsana on the Vietnam coast near Da Nang in 2009 and characterize the sedimentological and environmental impacts of this tropical cyclone. The documentation of the geological evidence of catastrophic marine inundation events will contribute to a better understanding of tropical cyclones and their associated processes.</p> <p>Microfossil and physical sedimentological data analysis are used to characterize the impacts of Typhoon Ketsana. Microfossil composition of the deposits and physical sedimentological data are compared with samples collected from the beach face and offshore. Distinct microfossil assemblages were found within surface lagoon and marine samples, as well as within sediment core samples. Additional microfossil data and statistical analysis will contribute to the specific characterization of the marine inundation event associated with Typhoon Ketsana. Finally, the coastal stratigraphic record in Vietnam can be compared with other depositional records from tropical cyclones to help calibrate the characteristics of past storm events in sediment records.</p> <p>Overall, the combination of physical sedimentology and microfossil analysis of coastal sediment sequences allows identification and characterization of storms. Characterization of tropical cyclone events is immensely important for advancing knowledge and understanding within geologic, oceanographic, and environmental fields. A better understanding of tropical cyclone processes is imperative in order to predict and mitigate the effects of similar future storms on the environment and expanding coastal communities. Additional knowledge of coastal storm deposits will contribute to more accurate estimates of coastal risk assessment and hazards.&nbsp;Southeast Asia is susceptible to frequent typhoons and severe damage, and rapidly expanding populations tend to settle on the coasts where there is concentrated economic activity, exacerbating the negative consequences of coastal hazards. The results of this research can be combined with the findings from other researchers and institutions and be used by local government and non-academic stakeholders in the region for effective coastal planning and education of coastal communities to better prepare for future tropical cyclone events.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;S&nbsp;Walker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coastal sediments archive geologic evidence of tropical cyclones and these sedimentary deposits improve our understanding of landfalling storm processes. The objective of this project was to analyze sediment deposits left by the storm surge associated with Typhoon Ketsana on the Vietnam coast near Da Nang in 2009 and characterize the sedimentological and environmental impacts of this tropical cyclone. The documentation of the geological evidence of catastrophic marine inundation events will contribute to a better understanding of tropical cyclones and their associated processes.  Microfossil and physical sedimentological data analysis are used to characterize the impacts of Typhoon Ketsana. Microfossil composition of the deposits and physical sedimentological data are compared with samples collected from the beach face and offshore. Distinct microfossil assemblages were found within surface lagoon and marine samples, as well as within sediment core samples. Additional microfossil data and statistical analysis will contribute to the specific characterization of the marine inundation event associated with Typhoon Ketsana. Finally, the coastal stratigraphic record in Vietnam can be compared with other depositional records from tropical cyclones to help calibrate the characteristics of past storm events in sediment records.  Overall, the combination of physical sedimentology and microfossil analysis of coastal sediment sequences allows identification and characterization of storms. Characterization of tropical cyclone events is immensely important for advancing knowledge and understanding within geologic, oceanographic, and environmental fields. A better understanding of tropical cyclone processes is imperative in order to predict and mitigate the effects of similar future storms on the environment and expanding coastal communities. Additional knowledge of coastal storm deposits will contribute to more accurate estimates of coastal risk assessment and hazards. Southeast Asia is susceptible to frequent typhoons and severe damage, and rapidly expanding populations tend to settle on the coasts where there is concentrated economic activity, exacerbating the negative consequences of coastal hazards. The results of this research can be combined with the findings from other researchers and institutions and be used by local government and non-academic stakeholders in the region for effective coastal planning and education of coastal communities to better prepare for future tropical cyclone events.       Last Modified: 03/14/2017       Submitted by: Jennifer S Walker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
