<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Sensitivity Enhancement in Solution NMR by Nonlinear High-Field Effects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports research in a collaboration with Prof. Ying-Chih Lin, a world-renowned expert on high-field NMR and instrumentation, in the department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University (NTU) in Taiwan to develop innovative methodology in the field of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). This new development could significantly enhance the spectral sensitivity in NMR and image contrast in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) for heteronuclei such as of Carbon-13. Over the 8-week funding period, we will focus on MRI contrast enhancement. Current MRI technique suffers from the poor contrast and sensitivity and the presence of huge background signals in our body. Heteronuclear molecular imaging (e.g. Carbon-13) can resolve the problem of background signal, but again suffers from poor sensitivity. The current collaborative project is to develop innovative approaches to enhance the sensitivity and/or contrast using Carbon-13 MR spectroscopy and micro imaging based on the nonlinear spin dynamics. The broader impact includes the very early detection (stage I or II) of tiny malignant tumor, which can save about 30% of those who die of cancers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will encompass a balanced approach to develop a rigorous theoretical understanding of nonlinear spin dynamics at UCLA on one hand and sound methodology and instrumentation to   demonstrate significant sensitivity enhancement in biomolecular NMR during the EAPSI research at NTU. This will utilize two major findings i) active feedback mechanism and ii) indirect detection of Carbon-13 through dipolar interaction to alleviate the fundamental limitation in NMR sensitivity. The intellectual merits of the proposed research lie in channeling progress in spin physics (Active-Feedback Magnetic Resonance) into significant improvements in heteronuclear MRI with valuable biomedical applications (molecular imaging and early tumor detection). Its broader impacts lie in accelerating future developments of MR-based physical oncology and nano medicine, thereby transforming magnetic resonance and fundamental imaging research into life-saving applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1614428</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sayoni</FirstName>
<LastName>Ray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sayoni Ray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>4245297050</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710761</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ray                     Sayoni</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900247243</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University Of California, Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951569</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>EAPSI: Sensitivity and Contrast Enhancement in Magnetic Resonance Imaging by Nonlinear High-Field Effects</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Sayoni Ray</p> <p style="text-align: center;">Department of Chemistry, University of California Los Angles,&nbsp;607 Charles E Young Dr E, Los Angeles, CA 90095, United States</p> <p>Cancer is the second highest leading cause of death in the United States according to the US Mortality Data. The prognosis for cancer becomes rather poor when the malignant tumor is detected at a late stage. The detection of a tiny malignant tumor at the very early stage of its development significantly increases the treatment options and the patient's chance of recovering from the disease. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is a medical imaging technique that uses a strong magnetic field and pulses of radio wave energy to map the concentration of hydrogen atoms and make pictures of organs inside the body. In biomedical diagnostics, MRI prides itself on its use of low-energy, non-ionizing radiation and is generally favored over other imaging techniques such as computed tomography scan.</p> <p>While MRI has its advantages over other methods of imaging modality, it is limited by low thermal polarization and limited contrast. Contrast is typically developed by taking advantage of the different relaxation times of the hydrogen atom in the healthy and cancerous tissues. Relaxation-based conventional MRI technique has its limitations in detecting tumors at an early stage, when both the healthy and early tumor tissues share a common morphology, making it very difficult to distinguish them on the basis of relaxation parameters. As a result, early tumors are essentially invisible to both longitudinal (<em>T</em><sub>1</sub>) and transverse (<em>T</em><sub>2</sub><em>/T<sub>2</sub>*</em>) relaxation-based conventional MRI techniques.</p> <p>In this collaborative project, EAPSI fellow Ms. Sayoni Ray from University of California, Los Angeles, worked with Prof. Ying-Chih Lin &ndash; a world-renowned expert on high-field NMR and instrumentation, in the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University (NTU) in Taiwan to develop innovative methodology in the field of MRI to detect early tumor by (1) designing suitable nanoparticles which could target cancer cells and act as &ldquo;molecular beacons&rdquo; by changing local relaxation parameters to enhance the contrast, and (2) exploring novel contrast mechanisms using magnetic properties to differentiate healthy and malignant tissues.</p> <p>They have taken the advantage of nonlinear/chaotic spin dynamics which produces "avalanching effect" (i.e., extreme sensitivity to initial conditions) and utilized it in a homebuilt active feedback device to engineer novel pulse sequences to amplify the contrast between healthy and tumor tissue at an early stage. They have further synthesized a theranostic nanoparticle, Gadolinium (Gd) encapsulated liposome, to show the successful application of this method. Robust detection of early tumor growth in subcutaneous glioblastoma multiform (GBM) mice models injected with the theranostic nanoparticle was shown by using continuous wave (CW) irradiation in the presence of the feedback magnetic field and compared with the results from conventional (T<sub>1</sub>/T<sub>2</sub>) methods. This method demonstrated a visible difference in the contrast at an early stage, where other conventional methods were not able to detect the early tumor. These new results were supported by rigorous theoretical understanding and spin dynamics simulation.</p> <p>This work convincingly shows that this novel imaging technique, coupled with computer simulation and&nbsp;<em>in vivo</em>&nbsp;mouse cancer model experiments, could be used as a powerful analytical tool for the detection and therapeutics of high-grade malignancy at early stages.</p> <p>The<strong> intellectual merits</strong> of this research are: (i) Channeling progress in spin physics into improvements in MR with valuable biomedical applications. (ii) Utilizing emerging aspects of nonlinear spin dynamics for the first time to alleviate the fundamental limitation in MR sensitivity/contrast. (iii) Engineering a general sensitivity/contrast enhancement mechanism based on indirect detection and spin amplification at high fields. (iv) Controlling the nonlinear spin dynamics and optimizing the amplification gains by an electronic feedback control device. The <strong>broader impacts</strong> of the research lie in its significant benefits to our societies. If early tumor detection in stage I or II could be made feasible and routine, about 30% (based on various assumptions) of those who die of cancers could be saved. The PI also envisions that the success of MRI would accelerate future developments of MR physical oncology and MR nano-theranostic ((simultaneous diagnosis and therapy) medicine, thereby transforming magnetic resonance and fundamental imaging research into truly life-saving applications.</p> <p style="text-align: center;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Sayoni&nbsp;Ray</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[EAPSI: Sensitivity and Contrast Enhancement in Magnetic Resonance Imaging by Nonlinear High-Field Effects  Sayoni Ray Department of Chemistry, University of California Los Angles, 607 Charles E Young Dr E, Los Angeles, CA 90095, United States  Cancer is the second highest leading cause of death in the United States according to the US Mortality Data. The prognosis for cancer becomes rather poor when the malignant tumor is detected at a late stage. The detection of a tiny malignant tumor at the very early stage of its development significantly increases the treatment options and the patient's chance of recovering from the disease. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is a medical imaging technique that uses a strong magnetic field and pulses of radio wave energy to map the concentration of hydrogen atoms and make pictures of organs inside the body. In biomedical diagnostics, MRI prides itself on its use of low-energy, non-ionizing radiation and is generally favored over other imaging techniques such as computed tomography scan.  While MRI has its advantages over other methods of imaging modality, it is limited by low thermal polarization and limited contrast. Contrast is typically developed by taking advantage of the different relaxation times of the hydrogen atom in the healthy and cancerous tissues. Relaxation-based conventional MRI technique has its limitations in detecting tumors at an early stage, when both the healthy and early tumor tissues share a common morphology, making it very difficult to distinguish them on the basis of relaxation parameters. As a result, early tumors are essentially invisible to both longitudinal (T1) and transverse (T2/T2*) relaxation-based conventional MRI techniques.  In this collaborative project, EAPSI fellow Ms. Sayoni Ray from University of California, Los Angeles, worked with Prof. Ying-Chih Lin &ndash; a world-renowned expert on high-field NMR and instrumentation, in the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University (NTU) in Taiwan to develop innovative methodology in the field of MRI to detect early tumor by (1) designing suitable nanoparticles which could target cancer cells and act as "molecular beacons" by changing local relaxation parameters to enhance the contrast, and (2) exploring novel contrast mechanisms using magnetic properties to differentiate healthy and malignant tissues.  They have taken the advantage of nonlinear/chaotic spin dynamics which produces "avalanching effect" (i.e., extreme sensitivity to initial conditions) and utilized it in a homebuilt active feedback device to engineer novel pulse sequences to amplify the contrast between healthy and tumor tissue at an early stage. They have further synthesized a theranostic nanoparticle, Gadolinium (Gd) encapsulated liposome, to show the successful application of this method. Robust detection of early tumor growth in subcutaneous glioblastoma multiform (GBM) mice models injected with the theranostic nanoparticle was shown by using continuous wave (CW) irradiation in the presence of the feedback magnetic field and compared with the results from conventional (T1/T2) methods. This method demonstrated a visible difference in the contrast at an early stage, where other conventional methods were not able to detect the early tumor. These new results were supported by rigorous theoretical understanding and spin dynamics simulation.  This work convincingly shows that this novel imaging technique, coupled with computer simulation and in vivo mouse cancer model experiments, could be used as a powerful analytical tool for the detection and therapeutics of high-grade malignancy at early stages.  The intellectual merits of this research are: (i) Channeling progress in spin physics into improvements in MR with valuable biomedical applications. (ii) Utilizing emerging aspects of nonlinear spin dynamics for the first time to alleviate the fundamental limitation in MR sensitivity/contrast. (iii) Engineering a general sensitivity/contrast enhancement mechanism based on indirect detection and spin amplification at high fields. (iv) Controlling the nonlinear spin dynamics and optimizing the amplification gains by an electronic feedback control device. The broader impacts of the research lie in its significant benefits to our societies. If early tumor detection in stage I or II could be made feasible and routine, about 30% (based on various assumptions) of those who die of cancers could be saved. The PI also envisions that the success of MRI would accelerate future developments of MR physical oncology and MR nano-theranostic ((simultaneous diagnosis and therapy) medicine, thereby transforming magnetic resonance and fundamental imaging research into truly life-saving applications.         Last Modified: 03/15/2017       Submitted by: Sayoni Ray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
