<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Magnetization Dynamics at Nanoscale</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project investigates questions in the area of magnetic materials, emphasizing modeling, analysis, and numerical explorations of nanoscale systems.  Magnetic materials have been an indispensable ingredient for information storage since the advent of the computer age and presently hold great promise for the development of revolutionary new computer and information technologies.  Recent advances in nanofabrication allow an unprecedented precision in building magnetic multilayer structures, using ultrathin films with thickness down to a single atomic layer and a lateral extent down to ten nanometers.  At these very small scales, new physical effects become prominent, driving interesting new phenomena such as spin transfer torque, chiral domain walls, magnetic skyrmions, spin, inverse spin, and topological Hall effects.  This new physics needs to be incorporated into the micromagnetic modeling framework that proved very successful in the previous studies of magnetic systems at larger scales.  This research project explores the multiscale, nonlinear, nonlocal, and often stochastic nature of the new models, which represents a significant challenge to understanding and predicting the behavior of such systems.  A key component of the project is the involvement of a new generation of applied mathematicians in this highly interdisciplinary area of research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to formulate and analyze models of ultrathin ferromagnetic films in the presence of antisymmetric exchange interaction, which produces a non-trivial interplay with the topological characteristics of the magnetization.  Particular care will be taken to incorporate into the models the non-local effects of the stray field via rigorous analysis of the appropriate asymptotic thin film limits arising from the full three-dimensional treatment.  Within the obtained reduced thin film models, the properties of charged domain walls, chiral domain walls, and magnetic skyrmions will be investigated, using a combination of analytical, formal asymptotic, and numerical tools.  The questions of existence and asymptotic properties of these coherent structures give rise to challenging problems of energy-driven pattern formation and calculus of variations.  The research is strongly motivated by the rapidly expanding field of spintronics.  All the special magnetization configurations that will be considered in the project are currently targets for potential applications in spintronics devices and, in particular, for the development of non-volatile sequential and random access computer memories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1614948</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cyrill</FirstName>
<LastName>Muratov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cyrill B Muratov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>muratov@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9735965833</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Heights</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075162990</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW JERSEY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075162990</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Jersey Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[323 DOCTOR MARTIN LUTHER]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ferromagnetism is a physical phenomenon whereby certain substances may exhibit noticeable attractive or repulsive forces at large distances. While it provides one of the oldest known examples of action at a distance, understanding its mechanism only began to emerge in the early 20th century with the advent of quantum mechanics and is attributed to the fundamentally quantum spin degree of freedom of an electron. In ferromagnetic materials, the competition of the short-range exchange interaction and the long-range dipolar interaction gives rise to a remarkably diverse array of observed magnetization configurations. This makes ferromagnetic materials both a fascinating example of pattern forming systems suitable for a wide array of technological applications and a challenge for explaining the magnetic properties of these materials.</p> <p><br />From the point of view of technology, one is particularly interested in the properties of thin film ferromagnetic materials. Advances in nanofabrication techniques allow unprecedented precision in building magnetic multilayers, using ultrathin films with thickness down to a single atomic layer and a lateral extent down to ten nanometers. At these scales, new physical effects come into play which are typically absent in bulk crystalline materials. In recent years, a great deal of attention has been drawn to the so-called antisymmetric exchange, or Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, which becomes important in nanometer-thick ferromagnetic layers. This interaction fundamentally alters the properties of ferromagnetic nanomaterials by enabling a host of novel types of non-collinear spin textures.</p> <p><br />This project took an aim to carry out a combined modeling, analytical and computational investigation of ultrathin ferromagnetic layers with or without perpendicular magnetic anisotropy and/or the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction. To this end, the PI carried out studies of several types of domain wall configurations in the systems under consideration, providing new analytical and numerical tools for quantitative understanding of these emergent magnetic behaviors at nanoscale. In particular, several intriguing new phenomena, such as the emergence of domain wall tilt under the action of in-plane magnetic fields on chiral domain walls illustrated in Fig. 1 have been explained. Furthermore, topological aspects of spin textures observed in these systems were tackled in the first detailed analysis of a realistic variational model of&nbsp; compact magnetic skyrmions -- particle-like topologically non-trivial perturbations of the ferromagnetic ground state -- that hold great promise as potential information carriers in the new generation of spintronic memory and logic devices. These findings are illustrated in Fig. 2, which shows the predictions of rigorous asymptotic theory of skyrmion solutions for their main characteristics, as well as an example of the solution itself obtained numerically for relevant material parameters.</p> <p><br />The obtained results will be invaluable to guide the development of the prototypes for future magnetoelectronic devices and provide further ideas for novel device principles. More broadly, the obtained results advance our understanding of energy driven pattern formation problems, whose behavior is governed by a competition of short-range attractive and long-range repulsive interactions of different physical nature. Also, the research carried out in this project provided a fertile ground for training a new generation of applied mathematicians and stimulated interdisciplinary collaborations between researchers of diverse scientific backgrounds.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Cyrill&nbsp;B&nbsp;Muratov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1614948/1614948_10430170_1605208344028_tilt2dnum--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1614948/1614948_10430170_1605208344028_tilt2dnum--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tilted chiral wall"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1614948/1614948_10430170_1605208344028_tilt2dnum--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tilted chiral wall"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A tilted domain wall profile in a ferromagnetic nanostrip subject to an applied in-plane magnetic field in the presence of Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction.</div> <div class="imageCredit">10.1103/PhysRevB.96.134417</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cyrill&nbsp;B&nbsp;Muratov</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tilted chiral wall</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1614948/1614948_10430170_1605209413869_blochneel--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1614948/1614948_10430170_1605209413869_blochneel--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Skyrmion characteristics and a profile"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1614948/1614948_10430170_1605209413869_blochneel--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Skyrmion characteristics and a profile"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Parametric dependences of the compact skyrmion characteristics in the low Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya regime (a-c) and a mixed Neel-Bloch skyrmion profile computed for the parameters indicated with the dot (d).</div> <div class="imageCredit">10.1103/PhysRevB.101.045416, APS</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cyrill&nbsp;B&nbsp;Muratov</div> <div class="imageTitle">Skyrmion characteristics and a profile</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ferromagnetism is a physical phenomenon whereby certain substances may exhibit noticeable attractive or repulsive forces at large distances. While it provides one of the oldest known examples of action at a distance, understanding its mechanism only began to emerge in the early 20th century with the advent of quantum mechanics and is attributed to the fundamentally quantum spin degree of freedom of an electron. In ferromagnetic materials, the competition of the short-range exchange interaction and the long-range dipolar interaction gives rise to a remarkably diverse array of observed magnetization configurations. This makes ferromagnetic materials both a fascinating example of pattern forming systems suitable for a wide array of technological applications and a challenge for explaining the magnetic properties of these materials.   From the point of view of technology, one is particularly interested in the properties of thin film ferromagnetic materials. Advances in nanofabrication techniques allow unprecedented precision in building magnetic multilayers, using ultrathin films with thickness down to a single atomic layer and a lateral extent down to ten nanometers. At these scales, new physical effects come into play which are typically absent in bulk crystalline materials. In recent years, a great deal of attention has been drawn to the so-called antisymmetric exchange, or Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, which becomes important in nanometer-thick ferromagnetic layers. This interaction fundamentally alters the properties of ferromagnetic nanomaterials by enabling a host of novel types of non-collinear spin textures.   This project took an aim to carry out a combined modeling, analytical and computational investigation of ultrathin ferromagnetic layers with or without perpendicular magnetic anisotropy and/or the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction. To this end, the PI carried out studies of several types of domain wall configurations in the systems under consideration, providing new analytical and numerical tools for quantitative understanding of these emergent magnetic behaviors at nanoscale. In particular, several intriguing new phenomena, such as the emergence of domain wall tilt under the action of in-plane magnetic fields on chiral domain walls illustrated in Fig. 1 have been explained. Furthermore, topological aspects of spin textures observed in these systems were tackled in the first detailed analysis of a realistic variational model of  compact magnetic skyrmions -- particle-like topologically non-trivial perturbations of the ferromagnetic ground state -- that hold great promise as potential information carriers in the new generation of spintronic memory and logic devices. These findings are illustrated in Fig. 2, which shows the predictions of rigorous asymptotic theory of skyrmion solutions for their main characteristics, as well as an example of the solution itself obtained numerically for relevant material parameters.   The obtained results will be invaluable to guide the development of the prototypes for future magnetoelectronic devices and provide further ideas for novel device principles. More broadly, the obtained results advance our understanding of energy driven pattern formation problems, whose behavior is governed by a competition of short-range attractive and long-range repulsive interactions of different physical nature. Also, the research carried out in this project provided a fertile ground for training a new generation of applied mathematicians and stimulated interdisciplinary collaborations between researchers of diverse scientific backgrounds.       Last Modified: 11/12/2020       Submitted by: Cyrill B Muratov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
