<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Molecular analysis of SCD complex function in Rab signaling in cell morphogenesis and function</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>800000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>800000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Cunningham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chacunni@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objectives of this project are to better understand how plant cells divide and enlarge, which are key aspects of plant biology necessary for the growth and health of plants. The final step of cell division, known as cytokinesis, involves the splitting of a cell into two daughter cells and is followed by expansion of the new cells.  However, many of the mechanisms involved in these processes are not well understood in either plants or animals. Specifically, this project will focus on how new membrane barriers and cell wall form between and around newly divided plant cells. The information gained has the potential to reveal new strategies for improving crop yield and quality on American farms necessary for increased food security and energy independence. In addition, young scientists at the high school, undergraduate, graduate, and postgraduate level will receive advanced research training in the areas of biochemistry, genetics and microscopy. Graduate students and postdoctoral fellows will also gain teaching and mentoring skills by supervising high school and undergraduates including underrepresented students in the UW-Madison IBS Summer Research Program. Additionally, the project will generate research tools for both the plant and the general research communities including image analysis software for the quantitative tracking of biological molecules and non-biological materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long-term objective of this project is to understand the molecular mechanisms involved in intracellular membrane trafficking required for plant growth and development including: cytokinesis, cell wall biosynthesis, hormone signaling, nutrient uptake, and pathogen defense. SCD1 and SCD2 encode plant-specific clathrin-coated vesicle proteins necessary for cytokinesis, cell expansion and pathogen defense. Recent studies have demonstrated that SCD1 and SCD2 are subunits of a previously uncharacterized protein complex that interacts with Rab proteins, which are central regulators of vesicle trafficking. The focus of this project is to investigate the function of this newly identified SCD complex and its regulation of Rab/clathrin-dependent membrane trafficking in dividing and non-dividing cells. The specific aims of this project are to 1) Biochemically characterize the composition and activity of the SCD complex, 2) Define effectors and regulators of the SCD/Rab complex, and 3) Develop and apply quantitative imaging approaches to analyze and describe the function of the SCD complex and its cognate Rabs in intracellular membrane trafficking necessary for plant cell morphogenesis. These studies will generate fundamental knowledge into the function of plant-specific and evolutionarily conserved membrane-trafficking proteins in plants and other eukaryotic systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1614915</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sebastian</FirstName>
<LastName>Bednarek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sebastian Y Bednarek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sybednar@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082630309</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336006</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Eliceiri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin W Eliceiri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eliceiri@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082636288</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000398380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin - Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street, Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~800000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp;</strong>The long-term objective of this work is to understand the molecular mechanisms involved in intracellular membrane trafficking required for processes underlying plant growth and development including, cytokinesis, cell wall biosynthesis, hormone signaling, nutrient uptake and pathogen defense. Many of the key factors involved in post-Golgi exocytic trafficking to the plasma membrane, including Rab GTPases are evolutionarily conserved in eukaryotes. However, our recent studies have demonstrated that activation of the exocytic RabE1 GTPase family, which function in trafficking required for cytokinesis and polarized cell expansion, is dependent upon a protein complex, known as the SCD complex, that is absent from yeast and metazoan cells.</p> <p>Subunits of the SCD complex include SCD1, which contains an evolutionarily conserved N-terminal DENN domain that in metazoans activates Rab GTPases, and SCD2, a protein of unknown function, both of which were previously demonstrated to be required for membrane trafficking essential to&nbsp; cytokinesis and cell growth in <em>Arabidopsis thaliana</em>. Consistent with their role in exocytic membrane trafficking, <em>scd1</em> and <em>scd2</em> mutants display impaired post-Golgi trafficking of proteins to the plasma membrane, including the auxin efflux carrier PIN2, which may contribute to the dwarf stature and other observed developmental phenotypes including infertility and altered pathogen defense responses.</p> <p>Using a combination of live-cell imaging, subcellular fractionation and biochemical interaction studies we have shown that subunits of the SCD complex colocalize at the cell plate, plasma membrane, and in transport vesicles with the exocyst subunit SEC15B and members of the RabE1 GTPase family. Importantly, the SCD complex from Arabidopsis cell extracts binds selectively to &ldquo;inactive&rdquo; (GDP-locked) mutant RabE1 <em>in vitro</em> and <em>in vivo</em>, and <em>scd1</em> mutants are rescued by overexpression of constitutively active (GTP-locked) RabE1, suggesting that the SCD complex functions to activate members of the RabE1 family.</p> <p>Mass spectrometry analysis of SCD complex purified from Arabidopsis cells identified several additional subunits including two SCD2-related proteins, SCD2b and SCD2c, as well as a protein we have termed MyTH1. The association of SCD2b, SCD2c and MyTH1 with SCD1 and SCD2 was validated by reciprocal analyses of SCD complexes purified from plant cells expressing affinity tagged versions of these proteins as well as <em>in vitro</em> binding studies using recombinant SCD complex proteins. Similar to the class I myosin tail homology (TH1) membrane binding domain for which the protein is named, MyTH1, interacts with phosphatidylinositol phosphate lipids suggesting that it facilitates membrane association of the SCD complex.</p> <p>Ongoing structure/function studies of SCD1 and SCD2 in Arabidopsis will provide a framework for understanding the evolutionarily conserved and plant-specific mechanisms that regulate SCD complex activity and its function in membrane trafficking in dividing and non-dividing cells. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">:</span></strong>This project integrated the complementary expertise of the PI and Co-PI to investigate the evolutionarily-conserved and plant-specific mechanisms that regulate intracellular trafficking in plants required for cytokinesis and other essential cellular functions including cell wall formation and cell expansion, which are vital to plant growth and development. The findings generated by this project will thus, in the long-term, aid efforts to improve the quality and quantity of plants for food, biofuel, and other agronomically important products. In addition, these studies have generated fundamental new knowledge about the function of evolutionarily conserved membrane-trafficking proteins in other eukaryotic systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The project provided meaningful research, training, and mentorship experiences for 1 postdoctoral fellow, 4 graduate students, 7 undergraduates, and 1 high school student through &ldquo;hands-on&rdquo; research experiences in the areas of biochemistry, genetics, and microscopy. These research and training experiences provided the post-doctoral fellow and students key opportunities to enhance their critical thinking skills and refine their oral and written communication skills through the presentation of research findings at local and national meetings necessary for their career development. In addition, these studies have led to the development of important new tools for the plant and general research communities including TrackMate, an open-source FIJI plug-in for quantitative single particle tracking of subcellular organelles. All proteomic datasets, software, plant lines, reagents and techniques generated during the course of this study have been made freely available to all researchers.</p> <p><strong>Products/Publications</strong><strong>:<em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>TrackMate, a particle tracking image analysis plugin for FIJI:&nbsp;<a href="http://fiji.sc/TrackMate">http://fiji.sc/TrackMate</a><strong><em>.</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>Mayers et al. (2017) SCD1 and SCD2 Form a Complex That Functions with the Exocyst and RabE1 in Exocytosis and Cytokinesis<em>.</em>&nbsp;Plant Cell doi:10.1105/tpc.17.00409</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Reynolds, G.D. (2018) Inroads into Internalization: Five Years of Endocytic Exploration<em>.</em>&nbsp;Plant Physiol. doi: 10.1104/pp.17.01117</p> <p>Johnson, A. et al. (2020) Experimental toolbox for the study of clathrin-mediated endocytosis in Arabidopsis. J. Cell Sci. doi: 10.1242/jcs.248062</p> <p>Ekanayake, G. et al.&nbsp; (2020) DYNAMIN-RELATED PROTEIN DRP1A functions with DRP2B in plant growth, immune responses and FLS2 endocytosis. Plant Physiol, in press.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2021<br>      Modified by: Sebastian&nbsp;Y&nbsp;Bednarek</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: The long-term objective of this work is to understand the molecular mechanisms involved in intracellular membrane trafficking required for processes underlying plant growth and development including, cytokinesis, cell wall biosynthesis, hormone signaling, nutrient uptake and pathogen defense. Many of the key factors involved in post-Golgi exocytic trafficking to the plasma membrane, including Rab GTPases are evolutionarily conserved in eukaryotes. However, our recent studies have demonstrated that activation of the exocytic RabE1 GTPase family, which function in trafficking required for cytokinesis and polarized cell expansion, is dependent upon a protein complex, known as the SCD complex, that is absent from yeast and metazoan cells.  Subunits of the SCD complex include SCD1, which contains an evolutionarily conserved N-terminal DENN domain that in metazoans activates Rab GTPases, and SCD2, a protein of unknown function, both of which were previously demonstrated to be required for membrane trafficking essential to  cytokinesis and cell growth in Arabidopsis thaliana. Consistent with their role in exocytic membrane trafficking, scd1 and scd2 mutants display impaired post-Golgi trafficking of proteins to the plasma membrane, including the auxin efflux carrier PIN2, which may contribute to the dwarf stature and other observed developmental phenotypes including infertility and altered pathogen defense responses.  Using a combination of live-cell imaging, subcellular fractionation and biochemical interaction studies we have shown that subunits of the SCD complex colocalize at the cell plate, plasma membrane, and in transport vesicles with the exocyst subunit SEC15B and members of the RabE1 GTPase family. Importantly, the SCD complex from Arabidopsis cell extracts binds selectively to "inactive" (GDP-locked) mutant RabE1 in vitro and in vivo, and scd1 mutants are rescued by overexpression of constitutively active (GTP-locked) RabE1, suggesting that the SCD complex functions to activate members of the RabE1 family.  Mass spectrometry analysis of SCD complex purified from Arabidopsis cells identified several additional subunits including two SCD2-related proteins, SCD2b and SCD2c, as well as a protein we have termed MyTH1. The association of SCD2b, SCD2c and MyTH1 with SCD1 and SCD2 was validated by reciprocal analyses of SCD complexes purified from plant cells expressing affinity tagged versions of these proteins as well as in vitro binding studies using recombinant SCD complex proteins. Similar to the class I myosin tail homology (TH1) membrane binding domain for which the protein is named, MyTH1, interacts with phosphatidylinositol phosphate lipids suggesting that it facilitates membrane association of the SCD complex.  Ongoing structure/function studies of SCD1 and SCD2 in Arabidopsis will provide a framework for understanding the evolutionarily conserved and plant-specific mechanisms that regulate SCD complex activity and its function in membrane trafficking in dividing and non-dividing cells.     Broader Impacts:This project integrated the complementary expertise of the PI and Co-PI to investigate the evolutionarily-conserved and plant-specific mechanisms that regulate intracellular trafficking in plants required for cytokinesis and other essential cellular functions including cell wall formation and cell expansion, which are vital to plant growth and development. The findings generated by this project will thus, in the long-term, aid efforts to improve the quality and quantity of plants for food, biofuel, and other agronomically important products. In addition, these studies have generated fundamental new knowledge about the function of evolutionarily conserved membrane-trafficking proteins in other eukaryotic systems.              The project provided meaningful research, training, and mentorship experiences for 1 postdoctoral fellow, 4 graduate students, 7 undergraduates, and 1 high school student through "hands-on" research experiences in the areas of biochemistry, genetics, and microscopy. These research and training experiences provided the post-doctoral fellow and students key opportunities to enhance their critical thinking skills and refine their oral and written communication skills through the presentation of research findings at local and national meetings necessary for their career development. In addition, these studies have led to the development of important new tools for the plant and general research communities including TrackMate, an open-source FIJI plug-in for quantitative single particle tracking of subcellular organelles. All proteomic datasets, software, plant lines, reagents and techniques generated during the course of this study have been made freely available to all researchers.  Products/Publications:   TrackMate, a particle tracking image analysis plugin for FIJI: http://fiji.sc/TrackMate.   Mayers et al. (2017) SCD1 and SCD2 Form a Complex That Functions with the Exocyst and RabE1 in Exocytosis and Cytokinesis. Plant Cell doi:10.1105/tpc.17.00409 Reynolds, G.D. (2018) Inroads into Internalization: Five Years of Endocytic Exploration. Plant Physiol. doi: 10.1104/pp.17.01117  Johnson, A. et al. (2020) Experimental toolbox for the study of clathrin-mediated endocytosis in Arabidopsis. J. Cell Sci. doi: 10.1242/jcs.248062  Ekanayake, G. et al.  (2020) DYNAMIN-RELATED PROTEIN DRP1A functions with DRP2B in plant growth, immune responses and FLS2 endocytosis. Plant Physiol, in press.             Last Modified: 01/17/2021       Submitted by: Sebastian Y Bednarek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
