<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Studies of the Structure of the Nucleon</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>810000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>810000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Advances in the physics goal of understanding the universe at its most fundamental level have shown that matter is composed of a set of fundamental particles that combine to form other particles that group together to generate the structures that we recognize around us. For example, the nucleus of an atom is formed from a mixture of protons and neutrons.  These protons and neutrons are made from constituents, called quarks and gluons, which give substructure to these particles. The goal of this project is to determine aspects of the structure of the proton and neutron, and how this structure is affected when placed in the nucleus. The experiments focus on how the quarks are distributed in space and in momentum. An on-going puzzle is whether the proton size is not the same when measured with atomic hydrogen and its counterpart, muonic-hydrogen, where the electron in the hydrogen atom has been replaced by its heavier cousin, the muon. The project includes measurement of electron and muon scattering from protons to provide an independent measurement of the proton radius. In addition to the direct scientific goals of the project, the experiments provide students and young scientists experience and training in working in the international collaborations of modern scientific experiments, with state of the art technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of this proposal is study the structure of the nucleon. The ongoing Fermilab SEAQUEST experiment uses Drell-Yan cross sections to determine the ratio of anti-d to anti-u quarks in the nucleon as a function of quark momentum, to study transverse momentum distributions, to investigate the EMC effect, to study quark energy loss in cold nuclear matter, and to investigate the possible existence of dark photons in a parameter region of higher mass but lower coupling constant to ordinary matter. The Fermilab MINERvA experiment provides a complementary view of nucleon and nuclear structure by scattering few GeV neutrinos from protons and from nuclei. At Jefferson Lab, experiments on tritium targets will be run in 2017. The MARATHON experiment, through a comparison of deep inelastic scattering of electrons on 3H to 3He, provides information on the ratio of the proton and neutron F2 structure functions at high x, testing decades old perturbative quantum chromodynamics model calculations. The preliminary phases of creating a new experiment to elastically scatter muons and electrons from the proton, the MUSE experiment at the Paul Scherrer Institute in Switzerland, are in progress, with the goal of measuring the distribution of charge in the proton.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1614456</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Ransome</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ronald D Ransome</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ransome@physics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484458779</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417273</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ronald Gilman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rgilman@physics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484458775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Fermilab]]></Name>
<CityName>Batavia</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>605105011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Wilson & Kirk Roads]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1232</Code>
<Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~270000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~270000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~270000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal of this proposal was to advance several multiyear experiments that will&nbsp; improve our understanding of how nucleons are made up of quarks, and possibly reveal interesting novel physics. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The main effort in this proposal was focused on the MUSE experiment, which takes place at the Paul Scherrer Institute in Switzerland. MUSE determines the charge distribution of protons using both electrons and muons as probes, and investigates a puzzle that the proton radius seems to be different depending on whether it is determined with an&nbsp; electron versus a muon probe. The experiment also studies some corrections needed to get the radius from the data. During this proposal, the experiment was brought together so that we took the first ``dress-rehearsal'' data with a fully assembled experimental system. We have started analyzing the data to determine the performance of the system, and to identify any issues thst need to be resolved before we can take production quality data.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>A second major effort in this work was the Seaquest experiment, which takes place at Fermilab, in Batavia, IL. Seaquest studies the distribution of anti-quarks in nucleons and nuclei as a function of momentum. Seaquest completed and has been analyzing its measurements. We have presented results in conferences and are now drafting papers for publication. In earlier experiments, the distributions measured for the anti-quarks were hard to understand with theoretical models over part of the momentum range. The Seaquest measurements of these distributions agrees better with the theory estimates than with the old data in the region where there were disagreements.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The primary broader impact of this work remains the training of students and postdocs. We typically have 1 or 2 undergraduates working with us each year; two of the recent undergraduates of the past few years are now in graduate school. We have had four graduate students supported by this grant; two graduated immediately before this grant reporting period and are now postdocs, while the other two continue to work on MUSE. The one postdoc supported by this grant became, at the start of this reporting period, a staff scientist at a Swiss laboratory.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/15/2020<br>      Modified by: Ronald&nbsp;Gilman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this proposal was to advance several multiyear experiments that will  improve our understanding of how nucleons are made up of quarks, and possibly reveal interesting novel physics.       The main effort in this proposal was focused on the MUSE experiment, which takes place at the Paul Scherrer Institute in Switzerland. MUSE determines the charge distribution of protons using both electrons and muons as probes, and investigates a puzzle that the proton radius seems to be different depending on whether it is determined with an  electron versus a muon probe. The experiment also studies some corrections needed to get the radius from the data. During this proposal, the experiment was brought together so that we took the first ``dress-rehearsal'' data with a fully assembled experimental system. We have started analyzing the data to determine the performance of the system, and to identify any issues thst need to be resolved before we can take production quality data.     A second major effort in this work was the Seaquest experiment, which takes place at Fermilab, in Batavia, IL. Seaquest studies the distribution of anti-quarks in nucleons and nuclei as a function of momentum. Seaquest completed and has been analyzing its measurements. We have presented results in conferences and are now drafting papers for publication. In earlier experiments, the distributions measured for the anti-quarks were hard to understand with theoretical models over part of the momentum range. The Seaquest measurements of these distributions agrees better with the theory estimates than with the old data in the region where there were disagreements.     The primary broader impact of this work remains the training of students and postdocs. We typically have 1 or 2 undergraduates working with us each year; two of the recent undergraduates of the past few years are now in graduate school. We have had four graduate students supported by this grant; two graduated immediately before this grant reporting period and are now postdocs, while the other two continue to work on MUSE. The one postdoc supported by this grant became, at the start of this reporting period, a staff scientist at a Swiss laboratory.            Last Modified: 05/15/2020       Submitted by: Ronald Gilman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
