<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Development of a platform enabling analysis of membrane protein interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Engin Serpersu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eserpers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: Collaborative research: Development of a platform enabling analysis of membrane protein interactions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proteins embedded within or associated with cellular membranes make up 30% of all proteins. These cellular gatekeepers are critical in biological functions, including transport in and out of cells, recognition and transduction of information, energy production and communication amongst cells. Despite the importance of membrane proteins, understanding of the interactions and functions of the membrane proteome is still greatly hampered by technical challenges; there is an urgent need for innovative approaches to uncover how membrane proteins interact with one another and with their binding partners in the native membrane environment. This project will develop a versatile experimental platform that provides maps of protein-protein and protein-membrane interactions. Under-represented minorities will receive STEM education and training at undergraduate graduate level. The proposal will also provide video instructions for high school students to attract students in STEM fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative research will establish a versatile experimental platform that provides information on protein-protein and protein-membrane assemblies in Nanodiscs, which represent a native-like model membrane system. The goals of this research are to establish a versatile experimental platform that provides vector maps of protein-protein and protein-membrane assemblies. Key cornerstones of the approach are the use of lipid bilayer nanodiscs (NDs) as a native-like membrane platform and biophysical approaches that rely on strategically positioned lanthanide-binding tags (LBTs). The LBTs are dual-function probes that insert atoms for physical measurements enabling the construction of three-dimensional vector maps of protein assemblies relative to the membrane plane. Measurements will be accomplished via small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) and anomalous SAXS (ASAXS) to provide distances between lanthanides and center of mass and inter-lanthanide distances. The construction of vector maps will allow accurate measurement of the response of proteins to the presence and absence of binding partners, dynamic protein modifications, and indeed the composition of the membrane itself-thus defining the critical determinants of both assembly and function. This project is supported by the Molecular Biophysics Cluster of the Molecular and Cellular Biosciences Division in the Directorate for Biological Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1615252</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Imperiali</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Imperiali</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>imper@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172531838</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Deriving insight into the structure and function of proteins that are partially or fully embedded in the cell membrane and the complexes that these membrane proteins form necessitates a precise understanding of the organization of proteins in a membrane-like environment and the role of the membrane components in these interactions. Many studies involving membrane proteins have been performed in the presence of detergent, which can fundamentally alter interactions. Our goals are to establish the applicability of small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) and lanthanide resonance energy transfer (LRET) measurements using small peptide-based binding tags that bind lanthanides (LBTs) for defining specific inter- and intramolecular distances to create a map of the interactions between membrane-associated proteins and protein complexes in small model membrane membrane nanoparticles, including Nanodiscs (NDs) and Styrene Maleic Acid Lipoparticles( SMALPs), of defined dimensions and with controlled compositions. Through this work we have established a proof-of-concept system for SAXS in NDs on a membrane-embedded protein involved in phosphoglycosyl transfer. In these experiments, the measured distances clearly match those calculated from the known protein structure. We have also developed a two-component membrane protein system comprising two characterized membrane proteins that are known to interact at the membrane interface. Most recently, we have established unnatural amino acid mutagenesis and bioconjugation protocols that can be used in conjunction with SMALP for the detergent-free single step purification of labeled membrane proteins in native lipid bilayer particles. In community outreach initiatives, we have expanded the utility of X-ray fluorescence microscopy (XFM) as a broadly applicable method to incorporate selected metals rather than being limited to those naturally occurring in the cell. As XFM achieves high resolution, even substructures in bacterial cells can be distinguished (Victor et al. 2018, Scientific Reports), including the cell outer membrane itself.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2019<br>      Modified by: Barbara&nbsp;Imperiali</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Deriving insight into the structure and function of proteins that are partially or fully embedded in the cell membrane and the complexes that these membrane proteins form necessitates a precise understanding of the organization of proteins in a membrane-like environment and the role of the membrane components in these interactions. Many studies involving membrane proteins have been performed in the presence of detergent, which can fundamentally alter interactions. Our goals are to establish the applicability of small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) and lanthanide resonance energy transfer (LRET) measurements using small peptide-based binding tags that bind lanthanides (LBTs) for defining specific inter- and intramolecular distances to create a map of the interactions between membrane-associated proteins and protein complexes in small model membrane membrane nanoparticles, including Nanodiscs (NDs) and Styrene Maleic Acid Lipoparticles( SMALPs), of defined dimensions and with controlled compositions. Through this work we have established a proof-of-concept system for SAXS in NDs on a membrane-embedded protein involved in phosphoglycosyl transfer. In these experiments, the measured distances clearly match those calculated from the known protein structure. We have also developed a two-component membrane protein system comprising two characterized membrane proteins that are known to interact at the membrane interface. Most recently, we have established unnatural amino acid mutagenesis and bioconjugation protocols that can be used in conjunction with SMALP for the detergent-free single step purification of labeled membrane proteins in native lipid bilayer particles. In community outreach initiatives, we have expanded the utility of X-ray fluorescence microscopy (XFM) as a broadly applicable method to incorporate selected metals rather than being limited to those naturally occurring in the cell. As XFM achieves high resolution, even substructures in bacterial cells can be distinguished (Victor et al. 2018, Scientific Reports), including the cell outer membrane itself.          Last Modified: 07/10/2019       Submitted by: Barbara Imperiali]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
