<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Dust, Gas, and Star Formation: Synthesizing 20 Years of Radio, Millimeter, and Infrared Surveys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>379574.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>379574</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glen Langston</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>glangsto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924937</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Galaxies grow by converting interstellar gas into new generations of stars. A main step in that process is the conversion of low-density, atomic gas into cold, dense, star-forming clouds. Interstellar dust controls this process by shielding gas from destructive ultraviolet radiation and promoting chemical reactions. The abundance of both dust and cold gas depend on local environment in a galaxy, but the nature of this dependence is still debated at a very basic level. This project will test competing hypotheses for what sets the amount of dust and cold gas in galaxies by mapping dust, neutral interstellar gas (diffuse atomic gas and cold, dense molecular gas), and local conditions in a sample of nearby galaxies ten times larger than those used in previous studies. The investigators will use these observations database to answer two questions about gas and star formation in galaxies.  The first question is what sets the amount of cold, star-forming gas?  The second question is what determines the abundance of dust? These two intertwined questions are critical to understand how galaxies grow and change over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will assemble the next generation database of dust and gas distributions in galaxies. To do this, they will combine new and archival observations of atomic hydrogen (HI) from the NSF-funded Very Large Array with Herschel spacecraft measurements of the distribution and properties of interstellar dust.  They will increase, by an order of magnitude, the sample of galaxies with such observations.  An order of magnitude increase in the set of galaxies studied in this way will advance the field into a new regime of statistical hypothesis testing, a potentially transformative step in understanding the physics of gas in galaxies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The observing database will be shared on the internet with other astronomers and also the public.  The investigators will build on the Zooniverse project to share their observations with the public.  Zooniverse is an internet tool that allows the public to view and classify scientific observations.  With this tool, the public can both appreciate the observations and aid in the research. The investigators plan to create 'the HI Holes Project', in which volunteer citizen scientists will identify giant holes in the gaseous interstellar medium of real and simulated galaxies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1615728</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karin</FirstName>
<LastName>Sandstrom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karin M Sandstrom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmsandstrom@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8582460552</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683473</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930424</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1216</Code>
<Text>GALACTIC ASTRONOMY PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~379574</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-66e96174-7fff-5b40-8b5a-ef3791b3c717"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Prior to forming new stars, gas in the interstellar medium (ISM) of galaxies must reach high densities and cool temperatures to allow gravitational collapse of regions of a cloud. In this process, low density gas where hydrogen is primarily atomic becomes denser and eventually transitions to being primarily molecular.&nbsp; The physics of this process are critical to understanding how galaxies form new stars out of their reservoir of interstellar gas. Dust grains appear to play a key role in this process because they block the molecule-dissociating UV radiation from other nearby young stars and they provide a catalyst for the chemical reaction that creates molecular hydrogen.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In this project, our goal was to provide new and comprehensive measurements of the amount of dust relative to gas in the ISM of nearby galaxies and to characterize the role dust plays in the transition from atomic to molecular gas.&nbsp; To do this, we uniformly analyzed large datasets of nearby galaxy mapping at infrared, millimeter, and radio wavelengths. In particular, we used infrared observations tracing dust emission from the Wide Field Infrared Sky Explorer and the Herschel Space Observatory; millimeter observations tracing molecular gas from several observatories including the Atacama Large Millimeter Array; and radio observations tracing atomic hydrogen from the Very Large Array. In total, we have created maps of the dust mass for approximately 1000 galaxies and maps of the atomic hydrogen for approximately 500.&nbsp; We are in the process of preparing these reduced datasets for permanent archiving.&nbsp; We have also used the maps to facilitate a number of investigations into the state of the gas and dust in galaxies.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>One of the major outcomes from our project is a comprehensive investigation of the ?dust-to-metals ratio? in nearby galaxies. The dust-to-metals ratio represents the fraction of the available heavy elements that are in dust grains. This quantity is deeply connected to the processes that form, destroy, and alter dust grains.&nbsp; Graduate student I-Da Chiang led two papers focused on measuring the dust-to-metals ratio and its spatial variation within galaxies as part of his PhD thesis. From these studies we learned that: 1) dust-to-metals is not the same everywhere - it increases when heavy elements are abundant and in regions where the ISM is denser and colder; 2) the measurement of the dust-to-metals ratio is very dependent on how we trace the amount of molecular gas, and many existing approaches to this issue appear to not work for all galaxies; and 3) with our best knowledge of molecular gas, the dust-to-metals ratio appears to be consistent with models that require rapid growth of dust in the ISM.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>A key part of our project involved investigating the accuracy of various approaches to measuring dust mass in galaxies.&nbsp; This is critical for measuring dust-to-metals, but it also has important implications for other studies of dust and galaxy evolution.&nbsp; Postdoctoral researcher Dyas Utomo investigated the effects of averaging an entire galaxy together when measuring the dust mass and temperature, as must be done for distant galaxies.&nbsp; Because the dust temperature varies within a galaxy and hotter dust emits more brightly than cooler dust, there is a bias to overestimate the dust temperature (and thereby underestimate the dust mass) when treating the whole galaxy as one measurement.&nbsp; Our work demonstrated that this overestimate depends on the galaxy properties and how clumpy the star formation is within the galaxy.&nbsp; Postdoctoral researcher Dr. Jeremy Chastenet performed the first benchmark of dust models in an extragalactic environment, to compare the results of different approaches to interpreting the infrared emission from dust.&nbsp; This work demonstrated that many models produce dust masses that are inconsistent with the available abundance of heavy elements.&nbsp; Our work showed that these inconsistencies are tied to the way the models are calibrated using Milky Way observations.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our project enabled several additional studies of gas and dust in nearby galaxies. Eric Koch used Very Large Array observations of M31 and M33 to investigate the amount of cold, opaque, atomic gas that may be missed in tracing gas in galaxies and showed that contrary to previous results, this difficult-to-trace gas does not appear to be pervasive. Jeremy Chastenet studied the abundance of the smallest carbonaceous dust grains in the Magellanic Clouds and showed that their abundance varies due to the destruction of the small grains in regions of intense radiation fields and/or ionized gas.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Beyond the scientific goals of our project, we also aimed to increase participation of underrepresented groups in STEM PhD programs by participation in the Cal-Bridge mentoring program.&nbsp; This program is designed to provide mentorship and support to students from underrepresented groups at Cal State institutions to encourage them to apply to graduate school in Astronomy and Physics. co-PI Sandstrom mentored three students over the course of the project.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/09/2021<br>      Modified by: Karin&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sandstrom</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Prior to forming new stars, gas in the interstellar medium (ISM) of galaxies must reach high densities and cool temperatures to allow gravitational collapse of regions of a cloud. In this process, low density gas where hydrogen is primarily atomic becomes denser and eventually transitions to being primarily molecular.  The physics of this process are critical to understanding how galaxies form new stars out of their reservoir of interstellar gas. Dust grains appear to play a key role in this process because they block the molecule-dissociating UV radiation from other nearby young stars and they provide a catalyst for the chemical reaction that creates molecular hydrogen.     In this project, our goal was to provide new and comprehensive measurements of the amount of dust relative to gas in the ISM of nearby galaxies and to characterize the role dust plays in the transition from atomic to molecular gas.  To do this, we uniformly analyzed large datasets of nearby galaxy mapping at infrared, millimeter, and radio wavelengths. In particular, we used infrared observations tracing dust emission from the Wide Field Infrared Sky Explorer and the Herschel Space Observatory; millimeter observations tracing molecular gas from several observatories including the Atacama Large Millimeter Array; and radio observations tracing atomic hydrogen from the Very Large Array. In total, we have created maps of the dust mass for approximately 1000 galaxies and maps of the atomic hydrogen for approximately 500.  We are in the process of preparing these reduced datasets for permanent archiving.  We have also used the maps to facilitate a number of investigations into the state of the gas and dust in galaxies.    One of the major outcomes from our project is a comprehensive investigation of the ?dust-to-metals ratio? in nearby galaxies. The dust-to-metals ratio represents the fraction of the available heavy elements that are in dust grains. This quantity is deeply connected to the processes that form, destroy, and alter dust grains.  Graduate student I-Da Chiang led two papers focused on measuring the dust-to-metals ratio and its spatial variation within galaxies as part of his PhD thesis. From these studies we learned that: 1) dust-to-metals is not the same everywhere - it increases when heavy elements are abundant and in regions where the ISM is denser and colder; 2) the measurement of the dust-to-metals ratio is very dependent on how we trace the amount of molecular gas, and many existing approaches to this issue appear to not work for all galaxies; and 3) with our best knowledge of molecular gas, the dust-to-metals ratio appears to be consistent with models that require rapid growth of dust in the ISM.    A key part of our project involved investigating the accuracy of various approaches to measuring dust mass in galaxies.  This is critical for measuring dust-to-metals, but it also has important implications for other studies of dust and galaxy evolution.  Postdoctoral researcher Dyas Utomo investigated the effects of averaging an entire galaxy together when measuring the dust mass and temperature, as must be done for distant galaxies.  Because the dust temperature varies within a galaxy and hotter dust emits more brightly than cooler dust, there is a bias to overestimate the dust temperature (and thereby underestimate the dust mass) when treating the whole galaxy as one measurement.  Our work demonstrated that this overestimate depends on the galaxy properties and how clumpy the star formation is within the galaxy.  Postdoctoral researcher Dr. Jeremy Chastenet performed the first benchmark of dust models in an extragalactic environment, to compare the results of different approaches to interpreting the infrared emission from dust.  This work demonstrated that many models produce dust masses that are inconsistent with the available abundance of heavy elements.  Our work showed that these inconsistencies are tied to the way the models are calibrated using Milky Way observations.      Our project enabled several additional studies of gas and dust in nearby galaxies. Eric Koch used Very Large Array observations of M31 and M33 to investigate the amount of cold, opaque, atomic gas that may be missed in tracing gas in galaxies and showed that contrary to previous results, this difficult-to-trace gas does not appear to be pervasive. Jeremy Chastenet studied the abundance of the smallest carbonaceous dust grains in the Magellanic Clouds and showed that their abundance varies due to the destruction of the small grains in regions of intense radiation fields and/or ionized gas.    Beyond the scientific goals of our project, we also aimed to increase participation of underrepresented groups in STEM PhD programs by participation in the Cal-Bridge mentoring program.  This program is designed to provide mentorship and support to students from underrepresented groups at Cal State institutions to encourage them to apply to graduate school in Astronomy and Physics. co-PI Sandstrom mentored three students over the course of the project.             Last Modified: 04/09/2021       Submitted by: Karin M Sandstrom]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
