<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2016 Plasma Processing Science: Plasmas with Complex Interactions: Exploiting the Non-Equilibrium.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Humanity faces significant grand challenges in the areas of energy, human health, and environmental sustainability, and low temperature plasmas are at the heart of many technologies promising to provide solutions for these grand challenges. This award will provide support for students to participate in one of the most important biennial conference series in the field of low temperature plasmas, the 2016 Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing Science to be held July 24-29, 2016, at Proctor Academy, Andover, NH.  The conference will feature a comprehensive program that will highlight the most cutting edge scientific advances in low temperature plasma science and will explore the applications of low temperature plasma technology relative to many grand societal challenges.  Associated with the conference is a weekend-long Gordon Research Seminar, which features attendance limited to graduate students and post-doctoral associates, allowing for scientific interaction in a non-threatening environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award will be used to provide registration fee support for US students and postdocs to attend the conference and the seminar.  Seminar participation of 22 students and postdocs, and further conference participation of 5 students and postdocs will be facilitated by this award. The special format of the Gordon Conferences, with programmed discussion sessions and ample time for informal gatherings in the afternoons and evenings, will provide for a great learning environment for the students and postdocs, as well as a fertile atmosphere of brainstorming and creative thinking for all of the attendees.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1615381</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Bruggeman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter J Bruggeman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbruggem@me.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126268391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000625582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Operational Summary</span></strong></p> <p>The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Plasma Processing Science were held at Proctor Academy in Andover, New Hampshire from July 23-29, 2016.&nbsp;&nbsp; The meeting covered a variety of scientific topics and the content presented was highly rated by participants.</p> <p class="Default"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Participants</span></strong></p> <p>The Conference was well-attended with 116 participants. Scientists from academia represented 89% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 7% and those from industry totaled 4%. The meeting also attracted a strong mix of young investigators and senior scientists.&nbsp; Students and post-docs accounted for 46% of all attendees. Approximately 17% of the participants at the 2016 meeting were women.</p> <p class="Default"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Seminar Participants</strong></span></p> <p>The Seminar was well-attended with 47 participants. Scientists from academia represented 100% of the participants. Students and post docs combined accounted for 96% of all attendees. Approximately 25% of the participants at the 2016 seminar were women.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Program &ndash; GRC</span></strong></p> <p>Plasma processing science is at the core of numerous technologies for many applications ranging from material synthesis, energy conversion and storage to the interaction of plasmas with biological systems. The 2016 Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing highlighted the most cutting edge scientific advances in these areas and identified new emerging trends and hot topics. Plasma processing science is nowadays an extremely interdisciplinary field embracing the disciplines of physics, chemistry, biology and engineering. Plasmas exhibit a strong non-equilibrium nature, which enables new reaction and synthesis routes. This unique property of plasmas led to the introduction of dry etching in microelectronics and more recently to the emerging field of plasma medicine. A common aspect is the complex interaction of non-equilibrium plasmas across aggregate interfaces to solids and liquids</p> <p>The program of the 2016 Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing was devoted to identifying future interdisciplinary areas, where plasmas will play a role. Examples are the use of plasma for soft ionisation, the cross fertilization of plasma technology and nuclear fusion science and the use of extremely short pulsed plasmas to trigger chemistry in liquids and biological systems. The conference brought together leaders in the field with junior investigators and graduate students. The special format of the Gordon Conferences, with programmed discussion sessions and ample time for informal gatherings in the afternoons and evenings, provided for a fertile atmosphere of brainstorming and creative thinking among the attendees.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Program &ndash; GRS</span></strong></p> <p>The Gordon Research Seminar on Plasma Processing Science is an international forum primarily intended for advanced graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and junior scientists currently pursuing cutting-edge research within the field of Plasma Processing Science. This Seminar preceded the larger Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing Science (July 24-29, 2016). <br /> <br /> The program of the 2016 Gordon Research Seminar on Plasma Processing Science highlighted recent progress concerning breakthrough innovations in the fields of plasma medicine, plasma interaction with liquids and plasma assisted nanofabrication. Participants were encouraged to showcase and present their pioneering and unpublished research, discuss recent advancements and future directions with established leaders in the field, and build networks with their peers that will lead to a lifetime of scientific collaboration and achievement. Furthermore, in order to promote the discussion of cutting-edge research, Gordon Research Seminars are officially "off-the-record,&rdquo; with no abstracts or proceedings published before, during or after the conference, and ample time is provided between sessions for socializing and informal discussions with fellow attendees. In addition, the 2016 Gordon Research Seminar on Plasma Processing Science featured a mentoring session for graduate students and postdocs that discussed the necessary steps for launching a successful career and the options that are open to PhD holders in the plasma field.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Budget</span></strong></p> <p>Funding provided by the National Science Foundation supported partial registration for 13 graduate students and 2 post docs.&nbsp; Funding provided for the GRS covered full or partial registration fees for 11 graduate students and 2 post docs.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Feedback</span></strong></p> <p>Participants had an opportunity to provide feedback at the end of the Conference. The feedback collected from the meeting was extremely positive. Evaluations included numerous positive remarks regarding the excellence of talks, impressive poster sessions, and many opportunities for discussion.&nbsp; The feedback from the GRS included many positive remarks regarding discussion sessions and poster sessions.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conclusion</span></strong></p> <p class="Default">The contributions received from the National Science Foundation have been critical to the success of the conferences, particularly for enabling graduate students and postdocs to attend this meeting and are having a measurable impact in advancing the frontiers of science worldwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Bruggeman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Operational Summary  The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Plasma Processing Science were held at Proctor Academy in Andover, New Hampshire from July 23-29, 2016.   The meeting covered a variety of scientific topics and the content presented was highly rated by participants. Conference Participants  The Conference was well-attended with 116 participants. Scientists from academia represented 89% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 7% and those from industry totaled 4%. The meeting also attracted a strong mix of young investigators and senior scientists.  Students and post-docs accounted for 46% of all attendees. Approximately 17% of the participants at the 2016 meeting were women. Seminar Participants  The Seminar was well-attended with 47 participants. Scientists from academia represented 100% of the participants. Students and post docs combined accounted for 96% of all attendees. Approximately 25% of the participants at the 2016 seminar were women.  Conference Program &ndash; GRC  Plasma processing science is at the core of numerous technologies for many applications ranging from material synthesis, energy conversion and storage to the interaction of plasmas with biological systems. The 2016 Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing highlighted the most cutting edge scientific advances in these areas and identified new emerging trends and hot topics. Plasma processing science is nowadays an extremely interdisciplinary field embracing the disciplines of physics, chemistry, biology and engineering. Plasmas exhibit a strong non-equilibrium nature, which enables new reaction and synthesis routes. This unique property of plasmas led to the introduction of dry etching in microelectronics and more recently to the emerging field of plasma medicine. A common aspect is the complex interaction of non-equilibrium plasmas across aggregate interfaces to solids and liquids  The program of the 2016 Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing was devoted to identifying future interdisciplinary areas, where plasmas will play a role. Examples are the use of plasma for soft ionisation, the cross fertilization of plasma technology and nuclear fusion science and the use of extremely short pulsed plasmas to trigger chemistry in liquids and biological systems. The conference brought together leaders in the field with junior investigators and graduate students. The special format of the Gordon Conferences, with programmed discussion sessions and ample time for informal gatherings in the afternoons and evenings, provided for a fertile atmosphere of brainstorming and creative thinking among the attendees.  Conference Program &ndash; GRS  The Gordon Research Seminar on Plasma Processing Science is an international forum primarily intended for advanced graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and junior scientists currently pursuing cutting-edge research within the field of Plasma Processing Science. This Seminar preceded the larger Gordon Research Conference on Plasma Processing Science (July 24-29, 2016).     The program of the 2016 Gordon Research Seminar on Plasma Processing Science highlighted recent progress concerning breakthrough innovations in the fields of plasma medicine, plasma interaction with liquids and plasma assisted nanofabrication. Participants were encouraged to showcase and present their pioneering and unpublished research, discuss recent advancements and future directions with established leaders in the field, and build networks with their peers that will lead to a lifetime of scientific collaboration and achievement. Furthermore, in order to promote the discussion of cutting-edge research, Gordon Research Seminars are officially "off-the-record," with no abstracts or proceedings published before, during or after the conference, and ample time is provided between sessions for socializing and informal discussions with fellow attendees. In addition, the 2016 Gordon Research Seminar on Plasma Processing Science featured a mentoring session for graduate students and postdocs that discussed the necessary steps for launching a successful career and the options that are open to PhD holders in the plasma field.  Conference Budget  Funding provided by the National Science Foundation supported partial registration for 13 graduate students and 2 post docs.  Funding provided for the GRS covered full or partial registration fees for 11 graduate students and 2 post docs.  Conference Feedback  Participants had an opportunity to provide feedback at the end of the Conference. The feedback collected from the meeting was extremely positive. Evaluations included numerous positive remarks regarding the excellence of talks, impressive poster sessions, and many opportunities for discussion.  The feedback from the GRS included many positive remarks regarding discussion sessions and poster sessions.  Conclusion The contributions received from the National Science Foundation have been critical to the success of the conferences, particularly for enabling graduate students and postdocs to attend this meeting and are having a measurable impact in advancing the frontiers of science worldwide.       Last Modified: 10/28/2016       Submitted by: Peter J Bruggeman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
