<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Resolution Observations of the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect to Measure the Physics of Distant Clusters of Galaxies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>555205.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>608458</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this program is to measure the physics of distant clusters of galaxies with MUSTANG2, a 215-pixel bolometer camera observing at 3mm wavelength on the Green Bank Telescope.  This will help in understanding of the evolution of structure in the early universe. Broader impacts include training of undergraduate graduate students in astronomical instrumentation, especially those from underrepresented groups.  In addition, members of the team are actively involved in public outreach in the Philadelphia area including star parties, the Philadelphia science festival, and mentoring in low-performing schools.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect, a diminution in the Microwave Background as it passes through clusters, will be observed at 9 arc-second angular resolution.  Other telescopes making such measurements do not have this level of resolution. The authors plan to examine various aspects of cluster physics, including scaling relations, pressure profiles to large radii, and pressure differences in radio bubbles.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1615604</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Devlin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark J Devlin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>devlin@physics.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2155737521</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000199177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Mason</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian S Mason</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmason@nrao.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342446831</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000517203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sievers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan L Sievers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jonathan.sievers@mcgill.ca</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4383464857</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000604714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046396</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[209 South 33rd St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~555205</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~53253</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Clusters of galaxies -- the largest gravitationally-bound objects in the Universe -- serve as cosmological probes and rich astrophysical laboratories for events such as mergers and AGN outbursts, the two most energetic classes of events to happen since the Big Bang.&nbsp; As tracers of the evolution of structure, galaxy clusters are being exploited for cosmology by a host of current and future projects which are now producing large samples of clusters.&nbsp; However, the uncertainty in scaling relations between cluster mass and observables such as their Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (SZE) or X-ray signatures is the dominant systematic limiting cluster cosmology, not the sample sizes.&nbsp; Cross-correlation of these new large samples from the X-ray, optical, and millimeter-wave show dramatic discrepancies attributed to cluster astrophysics and provide tantalizing target lists for high-resolution follow-up.&nbsp; For example, some clusters strongly detected in the optical have no SZE signal in millimeter-wave surveys due to in-filling from radio sources.&nbsp; Pairs of clusters detected in surveys have emission which could be associated with filamentary structure from the cosmic web.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;MUSTANG2 SZE observations, combined with X-ray images, have allowed us to determine the dynamical state and thermal properties of intracluster gas in even the highest redshift clusters.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>MUSTANG2 is a 215-pixel bolometer array of superconducting transition edge detectors providing background-limited performance at 90 GHz. Operating on the GBT, the 4.3 arcmin field of view enables high-precision resolved cluster observations. MUSTANG2 has measured the SZE effect in moderate redshift clusters with an integrated signal to noise of over 100 sigma, far beyond the capabilities of cluster survey instruments such as ACT and SPT.&nbsp; This has ushered in a new era of precision SZE measurements.&nbsp;</p> <p>MUSTANG2 has produced high-resolution, 15 micro-K RMS images of the SZE in galaxy clusters.&nbsp; To date, MUSTANG2 has imaged over 40 clusters and has been able to measure cluster pressure profiles out to a radius of 3 arcmin.&nbsp; This statistically useful sample of clusters is essential to characterize the scatter in cluster-mass/SZE observable scaling relations due to mergers, evolution, and AGN feedback.&nbsp; &nbsp;Much of our major results come from cross-correlating MUSTANG2 clusters with other surveys like those from MaDCoWs and ACT.&nbsp; We have found that the richness measure (number of galaxies in a cluster) of cluster mass by MaDCoWs does not appear to be a good proxy for the cluster mass.&nbsp; When we combine our work with the ACT cluster catalog, this is even more apparent.&nbsp; Our high-resolution measurements show that in-filling of the SZ signal from unresolved radio sources may be biasing the ACT cluster catalog.&nbsp; The high-resolution MUSTANG2 images are able to directly detect the point sources and independently fit for the SZ signal.&nbsp; This ongoing work may provide a path to using cluster more effectively to extract cosmology.</p> <p>Our team has 11 referred publications as part of this program.&nbsp; In addition to the cluster work described above, we have supported work on dust and star formation in our galaxy, observed the time evolution of a stellar flare, and even looked at the Moon to understand the mineral properties just beneath the surface.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Devlin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Clusters of galaxies -- the largest gravitationally-bound objects in the Universe -- serve as cosmological probes and rich astrophysical laboratories for events such as mergers and AGN outbursts, the two most energetic classes of events to happen since the Big Bang.  As tracers of the evolution of structure, galaxy clusters are being exploited for cosmology by a host of current and future projects which are now producing large samples of clusters.  However, the uncertainty in scaling relations between cluster mass and observables such as their Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (SZE) or X-ray signatures is the dominant systematic limiting cluster cosmology, not the sample sizes.  Cross-correlation of these new large samples from the X-ray, optical, and millimeter-wave show dramatic discrepancies attributed to cluster astrophysics and provide tantalizing target lists for high-resolution follow-up.  For example, some clusters strongly detected in the optical have no SZE signal in millimeter-wave surveys due to in-filling from radio sources.  Pairs of clusters detected in surveys have emission which could be associated with filamentary structure from the cosmic web.    MUSTANG2 SZE observations, combined with X-ray images, have allowed us to determine the dynamical state and thermal properties of intracluster gas in even the highest redshift clusters.      MUSTANG2 is a 215-pixel bolometer array of superconducting transition edge detectors providing background-limited performance at 90 GHz. Operating on the GBT, the 4.3 arcmin field of view enables high-precision resolved cluster observations. MUSTANG2 has measured the SZE effect in moderate redshift clusters with an integrated signal to noise of over 100 sigma, far beyond the capabilities of cluster survey instruments such as ACT and SPT.  This has ushered in a new era of precision SZE measurements.   MUSTANG2 has produced high-resolution, 15 micro-K RMS images of the SZE in galaxy clusters.  To date, MUSTANG2 has imaged over 40 clusters and has been able to measure cluster pressure profiles out to a radius of 3 arcmin.  This statistically useful sample of clusters is essential to characterize the scatter in cluster-mass/SZE observable scaling relations due to mergers, evolution, and AGN feedback.   Much of our major results come from cross-correlating MUSTANG2 clusters with other surveys like those from MaDCoWs and ACT.  We have found that the richness measure (number of galaxies in a cluster) of cluster mass by MaDCoWs does not appear to be a good proxy for the cluster mass.  When we combine our work with the ACT cluster catalog, this is even more apparent.  Our high-resolution measurements show that in-filling of the SZ signal from unresolved radio sources may be biasing the ACT cluster catalog.  The high-resolution MUSTANG2 images are able to directly detect the point sources and independently fit for the SZ signal.  This ongoing work may provide a path to using cluster more effectively to extract cosmology.  Our team has 11 referred publications as part of this program.  In addition to the cluster work described above, we have supported work on dust and star formation in our galaxy, observed the time evolution of a stellar flare, and even looked at the Moon to understand the mineral properties just beneath the surface.          Last Modified: 12/09/2020       Submitted by: Mark J Devlin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
