<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarship Support for the 2016 Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>148856.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>148856</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Janice Cuny</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) supports student attendance at and development of the Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing. The Tapia Conference series highlights the technical achievements of diverse researchers in computing. It provides a unique forum to support diverse students (undergraduates and graduate students) and professionals. The conference programs include invited speakers, workshops, birds-of-a-feather sessions, panels, a student poster competition and a doctoral consortium. The programs allow leadership development activities for the students as well as young professionals. Moreover, they include significant time for networking about research collaborations and professional development. This proposal will support student scholarships for the conference and the doctoral consortium in 2016.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1615356</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valerie</FirstName>
<LastName>Taylor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valerie E Taylor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vtaylor2@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9795743722</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000307769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Association Computing Machinery</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>101210799</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128697440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 Penn Plaza</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 701]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064931736</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATION FOR COMPUTING MACHINERY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064931736</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1470 William D Fitch Pkwy]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~148856</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The funding was used to support student scholarships and participants in the doctoral consortium at the 2016 Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Conference, which took place September 14-17, 2016 in Austin, Texas. &nbsp;</p> <p>The Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Conference is the main conference for celebrating the diversity that exists in computing. &nbsp;The conference mission is to bring together undergraduate and graduate students, professionals, and faculty in computer science and computer engineering from all backgrounds and ethnicities to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Celebrate</strong> the diversity that currently exists in computer science and computer engineering.</li> <li><strong>Connect</strong> with others with common backgrounds, ethnicities, disabilities, and gender so as to create communities that extend beyond the conference.</li> <li><strong>Receive advice</strong> from and make useful contacts with computer science and computer engineering leaders in academia and industry.</li> <li><strong>Be inspired</strong> by great presentations and conversations with successful people in computer science and computer engineering who have similar backgrounds, ethnicities, disabilities, and gender to the attendees.</li> </ul> <p>The Tapia Conference has grown from 164 attendees in 2001 (the first conference) to 965 attendees in 2016.&nbsp; The <strong>2016 Tapia Conference</strong> was held in Austin, Texas with the following attendee demographics:</p> <ul> <li>53% women</li> <li>29% Black/African American </li> <li>23% Hispanic/Latino </li> <li>21% White/Caucasian</li> <li>13% Asian/Southeast Asian</li> <li>1% Native American/Native Alaskan/Native Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</li> <li>4% Multiracial</li> <li>11% Persons with Disabilities &nbsp;</li> <li>2% Active/Inactive U.S. Military</li> </ul> <p>In addition, 55% of the conference attendees were students, of which 66% were undergraduate students.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to technical talks, the Tapia Conference series generally includes the following components:</p> <ul> <li><em>Student-oriented panels</em> focused on topics such as graduate school, resume writing, and career paths in computing.&nbsp; </li> <li><em>Professional development workshops</em> focused on topics such as navigating the tenure process, climbing the corporate ladder, and proposal writing.</li> <li><em>Birds of a feather sessions</em> that facilitate the formation of communities focused on particular topics related to diversity in computing.</li> <li><em>Leadership panels </em>that include top leaders that can provide strategies for effective leadership based upon experience.</li> <li><em>Industry Panels </em>that focus on the latest areas of technological innovation and research.</li> <li><em>Student poster competition </em>that allows students to present their latest research results and compete based upon presentation of their research and the ability to answer questions.</li> <li><em>Doctoral Consortium </em>that takes place the day before the first day of the conference and allows senior doctoral students to present their research to experts in their area and receive very valuable and detailed feedback.</li> <li><em>Supporter information area </em>that allows conference supporters to disseminate materials particular to their organization or university and talk one-on-one with conference attendees.</li> </ul> <p>Speaker hightlights from <strong>Tapia 2016</strong> include the following:</p> <ul> <li><em>Melanie Moses</em>, Associate Professor of Computer Science at the University of New Mexico and External Faculty at the Santa Fe Institute</li> <li><em>Raquel Romano</em>, Senior Software Engineer, Google</li> <li><em>Daniel Sonnenfeld</em>, Technical Program Management Director, Salesforce</li> <li><em>Joseph Teran</em>, Professor of Applied Mathematics at UCLA</li> <li><em>Panel of Chief Diversity Officers</em> from HP, Microsoft, IBM, and Capital One</li> </ul> <p>The 2016 Richard A. Tapia Achievement Award for Scientific Scholarship, Civic Science and Diversifying Computing award recipient was David Patterson, retired professor at University of California at Berkeley.</p> <p>Based upon the <strong>Tapia 2016</strong> conference survey,</p> <ul> <li>85% of the students agreed or strongly agreed that attending Tapia 2016 increased their dedication to completing their degree in computing </li> <li>93% of the students agreed or strongly agreed that they found Tapia 2016 inspiring with respect to learning about the various opportunities in computing</li> <li>97% of the students agreed or strongly agreed that attending Tapia 2016 provided an opportunity to make new connections</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Valerie&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taylor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112860512_Speaker--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112860512_Speaker--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tapia 2016 Plenary Speaker"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112860512_Speaker--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tapia 2016 Plenary Speaker"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Daniel Sonnenfeld, Technical Program Management Director, Salesforce, giving a plenary presentation at Tapia 2016.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CMD-IT</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Valerie&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taylor</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tapia 2016 Plenary Speaker</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112941906_Attendees--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112941906_Attendees--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tapia 2016 Attendees"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112941906_Attendees--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tapia 2016 Attendees"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees at the 2016 Tapia Conference</div> <div class="imageCredit">CMD-IT</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Valerie&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taylor</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tapia 2016 Attendees</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112676453_PosterSession--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112676453_PosterSession--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tapia 2016 Poster Session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504112676453_PosterSession--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tapia 2016 Poster Session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Poster presenter discussion his research poster with a conference participant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CMD-IT</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Valerie&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taylor</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tapia 2016 Poster Session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504113031861_Attendees2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504113031861_Attendees2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tapia 2016 Attendees"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1615356/1615356_10425223_1504113031861_Attendees2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tapia 2016 Attendees"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees at the 2016 Tapia Conference</div> <div class="imageCredit">CMD-IT</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Valerie&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taylor</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tapia 2016 Attendees</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The funding was used to support student scholarships and participants in the doctoral consortium at the 2016 Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Conference, which took place September 14-17, 2016 in Austin, Texas.    The Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Conference is the main conference for celebrating the diversity that exists in computing.  The conference mission is to bring together undergraduate and graduate students, professionals, and faculty in computer science and computer engineering from all backgrounds and ethnicities to:  Celebrate the diversity that currently exists in computer science and computer engineering. Connect with others with common backgrounds, ethnicities, disabilities, and gender so as to create communities that extend beyond the conference. Receive advice from and make useful contacts with computer science and computer engineering leaders in academia and industry. Be inspired by great presentations and conversations with successful people in computer science and computer engineering who have similar backgrounds, ethnicities, disabilities, and gender to the attendees.   The Tapia Conference has grown from 164 attendees in 2001 (the first conference) to 965 attendees in 2016.  The 2016 Tapia Conference was held in Austin, Texas with the following attendee demographics:  53% women 29% Black/African American  23% Hispanic/Latino  21% White/Caucasian 13% Asian/Southeast Asian 1% Native American/Native Alaskan/Native Hawaiian/Pacific Islander 4% Multiracial 11% Persons with Disabilities   2% Active/Inactive U.S. Military   In addition, 55% of the conference attendees were students, of which 66% were undergraduate students.   In addition to technical talks, the Tapia Conference series generally includes the following components:  Student-oriented panels focused on topics such as graduate school, resume writing, and career paths in computing.   Professional development workshops focused on topics such as navigating the tenure process, climbing the corporate ladder, and proposal writing. Birds of a feather sessions that facilitate the formation of communities focused on particular topics related to diversity in computing. Leadership panels that include top leaders that can provide strategies for effective leadership based upon experience. Industry Panels that focus on the latest areas of technological innovation and research. Student poster competition that allows students to present their latest research results and compete based upon presentation of their research and the ability to answer questions. Doctoral Consortium that takes place the day before the first day of the conference and allows senior doctoral students to present their research to experts in their area and receive very valuable and detailed feedback. Supporter information area that allows conference supporters to disseminate materials particular to their organization or university and talk one-on-one with conference attendees.   Speaker hightlights from Tapia 2016 include the following:  Melanie Moses, Associate Professor of Computer Science at the University of New Mexico and External Faculty at the Santa Fe Institute Raquel Romano, Senior Software Engineer, Google Daniel Sonnenfeld, Technical Program Management Director, Salesforce Joseph Teran, Professor of Applied Mathematics at UCLA Panel of Chief Diversity Officers from HP, Microsoft, IBM, and Capital One   The 2016 Richard A. Tapia Achievement Award for Scientific Scholarship, Civic Science and Diversifying Computing award recipient was David Patterson, retired professor at University of California at Berkeley.  Based upon the Tapia 2016 conference survey,  85% of the students agreed or strongly agreed that attending Tapia 2016 increased their dedication to completing their degree in computing  93% of the students agreed or strongly agreed that they found Tapia 2016 inspiring with respect to learning about the various opportunities in computing 97% of the students agreed or strongly agreed that attending Tapia 2016 provided an opportunity to make new connections              Last Modified: 08/30/2017       Submitted by: Valerie E Taylor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
