<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CDS&amp;E: Renaissance Simulations Laboratory to Model and Explore the First Galaxies in the Universe</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>171469.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171469</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Ajhar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eajhar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927456</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A great challenge in astrophysics is to understand in detail how the initial smooth distribution of matter in the early Universe formed the first galaxies.  Complementing observations of real galaxies, researchers use computational simulations to model the early Universe and study the results.  This process allows one to learn how these first galaxies might have formed.  However, the sheer size and complexity of such galaxy simulations present their own challenge as a single research group lacks the capacity to explore them fully.  As a result, maximizing the scientific value of simulations demands new tools and services designed to foster the growth of a collaborative, multi-group research community.  This project aims to develop and use a new virtual laboratory to enable transformative scientific inquiry on new and existing galaxy simulations, some of which were produced by prior NSF support.  Enabling public access and unrestricted analysis and fostering a collaborative environment for sharing technology and results will ensure that galaxy simulations continue to be valuable within and beyond the research group that originally conducted them.  This project addresses the national imperative to develop US cyber infrastructure and to develop US leadership in scientific research in astrophysics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More technically, with prior NSF support the investigators used the Blue Waters supercomputer at the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA) to perform the Renaissance Simulations: among the largest, most detailed simulations of the formation and evolution of the first galaxies to date.  The Renaissance Simulations yielded a sample of over 3,000 high redshift (20 &gt; z &gt; 7) galaxies and were specifically designed to simulate the dominant sources responsible for preheating the intergalactic medium and reionization at an unprecedented level of detail.  This project plans two related activities: (1) further analysis of the Renaissance Simulations; and (2) the creation of an open-data access portal, the Renaissance Simulation Laboratory (RSL), which will provide open access to this unique data corpus along with associated data analysis tools for the astronomical research community.  Driving its design and utility, the investigators will use the RSL to carry out their own research investigations.  The investigators' research processes will become part of the RSL in the form of executable "Jupyter" notebooks.  The Jupyter Notebook, an evolution of the iPython Notebook, is a fundamental part of the RSL and is ushering in the era of open science.  The investigators' use of Docker containers is equally compelling.  By containerizing Jupyter Notebooks which execute pre-programmed data analysis workflows the investigators are able to bring computation to the data and share how they obtain their scientific results, a key step toward reproducible science.  Users will have the option of downloading notebooks and associated data to their own platforms or executing them on San Diego Supercomputer Center and NCSA high performance platforms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1615001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Turk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Turk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mjturk@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000685745</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kacper</FirstName>
<LastName>Kowalik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kacper Kowalik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kowalikk@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000711041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~171469</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project analyzed data from a suite of state-of-the-art supercomputer simulations to improve our understanding how the universe transitioned from one with no stars and galaxies whatsoever to one with them. We are particularly interested in how the first generation of galaxies form, and how the UV light from their young stars reionize the universe within the first billion years as observed. According to the Renaissance Simulations, as they are called, the first galaxies form from the ashes of the first generation of primordial stars which enrich the universe with heavy elements and produce the first stellar mass black holes. The simulations were performed on the Blue Waters supercomputer at the National Center for Supercomputer Applications at the University of Illinois. A first analysis of the Renaissance Simulations under a previous NSF grant yielded over a half dozen scientific publications. In this project we opened the data up to a broader community of researchers to unlock its full discovery potential, and to stimulate new research. This research was facilitated by an open science software resource called the Renaissance Simulation Laboratory, which provides data and analysis tools over the web.&nbsp; The project resulted in an additional 9 journal publications exploring different aspects of the first galaxies, including: (1) how they would look to the Hubble and James Webb Space Telescopes, (2) how they pollute the universe with heavy elements forged in massive stars that explode as supernova, (3) how they emit ultraviolet light into space that eventually ionizes all the hydrogen in the universe, as observed.</p> <p><br />An important discovery we found in the data has implications on the mechanism by which supermassive black holes form within the first billion years of the universe, as observed the population of distant bright quasars. We found that certain galaxies assemble so fast that ordinary star formation is suppressed. Rather, a large amount of pristine gas assembles with conditions conducive to the formation of single supermassive stars. These would collapse to black holes in a few million years, making them excellent seed to accrete even more gas, eventually becoming the billion solar mass black holes we observe. This work was published in the prestigious international journal Nature in early 2019.</p> <p><br />The project provided a training ground for over a dozen young astrophysics researchers and students, including several undergraduate students who got their first research experience.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;Turk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245166229_img2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245166229_img2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Central region of atomic cooling halo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245166229_img2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Central region of atomic cooling halo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image shows the inner 30 light-years of a dark matter halo in a cluster of young galaxies.  The rotating gaseous disk breaks apart into three clumps that collapse under their own gravity to form supermassive stars.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Wise, Georgia Tech</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;Turk</div> <div class="imageTitle">Central region of atomic cooling halo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245090181_img3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245090181_img3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="First galaxy image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245090181_img3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="First galaxy image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A simulated z = 15 high redshift protogalaxy and its photometric appearance with Hubble Space Telescope and the James Webb Space Telescope.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Norman and B. Smith, UCSD</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;Turk</div> <div class="imageTitle">First galaxy image</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245009452_img1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245009452_img1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Renaissance Simulation Laboratory Home Page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245009452_img1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Renaissance Simulation Laboratory Home Page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Renaissance Simulation Laboratory Home Page</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Norman and B. Smith, UCSD, M. Turk and K. Kowalik, UIUC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;Turk</div> <div class="imageTitle">Renaissance Simulation Laboratory Home Page</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245248836_img4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245248836_img4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Large scale environment of atomic cooling halo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1615001/1615001_10438531_1611245248836_img4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Large scale environment of atomic cooling halo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image shows a 30,000 light-year region from the Renaissance Simulation, centered on a cluster of young galaxies that generate radiation (white) and metals (green) while heating the surrounding gas.  A dark matter halo just outside this heated region forms three supermassive stars (inset).</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Wise, Georgia Tech</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;Turk</div> <div class="imageTitle">Large scale environment of atomic cooling halo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project analyzed data from a suite of state-of-the-art supercomputer simulations to improve our understanding how the universe transitioned from one with no stars and galaxies whatsoever to one with them. We are particularly interested in how the first generation of galaxies form, and how the UV light from their young stars reionize the universe within the first billion years as observed. According to the Renaissance Simulations, as they are called, the first galaxies form from the ashes of the first generation of primordial stars which enrich the universe with heavy elements and produce the first stellar mass black holes. The simulations were performed on the Blue Waters supercomputer at the National Center for Supercomputer Applications at the University of Illinois. A first analysis of the Renaissance Simulations under a previous NSF grant yielded over a half dozen scientific publications. In this project we opened the data up to a broader community of researchers to unlock its full discovery potential, and to stimulate new research. This research was facilitated by an open science software resource called the Renaissance Simulation Laboratory, which provides data and analysis tools over the web.  The project resulted in an additional 9 journal publications exploring different aspects of the first galaxies, including: (1) how they would look to the Hubble and James Webb Space Telescopes, (2) how they pollute the universe with heavy elements forged in massive stars that explode as supernova, (3) how they emit ultraviolet light into space that eventually ionizes all the hydrogen in the universe, as observed.   An important discovery we found in the data has implications on the mechanism by which supermassive black holes form within the first billion years of the universe, as observed the population of distant bright quasars. We found that certain galaxies assemble so fast that ordinary star formation is suppressed. Rather, a large amount of pristine gas assembles with conditions conducive to the formation of single supermassive stars. These would collapse to black holes in a few million years, making them excellent seed to accrete even more gas, eventually becoming the billion solar mass black holes we observe. This work was published in the prestigious international journal Nature in early 2019.   The project provided a training ground for over a dozen young astrophysics researchers and students, including several undergraduate students who got their first research experience.       Last Modified: 02/01/2021       Submitted by: Matthew Turk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
