<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Non-thermal Radio Halos of Spiral Galaxies as Clues to Galaxy Evolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To understand how stars like the Sun and planets like Earth came to be, we must understand how galaxies, such as our Milky Way, form and evolve. This project is an attempt to understand how interstellar gas and energetic particles are ejected from galaxy disks, where most of the gas and stars are found, and interact with the galaxy halo.  This cyclical process is important for understanding how star formation proceeds in galaxies, and the rate at which galaxies grew when they were forming.  The study makes use of radio images from the NSF-funded Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array (VLA) and the Green Bank Telescope (GBT), optical data from the Apache Point 3.5-meter telescope, as well as archival infrared data.  The project will provide opportunities for two PhD student theses at Hispanic Serving Institutions, and the PIs will also contribute to a training program run by the National Radio Astronomy Observatory for faculty at small colleges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Galaxy growth and evolution depend on both the acquisition of gas from the galaxy environment and energetic outflows from disks. The detailed physics of these processes needs to be understood, and nearby edge-on galaxies are the best objects where it is possible to cleanly separate disk and halo components. The project leverages a major new survey of radio continuum emission from edge-on galaxies called CHANG-ES (Continuum Halos in Nearby Galaxies: an EVLA Survey). The first goal is to further our understanding of the dynamics of disk-halo flows by assessing the role of non-thermal gas pressure gradients in galaxy halos, using radio maps made from the VLA and GBT.  The second goal focuses on identifying sites of cosmic ray (CR) injection and propagation into galaxy halos.  For this, the spatial variation of the non-thermal spectral index will be mapped, after robustly separating thermal and non-thermal radio emission using CHANG-ES maps in conjunction with infrared data and H-alpha images.  The third science goal is to examine the connection between CR outflows and disk-halo cycling of thermal gas, and whether this relation depends on factors such as star formation rate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1616513</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Rand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard J Rand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rjr@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052772073</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000464734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868853094</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 Lomas Blvd, Suite 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~275750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project resulted in two significant contributions to the reduction and analysis of data from radio telescopes by UNM graduate student Tim Braun.&nbsp; The first is software for the reduction of data from a new, broadband receiver on NRAO&rsquo;s Green Bank Telescope (GBT).&nbsp; This software was used to create radio maps at a wavelength of 6cm for over 30 edge-on spiral galaxies.&nbsp; The second is vital contributions to state-of-the-art software used to combine data from the GBT and the Very Large Array (VLA), necessary to make radio maps of cosmic sources with high-resolution and complete information about the distribution of radio emission.&nbsp; The software was used to create a radio map of the combined GBT and VLA data from the iconic edge-on spiral galaxy NGC 891.&nbsp; We should be able to go on and create such maps for many more edge-on galaxies.</p> <p>The scientific goal of this project in creating such maps is to understand the origin of so-called lagging halos of spiral galaxies, wherein the speed with which interstellar gas rotates in such galaxies decreases with height above the midplane.&nbsp; The origin of this effect is not clear.&nbsp; It is known that in spiral galaxies with sufficient star forming activity that a cycling of gas upward from the midplane occurs.&nbsp; Our aforementioned maps can be used to test one important possible explanation &ndash; gradients of interstellar pressure may be effective in pushing gas outward as it cycles upwards from the disk.&nbsp; The most important sources of pressure involve the magnetic field of a galaxy and can be measured from our radio maps.&nbsp; This requires three-dimensional modeling of the magnetic field strength, which can be achieved by predicting the radio emission for a certain magnetic field distribution and comparing it with the actual radio emission from a galaxy.&nbsp; Braun adapted other software to create the modeled magnetic field distribution.&nbsp; We are almost in a position to apply this modeling to our radio map of NGC 891 and test this origin of lagging halos.</p> <p>This work was mostly done as part of a larger collaboration called CHANG-ES (Continuum Halos of Nearby Galaxies &ndash; an EVLA Study), which involved radio mapping of 35 edge-on spirals. &nbsp;Braun also learned how to reduce radio data from the VLA and did so for data from two galaxies in the sample.&nbsp; PI Rand also made contributions to four other projects within this collaboration.&nbsp; This NSF grant was a Collaborative Research grant with R. Walterbos of NMSU, and Rand contributed to two papers by his student C. Vargas, including evidence that edge-on galaxies are not transparent at infrared wavelengths.</p> <p>Rand contributed to an NRAO summer program called the Chautauqua Short Course, designed to expose small college faculty to radio astronomy telescopes and research.&nbsp; He lectured on interstellar gas and star formation in galaxies using radio telescopes.&nbsp; He also participated in a UNM summer program to expose students interested in STEM majors to research in STEM.&nbsp; He lectured on radio astronomy telescopes and techniques and helped lead a field trip to the VLA for several such students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Rand</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project resulted in two significant contributions to the reduction and analysis of data from radio telescopes by UNM graduate student Tim Braun.  The first is software for the reduction of data from a new, broadband receiver on NRAO’s Green Bank Telescope (GBT).  This software was used to create radio maps at a wavelength of 6cm for over 30 edge-on spiral galaxies.  The second is vital contributions to state-of-the-art software used to combine data from the GBT and the Very Large Array (VLA), necessary to make radio maps of cosmic sources with high-resolution and complete information about the distribution of radio emission.  The software was used to create a radio map of the combined GBT and VLA data from the iconic edge-on spiral galaxy NGC 891.  We should be able to go on and create such maps for many more edge-on galaxies.  The scientific goal of this project in creating such maps is to understand the origin of so-called lagging halos of spiral galaxies, wherein the speed with which interstellar gas rotates in such galaxies decreases with height above the midplane.  The origin of this effect is not clear.  It is known that in spiral galaxies with sufficient star forming activity that a cycling of gas upward from the midplane occurs.  Our aforementioned maps can be used to test one important possible explanation &ndash; gradients of interstellar pressure may be effective in pushing gas outward as it cycles upwards from the disk.  The most important sources of pressure involve the magnetic field of a galaxy and can be measured from our radio maps.  This requires three-dimensional modeling of the magnetic field strength, which can be achieved by predicting the radio emission for a certain magnetic field distribution and comparing it with the actual radio emission from a galaxy.  Braun adapted other software to create the modeled magnetic field distribution.  We are almost in a position to apply this modeling to our radio map of NGC 891 and test this origin of lagging halos.  This work was mostly done as part of a larger collaboration called CHANG-ES (Continuum Halos of Nearby Galaxies &ndash; an EVLA Study), which involved radio mapping of 35 edge-on spirals.  Braun also learned how to reduce radio data from the VLA and did so for data from two galaxies in the sample.  PI Rand also made contributions to four other projects within this collaboration.  This NSF grant was a Collaborative Research grant with R. Walterbos of NMSU, and Rand contributed to two papers by his student C. Vargas, including evidence that edge-on galaxies are not transparent at infrared wavelengths.  Rand contributed to an NRAO summer program called the Chautauqua Short Course, designed to expose small college faculty to radio astronomy telescopes and research.  He lectured on interstellar gas and star formation in galaxies using radio telescopes.  He also participated in a UNM summer program to expose students interested in STEM majors to research in STEM.  He lectured on radio astronomy telescopes and techniques and helped lead a field trip to the VLA for several such students.       Last Modified: 11/29/2020       Submitted by: Richard J Rand]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
