<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Tracing the Evolution of Planetary Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>28685.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>28685</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Debris disks, the disks of dust around many stars, are the places where planets form. We have, so far, observed the dust and grains of different brightness in twenty-four debris disks around other stars. We still, however, do not know the detailed properties of these grains. Debris disks are examples for studies of how planetary systems form and change with time. The investigators will use the Gemini South Observatory telescope's Gemini Planet Imager (GPI) Integral Field Spectrograph and Polarimeter to observe the properties of the dust in many debris disks in detail, including grain colors, sizes, compositions, and how thick the grains are in the disks. They will combine these observations with data from other telescopes to provide an overall picture of the properties of the dust grains in different debris disks. The results of this research help to find our Solar System's place with other planetary systems. This program serves the national interest by increasing our understanding of how the early Solar System and other planetary systems formed. The investigators will make a program and video that explain the new GPI instrument, and the science we can learn using it, for the general public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Circumstellar accretion disks (debris disks), the dusty disks around main sequence stars, are the likely sites of planet formation. To date, twenty-four debris disks have been spatially resolved in scattered light, revealing the location of the dust and the reflectivities of the grains. The detailed properties of these grains are, however, not well understood. Debris disks serve as laboratories for studies of planetary system formation and evolution that help to place our Solar System into context with other planetary systems. Gemini Planet Imager Integral Field Spectrograph (IFS) and Polarimeter observations planned by these investigators will provide an unprecedented opportunity to discern grain properties. IFS observations will be sensitive to spectral features and will better constrain the color of the scattered light, therefore constraining the particle composition and size. Polarimetry will allow us to determine the difference between particle size and porosity. This team will combine the GPI observations with complementary high contrast imaging and thermal mapping data from the Hubble Space Telescope, Magellan Adaptive Optics, and Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array to develop holistic models that will significantly improve our understanding of the materials available during the late stages of planetary system formation. The investigators will create a program that showcases the new GPI instrument, including a video to explain the instrument and the science it enables, for the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1616479</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gaspard</FirstName>
<LastName>Duchene</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gaspard Duchene</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gduchene@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104672674</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000547683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1214</Code>
<Text>PLANETARY ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~28685</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF project aimed at obtaining and analyzing images of dusty disks around nearby stars that are the byproducts of planet formation. By combinbin images, spectra and polarization observations over a range of wavelengths, our specific goals were to 1) determine the gfeoemtry of these disks and assess whether there are any signs of dynamical interactions with underlying planetary systems, and 2) characterize the dust populations they host and compare them to Solar System dust, most of which originates in comets and asteroids. To this end, we gathered high contrast, high resolution observations of a dozen disks with the Gemini Planet Imager (GPI), a state-of-the-art instrument installed on the Gemini South telescope in Chile.<br /><br />Throughout this project, we have developed new methods to improve the analysis of GPI observations, which we have combined with numerical studies of the interaction between dust grains and the starlight that illuminate these disks. We have found that dust in disks around other stars behaves in very much the same way as that found in the Solar System and, maybe more surpizingly, that this similarity holds for both cometary dust in the Solar System as it does for dust particles in Jupiter's and Saturn's ring. Since these dust populations are characterized by different compositions and grain sizes, this indicates that the fundamental unifying property of all these populations is that the grains are fluffy aggregates, which in turn appears true for disks around other stars.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Gaspard&nbsp;Duchene</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF project aimed at obtaining and analyzing images of dusty disks around nearby stars that are the byproducts of planet formation. By combinbin images, spectra and polarization observations over a range of wavelengths, our specific goals were to 1) determine the gfeoemtry of these disks and assess whether there are any signs of dynamical interactions with underlying planetary systems, and 2) characterize the dust populations they host and compare them to Solar System dust, most of which originates in comets and asteroids. To this end, we gathered high contrast, high resolution observations of a dozen disks with the Gemini Planet Imager (GPI), a state-of-the-art instrument installed on the Gemini South telescope in Chile.  Throughout this project, we have developed new methods to improve the analysis of GPI observations, which we have combined with numerical studies of the interaction between dust grains and the starlight that illuminate these disks. We have found that dust in disks around other stars behaves in very much the same way as that found in the Solar System and, maybe more surpizingly, that this similarity holds for both cometary dust in the Solar System as it does for dust particles in Jupiter's and Saturn's ring. Since these dust populations are characterized by different compositions and grain sizes, this indicates that the fundamental unifying property of all these populations is that the grains are fluffy aggregates, which in turn appears true for disks around other stars.       Last Modified: 11/07/2018       Submitted by: Gaspard Duchene]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
