<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBE: Small: Technological Con-Artistry: An Analysis of Social Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350386.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350386</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the most serious threats in the world today to the security of cyberspace is "social engineering" - the process by which people with access to critical information regarding information systems security are tricked or manipulated into surrendering such information to unauthorized persons, thereby allowing them access to otherwise secure systems.  To date, little systematic research has been conducted on social engineering.  This research will fill this void by examining who social engineers are, why they engage in social engineering, the processes they use to conceive of and implement social engineering projects, and how they view information privacy and security and justify their behavior.  Further, to understand how organizations affected by social engineering cope with the threat it poses, this research also examines the perspectives on social engineering of IT professionals who oversee organizational computer systems and the security of potentially sensitive information. Through gaining a deeper and more accurate understanding of social engineering - a phenomenon currently shrouded in myth and misconception for many - this research will contribute to important advances in criminology and other fields with a vested interest in learning about the human dimensions of information security and inform the development of information security strategies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study uses a cross-sectional, non-experimental research design that employs both qualitative and quantitative data. The qualitative component involves semi-structured interviews of social engineers "in the wild," security auditors, and IT professionals. Open-ended interview questions will be used to elicit this data. In addition, these interviews will be used to gather quantitative data to measure demographic, computer use, and other social characteristics of social engineers. A set of structured survey questions will be administered by the interviewer as part of the interview process.  To select a sample of subjects, a nonprobability, purposive, "snowball" sampling design is used, which is well-suited for studying "hidden" populations such as social engineers. To analyze the qualitative data, grounded theory techniques are used which involve the transformation of data into concepts, which are then summarized into broader analytic categories, leading to the isolation of patterns in the data. Quantitative data will be analyzed through an assortment of univariate, bivariate, and multivariate techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1616804</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>W</FirstName>
<LastName>Goe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>W R Goe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>goe@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7855326865</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000285021</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Steinmetz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin F Steinmetz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kfsteinmetz@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7855326804</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000709346</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kansas State University</Name>
<CityName>Manhattan</CityName>
<ZipCode>665061100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7855326804</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 FAIRCHILD HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1601 VATTIER STREET]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929773554</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041146432</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kansas State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>665061103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~350386</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The current project studies &ldquo;social engineering&rdquo; or the manipulation of the human element of information security for the purposes of gaining access to sensitive information or computer networks. This research is largely exploratory and involves qualitative, semi-structured interviews with security auditors who make use of social engineering techniques, non-professional social engineers, and IT professionals tasked with protecting organizations from social engineering threats. The final sample includes 54 participants (37 social engineers/security auditors and 17 IT professionals). The project provides a sociologically and criminologically grounded understanding of the phenomenon.</p> <p>Five major analyses of the data have been conducted two date. The first analysis explored definitions of social engineering held by study participants. The results of this analysis indicate that social engineering parallels other forms of fraud or influence and is primarily distinguished by the manner in which participants frame the concept. Participant descriptions indicate that definitions of social engineering are indicative of values and ideologies of its practitioners and reflect views of the world that frame humans and social interaction in computational terms&mdash;that interacting with people is, in some ways, akin to working with computers.</p> <p>The second analysis addresses the question &ldquo;what are the attributes of successful and effective social engineering deceptions according to social engineers?&rdquo; The results of this study indicate that effective social engineering deceptions (1) are well researched, (2) take into account the demographic characteristics, prior experiences, and skillsets of the social engineer, (3) consider the routine activities of the target and incorporate current events, (4) foster a positive relationship with the victim, (5) embed the social engineer within the victim&rsquo;s social networks, (6) appeal to the target for help, (7) provide an incentive for the mark to act, (8) possess authenticity, (9) appear business-as-usual, (10) overwhelm the mark, (11) are quick and simple in design and execution, and (12) consider the mark&rsquo;s reactions to the ruse and adjusts accordingly to maintain the deception. Any single social engineering engagement does not require all of these elements for success.&nbsp; The data from this study, however, suggest that successful and effective deceptions require at least some of them.</p> <p>The third analysis addresses the question &ldquo;what traits do social engineers associate with individuals vulnerable to social engineering deceptions?&rdquo; The results describe various attributes of a &ldquo;model victim&rdquo; for social engineers, a hypothetical person considered particularly susceptible to social engineering deceptions. First, the mark should have something to offer the social engineer, be it a resource (money, information, or access) or some experience (thrills). The model victim is uninformed and unconcerned about information security risks&mdash;&ldquo;don&rsquo;t know&rdquo; and &ldquo;don&rsquo;t care&rdquo; respectively. They are friendly and helpful. A model victim is also either socially isolated or overly-connected to others&mdash;having a range of social connections to others. Finally, a model victim is one that experiences too much control or too little. In other words, they are not bound by the rules governing information security or, paradoxically, care too much about the rules.</p> <p>The fourth analysis examined the traits participants associated with organizations vulnerable to social engineering. The results of this study indicate that organizations viewed as more vulnerable by social engineers are those that (1) offer a resource or experience desired by the social engineer, (2) lack in structural controls within the organization (policies, trainings, audits, and technological controls), (3) have diminished organizational efficacy (the willingness and ability to organizational members to uphold organizational information security), and (4) regularly expose organizational members and data to external actors. These four traits are said to have direct effects on organizational vulnerability to social engineering. Two additional traits were described as having indirect effects on organizational vulnerability&mdash;organizational size (the amount of people in the organization) and purpose (what the organization does). These traits appears to impact organizational susceptibility to social engineering by impacting the presence and prevalence of the four traits with direct effects. Further, these traits appeared to operate as heuristic devices (perceptual shorthand) used by social engineers in assessing organizational vulnerability.</p> <p>The final analysis conducted to date examines the emotional experiences involved in the execution of social engineering deceptions. The results of this analysis indicate that social engineering interactions are characterized by an emotional experience of situational tension and the subsequent resolution of that tension. The analysis then turns to factors that modulate the quality and intensity of the emotional experience of social engineering perpetration. These factors include the social distance between the social engineer and the mark (did they approach the target through phone, email, or telephone?), the social engineer&rsquo;s framing the mark (is the target understood as worthy of deception?), and both perceived and actual efficacy in utilizing skills involved in management of self and situation (how skilled is the social engineering in managing their emotions and their interactions?).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;F&nbsp;Steinmetz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The current project studies "social engineering" or the manipulation of the human element of information security for the purposes of gaining access to sensitive information or computer networks. This research is largely exploratory and involves qualitative, semi-structured interviews with security auditors who make use of social engineering techniques, non-professional social engineers, and IT professionals tasked with protecting organizations from social engineering threats. The final sample includes 54 participants (37 social engineers/security auditors and 17 IT professionals). The project provides a sociologically and criminologically grounded understanding of the phenomenon.  Five major analyses of the data have been conducted two date. The first analysis explored definitions of social engineering held by study participants. The results of this analysis indicate that social engineering parallels other forms of fraud or influence and is primarily distinguished by the manner in which participants frame the concept. Participant descriptions indicate that definitions of social engineering are indicative of values and ideologies of its practitioners and reflect views of the world that frame humans and social interaction in computational terms&mdash;that interacting with people is, in some ways, akin to working with computers.  The second analysis addresses the question "what are the attributes of successful and effective social engineering deceptions according to social engineers?" The results of this study indicate that effective social engineering deceptions (1) are well researched, (2) take into account the demographic characteristics, prior experiences, and skillsets of the social engineer, (3) consider the routine activities of the target and incorporate current events, (4) foster a positive relationship with the victim, (5) embed the social engineer within the victim’s social networks, (6) appeal to the target for help, (7) provide an incentive for the mark to act, (8) possess authenticity, (9) appear business-as-usual, (10) overwhelm the mark, (11) are quick and simple in design and execution, and (12) consider the mark’s reactions to the ruse and adjusts accordingly to maintain the deception. Any single social engineering engagement does not require all of these elements for success.  The data from this study, however, suggest that successful and effective deceptions require at least some of them.  The third analysis addresses the question "what traits do social engineers associate with individuals vulnerable to social engineering deceptions?" The results describe various attributes of a "model victim" for social engineers, a hypothetical person considered particularly susceptible to social engineering deceptions. First, the mark should have something to offer the social engineer, be it a resource (money, information, or access) or some experience (thrills). The model victim is uninformed and unconcerned about information security risks&mdash;"don’t know" and "don’t care" respectively. They are friendly and helpful. A model victim is also either socially isolated or overly-connected to others&mdash;having a range of social connections to others. Finally, a model victim is one that experiences too much control or too little. In other words, they are not bound by the rules governing information security or, paradoxically, care too much about the rules.  The fourth analysis examined the traits participants associated with organizations vulnerable to social engineering. The results of this study indicate that organizations viewed as more vulnerable by social engineers are those that (1) offer a resource or experience desired by the social engineer, (2) lack in structural controls within the organization (policies, trainings, audits, and technological controls), (3) have diminished organizational efficacy (the willingness and ability to organizational members to uphold organizational information security), and (4) regularly expose organizational members and data to external actors. These four traits are said to have direct effects on organizational vulnerability to social engineering. Two additional traits were described as having indirect effects on organizational vulnerability&mdash;organizational size (the amount of people in the organization) and purpose (what the organization does). These traits appears to impact organizational susceptibility to social engineering by impacting the presence and prevalence of the four traits with direct effects. Further, these traits appeared to operate as heuristic devices (perceptual shorthand) used by social engineers in assessing organizational vulnerability.  The final analysis conducted to date examines the emotional experiences involved in the execution of social engineering deceptions. The results of this analysis indicate that social engineering interactions are characterized by an emotional experience of situational tension and the subsequent resolution of that tension. The analysis then turns to factors that modulate the quality and intensity of the emotional experience of social engineering perpetration. These factors include the social distance between the social engineer and the mark (did they approach the target through phone, email, or telephone?), the social engineer’s framing the mark (is the target understood as worthy of deception?), and both perceived and actual efficacy in utilizing skills involved in management of self and situation (how skilled is the social engineering in managing their emotions and their interactions?).       Last Modified: 09/02/2020       Submitted by: Kevin F Steinmetz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
