<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TWC: Small: Bridging the Gap Between Cutting-Edge Cryptography and Practice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>490927.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>490927</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>namla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927991</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The cloud is becoming increasingly integral to our daily lives, the business ecosystem, and society at large.  Recently, cutting-edge cryptosystems have been developed that provide the first-ever theoretical solutions to many cloud-related tasks.  Such tasks include fine-grained access control to encrypted data, broadcasting to a set of recipients with minimal communication overhead, hiding secrets in public code, and much more. Unfortunately, these recent systems are far from being ready for deployment, due both to significant computational inefficiencies and to new and thus little-understood underlying computational assumptions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is bringing cutting-edge cryptographic applications closer to practice by improving the efficiency and security of said applications.  A particular focus is program obfuscation, a powerful new tool at the heart of many of the recent theoretical advances in cryptography.  This project develops new constructions and security analyses for obfuscation and other related cryptographic tools, yielding more efficient protocols and increasing our confidence in their security. In addition, education is integral to this project, as the PI develops new cryptography courses and advises undergraduates and graduate students alike in order to cultivate the next generation of scholars and practitioners.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1616442</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhandry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark L Zhandry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mzhandry@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000706682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[87 Prospect Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~490927</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The cloud is becoming an increasingly integral part of our daily lives, the business ecosystem, and society at large. Many cutting-edge cryptosystems have recently been developed to secure the cloud in many settings.&nbsp;</span>One of the central advances that has enabled many of these new systems is general purpose program obfuscation.&nbsp;The goal of obfuscation is to prevent reverse engineering by scrambling a piece of software, thereby hiding the inner-workings of the original code while preserving functionality. Unfortuantely, numerous security vulnerabilities have been uncovered in early obfuscation schemes.</p> <p>This project has thoroughly investiaged the mathematical tools behind obfuscation and other cutting-edge cryptosystems, developing a comprehensive understanding of their security. Additionally, new cryptographic tools and techniques have been uncovered.&nbsp;As a result, this project has lead to several new obfuscation schemes and other cryptographic applications that resist all known attacks. Along the way, this project has also improved the efficiency of obfuscation as well as many of its cutting-edge applications. This projected has also explored the relationship between obfuscation and the broader study of computer science, such as pseudoradomness, quantum computing, and differential privacy.</p> <p>Funding from this project has supported several graduate students, aiding in their professional development. This project has also facilitated the development of new undergraduate and graduate-level cryptography courses, whose materials have been made publicaly available.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/13/2020<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;L&nbsp;Zhandry</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The cloud is becoming an increasingly integral part of our daily lives, the business ecosystem, and society at large. Many cutting-edge cryptosystems have recently been developed to secure the cloud in many settings. One of the central advances that has enabled many of these new systems is general purpose program obfuscation. The goal of obfuscation is to prevent reverse engineering by scrambling a piece of software, thereby hiding the inner-workings of the original code while preserving functionality. Unfortuantely, numerous security vulnerabilities have been uncovered in early obfuscation schemes.  This project has thoroughly investiaged the mathematical tools behind obfuscation and other cutting-edge cryptosystems, developing a comprehensive understanding of their security. Additionally, new cryptographic tools and techniques have been uncovered. As a result, this project has lead to several new obfuscation schemes and other cryptographic applications that resist all known attacks. Along the way, this project has also improved the efficiency of obfuscation as well as many of its cutting-edge applications. This projected has also explored the relationship between obfuscation and the broader study of computer science, such as pseudoradomness, quantum computing, and differential privacy.  Funding from this project has supported several graduate students, aiding in their professional development. This project has also facilitated the development of new undergraduate and graduate-level cryptography courses, whose materials have been made publicaly available.       Last Modified: 10/13/2020       Submitted by: Mark L Zhandry]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
