<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Occultations by Pluto, Triton and Large Trans-Neptunian Objects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>458821.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>458821</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Luke Sollitt</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lsollitt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Solar System objects pass in front of bright stars from time to time, cutting out the starlight. The amount of light that is cut coupled with the amount of time during these passages tells us about the size, shape, whether the object has an atmosphere, and how thick the atmosphere might be. These events are called occultations. This project will observe occultations of stars by the Trans-Neptunian Objects Pluto, Triton, Makemake, Quaoar, and Salacia. Since 1988, Pluto's atmosphere has been tracked by occultations. Its atmosphere has gotten thicker during this time. It is now expected to get thinner as Pluto moves farther away from the Sun in its orbit, and its temperature gets cooler. Two occultations by Pluto will be observed over the next three years to record changes in the thickness of Pluto's atmosphere. These changes will be modeled with data that we already have to describe how Pluto's atmosphere changes. The other large TNOs, covered with bright ice, could also have changing atmospheres like Pluto. Observations of one occultation are planned for each of the other objects listed above.  Many amateur astronomers and students will be trained to be part of the occultation observations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Occultations of reasonably bright stars by Trans-Neptunian Objects (TNOs) provide an opportunity to learn their sizes, shapes and densities, and presence and details of any thin atmospheres. This project will observe occultations of stars by the TNOs Pluto, Triton, Makemake, Quaoar, and Salacia, resulting in data that are crucial to building accurate atmospheric models for these objects. Pluto's atmosphere has been monitored by occultations since its discovery in 1988. It has been doubling in size roughly every ten years, despite the fact that Pluto itself has move farther from the Sun in its orbit. Images of Pluto's surface from the New Horizons spacecraft show large ice reservoirs that are the source of Pluto's atmosphere. These reservoirs have been getting slightly warmer as Pluto has moved away from the Sun, suggesting that Pluto's subsurface stores heat. Models predict, however, that Pluto's frost temperatures will soon start to fall. Two occultations by Pluto will be observed over the next three years to monitor changes in the amount of Pluto's atmosphere. Other large TNOs, covered with bright ice, potentially have changing atmospheres like Pluto. Observations of one occultation are planned for each of the other objects listed above.  The planned observations will be sensitive to very thin atmospheres and will refine the size and shape estimates for all objects. Many amateur astronomers and student researchers will be trained and added to support the occultation observations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1616115</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eliot</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eliot Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>efy@boulder.swri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3035466807</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000106798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Southwest Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782385166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2105222231</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6220 Culebra Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Drawer 28510]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007936842</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHWEST RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007936842</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southwest Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803025142</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 Walnut Street, suite 300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1214</Code>
<Text>PLANETARY ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~159323</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~163092</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~136406</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Pluto has been receding from the Sun over the past quarter-century. It now receives 20% less solar energy than it did in 1988. Pluto has a nitrogen atmosphere, like the Earth&rsquo;s, but Pluto&rsquo;s atmosphere is due to nitrogen vapor that sublimates from large N2 ice deposits. It&rsquo;s been something of a mystery that Pluto&rsquo;s atmosphere has been increasing during a time when its received solar energy has been decreasing, and there has been the general expectation that Pluto&rsquo;s atmosphere will begin to freeze out shortly. We observed Pluto in 2018 as it passed in front of a bright star, specifically, we observed the starlight refracted by Pluto&rsquo;s atmosphere. We determined that the growth of Pluto&rsquo;s atmosphere has stopped between 2015 and 2018, suggesting that Pluto&rsquo;s &ldquo;atmospheric freeze out&rdquo; is imminent.</p> <p class="p1">The New Horizons mission showed dramatic haze layers in Pluto's atmosphere. We analyzed past occultations to see how thick Pluto's haze was in 2002, 2007, 2011 and 2015. We find that Pluto's haze opacity changes by orders of magnitude over timescales of a few years. The haze optical depth dropped by more than a factor of 30 between 2002 and 2007.</p> <p class="p1">Central flashes are observed when on observer is located near the center of an occultation shadow. We observed central flashes in 2007, 2015 and 2018. The 2007 flash had two peaks, which could be due to fast zonal winds on Pluto. The other two events were single-peaked, suggesting no observable oblateness in Pluto's atmosphere. The cause of the double peak is still a mystery.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/26/2021<br>      Modified by: Eliot&nbsp;Young</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Pluto has been receding from the Sun over the past quarter-century. It now receives 20% less solar energy than it did in 1988. Pluto has a nitrogen atmosphere, like the Earth’s, but Pluto’s atmosphere is due to nitrogen vapor that sublimates from large N2 ice deposits. It’s been something of a mystery that Pluto’s atmosphere has been increasing during a time when its received solar energy has been decreasing, and there has been the general expectation that Pluto’s atmosphere will begin to freeze out shortly. We observed Pluto in 2018 as it passed in front of a bright star, specifically, we observed the starlight refracted by Pluto’s atmosphere. We determined that the growth of Pluto’s atmosphere has stopped between 2015 and 2018, suggesting that Pluto’s "atmospheric freeze out" is imminent. The New Horizons mission showed dramatic haze layers in Pluto's atmosphere. We analyzed past occultations to see how thick Pluto's haze was in 2002, 2007, 2011 and 2015. We find that Pluto's haze opacity changes by orders of magnitude over timescales of a few years. The haze optical depth dropped by more than a factor of 30 between 2002 and 2007. Central flashes are observed when on observer is located near the center of an occultation shadow. We observed central flashes in 2007, 2015 and 2018. The 2007 flash had two peaks, which could be due to fast zonal winds on Pluto. The other two events were single-peaked, suggesting no observable oblateness in Pluto's atmosphere. The cause of the double peak is still a mystery.       Last Modified: 02/26/2021       Submitted by: Eliot Young]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
