<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Establishing the microtubule-actin crosstalk in the preprophase band by the rice kinesin OsKCH2</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>489575.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>489575</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Cyr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rcyr@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928440</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project studies the fundamental mechanisms that regulate cell division and growth of the rice plant and is expected to have a broad spectrum of societal impacts. First, findings from this project will impact future breeding of rice, which feeds half of the world's population. Second, young scientists at both Oregon State University and University of California in Davis will be trained in multi-disciplinary areas by participating in the discovery-oriented research. Third, this project contains light microscopy-based short courses and hands-on training opportunities for underserved students, which will stimulate their interests in STEM disciplines. In addition, to increase public awareness of cutting-edge research programs, plant motor proteins will be included as living examples in advanced light microscopy workshops for high school and community college science teachers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, this project is aimed at investigating how OsKCH2, a plant-specific kinesin in the rice plant Oryza sativa, enables the crosstalk between microtubules (MTs) and filamentous actins (F-actins) at the cortical division site and how it regulates cell division. Kinesins are motor proteins that use the energy from ATP hydrolysis to power numerous essential cellular processes such as transporting cargos along MTs and organizing/remodeling physiologically important MT-based arrays. OsKCH2 belongs to the group of Kinesins with a Calponin Homology domain (KCHs) in high plants. KCHs are known to crosslink MTs and F-actin in vitro, but their functions in plant growth and development remain poorly understood. The project is based on several critical preliminary findings including: (1) mutations in OsKCH2 caused a dwarfism phenotype, (2) OsKCH2 is specifically associated with the PPB during early stages of mitosis, (3) OsKCH2 directly binds to and transports F-actin on microtubules in vitro, and (4) OsKCH2 is the first minus end-directed Kinesin-14 to demonstrate processive motility as a single dimer.  This project will use a multi-disciplinary approach to address two objectives: (1) dissecting the regulatory mechanism underlying the processive motility of OsKCH2 using in vitro single-molecule imaging, and (2) interrogating the in vivo functions of OsKCH2 in cell division and plant growth by examining phenotypes linked to a null kch2 mutation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1616076</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bo</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bo Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bliu@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307548138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000260734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956168671</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Shields Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~324394</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~165181</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Plant growth is dependent on patterned cell division in all tissues across the plant body throughout its lifetime.&nbsp; Cell division is brought about by coordinated actions of the dynamic cytoskeletal systems of microtubules and actin microfilaments.&nbsp; Plant cell division distinguishes itself from that in fungi and animals for establishing an evolutionarily advanced mechanism that regulates the division plane orientation by employing the preprophase band of microtubules and actin microfilaments.&nbsp; Actin microfilaments play a critical role to regulate the organization of microtubules during preprophase band development so that plant cells can establish the division site for the placement of the cell plate accurately during cytokinesis. &nbsp;This project is devoted to advancing our knowledge of the molecular connection between the two cytoskeletons during cell division.&nbsp; It was built on the discovery of a novel microtubule-based motor protein in rice, OsKCH2 for <em>Oryza sativa</em> Kinesin with Calponin Homology domain 2, because of its direct interaction with actin microfilaments. &nbsp;We hypothesized that this OsKCH2 protein functions as a dynamic linker of microtubules and actin microfilaments in the preprophase band.&nbsp; To test this hypothesis, we have employed experimental approaches of protein biochemistry, biophysics, cell biology, and molecular genetics in order to gain insights into the function of kinesins and other proteins associated with the preprophase band.&nbsp; Our investigations of the in vivo activities of OsKCH2 was complemented by a collaboration with colleagues at Oregon State University.&nbsp; In an in vitro assay, the motor traveled towards the minus end of polar microtubule tracks in a processive manner.&nbsp; Our in vivo experiment revealed that it exhibits a cell cycle-dependent localization pattern of exclusive association with the preprophase band.&nbsp; To facilitate our investigations of plant cell division, we also developed a new mitotic model system by rapidly inducing differentiated tobacco leaf cells to re-enter the cell division cycle.&nbsp; Our experiments led to the discovery of a hypothesized scaffold protein at the preprophase band and two new kinesins that function during cell division.&nbsp; Results garnered from our experiments start to uncover an interactive protein network including kinesins and other regulatory proteins that are organized by scaffold proteins to execute cell division in a spatiotemporally regulated manner in flowering plants.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/26/2020<br>      Modified by: Bo&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1616076/1616076_10446028_1587881800145_Mitoticinduction--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1616076/1616076_10446028_1587881800145_Mitoticinduction--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Induction of cell division in tobacco leaf cells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1616076/1616076_10446028_1587881800145_Mitoticinduction--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Induction of cell division in tobacco leaf cells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Leaf pavement cells re-enter the cell division cycle upon ectopic expression of cyclin D3;1.  Cyclin D-induced cells (right) assemble the spindle (arrows) and phragmoplast (arrowheads) microtubule arrays (green) while the control cells (left) remain in interphase (red, DNA).  Scale bar, 20 microns.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liu lab at UC Davis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bo&nbsp;Liu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Induction of cell division in tobacco leaf cells</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Plant growth is dependent on patterned cell division in all tissues across the plant body throughout its lifetime.  Cell division is brought about by coordinated actions of the dynamic cytoskeletal systems of microtubules and actin microfilaments.  Plant cell division distinguishes itself from that in fungi and animals for establishing an evolutionarily advanced mechanism that regulates the division plane orientation by employing the preprophase band of microtubules and actin microfilaments.  Actin microfilaments play a critical role to regulate the organization of microtubules during preprophase band development so that plant cells can establish the division site for the placement of the cell plate accurately during cytokinesis.  This project is devoted to advancing our knowledge of the molecular connection between the two cytoskeletons during cell division.  It was built on the discovery of a novel microtubule-based motor protein in rice, OsKCH2 for Oryza sativa Kinesin with Calponin Homology domain 2, because of its direct interaction with actin microfilaments.  We hypothesized that this OsKCH2 protein functions as a dynamic linker of microtubules and actin microfilaments in the preprophase band.  To test this hypothesis, we have employed experimental approaches of protein biochemistry, biophysics, cell biology, and molecular genetics in order to gain insights into the function of kinesins and other proteins associated with the preprophase band.  Our investigations of the in vivo activities of OsKCH2 was complemented by a collaboration with colleagues at Oregon State University.  In an in vitro assay, the motor traveled towards the minus end of polar microtubule tracks in a processive manner.  Our in vivo experiment revealed that it exhibits a cell cycle-dependent localization pattern of exclusive association with the preprophase band.  To facilitate our investigations of plant cell division, we also developed a new mitotic model system by rapidly inducing differentiated tobacco leaf cells to re-enter the cell division cycle.  Our experiments led to the discovery of a hypothesized scaffold protein at the preprophase band and two new kinesins that function during cell division.  Results garnered from our experiments start to uncover an interactive protein network including kinesins and other regulatory proteins that are organized by scaffold proteins to execute cell division in a spatiotemporally regulated manner in flowering plants.           Last Modified: 04/26/2020       Submitted by: Bo Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
