<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: The Role Of Fortifications In Reifying Social Structure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24153.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24153</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The modern world is characterized by countless differences that cut along economic, social, and political lines. Such structured and hierarchical divisions within human society are neither an essential nor inevitable condition of collective life, but develop under specific historical circumstances. Archaeology is uniquely poised to study how such "complex societies" come about, as it allows researchers to trace changes in social organization over the span of millennia through the material remains of human action. Such understanding helps one to better recognize both the opportunities and tradeoffs that come with different approaches to political life. Ms. Eilis Monahan of Cornell University will undertake research that investigates the early formation of complex societies, through a particular focus on landscapes and the built environment. Specifically, the research seeks to explain the roles played by defensive structures, such as fortifications, in creating the kinds of social and political boundaries that we take for granted today as basic features of modern societies. In many parts of the world, fortifications and other dramatic alterations to the landscape occur during times of transition to increased complexity. This research is therefore of broad social scientific relevance, contributing to wider debates on the relationships among power, society, and defense. Ms. Monahan's study is undertaken in collaboration with the Department of Antiquities, Cyprus and will foster collegial intellectual and professional relationships between U.S., E.U. and Cypriot students and scholars. This project will also document threatened sites of cultural and historical significance, which will aid in the development of future heritage management planning in the region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ms. Monahan will investigate how the construction of fortifications creates a "disciplinary landscape" that alters how people experience and perceive space, and the impacts this has on the development and reinforcement of inequality. This project focuses on a cluster of four Middle Bronze Age fortresses in the Ayios Sozomenos region in central Cyprus. Located near vital copper sources, and situated at crossroads of communication and trade across the island, these massive fortified sites appear during the dramatic transformation of Cyprus from an insular and egalitarian village-based society to a socially-stratified urban society, engaged in diplomatic relations and trade with the great polities of the Eastern Mediterranean. Combining excavation, survey, and museum study, the research will investigate how these fortresses were constructed and used in conjunction with the location and chronology of other sites in the region. By evaluating how fortresses alter the ways that people can move, see, and act, and by analyzing shifting patterns of settlement, this research will reveal how fortifications change the ways in which people interact with each other and how, in turn, this contributes to the transformation of society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1617174</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lori</FirstName>
<LastName>Khatchadourian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lori Khatchadourian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lk323@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7733157837</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eilis</FirstName>
<LastName>Monahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eilis M Monahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emm66@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000695270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~24153</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF-funded Doctoral Dissertation research by Eilis Monahan, working in collaboration with the Cyprus Department of Antiquities Agios Sozomenos Excavation and Survey Project (ASESP), produced exciting results from the study of the Bronze Age fortifications and settlements in central Cyprus, while the analyses completed contribute to wider discussions of militarization and political regime formation across regions and time periods. The results of the research were used in the completion of the award recipient?s dissertation, have been shared in multiple academic and public publications and presentations in both the United States and Cyprus, and directly support future research and conservation efforts in Cyprus.</p> <p><span> </span></p> <p>The Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award funded five weeks of pedestrian survey in the Agios Sozomenos Region, an area of 25 km<sup>2</sup> in the geographic center of the island of Cyprus, in order to document the development of Bronze Age settlement in the region, and the relationships between settlements and the construction of contemporaneous fortifications. Of 27 previously recorded sites, 16 were relocated and 11 studied in greater detail, including three large fortified enclosures. Two new sites were also identified and recorded: one Late Bronze Age building, likely associated with agricultural production, and the other likely a small Bronze Age cemetery. The location, spatial distribution of archaeological materials, and condition of each site were recorded, and spatially-stratified systematic samples of ceramics and other small artifacts were collected for analysis. These data were used to estimate the spatial and temporal extent of each site, and to identify possible activities that occurred within sites. ASESP also undertook excavations at two fortresses and two settlements. The ceramics and other finds were analyzed during the 2016-2017 academic year at the Cyprus Museum. A subsequent short season allowed the results of GIS visibility analyses to be tested, and for additional contemporaneous sites on Cyprus to be visited and recorded. &nbsp;</p> <p><span> </span></p> <p>The region as a whole was largely unpopulated prior to the Bronze Age, when the first settlements appear. Occupation intensifies through the Middle and Late Bronze Age, with evolving settlement patterns clearly centered on the contemporaneous fortresses. Significant findings included diverse and elaborate Bronze Age fortification systems, including a previously unattested double-wall-and-ditch enclosure at the fortress of <em>Barsak</em>, and a monumental tower and elaborate entrance with ashlar masonry and casemate rooms at the fortress at <em>Nikolidhes</em>. Additionally, investigations at the large settlements at <em>Glykia Vrysi</em> and <em>Ambelia</em> revealed patterns of settlement growth and consolidation, as well as possible settlement specialization, with one site producing evidence for metallurgical activities, and the other containing facilities for large-scale processing and storage of agricultural goods.</p> <p><span> </span></p> <p>Analysis of the architecture, landscape, and settlement patterns in the Agios Sozomenos region reveal the dynamics of these relationships and contribute to the theory developed by the co-PI in her dissertation that these, and other, fortresses may be understood as a type of Foucauldian apparatus, meaning that the components of the fortresses work together to generate political power, specifically in three modes: defensive (or militaristic) power, monumental (or communicative) power, and disciplinary power (a power that drives people to regulate their own behaviors). Analytical methods including architectural energetics, spatial syntax and architectonics, were utlized to invetigate how labor, building materials, and the design of fortifications create the defensive efficacy of the fortress, its monumental influence, and how it monitors and shapes human behavior. At the scale of the landscape, Geographic Information System analyses of prominence, intervisibility, and movement iwere used to probe the role of fortresses in processes of surveillance and territorialization. The results demonstrate that the forces produced by the construction and operation of fortifications in the landscape have the potential to create political subjects and territories, by changing the way that people experience and understand political authority.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Eilis&nbsp;M&nbsp;Monahan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF-funded Doctoral Dissertation research by Eilis Monahan, working in collaboration with the Cyprus Department of Antiquities Agios Sozomenos Excavation and Survey Project (ASESP), produced exciting results from the study of the Bronze Age fortifications and settlements in central Cyprus, while the analyses completed contribute to wider discussions of militarization and political regime formation across regions and time periods. The results of the research were used in the completion of the award recipient?s dissertation, have been shared in multiple academic and public publications and presentations in both the United States and Cyprus, and directly support future research and conservation efforts in Cyprus.     The Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award funded five weeks of pedestrian survey in the Agios Sozomenos Region, an area of 25 km2 in the geographic center of the island of Cyprus, in order to document the development of Bronze Age settlement in the region, and the relationships between settlements and the construction of contemporaneous fortifications. Of 27 previously recorded sites, 16 were relocated and 11 studied in greater detail, including three large fortified enclosures. Two new sites were also identified and recorded: one Late Bronze Age building, likely associated with agricultural production, and the other likely a small Bronze Age cemetery. The location, spatial distribution of archaeological materials, and condition of each site were recorded, and spatially-stratified systematic samples of ceramics and other small artifacts were collected for analysis. These data were used to estimate the spatial and temporal extent of each site, and to identify possible activities that occurred within sites. ASESP also undertook excavations at two fortresses and two settlements. The ceramics and other finds were analyzed during the 2016-2017 academic year at the Cyprus Museum. A subsequent short season allowed the results of GIS visibility analyses to be tested, and for additional contemporaneous sites on Cyprus to be visited and recorded.       The region as a whole was largely unpopulated prior to the Bronze Age, when the first settlements appear. Occupation intensifies through the Middle and Late Bronze Age, with evolving settlement patterns clearly centered on the contemporaneous fortresses. Significant findings included diverse and elaborate Bronze Age fortification systems, including a previously unattested double-wall-and-ditch enclosure at the fortress of Barsak, and a monumental tower and elaborate entrance with ashlar masonry and casemate rooms at the fortress at Nikolidhes. Additionally, investigations at the large settlements at Glykia Vrysi and Ambelia revealed patterns of settlement growth and consolidation, as well as possible settlement specialization, with one site producing evidence for metallurgical activities, and the other containing facilities for large-scale processing and storage of agricultural goods.     Analysis of the architecture, landscape, and settlement patterns in the Agios Sozomenos region reveal the dynamics of these relationships and contribute to the theory developed by the co-PI in her dissertation that these, and other, fortresses may be understood as a type of Foucauldian apparatus, meaning that the components of the fortresses work together to generate political power, specifically in three modes: defensive (or militaristic) power, monumental (or communicative) power, and disciplinary power (a power that drives people to regulate their own behaviors). Analytical methods including architectural energetics, spatial syntax and architectonics, were utlized to invetigate how labor, building materials, and the design of fortifications create the defensive efficacy of the fortress, its monumental influence, and how it monitors and shapes human behavior. At the scale of the landscape, Geographic Information System analyses of prominence, intervisibility, and movement iwere used to probe the role of fortresses in processes of surveillance and territorialization. The results demonstrate that the forces produced by the construction and operation of fortifications in the landscape have the potential to create political subjects and territories, by changing the way that people experience and understand political authority.              Last Modified: 02/27/2020       Submitted by: Eilis M Monahan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
