<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHF:Small: Reducing Test Time and Improving Diagnosis for Increasingly Dense ICs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The amount of data required to test and diagnose integrated circuits continues to grow dramatically as technology scales, not only because of larger designs, but also the need for additional tests to target new defects. The density of ICs continues to grow faster than the test data bandwidth between automatic test equipment (ATE) and the chip-under-test, which is constrained by the number of channels on the tester and pins on the chip. This project involves developing new approaches for compression and extraction of data that are fundamentally different from existing techniques and capable of more efficiently reducing the amount of data and significantly improving test time and diagnosis accuracy.  The project will provide advanced training to both graduate and undergraduate students, including those from underrepresented groups, in the latest design and test technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Several new research directions for improving compression and extraction of test data will be investigated in this project.  A fundamentally new approach for extracting information from linear signatures using symbolic canceling will be studied for finding error locations to aid in diagnosis.  By combining information from the signature together with structural information from the circuit, much greater diagnostic precision is possible. Improvements in test compression will be pursued through new concepts including (i) bandwidth sharing between test stimulus decompression and output response compaction, (ii) combining linear and non-linear encoding, (iii) low fan-out response compaction architectures, and (iv) dynamic extraction from linear compactors.  The new techniques and architectures developed in this project will be implemented and their performance evaluated.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1617665</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nur</FirstName>
<LastName>Touba</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nur A Touba</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>touba@ece.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122321456</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 East 24th St., POB 6.132]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~350000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal of this project was to explore new ideas, concepts, and directions for reducing test time and improving diagnosis.&nbsp; One of the most effective ways to reduce test time is to&nbsp;reduce the amount of&nbsp;data that has to be transferred across the low bandwidth link between the tester and the chip-under-test.&nbsp; However, in a test compression environment where the output response is highly compacted,&nbsp;performing accurate diagnosis using production test data&nbsp;is a significant challenge.</span></p> <p>One of the key outcomes of this project was to develop a fundamentally new and powerful approach for extracting information from linear signatures using symbolic canceling.&nbsp; It was shown that for propagation cones smaller than the size of the signature register, the exact error locations can be obtained, and for larger propogation cones, the number of suspects for diagnosis could be significantly reduced even in the presence of unknown X values.&nbsp; This approach was applied to both combinational and sequential linear compactors which are widely used in industry.</p> <p>Other significant outcomes included developing new response compaction techniques that can provide observabilty even in the presense of very high densities of unknown X values.&nbsp; Techniques for using reconfigurable feedback polynomials to enhance diagnosis.&nbsp; Lastly, the project let to several new methodologies for encoding test vectors that eliminate the need for pre-loading the decompressor and can achieve significant boosts in the amount of compression achieved resulting in reduced test time.</p> <p>Both undergraduate and graduate students participated in the project and gained valuable research experience.&nbsp; Four Ph.D. students supported by this project have graduated and are employed by US-based companies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2021<br>      Modified by: Nur&nbsp;A&nbsp;Touba</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to explore new ideas, concepts, and directions for reducing test time and improving diagnosis.  One of the most effective ways to reduce test time is to reduce the amount of data that has to be transferred across the low bandwidth link between the tester and the chip-under-test.  However, in a test compression environment where the output response is highly compacted, performing accurate diagnosis using production test data is a significant challenge.  One of the key outcomes of this project was to develop a fundamentally new and powerful approach for extracting information from linear signatures using symbolic canceling.  It was shown that for propagation cones smaller than the size of the signature register, the exact error locations can be obtained, and for larger propogation cones, the number of suspects for diagnosis could be significantly reduced even in the presence of unknown X values.  This approach was applied to both combinational and sequential linear compactors which are widely used in industry.  Other significant outcomes included developing new response compaction techniques that can provide observabilty even in the presense of very high densities of unknown X values.  Techniques for using reconfigurable feedback polynomials to enhance diagnosis.  Lastly, the project let to several new methodologies for encoding test vectors that eliminate the need for pre-loading the decompressor and can achieve significant boosts in the amount of compression achieved resulting in reduced test time.  Both undergraduate and graduate students participated in the project and gained valuable research experience.  Four Ph.D. students supported by this project have graduated and are employed by US-based companies.       Last Modified: 07/10/2021       Submitted by: Nur A Touba]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
