<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>III: Small: High-Throughput Annotation of Cellular Functions of Intrinsic Disorder in Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of fundamental problems in molecular biology is to decipher functions of millions of uncharacterized protein sequences that are rapidly generated by high-throughput genome sequencing. The sequence-to-structure-to-function paradigm was used for decades to determine functions of proteins. However, recent research has broadened this paradigm by adding new players, proteins with intrinsic disorder (ID). They are highly abundant and cannot be solved with the structure-driven approach. While there are many widely used computational methods that accurately predict ID in protein sequences, methods for the prediction of the many functions of ID are lacking. This project will develop a family of novel, accurate, and high-throughput computational methods that predict all major functions of ID in protein sequences. It will produce putative functional annotations on an unprecedented scale of thousands of species, addressing the problem of high rate acquisition of raw sequence data and contributing to the increase of the rate of scientific discovery. These results will advance our understanding of fundamental biological processes and human health given the high prevalence of ID in human diseases and attractiveness of proteins with ID as drug targets. This project will also contribute to training of STEM students and researchers via short workshops and undergraduate and graduate level lectures and mentoring, focusing on demonstrating relevance and value of education and research in the emerging areas of protein bioinformatics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will conceptualize, design, rigorously test and deploy predictors of all major functions of intrinsic disorder including protein-RNA, protein-DNA, protein-protein, protein-ligand and protein-lipid interaction, flexible linkers and spacers, regions that host post-translational modifications, and moonlighting regions. These methods will provide fast and accurate predictions in the absence of sequence similarity when the commonly used sequence alignment-based approaches fail. The design will include a novel, hybrid function-specific feature extraction, empirical feature selection, and optimization of predictive models generated with modern machine learning algorithms. The inputs to these predictive models will be quantified and aggregated from a comprehensive set of empirically selected and sequence-derived structural and biophysical characteristics of proteins. The resulting methods will be benchmarked and made freely available to the broad research community via a web-based, server-side portal. The results will be also deposited into relevant public databases.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1617369</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lukasz</FirstName>
<LastName>Kurgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lukasz Kurgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lkurgan@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8048286772</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000711237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>105300446</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>105300446</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Commonwealth University]]></Name>
<CityName>Richmond</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>232843019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[401 West Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Proteins are remarkable biological machines that are responsible for function, structure and regulation of all cells and tissues across all organisms. Over the last two decades we collectively managed to decode nearly 200 million protein sequences across many thousands of species. This ongoing effort is expected to produce hundreds of millions of protein sequences in the future. Perhaps surprisingly, we do not know what significant majority of these proteins do. The sequence-to-structure-to-function paradigm for decades determined how we learn protein functions. However, recent research has broadened this paradigm by adding a new player, the intrinsic disorder (ID). Proteins with ID are highly abundant in nature, particularly among eukaryotic species, and carry out their functions without fully folding into a rigid molecule. In fact, majority of human proteins are projected to have ID. Functions of these proteins cannot be deciphered with the structure-driven approach. Instead, computational methods that predict ID directly from protein sequences have emerged as a viable and commonly used alternative to investigate ID. However, methods for the prediction of ID functions are lacking.</p> <p>This project utilized modern machine learning techniques to conceptualize, design, implement, test, publish and deploy a large family of novel and accurate methods that predict all major functions of ID. The ultimate end product is the innovative DEPICTER (DisorderEd PredictIon CenTER) web-based portal for integrated and fast prediction of multiple functions of ID. This user-friendly webserver is available publicly and targets a broad range of users including structural biologists, biophysicists and bioinformaticians, particularly those who are not experts in computational modelling. Users can utilize these new services to obtain putative information about the presence and functions of disorder for their not-yet-characterized protein sequences. Use of our tools in the long run will substantially speed up the rate of scientific discovery. Along this research line, we applied these computational tools to study and learn interesting new details about ID. For instance, we managed to map ID into the human cell, identified relations between certain disorder functions and the enrichment in ID among the "non-smelly" proteins (proteins depleted in the aromatic amino acids), and contributed to the characterization of human hub proteins and their relation to human diseases.</p> <p>In the course of this project, we deployed 6 publicly available webservers that support prediction of disorder and disorder functions, including DEPICTER. We published 28 peer-reviewed works including 16 journal articles, 3 conference papers and 9 book chapters that introduce, describe, test, popularize and apply these tools. Moreover, we facilitated new collaborations among a broader research community by organizing successful conference session and journal issue that focused on the computational analysis and predictions of ID functions. Importantly, this award has also significantly contributed to our educational mission. It provided training for multiple postdoctoral fellows, doctoral students and undergraduates. We introduced new stimulating projects in our undergraduate courses and contributed to STEM education among high schoolers by delivering public talks and contributing to organize programming competitions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/11/2020<br>      Modified by: Lukasz&nbsp;Kurgan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Proteins are remarkable biological machines that are responsible for function, structure and regulation of all cells and tissues across all organisms. Over the last two decades we collectively managed to decode nearly 200 million protein sequences across many thousands of species. This ongoing effort is expected to produce hundreds of millions of protein sequences in the future. Perhaps surprisingly, we do not know what significant majority of these proteins do. The sequence-to-structure-to-function paradigm for decades determined how we learn protein functions. However, recent research has broadened this paradigm by adding a new player, the intrinsic disorder (ID). Proteins with ID are highly abundant in nature, particularly among eukaryotic species, and carry out their functions without fully folding into a rigid molecule. In fact, majority of human proteins are projected to have ID. Functions of these proteins cannot be deciphered with the structure-driven approach. Instead, computational methods that predict ID directly from protein sequences have emerged as a viable and commonly used alternative to investigate ID. However, methods for the prediction of ID functions are lacking.  This project utilized modern machine learning techniques to conceptualize, design, implement, test, publish and deploy a large family of novel and accurate methods that predict all major functions of ID. The ultimate end product is the innovative DEPICTER (DisorderEd PredictIon CenTER) web-based portal for integrated and fast prediction of multiple functions of ID. This user-friendly webserver is available publicly and targets a broad range of users including structural biologists, biophysicists and bioinformaticians, particularly those who are not experts in computational modelling. Users can utilize these new services to obtain putative information about the presence and functions of disorder for their not-yet-characterized protein sequences. Use of our tools in the long run will substantially speed up the rate of scientific discovery. Along this research line, we applied these computational tools to study and learn interesting new details about ID. For instance, we managed to map ID into the human cell, identified relations between certain disorder functions and the enrichment in ID among the "non-smelly" proteins (proteins depleted in the aromatic amino acids), and contributed to the characterization of human hub proteins and their relation to human diseases.  In the course of this project, we deployed 6 publicly available webservers that support prediction of disorder and disorder functions, including DEPICTER. We published 28 peer-reviewed works including 16 journal articles, 3 conference papers and 9 book chapters that introduce, describe, test, popularize and apply these tools. Moreover, we facilitated new collaborations among a broader research community by organizing successful conference session and journal issue that focused on the computational analysis and predictions of ID functions. Importantly, this award has also significantly contributed to our educational mission. It provided training for multiple postdoctoral fellows, doctoral students and undergraduates. We introduced new stimulating projects in our undergraduate courses and contributed to STEM education among high schoolers by delivering public talks and contributing to organize programming competitions.       Last Modified: 11/11/2020       Submitted by: Lukasz Kurgan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
