<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSR: Small: RF-Wear: Enabling RF Sensing on Wearable Devices for Non-Intrusive Human Activity, Vital Sign and Context Monitoring</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>496271.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>496271</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wearable devices are growing in popularity at a tremendous rate. Today, millions of people wear fitness trackers and smart watches on a daily basis to track steps, heart rates and sleep. However, the constraints of the built-in sensors in existing wearable devices act as key bottlenecks that limit the broader impact of wearable devices. In particular, accelerometers and gyroscopes can only sense motion and rotation of body parts to which they are attached. Microphones and cameras can capture rich information but come with severe privacy concerns. Many physiological sensors such as respiration and electrocardiogram sensors are intrusive in that they must be placed at certain body locations and require tight skin contact to function. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on pushing the boundaries of wearable devices by exploring wireless radio as a new sensing modality on wearable devices for human physical activity, vital sign, and context sensing. Compared to existing sensing modalities in wearable devices, radio provides a contactless and privacy-preserving approach to capture rich information about users and their context. The underpinning principle is that movements of different parts of human body caused by different human activities (physical, physiological and contextual) generate different changes on radio signals. By analyzing these changes, the activity that causes the changes can be recognized. Based on this principle, this project aims to pursue five tightly coupled research tasks associated with the goal of exploring radio based sensing on wearable devices: (1) investigating radio as a whole-body motion sensor for recognizing activities of daily living (ADLs); (2) investigating radio as a contact-less physiological sensor for monitoring vital signs; (3) investigating radio as a context sensor for identifying the object a user is interacting with; (4) putting everything together to use a single radio sensing modality for recognizing ADLs, monitoring vital signs, and identifying context simultaneously; and (5) developing power-aware schemes to minimize the power consumption of the wearable device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will advance the knowledge and understanding of radio based sensing on wearable devices. It has the potential to fundamentally transform wearable devices as they are currently known. If successful, this project will not only make a theoretical contribution to radio based sensing on wearable devices but also yield a prototype platform, opening up a new world of applications in domains such as healthcare, entertainment, social computing and education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1617627</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prem</FirstName>
<LastName>Chahal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Prem Chahal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chahal@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173550248</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mi</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mi Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mizhang@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174324682</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000687999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241226</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[428 S. Shaw Lane, Rm 3530]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~496271</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this award was to explore the feasibility of using a single RF sensing modality on wearable devices for non-intrusive physical activity, physiological signal, and context monitoring and to develop power-aware schemes to minimize the power consumption of RF sensing on wearable devices.</p> <p>The project resulted in multiple outcomes. First, the project resulted in several machine/deep learning-based wireless signal processing pipelines for recognizing activities of daily living and user contexts involving eating, drinking, coughing, speaking, being stationary, walking, riding a bike, shaking hands, doing free-weight exercises as well as measuring vital signs including breathing rate and heartbeat rate. Significant advances were made in developing deep learning-based pipelines for processing wireless signals, where deep neural network models which are traditionally used for processing images and audios are repurposed to process multi-channel wireless signals. Second, the project resulted in new complex number-based deep learning framework that can directly process the wireless signal in its raw complex number form for human activity recognition. Third, fundamental contributions were also made to the area of deep neural network compression. The project contributed to the development of novel deep neural network model compression techniques that can successfully reduce the computational and memory intensity and power consumption of deep neural network models such that the deep learning based wireless signal processing pipelines can be implemented in resource-constrained wearable devices. Fourth, this project contributed to the design and development of automated machine learning methods that can automatically identify the architectures of the deep learning models for processing the wireless signals for human activity recognition on wearable devices. This outcome is important to demonstrate the feasibility of automating the process of developing deep learning-based wireless signal processing pipelines for RF sensing on wearable devices. Lastly, the project resulted in two RF sensing wearable system prototypes that use wireless signal as a single sensing modality for physical activity, user context, and vital sign monitoring.</p> <p>The project also contributed to the collection of two high-quality datasets. The first dataset was collected in well-controlled laboratory settings whereas the second dataset was collected in real-world environments. These two datasets not only provide the training samples and testbenches to develop and evaluate our deep learning-based RF sensing pipelines for wearable devices, but only provide insights into how real-world interferences affect the performance of the RF sensing wearable system. The results are expected to aid in identifying more interference-robust techniques to enhance the performance of the RF sensing wearable system.</p> <p>Collectively, the project contributed to one book chapter, one journal publication, and thirteen conference publications, two PhD dissertations, and one Master&rsquo;s thesis. It provided training opportunities to six PhD students, two Master students, and one undergrad student. The wearable wireless sensing technology developed in this project has a significant societal impact on reducing costs of healthcare as well as enhancing people&rsquo;s quality of lives.&nbsp; Finally, the findings of this project have been integrated into the teaching materials of the PI&rsquo;s graduate course and have been disseminated through the presentations at a number of premier international conferences, the invited talks at universities and companies, and the coverage of leading national and international media.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Mi&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this award was to explore the feasibility of using a single RF sensing modality on wearable devices for non-intrusive physical activity, physiological signal, and context monitoring and to develop power-aware schemes to minimize the power consumption of RF sensing on wearable devices.  The project resulted in multiple outcomes. First, the project resulted in several machine/deep learning-based wireless signal processing pipelines for recognizing activities of daily living and user contexts involving eating, drinking, coughing, speaking, being stationary, walking, riding a bike, shaking hands, doing free-weight exercises as well as measuring vital signs including breathing rate and heartbeat rate. Significant advances were made in developing deep learning-based pipelines for processing wireless signals, where deep neural network models which are traditionally used for processing images and audios are repurposed to process multi-channel wireless signals. Second, the project resulted in new complex number-based deep learning framework that can directly process the wireless signal in its raw complex number form for human activity recognition. Third, fundamental contributions were also made to the area of deep neural network compression. The project contributed to the development of novel deep neural network model compression techniques that can successfully reduce the computational and memory intensity and power consumption of deep neural network models such that the deep learning based wireless signal processing pipelines can be implemented in resource-constrained wearable devices. Fourth, this project contributed to the design and development of automated machine learning methods that can automatically identify the architectures of the deep learning models for processing the wireless signals for human activity recognition on wearable devices. This outcome is important to demonstrate the feasibility of automating the process of developing deep learning-based wireless signal processing pipelines for RF sensing on wearable devices. Lastly, the project resulted in two RF sensing wearable system prototypes that use wireless signal as a single sensing modality for physical activity, user context, and vital sign monitoring.  The project also contributed to the collection of two high-quality datasets. The first dataset was collected in well-controlled laboratory settings whereas the second dataset was collected in real-world environments. These two datasets not only provide the training samples and testbenches to develop and evaluate our deep learning-based RF sensing pipelines for wearable devices, but only provide insights into how real-world interferences affect the performance of the RF sensing wearable system. The results are expected to aid in identifying more interference-robust techniques to enhance the performance of the RF sensing wearable system.  Collectively, the project contributed to one book chapter, one journal publication, and thirteen conference publications, two PhD dissertations, and one Master’s thesis. It provided training opportunities to six PhD students, two Master students, and one undergrad student. The wearable wireless sensing technology developed in this project has a significant societal impact on reducing costs of healthcare as well as enhancing people’s quality of lives.  Finally, the findings of this project have been integrated into the teaching materials of the PI’s graduate course and have been disseminated through the presentations at a number of premier international conferences, the invited talks at universities and companies, and the coverage of leading national and international media.          Last Modified: 04/29/2021       Submitted by: Mi Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
