<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Collaborative Research: Towards Privacy-Preserving Autonomous Vehicle Sharing Services</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the past several years, the automobile and technology industries have made significant leaps in bringing computerization and automation to car driving. Autonomous Vehicles (AVs) have the potential to fundamentally improve transportation systems by dramatically reducing crashes, assisting traffic flows, reducing travel time and energy consumption, providing critical mobility to the elderly and disabled, and making vehicle sharing convenient, popular, and necessary. This project studies the architecture and privacy issues related to autonomous vehicle sharing (AVS) that can revolutionize our transportation experience by providing novel time-sharing and ride-sharing services. The time-sharing services allow AVs to be shared by different users at non-overlapping time periods, while the ride-sharing services allow AVs to be shared by users taking similar trips during the same time period. With autonomous driving techniques, the quality of both services can be significantly enhanced to benefit commuters. However, the time- and ride- sharing systems need to communicate with users to organize shared vehicles, which is not risk free. Massive information on users' activities can be exposed in case of privacy breach. Existing privacy-preserving techniques cannot be applied effectively and efficiently in AVS due to problems and requirements unique to AVS, e.g., location- and time- sensitive trips and multi-user coordination. This project addresses the unique privacy problems raised by AVS and proposes effective and efficient privacy-preserving techniques, which can promote AVS among users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research in this project will have major technological impacts on privacy-preserving AV sharing services. The project will study the privacy-preserving task matching problem for the time-sharing service and the privacy-preserving trip searching problem for the ride-sharing service, while computation and communication overhead, trip delays due to unexpected conditions, costs of transitional trips, users' social preferences, and different privacy protection levels will be considered. The proposed research activities will trigger further research in other applications such as social networks, vehicular ad hoc networks, smart grid, and electric vehicles communications, where privacy is an important factor. The results from this research will be disseminated through conference and journal publications, online documents, and software release. Seminars to high school and community colleges students will be offered in the Boston and Cookeville areas, and presentations regarding the proposed research will be delivered to demonstrate how science and engineering can enhance quality of life in order to stimulate the students' interest in technology. Students in under-represented groups will be encouraged to participate in the proposed research activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1618893</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaohui</FirstName>
<LastName>Liang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaohui Liang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Xiaohui.Liang@umb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172876791</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000705165</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Boston</Name>
<CityName>Dorchester</CityName>
<ZipCode>021253300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172875370</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 Morrissey Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>808008122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Boston]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021253393</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Morrissey Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~199994</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aims to study the architecture and privacy issues related to autonomous vehicle sharing that will revolutionize our transportation experience by providing novel time-sharing and ride-sharing services. Time-sharing services allow autonomous vehicles (AVs) to be shared by different users at non-overlapping periods, while ride-sharing services allow AVs to be shared by users taking similar trips during the same period. The autonomous vehicle sharing raises unique requirements and privacy challenges in the evaluation of location- and time-sensitive trips and multi-user coordination. This project has addressed these research challenges by developing effective and efficient privacy-preserving techniques for autonomous vehicle sharing services. The definition, design, development, and evaluation of the autonomous vehicle sharing services in this project are significant efforts in understanding the autonomous vehicles and the privacy concerns and usage models from the users&rsquo; perspective.</p> <p>We have developed a framework of autonomous vehicle sharing services and a collection of privacy-preserving techniques that protect AV users' privacy-sensitive information, including identities, locations, and trips, from unnecessary disclosure. The framework includes AV users, map servers, traffic servers, and customized matching servers that are dedicated to coordinate multi-users' trips in the time-sharing or ride-sharing services. The matching servers collect privacy-sensitive information from users without direct access to the information and effectively determine whether their usages of AVs are conflicting or not.&nbsp;</p> <p>One of our major outcomes is a time-sharing service model, including entities of AV owners, AV requesters, and matching/scheduling/traffic servers and design objectives of unique privacy, accuracy, and flexibility requirements. A set of privacy-preserving techniques has been proposed to minimize information disclosure while enabling an accurate matching process of multi-users' trips based on the system admin's flexible criteria. One essential privacy-preserving technique is calculating the AV's time duration to travel from one user's location to another user's location while having no direct access to their locations. Besides, efficient scheduling schemes in a multi-user scenario are designed to choose the most efficient requester's task to be assigned to an AV owner, and vice-versa. The evaluation of the proposed model and techniques demonstrated their accuracy and efficiency through experiments using a real map and traffic data. The results confirmed that the privacy-preserving techniques do not disclose users' privacy-sensitive information before a successful matching is concluded. The techniques with additional consideration of the dynamic traffic patterns in the map area achieved enhanced accuracy. The comparison results on the effectiveness of different scheduling schemes have been discussed.</p> <p>Another major outcome of our framework is a ride-sharing service model where multiple users share their trips together in one vehicle instead of using multiple vehicles during the same period, with an assistant of a Trip Organization Server (TOS). One key contribution is to measure the similarity over encrypted data to preserve the privacy of trip data. The trip data is represented as binary vectors, and only encrypted vectors are shared for similarity measurement. The basic model is implemented with a k-Nearest-Neighbor (kNN) encryption scheme, the Bloom filter technique, and group signature. In addition, ride-sharing service is further divided into two subcategories: a non-transferable ride-sharing service (NRS) where a rider can share a ride from its source to destination with only one driver, and a transferable ride-sharing service (TRS) where a rider can transfer between multiple drivers while en-route until he reaches his destination. In NRS, Bloom filters are used to represent the trip data compactly; and in TRS, the TOS builds an encrypted directed graph that is passed to a modified version of Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm for an optimal path of rides based on the riders' preferences. The experiment was conducted via Visual C program on a real map, and the results have shown that the proposed techniques are much more efficient than the existing ones, especially for large cities.</p> <p>This project contributes to the foundation and design of privacy-preserving AV sharing services. The privacy-preserving techniques have been further applied to critical and emerging research areas, including electric vehicle communication, social networks, mobile health applications. The results of this project have been published in IEEE flagship conferences and top-tier communication and security journals. At the University of Massachusetts Boston, we have developed and offered two new joint-level undergraduate and graduate courses on "Cybersecurity in the Internet of Things" and "Applied Cryptography" to 33 female and 63 male students. Multiple students, including two PhD students who graduated in 2018 and 2019 and one female undergraduate student, have worked on the project. At Tennessee Technological University, two new graduate courses on "Advanced Cryptography Applications in Emerging Wireless Networks" and &ldquo;Machine Learning in Cybersecurity&rdquo; were developed, and this project has been integrated with an REU project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Xiaohui&nbsp;Liang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aims to study the architecture and privacy issues related to autonomous vehicle sharing that will revolutionize our transportation experience by providing novel time-sharing and ride-sharing services. Time-sharing services allow autonomous vehicles (AVs) to be shared by different users at non-overlapping periods, while ride-sharing services allow AVs to be shared by users taking similar trips during the same period. The autonomous vehicle sharing raises unique requirements and privacy challenges in the evaluation of location- and time-sensitive trips and multi-user coordination. This project has addressed these research challenges by developing effective and efficient privacy-preserving techniques for autonomous vehicle sharing services. The definition, design, development, and evaluation of the autonomous vehicle sharing services in this project are significant efforts in understanding the autonomous vehicles and the privacy concerns and usage models from the users’ perspective.  We have developed a framework of autonomous vehicle sharing services and a collection of privacy-preserving techniques that protect AV users' privacy-sensitive information, including identities, locations, and trips, from unnecessary disclosure. The framework includes AV users, map servers, traffic servers, and customized matching servers that are dedicated to coordinate multi-users' trips in the time-sharing or ride-sharing services. The matching servers collect privacy-sensitive information from users without direct access to the information and effectively determine whether their usages of AVs are conflicting or not.   One of our major outcomes is a time-sharing service model, including entities of AV owners, AV requesters, and matching/scheduling/traffic servers and design objectives of unique privacy, accuracy, and flexibility requirements. A set of privacy-preserving techniques has been proposed to minimize information disclosure while enabling an accurate matching process of multi-users' trips based on the system admin's flexible criteria. One essential privacy-preserving technique is calculating the AV's time duration to travel from one user's location to another user's location while having no direct access to their locations. Besides, efficient scheduling schemes in a multi-user scenario are designed to choose the most efficient requester's task to be assigned to an AV owner, and vice-versa. The evaluation of the proposed model and techniques demonstrated their accuracy and efficiency through experiments using a real map and traffic data. The results confirmed that the privacy-preserving techniques do not disclose users' privacy-sensitive information before a successful matching is concluded. The techniques with additional consideration of the dynamic traffic patterns in the map area achieved enhanced accuracy. The comparison results on the effectiveness of different scheduling schemes have been discussed.  Another major outcome of our framework is a ride-sharing service model where multiple users share their trips together in one vehicle instead of using multiple vehicles during the same period, with an assistant of a Trip Organization Server (TOS). One key contribution is to measure the similarity over encrypted data to preserve the privacy of trip data. The trip data is represented as binary vectors, and only encrypted vectors are shared for similarity measurement. The basic model is implemented with a k-Nearest-Neighbor (kNN) encryption scheme, the Bloom filter technique, and group signature. In addition, ride-sharing service is further divided into two subcategories: a non-transferable ride-sharing service (NRS) where a rider can share a ride from its source to destination with only one driver, and a transferable ride-sharing service (TRS) where a rider can transfer between multiple drivers while en-route until he reaches his destination. In NRS, Bloom filters are used to represent the trip data compactly; and in TRS, the TOS builds an encrypted directed graph that is passed to a modified version of Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm for an optimal path of rides based on the riders' preferences. The experiment was conducted via Visual C program on a real map, and the results have shown that the proposed techniques are much more efficient than the existing ones, especially for large cities.  This project contributes to the foundation and design of privacy-preserving AV sharing services. The privacy-preserving techniques have been further applied to critical and emerging research areas, including electric vehicle communication, social networks, mobile health applications. The results of this project have been published in IEEE flagship conferences and top-tier communication and security journals. At the University of Massachusetts Boston, we have developed and offered two new joint-level undergraduate and graduate courses on "Cybersecurity in the Internet of Things" and "Applied Cryptography" to 33 female and 63 male students. Multiple students, including two PhD students who graduated in 2018 and 2019 and one female undergraduate student, have worked on the project. At Tennessee Technological University, two new graduate courses on "Advanced Cryptography Applications in Emerging Wireless Networks" and "Machine Learning in Cybersecurity" were developed, and this project has been integrated with an REU project.          Last Modified: 12/28/2020       Submitted by: Xiaohui Liang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
