<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computational Methods for Symmetric Tensor Problems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project targets at symmetric computational problems. Tensors are generalizations of matrices. The entries of symmetric tensors obey symmetric patterns. Computational problems about them become more and more important in big data time. Like the case of matrices, basic problems about symmetric tensors are computing their decompositions over the real and complex fields, determining their ranks, computing low-rank approximations, and applying them in relevant applications. This project devotes to the research of computational problems about symmetric tensors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tensor is a powerful tool in computational mathematics. Symmetric tensors have beautiful algebraic and geometric properties. A problem of fundamental importance is to write a tensor as a sum of rank one tensors, with minimum length. This is the so-called tensor decomposition problem. Tensor decompositions can be over either the real or complex field. Although they are related, the decomposition over the real field is very different from the case of complex field. In applications, tensors can be very large, but their ranks may be small. People often need to approximate a symmetric tensor by a low rank one, as close as possible. Generating polynomial is an efficient tool for solving symmetric tensor computational problems. It uses the algebraic properties elegantly.  A symmetric tensor can be viewed as a symmetric multi-linear functional, which can be expressed by a multivariate polynomial. This project uses mathematical knowledge from computational algebra, polynomial systems, matrix computations, complex and real algebraic geometry, and optimization. The results produced by this project have potential applications in multilinear algebra, signal processing, blind source separation, numerical analysis, higher order Markov chains. The project is going to provide training for students and young researchers who are interested in the subject. Produced results will be promptly disseminated to the scientific community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1619973</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jiawang</FirstName>
<LastName>Nie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jiawang Nie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>njw@math.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585346015</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000078688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930112</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project is about computational methods for solving symmetric tensor problems. A tensor can be viewed a multi-indexed array. It is symmetric if its entries obey certain symmetric patterns. The core task is the tensor decomposition problem, which is to write a given tensor as a sum of rank one tensors, with the length of the sum as small as possible. A symmetric tensor can also be written as a sum of nonsymmetric rank one tensors. This causes symmetric tensors to have two different notions of ranks, which are cp ranks and symmetric ranks. Tensor decompositions can be done over either the real and complex field. Although the problems look similar, the computation for the real field is very different from the case of complex filed. This is because the real field is not algebraically closed, while the complex field is. In applications, tensors are often large scale, but their ranks may not be very big. Moreover, people often need to approximate a tensor by a low rank one, as close as possible. Unlike the matrix case, the best low rank approximation may not exist for tensors, but there always exist nearly optimal approximations. Generating polynomial is an efficient tool for computing tensor decompositions. This is because every symmetric tensor can be viewed as a homogeneous polynomial. The underlying mathematical techniques include computational algebra,&nbsp; polynomial and moment optimization, and relevant computational science. The PI has done research work on topics of low rank symmetric tensor approximations, tensor nuclear norms, Hankel tensor decompositions, detection of copositive matrices and tensors, completely positive binary tensors, tensor complementarity eigenvalues, polynomial optimization, Hermitian tensor decompositions, and related questions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Jiawang&nbsp;Nie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project is about computational methods for solving symmetric tensor problems. A tensor can be viewed a multi-indexed array. It is symmetric if its entries obey certain symmetric patterns. The core task is the tensor decomposition problem, which is to write a given tensor as a sum of rank one tensors, with the length of the sum as small as possible. A symmetric tensor can also be written as a sum of nonsymmetric rank one tensors. This causes symmetric tensors to have two different notions of ranks, which are cp ranks and symmetric ranks. Tensor decompositions can be done over either the real and complex field. Although the problems look similar, the computation for the real field is very different from the case of complex filed. This is because the real field is not algebraically closed, while the complex field is. In applications, tensors are often large scale, but their ranks may not be very big. Moreover, people often need to approximate a tensor by a low rank one, as close as possible. Unlike the matrix case, the best low rank approximation may not exist for tensors, but there always exist nearly optimal approximations. Generating polynomial is an efficient tool for computing tensor decompositions. This is because every symmetric tensor can be viewed as a homogeneous polynomial. The underlying mathematical techniques include computational algebra,  polynomial and moment optimization, and relevant computational science. The PI has done research work on topics of low rank symmetric tensor approximations, tensor nuclear norms, Hankel tensor decompositions, detection of copositive matrices and tensors, completely positive binary tensors, tensor complementarity eigenvalues, polynomial optimization, Hermitian tensor decompositions, and related questions.       Last Modified: 09/28/2020       Submitted by: Jiawang Nie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
