<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Kinetic Characterization of Three-Dimensional (3D) Magnetic Reconnection: A Transformative Step</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lisa Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwinter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928519</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the plasma and magnetic field conditions in the micro-scale regions where magnetic energy is converted to plasma kinetic energy during magnetic reconnection. Magnetic reconnection is, in effect, the breaking and reconnecting of magnetic field lines, which is accompanied by an explosive release of energy.  This explosive energy release is an important component of space weather disturbances in Earth's vicinity. Satellite observations and plasma simulations will be combined to study the energy conversion process. The science objectives of this proposal are closely aligned with the priorities of the NSF-DOE Plasma Physics Partnership.  As part of this program, NSF and the Department of Energy (DOE) will collaborate in supporting the investigation. The project will provide research training for a postdoctoral student, contributing to the future scientific workforce. The results of this research into a key energy conversion process in plasmas (magnetic reconnection) will be of interest to scientific disciplines outside of Geospace, including the astrophysics and laboratory fusion communities.  In the longer term, new knowledge about the triggers of explosive energy release during space storms will improve space weather prediction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An important element of the proposed investigation is the synthesis of satellite observations of the space environment and cutting-edge plasma simulations.  The space data will be obtained from a recently launched configuration of 4 satellites that form the Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) mission. MMS is capable of measuring the state of the electrons at two orders of magnitude higher cadence than any previous space missions.  This is vital in order to resolve plasma structures in these very spatially limited regions as the satellites fly through. The simulations will be done using a state-of-the-art 3D Particle-in-Cell (PIC) model optimized to run efficiently on supercomputers. Significant advances in knowledge are expected about: (1) plasma energization in various types of naturally occurring 3D magnetic and electric field configurations and (2) electric and magnetic field structures and their self-consistent plasma flow patterns in reconnection regions at the magnetopause and in the magnetotail.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1619584</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Li-Jen</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Li-Jen Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lijen@mailaps.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3012865358</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000429213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/29/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naoki</FirstName>
<LastName>Bessho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naoki Bessho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>naoki.bessho@nasa.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3012863368</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shan</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shan Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>swang90@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6036098487</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000789256</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5750</Code>
<Text>MAGNETOSPHERIC PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~97150</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~99973</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~102878</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aims to characterizing plasma energization in 3D reconnection configurations, and predicting and measuring electric and magnetic field structures of 3D reconnection pertaining to reconnection in the Earth&rsquo;s magnetosphere. The key outcomes are summarized as follows.</p> <p>1. We make progress in modeling the electron velocity distributions in the central reconnection region. By using the particle-in-cell simulations and theoretical analyses, the effects of the electron acceleration by the reconnection electric field and deflection by the guide magnetic field are incorporated in the model.</p> <p>2. The electron dynamics and energization in the central reconnection region are characterized using space observations by the Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) spacecraft. The observation results confirm the role of electron acceleration by the reconnection electric field, and discovered the effect of the guide field in alternating the electron orbit and creating beams in the distribution functions.</p> <p>3. We analyzed the energy partition between ions and electrons in reconnection with asymmetric upstream conditions, and the roles of different components of the electric fields, emphasizing the dependence on the distances from the reconnection X-line.</p> <p>4. We investigated the effect of the variation in the 3<sup>rd</sup> direction in addition to the reconnection plane, which was usually neglected in previous studies. The 3D effect enables generation of waves. We found with MMS observations that the lower-hybrid waves at the inflow-outflow boundary of the low-density side enables transport of electrons towards the inflow region, which alters the inflow plasma condition and affects electron heating. The lower-hybrid waves could also be generated in the central electron diffusion region during magnetotail reconnection due to the presence of the guide field, and the wave produces electron vortices and heating perpendicular to the magnetic field. The lower-hybrid waves associated with electron vortices close to the electron diffusion region is also found in particle-in-cell simulations . The observations in magnetotail also revealed that the kink-mode fluctuations enhance mixing of ions in reconnecting current sheets.</p> <p>5. We found magnetic reconnection in the transition of the Earth&rsquo;s bow shock in both MMS observations and particle-in-cell simulations. It opens a new direction of research, and will enable further understanding of reconnection and shocks as fundamental plasma phenomena.</p> <p>Our studies address the intellectual merit that improves the understanding of electron energization in laminar reconnection, reveals the 3D effects of reconnection in plasma dynamics and energization through waves and instabilities, and discovers reconnection in the shock transition region as an additional energy dissipation mechanism at shocks.</p> <p>In terms of broader impacts, our research could benefit the magnetosphere, astrophysical, and laboratory experiment communities that study magnetic reconnection or general plasma physics. During the project, Dr. Li-Jen Chen was promoted from an associate research scientist to a research scientist, Dr. Naoki Bessho was promoted from an assistant research scientist to an associate research scientist, Dr. Shan Wang was promoted from a postdoc to an assistant research scientist, and Dr. Jonathan Ng is involved as a postdoc.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Shan&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aims to characterizing plasma energization in 3D reconnection configurations, and predicting and measuring electric and magnetic field structures of 3D reconnection pertaining to reconnection in the Earth’s magnetosphere. The key outcomes are summarized as follows.  1. We make progress in modeling the electron velocity distributions in the central reconnection region. By using the particle-in-cell simulations and theoretical analyses, the effects of the electron acceleration by the reconnection electric field and deflection by the guide magnetic field are incorporated in the model.  2. The electron dynamics and energization in the central reconnection region are characterized using space observations by the Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) spacecraft. The observation results confirm the role of electron acceleration by the reconnection electric field, and discovered the effect of the guide field in alternating the electron orbit and creating beams in the distribution functions.  3. We analyzed the energy partition between ions and electrons in reconnection with asymmetric upstream conditions, and the roles of different components of the electric fields, emphasizing the dependence on the distances from the reconnection X-line.  4. We investigated the effect of the variation in the 3rd direction in addition to the reconnection plane, which was usually neglected in previous studies. The 3D effect enables generation of waves. We found with MMS observations that the lower-hybrid waves at the inflow-outflow boundary of the low-density side enables transport of electrons towards the inflow region, which alters the inflow plasma condition and affects electron heating. The lower-hybrid waves could also be generated in the central electron diffusion region during magnetotail reconnection due to the presence of the guide field, and the wave produces electron vortices and heating perpendicular to the magnetic field. The lower-hybrid waves associated with electron vortices close to the electron diffusion region is also found in particle-in-cell simulations . The observations in magnetotail also revealed that the kink-mode fluctuations enhance mixing of ions in reconnecting current sheets.  5. We found magnetic reconnection in the transition of the Earth’s bow shock in both MMS observations and particle-in-cell simulations. It opens a new direction of research, and will enable further understanding of reconnection and shocks as fundamental plasma phenomena.  Our studies address the intellectual merit that improves the understanding of electron energization in laminar reconnection, reveals the 3D effects of reconnection in plasma dynamics and energization through waves and instabilities, and discovers reconnection in the shock transition region as an additional energy dissipation mechanism at shocks.  In terms of broader impacts, our research could benefit the magnetosphere, astrophysical, and laboratory experiment communities that study magnetic reconnection or general plasma physics. During the project, Dr. Li-Jen Chen was promoted from an associate research scientist to a research scientist, Dr. Naoki Bessho was promoted from an assistant research scientist to an associate research scientist, Dr. Shan Wang was promoted from a postdoc to an assistant research scientist, and Dr. Jonathan Ng is involved as a postdoc.          Last Modified: 09/05/2020       Submitted by: Shan Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
