<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Reduced order models for imaging and inversion with waves and diffusive fields</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>209879.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>209879</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project's focus is on development of novel techniques for computational inversion and imaging problems arising in medical imaging, geophysical exploration, nondestructive evaluation and testing and other applications where the internal structure and properties of objects must be determined without direct access to the object's interior. The object is subjected to probing fields and the measurements of its response are made. Electromagnetic fields and acoustic waves are most often used for probing. Conventionally an inverse problem of determining an object's properties from the measurements is formulated as a minimization of a misfit between the measured data and the prediction of a forward model. Such problems are notoriously difficult to solve due to a highly nonlinear dependence of measurements on model properties. We propose an approach to inversion and imaging based on the theory of reduced order models (ROMs). This approach aims to alleviate the nonlinearity of the inverse problem thus making it much easier to solve. It allows one to obtain images free from various types of artifacts that conventional methods often struggle to remove. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed framework is general enough and can be applied to inversion and imaging both with waves and in diffusive regimes. First, a ROM is constructed as a projection of the partial differential equation (PDE) operator on subspaces of PDE solution snapshots either in the time or the frequency domain. This ensures that the ROM response interpolates the measured data. Even though neither the PDE operator nor the solution snapshots are directly accessible in inversion, projections can be computed from the measured data using the tools of linear algebra. After the ROM is constructed it may be used in at least two ways. First, it can be used in an imaging algorithm. Since the ROM is a projection of the PDE operator, an image can be constructed from the back-projection of a ROM. Model reduction takes into account nonlinear interactions between the reflectors and thus allows one to eliminate artifacts caused by multiple reflections. This is a vast improvement over conventional imaging approaches that are often based on linearizations (Born, Kirchhoff) which miss or misinterpret the nonlinear effects. Second, the ROM can be used to reformulate conventional optimization problems to minimize ROM misfit instead of data misfit. Such optimization objective is expected to be more convex which makes inversion less prone to local minima. Another consequence is accelerated convergence. The following specific aspects of ROMs for inversion and imaging are proposed: (1) new imaging functionals;(2) backscattering and non-collocated source/receiver data measurement settings; (3) nonlinear data preprocessing; (4) reformulations of conventional optimization approaches; (5) non-iterative inversion methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1619821</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Mamonov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Mamonov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mamonov@math.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137430297</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000708110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~64173</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~72500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~73206</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project addressed the development of a novel framework for computational solution of inverse problems for imaging with waves or diffuse fields based on the theory and techniques of model order reduction. Inverse problems are ubiquitous in medical imaging, geophysical exploration, nondestructive evaluation and testing and other applications where the internal structure and properties of an object must be determined without direct access to its interior. In such settings, the object of interest is probed by acoustic, elastic or electromagnetic waves while its response to probing pulses is measured at an array of sensors located close to or directly on its surface. An inverse problem of determining the object's interior properties from the measured response (data) is typically formulated as an optimization problem of minimizing a misfit between the data and a prediction of a forward model and is solved iteratively. Due to a highly nonlinear dependence of the measurements on the forward model parameters, such optimization problems are notoriously difficult to solve. Our framework based on reduced order models (ROM) alleviates these issues by "absorbing" much of this nonlinearity into the computation of the ROM from the measured data. Then, the reformulated inverse problem is both easier to solve numerically and it allows to obtain a higher quality estimate of object's properties compared to conventional approaches.</p> <p>In ROM-based framework for inversion, a ROM of the partial differential equation (PDE) operator that describes object's behavior is computed from the measured data. The first major achievement of the project is the derivation of formulas for such computation for both time-domain and frequency-domain measurements. The dependency of the computed "data-driven" ROM on the object's parameters of interest is relatively benign which leads to the following uses of the ROM that were fully developed in this project:</p> <p>(1) Novel techniques for imaging reflective structures with waves that are free from the multiple reflection artifacts. This is achieved due to the property of the ROM to take into account the nonlinear interactions between the reflectors. Our techniques offer a vast improvement over conventional imaging based on linearizations (e.g., reverse time migration) which often misinterprets multiple reflections leading to image deterioration (e.g., repetition artifacts in medical ultrasound imaging);</p> <p>(2) An approach to accurately approximate the solutions of the modeling PDE in the object's interior for the case of diffuse probing fields. This transforms the difficult inverse problem with boundary measurements into a much easier one with interior information. Subsequently, it can be solved using the techniques that exist for inversion with interior measurements;</p> <p>(3) A method for transforming the multiply scattered full waveform data into the data that would be measured if the waves in the object of interest propagated in the single scattering (Born) regime, the so-called Data-to-Born (DtB) transform. The DtB transform can be used as a nonlinear preprocessing step in existing inversion and imaging workflows based on linearized algorithms. While those algorithms produce incorrect results when applied to full waveform data, this can be rectified by feeding the DtB-transformed data instead. This method has a potential high impact in exploration geophysics;</p> <p>(4) Quantitative imaging algorithm for determining both the locations and strengths of scatterers. The use of ROMs makes it possible to design an algorithm that converges much faster than conventional iterative schemes and is less prone to getting stuck in local minima. It also outperforms existing schemes in terms of the quality of images for scenes with many scatterers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Mamonov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project addressed the development of a novel framework for computational solution of inverse problems for imaging with waves or diffuse fields based on the theory and techniques of model order reduction. Inverse problems are ubiquitous in medical imaging, geophysical exploration, nondestructive evaluation and testing and other applications where the internal structure and properties of an object must be determined without direct access to its interior. In such settings, the object of interest is probed by acoustic, elastic or electromagnetic waves while its response to probing pulses is measured at an array of sensors located close to or directly on its surface. An inverse problem of determining the object's interior properties from the measured response (data) is typically formulated as an optimization problem of minimizing a misfit between the data and a prediction of a forward model and is solved iteratively. Due to a highly nonlinear dependence of the measurements on the forward model parameters, such optimization problems are notoriously difficult to solve. Our framework based on reduced order models (ROM) alleviates these issues by "absorbing" much of this nonlinearity into the computation of the ROM from the measured data. Then, the reformulated inverse problem is both easier to solve numerically and it allows to obtain a higher quality estimate of object's properties compared to conventional approaches.  In ROM-based framework for inversion, a ROM of the partial differential equation (PDE) operator that describes object's behavior is computed from the measured data. The first major achievement of the project is the derivation of formulas for such computation for both time-domain and frequency-domain measurements. The dependency of the computed "data-driven" ROM on the object's parameters of interest is relatively benign which leads to the following uses of the ROM that were fully developed in this project:  (1) Novel techniques for imaging reflective structures with waves that are free from the multiple reflection artifacts. This is achieved due to the property of the ROM to take into account the nonlinear interactions between the reflectors. Our techniques offer a vast improvement over conventional imaging based on linearizations (e.g., reverse time migration) which often misinterprets multiple reflections leading to image deterioration (e.g., repetition artifacts in medical ultrasound imaging);  (2) An approach to accurately approximate the solutions of the modeling PDE in the object's interior for the case of diffuse probing fields. This transforms the difficult inverse problem with boundary measurements into a much easier one with interior information. Subsequently, it can be solved using the techniques that exist for inversion with interior measurements;  (3) A method for transforming the multiply scattered full waveform data into the data that would be measured if the waves in the object of interest propagated in the single scattering (Born) regime, the so-called Data-to-Born (DtB) transform. The DtB transform can be used as a nonlinear preprocessing step in existing inversion and imaging workflows based on linearized algorithms. While those algorithms produce incorrect results when applied to full waveform data, this can be rectified by feeding the DtB-transformed data instead. This method has a potential high impact in exploration geophysics;  (4) Quantitative imaging algorithm for determining both the locations and strengths of scatterers. The use of ROMs makes it possible to design an algorithm that converges much faster than conventional iterative schemes and is less prone to getting stuck in local minima. It also outperforms existing schemes in terms of the quality of images for scenes with many scatterers.          Last Modified: 09/27/2020       Submitted by: Alexander Mamonov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
