<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theoretical Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1950000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1950000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professors Maria C. Gonzalez-Garcia, Christopher P. Herzog, Patrick Meade, Leonardo Rastelli, Martin Rocek, Robert Shrock, Warren Siegel and George Sterman at Stony Brook University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Physics is constantly evolving as new techniques and capabilities are developed to understand the natural world.  This award supports research in a broad but deeply related set of topics in Theoretical Physics, and engagement at each of these frontiers of knowledge serves the national interest by advancing fundamental scientific progress in the United States.    Investigations will include the analysis of high-energy collisions of elementary particles, which probe the fundamental laws upon which the material universe is based, and proposals for new experiments involving elementary particles and atomic nuclei.    These subjects are closely related to the deep mysteries of gravity, space and time, and the possibility that all of the known forces in nature are related, possibly unifying gravity itself with the forces that are seen in electrical phenomena, in radioactivity, and in nuclear physics.   The theoretical methods developed in particle and nuclear physics have also been found to have exciting applications to chemical compounds and metals with unusual properties, like superconductivity.  New theoretical methods, sometimes relying on modern computational capabilities, are making possible reliable predictions for the properties of solids and liquids that were previously thought intractable.   This research, by advancing our knowledge of the laws of nature and by contributing to a better understanding of the physical universe, including practical materials, has significant broader impacts and implications for our world view. Indeed, many of the topics under study by the senior participants are frequently discussed in the media, including the Higgs boson, black holes, the role of neutrinos in the Universe, string theory, the quark-gluon plasma, and quantum entanglement. The research carried out under this award will also serve in the training of graduate students and mentoring of postdoctoral fellows at the highest levels. The faculty on this proposal conduct their research with graduate students, and share their experience and expertise with undergraduates and community members, in and beyond the classroom.   Individual members will also continue their own outreach activities, which have included successful traditions in high-school research mentoring and in the organization of science playwriting competitions.       &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At the technical level, this award will support research over a wide range of theoretical physics, largely based on quantum field theory and string theory. Recent years have seen a strengthening engagement of theory and experiment in particle physics, with new and exciting data from the Large Hadron Collider, from neutrino observatories and cosmic ray satellites. These new sources of information concerning our universe enable theorists to test long-standing ideas against evolving data, and to develop new theoretical methods to guide experiment.    At the same time, novel applications of quantum field and string theory, such as applications of duality and the conformal bootstrap, have been developed in and beyond particle physics, opening unexpected avenues of research into nuclear physics, condensed matter physics, and quantum information, sometimes with applications in pure mathematics. As active participants in these historic developments, the senior personnel of this award will continue and develop their work in high energy collider phenomenology, quantum chromodynamics, in neutrino and astroparticle physics, in applications of gauge-gravity duality, conformal field theory, extensions of the Standard Model, electroweak symmetry breaking, superstrings, and the geometry of supersymmetric gauge theories.   This research will also help train a new generation of theorists at the postdoctoral and graduate levels.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620628</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Shrock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert E Shrock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.shrock@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316327986</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000098140</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Sterman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George Sterman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>george.sterman@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316327967</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000231081</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Rocek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin Rocek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rocek@max2.physics.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316327965</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117943840</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~650000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~811447</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~488553</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The project "Theoretical Physics" resulted in significant advances in broad areas of theoretical physics. Many of these advances relate to quantum field theory, an indispensible contemporary tool to study nature, from elementary particles and forces to materials with special electronic properties and applications. As faculty members at Stony Brook University, the project's senior participants engage in both undergraduate and graduate instruction, which is enriched by their research activities. Mentorship by senior participants promoted the career development of junior participants through doctoral and postdoctoral research and training.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;These advances are summarized briefly below.</span></p> <p><span>Intellectual Merit: A frontier area in elementary particle physics is the study of neutrinos, where experiments in the US and Japan are seeking to determine properties of these mysterious particles, possibly related to the dominance of matter over antimatter in the universe. New studies were published that statistically synthesize the world's current data on neutrinos. These studies are widely used, serving as benchmarks for the development of such national programs as "Dune", the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment.&nbsp;Neutrinos also play a critical role in how the sun shines.&nbsp;&nbsp;A study comparing particle experiments and solar observations was continued.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Studies produced from this award also serve to provide theoretical guidance for the exploration of fundamental matter and forces at the Large Hadron Collider, the world's highest-energy particle accelerator. New methods were described on how and where to look for evidence for extensions of the Standard Model.&nbsp;&nbsp;The Standard Model describes visible matter, the structure of atoms and their nuclei, including forces that produce the decay of elementary particles and mediate the production of energy in stars.&nbsp;&nbsp;Experiments at particle colliders also provide information on possible ways in which the Standard Model can arise from more fundamental theories, and how the visible world may have emerged at the earliest moments of our expanding universe.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;New ideas were developed and published that explore these connections, and which suggest experiments that can be carried out to test the Standard Model in new ways.</span></p> <p><span>The Standard Model is a set of quantum field theories, and our investigations into nature naturally pose the question of what kinds of quantum fields are possible, whether it is conceivable to "chart" a space of self-consistent field theories.&nbsp;&nbsp;In the award period, considerable progress has been made in analyzing properties of theories on the basis of their internal mathematical structure, their "symmetries".&nbsp;&nbsp;Such studies do not rely on assuming a list of the theory's particles and the mutual forces between them, which had conventionally been thought unavoidable.&nbsp;Important results were reported starting from this more abstract point of view. &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Within the Standard Model, studies were carried out on properties of quantum field theories that are particularly relevant to the nuclear, or "strong" force in the Standard Model, which binds together atomic nuclei. New approaches to quantum fields were explored in model field theories, which have already improved our understanding of how the strong force can produce composite particles like the proton and neutron out of elementary particles like quarks and gluons, and on the production of new particles in collisions at accelerators.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>To understand the ultimate origin of the quantum fields that we observe in nature, string theory offers a compelling template, which appears to require that there are as-yet unobserved dimensions beyond the three plus time that we observe around us. Methods to explore the theoretical potential of these proposals have been developed. The analysis of string theories requires the creation of new mathematical tools for curved space-time, and progress was made in the exploration of these possibilities.&nbsp;&nbsp;Studies were also carried out on a property of quantum fields known as entanglement, which is the basis of quantum computing, and which has become an area of focus worldwide for its profound interest and its potential applications. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Broader Impact: Much of this work was carried out with doctoral students and junior postdoctoral researchers, as an integral part of their professional training. The senior investigators participate in teaching at the graduate and undergraduate levels at Stony Brook University, and are also active in outreach and training outside the university, including lectures at advanced international schools. Project participants contributed to national planning exercises for the use of existing and the development of future scientific facilities. Activities engaging science with drama were sponsored by senior participants, and members provided varied outreach lectures to the public.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The scientific progress described above contributes to the understanding of our physical world at both its fundamental and emergent levels, and also to the national interest, through the maintenance of frontier research and the development of a workforce that is equipped with technical training and experience in solving challenging problems.&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2019<br>      Modified by: George&nbsp;Sterman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project "Theoretical Physics" resulted in significant advances in broad areas of theoretical physics. Many of these advances relate to quantum field theory, an indispensible contemporary tool to study nature, from elementary particles and forces to materials with special electronic properties and applications. As faculty members at Stony Brook University, the project's senior participants engage in both undergraduate and graduate instruction, which is enriched by their research activities. Mentorship by senior participants promoted the career development of junior participants through doctoral and postdoctoral research and training.   These advances are summarized briefly below.  Intellectual Merit: A frontier area in elementary particle physics is the study of neutrinos, where experiments in the US and Japan are seeking to determine properties of these mysterious particles, possibly related to the dominance of matter over antimatter in the universe. New studies were published that statistically synthesize the world's current data on neutrinos. These studies are widely used, serving as benchmarks for the development of such national programs as "Dune", the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment. Neutrinos also play a critical role in how the sun shines.  A study comparing particle experiments and solar observations was continued.   Studies produced from this award also serve to provide theoretical guidance for the exploration of fundamental matter and forces at the Large Hadron Collider, the world's highest-energy particle accelerator. New methods were described on how and where to look for evidence for extensions of the Standard Model.  The Standard Model describes visible matter, the structure of atoms and their nuclei, including forces that produce the decay of elementary particles and mediate the production of energy in stars.  Experiments at particle colliders also provide information on possible ways in which the Standard Model can arise from more fundamental theories, and how the visible world may have emerged at the earliest moments of our expanding universe.   New ideas were developed and published that explore these connections, and which suggest experiments that can be carried out to test the Standard Model in new ways.  The Standard Model is a set of quantum field theories, and our investigations into nature naturally pose the question of what kinds of quantum fields are possible, whether it is conceivable to "chart" a space of self-consistent field theories.  In the award period, considerable progress has been made in analyzing properties of theories on the basis of their internal mathematical structure, their "symmetries".  Such studies do not rely on assuming a list of the theory's particles and the mutual forces between them, which had conventionally been thought unavoidable. Important results were reported starting from this more abstract point of view.     Within the Standard Model, studies were carried out on properties of quantum field theories that are particularly relevant to the nuclear, or "strong" force in the Standard Model, which binds together atomic nuclei. New approaches to quantum fields were explored in model field theories, which have already improved our understanding of how the strong force can produce composite particles like the proton and neutron out of elementary particles like quarks and gluons, and on the production of new particles in collisions at accelerators.   To understand the ultimate origin of the quantum fields that we observe in nature, string theory offers a compelling template, which appears to require that there are as-yet unobserved dimensions beyond the three plus time that we observe around us. Methods to explore the theoretical potential of these proposals have been developed. The analysis of string theories requires the creation of new mathematical tools for curved space-time, and progress was made in the exploration of these possibilities.  Studies were also carried out on a property of quantum fields known as entanglement, which is the basis of quantum computing, and which has become an area of focus worldwide for its profound interest and its potential applications.    Broader Impact: Much of this work was carried out with doctoral students and junior postdoctoral researchers, as an integral part of their professional training. The senior investigators participate in teaching at the graduate and undergraduate levels at Stony Brook University, and are also active in outreach and training outside the university, including lectures at advanced international schools. Project participants contributed to national planning exercises for the use of existing and the development of future scientific facilities. Activities engaging science with drama were sponsored by senior participants, and members provided varied outreach lectures to the public.   The scientific progress described above contributes to the understanding of our physical world at both its fundamental and emergent levels, and also to the national interest, through the maintenance of frontier research and the development of a workforce that is equipped with technical training and experience in solving challenging problems.             Last Modified: 12/18/2019       Submitted by: George Sterman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
