<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Adaptive Multiscale Simulation Framework for Reduced-Order Modeling in Perforated Domains</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Processes in perforated domains occur in many important applications. These include complex processes in soil, membranes, and filters. With current imaging techniques, detailed microscale geometries of these perforated materials can be constructed. However, it is prohibitively expensive to solve complex processes in these perforated domains due to a rich hierarchy of scales. For this reason, some types of reduced-order computational techniques are needed. The goal of this project is to develop and analyze novel computational techniques for solving challenging multiscale problems in perforated domains. The new approaches will bring the information from the detailed geometries to large-scale simulations and will improve the predictions in the simulations. This will further allow deigning new materials and optimize processes.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Many current approaches for multiscale methods for problems in perforated domains have been restricted to homogenization, which is applicable when the media has scale separation. However, in many realistic perforated media, there is no scale separation, i.e., pore sizes can have a wide variety of scales. The multiscale methods of this project develop a general framework that allows rigorous and systematic reduction. The PI's goals are: (1) to develop systematic local model reduction tools for computing multiscale basis functions; (2) to develop and analyze new finite element techniques using these basis functions; (3) to study the interplay between localization of the basis functions and the global coupling mechanism; (4) to apply the developed methods to a wide variety of flows with nonlinearities and multiphysics in 3D; (5) to test and demonstrate their capabilities for solving problems in engineering and geosciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620318</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raytcho</FirstName>
<LastName>Lazarov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raytcho D Lazarov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lazarov@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7862021878</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000413976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/11/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yalchin</FirstName>
<LastName>Efendiev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yalchin Efendiev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>efendiev@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798451972</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433368</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Blocker 608K]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~85448</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~79389</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~45163</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project deals with the development of efficient computational techniques for problems in complex domains. One of challenging complex domain problems consists of multiphysics problems formulated in perforated domains. Such domains arise in many applications, for example, filters, porous media, membranes and so on. In all these applications, processes occur in small regions around inclusions of various shapes. Simulations of these problems are challenging as the computational mesh needs to be adjusted.&nbsp;Pore sizes can have large variations with different pore throat sizes and geometries. One often needs to solve the problem for each realization representing heterogeneities. Thus, model reduction across small scales is the most promising approach in substantially reducing the computational complexity. In this proposal, we have made some important contributions in solving such challenging problems. Designing multiscale model reduction techniques that can provide accurate solutions and are robust is a challenging problem and is the proposal&rsquo;s main objective.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In the proposal, we have formulated a general simulation framework for solving challengiing problems in perforated domains. Our approaches generate multiscale basis functions that capture both geometry and physics and couple it via a global formulation. In this framework, a coarse mesh that is much larger compared perforations can be used for computation. This allows deriving macroscopic model and finding an accurate solution. Moreover, these techniques allow using machine learning and solving inverse problems.</p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>This project presents a decisive step toward developing rigorous multiscale model reduction techniques that use the framework of Galerkin methods and can apply to various complex problems. The proposed methods are robust with respect to physical parameters and allow a systematically reducing of the degrees of freedom. This is important for many applications, especially when the problem needs to be repeated solving for different parameter values, source terms, and boundary conditions due to nonlinearities and uncertainties. Our approach aid solving challenging problems in different application domains. </span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The novel methods and algorithms developed here significantly advance current state-of-the-art numerical methods and their applications for multiscale problems in per- forated media. These, in turn, will improve our ability to compute efficiently problem solutions in highly heterogeneous media. This project trained graduate students. </span></p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Yalchin&nbsp;Efendiev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project deals with the development of efficient computational techniques for problems in complex domains. One of challenging complex domain problems consists of multiphysics problems formulated in perforated domains. Such domains arise in many applications, for example, filters, porous media, membranes and so on. In all these applications, processes occur in small regions around inclusions of various shapes. Simulations of these problems are challenging as the computational mesh needs to be adjusted. Pore sizes can have large variations with different pore throat sizes and geometries. One often needs to solve the problem for each realization representing heterogeneities. Thus, model reduction across small scales is the most promising approach in substantially reducing the computational complexity. In this proposal, we have made some important contributions in solving such challenging problems. Designing multiscale model reduction techniques that can provide accurate solutions and are robust is a challenging problem and is the proposal’s main objective.        In the proposal, we have formulated a general simulation framework for solving challengiing problems in perforated domains. Our approaches generate multiscale basis functions that capture both geometry and physics and couple it via a global formulation. In this framework, a coarse mesh that is much larger compared perforations can be used for computation. This allows deriving macroscopic model and finding an accurate solution. Moreover, these techniques allow using machine learning and solving inverse problems.     This project presents a decisive step toward developing rigorous multiscale model reduction techniques that use the framework of Galerkin methods and can apply to various complex problems. The proposed methods are robust with respect to physical parameters and allow a systematically reducing of the degrees of freedom. This is important for many applications, especially when the problem needs to be repeated solving for different parameter values, source terms, and boundary conditions due to nonlinearities and uncertainties. Our approach aid solving challenging problems in different application domains.            The novel methods and algorithms developed here significantly advance current state-of-the-art numerical methods and their applications for multiscale problems in per- forated media. These, in turn, will improve our ability to compute efficiently problem solutions in highly heterogeneous media. This project trained graduate students.           Last Modified: 07/05/2021       Submitted by: Yalchin Efendiev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
