<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computing and Intersectionality (The Social and Behavioral Structures at Play for Black Women in the Computing Sciences): An Inclusive Agenda for Computing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49228.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49228</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Janice Cuny</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Broadening participation in all of the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields as well as in computing, which is critical to all of the STEM fields, is a national challenge. Achieving gender equity in computing is one of the more pressing challenges in the broadening participation effort because of the precipitous decline in the proportion of women earning degrees in computing over the last 20 years. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will bring together thought leaders to share experiences in an effort to understand the issues faced by black women in computing. Black women, as a group, face acute underrepresentation in computing. Their challenges rest at the intersection of race and gender in the larger broadening participation effort. The goals of this workshop are to: 1) explore the intersectional experiences (race and gender) of black women in CS; and 2) formulate strategies and a plan of action to address the lack of awareness and action around this intersectionality. The workshop addresses these goals by featuring break-out sessions that will enable the collection of rich, qualitative information about the experiences of black women in computing, as well as capture best practices for supporting this population. The data and report from the workshop will inform the STEM+C research community on the specific factors associated with women of color in computing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620932</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jakita</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jakita O Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jnt0020@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348446498</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000559417</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Legand</FirstName>
<LastName>Burge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Legand L Burge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>blegand@scs.howard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028064852</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000454593</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/25/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamika</FirstName>
<LastName>Burge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamika D Burge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jamika.burge@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5409031573</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643684</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamika</FirstName>
<LastName>Burge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamika D Burge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jamika.burge@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5409031573</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643684</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/25/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Howard University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200599000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028064759</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2400 Sixth Street N W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>056282296</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HOWARD UNIVERSITY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>056282296</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Howard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200590002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 Sixth Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~49228</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SUMMARY</p> <p>This two-day workshop explored the intersectional experiences of black women in the computing sciences and formulated strategies into an actionable plan that addressed the lack of awareness and action around this intersectionality.&nbsp;This workshop explored questions issues relating to improving and/or supporting black women's experiences in their computing careers, which can be represented broadly by the intersectionality of race and gender, to contribute to the body of computer science education research. The goals of the two-day workshop were to 1) explore the intersectional experiences of black women in the computing sciences, and 2) formulate strategies into an actionable plan that will address the lack of awareness around this intersectionality. &nbsp;This report describes data collected from the workshop (via focus group-style breakout sessions and post-workshop surveys), and seeks to inform the larger STEM+C research community of the specific factors associated with black women in computing. These results may also speak to women of color in computing more broadly, though additional research is needed.</p> <p>GUIDING QUESTIONS DURING THE WORKSHOP</p> <p>There were three main guiding questions during the workshop:</p> <p>1. Why don&rsquo;t interventions for women in computing work for black women in computing? For example, how are white women&rsquo;s experiences at the Grace Hopper Conference (GHC) different from black women&rsquo;s experiences at GHC?</p> <p>2. What are the implicit and explicit gender and stereotype biases for black women in computing? For example, what are the stereotype threats, implicit biases, isolation management strategies, etc. for black women, and how do they differ from the experiences of other women?</p> <p>3. What are tangible intervention/ support strategies for black women in computing? For example, can we develop strategies for attending technical conferences, creating a&nbsp;model for computing education that includes culture-specific content?</p> <p>For two days in January 2016, 24 black women in computing representing academe, industry, and government convened to discuss these guiding questions and strategize over how to improve the experiences, and success rates, of black women in computing. The workshop included small-group breakout sessions to discuss these guiding questions, and then culminated in a whole group discussion and action planning.&nbsp;</p> <p>OUTCOMES</p> <p>Workshop participants developed the following seven themes:</p> <ul> <li>Theme 1: Linking black women in computing to the bottom line for accountability</li> <li>Theme 2: Developing key influencers and thought leaders</li> <li>Theme 3: Increased cultural and educational supports for black women in computing</li> <li>Theme 4: Leadership development</li> <li>Theme 5: Lack of collective research about black women in computing</li> <li>Theme 6: Our voices: Illuminating our trials and triumphs</li> <li>Theme 7: Branding and communication</li> </ul> <p>The participants discussed key issues, concerns, and strategies for each theme. They created an action plan of next steps for each, creating an initial working tem and assigning a lead for each theme. &nbsp;</p> <p>Data from the observations gathered during the breakouts showed that every participant during the small breakout sessions made contributions to the discussion, and they were active listeners. Participants also provide feedback via surveys as a result of their breakout session and post-workshop experiences.&nbsp; Survey results showed, consistently, that participants valued the importance of creating a safe, open, and supportive environment to talk about the experiences of black women in computing. &ldquo;I am not alone!&rdquo; mantra was common across the surveys. A respondent eloquently stated, &ldquo;[It was a] safe space created by the organizers and facilitators that allowed the women to interact authentically&rdquo;. Affirming the intersectionality of race and gender in computing with others was particularly &ldquo;refreshing&rdquo;, &ldquo;inspiring&rdquo;, and &ldquo;heartwarming.&rdquo; As one respondent noted, &ldquo;As black women, we have been integrating ourselves for far too long. The result is that sometimes we can lose our identity in the process. This was clear to me when we had some hesitation using black women instead of like-minded people when developing action items related to community.&rdquo; Collectively creating an action plan for and by black women in computing was highlighted by many respondents. A respondent stated the workshop was beneficial for &ldquo;organizing a movement around black women in computing to fight against not being seen or heard.&rdquo;&nbsp;</p> <p>CONCLUSION &amp; NEXT STEPS</p> <p>Benefits that were most commonly cited by the participants include:</p> <ul> <li>Sharing their experiences in a safe and supportive environment,</li> <li>Affirming the intersectionality of race and gender, and owning the identity and role of black women in computing, and</li> <li>Collectively creating an action plan of solutions to promote black women in computing.</li> </ul> <p>The recommendations and next steps show the action plan by theme identified during the workshop. During the workshop, participants signed up to take the lead and created working groups focused on each theme with action items and next steps (often with timelines). As one participant noted, this is the first step in continuing to address and&nbsp;meet the needs of black women in computing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Legand&nbsp;L&nbsp;Burge</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SUMMARY  This two-day workshop explored the intersectional experiences of black women in the computing sciences and formulated strategies into an actionable plan that addressed the lack of awareness and action around this intersectionality. This workshop explored questions issues relating to improving and/or supporting black women's experiences in their computing careers, which can be represented broadly by the intersectionality of race and gender, to contribute to the body of computer science education research. The goals of the two-day workshop were to 1) explore the intersectional experiences of black women in the computing sciences, and 2) formulate strategies into an actionable plan that will address the lack of awareness around this intersectionality.  This report describes data collected from the workshop (via focus group-style breakout sessions and post-workshop surveys), and seeks to inform the larger STEM+C research community of the specific factors associated with black women in computing. These results may also speak to women of color in computing more broadly, though additional research is needed.  GUIDING QUESTIONS DURING THE WORKSHOP  There were three main guiding questions during the workshop:  1. Why don?t interventions for women in computing work for black women in computing? For example, how are white women?s experiences at the Grace Hopper Conference (GHC) different from black women?s experiences at GHC?  2. What are the implicit and explicit gender and stereotype biases for black women in computing? For example, what are the stereotype threats, implicit biases, isolation management strategies, etc. for black women, and how do they differ from the experiences of other women?  3. What are tangible intervention/ support strategies for black women in computing? For example, can we develop strategies for attending technical conferences, creating a model for computing education that includes culture-specific content?  For two days in January 2016, 24 black women in computing representing academe, industry, and government convened to discuss these guiding questions and strategize over how to improve the experiences, and success rates, of black women in computing. The workshop included small-group breakout sessions to discuss these guiding questions, and then culminated in a whole group discussion and action planning.   OUTCOMES  Workshop participants developed the following seven themes:  Theme 1: Linking black women in computing to the bottom line for accountability Theme 2: Developing key influencers and thought leaders Theme 3: Increased cultural and educational supports for black women in computing Theme 4: Leadership development Theme 5: Lack of collective research about black women in computing Theme 6: Our voices: Illuminating our trials and triumphs Theme 7: Branding and communication   The participants discussed key issues, concerns, and strategies for each theme. They created an action plan of next steps for each, creating an initial working tem and assigning a lead for each theme.    Data from the observations gathered during the breakouts showed that every participant during the small breakout sessions made contributions to the discussion, and they were active listeners. Participants also provide feedback via surveys as a result of their breakout session and post-workshop experiences.  Survey results showed, consistently, that participants valued the importance of creating a safe, open, and supportive environment to talk about the experiences of black women in computing. "I am not alone!" mantra was common across the surveys. A respondent eloquently stated, "[It was a] safe space created by the organizers and facilitators that allowed the women to interact authentically". Affirming the intersectionality of race and gender in computing with others was particularly "refreshing", "inspiring", and "heartwarming." As one respondent noted, "As black women, we have been integrating ourselves for far too long. The result is that sometimes we can lose our identity in the process. This was clear to me when we had some hesitation using black women instead of like-minded people when developing action items related to community." Collectively creating an action plan for and by black women in computing was highlighted by many respondents. A respondent stated the workshop was beneficial for "organizing a movement around black women in computing to fight against not being seen or heard."   CONCLUSION &amp; NEXT STEPS  Benefits that were most commonly cited by the participants include:  Sharing their experiences in a safe and supportive environment, Affirming the intersectionality of race and gender, and owning the identity and role of black women in computing, and Collectively creating an action plan of solutions to promote black women in computing.   The recommendations and next steps show the action plan by theme identified during the workshop. During the workshop, participants signed up to take the lead and created working groups focused on each theme with action items and next steps (often with timelines). As one participant noted, this is the first step in continuing to address and meet the needs of black women in computing.       Last Modified: 09/29/2017       Submitted by: Legand L Burge]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
