<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nonlinear Instability of Navier-Stokes equations from a probabilistic point of view: Numerics and Simulations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>183001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>183001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>During the last two decades, there has been a widespread interest in uncertainty quantification from academia to industry, where stochastic models and approaches have been developed to effectively describe the propagation of uncertainty of different sources in complex systems, and the interplay of mathematical modeling and experimental data. For example, classical deterministic differential equations have been relaxed to a random one by taking into account the uncertainty in physical parameters, initial/boundary conditions, etc. This strategy is being employed more and more in industrial design to enhance robustness and efficiency. Bayesian inference has been applied to inverse problems in a more natural way to deal with the noisy observations, which actually turns an ill-posed deterministic inverse problem into a well-posed one from the probabilistic point of view. In this project the Principal Investigator considers a stochastic formulation of a classical problem in dynamical system - nonlinear instability of wall-bounded parallel shear flows.  The strategy will be based on a very general observation: under the excitation of noise, no matter how small the amplitude of noise is, states that are impossible for a deterministic mathematical model can be explored by a stochastic model. The issue of particular interest is the transitions to the anomalous states that occur rarely but have major impact, such as system failure, loss of stability, etc. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The main mathematical tool in this project is the Freidlin-Wentzell theory of large deviations for small random perturbations of dynamical systems. One typical scenario of nonlinear instability in many wall-bounded flows is the subcritical bifurcation of Navier-Stokes equations with respect to the Reynolds number, where the equation can have at least two stable solutions for a certain Reynolds number. The Principal Investigator will recast nonlinear instability in a stochastic setting and regard it as a rare event triggered by small noise. Mathematically, a question considered is how the nonlinear instability develops as the amplitude of noise goes to zero. The large deviation principle asserts that such a transition will occur mainly following a path given by the minimizer of the action functional.  The mail goal of this project is twofold: 1) Develop efficient numerical algorithms to seek the most probable transition path that is critical for the development of nonlinear instability; and 2) Extensive numerical studies of the subcritical bifurcation of wall-bounded parallel shear flows. The first task will be achieved by hp adaptive finite element discretization in time direction and spectral method for spatial discretization incorporating with parallel computing. In particular, the pressure will be removed from the formula using a divergence-free space such that one can reduce the number of degrees of freedom and just focus on the instability. In the second task, the focus is on the relation between the action-based stability theory and classical stability theories such as linear stability theory, nonlinear stability theory, nonmodal theory, edge state and minimal energy perturbation study. More specifically, small noise will be added to some classical deterministic models in literature to seek extra information that cannot be given by deterministic stability theories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620026</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoliang</FirstName>
<LastName>Wan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoliang Wan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xlwan@math.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255782760</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000531549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University & Agricultural and Mechanical College]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~183001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the past two decades, there has been a widespread interest in uncertainty quantification (UQ) to develop stochastic models and approaches to quantitatively describe the propagation of uncertainty of difference sources in complex systems, and the interplay of mathematical modeling and experimental data. Through these efforts a deeper understanding or more informative predictions can be obtained for realistic applications. To achieve this, we need to develop efficient algorithms to leverage the capability of scientific computing. In this project, we studied a probabilistic strategy to understand the nonlinearity of Navier-Stokes equations, which describe the motion of fluids and have a wide range of applications in reality. Although the modern hydrodynamic stability theory has evolved for more than a century and many remarkable accomplishments have been achieved, many fundamental problems remain quite open, from the development of nonlinear instability to the transition to turbulence. One typical scenario of nonlinear instability in many wall-bounded flows is the subcritical bifurcation of Naiver-Stokes equations with respect to the Reynolds number, where the equation can have at least two stable solutions for a certain Reynolds number. The widely used linear stability theory fails to predict a reasonable Reynolds number that can be justified in experiments. We have recast the nonlinear instability of Navier-Stokes equations in a stochastic setting. &nbsp;We add a small random forcing and quantify the effects by the large deviation theory. This provides an opportunity to study the global behaviors induced by perturbations instead of the local behaviors studied by classical stability theories.</p> <p>In this project we have endeavored to develop necessary algorithms to apply the large deviation theory to Navier-Stokes equations and other dynamical systems. We have achieved the following main results: 1) We have unified the minimum action method induced by the large deviation theory and the dynamic solver induced by the discretization of Navier-Stokes equations. The transition path of the maximum likelihood given by the minimum action method can be examined in detail the by dynamical solver in the same configuration space. 2) We have established and analyzed a new minimum action method in the framework of finite element method. The new method integrates the a posteriori estimate and hp-adaptivity into the minimum action method. Furthermore, the new method can deal with a wider range of problems compared to available approaches. 3) We have achieved a preliminary success in integrating recently developed deep learning techniques into our methodology. We have proposed new deep generative models for density estimation and examined their applications into importance sampling and variational Bayes. The aforementioned and other results have been summarized in ten journal papers, where nine of them have been &nbsp;published or accepted and the other one is under peer review. This project has also partially supported two PhD dissertations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Xiaoliang&nbsp;Wan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the past two decades, there has been a widespread interest in uncertainty quantification (UQ) to develop stochastic models and approaches to quantitatively describe the propagation of uncertainty of difference sources in complex systems, and the interplay of mathematical modeling and experimental data. Through these efforts a deeper understanding or more informative predictions can be obtained for realistic applications. To achieve this, we need to develop efficient algorithms to leverage the capability of scientific computing. In this project, we studied a probabilistic strategy to understand the nonlinearity of Navier-Stokes equations, which describe the motion of fluids and have a wide range of applications in reality. Although the modern hydrodynamic stability theory has evolved for more than a century and many remarkable accomplishments have been achieved, many fundamental problems remain quite open, from the development of nonlinear instability to the transition to turbulence. One typical scenario of nonlinear instability in many wall-bounded flows is the subcritical bifurcation of Naiver-Stokes equations with respect to the Reynolds number, where the equation can have at least two stable solutions for a certain Reynolds number. The widely used linear stability theory fails to predict a reasonable Reynolds number that can be justified in experiments. We have recast the nonlinear instability of Navier-Stokes equations in a stochastic setting.  We add a small random forcing and quantify the effects by the large deviation theory. This provides an opportunity to study the global behaviors induced by perturbations instead of the local behaviors studied by classical stability theories.  In this project we have endeavored to develop necessary algorithms to apply the large deviation theory to Navier-Stokes equations and other dynamical systems. We have achieved the following main results: 1) We have unified the minimum action method induced by the large deviation theory and the dynamic solver induced by the discretization of Navier-Stokes equations. The transition path of the maximum likelihood given by the minimum action method can be examined in detail the by dynamical solver in the same configuration space. 2) We have established and analyzed a new minimum action method in the framework of finite element method. The new method integrates the a posteriori estimate and hp-adaptivity into the minimum action method. Furthermore, the new method can deal with a wider range of problems compared to available approaches. 3) We have achieved a preliminary success in integrating recently developed deep learning techniques into our methodology. We have proposed new deep generative models for density estimation and examined their applications into importance sampling and variational Bayes. The aforementioned and other results have been summarized in ten journal papers, where nine of them have been  published or accepted and the other one is under peer review. This project has also partially supported two PhD dissertations.          Last Modified: 10/28/2020       Submitted by: Xiaoliang Wan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
