<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF-SIAM Optics and Photonics Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Principal Investigator will organize the "NSF-SIAM Optics and Photonics Workshop" which will be held as part of the Annual Meeting of the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) in Boston, MA, July 11-15, 2016.  Advances in our understanding of the behavior of light are necessary both for improvements on current technologies and for the realization of new and envisioned technologies.  These technologies influence directly a variety of sectors in our society, including communications, defense and national security, energy, and medicine.  Due to recent advances in computational tools, materials science, and nanostructure fabrication, mathematicians have a larger role than ever to play in this field.  This workshop will allow leading applied mathematicians to bring their vision of the future of mathematics in optics and photonics to a large mathematical audience.  The meeting will encourage collaborations among researchers in this field from a diverse set of scientific backgrounds, and the majority of the funding will be devoted to supporting the participation of early career researchers and applied mathematicians from underrepresented groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will take place completely on the first day of the SIAM Annual Meeting, Monday, July 11, 2016, and will feature several accomplished applied mathematicians in the field of optics and photonics.  The talks will survey the field and its open problems for the broader applied mathematics community.  Topics that will be covered include (1) research on light-matter interaction, including low-loss metamaterials, plasmonics, and quantum phenomena; (2) multiphysics coupling between classical electromagnetic and quantum mechanical phenomena; (3) the science of light propagation and imaging through scattering, dispersive, and turbulent media, which encompasses advances in radiative transport theory, statistical inverse theory, numerical inversion methods, simulation models, and hybrid imaging models; (4) nonlinear photonics and the interplay between nonlinearity and randomness.  Representatives from the NSF Division of Mathematical Sciences will be present to discuss and answer questions about the new NSF program in Optics and Photonics.  The conference will be advertised through the SIAM annual meeting website at http://www.siam.org/meetings/an16/workshops.php</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620860</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shari</FirstName>
<LastName>Moskow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shari L Moskow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>moskow@math.drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158952668</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000223777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drexel University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158956342</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 10th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DREXEL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drexel University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191042875</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3141 Chestnut Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~31200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The "NSF-SIAM Optics and Photonics Workshop" was held on Monday, July 11, 2016 as part of SIAM's 2016 Annual Meeting in Boston, MA. The program featured 11 accomplished applied mathematicians in the field of optics and photonics. It was run on the first full day of the larger SIAM meeting, and therefore highlighted this field and its important open problems to the broader applied mathematics community.&nbsp;<br /><br /><br /><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></span>. &nbsp;In this workshop leading researchers brought their vision of the future of this field to a large mathematical audience, and at the same time raised awareness about current NSF call for proposals &nbsp;"Optics and Photonics". &nbsp;Among others, topics included (1) Research on light-matter interaction, including, but not limited to, low-loss metamaterials, plasmonics and quantum phenomena; (2) Multiphysics coupling between classical electromagnetic and quantum mechanical phenomena; (3) The science of light propagation and imaging through scattering, dispersive and turbulent media, which encompasses advances in radiative transport theory, statistical inverse theory, numerical inversion methods, simulation models, and hybrid imaging models; (4) Nonlinear photonics and interplay between nonlinearity and randomness. &nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Broader Impact</strong></span>. This meeting encouraged the participation of mathematicians and computational scientists in optics and photonics, and was broadly publicized to the applied mathematics communty. Discussions were lively and included many questions from the audience. This workshop included researchers from underrepresented groups, graduate students, postdoctoral associates, and junior researchers. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Shari&nbsp;L&nbsp;Moskow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The "NSF-SIAM Optics and Photonics Workshop" was held on Monday, July 11, 2016 as part of SIAM's 2016 Annual Meeting in Boston, MA. The program featured 11 accomplished applied mathematicians in the field of optics and photonics. It was run on the first full day of the larger SIAM meeting, and therefore highlighted this field and its important open problems to the broader applied mathematics community.    Intellectual Merit.  In this workshop leading researchers brought their vision of the future of this field to a large mathematical audience, and at the same time raised awareness about current NSF call for proposals  "Optics and Photonics".  Among others, topics included (1) Research on light-matter interaction, including, but not limited to, low-loss metamaterials, plasmonics and quantum phenomena; (2) Multiphysics coupling between classical electromagnetic and quantum mechanical phenomena; (3) The science of light propagation and imaging through scattering, dispersive and turbulent media, which encompasses advances in radiative transport theory, statistical inverse theory, numerical inversion methods, simulation models, and hybrid imaging models; (4) Nonlinear photonics and interplay between nonlinearity and randomness.    Broader Impact. This meeting encouraged the participation of mathematicians and computational scientists in optics and photonics, and was broadly publicized to the applied mathematics communty. Discussions were lively and included many questions from the audience. This workshop included researchers from underrepresented groups, graduate students, postdoctoral associates, and junior researchers.         Last Modified: 07/31/2017       Submitted by: Shari L Moskow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
