<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal:   Faculty and Undergraduate Research Student Teams (FURST)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>64940.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>64940</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Faculty and Undergraduate Research Student Teams (FURST) program brings together small research groups comprised of undergraduate students and faculty from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUI) in order to provide them with a year-long research experience. The program also provides a one month long intensive summer immersion for its participants at an established summer REU site at Fresno State. FURST students get an opportunity to participate in professional workshops, presentations and academic discussions along with the REU students, whereas FURST faculty can take advantage of an on-site, in-person research collaboration with their peers within the FURST program. The program's main goal is to foster both student and faculty research at PUIs, with the specific goal of producing student and faculty authored publications, as well as presentations. The program is designed to be inclusive and accessible to teams from institutions with varying research focus and support, in order to mitigate cultural changes at institutions which may not consider research a quintessential component of their mission.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;FURST students will be working on open problems in mathematics under the guidance of their faculty mentors. Research topics include community detection problems in networks, expanding the framework and analysis of the cop and robber game, the use of coarse Ricci curvature in data analysis and interpolation problems, the study and solution of the non-linear Riccati-Ermakov equation, as well as other non-linear dispersive partial differential equations. Strengthening their background in the selected research topic through readings and lecture at their home institutions will prepare FURST students to engage in research at the same speed as the REU students during the immersion phase. Students will be expected to submit the end product of their research for publication in a peer reviewed journal. FURST faculty will engage in solving open problems in their area of research while building collaborations with faculty at other institutions. Faculty are also expected to produce publishable work as a result of participating in the program. In accordance with the stated goals, the program will improve access to research for students at PUIs, where such opportunities are typically limited. It will also (re)-energize faculty at PUIs so that they remain active in research. By doing so, FURST will help transform the research culture at the participating institutions, especially since the bulk of the research activities will take place at FURST teams' home institutions. While FURST student participants will learn skills through the program that are invaluable in graduate school and in the scientific workplace, the program will broadly impact the students at the involved PUIs by demonstrating to them (through student talks and presentations) that research can be part of the undergraduate educational experience. Finally, through the immersion in an active REU site, FURST students will gain exposure to the workings of an REU program, and will be able to make better informed choices about applying to REU as a potential next step in their academic development.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620268</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tamas</FirstName>
<LastName>Forgacs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tamas Forgacs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tforgacs@csufresno.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5592784907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000547111</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State University-Fresno Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Fresno</CityName>
<ZipCode>937400001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5592780840</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5241 N. Maple Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[M/S TA53]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150837003</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY FRESNO FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>150837003</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Fresno]]></Name>
<CityName>Fresno</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>937261852</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5245 N. Backer Ave M/S PB108]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~64940</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The FURST project brought research teams from CSU East Bay, Cal Poly San Luis Obispo, University of Texas Rio Grande Valley, Williams College, and Youngstown State University to the campus of Fresno State for an immersive research experience. Of the seven faculty involved, 3 were female, 4 were male; 3 were Hispanic, and 4 were non-Hispanic. 15 students participated in the program (6 female/9 male, 8 from underrepresented minorities (URM) in Mathematics, and 7 non-URM).</p> <p>Both the 2017 and 2018 cohorts completed original research while being hosted at the Fresno State REU site, as well as a string of professional development workshops. The program spanned&nbsp; several research areas, including analytic and numerical partial differential equations, differential geometry on graphs, as well as image processing and machine learning. In particular, teams worked on improving the facial recognition capabilities of AI systems, on analyzing the persistence of superoscillations in Schroedinger equations with variable coefficients, on understanding course Ricci curvature of a family of graphs, and on developing an individualized course schedule recommendation algorithm based on network analysis tools. Since teams continued to work on their project well beyond the summer immersion phase, for final research results the reader is referred the final outcome reports of each collaborating grantee respectively.</p> <p>Faculty from both the 2017 and the 2018 cohorts gave talks in the REU colloquium series. They also served on a panel discussing their experiences in graduate school, and the potential difficulties students face during their PhD studies. Having a diverse faculty panel proved very valuable for all participating students, who expressed appreciation for faculty's candor and openness in talking about their own struggles. Student members of the FURST research teams gave weekly oral presentations on their progress, long with a research poster presentation at the end of their stay.</p> <p>PI Forg&aacute;cs (who directed both the FURST and the REU program during the  award period) was responsible for program logistics (arranging housing,  transportation, organizing schedules etc), with an emphasis on  integrating the FURST teams into the REU activities seamlessly. This was  achieved by holding joined workshops, weekly student presentations with  faculty evaluation and feedback, regular social events open to all faculty and  students, and personally interacting with the participants of both programs on a daily basis.</p> <p>PI Forg&aacute;cs wrote a book review for the <em>Notices of the AMS</em> during the award period of a publication in which the FURST program  is described in detail. He has traveled to San Diego, CA (Joint Mathematics  Meeting of the AMS and the MAA), Denver, CO (MathFest), San Luis Obispo, CA  and Conway, SC (invited lectures) to talk about the FURST program, to  discuss undergraduate research program designs and funding  opportunities, and to train junior mathematicians on how to incorporate  undergraduate research into their early career development plan.</p> <p>Overall the FURST program succeeded in providing research experiences to students from primarily undergraduate institutions and early career faculty (at the time of participation 6 assistant and 1 associate professor) while taking advantage of the benefits offered by an established and effective REU site.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Tamas&nbsp;Forgacs</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The FURST project brought research teams from CSU East Bay, Cal Poly San Luis Obispo, University of Texas Rio Grande Valley, Williams College, and Youngstown State University to the campus of Fresno State for an immersive research experience. Of the seven faculty involved, 3 were female, 4 were male; 3 were Hispanic, and 4 were non-Hispanic. 15 students participated in the program (6 female/9 male, 8 from underrepresented minorities (URM) in Mathematics, and 7 non-URM).  Both the 2017 and 2018 cohorts completed original research while being hosted at the Fresno State REU site, as well as a string of professional development workshops. The program spanned  several research areas, including analytic and numerical partial differential equations, differential geometry on graphs, as well as image processing and machine learning. In particular, teams worked on improving the facial recognition capabilities of AI systems, on analyzing the persistence of superoscillations in Schroedinger equations with variable coefficients, on understanding course Ricci curvature of a family of graphs, and on developing an individualized course schedule recommendation algorithm based on network analysis tools. Since teams continued to work on their project well beyond the summer immersion phase, for final research results the reader is referred the final outcome reports of each collaborating grantee respectively.  Faculty from both the 2017 and the 2018 cohorts gave talks in the REU colloquium series. They also served on a panel discussing their experiences in graduate school, and the potential difficulties students face during their PhD studies. Having a diverse faculty panel proved very valuable for all participating students, who expressed appreciation for faculty's candor and openness in talking about their own struggles. Student members of the FURST research teams gave weekly oral presentations on their progress, long with a research poster presentation at the end of their stay.  PI Forg&aacute;cs (who directed both the FURST and the REU program during the  award period) was responsible for program logistics (arranging housing,  transportation, organizing schedules etc), with an emphasis on  integrating the FURST teams into the REU activities seamlessly. This was  achieved by holding joined workshops, weekly student presentations with  faculty evaluation and feedback, regular social events open to all faculty and  students, and personally interacting with the participants of both programs on a daily basis.  PI Forg&aacute;cs wrote a book review for the Notices of the AMS during the award period of a publication in which the FURST program  is described in detail. He has traveled to San Diego, CA (Joint Mathematics  Meeting of the AMS and the MAA), Denver, CO (MathFest), San Luis Obispo, CA  and Conway, SC (invited lectures) to talk about the FURST program, to  discuss undergraduate research program designs and funding  opportunities, and to train junior mathematicians on how to incorporate  undergraduate research into their early career development plan.  Overall the FURST program succeeded in providing research experiences to students from primarily undergraduate institutions and early career faculty (at the time of participation 6 assistant and 1 associate professor) while taking advantage of the benefits offered by an established and effective REU site.          Last Modified: 02/01/2019       Submitted by: Tamas Forgacs]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
