<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Beyond the Standard Model in Particle Physics and Cosmology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1650000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1650000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professors Kaustubh Agashe, Zacharia Chacko, S. James Gates,Jr. Rabindra N. Mohapatra and Raman Sundrum at the University of Maryland. The project deals with understanding the fundamental forces and matter in the universe. Our current understanding of them is based on the standard model, which has been extremely successful in explaining most known natural phenomena. There are however several aspects of the model that indicate that there is a lot of unknown physics beyond it waiting to be unearthed. The existence of masses for a tiny particle called neutrino that fills the universe and the existence of dark matter, the dominant form of matter in the universe, are but two examples which the standard model cannot explain. On a conceptual level, why the recently discovered Higgs boson weighs as much as it does, why is there more matter than antimatter in the universe, and why there are three kinds of building blocks of matter which are very similar, are some other examples that cry out for physics beyond the standard model for their understanding. Using the new funding, the investigators will continue their attempts to solve these problems, using approaches suggested by them and others, and propose ways to test them at the CERN Large Hadron Collider (LHC) as well as planned neutrino experiments at Fermilab. It is hoped that these studies will uncover new forces and new forms of matter which will revolutionize our thinking about the universe and its evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers are recognized in the community for having made seminal contributions to some of the major approaches to address the problems mentioned : warped extra dimensions (known as "Randall-Sundrum models"), existence of new boson fermion symmetries (known as supergravity) and ways to break this symmetry (known as "gaugino- and anomaly mediated susy breaking"),  twin Higgs theory as a way to understand the Higgs boson mass, grand unification of all forces and matter, left-right symmetry of all forces as a precursor to grand unification and seesaw mechanism for understanding why neutrino masses are so tiny. Together with their postdocs and students they want to continue their activities while at the same time paying attention to any new discoveries from LHC as well as other experiments</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1620074</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rabindra</FirstName>
<LastName>Mohapatra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rabindra N Mohapatra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rmohapat@physics.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056022</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000175537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>S. James</FirstName>
<LastName>Gates</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>S. James Gates</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sylvester_gates@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018636452</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000267799</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raman</FirstName>
<LastName>Sundrum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raman Sundrum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>raman@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056012</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zackaria</FirstName>
<LastName>Chacko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zackaria Chacko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zchacko@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014051774</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000236508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaustubh</FirstName>
<LastName>Agashe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaustubh Agashe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kagashe@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056018</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489781</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~550000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~550000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~550000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF award was made to five principal investigators, Kaustubh Agashe, Zacharia Chacko, S. James Gates Jr., Rabindra N. Mohapatra and Raman Sundrum. The goals of this project were to conduct theoretical investigations to expand our knowledge of the fundamental forces and microscopic constituents of nature, and to combine this with the cosmic expansion of spacetime to understand the evolution of the Universe as a whole. A broad range of topics were studied, such as supersymmetry, extra space dimensions, neutrino physics, grand unification of matter and forces, the cosmic origin of matter, the inflationary ?growth spurt? of the early universe, and dark matter/energy and their implications for large scale structure of the universe. The unifying theme was the search for new physics ideas testable at the CERN Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and various ongoing non-accelerator searches, as well as in precision cosmological measurements of the ?fossils? of the Big Bang, such as the cosmic microwave background (CMB), galaxy distributions and gravitational waves. Our results help extend the frontier of understanding of quark-lepton phenomena and the early Universe.</p> <p><strong>Major outcomes.&nbsp;</strong>We found new ways to test the origin of neutrino masses and the matter-anti-matter asymmetry of the universe using LHC data, proton decay searches and CMB measurements, motivated by developing a variety of theoretical models. New mechanisms&nbsp;were constructed to understand the puzzles of dark matter physics, leading to new tests in direct dark matter search experiments as well as at the LHC. We found new ways to test physics beyond the standard model in cosmology, especially the presence of heavy particles, using their imprint on the CMB and galactic structure. Phase transitions in the cosmic ``soup" of the early universe were shown to carry valuable information about the origins of inhomogeneities, observable in proposed gravitational wave experiments. A proposal for a new detector for the CERN Large Hadron Collider to search for long-lived particles (MATHUSLA) was proposed at Maryland in 2017 and is being strongly considered at CERN. The work of SJG explored new connections of supersymmetry to information theory, graph theory, and algebraic geometry.</p> <p><strong>Broader impact and outreach</strong>.&nbsp;The PIs had a substantial role in training graduate students and post-doctoral researchers. During the past four years, five students received their Ph. D. from our group and we trained about six post-docs (although our NSF grant had support only for one postdoc during this grant and the extra postdoc support came from University funds.) We also mentored several undergraduate students. Our research results were disseminated&nbsp;via publications in peer reviewed journals as well as through presentations in international conferences and have spurred further research in the field. The excitement of fundamental physics was conveyed more broadly in public lectures as well high school presentations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Rabindra&nbsp;N&nbsp;Mohapatra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF award was made to five principal investigators, Kaustubh Agashe, Zacharia Chacko, S. James Gates Jr., Rabindra N. Mohapatra and Raman Sundrum. The goals of this project were to conduct theoretical investigations to expand our knowledge of the fundamental forces and microscopic constituents of nature, and to combine this with the cosmic expansion of spacetime to understand the evolution of the Universe as a whole. A broad range of topics were studied, such as supersymmetry, extra space dimensions, neutrino physics, grand unification of matter and forces, the cosmic origin of matter, the inflationary ?growth spurt? of the early universe, and dark matter/energy and their implications for large scale structure of the universe. The unifying theme was the search for new physics ideas testable at the CERN Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and various ongoing non-accelerator searches, as well as in precision cosmological measurements of the ?fossils? of the Big Bang, such as the cosmic microwave background (CMB), galaxy distributions and gravitational waves. Our results help extend the frontier of understanding of quark-lepton phenomena and the early Universe.  Major outcomes. We found new ways to test the origin of neutrino masses and the matter-anti-matter asymmetry of the universe using LHC data, proton decay searches and CMB measurements, motivated by developing a variety of theoretical models. New mechanisms were constructed to understand the puzzles of dark matter physics, leading to new tests in direct dark matter search experiments as well as at the LHC. We found new ways to test physics beyond the standard model in cosmology, especially the presence of heavy particles, using their imprint on the CMB and galactic structure. Phase transitions in the cosmic ``soup" of the early universe were shown to carry valuable information about the origins of inhomogeneities, observable in proposed gravitational wave experiments. A proposal for a new detector for the CERN Large Hadron Collider to search for long-lived particles (MATHUSLA) was proposed at Maryland in 2017 and is being strongly considered at CERN. The work of SJG explored new connections of supersymmetry to information theory, graph theory, and algebraic geometry.  Broader impact and outreach. The PIs had a substantial role in training graduate students and post-doctoral researchers. During the past four years, five students received their Ph. D. from our group and we trained about six post-docs (although our NSF grant had support only for one postdoc during this grant and the extra postdoc support came from University funds.) We also mentored several undergraduate students. Our research results were disseminated via publications in peer reviewed journals as well as through presentations in international conferences and have spurred further research in the field. The excitement of fundamental physics was conveyed more broadly in public lectures as well high school presentations.           Last Modified: 11/17/2019       Submitted by: Rabindra N Mohapatra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
