<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Affordable Microfluidics-based Educational Kits and Custom Instruments for Students and Biologists</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) project is to develop an affordable suite of modular devices and software that makes it easy to design, assemble, and automate a custom bioinstrument. The goal is to provide biologists with an effective method to employ microfluidic tools and automation to accelerate scientific progress and commercialize new technologies.  Microfluidic technologies promise revolutionary improvements in diagnostics and life sciences, but their market penetration is hampered by high costs, a lack of available instruments, and ineffective training curricula.  The components of this suite will be designed to be inexpensive and re-usable, so when the biologists' needs change, they can be repurposed. The software will be designed to provide step-by-step assembly instructions and automatically configure devices, so making an instrument will be like putting together a Lego set. The technology may be used to train high school and college students in real-world laboratory techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop modular devices and software that will enable biologists to produce custom bioinstrumentation to accelerate their research. The Phase I effort will focus on new microfluidics tools and will include prototyping and testing.  This development proceeds on three fronts:  1) Implementing the software to allow simultaneous and nested automation-script execution.  This allows virtualizing instruments into blocks and hiding operational complexities from users.  2) Expanding device functionality to include thermal control, e.g., for rapid PCR, incubation, sterilization, etc., and to perform accurate, pulse-free, high-temporal-response fluid dispensing for droplet generation, HPLC, sample preparation, etc.  3) Prototyping and refining user-interface and curriculum materials on biology and engineering students in high school and college to find effective graphical interfaces for instrument design and assembly. In Phase II, the plan is to incorporate these interfaces into the software, so top-level design is intuitive, and instrument assembly follows clear step-by-step visual instructions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1621630</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kirsten</FirstName>
<LastName>Pace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kirsten Pace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kpace@labsmith.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9252925161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000712339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LabSmith, Inc</Name>
<CityName>Livermore</CityName>
<ZipCode>945515136</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9252925161</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6111 Southfront Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite E]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045733743</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LABSMITH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LabSmith, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Livermore</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>945515136</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6111 Southfront Rd, Suite E]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>LabSmith bioProcess Suite</strong></p> <p>The goal of this SBIR project is to develop the &ldquo;bioProcess Suite,&rdquo; a comprehensive product suite including software, hardware, and reference applications that allows students, researchers, and technicians to create research-grade microfluidic instrumentation. Coupled with a curriculum package, the bioProcess Suite (bPS) becomes a highly effective and affordable STEM teaching tool that educators will use to expand hands-on learning in the fields of engineering, computer science, and application-specific topics such as biology, chemistry and physics. LabSmith has made progress on all of aspects of the bPS (hardware, software, and applications/curriculum) during the Phase-I effort.</p> <p><strong>Hardware Development</strong></p> <p>Phase-I work added a new family of devices comprising smart loads and a smart-load driver and a variety of smart sensors to expand what bPS can control and measure. It also developed a novel modular flow controller device. This added functionality radically expands the physical capabilities of the bPS, enabling seamless thermal control, support for mechanical lysing, ultraviolet (UV) absorption detection, and high-pressure and vacuum generation. Moreover, the smart-sensor and smart-load frameworks developed in Phase-I streamline the addition of new and user-customized actuators. This new functionality allows users to easily create complete instruments, from sample preparation to detection, from a bPS toolkit.</p> <p><strong>Software Development</strong></p> <p>Phase I work incorporated bPS software functionality into LabSmith&rsquo;s uProcess automation tool, which was released for broad beta testing (labsmith.com/education). The new release added software and firmware support for the new devices and sensors, including a new framework to support smart loads. It also contained a new scripting framework that added support for variables, math, conditionals and programming structures, while retaining the ease of use of the &ldquo;wizard-assisted&rdquo; scripting of the previous version. This new frame supports new capabilities, such as compound-devices, in which multiple modules work together as an advanced device. For example, a flow-controller compound device may comprise a syringe pump, pressure sensor, digitizer, valve, and valve driver with hardware-level digital feedback. In the new framework, a user can script the compound device by commanding it to dispense a set volume or to regulate to a set pressure. The compound devices internally manage the control the individual modules.&nbsp; Revisions to the scripting engine also improved speed, as scripts run as semi-compiled programs.</p> <p><strong>Applications/Curriculum Development</strong></p> <p>Phase-I work created and refined a curriculum package for the bPS that was tested on 92 high school students in 5 sessions. These sessions comprised an hour of assembly of a microfluidic system, following step-by-step graphical instructions, an hour of learning to operate and automate the system, and an hour of solving an open-ended automation challenge. For many students, this was a first introduction to programming. Student engagement and enthusiasm was high, with most wanting to stay longer to try more advanced automation. Students who had previous exposure to coding consistently ranked the bPS programming experience as superior. A key reason, they explained in evaluations, was the bPS&rsquo;s graphical scripting wizard, which produced a working first draft of their code, so they could run programs and see how the syntax works without needing a manual. It was then easy for them to edit the working code to modify its behavior. The curriculum included advanced programming concepts, such as &ldquo;while&rdquo; loops and variables, which the students were able to master after just about an hour of training and experimenting. Six copies of this curriculum package, including hardware and software, are fielded to a rotating group of teacher/beta testers from a list of 74 compiled when LabSmith previewed the bPS at the National Science Teachers Association (NSTA) Conference in Los Angeles CA in April 2017.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Kirsten&nbsp;Pace</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1621630/1621630_10434041_1504125839918_DSC_0395--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1621630/1621630_10434041_1504125839918_DSC_0395--rgov-800width.jpg" title="bioProcess Suite Education Kit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1621630/1621630_10434041_1504125839918_DSC_0395--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="bioProcess Suite Education Kit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Assembled bioProcess Suite uPlatform Kit showing red and blue dye through the microfluidic chip</div> <div class="imageCredit">LabSmith</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kirsten&nbsp;Pace</div> <div class="imageTitle">bioProcess Suite Education Kit</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ LabSmith bioProcess Suite  The goal of this SBIR project is to develop the "bioProcess Suite," a comprehensive product suite including software, hardware, and reference applications that allows students, researchers, and technicians to create research-grade microfluidic instrumentation. Coupled with a curriculum package, the bioProcess Suite (bPS) becomes a highly effective and affordable STEM teaching tool that educators will use to expand hands-on learning in the fields of engineering, computer science, and application-specific topics such as biology, chemistry and physics. LabSmith has made progress on all of aspects of the bPS (hardware, software, and applications/curriculum) during the Phase-I effort.  Hardware Development  Phase-I work added a new family of devices comprising smart loads and a smart-load driver and a variety of smart sensors to expand what bPS can control and measure. It also developed a novel modular flow controller device. This added functionality radically expands the physical capabilities of the bPS, enabling seamless thermal control, support for mechanical lysing, ultraviolet (UV) absorption detection, and high-pressure and vacuum generation. Moreover, the smart-sensor and smart-load frameworks developed in Phase-I streamline the addition of new and user-customized actuators. This new functionality allows users to easily create complete instruments, from sample preparation to detection, from a bPS toolkit.  Software Development  Phase I work incorporated bPS software functionality into LabSmith?s uProcess automation tool, which was released for broad beta testing (labsmith.com/education). The new release added software and firmware support for the new devices and sensors, including a new framework to support smart loads. It also contained a new scripting framework that added support for variables, math, conditionals and programming structures, while retaining the ease of use of the "wizard-assisted" scripting of the previous version. This new frame supports new capabilities, such as compound-devices, in which multiple modules work together as an advanced device. For example, a flow-controller compound device may comprise a syringe pump, pressure sensor, digitizer, valve, and valve driver with hardware-level digital feedback. In the new framework, a user can script the compound device by commanding it to dispense a set volume or to regulate to a set pressure. The compound devices internally manage the control the individual modules.  Revisions to the scripting engine also improved speed, as scripts run as semi-compiled programs.  Applications/Curriculum Development  Phase-I work created and refined a curriculum package for the bPS that was tested on 92 high school students in 5 sessions. These sessions comprised an hour of assembly of a microfluidic system, following step-by-step graphical instructions, an hour of learning to operate and automate the system, and an hour of solving an open-ended automation challenge. For many students, this was a first introduction to programming. Student engagement and enthusiasm was high, with most wanting to stay longer to try more advanced automation. Students who had previous exposure to coding consistently ranked the bPS programming experience as superior. A key reason, they explained in evaluations, was the bPS?s graphical scripting wizard, which produced a working first draft of their code, so they could run programs and see how the syntax works without needing a manual. It was then easy for them to edit the working code to modify its behavior. The curriculum included advanced programming concepts, such as "while" loops and variables, which the students were able to master after just about an hour of training and experimenting. Six copies of this curriculum package, including hardware and software, are fielded to a rotating group of teacher/beta testers from a list of 74 compiled when LabSmith previewed the bPS at the National Science Teachers Association (NSTA) Conference in Los Angeles CA in April 2017.             Last Modified: 08/30/2017       Submitted by: Kirsten Pace]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
