<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of high-order accurate numerical methods for the shallow-water equations and other hyperbolic conversation laws with source terms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>63981.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>63981</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rosemary Renaut</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of the proposed project is to provide a class of novel high-order accurate and efficient well-balanced discontinuous Galerkin (DG) and Weighted Essentially Non-Oscillatory (WENO) schemes for the shallow-water equations and other hyperbolic conservation laws with source terms. The proposed activity includes a comprehensive coverage of new algorithm development, theoretical numerical analysis, numerical implementation issues and practical applications. The investigator proposes to provide a detailed study of highly efficient high-order well-balanced methods in the following directions: 1. Development of well-balanced methods: Very accurate well-balanced numerical methods will be developed for several equations arising in different areas; 2.  Shallow-water equations: Positivity-preserving well-balanced methods for the shallow-water equations will be developed. Then, the investigator will investigate their performance, including efficiency, scalability, etc., and study their potential application in the coastal ocean modeling; 3.  Euler equations under a gravitational field: Hydrodynamical evolution in a gravitational field arises in most astrophysical problems. The investigator will develop well-balanced methods for such system; 4. Nonlinear water wave equations: Conservative DG methods will be developed for nonlinear dispersive wave equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will provide more efficient and accurate numerical approaches to solve the shallow-water equations, and other conservation laws with source term. It will have a direct impact in many application problems arising from hydraulic engineering and atmospheric modeling, and is suitable for other source-term problems in chemistry, biology, fluid dynamics, astrophysics, and meteorology. Due to its multi-disciplinary nature, the proposed research will initiate and serve as a solid foundation for collaborative research work with applied mathematicians, hydraulic engineers and astrophysicists, and promote interdisciplinary research between Oak Ridge National Laboratory and the University of Tennessee. The proposed project will also provide training and education opportunities for both graduate and undergraduate students interested in computational mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1621111</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yulong</FirstName>
<LastName>Xing</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yulong Xing</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xing.205@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142924015</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553115</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~63981</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of the proposed project is to provide a class of novel high&shy;-order accurate and efficient well&shy;-balanced discontinuous Galerkin (DG) and Weighted Essentially Non-&shy;Oscillatory (WENO) schemes for the shallow-&shy;water equations (SWEs) and other hyperbolic conservation laws with source terms. During the funded period, we have successfully developed new well-balanced positivity-preserving DG methods for the two-dimensional SWEs to address two challenges in their hydrology application: non-flat bottom and wetting and drying front. The proposed DG methods on unstructured triangular meshes have been implemented and tested on parallel machines and nice numerical performance has been observed. We also proposed the first well-balanced finite element method for the SWEs which can preserve the general moving water equilibrium steady state, and capture the small perturbation to such system well. For the SWEs through channels with irregular geometry, we design high order finite volume WENO methods which also have the positivity-preserving feature. These results will lead to efficient numerical simulation of the SWEs in their hydraulic applications, and we have studied the extension of our methods for tidal bores problem with engineers. The other mathematical model under consideration is the Euler equation in a gravitational field. We have designed both DG and WENO methods that can preserve not only the isothermal but also the polytropic hydrostatic balance exactly. These methods have great potential in the related astrophysical applications. In addition, we designed energy conserving DG methods for various linear and nonlinear wave equations including the second order wave equation, generalized Korteweg-de Vries equation, nonlinear Camassa-Holm equation and nonlinear Schrodinger equations. Detailed numerical analysis has been carried out to verify their convergence rate. <br /><br />Our methods have great potential to be utilized in hydraulic, climate and astrophysical applications. 19 papers have been published or accepted for publication in peer-reviewed journals as a result of this project. Other broader impact of this project includes the training and education of graduate and undergraduate students including the woman and underrepresented minority students. The project has been presented at many conferences and workshops. I have taught both graduate and undergraduate courses in numerical analysis, and some results from this project have been used in the class to promote the students&rsquo; interest in computational mathematics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Yulong&nbsp;Xing</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of the proposed project is to provide a class of novel high&shy;-order accurate and efficient well&shy;-balanced discontinuous Galerkin (DG) and Weighted Essentially Non-&shy;Oscillatory (WENO) schemes for the shallow-&shy;water equations (SWEs) and other hyperbolic conservation laws with source terms. During the funded period, we have successfully developed new well-balanced positivity-preserving DG methods for the two-dimensional SWEs to address two challenges in their hydrology application: non-flat bottom and wetting and drying front. The proposed DG methods on unstructured triangular meshes have been implemented and tested on parallel machines and nice numerical performance has been observed. We also proposed the first well-balanced finite element method for the SWEs which can preserve the general moving water equilibrium steady state, and capture the small perturbation to such system well. For the SWEs through channels with irregular geometry, we design high order finite volume WENO methods which also have the positivity-preserving feature. These results will lead to efficient numerical simulation of the SWEs in their hydraulic applications, and we have studied the extension of our methods for tidal bores problem with engineers. The other mathematical model under consideration is the Euler equation in a gravitational field. We have designed both DG and WENO methods that can preserve not only the isothermal but also the polytropic hydrostatic balance exactly. These methods have great potential in the related astrophysical applications. In addition, we designed energy conserving DG methods for various linear and nonlinear wave equations including the second order wave equation, generalized Korteweg-de Vries equation, nonlinear Camassa-Holm equation and nonlinear Schrodinger equations. Detailed numerical analysis has been carried out to verify their convergence rate.   Our methods have great potential to be utilized in hydraulic, climate and astrophysical applications. 19 papers have been published or accepted for publication in peer-reviewed journals as a result of this project. Other broader impact of this project includes the training and education of graduate and undergraduate students including the woman and underrepresented minority students. The project has been presented at many conferences and workshops. I have taught both graduate and undergraduate courses in numerical analysis, and some results from this project have been used in the class to promote the students? interest in computational mathematics.       Last Modified: 10/23/2016       Submitted by: Yulong Xing]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
