<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Developing a Model of STEM-Focused Elementary Schools (eSTEM)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>646545.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>646545</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Ochsendorf</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rochsend@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922760</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the United States (U.S.) certain groups are persistently underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) education and careers, especially Blacks, Hispanics, and low-income students who disproportionately fall out of the high-achieving group in K-12 education. Policymakers argue that future STEM workforce needs will only be met if there is broader diversity participating in STEM education and careers. Recent reports have suggested that the nation would benefit from more STEM-focused schools, including at the elementary school level, to inspire interest and prepare students for future STEM endeavors. However, there is currently little information on the number and quality of elementary STEM (eSTEM) schools and the extent to which underrepresented groups have access to them. This project will study five elementary STEM schools from across the U.S. that are inclusive of students from underrepresented groups in order to determine what defines these schools. The project team, which includes investigators from SRI International and George Mason University, initially identified twenty candidate critical components that define inclusive STEM-focused elementary schools and will refine and further clarify the critical components through the research study. The resulting research products could support the development of future eSTEM schools and research on their effectiveness. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Discovery Research K-12 (DRK-12) program seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) by preK-12 students and teachers, through research and development of innovative resources, models, and tools. Projects in the DRK-12 program build on fundamental research in STEM education and prior research and development efforts that provide theoretical and empirical justification for proposed projects. This Exploratory Learning Strand project will use an iterative case study replication design to study the design and implementation of five exemplary eSTEM schools with the goal of developing a logic model that highlights the commonalities in core components and target outcomes across the schools, despite the different school contexts. A framework of twenty design components, taken from research on inclusive STEM high schools and research on successful elementary schools, will inform the data collection, analysis, and logic model development. Schools as critical cases will be selected through a nomination process by experts, followed by screening and categorization according to key design components. School documents and public database information, a school survey, and telephone interviews with school administrators will inform screening and selection of candidate schools. Researchers will then conduct multi-day, on-site visitations to each selected school, collecting data from classroom observations, interviews with students, focus groups with teachers and administrators, and discussions with critical members of the school community. The project is also gathering data on school-level student outcome indicators. Using axial and open coding, the analysis aims to develop rich descriptions that showcase characteristics of the schools to iteratively determine a theory of action that illustrates interconnections among context, design, implementation, and outcomes. Research findings will be communicated through a logic model and blueprint, school case study reports, and conference proceedings and publications that will be provided on a project website, providing an immediate and ongoing resource for education leaders, researchers and policymakers to learn about research on these schools and particular models. Findings will also be disseminated by more traditional means, such as papers in peer-reviewed journals and conference presentations, and webinars.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/25/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1621005</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters-Burton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erin E Peters-Burton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>epeters1@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039939695</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000207719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>House</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ann House</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ann@houseandco.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5102957971</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518343</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/25/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Remold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie Remold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>julie.remold@sri.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6508594136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000579405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vanessa L Peters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vanessa.peters@sri.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6508592651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000705972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SRI International</Name>
<CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7032478529</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009232752</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SRI INTERNATIONAL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009232752</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SRI International]]></Name>
<CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[333 Ravenswood Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~646545</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-931ef996-7fff-af57-ce88-7a863428c2f9"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The eSTEM project set out to build on knowledge of STEM-focused schools by systematically describing the approaches and school design characteristics of exemplar STEM-focused elementary schools. The project also worked to bring the results of this research to people working in the field and engaged in the design of STEM-focused schools.</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong><span>The eSTEM project sought to advance knowledge of STEM-focused school design beyond high school models. This work identified built upon the common critical components known about STEM-focused high schools, and expanded on this work to describe the components key to the designs of exemplar STEM-focused elementary (eSTEM) schools.</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Using a cross-case analysis of 5 exemplar STEM-focused elementary schools, researchers identified 17 critical components of elementary STEM school design organized them into a logic model format. The 17 components are: Inclusive STEM Mission, Climate of Intellectual Safety, Distributed Leadership, Community Engagement in STEM, Supporting STEM Partnerships, Teachers Develop &amp; Refine Core Curricula, Teachers as STEM Educators, Dedicated STEM Staff, Technology used to Support STEM, School Physical Setting, Interdisciplinary STEM Lessons, Participation in STEM Practices, Widespread Use of Design Cycle, 21</span><span><span>st</span></span><span> Century Skills used for STEM Learning, High-level STEM Content, Student Ownership of Learning, and Evidence-based Improvement. Component descriptions and their organization into a conceptual framework are featured on the project website, </span><a href="https://inclusivestemschools.org/"><span>https://inclusivestemschools.org/</span></a><span>. These components provide actionable information for school leaders, as well as advance the field&rsquo;s understanding of the organization of STEM-focused school design.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /><span><strong>Broader Impacts</strong>: </span><span>Many schools and districts are interested in expanding quality STEM-related learning opportunities by creating schools with STEM integral to their mission and design. The more widely known STEM-focused schools were high schools. Among the goals of eSTEM was to inform designers of elementary schools interested in adopting a STEM focused models or improving their STEM teaching and learning at the elementary grades. In the last year researchers led two 90-minute dissemination webinars. Invitations to the webinars were shared widely in networks of STEM schools, NARST, and other networks with both researcher and practitioner participants. Webinar 1 had 35 participants, and Webinar 2 had 14 participants. In addition to attendees, 3-4 school leaders from the case study schools involved in the study attended and contributed to the presentation of the common critical components. These practitioner experts were able to address participant questions with lived experience from the field. Attendees of the webinars included NSF staff, graduate students, academic faculty and school leaders. Two of the attendees included a doctoral student who is considering using our common critical components as the framework for her dissertation research, and a science instructional coordinator at a state-level office of education who will use the components in professional development sessions for science teachers in her state.</span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;Remold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The eSTEM project set out to build on knowledge of STEM-focused schools by systematically describing the approaches and school design characteristics of exemplar STEM-focused elementary schools. The project also worked to bring the results of this research to people working in the field and engaged in the design of STEM-focused schools.   Intellectual Merit: The eSTEM project sought to advance knowledge of STEM-focused school design beyond high school models. This work identified built upon the common critical components known about STEM-focused high schools, and expanded on this work to describe the components key to the designs of exemplar STEM-focused elementary (eSTEM) schools.   Using a cross-case analysis of 5 exemplar STEM-focused elementary schools, researchers identified 17 critical components of elementary STEM school design organized them into a logic model format. The 17 components are: Inclusive STEM Mission, Climate of Intellectual Safety, Distributed Leadership, Community Engagement in STEM, Supporting STEM Partnerships, Teachers Develop &amp; Refine Core Curricula, Teachers as STEM Educators, Dedicated STEM Staff, Technology used to Support STEM, School Physical Setting, Interdisciplinary STEM Lessons, Participation in STEM Practices, Widespread Use of Design Cycle, 21st Century Skills used for STEM Learning, High-level STEM Content, Student Ownership of Learning, and Evidence-based Improvement. Component descriptions and their organization into a conceptual framework are featured on the project website, https://inclusivestemschools.org/. These components provide actionable information for school leaders, as well as advance the field’s understanding of the organization of STEM-focused school design.   Broader Impacts: Many schools and districts are interested in expanding quality STEM-related learning opportunities by creating schools with STEM integral to their mission and design. The more widely known STEM-focused schools were high schools. Among the goals of eSTEM was to inform designers of elementary schools interested in adopting a STEM focused models or improving their STEM teaching and learning at the elementary grades. In the last year researchers led two 90-minute dissemination webinars. Invitations to the webinars were shared widely in networks of STEM schools, NARST, and other networks with both researcher and practitioner participants. Webinar 1 had 35 participants, and Webinar 2 had 14 participants. In addition to attendees, 3-4 school leaders from the case study schools involved in the study attended and contributed to the presentation of the common critical components. These practitioner experts were able to address participant questions with lived experience from the field. Attendees of the webinars included NSF staff, graduate students, academic faculty and school leaders. Two of the attendees included a doctoral student who is considering using our common critical components as the framework for her dissertation research, and a science instructional coordinator at a state-level office of education who will use the components in professional development sessions for science teachers in her state.          Last Modified: 01/31/2020       Submitted by: Julie Remold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
