<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Effective Treatment of Groundwater Pollution Using a System Utilizing Controlled Release Polymer Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224934.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224934</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is to develop a technology for remediating contaminated  water.  These  new  materials that called controlled release polymer structures  (CRPS) are being developed for In Situ Chemical Oxidation (ISCO). ISCO is an advanced remediation technology that has proven efficacy in reducing groundwater pollution. There are currently 1,322 sites on the EPA's National Priorities List where hazardous contaminants have or are expected to be released into the environment. CRPS serves this large $60 billion market with a low-cost, flexible remediation material. This proprietary technology offsets growing water scarcity and aging infrastructure that leads to compromised water sources. Current ISCO methods require using hazardous liquid oxidizers that pose significant worker safety risk and are not effective in all environments. CRPS can be delivered as a solid designed to treat specific contaminated zones over the course of months to years. It is expected that CRPS can transform the remediation industry by: 1) ensuring worker safety, 2) reducing labor costs, 3) allowing sustained, long  term treatment decreasing  redeployment cost, 3) providing  tunability  to  meet specific site characteristics or toxins, and 4) allowing ISCO to be a more attractive remediation approach due to increased ease of use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technical objectives in this Phase I research project are to  support  scale-up  manufacturing  and efficacy testing in preparation for field-testing at a contaminated groundwater  site.  This  program  will develop and optimize material formulation including active ingredient loading, stability, and handling / transport for commercial use. Likewise, methods amendable to large-scale manufacturing will be investigated as well as performance testing in dynamic flow contaminated water studies. Work  will investigate the ability of CRPS to be tuned for controlled release rates under multiple environmental simulations to determine contaminant degradation such as methyl tert-butyl ether (MTBE). MTBE is used as a fuel additive and is a common groundwater  contaminant  that  results  from  leaking  underground storage tanks. MTBE is particularly problematic due to its solubility and mobility in water as well as environmental persistence. Contaminant degradation by CRPS will be tested  over  a  range  of concentrations to yield dose response curves. Collectively, this Phase I program will result in a clear understanding of CRPS performance guiding future pilot scale field studies. Cost  and  deployment strategies of the CRPS compared to current ISCO remediation technologies will be evaluated in preparation for commercialization</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1622866</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Luster-Teasley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie L Luster-Teasley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>luster@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3363347575</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000245998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Gause</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Gause</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cgause@axnano.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402303881</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636308</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>AxNano LLC</Name>
<CityName>Danville</CityName>
<ZipCode>245411405</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402303881</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>527 Bridge Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969638274</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AXNANO, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[AxNano LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274014901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2901 E. Gate City Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~224934</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A common route of human exposure to hazardous chemicals is through ingestion or skin contact with contaminated water. Given that the EPA estimates roughly 1 in every 5 Americans lives within three miles of a hazardous waste site (EPA, 2015), the opportunity for exposure is significant. &nbsp;The $60 billion environmental remediation market is focused on cleaning-up hazardous air, water and soil. With over 1300 sites on the National Priorities list, environmental engineers constantly face significant challenges in successfully cleaning contaminated sites. New technologies that remediate sites faster, cheaper and more completely offer tremendous market value. Specifically, the issue of <em>contaminant rebounding</em> is a constant pain point for environmental engineers. Rebounding is the return of contaminant levels following treatment, and is currently remedied by repeated treatments &ndash; driving up cost, delaying time to completion, and prolonging exposure opportunities.</p> <p>This STTR Phase I program provided proof-of-concept testing and a path to commercialization for AxNano&rsquo;s patented controlled release polymer systems (CRPS) as novel in situ remediation agents. In situ chemical oxidation (ISCO) cleans contaminants directly &ldquo;as they lie&rdquo; as opposed to more expensive pump-and-treat methods. While effective oxidants exist, current delivery methods to the subsurface are mostly limited to liquid injections that require multiple re-injections to address contaminant rebounding (return of contaminant levels following treatment). Rebounding leads to increased remediation project cost and an unpredictable timing to cleanup. Similar to the way that controlled release drugs revolutionized the pharmaceutical industry, our CRPS will transform the remediation market by providing a sustained oxidant delivery to overcome rebounding issues with a single application, increasing efficacy and lowering overall project costs by an estimated 50%.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>Key Phase I Accomplishments: </strong></p> <ol> <li>CRPS formula optimization for a robust, stable pellet form</li> <li>Proved tunable and sustained release under a variety of      environmental conditions</li> <li>Proved efficacy against several common groundwater      contaminants</li> <li>Designed a scalable manufacturing process </li> <li>Identified potential field sites for Phase II implementation.</li> <li>Identified our customer archetype target and initial go-to-market strategy.</li> </ol> <p>As shown in the attached image, CRPS pellets trap contaminant-degrading oxidants within an environmentally friendly polymer matrix. The pellets are delivered via predrilled wells that access contaminated groundwater zones.&nbsp; Water diffusion through CRPS micro-fissures is the treatment mechanism resulting in sustained oxidant delivery producing clean water through a low-energy, minimal labor process.&nbsp; The innovation of CRPS is the use of a highly tunable polymer-based matrix that allows release of targeted oxidant doses under specific treatment times and conditions. Complicated hydrogeological aspects in the subsurface mean that each contaminated site is unique. Our tunable CRPS technology allows for a prescriptive remediation strategy that is not possible with traditional dissolved oxidant solutions. CRPS are made of environmentally friendly polymer components making them safe to handle, easy to deploy, and without negative effects to the environment &ndash; providing safe, clean water.</p> <p>In summary, this Phase I STTR program developed and evaluated four Minimum Viable Products (MVPs) for future field testing. Likewise, intellectual property was secured for future commercialization with our STTR research and development partner, North Carolina Agricultural &amp;Technical State University. Lastly, key resources were established including: 1) environmental engineering support for product design and field testing assistance in the form of CRPS deployment design and implementation; 2) chemical engineering support for pilot scale manufacturing as well as, 3) an identified toll manufacturer relationship for future large (&gt; 1,000 lb) deployment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;Gause</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622866/1622866_10436935_1500997488318_CRPSImageV1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622866/1622866_10436935_1500997488318_CRPSImageV1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Effective Treatment of Groundwater Pollution Utilizing Controlled Release Polymer Materials"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622866/1622866_10436935_1500997488318_CRPSImageV1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Effective Treatment of Groundwater Pollution Utilizing Controlled Release Polymer Materials"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CRPS pellets provide sustained delivery of oxidant directly to contaminated water in the subsurface, degrading contaminants completely in a single application</div> <div class="imageCredit">AxNano, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;Gause</div> <div class="imageTitle">Effective Treatment of Groundwater Pollution Utilizing Controlled Release Polymer Materials</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A common route of human exposure to hazardous chemicals is through ingestion or skin contact with contaminated water. Given that the EPA estimates roughly 1 in every 5 Americans lives within three miles of a hazardous waste site (EPA, 2015), the opportunity for exposure is significant.  The $60 billion environmental remediation market is focused on cleaning-up hazardous air, water and soil. With over 1300 sites on the National Priorities list, environmental engineers constantly face significant challenges in successfully cleaning contaminated sites. New technologies that remediate sites faster, cheaper and more completely offer tremendous market value. Specifically, the issue of contaminant rebounding is a constant pain point for environmental engineers. Rebounding is the return of contaminant levels following treatment, and is currently remedied by repeated treatments &ndash; driving up cost, delaying time to completion, and prolonging exposure opportunities.  This STTR Phase I program provided proof-of-concept testing and a path to commercialization for AxNano?s patented controlled release polymer systems (CRPS) as novel in situ remediation agents. In situ chemical oxidation (ISCO) cleans contaminants directly "as they lie" as opposed to more expensive pump-and-treat methods. While effective oxidants exist, current delivery methods to the subsurface are mostly limited to liquid injections that require multiple re-injections to address contaminant rebounding (return of contaminant levels following treatment). Rebounding leads to increased remediation project cost and an unpredictable timing to cleanup. Similar to the way that controlled release drugs revolutionized the pharmaceutical industry, our CRPS will transform the remediation market by providing a sustained oxidant delivery to overcome rebounding issues with a single application, increasing efficacy and lowering overall project costs by an estimated 50%.   Key Phase I Accomplishments:   CRPS formula optimization for a robust, stable pellet form Proved tunable and sustained release under a variety of      environmental conditions Proved efficacy against several common groundwater      contaminants Designed a scalable manufacturing process  Identified potential field sites for Phase II implementation. Identified our customer archetype target and initial go-to-market strategy.   As shown in the attached image, CRPS pellets trap contaminant-degrading oxidants within an environmentally friendly polymer matrix. The pellets are delivered via predrilled wells that access contaminated groundwater zones.  Water diffusion through CRPS micro-fissures is the treatment mechanism resulting in sustained oxidant delivery producing clean water through a low-energy, minimal labor process.  The innovation of CRPS is the use of a highly tunable polymer-based matrix that allows release of targeted oxidant doses under specific treatment times and conditions. Complicated hydrogeological aspects in the subsurface mean that each contaminated site is unique. Our tunable CRPS technology allows for a prescriptive remediation strategy that is not possible with traditional dissolved oxidant solutions. CRPS are made of environmentally friendly polymer components making them safe to handle, easy to deploy, and without negative effects to the environment &ndash; providing safe, clean water.  In summary, this Phase I STTR program developed and evaluated four Minimum Viable Products (MVPs) for future field testing. Likewise, intellectual property was secured for future commercialization with our STTR research and development partner, North Carolina Agricultural &amp;Technical State University. Lastly, key resources were established including: 1) environmental engineering support for product design and field testing assistance in the form of CRPS deployment design and implementation; 2) chemical engineering support for pilot scale manufacturing as well as, 3) an identified toll manufacturer relationship for future large (&gt; 1,000 lb) deployment.                Last Modified: 07/25/2017       Submitted by: Charles Gause]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
