<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  A micro-Thermionic Ionization Source for Chemical Detection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Debasis Majumdar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmajumda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I project will advance the development of new portable gas analysis systems. Portable analysis systems can provide timely information about the surroundings, leading to better decisions in critical situations.  For law enforcement, a portable detector based on the proposed technology will enable officers to focus an investigation on specific targets, whether narcotics or explosives.  Likewise, for military and civil defense operations, trace explosives can be detected even when the bulk of the material is well concealed. A portable system with the proposed detector will easily be able to identify and quantify chemical warfare agents and pesticides at single part-per-billion levels in complex backgrounds.  With precise agent detection at these low levels, the users of these systems will have better information and more time to act on that information.  In agriculture, a better detector will lead to a more judicious use of pesticides and thereby increase their effectiveness while reducing human exposure.  Considering all of the potential applications, the proposed work could lead to significant advancements in a $600 million segment of the $2 billion annual gas detection market.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is based on the years of work that Sandia National Laboratories and Defiant Technologies have invested in the development of micro components and systems for chemical detection.  The proposal objective is to develop a new ionization source that can replace radioactive materials, and other larger and more power hungry thermionic sources. The new thermionic ionization source will use micro-electro-mechanical systems (MEMS) fabrication techniques to form a millimeter-scale heating element that operates efficiently at 600 degrees C. New techniques to formulate and deposit low function work materials on these heaters will be developed and exploited to construct the ionization sources. The research will entail an exploration of alkali metal formulations for the low-work function material, heater fabrication for longevity, and source operating conditions for possible failure mechanisms. At the end of this Phase I effort, the goal is to develop an ionization source that can be coupled with portable gas chromatograph and portable ion mobility systems for the detection and analysis of explosives, chemical warfare agents, pesticides, and narcotics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1622771</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick R Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>prlewis@defiant-tech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5059995880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000566624</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Adkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Adkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adkins@defiant-tech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5059995880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713300</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Defiant Technologies Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871094406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5059995880</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6814 Academy Parkway West NE Ste</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>198044682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DEFIANT TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Defiant Technologies]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871094482</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6814 Academy Parkway W NE Ste A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>104E</Code>
<Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span>A micro-Thermionic Ionization Source for Chemical Detection</span></strong></p> <p><span>Through this Phase I STTR effort, Defiant Technologies developed an ionization-based detector </span><span>that was combined with the portable gas chromatography systems currently produced by Defiant Technologies.<span>&nbsp; </span>This new detector will allow Defiant to analyze a broader range of analytes and enter new markets. The new ionization source was also combined with an ion mobility spectrometer (IMS) that is produced by Sandia National Laboratories. Not only can this source eliminate the need for radioactive materials in an IMS, it offers Defiant the opportunity to add a whole new product line to their chemical analysis systems.</span></p> <p><span>The thermionic ionization source preferentially ionizes nitrogen and phosphorous containing compounds making it ideal for detecting pesticides, drugs, explosives, and chemical warfare agents. When joined with Defiant Technologies&rsquo; micro-GC column and preconcentrator it becomes a fully integrated portable gas analysis system.<span>&nbsp; </span>Further, when integrated with Sandia National Labs&rsquo; miniature IMS, it will be a fast-response explosives detection system.</span></p> <p><span>The prototype thermionic ionization detector is shown in Figure 1 with the source shown as an inset in the lower right. This system was challenged with several categories of analytes to test the performance of various formulations of sources and discover problems that may arise with some challenge compounds.<span>&nbsp; </span>It was known before starting this project that halogenated compounds can cause ionization promoting materials to fail. Through this work, however, a composition of low-work functions materials was discovered that did not falter when exposed to chlorinated compounds as is shown in Figure 2.</span></p> <p><span>Once the ionization-based detector was developed, the next phase was to test the detector in a full chemical analysis system.<span>&nbsp; </span>This was first accomplished with a portable gas chromatography system that Defiant manufactures and markets called the FROG-5000&trade;. The system that is shown in Figure 3 is a FROG combined with the thermionic ionization detector. While further integration is necessary, the results shown in Figure 4 demonstrate the capability to collect, separate, and detect chemicals that could not be analyzed with Defiant&rsquo;s current portable GC product. </span></p> <p><span>The thermionic ionization source was also successfully used in Sandia&rsquo;s portable IMS. The thermionic source replaced an americium source that was used in the original system.<span>&nbsp; </span>With the ionization source at the inlet of the drift tube, it was possible to ionize nitrate and nitrile compounds and observe separate signals on and oscilloscope that are characteristic to the drift time of the compound.<span>&nbsp; </span>These results represent the first time that Sandia&rsquo;s IMS has been shown to function without an ionization source and opens new commercialization opportunities for the system.</span></p> <p><span>This Phase I work has provided a firm basis for follow-on activities and both Defiant Technologies and Sandia National Laboratories would like to thank the National Science Foundation for this opportunity. There is now a solid concept for constructing the thermionic ionization sources.<span>&nbsp; </span>In addition, the electrometer that was developed works better than many commercial rack-mounted systems. <span>&nbsp;</span>There will be follow on efforts at Defiant Technologies to refine the development of the thermal ionization detector.<span>&nbsp; </span>Designs are being made to combine the TIS and electrometer electronics into a single package with a simple-to-replace TIS element.<span>&nbsp; </span>Further work will also focus on integrating this new detector into portable gas chromatography products and testing to optimize the performance.<span>&nbsp; </span></span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>"This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content."</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/12/2017<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;Adkins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491517278103_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491517278103_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Miniature Electrometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491517278103_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Miniature Electrometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Electrometer in system for testing for testing thermionic ionization source elements.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Defiant Technologies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;Adkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Miniature Electrometer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491518010581_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491518010581_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Detector Test Results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491518010581_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Detector Test Results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Tests of a thermionic ionization source coating with exposure to chlorinated compounds. Head-space exposure to methylene chloride and chloroform had only a minor impact to butyl nitrate response.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Defiant Technologies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;Adkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Detector Test Results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491518499224_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491518499224_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Detector in a GC system"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491518499224_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Detector in a GC system"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3.  Combining the thermionic ionization detector with Defiant Technologies' portable GC system.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Defiant Technologies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;Adkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Detector in a GC system</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491519110583_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491519110583_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Detector Results in a GC System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491519110583_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Detector Results in a GC System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4. Test results for the GC system with a thermionic ionization source detector.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Defiant Technologies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;Adkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Detector Results in a GC System</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491519292482_Figure5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491519292482_Figure5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Thermionic Ionization Source in a Ion Mobility Spectrometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1622771/1622771_10437090_1491519292482_Figure5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Thermionic Ionization Source in a Ion Mobility Spectrometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5.  Thermionic ionization source installed in Sandia National Laboratories? ion mobility spectrometer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Defiant Technologies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;Adkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Thermionic Ionization Source in a Ion Mobility Spectrometer</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A micro-Thermionic Ionization Source for Chemical Detection  Through this Phase I STTR effort, Defiant Technologies developed an ionization-based detector that was combined with the portable gas chromatography systems currently produced by Defiant Technologies.  This new detector will allow Defiant to analyze a broader range of analytes and enter new markets. The new ionization source was also combined with an ion mobility spectrometer (IMS) that is produced by Sandia National Laboratories. Not only can this source eliminate the need for radioactive materials in an IMS, it offers Defiant the opportunity to add a whole new product line to their chemical analysis systems.  The thermionic ionization source preferentially ionizes nitrogen and phosphorous containing compounds making it ideal for detecting pesticides, drugs, explosives, and chemical warfare agents. When joined with Defiant Technologies? micro-GC column and preconcentrator it becomes a fully integrated portable gas analysis system.  Further, when integrated with Sandia National Labs? miniature IMS, it will be a fast-response explosives detection system.  The prototype thermionic ionization detector is shown in Figure 1 with the source shown as an inset in the lower right. This system was challenged with several categories of analytes to test the performance of various formulations of sources and discover problems that may arise with some challenge compounds.  It was known before starting this project that halogenated compounds can cause ionization promoting materials to fail. Through this work, however, a composition of low-work functions materials was discovered that did not falter when exposed to chlorinated compounds as is shown in Figure 2.  Once the ionization-based detector was developed, the next phase was to test the detector in a full chemical analysis system.  This was first accomplished with a portable gas chromatography system that Defiant manufactures and markets called the FROG-5000&trade;. The system that is shown in Figure 3 is a FROG combined with the thermionic ionization detector. While further integration is necessary, the results shown in Figure 4 demonstrate the capability to collect, separate, and detect chemicals that could not be analyzed with Defiant?s current portable GC product.   The thermionic ionization source was also successfully used in Sandia?s portable IMS. The thermionic source replaced an americium source that was used in the original system.  With the ionization source at the inlet of the drift tube, it was possible to ionize nitrate and nitrile compounds and observe separate signals on and oscilloscope that are characteristic to the drift time of the compound.  These results represent the first time that Sandia?s IMS has been shown to function without an ionization source and opens new commercialization opportunities for the system.  This Phase I work has provided a firm basis for follow-on activities and both Defiant Technologies and Sandia National Laboratories would like to thank the National Science Foundation for this opportunity. There is now a solid concept for constructing the thermionic ionization sources.  In addition, the electrometer that was developed works better than many commercial rack-mounted systems.  There will be follow on efforts at Defiant Technologies to refine the development of the thermal ionization detector.  Designs are being made to combine the TIS and electrometer electronics into a single package with a simple-to-replace TIS element.  Further work will also focus on integrating this new detector into portable gas chromatography products and testing to optimize the performance.       "This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content."              Last Modified: 05/12/2017       Submitted by: Douglas Adkins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
