<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Revealing the Geometry of Spatio-temporal Chaos with Computational Topology: Theory, Numerics and Experiments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>106000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The weather we experience is driven by convection, sunlight warms the earth which heats the atmosphere which is cooled by the cold temperatures of outer space. Most people are not interested in microscopic behavior, for example the behavior of the individual molecules in the air, nor macroscopic behavior, such as worldwide average temperature. What is of interest are mesoscopic patterns, for example weather fronts which result in local changes in temperature. This interest in mesoscopic, as opposed to micro- or macroscopic features, of large scale systems occurs in a wide variety of complex large scale physical phenomena such as combustion in engines, dynamics of biomass in the oceans, ventricle fibrillation in a human heart, etc. These mesoscopic patterns take on many different shapes and sizes and change with time, sometimes slowly and sometimes rapidly. The form of these patterns and how they evolve in time is often very dependent on parameters. New technologies are greatly increasing our abilities to measure and simulate these physical phenomena, resulting in enormous data sets, but our ability to extract and quantify this information in a way that leads to understanding, predictability, and control of these systems is not keeping pace. We will explore the use of new mathematical tools to address this problem.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The spatial and temporal complexity of Rayleigh-Bénard convection produces high dimensional time series data. A relatively new algebraic topological tool called Persistent Homology will be used to provide new tools for nonlinear dimension reduction. To ensure the applicability of these methods and that physically important mesoscopic features of the dynamics are preserved they will be developed in conjunction with the further development of carefully controlled high precision convection experiments and state-of-the-art, large scale, high-resolution numerical simulations of the Boussinesq equations. This includes the analysis of the geometry of covariant Lyapunov exponents. The new computational tools developed in this work should find broad application in a wide variety of problems involving complex nonequilibrium systems in nature (oceanic and atmospheric flows, climate and weather forecasting) and in technology (nonlinear optical systems, combustion and chemical reactions) where understanding and prediction of complex behavior is desired.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1622299</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Paul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark R Paul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mrp@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402314758</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481343</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[635 Prices Fork Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was a focussed effort to explore fundamental and open questions regarding the complex dynamics of large and spatially-extended systems that are driven far-from-equilibrium. Example systems include the dynamics of the atmosphere and oceans, the complex dynamics of chemical reagents in a solution, and turbulent fluid flow. A common feature in problems such as these is that the dynamics is composed of a very large number of interacting degrees of freedom. However, it is currently not well understood how to identify, quantify, and represent these underlying degrees of freedom in a rigorous manner. As a result, these systems are very difficult to model, predict, and control and extremely large data sets are needed to describe the dynamics. The overall goal of our project was to investigate these questions using numerics, experiment, and mathematics for a problem that is accessible to laboratory experiments.&nbsp;</p> <p>We focussed our attention on the dynamics of a layer of fluid heated uniformly from below to address these open challenges. As the fluid is heated it will exhibit buoyancy driven motion of increasing complexity including periodic, chaotic, and eventually turbulent dynamics. We performed high-order and large-scale numerical simulations of chaotic thermal convection for the precise conditions of experiment. Our numerical investigation explored a wide range of parameters and our computational effort included the finite geometry of the fluid domain and experimentally accurate boundary conditions. The results of these numerical simulations generated data that were used for direct comparison with experiment and for the development of homological ideas to describe the high-dimensional dynamics. We probed the sensitivity of the dynamics to small disturbances in space and time by quantifying the growth and decay of infinitesimal perturbations. We highlight that this probing of the dynamics is only possible numerically and can not be measured directly in an experiment using currently available technologies. Our results elucidated the role of the sidewall boundary conditions on the chaotic dynamics and identified localized fluid structures where perturbations grew most rapidly. These computational results provided insights into the dynamics that were used in the development of a homological description of the flow field by locating spatial features of the fluid, and the instances of time when they occur, that contribute significantly to the dynamics.&nbsp; We also used models, composed of large lattices of coupled-maps, to explore high-dimensional chaotic dynamics well beyond what is possible for fluid convection using currently available resources. The project provided support for graduate and undergraduate research. The PI used ideas from this project in a multidisciplinary advanced graduate course on chaos and nonlinear dynamics at Virginia Tech.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;R&nbsp;Paul</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was a focussed effort to explore fundamental and open questions regarding the complex dynamics of large and spatially-extended systems that are driven far-from-equilibrium. Example systems include the dynamics of the atmosphere and oceans, the complex dynamics of chemical reagents in a solution, and turbulent fluid flow. A common feature in problems such as these is that the dynamics is composed of a very large number of interacting degrees of freedom. However, it is currently not well understood how to identify, quantify, and represent these underlying degrees of freedom in a rigorous manner. As a result, these systems are very difficult to model, predict, and control and extremely large data sets are needed to describe the dynamics. The overall goal of our project was to investigate these questions using numerics, experiment, and mathematics for a problem that is accessible to laboratory experiments.   We focussed our attention on the dynamics of a layer of fluid heated uniformly from below to address these open challenges. As the fluid is heated it will exhibit buoyancy driven motion of increasing complexity including periodic, chaotic, and eventually turbulent dynamics. We performed high-order and large-scale numerical simulations of chaotic thermal convection for the precise conditions of experiment. Our numerical investigation explored a wide range of parameters and our computational effort included the finite geometry of the fluid domain and experimentally accurate boundary conditions. The results of these numerical simulations generated data that were used for direct comparison with experiment and for the development of homological ideas to describe the high-dimensional dynamics. We probed the sensitivity of the dynamics to small disturbances in space and time by quantifying the growth and decay of infinitesimal perturbations. We highlight that this probing of the dynamics is only possible numerically and can not be measured directly in an experiment using currently available technologies. Our results elucidated the role of the sidewall boundary conditions on the chaotic dynamics and identified localized fluid structures where perturbations grew most rapidly. These computational results provided insights into the dynamics that were used in the development of a homological description of the flow field by locating spatial features of the fluid, and the instances of time when they occur, that contribute significantly to the dynamics.  We also used models, composed of large lattices of coupled-maps, to explore high-dimensional chaotic dynamics well beyond what is possible for fluid convection using currently available resources. The project provided support for graduate and undergraduate research. The PI used ideas from this project in a multidisciplinary advanced graduate course on chaos and nonlinear dynamics at Virginia Tech.       Last Modified: 11/23/2020       Submitted by: Mark R Paul]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
