<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project: Enhancement of Materials Science Education through Active Learning at Florida A&amp;M University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399910.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399910</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Claville</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mclavill@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927751</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue science, technology, engineering or mathematics (STEM) graduate programs and/or careers. The project at Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University seeks to utilize active learning approaches in courses in biomedical and chemical engineering and incorporate research into the curriculum. The activities and strategies are evidence-based and a strong plan for formative and summative evaluation is part of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has the specific goals to: increase the number of pre-engineering students that choose an engineering major; increase the number of students that choose the materials science option; increase the number of students participating in undergraduate research; and prepare students to pursue graduate studies and/or enter the workforce. To achieve the goals, the project will:  infuse modules and laboratory experiments in materials science into fourteen existing undergraduate courses in chemical and biomedical engineering; and involve undergraduate students and faculty in research investigating the consequences of structure-function relationships in nanoparticle suspensions. The project could serve as a model for small departments that are trying to grow enrollment, while at the same time keeping faculty engaged in research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1623206</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Telotte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John C Telotte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>telotte@eng.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8504106168</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000357990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Subramanian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ramakrishnan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Subramanian Ramakrishnan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>subramanian.ramakrishnan@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8504913907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000066292</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University</Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<ZipCode>323073200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8505993531</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lee Hall Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[400 Foote-Hilyer Admin Center]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>623751831</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University]]></Name>
<CityName>tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323105046</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 wahnish way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~399910</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main goals of the project was to increase the number of pre-engineering students that pick an engineering major, specifically chemical engineering; increase the number of students that specialize in the engineering materials major; increase the number of students participating in an undergraduate research project; and motivating and encouraging students to pursue and complete graduate studies in chemical engineering and materials science. In summary, this three-year TIP project initiated catalytic changes in Chemical Engineering, with crossover to other FAMU departments such as Chemistry, Physics and the FAMU-FSU College of Engineering as a whole. The project team is enhanced by its diversity, across levels (faculty, graduate, undergraduate) and metrics (race, national origin, gender, socioeconomic status, etc.). With active learning labs and modules (in both engineering and sciences), the curricular and mentored research interventions were found to be associated with learning gains as well as increased productivity and success metrics for its supported students, postdoctoral fellows, and faculty. These gains were particularly realized beginning in year 2 with wider implementation of the project across lab sections and across instructors.</p> <p>Research products resulted from the main project as well as the evaluation. Undergraduate and graduate students supported by this project completed degrees, presented their work, published, and successfully completed graduate and post-graduate school success with research and funding support. As detailed in the report, major achievements including publications, national fellowships, and university awards were granted to undergraduates, graduates, and investigators on the project, signaling success on the feasibility front: to enhance undergraduate training while also continuing to support research across the materials science pipeline. Recommendations include generating wider buy-in and use of active learning labs across department faculty, more consistent and up to date information on undergraduate materials science extracurricular and research opportunities, and streamlining data access to support internal assessment of aims and goals beyond evaluation efforts led by this team.&nbsp; In addition, the proposed research projects resulted in an increased number of FAMU undergraduates applying to graduate school with students from other disciplines such as chemistry applying to engineering. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Subramanian&nbsp;Ramakrishnan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520813533_1.Conference--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520813533_1.Conference--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ERN conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520813533_1.Conference--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ERN conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ERN conference by TIP students</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRamakrishnan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subramanian&nbsp;Ramakrishnan</div> <div class="imageTitle">ERN conference</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520885207_2.students--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520885207_2.students--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FAMU CREST TIP students"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520885207_2.students--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FAMU CREST TIP students"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CREST and TIP students at FAMU</div> <div class="imageCredit">SRamakrishnan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subramanian&nbsp;Ramakrishnan</div> <div class="imageTitle">FAMU CREST TIP students</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520930735_3.GEM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520930735_3.GEM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GEM Conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1623206/1623206_10450404_1619520930735_3.GEM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GEM Conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GEM conference organized at FAMU with the help of TIP grant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subramanian Ramakrishnan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Subramanian&nbsp;Ramakrishnan</div> <div class="imageTitle">GEM Conference</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goals of the project was to increase the number of pre-engineering students that pick an engineering major, specifically chemical engineering; increase the number of students that specialize in the engineering materials major; increase the number of students participating in an undergraduate research project; and motivating and encouraging students to pursue and complete graduate studies in chemical engineering and materials science. In summary, this three-year TIP project initiated catalytic changes in Chemical Engineering, with crossover to other FAMU departments such as Chemistry, Physics and the FAMU-FSU College of Engineering as a whole. The project team is enhanced by its diversity, across levels (faculty, graduate, undergraduate) and metrics (race, national origin, gender, socioeconomic status, etc.). With active learning labs and modules (in both engineering and sciences), the curricular and mentored research interventions were found to be associated with learning gains as well as increased productivity and success metrics for its supported students, postdoctoral fellows, and faculty. These gains were particularly realized beginning in year 2 with wider implementation of the project across lab sections and across instructors.  Research products resulted from the main project as well as the evaluation. Undergraduate and graduate students supported by this project completed degrees, presented their work, published, and successfully completed graduate and post-graduate school success with research and funding support. As detailed in the report, major achievements including publications, national fellowships, and university awards were granted to undergraduates, graduates, and investigators on the project, signaling success on the feasibility front: to enhance undergraduate training while also continuing to support research across the materials science pipeline. Recommendations include generating wider buy-in and use of active learning labs across department faculty, more consistent and up to date information on undergraduate materials science extracurricular and research opportunities, and streamlining data access to support internal assessment of aims and goals beyond evaluation efforts led by this team.  In addition, the proposed research projects resulted in an increased number of FAMU undergraduates applying to graduate school with students from other disciplines such as chemistry applying to engineering.            Last Modified: 05/14/2021       Submitted by: Subramanian Ramakrishnan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
