<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: The effect of an extreme El Nino event on tropical forest seedling regeneration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>165000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>165000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research will explore how trees in eight tropical forests respond to an El Niño event. The 2015-16 El Niño is among the three strongest since 1950. Strong El Niño events bring climate anomalies worldwide, including increased temperatures, reduced cloud cover, decreased rainfall, and drought over a large portion of the Tropics. The eight forests in this study occur along a steep rainfall gradient from the wet Caribbean to the dry Pacific coast of Panama. The project capitalizes on previously mapped populations of seedlings and trees in each of these forests. Although the 2015-16 El Niño initially benefitted trees by reducing cloud cover and increasing light availability during the 2015 rainy season, the dry season began earlier than normal, which likely means a severe drought lies ahead. The project will test several hypotheses about how tree species in normally wet and dry forests respond differently to reduced rainfall. The net effect of drought and increased light on the health of seedlings and adult trees will determine which species regenerate, potentially altering long-term composition of the forests. This project is important because tropical forests play a vital role in global carbon and water cycles and are the most biologically diverse ecosystem on the planet. Also, a deeper understanding of how plant species respond to El Niño events will provide insight into how forests will respond to long-term climate change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During the 2016 El Niño event, researchers will survey an existing network of tree seedling plots within eight forests that span a pronounced rainfall gradient in central in Panama. Censuses will measure seedling recruitment, growth and survival across two size classes and (1) determine which forest sites and tree species are most affected by an extreme El Niño event, (2) examine the relative roles of reduced soil water availability and increased light on seedling performance, (3) evaluate the predictive value of functional traits for seedling responses to El Niño, (4) measure the size distribution of El Niño-related seedling mortality, and (5) provide a baseline for modeling the effects of extreme El Niño events on tropical forests through assessing minimum soil and leaf water potentials and their variation across forests and species. The project is among the most comprehensive studies of the effects of an El Niño event on tropical forest regeneration to date and will provide insight into variation of responses within and among species, seedling size classes, and forests. The research will improve projections for consequences of global climate change for these forests, as well as for vegetation-climate feedbacks, which will be important for forest management under current and future climate conditions. The project will also facilitate future research efforts both in Panama and in other tropical regions by providing research infrastructure and data from a relatively new set of plots in Panama and by gathering comparative performance data for a wide range of species.  Data will be made publically available online.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1623775</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>S. Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Wright</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>S. Joseph Wright</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wrightj@si.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5072128132</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000192907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bettina</FirstName>
<LastName>Engelbrecht</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bettina M Engelbrecht</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>engelbrb@si.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5076662201</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000053719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jonesfr@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417372188</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000556378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liza</FirstName>
<LastName>Comita</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liza Comita</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>liza.comita@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2039275465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000584002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~165000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The strong 2015-16 El Ni?o Southern Oscillation event provided a rare opportunity to study the impact of severe drought on Central American tropical forest dynamics and was the focus of this RAPID project. Given that the severity and frequency of drought events are predicted to increase due to climate change, there is an urgent need to understand how tropical forests respond to severe drought events. In particular, a better understanding of drought impacts on the regeneration of tree seedlings is critical for determining future tropical forest composition, diversity, and function.</p> <p>We examined seedling dynamics before, during, and after the 2015 - 2016 ENSO event to test several hypotheses related to the response of tropical tree seedlings to severe seasonal drought.&nbsp; We measured seedling recruitment, growth, and mortality as well as soil and leaf water potentials and light across a network of 8 1-hectare forest inventory plots in Central Panama that are arrayed across a strong rainfall and seasonal drought gradient.&nbsp; Historical records from Barro Colorado Island, Panama (approximately ? way across the rainfall gradient) indicate that soil moisture was reduced in the late dry season of 2016 relative to historical levels (1971 to 2015). Soil moisture measurements show a strong linear relationship to mean annual precipitation in 2014 across our eight plots. Soil moisture was lower and more variable across these plots in 2016. To assess the impact of El Nino drought events on forest regeneration, we monitored &gt; 13,000 seedlings of 656 species in established plots across the gradient.&nbsp; We measured growth, survival, and recruitment of all seedlings in our focal plots. We found that overall mortality was around twice as high in the dry season than the wet season in 2016, suggesting significant stress caused by reduced rainfall during the dry season can increase seedling mortality. However, annual mortality rates for seedlings varied widely across the eight plots, and only two sites showed elevated mortality in the El Nino year compared to previous years.&nbsp; These sites were located not at the extreme ends of the gradient, but at the sites that were the second most extreme wet and dry sites (Sherman and Parque Metropolitano, respectively).&nbsp; While the Parque Metropolitano site showed much higher seedling mortality in the dry season relative the wet season during the El Nino year, seedling mortality was higher in the wet season than the dry season at Sherman that year suggesting that El Nino-related drought stress did not drive the elevated mortality at that site.</p> <p>Overall, these results suggest that the El Nino event did not result in widespread seedling mortality due to severe dry season drought stress. Instead, we saw that the impact of the El Nino event on community-wide seedling mortality varied across sites and did not show a clear relationship with mean annual rainfall across the precipitation gradient. This may be due to the fact that there is substantial turnover in species composition across the gradient, and individual species may be responding differentially to the El Nino event. We are in the process of exploring this possibility using published estimates of tree species sensitivity to moisture based on species distribution data from this region (Condit et al. 2013 PNAS). We are also in the process of linking available data on species functional traits (e.g. wood density, maximum stature, SLA, leaf area; Wright et al. 2010) to our seedling data in order to assess whether individual species response?s to drought stress are related to specific functional traits (or suites of traits).&nbsp; This project involved training for 2 postdoctoral research scientists and 6 research technicians.&nbsp; The outcomes of the research will likely identify specific tree species that may be resilient or susceptible to severe seasonal drought and how this will impact forest diversity and function in the future.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Frank&nbsp;Jones</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The strong 2015-16 El Ni?o Southern Oscillation event provided a rare opportunity to study the impact of severe drought on Central American tropical forest dynamics and was the focus of this RAPID project. Given that the severity and frequency of drought events are predicted to increase due to climate change, there is an urgent need to understand how tropical forests respond to severe drought events. In particular, a better understanding of drought impacts on the regeneration of tree seedlings is critical for determining future tropical forest composition, diversity, and function.  We examined seedling dynamics before, during, and after the 2015 - 2016 ENSO event to test several hypotheses related to the response of tropical tree seedlings to severe seasonal drought.  We measured seedling recruitment, growth, and mortality as well as soil and leaf water potentials and light across a network of 8 1-hectare forest inventory plots in Central Panama that are arrayed across a strong rainfall and seasonal drought gradient.  Historical records from Barro Colorado Island, Panama (approximately ? way across the rainfall gradient) indicate that soil moisture was reduced in the late dry season of 2016 relative to historical levels (1971 to 2015). Soil moisture measurements show a strong linear relationship to mean annual precipitation in 2014 across our eight plots. Soil moisture was lower and more variable across these plots in 2016. To assess the impact of El Nino drought events on forest regeneration, we monitored &gt; 13,000 seedlings of 656 species in established plots across the gradient.  We measured growth, survival, and recruitment of all seedlings in our focal plots. We found that overall mortality was around twice as high in the dry season than the wet season in 2016, suggesting significant stress caused by reduced rainfall during the dry season can increase seedling mortality. However, annual mortality rates for seedlings varied widely across the eight plots, and only two sites showed elevated mortality in the El Nino year compared to previous years.  These sites were located not at the extreme ends of the gradient, but at the sites that were the second most extreme wet and dry sites (Sherman and Parque Metropolitano, respectively).  While the Parque Metropolitano site showed much higher seedling mortality in the dry season relative the wet season during the El Nino year, seedling mortality was higher in the wet season than the dry season at Sherman that year suggesting that El Nino-related drought stress did not drive the elevated mortality at that site.  Overall, these results suggest that the El Nino event did not result in widespread seedling mortality due to severe dry season drought stress. Instead, we saw that the impact of the El Nino event on community-wide seedling mortality varied across sites and did not show a clear relationship with mean annual rainfall across the precipitation gradient. This may be due to the fact that there is substantial turnover in species composition across the gradient, and individual species may be responding differentially to the El Nino event. We are in the process of exploring this possibility using published estimates of tree species sensitivity to moisture based on species distribution data from this region (Condit et al. 2013 PNAS). We are also in the process of linking available data on species functional traits (e.g. wood density, maximum stature, SLA, leaf area; Wright et al. 2010) to our seedling data in order to assess whether individual species response?s to drought stress are related to specific functional traits (or suites of traits).  This project involved training for 2 postdoctoral research scientists and 6 research technicians.  The outcomes of the research will likely identify specific tree species that may be resilient or susceptible to severe seasonal drought and how this will impact forest diversity and function in the future.       Last Modified: 11/07/2018       Submitted by: Frank Jones]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
