<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project: Security Pedagogy Across the Curriculum: A Model to Integrate Cybersecurity into the Social Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399974.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>479818</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue science, technology, engineering or mathematics (STEM) graduate programs and/or careers. The project at Norfolk State University seeks to infuse cybersecurity within the social science undergraduate curriculum through experiential learning. The activities and strategies are evidence-based and grounded in a theoretical framework, and a strong plan for formative and summative evaluation is part of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of the project will be developing, implementing and assessing a set of laboratory and lecture modules which will integrate cybersecurity into sociology and criminal justice courses. The project has the specific objectives to: integrate cybersecurity into existing undergraduate sociology and criminal justice courses; host workshops to train social science faculty to teach cybersecurity content; replicate the modules beyond sociology and criminal justice programs; and create a new socio-cybersecurity course. The project will provide increased learning opportunities for an academically diverse population of undergraduate students in cybersecurity as these student do not usually pursue cybersecurity courses. The project has a strong collaboration with the Department of Computer Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1623201</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Hinds</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheryl Hinds</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chinds@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7578239551</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000558823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claude</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claude F Turner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cturner@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7578238311</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000680599</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlene</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlene Turner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmturner@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7578239053</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683576</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuying</FirstName>
<LastName>Shen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuying Shen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yshen@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7578238436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000686472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Perkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert K Perkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkperkins@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7578239053</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000686747</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Norfolk State University</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235048060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7578239053</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>700 Park Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[OSP; MCAR, Suite 601]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074754805</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORFOLK STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003133790</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Norfolk State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235048060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 Park Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~399974</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~79844</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The TIP - Infusing Cybersecurity into the Social Sciences Undergraduate Curriculum funded by the NSF's HBCU-UP program realized several significant intellectual merits and broader impacts. Some of these results were anticipated by the project team as evident in the original proposal, however, some these were positive and unanticipated outcomes. The following are some of the results achieved by the project team:</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">The Intellectual Merit</span></strong></p> <p>When this project was first proposed, the project team was convinced that there would be some value in integrating cybersecurity into sociology. Through this project we developed a name for this area of interest, and it is <strong><em>Socio-Cybersecurity</em></strong>. Sociocultural norms are important in understand how cybersecurity is changing our world and how different actors and groups are changing cybersecurity. The students impacted by the project also understand that this is how companies such as Cambridge Analytica became a dominant organization by practicing sociocultural cybersecurity.</p> <p>The original goal of the project was to infuse cybersecurity into the existing social science curriculum. This was successfully achieved as the project team created or oversaw the creation of 24 socio-cybersecurity modules. Eleven of these modules were deployed into sociology and criminal justice courses. It was also proposed that the modules would be targeted at six sociology/criminal justice course for infusion, however, we realized these stand-alone modules could be (and were) adopted to other courses at the university..</p> <p>It was also proposed that the module framework would be guided by social construction of reality theory and the scientific leaning cycle paradigm. Based on the development efforts, the team decided that, the most appropriate constructivist paradigm for the module creation and delivery was Vygotsky&rsquo;s experiential theory. The experiential pedagogy allowed for improvements in learning outcomes through hands-on activities and bringing the students own background and prior knowledge into the learning process. Based on the Tracer Survey Study, the students reported that the laboratory or hands-on exercises were the most impactful parts of the modules.</p> <p>The project team also proposed an extensive educational research program to assess the curriculum development process, we believe that we successfully achieved this goal. First, quasi-experimental methodology was used to gather students&rsquo; learning outcomes from the module integration. The process included: (1) a pre-test survey using a standardized questionnaire posted in Blackboard; (2) the socio-cybersecurity module taught by a sociologist and a computer scientist; and (3) the post-test, replicating the questions from the pre-test. The success rate from the data collection was positive, and the students were incentivized with a project USB drive. The collected data was analyzed using the paired T-test to check for statistically significant mean differences between students&rsquo; pre- and post-test responses to the cybersecurity concepts. There were several statistically significant differences indicating that the modules were having an impact on students learning outcomes.</p> <p>There were two other research efforts that produced interesting data from our three-year project. The first was the Socio-Cybersecurity Tracer Study Survey that was conducted between May to August 2019. The success rate was N=135. The major question from the survey was if the students was more cybersecurity aware. The answer &lsquo;very much so&rsquo; was given by most of the students (41.(%). Second, there were the interviews with over ten of the faculty members who were involved in the project as senior personnel or faculty associates. All interviewed faculty appreciated being involved in the project. When asked for suggestions and recommendations, they all said the projects efforts need to continue in the present form or in a more extended form.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">The Broader Impact</span></strong></p> <p>As proposed, the modules were taught to students at a HBCU, in the sociology department. The students that were reached were primarily from the sociology department, but there were also students from social work, psychology, interdisciplinary studies, political science, among others. Over 98% of the students who completed the modules were Black/African Americans. Sociology students are required to sit the general education course Introduction to Computer Concepts, but most have never been exposed to cybersecurity prior to the modules. This indicates that the modules successfully deployed new and innovative content to an academically diverse population.</p> <p>Another broader impact that was achieved in the project, the extension of the project to a population beyond the sociology and computer science departments. This was achieved through the faculty members who participated in the project. The Faculty Training Workshops brought in faculty from seven academic departments outside of the principal departments. The participating departments were: Psychology; Social Work; Counseling; School of Education; Mass Communications; Technology; and Mathematics. The faculty members created modules in two-member teams. They created modules can be readily adapted taught in their non-computer science discipline.</p> <p>Finally, based on the Tracer Study, some students believed that they can use socio-cybersecurity content in their future jobs. Therefore, the project's modules and courses have made our students future-job ready.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Carlene&nbsp;Turner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577342492259_WorkshopProgramCover--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577342492259_WorkshopProgramCover--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Faculty Workshop Program Cover"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577342492259_WorkshopProgramCover--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Faculty Workshop Program Cover"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Faculty Training Workshop Program Cover</div> <div class="imageCredit">TIP Socio-Cybersecurity Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlene&nbsp;Turner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Faculty Workshop Program Cover</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577342774678_ExampleofSocio-CybersecurityModule--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577342774678_ExampleofSocio-CybersecurityModule--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Digital Forensics_Court Systems Module"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577342774678_ExampleofSocio-CybersecurityModule--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Digital Forensics_Court Systems Module"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example of Socio-Cybersecurity Module</div> <div class="imageCredit">TIP Socio-Cybersecurity Project</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlene&nbsp;Turner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Digital Forensics_Court Systems Module</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577343400952_HBCU-UPPIConferece--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577343400952_HBCU-UPPIConferece--rgov-800width.jpg" title="HBCU-UP PI Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577343400952_HBCU-UPPIConferece--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="HBCU-UP PI Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PI presenting at HBCU-UP Workshop. Marriot Wardman, Washington D.C.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TIP Socio-Cybersecurity Project</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlene&nbsp;Turner</div> <div class="imageTitle">HBCU-UP PI Workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577344020525_ExperientialLearninginSmallGroups--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577344020525_ExperientialLearninginSmallGroups--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experiential Learning in Small Groups"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577344020525_ExperientialLearninginSmallGroups--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experiential Learning in Small Groups"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students Practicing their digital forensics collection skills in a Criminal Justice class.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TIP Socio-Cybersecurity Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlene&nbsp;Turner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Experiential Learning in Small Groups</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577344466366_StudentPresentingatERNConference--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577344466366_StudentPresentingatERNConference--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Student Presenting at the ERN Conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577344466366_StudentPresentingatERNConference--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Student Presenting at the ERN Conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Undergraduate Research Assistant Presenting Project Findings at the ERN Conference</div> <div class="imageCredit">TIP Socio-Cybersecurity Project</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlene&nbsp;Turner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Student Presenting at the ERN Conference</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577345518321_SecondFacultyTrainingWorkshop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577345518321_SecondFacultyTrainingWorkshop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Faculty Traing Workshop Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1623201/1623201_10452826_1577345518321_SecondFacultyTrainingWorkshop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Faculty Traing Workshop Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Training Faculty to Create and Teach the Socio-Cybersecurity Modules</div> <div class="imageCredit">TIP Socio-Cybersecurity Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlene&nbsp;Turner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Faculty Traing Workshop Participants</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The TIP - Infusing Cybersecurity into the Social Sciences Undergraduate Curriculum funded by the NSF's HBCU-UP program realized several significant intellectual merits and broader impacts. Some of these results were anticipated by the project team as evident in the original proposal, however, some these were positive and unanticipated outcomes. The following are some of the results achieved by the project team:  The Intellectual Merit  When this project was first proposed, the project team was convinced that there would be some value in integrating cybersecurity into sociology. Through this project we developed a name for this area of interest, and it is Socio-Cybersecurity. Sociocultural norms are important in understand how cybersecurity is changing our world and how different actors and groups are changing cybersecurity. The students impacted by the project also understand that this is how companies such as Cambridge Analytica became a dominant organization by practicing sociocultural cybersecurity.  The original goal of the project was to infuse cybersecurity into the existing social science curriculum. This was successfully achieved as the project team created or oversaw the creation of 24 socio-cybersecurity modules. Eleven of these modules were deployed into sociology and criminal justice courses. It was also proposed that the modules would be targeted at six sociology/criminal justice course for infusion, however, we realized these stand-alone modules could be (and were) adopted to other courses at the university..  It was also proposed that the module framework would be guided by social construction of reality theory and the scientific leaning cycle paradigm. Based on the development efforts, the team decided that, the most appropriate constructivist paradigm for the module creation and delivery was Vygotsky’s experiential theory. The experiential pedagogy allowed for improvements in learning outcomes through hands-on activities and bringing the students own background and prior knowledge into the learning process. Based on the Tracer Survey Study, the students reported that the laboratory or hands-on exercises were the most impactful parts of the modules.  The project team also proposed an extensive educational research program to assess the curriculum development process, we believe that we successfully achieved this goal. First, quasi-experimental methodology was used to gather students’ learning outcomes from the module integration. The process included: (1) a pre-test survey using a standardized questionnaire posted in Blackboard; (2) the socio-cybersecurity module taught by a sociologist and a computer scientist; and (3) the post-test, replicating the questions from the pre-test. The success rate from the data collection was positive, and the students were incentivized with a project USB drive. The collected data was analyzed using the paired T-test to check for statistically significant mean differences between students’ pre- and post-test responses to the cybersecurity concepts. There were several statistically significant differences indicating that the modules were having an impact on students learning outcomes.  There were two other research efforts that produced interesting data from our three-year project. The first was the Socio-Cybersecurity Tracer Study Survey that was conducted between May to August 2019. The success rate was N=135. The major question from the survey was if the students was more cybersecurity aware. The answer ‘very much so’ was given by most of the students (41.(%). Second, there were the interviews with over ten of the faculty members who were involved in the project as senior personnel or faculty associates. All interviewed faculty appreciated being involved in the project. When asked for suggestions and recommendations, they all said the projects efforts need to continue in the present form or in a more extended form.  The Broader Impact  As proposed, the modules were taught to students at a HBCU, in the sociology department. The students that were reached were primarily from the sociology department, but there were also students from social work, psychology, interdisciplinary studies, political science, among others. Over 98% of the students who completed the modules were Black/African Americans. Sociology students are required to sit the general education course Introduction to Computer Concepts, but most have never been exposed to cybersecurity prior to the modules. This indicates that the modules successfully deployed new and innovative content to an academically diverse population.  Another broader impact that was achieved in the project, the extension of the project to a population beyond the sociology and computer science departments. This was achieved through the faculty members who participated in the project. The Faculty Training Workshops brought in faculty from seven academic departments outside of the principal departments. The participating departments were: Psychology; Social Work; Counseling; School of Education; Mass Communications; Technology; and Mathematics. The faculty members created modules in two-member teams. They created modules can be readily adapted taught in their non-computer science discipline.  Finally, based on the Tracer Study, some students believed that they can use socio-cybersecurity content in their future jobs. Therefore, the project's modules and courses have made our students future-job ready.           Last Modified: 12/29/2019       Submitted by: Carlene Turner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
