<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Automated Software for Modeling of Linear and Non-linear Optical Properties</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Development of robust computational models and methods is a necessary step for advances in design and engineering of biomolecules and materials with desired optical and imaging-related properties. However, molecular simulations nowadays become increasingly more complicated and often involve a combination of techniques: molecular dynamics, Monte Carlo, molecular and quantum mechanics tools are integrated to provide an accurate physical picture of realistic systems. Integrating these tools is associated with many technical difficulties, including interoperability, interfacing and exchanging the data, and data analysis. Currently, most of these data-management tasks are performed by hand, which results in high human costs of computational modeling. In this project a software product is proposed that facilitates complicated computational modeling of optical and imaging properties of biomolecules and materials with less human involvement. The developed product is expected to dramatically lower the barrier to perform state-of-the-art simulations that are currently accessible only for the experts in the field. Thus, the new product ameliorates the quality of the computational modeling, while optimizing human time and involvement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to deliver to the market a computational software that helps users in both academia and industry to set-up and automate computations pertaining to their research, as well as maintain, organize and analyze the data, and share the data with colleagues. The software product is expected to provide unique opportunities for computing a variety of optical and imaging-related properties (one- and two-photon absorption and emission spectra, Raman cross-sections, polarizabilities and other non-linear properties) of biomarkers and imaging probes in realistic systems, thus facilitating development of these fields and strengthening interplay between experimental and computational research. This I-Corps team will conduct interviews to see if the intended initial product will find a market need that can be met via various delivery channels including a "software as a service" business model, also known as cloud computing, which could include charging subscription fees for using the software. The team's thought of a first potential user group with a need for the proposed software are researchers developing near-IR dyes, working with single-molecule spectroscopy techniques, FRET spectroscopy, and bio-imaging techniques. The team intends to connect with individuals and entities in this group to see how they currently meet their needs in this area, and if they are satisfied by the solutions currently available to them. The team will extend beyond this initial group of researchers to see if other and larger groups of potential users in a variety of industries are using simulation software, and if their needs have the potential to be met with our intended product. The team will use the information  gathered to help make the decision about whether to license the proposed technology, or pursue a route to a startup..</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1623911</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lyudmila</FirstName>
<LastName>Slipchenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lyudmila Slipchenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lslipchenko@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654945255</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000521431</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pradeep</FirstName>
<LastName>Gurunathan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pradeep Gurunathan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pgurunat@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941055</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000714813</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Cisneros</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark D Cisneros</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mark.cisneros@innovar-llc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3174946200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000714894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda M Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amanda.thompson@innovar-llc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3174946200</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000714895</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072084</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[560 Oval Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the efforts to bring laboratory research to the marketplace, the NSF has instituted i-Corps program to understand the needs and demands of the market. Our participation in this program was with reference to the technology developed in our research group - the Effective Fragment Potential method. This technology can be applied in numerous applications in research and development, however these applications are not well studied by the research community at large. Our research group took up the challenge of understanding the market needs before proposing solutions which may not be within the scope of the solutions the research community desires. As a part of this process, we identified areas which are in dire need of solutions, and we narrowed down the possible problems which can be tackled using our technology. We interviewed researchers and scientists across a variety of fields - from the oil and gas industry, to the chemical industry, to the pharma industry, to the biomedical device industry, to the dye industry, and all the way to establishing ties with fellow molecular simulations scientists. We were able to fathom the specific requirements within these industries, and decided to focus on pharma industry. In specific, we have decided to focus on crystal structure prediction. As a part of this process, we started the company - Simplexity Simulations LLC during May 2015, and this project has been immensely helpful in laying the groundwork for the company. With the lessons learned from the project, we hope to design better software that can tackle specific problems in the area of crystal structure prediction with the least amount of human intervention and cost. It is also to be noted that this venture has enabled the development of much-needed entrepreneurial skills for project participants.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Lyudmila&nbsp;Slipchenko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the efforts to bring laboratory research to the marketplace, the NSF has instituted i-Corps program to understand the needs and demands of the market. Our participation in this program was with reference to the technology developed in our research group - the Effective Fragment Potential method. This technology can be applied in numerous applications in research and development, however these applications are not well studied by the research community at large. Our research group took up the challenge of understanding the market needs before proposing solutions which may not be within the scope of the solutions the research community desires. As a part of this process, we identified areas which are in dire need of solutions, and we narrowed down the possible problems which can be tackled using our technology. We interviewed researchers and scientists across a variety of fields - from the oil and gas industry, to the chemical industry, to the pharma industry, to the biomedical device industry, to the dye industry, and all the way to establishing ties with fellow molecular simulations scientists. We were able to fathom the specific requirements within these industries, and decided to focus on pharma industry. In specific, we have decided to focus on crystal structure prediction. As a part of this process, we started the company - Simplexity Simulations LLC during May 2015, and this project has been immensely helpful in laying the groundwork for the company. With the lessons learned from the project, we hope to design better software that can tackle specific problems in the area of crystal structure prediction with the least amount of human intervention and cost. It is also to be noted that this venture has enabled the development of much-needed entrepreneurial skills for project participants.       Last Modified: 10/30/2016       Submitted by: Lyudmila Slipchenko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
