<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Unmanned Emissions Monitoring</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>lydia mcclure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Air pollution remains a major health hazard in the United States despite significant improvement in air quality since the passage of the Clean Air Act and formation of the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) in 1970. Globally, air pollution is the largest environmental risk to human health. Major causes of air pollution include mobile sources such as transportation, and stationary sources such as landfill gas, livestock, stationary power, and flare gas emissions. When stationary sources are distributed over large areas or have nearly inaccessible exhaust streams (i.e. power plant smoke stacks), it can be very difficult to identify the locations or severity of those sources. We have developed a unique method for measuring gases directly and in place. The proposed technology uses an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV), commonly referred to as a drone, to measure gasses and gaseous emissions. Location-specific gas concentration measurements are accomplished by integrating gas sensors into the drone, which is flown over the area of interest, and using the onboard GPS to determine the exact position of the measurement. This I-Corps team believes the most useful application of this technology is in the Oil &amp; Gas and Stationary Power industries. In addition, this has applications in Railroad, Large Bore Ships, and Agriculture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps team has developed a unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) to measure gases and gaseous emissions. The proposed innovation enables accurate and precise measurements of gas emissions in situ. The product's competitive advantage is the ability to access locations with ease regardless of any ground obstructions present and size of the survey area. Specific technical advancements include improved gas and emissions monitoring capabilities. The overarching goal of this project has clear environmental, societal, and economic benefits. The scope of possible applications has been significantly expanded to consider fuel cell manufacturers, large stationary power plants, mining, oil refineries, waste processing, large scale film processing industries, federal and state regulatory monitors and the list will most likely expand. The customer need that will be met by this technology is the ability to identify and quantify emissions sources ? whether for regulatory purposes or because these emissions represent product loss. Currently, the developmental status of the technology is at proof of principle. The UAV with sensor has been designed and a prototype was built that is undergoing validation testing. The team looks forward to learning a lot from the customer discovery sessions and further developing the technology into a minimum viable product. To demonstrate the technology, a data set will be developed using known standards for ease of comparison. The team can use this to benchmark the technology against competing technologies and for validation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1623875</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Strzelec</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Strzelec</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>strzelec@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082622403</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600013</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433123</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3123 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This I-Corps Team project focused on unmanned emissions (air pollution) monitoring. Air pollution remains a major health hazard in the United States despite significant improvement in air quality since the passage of the Clean Air Act and formation of the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) in 1970. Globally, air pollution is the largest environmental risk to human health. It rivals known risk factors including smoking, alcohol use and malnutrition. Major causes of air pollution include mobile sources such as transportation, and stationary sources such as landfill gas, livestock, stationary power, and flare gas. When stationary sources are distributed over large areas or have nearly inaccessible exhaust streams (i.e. power plant smoke stacks), it can be very difficult to identify the locations or severity of those sources. The need for abatement of air pollution is crucial, and the critical first step is locating and assessing the sources. The technology investigated in this work is a novel gas monitoring and mapping system used in conjunction with an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV).&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit of the work: </strong><em>There are currently no</em> commercial devices with the capabilities and portability of the proposed device. Our technology uses an unmanned helicopter to measure gas emissions directly in place. This is done by integrating a gas measurement sensor into the unmanned vehicle and then using the onboard GPS to determine the exact position of the measurement. Our competition uses remote measurement systems, such as an optical gas imaging camera, to measure emissions indirectly. These systems are very expensive and not easily portable. Our innovation enables accurate and precise measurements of gas emissions in situ. The product&rsquo;s competitive advantage is the ability to access locations with ease regardless of any ground obstructions present and size of the survey area. Specific technical advancements from this work include improved emissions monitoring capabilities.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts of the work: </strong><em>This work represents the critical first step</em> in developing this technology. The commercial impact of this work will have clear environmental, societal, and economic benefits. With the dialog so far developed by the I-corps exercise, the scope of possible applications has been significantly expanded to consider fuel cell manufacturers, large stationary power plants, mining, oil refineries, waste processing, large scale film processing industries, federal and state regulatory monitors and the list will most likely expand.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2016<br>      Modified by: Andrea&nbsp;Strzelec</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1623875/1623875_10407622_1468864746145_ICORPSEmissionsDrone--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1623875/1623875_10407622_1468864746145_ICORPSEmissionsDrone--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ICORPS Team 632 Emissions Drone"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1623875/1623875_10407622_1468864746145_ICORPSEmissionsDrone--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ICORPS Team 632 Emissions Drone"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image of the Unmanned Emissions Monitoring Vehicle in Flight.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Texas A&M University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class=...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This I-Corps Team project focused on unmanned emissions (air pollution) monitoring. Air pollution remains a major health hazard in the United States despite significant improvement in air quality since the passage of the Clean Air Act and formation of the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) in 1970. Globally, air pollution is the largest environmental risk to human health. It rivals known risk factors including smoking, alcohol use and malnutrition. Major causes of air pollution include mobile sources such as transportation, and stationary sources such as landfill gas, livestock, stationary power, and flare gas. When stationary sources are distributed over large areas or have nearly inaccessible exhaust streams (i.e. power plant smoke stacks), it can be very difficult to identify the locations or severity of those sources. The need for abatement of air pollution is crucial, and the critical first step is locating and assessing the sources. The technology investigated in this work is a novel gas monitoring and mapping system used in conjunction with an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV).   Intellectual merit of the work: There are currently no commercial devices with the capabilities and portability of the proposed device. Our technology uses an unmanned helicopter to measure gas emissions directly in place. This is done by integrating a gas measurement sensor into the unmanned vehicle and then using the onboard GPS to determine the exact position of the measurement. Our competition uses remote measurement systems, such as an optical gas imaging camera, to measure emissions indirectly. These systems are very expensive and not easily portable. Our innovation enables accurate and precise measurements of gas emissions in situ. The productÆs competitive advantage is the ability to access locations with ease regardless of any ground obstructions present and size of the survey area. Specific technical advancements from this work include improved emissions monitoring capabilities.   Broader Impacts of the work: This work represents the critical first step in developing this technology. The commercial impact of this work will have clear environmental, societal, and economic benefits. With the dialog so far developed by the I-corps exercise, the scope of possible applications has been significantly expanded to consider fuel cell manufacturers, large stationary power plants, mining, oil refineries, waste processing, large scale film processing industries, federal and state regulatory monitors and the list will most likely expand.        Last Modified: 07/18/2016       Submitted by: Andrea Strzelec]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
